<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kristina Putalik, Amos Klausner</title>
    <meta content="02PUTA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211790"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PUTALIK, KRISTINA LEE (KRISTINA LEE KLAUSNER)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLAUSNER, AMOS JOSEPH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E1DD1739F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="550" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kristina Putalik, Amos Klausner</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kristina Lee Putalik and Amos Joseph Klausner were married last evening in Tarrytown, N.Y. Rabbi Abraham J. Klausner, the bridegroom's father, performed the ceremony at the Castle at Tarrytown.</p>
        <p>The bride and bridegroom, both 28, have known each other since grade school and began dating at Byram Hills High School in Armonk, N.Y., where they grew up. They now live and work in California and are developing a Web site for entertainment and research for pre-teenage children. The bride teaches the third grade at the Park School in Mill Valley, and the bridegroom is the director of the San Francisco chapter of the American Institute of Graphic Arts, a professional organization.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kristina Lee Putalik and Amos Joseph Klausner were married last evening in Tarrytown, N.Y. Rabbi Abraham J. Klausner, the bridegroom's father, performed the ceremony at the Castle at Tarrytown.</p>
        <p>The bride and bridegroom, both 28, have known each other since grade school and began dating at Byram Hills High School in Armonk, N.Y., where they grew up. They now live and work in California and are developing a Web site for entertainment and research for pre-teenage children. The bride teaches the third grade at the Park School in Mill Valley, and the bridegroom is the director of the San Francisco chapter of the American Institute of Graphic Arts, a professional organization.</p>
        <p>The bride graduated from Connecticut College and received a master's degree in elementary education from the Bank Street College of Education. Her parents, Ann and Thomas L. Putalik, live in Armonk, where the bride's father is a management consultant and her mother is a broker for Vannier Real Estate.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom graduated from Boston University. His mother, Judith Klausner, and father now live in Santa Fe, N.M. The bridegroom's mother is a sculptor in bronze. His father retired from Temple Emanu-El in Yonkers.</p>
        <p>The couple became engaged last summer while hiking in the Dolomite Mountains in Italy. The bridegroom picked a bouquet of wildflowers and then presented the bride with a diamond ring that came into his father's hands at the end of World War II, when he was a United States Army chaplain in Europe.</p>
        <p>''I was really skeptical about having an old ring, because I didn't know who had had it prior to me -- I was nervous that maybe it wasn't a happy marriage,'' Ms. Putalik said. ''But when I heard the story of the ring, I felt so blessed, because the story to me means that two lovers were able to be together, and it brought a family back together.''</p>
        <p>The ring was originally given to Rabbi Klausner by a woman in Munich to be used in lieu of bail to obtain her husband's release from the Army Detainment Center. The rabbi secured the man's freedom without having to give up the ring, but before he could return it to the woman, the reunited couple had disappeared from Munich.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Klausner later gave the ring to be used as a black-market payment in helping a survivor of the Holocaust find his daughter. Years later, in Israel, the man and his wife met the black marketeer who had accepted the ring as payment and bought it back from him.</p>
        <p>In 1966, Rabbi and Mrs. Klausner, just married, traveled to Israel and visited the couple. Their hosts presented the ring to the new bride.</p>
        <p>''It just seems that it fits,'' Ms. Putalik said. ''This ring has survived, and our relationship has survived, and it makes sense.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
