<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Riki Swills Sake to Let In a Little Bit of City Haiku</title>
    <meta content="02BAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211822"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BENDING ELBOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Decibel (Nyc Bar)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamura, Rikiya</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leduff, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1DB1739F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Riki Swills Sake to Let In a Little Bit of City Haiku</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE LEDUFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leduff, Charlie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bending Elbows column describes scene at Decibel in Little Tokyo section of lower Manhattan, where Japanese immigrant Rikiya Hamura offers his opinions on love and work; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oriental poetry is of no use in New York, says Rikiya Hamura.</p>
        <p>''It's all about nature and obedience and tears and junk like that,'' he says. Rikiya  is one of thousands of young Japanese living in the city, one of his country's lost generation who have come to escape what they see as the ordered oppression of birth, school, work, death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oriental poetry is of no use in New York, says Rikiya Hamura.</p>
        <p>''It's all about nature and obedience and tears and junk like that,'' he says. Rikiya  is one of thousands of young Japanese living in the city, one of his country's lost generation who have come to escape what they see as the ordered oppression of birth, school, work, death.</p>
        <p>''It's all very nice poetry, but what the hell that got to do with living in city?'' Rikiya, 21, says. He gesticulates wildly and stabs at the sky as though it were a balloon filled with the stale gas of a thousand years of Japanese verse. He is half-cocked on sake. It is 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>His girlfriend walks four paces behind. Her name is Naomi Ogawa.</p>
        <p>''Let me tell you something: love equal work,'' he says, not bothering to check if she's still around. He descends into a cellar at Ninth Street and Second Avenue, the door opening into a cave of red lanterns. There are people with electric-pink hair and kimonos. Bottles of sake hang on the walls like stuffed ducks. The door closes on the girlfriend.</p>
        <p>This place, one of several on Ninth Street in a stretch its denizens call Little Tokyo, is named Decibel. It is where some of the best minds of this Japanese generation are destroyed by rice wine, stewing hysterical in a vat of boredom. They talk of poetry there.</p>
        <p>''Love equal work,'' Rikiya continues as he settles in with a warm bottle. Naomi drinks plum wine. ''When somebody writes that, then you got a good New York love poetry. Good New York love poetry.''</p>
        <p>The Americans he knows call him Riki Two Times. That is because he repeats himself in English to be absolutely sure he is understood. He repeats his words even when he is speaking only to himself.</p>
        <p>The Japanese young come to New York to learn individuality, Riki says, but it's imitation that leads the way. This year hip-hop and trip-hop are in, and Decibel is full of Japanese kids in cornrows and afros and nose rings and deep dark tans. Five years ago, it was the white boy thing with the tattoos.</p>
        <p>Riki is a flailing, frenetic scarecrow in a fishing cap. Naomi is a small thing with a wide mouth, small nose and glistening eyes. She is 11 years older than he, and is waiting for him to ask her to marry him. They are both supported by their families, who have sent them from Japan to learn English, and 4 p.m. is not an unusual time for a wakeup call.</p>
        <p>Naomi loves Riki and she loves drink and sometimes she will drink herself into the consistency of a wad of used gum.</p>
        <p>''Love equal work,'' Riki says yet again, pointing a finger at his lump of a woman. ''What I supposed to do with that?''</p>
        <p>An American tells him about an old Cajun folk song. A man puts his girlfriend out in the swamp. She is eaten by mosquitoes so large they leave nothing but her big toe, which the Cajun uses as a stopper for his rum bottle.</p>
        <p>Riki gags on that one. Smoke pours out of his nostrils like out of an incense jar.</p>
        <p>''That one tooooo good. Toooo good!'' A quick sip of sake. ''Finally, some poetry you can use!''</p>
        <p>CHARLIE LEDUFF</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BENDING ELBOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
