<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campaign Contrasts Grow Starker</title>
    <meta content="02SWIT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5D91539F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campaign Contrasts Grow Starker</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI and KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q; Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stark differences in personality and style of two presidential candidates described; George W Bush breezes past tough stuff in effort to remain forever buoyant, and can come across lighter than air; Al Gore, by contrast, fairly bludgeons listeners with his knowledge and can appear aloof; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush was all set and ready to go from New York City to Detroit on Tuesday when his campaign plane let out an enormous belch, drawing the attention of maintenance workers and stranding him and his entourage on the tarmac at La Guardia Airport. He seemed amused and unalarmed. ''This is an optimistic campaign,'' the Texas governor joked to the reporters who were sitting several rows behind but plenty close enough to see and hear him.</p>
        <p>When the delay dragged on, he wandered back, chatted about baseball and mused that a great virtue of this relatively unhurried stretch of the presidential campaign was that he had ample time to run and lift weights. He talked more about working out than working. There was just one public event on his campaign schedule for the day (although his morning was busy with several private meetings), and it was still many hours away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush was all set and ready to go from New York City to Detroit on Tuesday when his campaign plane let out an enormous belch, drawing the attention of maintenance workers and stranding him and his entourage on the tarmac at La Guardia Airport. He seemed amused and unalarmed. ''This is an optimistic campaign,'' the Texas governor joked to the reporters who were sitting several rows behind but plenty close enough to see and hear him.</p>
        <p>When the delay dragged on, he wandered back, chatted about baseball and mused that a great virtue of this relatively unhurried stretch of the presidential campaign was that he had ample time to run and lift weights. He talked more about working out than working. There was just one public event on his campaign schedule for the day (although his morning was busy with several private meetings), and it was still many hours away.</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore, meanwhile, was in Philadelphia, and had just finished a speech on energy and the environment that was chock-a-block with ideas, aspirations, painstakingly emphasized phrases and showy digressions, including a survey of transportation in the 20th century that began with horses, buggies and the environmental hazards they posed. ''Feed lots were crowding out farmland,'' Mr. Gore noted. He then headed to a convention hall to address union workers, effortlessly switching his focus from pollution to occupational safety and quickly establishing that he knew a lot about that, too. If he ever truly relaxed, it was not evident. Then again, the reporters on his plane, Air Force Two, had no glimpse of his cabin up front, and Mr. Gore never did drop by to say hello.</p>
        <p>And there, in the span of several hours, it was: the stark differences between the presumptive Republican and Democratic nominees for president, the widely divergent images they project to the world.</p>
        <p>One breezes past the tough stuff in an effort to remain forever buoyant, and can come across as lighter than air. The other fairly bludgeons listeners with all that he knows, and can come across as aloof. Each politician's appearances this week, tracked by reporters who switched places to take a fresh look at the man they usually did not cover, captured these contrasting styles, which also happen to tap into the candidates' strengths and especially their weaknesses, what they must take advantage of and what they must overcome.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's looseness and confidence may have something to do with his edge over Mr. Gore in most polls, but they also threaten to strain the appeal of levity to voters who undoubtedly want to look up to their president. Mr. Gore's diligence may have something to do with his need to catch up, but it also threatens to strain the appeal of gravity to voters who undoubtedly don't want their president to lecture them all the time.</p>
        <p>The candidates' days on the campaign trail this week also revealed another potentially crucial difference. Mr. Bush, guarding an apparent lead, let himself focus more intensely on fund-raising than on talking points, and collected about $9.5 million for the Republican National Committee. Mr. Gore was more absorbed in making the argument for his candidacy, and collected only about $1.5 million for the Democrats.</p>
        <p>Unlike Mr. Gore's fund-raisers, Mr. Bush's were closed to reporters, a strategic decision by Republicans, who said they worried that any discussion of the Texas governor and money served to reinforce their reputation as the party of the rich and to remind voters that Mr. Bush's candidacy has been fueled by an unprecedented sum of contributions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides even played down the tallies: the original estimate of money raised at a Tuesday breakfast of 55 people was $3 million, but the ultimate sum was $4 million. On Thursday, Mr. Bush did not have a single public campaign event, but he held a fund-raiser for the party in Dallas that brought in an estimated $4.5 million.</p>
        <p>His public appearances earlier in the week were scripted to highlight the idea that he was a ''different kind of Republican,'' one who would reach out to the minorities -- Latinos, blacks, immigrants, those with disabilities -- to whom his party had appeared indifferent if not hostile over the years.</p>
        <p>But these events were so glancing and his level of engagement so minimal that he raised doubts about his commitment to the process of campaigning. He spoke in short spurts -- his longest event lasted about 15 minutes -- and he gave the impression that his mere presence was more important than what he actually said. He frequently skipped over policy and details and implored his listeners to vote for him, saying they should simply trust him, even though, as he said at one point, ''until I'm the president, it's going to be hard for me to verify that I think I'll be more effective.''</p>
        <p>When he spoke at a news conference about being a ''different kind of Republican,'' he simply declared that the party was not ''anti-immigrant'' or ''anti-education,'' as some may have believed. But he did not try to build an argument.</p>
        <p>''Unfairly but truthfully, our party has been tagged as being against things,'' he told reporters in Cleveland. ''Anti-immigrant, for example. And we're not a party of anti-immigrants. Quite the opposite. We're a party that welcomes people.''</p>
        <p>''Slowly but surely,'' he concluded, ''I'm beginning to change the imagery.''</p>
        <p>Yet in the same week, he spent an evening in New York with members of the Congress for Racial Equality, once a leading civil-rights organization, now a collection of black conservatives. On the dais with Mr. Bush were people thought to be descendants of Thomas Jefferson and his slave Sally Hemings, as well as Barry Slotnick, the lawyer for Bernhard H. Goetz, the subway shooter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush seemed most comfortable not in front of audiences but one-on-one on his campaign plane, where he sets a tone of easy affability. There is an openness that is not possible on the more formal and restricted Air Force Two. On Monday, as reporters filed on board, the governor was standing in the press section scarfing down pizza and ready for chit-chat and hands-on schmoozing. He placed both paws on one reporter's shoulders, then pinched another on the cheek.</p>
        <p>Unlike Mr. Bush, Mr. Gore did not banter all that much, but he did talk and talk. He talked about the environment in front of a modernized power plant in Philadelphia and about ''community empowerment'' in a meeting hall in Columbus, Ohio. He talked about the scourge of AIDS and ''Afro-pessimism,'' or the wrong-headed belief that investment in Africa was a losing game.</p>
        <p>And he was, or at least appeared to be, in full command of each of these topics. But he was also strangely unvarying in his approach, so that his quasi-professorial, follow-along-with-me-if-you-can tone of voice followed him everywhere he went, even into a small fund-raiser late Tuesday night in a penthouse apartment in Washington where only about 20 high-rolling donors had gathered.</p>
        <p>He shared a personal story or two with them, but he also shared mini-tutorials on the evolution of the economy from the dark valley of stagflation in the late 1970's to the current peak of prosperity. He used the word now as a transition into each next point, the way a college instructor proceeding through an outline would. His pupils were standing at the edge of a plush living room, wine glasses in their hands, in poses decidedly less starched than Mr. Gore's language and demeanor.</p>
        <p>That was late Tuesday; halfway through Thursday, the vice president stood on the roof of a building jutting out into Lake Michigan, with the skyline of Chicago as his backdrop. He was pushing more federal spending on light rail, and mentioned that Portland had a nifty system, which he had seen himself. He offered evidence in the form of lengthy aside.</p>
        <p>''Each station celebrates the unique quality of life in Oregon,'' Mr. Gore said. ''One of them has a scarecrow weather vane, bronze rails and other things that are uniquely representative of the rural heritage in that area. Another one, they had a contest where the families participated in making the tiles themselves, and each family had a separate tile and they all come together to make up the stop. And some of them put their baby's footprints in the tile.''</p>
        <p>This went on for well over a minute, before Mr. Gore finally said, ''Now, Chicago, of course, is another great national model for mass transit.'' He had returned at last to the present place and time, but it was unclear how many people in the audience were still with him.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
