<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parents Beg Day Care Center Not to Leave Them Stranded</title>
    <meta content="02DAYC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211846"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: RIVERDALE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Day Care Centers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bon Secours Health Systems</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Schervier Child Care and Learning Center (Riverdale, Ny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Critchell, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Day Care Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7D81739F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parents Beg Day Care Center Not to Leave Them Stranded</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CRITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Critchell, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Parents petition Bon Secours Health Systems board to reopen money-losing Schervier Child Care and Learning Center in Riverdale, NY, and propose ways make center profitable, including increasing tuition and holding fund-raisers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Yael Levy accepted a job as an assistant district attorney in the Bronx last year, one reason she moved to Riverdale was the Schervier Child Care and Learning Center. It was the only such place in the area where she could take her 2-year-old year-round.</p>
        <p>Like the 55 other parents from the area who send their toddlers to the 11-year-old center, which is on Independence Avenue and is an adjunct to a large nursing home, she has been delighted with its quality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Yael Levy accepted a job as an assistant district attorney in the Bronx last year, one reason she moved to Riverdale was the Schervier Child Care and Learning Center. It was the only such place in the area where she could take her 2-year-old year-round.</p>
        <p>Like the 55 other parents from the area who send their toddlers to the 11-year-old center, which is on Independence Avenue and is an adjunct to a large nursing home, she has been delighted with its quality.</p>
        <p>So when Bon Secours Health Systems, the nonprofit group that runs both the nursing home and the day care center, announced last month that it would close the center by Aug. 31, Ms. Levy and other parents were distraught.</p>
        <p>''I'm six months pregnant, and I was planning on sending the baby there,'' Ms. Levy said recently. As for her son, Erez, ''My husband and I are going to have to take him to New Jersey every day,'' she said. ''Can you imagine?''</p>
        <p>But Todd Brooks, a spokesman for Bon Secours, said the day care center was simply no longer economically viable.</p>
        <p>''We lost $130,000 last year alone,'' he said. Income from the nursing home had covered expenses for the day care center in the past, Mr. Brooks said, but renovations and other work at the nursing home precluded this arrangement for the future.</p>
        <p>Still, parents have petitioned the board that manages the home and the center to reconsider. They also drafted a proposal last month outlining ways in which Schervier could turn the financial woes around.</p>
        <p>''When they closed, they didn't even consult us,'' said Bruce Tallerman, a Riverdale resident who sends his 14-month-old son to Schervier.</p>
        <p>A meeting last Monday between three parent representatives and most of the board members has left parents cautiously optimistic.</p>
        <p>''We understand the realities of an economic entity, but we would be willing to raise money for them, as well as pay higher tuition,'' said Michael Daily, the leader of the efforts to keep the center open. ''The meeting we had was clearly not just a catharsis for our benefit, so it was a minor victory.''</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Brooks, the board will convene on Thursday to discuss the parents' proposals further. A final decision would most likely come shortly after that, he said.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, parents said, they were scrambling to find other arrangements.</p>
        <p>''It's hard enough to find a place that you are happy with, but when it is pulled out from under you, it's very difficult,'' said Councilwoman June Eisland, a former Schervier board member who is working on the parents' behalf.</p>
        <p>DAVID CRITCHELL</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: RIVERDALE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
