<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Daily Life Is Examined Closely</title>
    <meta content="02ART.$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Whitney Museum of American Art (Stamford, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E3DD1030F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="965" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Daily Life Is Examined Closely</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM ZIMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmer, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Zimmer reviews Insites: Interior Spaces in Contemporary Art, works by participants in independent study program at Whitney Museum of Contemporary Art in Stamford, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A LARGE part of summer is spent out in the open, and the Whitney Museum's Fairfield County branch in Stamford is appropriately offering an extended experience from the outside looking in.</p>
        <p>''Insites: Interior Spaces in Contemporary Art'' is this year's presentation by participants in the Whitney Museum's Independent Study Program. The show reveals that before summer struck they did their homework.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A LARGE part of summer is spent out in the open, and the Whitney Museum's Fairfield County branch in Stamford is appropriately offering an extended experience from the outside looking in.</p>
        <p>''Insites: Interior Spaces in Contemporary Art'' is this year's presentation by participants in the Whitney Museum's Independent Study Program. The show reveals that before summer struck they did their homework.</p>
        <p>The exhibition has a decidedly contemporary look, but several important and influential works date from the early to mid-70's, which by now is another historical era.</p>
        <p>Art from that time often looks highly experimental. There is also an imaginative variety of work in most of the usual genres. The show demonstrates that when daily life is examined closely, a kind of anxiety results, and one thing this show lacks decidedly and on purpose is all the comforts of home.</p>
        <p>The curators -- Erin Barnett, Helen Burnham and Xiaoming Albert -- display a flaw common to projects that aim to be didactic. The wall labels overexplain, which has the effect of precluding individual experience.</p>
        <p>The wall information is also so peppered with questions addressed to viewers about aspects of a work they probably never even considered, that the questions come to feel like a small hammer pounding on the brain. In the end, though, the works chosen make the experience quite satisfying.</p>
        <p>Viewers might think they're being led by Alice; the exhibition resembles her Wonderland by including giant pieces as well as small ones. The towering sculpture is a mock but elegant wedding dress with a wide skirt ingeniously constructed by Gary Hulton out of overlapping white, plaster bags connected with wires and beer bottle tops. The notion of the dress and the person who would wear it is conflated with the idea of a living (or gestation) space, for the viewer is invited to enter the skirt.</p>
        <p>This entry would have been enough to get the Freudian point across, but suspended inside the skirt is a lightweight punching bag covered with designer initials and a stylized pair of boxing gloves the viewer can put on. One feels that Mr. Hulton went over the top because he didn't know where else to go.</p>
        <p>Also outsize is a drawing on Mylar by Cadence Giersbach. The central feature of the drawing is a spiral staircase so long that is doesn't fit comfortably on the museum wall.</p>
        <p>Ms. Giersbach's interior purports to be that of a traditional well-appointed room, but the awkwardness of the staircase becomes a stand-in for the inevitable rough edges of daily life. Also, ink on plastic tends to bead, and the staircase seems to break up before our eyes.</p>
        <p>A very fetching small work is the pairing of ''Portal No. 3, Negative'' and ''Portal No. 3, Positive,'' by Ricci Albenda. These two abstract sculptural images, which mirror each other, sink into the wall and bulge out from it. They are made with hydrocal, a lightweight plaster, and only minimal cutting into the museum wall was necessary for their creation.</p>
        <p>This streamlined example of transgression is related to a work it's placed near: Gordon Matta-Clark's ''Conical Intersect'' from 1975. Mr. Matta-Clark, armed with a chainsaw, would cut a series of large circles in the walls, floors and ceilings of abandoned buildings, then photograph his handiwork and make powerful but aesthetically pleasing collages out of the photographs.</p>
        <p>Two traditional paintings produce opposite effects: ''Aviary,'' by Greg Drasler, is an airy composition whose subject is absence and ambiguity; a birdcage and perch attest to this. Working with absence exacts a price: interest in the painting can dissipate. On the other hand, the expert realist Catherine Murphy keeps viewers' eyes riveted to the darting purple moire patterning of a portion of a chair that occupies almost her entire canvas. Ms. Burnham, quoting Freud, reminds viewers that Ms. Murphy might be overstepping ''the sober truth'' that the painting promises.</p>
        <p>The majority of pieces in ''Insites'' are photographs or video works, but some manipulation is involved in all of them.</p>
        <p>In the 70's Laurie Simmons was a pioneer in constructing tableaux out of plastic dolls and dollhouse furniture, then photographing them. In photography a fake scene can have the same presence as a genuine one.</p>
        <p>Although James Casebere's piece here is a new one, he is also a past master at giving constructed scenes the aura of reality. Lately his subject matter has been prisons or dungeons, and his large Polaroid of a dungeon is both forbidding and brittle-looking.</p>
        <p>An entire novel might be written about the goings-on in Tina Barney's large-format photographs that are like a window onto the complications and undercurrents now an inevitable aspect of middle-class life.</p>
        <p>In ''The Portrait,'' the picture hung on the wall of the room Ms. Barney photographs is of an angelic little blond girl. But in the real drama before us the girl is apparently being fought over by other characters, a situation that belies the straightforward sweetness of the portrait. Ultimately, though, ambiguity reigns: the behavior of the other people around the girl could be psychologically disturbing but it might also be innocent and mundane.</p>
        <p>''Insites: Interior Spaces in Contemporary Art'' is at the Whitney at Champion in Stamford through Aug. 23.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
