<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Invasive Plants Spread, State Fights Back</title>
    <meta content="02BITT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212206"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asiatic Bittersweet (Plant)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Connecticut Green Industries</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woodside, Christine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E2DB1F30F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1143" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Invasive Plants Spread, State Fights Back</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTINE WOODSIDE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Woodside, Christine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Connecticut Green Industries, organization that represents three trade groups, faced with possibility of legislative banning of sale of invasive ornamental plant Asiatic bittersweet, asks members to voluntarily halt its sale; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PEOPLE are starting to realize that the Asiatic bittersweet, a pretty vine with orange berries and pointed leaves, has unattractive habits. It smothers bushes, wraps itself around poles and squeezes trees to death. It's so aggressive that this year state lawmakers tried to have the plant outlawed.</p>
        <p>State Representative Kevin Ryan of Montville introduced a bill in April that would have made it illegal for any nursery to sell the vine in Connecticut. As he struggled to get the bill onto the floor before this year's short session closed in May, three nursery associations stepped forward with another idea. They would voluntarily stop selling bittersweet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PEOPLE are starting to realize that the Asiatic bittersweet, a pretty vine with orange berries and pointed leaves, has unattractive habits. It smothers bushes, wraps itself around poles and squeezes trees to death. It's so aggressive that this year state lawmakers tried to have the plant outlawed.</p>
        <p>State Representative Kevin Ryan of Montville introduced a bill in April that would have made it illegal for any nursery to sell the vine in Connecticut. As he struggled to get the bill onto the floor before this year's short session closed in May, three nursery associations stepped forward with another idea. They would voluntarily stop selling bittersweet.</p>
        <p>In a letter dated May 1, Robert Heffernan, executive director of Connecticut Green Industries, asked all plant-sellers to stop offering Asiatic bittersweet.</p>
        <p>''The longtime position of Connecticut's Green Industries is that laws banning certain ornamental plants would be extremely difficult to enforce and that voluntary public education about invasive plants would be far more effective,'' he n wrote.</p>
        <p>Connecticut Green Industries is the organization that represents three trade groups: the Connecticut Florists Association, Connecticut Greenhouse Growers Association, and Connecticut Nursery and Landscape Association.</p>
        <p>''It's pretty strongly worded, and if they didn't comply we could always re-enter the legislation to ban it, essentially,'' Mr. Ryan said. ''That was our goal, not to have it sold anymore, so if we didn't have to put it into law and they were willing to do that voluntarily, then that's good.''</p>
        <p>Asiatic bittersweet is one of the worst of a list of 23 non-native plants in Connecticut compiled this year by a group of scientists and policymakers.</p>
        <p>''Invasive species have always been a concern, but it's reached an epidemic,'' said Kenneth J. Metzler, a botanist at the State Department of Environmental Protection. Mr. Metzler is also a member of the Connecticut Invasive Plant Working Group.</p>
        <p>''It's a plague,'' he said. ''It really is.''</p>
        <p>Most of the plants were brought in by nurseries to dress up people's yards, but they spread over the years. In their native lands, many of these plants have enemies in microscopic parasites, insects and plant diseases. Here, they have no natural enemies, so they continue to march across the land.</p>
        <p>''There are so many ways plants are spread that we would prefer a public education campaign,'' Mr. Heffernan said. ''Plus, you can understand situations happening, like Grandma goes to visit her son down in Georgia and sees a cute little plant in the woods and digs it up and plants it up here and it becomes invasive. What are you going to do, put Grandma in jail?''</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Heffernan said, most nurseries already stopped selling Oriental bittersweet, and some decided to give up on native varieties of bittersweet because they look so similar.</p>
        <p>Among the worst culprits are Oriental bittersweet, garlic mustard, autumn olive, the common reed and multiflora rose. The bittersweet and multiflora rose seem to do best along roadsides, often where transportation crews once planted them to attract birds and control erosion.</p>
        <p>Garlic mustard grows all through the woods with shiny leaves and clusters of small white flowers. Autumn olive, originally from the Far East, is a small tree with grayish leaves, small pale yellow flowers, and light red fruits.</p>
        <p>The common reed is the tall, feathery-topped Phragmites australis, a marsh grass that has changed the coastal landscape. And the multiflora rose is a thorny shrub with pretty flat-looking pink roses. Its thickets crowd out other plants.</p>
        <p>Scientists are warning people to stop planting exotic plants and to get rid of those in their yards. But they never will be gone completely.</p>
        <p>Trying to eradicate bittersweet ''would be so comprehensive. I don't know how we would attack that,'' Mr. Ryan said.</p>
        <p>He speaks from experience. Mr. Ryan's district includes Montville, where bittersweet has crept over giant sections of trees and other growth along major roads, such as Route 32.</p>
        <p>The anti-bittersweet bill came to life because of complaints from residents such as Sandie Gregory, an avid gardener in Montville who is on a mission to stop the vine. As Ms. Gregory drives down Route 32, she gestures to the right and the left -- bittersweet is creeping around on all sides and has already killed many trees.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gregory said she removed 50 bittersweet shoots from her garden and put them in plastic bags because she has found out the hard way that the shoots re-root if she throws them in the compost.</p>
        <p>''There are so many scientists out there studying this stuff, but nobody's removing it,'' said Timothy Epperson, a resident of the Gales Ferry section of Ledyard, where bittersweet reigns along Route 12. Mr. Epperson testified in favor of the anti-bittersweet bill. He once mailed Mr. Metzler a foot-long piece of an Oriental bittersweet vine that had grown to several inches in diameter.</p>
        <p>Invasive plants got national attention last year, when President Clinton signed an executive order calling for the Interior Department to prevent the spread of ''invasive species'' including nonnative plants and also exotic marine animals, such as the zebra mussel.</p>
        <p>Scientists spent a lot of time and money last season pulling out a terribly pushy water weed, the water chestnut, in the Connecticut River. They went to this trouble, Mr. Metzler said, because the plant was so new to the river that it seemed worthwhile to try to stop it. The plant had already clogged stretches of the river in Massaschusetts.</p>
        <p>So far, scientists don't seem to know why invasive plants have become a bigger problem in the last decade. Some speculate that the popular species, such as bittersweet and multiflora rose, needed about 40 to 50 years to do their damage.</p>
        <p>''Many of these things were introduced for very legitimate and good reasons,'' said Leslie J. Mehrhoff, curator of the herbarium at the University of Connecticut and a member of the working group on invasive species. ''Some of them were introduced to stabilize banks. Many of them were introduced as ornamentals. They are invasive now because they did that well.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mehrhoff said as bad as these plants may be, a state law isn't the answer.</p>
        <p>''Birds don't read legislation,'' he said. ''Birds don't know they are not supposed to pick up bittersweet berries and then fly over to the next town and defecate. All the legislation in the world isn't going to stop the birds from doing that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
