<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is There Pity Enough for 'Hedda Gabler'?</title>
    <meta content="02THEA$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baitz, Jon Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Nicholas</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hedda Gabler (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E7DD1E30F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is There Pity Enough for 'Hedda Gabler'?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <dateline>SAG HARBOR</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alvin Klein reviews Jon Robin Baitz's new version of Henrik Ibsen play Hedda Gabler, directed by Nicholas Martin, at Bay Street Theater in Sag Harbor, Long Island (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is a play about being damned and cornered, and you have to feel the pressures on Hedda,'' writes the playwright Jon Robin Baitz in his program notes for his ''new version'' of Ibsen's ''Hedda Gabler,'' at the Bay Street Theater here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baitz nails it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is a play about being damned and cornered, and you have to feel the pressures on Hedda,'' writes the playwright Jon Robin Baitz in his program notes for his ''new version'' of Ibsen's ''Hedda Gabler,'' at the Bay Street Theater here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baitz nails it.</p>
        <p>One of the most unpleasant women in Western drama, Hedda Tesman, her sadly married name, is alienated and alienating. She has been called repulsive, a symbol of spiritual sterility, ''a poisonous snake,'' ''a hopeless specimen of degeneracy.'' And of course she is ceaselessly fascinating, the eternal mystery woman.</p>
        <p>Hedda must radiate a glamorous life that is forever lost, ''what it must have been like,'' in Mr. Baitz's stage words, as the daughter of the fabled General Gabler, ''surrounded by men dancing around her.'' At the same time, she must transport the audience into her own internal hell.</p>
        <p>In her compromised, doomed existence as the wife of a pedant and scholar, ordinariness and boredom conspire against Hedda's insistence on the fabulous and the liberating. To a controlling woman, uncontrollable events are intolerable. Given the dictates of destiny, why go on? It is inevitable that Hedda does not.</p>
        <p>Flighty and desperately social, Hedda, as reflected by Kate Burton under the uncertain direction of Nicholas Martin, exists in the whirling good times of the past. The future is illusory, the present unbearable. Ms. Burton is indeed flighty and flirtatious. If not indulged, she is petulant. Such aspects of her performance are plausible.</p>
        <p>Plausible to a fault, actually, when all at once, the calculating Hedda speaks of the absurdity of life, of her terminal boredom. Ms. Burton's Hedda suffers from missing segues, making those pronouncements of existential despair implausible.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baitz may have aimed for essential damnation and entrapment, but he did not reach it through language. Nor has Ms. Burton: This is not a dour Hedda, portending disaster. A fussy Hedda is not necessarily a fastidious one. If Ibsen's fatalism is grasped, it is not delivered.</p>
        <p>The director takes the colors and changes in the play for granted, instead of subtly revealing them. In avoiding what has become an obvious and overdone ominous air, Mr. Martin appears to be staging a drawing room play in a room bathed in light. Of course the intent is contradiction, but the outcome is affectation (obviousness of a different sort).</p>
        <p>Hedda draws the curtains incessantly, letting the sunshine in, shutting it out. Is it a neurasthenic act or a symbolic one? Darkness is hard to find in Ms. Burton's performance. Hedda's search for danger may be transparent to those who know the play, imperceptible to others. And one must simply take on hearsay that she is her father's daughter; the psychological residue that accounts for her grim gun fetish is unrealized. The aura of the absent General Gabler is lacking.</p>
        <p>Because the production seems infused with half-baked ideas, it is monochromatic and ultimately ineffectual. When her husband, desperately seeking frugality, says there will be no partygiving, no butler, no horses, ordering Hedda to ''put the horse out of your head,'' Mr. Baitz's forced attempt to be colloquial sounds silly.</p>
        <p>It doesn't help that Judge Brack (Harris Yulin) is so amorphous; one wonders: what's the threat? Tesman (Michael Emerson) seems more a manic wreck than an obsessed scholar, and the wild man Eilert Lovborg (David Lansbury) is immaculately groomed and pomaded. (Mr. Lansbury's slick mien is a bit mussed after his fateful night of debauchery, but the actor fails to transcend the orderliness of his appearance.)</p>
        <p>Thus Lovborg's hold on Mrs. Elvsted (Katie Finnernan) is just another unbelievable element. Too bad, for Ibsen's double-edged probing of two women, unfulfilled in different ways, went on 13 years after Nora's exit, a bolt heard all over the world. Mrs. Elvsted walked out on her wretched marriage quietly, and for what? Hedda's exit is grandly melodramatic; also, for what?</p>
        <p>It is unsettling to examine the futility of it all: women's search for signs of genuine freedom and self-worth, men's wrongheaded attempts to conform to false values.</p>
        <p>Ibsen tried to change the world, as artists must try, and he made an indelible dent. It is important to behold this great play as an enduring model of fascinating character and vitally disturbing content, more provocative than ever.</p>
        <p>If Bay Street's toneless staging imparts futility for all the wrong reasons, one hopes it will find its identity by the time it moves to the Williamstown Theater Festival in Massachusetts on July 19. Such alliances between regional theaters are crucial to the life of theater that counts. For audiences, the enlightenment of theater that travels, not as a touring package but as an evolving collaboration, is vital.</p>
        <p>''Hedda Gabler'' by Henrik Ibsen, in a new version by Jon Robin Baitz. Bay Street Theater on the Long Wharf in Sag Harbor. Performances through next Sunday. Ticket information: (631) 725-9500.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
