<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dan, of the Papers: 40 Years of Hamptons Lite</title>
    <meta content="02DAN.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212179"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dan's Papers (Newspaper)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rattiner, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Napoli, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE4DF1E30F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1276" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dan, of the Papers: 40 Years of Hamptons Lite</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELLE NAPOLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Napoli, Michelle</byline>
      <dateline>BRIDGEHAMPTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Dan's Papers, local newspaper on Long Island's East End which is celebrating its 40th anniversary; publisher, Dan Rattiner is easily recognizable and his breezy style and wry commentary keep readers coming back; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a media-saturated East End, it is hardly alone. But Dan's Papers does stand by itself. It does not deliver straight news or pose as fine literature, and it is hardly a stickler for correct punctuation. Sometimes it's even hard to sift fact from fantasy. Yet as its publisher, Dan Rattiner, celebrates his 40th anniversary in the business, Dan's Papers has managed to thrive in an area served by a handful of weekly newspapers and summertime glossy magazines.</p>
        <p>''I think the paper's probably read by people from every segment of the local community,'' said Mr. Rattiner (pronounced raht-TEEN-er), who is  60. ''It's kind of a bridge paper and it seems to be the most powerful advertiser on the East End.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a media-saturated East End, it is hardly alone. But Dan's Papers does stand by itself. It does not deliver straight news or pose as fine literature, and it is hardly a stickler for correct punctuation. Sometimes it's even hard to sift fact from fantasy. Yet as its publisher, Dan Rattiner, celebrates his 40th anniversary in the business, Dan's Papers has managed to thrive in an area served by a handful of weekly newspapers and summertime glossy magazines.</p>
        <p>''I think the paper's probably read by people from every segment of the local community,'' said Mr. Rattiner (pronounced raht-TEEN-er), who is  60. ''It's kind of a bridge paper and it seems to be the most powerful advertiser on the East End.''</p>
        <p>Not through any lack of self-promotion skills, Mr. Rattiner's first name, at least, has become widely recognized, and not just on the East End but in points west, from where so many Hamptons visitors and second-homeowners originate. And with his signature white beard and straw hat, his face has become almost as widely recognized as his name.</p>
        <p>But it is Mr. Rattiner's breezy style and wry commentary that appear to keep readers coming back. Reading a Rattiner essay, ''you feel like you've gone from one place to another'' said Abby Kenigsberg, executive director of the Long Island Coalition for Fair Broadcasting, which last year gave Mr. Rattiner her organization's top award for significant contributions to the Long Island community.</p>
        <p>Mortimer Zuckerman, a part-time East Hampton resident, owner of The Daily News and a member of the advisory board of Dan's Papers along with Ken Auletta, Avery Corman and George Plimpton among others, sees similar qualities. ''Dan has managed to give it a lively, feisty voice and has found a way to capture the spirit of the Hamptons,'' Mr. Zuckerman said.</p>
        <p>A typical issue of Dan's Papers today includes society gossip, a cooking column, art commentary, dining and shopping guides, a police blotter and Dan's essays on local issues, all on tabloid-sized newsprint sandwiched in a glossy color art cover.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rattiner does not pretend to be overly serious with his writing. He said he started The Montauk Pioneer, the forefather of Dan's Papers, because he thought the area could use a paper that was not so ''boring, serious, and cut-and-dry.''</p>
        <p>''I thought people on vacation, especially, want something funny, informative, and not necessarily everything,'' he said. ''There could be more selectivity involved by the editor.''</p>
        <p>The first issue of The Montauk Pioneer, published July 1, 1960, included a map of Montauk, a movie guide, tide table, train schedule and fishing news. One feature offered evening entertainment suggestions; another told of a 3,000-pound great white caught by the legendary shark fisherman Frank Mundus.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rattiner said that at first he had trouble persuading advertisers that people would pick up, and read, a free paper, but that by delivering copies to local motels he figured he could guarantee a readership. He distributed the papers himself.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rattiner said he ''absolutely fell in love with the area'' in a childhood otherwise spent in Millburn, N.J., when his family began spending weekends in Montauk. When he was 16, his parents moved to Montauk where his father, a pharmacist, bought White's, a local landmark. (The business was sold about 20 years ago, but the family still owns the property.)</p>
        <p>When he launched The Montauk Pioneer in 1960, Mr. Rattiner was between his sophomore and junior years at the University of Rochester. He returned each summer, through graduation and three years in architecture school at Harvard, and discovered he didn't want to be an architect after all. It was exciting to have people reading his work, he said, recalling the time he got a telephone call from an angry Long Island Rail Road station master, who was surrounded by an angry crowd that had missed the train west. ''I got the time wrong,'' Mr. Rattiner said.</p>
        <p>In 1965 he began publishing The East Hampton Summer Sun. In 1966 he added a Southampton publication, The Summer Day; in 1967 Westhampton's The Beach; and in 1968 a North Fork edition. Each edition was identified as ''One of Dan's Papers,'' and by the late 1970's they were all consolidated under the current title.</p>
        <p>Another major change -- the transition from summer-only to year-round publication -- was made in 1970, Mr. Rattiner said. In 1987 the cover began featuring paintings and two years later the cover went glossy, at first just in the summer and year-round in 1994. In 1988, Mr. Rattiner sold a majority interest in the business to News Communications Inc., which publishes newspapers in the New York metro and Washington, D.C., areas. But he retains full editorial control. In 1992, he began Manhattan delivery, at the request of readers, and Mr. Rattiner said that today its circulation reaches 71,000 in the summer.</p>
        <p>He said that what started as a one-man show in his bedroom in his parents' house now has more than 30 full-time employees in its Bridgehampton office and an equal number of part-timers and freelancers.</p>
        <p>His methods may be unusual, but Mr. Rattiner is celebrating the 40th anniversary in classic Hamptons style -- with lots of parties. On June 3, family, friends, employees and advertisers gathered at the Wolffer vineyard in Sagaponack for a celebration replete with cabaret entertainment. On June 10, Mr. Rattiner was feted at the Bridgehampton home of the Barnes &amp; Noble chief executive Leonard Riggio. Today, he returns to Montauk for a beach bonfire and fireworks party at Kirk Park Beach. A black-tie affair in Water Mill will culminate the celebration on July 15.</p>
        <p>He readily admits that he does not do a reporter's job of reporting. ''It was really from the get-go New Journalism, a lot of opinion,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dan's Papers, he said, hews to the ''plucked chicken school of journalism,'' and he offered this explanation: After a stormy Town Board meeting at which changes to taxes that might affect farmers were discussed, Mr. Rattiner wrote an article about a plucked chicken thrown at the town supervisor by the wife of a farmer. But one of his writers contradicted him, saying that it was a stuffed duck, and that it was handed to, not thrown at, the supervisor.</p>
        <p>''What I didn't do was get on the phone to the town supervisor and ask,'' he said. ''I deliberately did not because it illustrated it better.''</p>
        <p>He said a class exercise in college taught him that a roomful of people could come up with many different versions of an event. ''I concluded the truth was pretty much up for grabs,'' he said. ''Maybe I should say the truth was pretty hard to define.''</p>
        <p>People generally catch on to his intentions, Mr. Rattiner said, although occasionally he does get calls asking for corrections.</p>
        <p>''I think the paper has a philosophy and stuck by it,'' he said. ''We unabashedly promote the area. We honor people who do good things in it. We make suggestions -- sometimes very detailed suggestions -- on what we think could be improved and how to go about it. And we publish a lot of off-the-wall stuff that lightens up the absurdity of living on the planet.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
