<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Actor's Bronx Dream Is Realized in Bedford</title>
    <meta content="02CHAZ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212172"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEWCOMERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Beford (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Palminteri, Chazz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilgannon, Corey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE7D71130F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Actor's Bronx Dream Is Realized in Bedford</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
      <dateline>BEDFORD</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Actor Chazz Palminteri, who grew up on 189th Street in Bronx, recalls his childhood and comments on his dream house, which is being built in Bedford, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR the record, Chazz Palminteri and his family still spend afternoons out on the stoop, eating cheese sandwiches on white bread.</p>
        <p>Only now, the stoop is not concrete, but flagstone slate. And it is not on 189th Street in the Bronx, where Mr. Palminteri grew up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR the record, Chazz Palminteri and his family still spend afternoons out on the stoop, eating cheese sandwiches on white bread.</p>
        <p>Only now, the stoop is not concrete, but flagstone slate. And it is not on 189th Street in the Bronx, where Mr. Palminteri grew up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Palminteri, 47, moved out of the Bronx in 1975 into apartments in Manhattan and Los Angeles and more recently, a horse ranch in New Jersey. But now he is fulfilling a longtime dream and moving to Bedford, joining celebrities like Ralph Lauren and Glenn Close.</p>
        <p>''When I was young, I used to drive up here and look at the houses,'' he said recently in the house he is having built. ''I'd say, 'If I ever make it, I'm moving up here.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Palminteri has indeed made it; he is busier than ever, writing, directing and acting in films. Several years ago, he began visiting Bedford again, this time looking for property, and last year he saw several houses being built on large plots just off Route 22. One leafy, four-acre plot caught his eye, and soon an architect was hired to design this Bronx boy's dream house.</p>
        <p>''To me, this is something I never thought I could get,'' he said. ''Subconsciously, it's the culmination of my dreams and a lot of years of work.''</p>
        <p>Right now that culmination lies at the end of a long dirt driveway, nestled in a vale of tall oaks: a half-finished 7,000-square-foot house with five bedrooms and the bright open feel of an Italian palazzo.</p>
        <p>Mr. Palminteri and his wife, Gianna, presented their architect, Vincent M. Franze, with pictures of houses they liked. Most of their preferences were consistent with the Italian Renaissance style, including the arched interior doorways, the recessed porch and the balcony above it.</p>
        <p>Not exactly the modest third-floor apartment Mr. Palminteri grew up in, he said, walking into the master bedroom.</p>
        <p>''I grew up in an apartment that was barely bigger than this,'' he said. ''My parents had three children and slept on a pull-out couch.''</p>
        <p>After 10 years as a stage actor, Mr. Palminteri wrote and acted in ''A Bronx Tale'' onstage in New York. He rejected a $1 million offer for film rights, he said, because the deal excluded him.</p>
        <p>Then he got a phone call from Robert De Niro, who offered to direct the film and cast Mr. Palminteri as Sonny, a neighborhood mob boss. Mr. Palminteri got a role in Woody Allen's ''Bullets Over Broadway'' as a callous mob thug who develops a flair for playwriting, and the ensuing screen roles pulled Mr. Palminteri farther from the Bronx, but only physically, he said.</p>
        <p>''I'm not in the Bronx anymore, but my heart still belongs to the Bronx, so, in a way, I've never really left,'' he said. ''How could you leave a place you grew up in?''</p>
        <p>But what happens when a neighborhood kid moves to a wealthy suburb?</p>
        <p>''You get more comfortable,'' Mr. Palminteri said. ''You get a nicer car, a nicer house, maybe a limo and a driver, but you're still you. I still remember what got me here. I'm still from the streets of the Bronx, but this is where life took me.''</p>
        <p>He insists he will sleep soundly with rustling leaves replacing the sound of car alarms and street sweepers. But more importantly, his 4-year-old son, Dante, will.</p>
        <p>''Bedford is a beautiful place to live and raise a child,'' said Mr. Palminteri, whose father was a bus driver. ''As a parent you make a better life for your children.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Palminteri said he regularly visits the old neighborhood, often having dinner with old friends. He is also raising money for a children's hospital being built at the Montefiore Medical Center in the Norwood section of the Bronx. The hospital would be a center for pediatric health care, teaching and research, mostly for children of the Bronx and southern Westchester.</p>
        <p>Mr. Palminteri is proud of his Sicilian heritage and is a spokesman for Cooley's anemia, a disease that often affects Italians and others from the Mediterranean region.</p>
        <p>''I'm blessed that my son is healthy, and I thank God every day for that,'' he said. ''So if I can help ease someone else's pain, what does it take?''</p>
        <p>Speaking of the Bronx, Mr. Palminteri walked back out in front of the house, and his wife mentioned a polo match in Greenwich, a fund-raiser for the Montefiore children's hospital. Mr. Palminteri snickered.</p>
        <p>''We had the polo grounds, but Bronx guys didn't play polo,'' he quipped. He watched his family sitting on the stoop, Dante playing with rocks and Mrs. Palminteri picking out paint colors for the interior, and he laughed at the irony.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, it's a little different than 187th Street,'' he said, biting into a cheese sandwich, ''but, you know what? There will still be a lot of love in it. That's all that matters.''</p>
        <p>NEWCOMERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
