<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Watch Out Barney! Here Comes Zebby.</title>
    <meta content="02JOUR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212170"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Latin Long Island (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">America One</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wahl, Ed</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wahl, Tim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wahl, Matt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Firestone, Nora Wahl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diaz, Ed</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Zebby's Zoo (Tv Progam)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E4D81130F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Watch Out Barney! Here Comes Zebby.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Journal column: Zebby's Zoo, believed to be first nationally syndicated children's program conceived and produced on Long Island, developed by siblings Tim, Ed and Matt Wahl and Nora Wahl Firestone, is picked up by America One cable and satellite network; Tim Wahl describes program, featuring Zebby the Zebra, as Sesame Street on steroids; Ed Diaz, celebrating inaugural issue of Latin Long Island, chooses photo of many leaders of local Hispanic community to grace first cover; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOUNG children like to watch the same videos and listen to the same music cassettes over and over again. But repeatedly hearing their syrupy songs often makes parents cringe.</p>
        <p>Enter Tim, Ed, Matt Wahl and Nora Wahl Firestone, siblings nurtured on the music of Van Halen, Madonna and the Grateful Dead, raised watching ''Sesame Street'' and ''The Electric Company.'' If a purple dinosaur named Barney could capture the hearts -- and ears -- of millions of children, why couldn't they come up with a character who could enchant grown-ups too?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOUNG children like to watch the same videos and listen to the same music cassettes over and over again. But repeatedly hearing their syrupy songs often makes parents cringe.</p>
        <p>Enter Tim, Ed, Matt Wahl and Nora Wahl Firestone, siblings nurtured on the music of Van Halen, Madonna and the Grateful Dead, raised watching ''Sesame Street'' and ''The Electric Company.'' If a purple dinosaur named Barney could capture the hearts -- and ears -- of millions of children, why couldn't they come up with a character who could enchant grown-ups too?</p>
        <p>Four years ago, Ed Wahl, 33, a Nassau County police officer, and Matt Wahl, 26, an officer with the New York Police Department, wrote a rock 'n' roll soundtrack, using the same beat as the music they loved growing up in the Plainedge school district. Canvassing the alphabet, the Wahls chose a zebra as their star. Why? It was the only animal they could think of that wasn't already a known character.</p>
        <p>The strategy worked. Recently, ''Zebby's Zoo,'' believed to be the first nationally syndicated children's program conceived and produced on Long Island, was picked up by America One, the cable and satellite network. Added to Telecare, where the show has been broadcast twice a day, five times a week since its inception, and WLIW where it airs Saturday mornings at 7:30, ''Zebby's Zoo'' can now be seen in 62-million homes nationwide.</p>
        <p>''It's 'Sesame Street' on steroids,'' said Tim Wahl, 32, who produces the half-hour show and runs the business end of the fast-growing ''Zebby Zoo'' empire out of his Westbury home. ''It's very simple, but it's what the kids love; it's what the kids want to see,'' he said. ''It's very upbeat. It's something that the parents could really relate to. It's something that's easily tolerated.''</p>
        <p>Even by their mother. There was Karen Wahl, 56, on the stage at the Nassau County Fair in Uniondale recently, dressed in a Zebby the Zebra costume, dancing her way across the stage.</p>
        <p>From across the midway, by stroller and on foot, came the toddler and kindergarten set, gathering at the foot of the stage to sing and dance along with the zebra. ''Do the Zebby, do the Zebby. . . .'' blared from the speakers. While Zebby and a friend, the Lazy Lion, hoofed, Tim Wahl pulled out a table laden with Zebby  T-shirts, audio and video cassettes and Beanie-Baby knockoffs of Zebby.</p>
        <p>Merchandising, after all, is what ''Zebby's Zoo'' is all about.</p>
        <p>The children's entertainment program started with online sales of music cassettes. The characters weren't brought to life until the Wahls created the television show. By then, thousand of videos, cassettes and stuffed animals had been sold.</p>
        <p>''A TV show is developed and promoted and if it is successful, they go to the next step, which is licensing or manufacturing the merchandise,'' Tim Wahl said. ''We went exactly the opposite way. We didn't do it that way by accident. That was our objective. We knew from the beginning that we didn't have the experience in the TV industry and we didn't have the budget to do a Manhattan- style shoot where we could shoot 52 episodes. So we said first things first, let's get people to identify with who the Zebby Zoo character is.''</p>
        <p>Tim Wahl, after all, had been wholesaling 8,000 to 10,000 units a week of licensed ''Sesame Street,'' Barney and Arthur products. He knew the market. His brothers knew music.</p>
        <p>''A lot of the stuff I write in my head while I'm working,'' said Ed Wahl, concentrating on lessons about manners, safety, family values, counting and spelling. He then sings the compositions into his answering machine.</p>
        <p>Along with other partners, the Wahls have invested $350,000 in ''Zebby's Zoo.'' They expect to turn a profit by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>When the Telecare show started, Tim Wahl said, hits to the Zebby Web site -- www.Zebbyszoo.com -- soared. Fans, known as Zebheads, started chat rooms. A live ''Zebby's Zoo'' production at the Westbury Music Fair soon followed. Earlier this year, two shows at the Vanderbilt in Plainview were standing room only at $12 a ticket.</p>
        <p>''We had a solid foundation,'' Tim Wahl said. ''We had 120,000 kids ages 2 to 7 in Nassau and Suffolk county who not only knew who Zebby Zoo was, but they had merchandise in their bedroom they could identify with. We felt that really helped propel the TV show to its popularity.''</p>
        <p>Seven minutes of each episode -- 72 have been made -- are shot on location around the Island, from the Hewlett Fire Department to the Long Island Game Farm in Manorville and the jungle gym in Wantagh Park.</p>
        <p>And Zebby has a new line of sliced white bread, baked at Zebby's Bread Company in Toronto. Already one million 24-ounce loaves have been sold. The bread is available at some Costcos, King Kullens, Farmers Bazaars, Key Foods, C-Towns and Waldbaums. Zebby's doughnuts will be out in the fall.</p>
        <p>And the Wahls are compiling ''Zebby Songs,'' an album of 13 popular songs, like Woody Guthrie's ''This Land is Your Land,'' sung by the zebra. (Several vocalists sing Zebby's role; a search is under way for a single voice.)</p>
        <p>Still, the show is not technologically sophisticated. Animation is done in a friend's basement in Franklin  Square. ''We didn't feel we had to compete with ''Sesame Street'' and Barney,'' said Tim Wahl, looking to take ''Zebby's Zoo'' to the next level.  ''There are always going to be kids. There are always going to be parents. Even if the economy is down, if the parents have $10 in their pockets they are going to buy their kid a toy before they buy themselves lunch. If we can turn on the kids, that's great, but if we can turn on their parents, it's a double whammy.''</p>
        <p>Spanish in English</p>
        <p>For the cover of the inaugural issue of Latin Long Island, Ed Diaz chose a photograph of many of the leaders of the Hispanic community. ''We're here,'' Mr. Diaz said recently at a  party at the Huntington Town House celebrating the launching of the new magazine. ''We're not going anywhere. We want to be recognized.''</p>
        <p>Among the featured movers and shakers: Yvonne Pena, executive director of the Suffolk County Human Rights Commission; Pilar Delgado, staffing coordinator for Sterling Personnel Services in Hauppauge; and Miriam Garcia, executive director of Adelante of Suffolk County, the cultural and civic center in Brentwood that sponsors the Hispanic Day Parade and myriad job training, youth leadership and social services.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of misconceptions and misperceptions about Latinos on Long Island,'' Mr. Diaz said. ''That can be overcome by highlighting the positive in our community. This magazine is about bringing people together.''</p>
        <p>The second issue, due out later this month, will feature Jack Gallagher, chief executive officer of North Shore/LIJ Health Care System. Mr. Gallagher's mother was Colombian.</p>
        <p>Twelve years ago, Mr. Diaz, of Babylon, the owner of a collections agency, helped found the Long Island Hispanic Chamber of Commerce. The glossy new publication, he said, is the next step and the proper venue to both tout the Island's top Hispanics and create a forum to bridge the communications gap between different Latino communities. Latin Long Island, however, is published in English.</p>
        <p>''This magazine will allow people who don't know about the Latino community, who don't read or speak Spanish to read a publication that will highlight the creme de la creme of the Latinos, learn what we are all about and the contributions we make to Long Island, '' Mr. Diaz said. Included among those potential readers of the soon-to-be monthly magazine, he noted, are English-speaking advertising executives who place ads in local Spanish periodicals like Hoy or Noticias but can't read their own copy.</p>
        <p>''I am anxious to overcome some of that ignorance that still is out there,'' Mr. Diaz said. ''Some people will perceive Latinos out of ignorance as unsophisticated, being worthy of only low-paying jobs in restaurants and assembly lines and that not what we're all about.''</p>
        <p>Latinos own more than 5,000 Long Island businesses, come from 26 different countries and live in communities from Riverhead to Freeport, Glen Cove and Brentwood. What they have in common is the Spanish language, although by the second generation, many no longer use it, Mr. Diaz said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Diaz was born in the Bronx. Though his parents spoke Spanish, English was always his main language.</p>
        <p>''In my English-dominant world, practically every person I know here who is Hispanic watches very little Spanish language television and rarely ever reads Spanish language newspapers,'' he said.</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL E-mail address: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
