<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mexico's Third Way</title>
    <meta content="02FOXLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212095"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cardenas, Cuauhtemoc (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox Quesada, Vicente (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labastida Ochoa, Francisco</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berman, Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E2DC1230F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="5392" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mexico's Third Way</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Paul Berman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berman, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paul Berman article on Vincent Fox, rightist candidate in Mexico's presidential election; says Fox is courting leftists in July 2 vote, hoping to take votes away from leftist candidate Cuauhtemoc Cardenas; holds if Fox succeeds in winning trust of voters who would vote for Cardenas, he could put an end to Institutional Revolutionary Party's 71 years of authoritarian rule; PRI candidate is Francisco Labastida; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vicente Fox climbed a podium in the broiling sun at Minatitlan -- a tropical oil town on Mexico's Gulf Coast oozing with heat and petroleum. A few thousand people gazed at him from under their sun umbrellas and straw sombreros. And he cried out in his booming bass voice, ''When is Mexico going to change?''</p>
        <p>Fox is running for president of Mexico in today's election, and the people in the street knew his slogan and shouted it back at him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vicente Fox climbed a podium in the broiling sun at Minatitlan -- a tropical oil town on Mexico's Gulf Coast oozing with heat and petroleum. A few thousand people gazed at him from under their sun umbrellas and straw sombreros. And he cried out in his booming bass voice, ''When is Mexico going to change?''</p>
        <p>Fox is running for president of Mexico in today's election, and the people in the street knew his slogan and shouted it back at him.</p>
        <p>''Today!''</p>
        <p>''When is Minatitlan going to change?''</p>
        <p>Everyone shouted, ''Today!''</p>
        <p>Fox shouted out denunciations of Mexico's Institutional Revolutionary Party, or PRI. The PRI has been governing Mexico for 71 years. The PRI is the world's oldest continuously ruling party. It is a tired old dinosaur, dragging its tail through the dust.</p>
        <p>''They are corrupt!'' he shouted, and the r's in the Spanish corruptos trilled through the loudspeakers. Fox said that 40 million Mexicans live in the most wretched poverty. Millions more have fled to the United States, where they are persecuted and mistreated. Those are the PRI's achievements! He talked about Mexico's presidential palace, Los Pinos. ''When are we going to drag the PRI out of Los Pinos?''</p>
        <p>And Vicente Fox Quesada and the people of Minatitlan began to chant, ''Today! Today! Today!''</p>
        <p>Those were campaign slogans. But Fox's question -- When is Mexico going to change?'' -- is a question that, in a quieter mood, ordinary Mexicans have been asking themselves for a long time. People get wistful on the topic. They say -- they have said to me a hundred times -- Mexico is rich. We have oil, agriculture, industry. We have a good and honest people. We are creative. We have an artistic soul. So why is Mexico stuck where it is: poor, fearful, awash in baroque crimes and gargantuan bank scandals?''</p>
        <p>Mexicans are perfectly aware that all over the world in the last dozen years, one country after another has shaken off the oppression of the ages, has overthrown its authoritarian government and has sometimes lifted itself out of poverty too. Fox plays on that awareness. He invokes the names of Nelson Mandela and Lech Walesa. When he cries out, ''When will Mexico change?'' he wants people to think, ''When Vicente Fox gets into power.'' He wants them to swell with hope. And they do. They shout, ''Today!'' But you can almost hear them adding, in a dark tone of fatalism, ''Maybe!''</p>
        <p>For how else can Mexicans feel? They have had their hopes raised before. Twelve years ago, in 1988, one of the princes of the PRI, Cuauhtemoc Cardenas Solorzano, having defected from the old party, ran for president as an opposition candidate with support from the left. That time, the feeling of hope was sharp and fiery. Cardenas won the election, or so it is thought by a good many people. But the PRI is a past master at election frauds. The vote-counters announced a computer crash. The PRI's candidate, Carlos Salinas de Gortari, was declared the winner. And Salinas's circle turned out to be spectacularly corrupt, and slightly murderous to boot.</p>
        <p>In the 1994 election, people again began to imagine that, at last, the PRI might get overthrown. Cardenas, the old hero from 1988, had lost some of his sheen by then -- partly because a wave of killings during the Salinas years had decimated his left-wing party. But in Mexico there has always been a right-wing opposition, too, the National Action party, which is Catholic and pro-business. In 1994, someone from National Action stepped forward to lead the new crusade -- a dapper, bearded politician named Diego Fernandez de Cevallos, who seemed to be a man of talent.</p>
        <p>That year, as in 1988, I watched the goings-on. I remember Diego Fernandez's face glowing from a television screen in a Coyoacan cantina, and the whole room shouting ''Diego!'' Yet, just when Diego Fernandez seemed to be doing pretty well against the PRI, he stopped campaigning; no one knows why. The PRI sailed to victory yet again. Ernesto Zedillo became president. And ordinary Mexicans sank still deeper into the gray swamp that surrounds authoritarian societies everywhere -- the miasmas of resignation and cynicism, streaked with bizarre and sinister conspiracy theories and brightly colored millenarian fantasies that cannot possibly come to pass.</p>
        <p>In the years after Cardenas's powerful showing in the 1988 race, Mexico did, in its timid way, begin to change. The PRI was always a giant octopus of an organization, with business interests, state enterprises, its own labor unions, street mobs and mass organizations of the poor and a dozen other tentacles, known and unknown, all of them attached to the octopus's head, which consists of money and corruption. Even today, the old organization makes a fairly open habit of buying votes in poor neighborhoods. The PRI's candidate for president in today's election, Francisco Labastida Ochoa, has shown no embarrassment at all in surrounding himself with some of the shadiest faces from the PRI's old guard.</p>
        <p>And yet, the democratic breeze has been blowing for a long time now, and the PRI has had to bend with the wind. The old party has allowed one and another opposition politician to win local elections in the last few years, including Cardenas, who became the mayor of Mexico City, and Vicente Fox, who became the governor of Guanajuato state. Freedom of the press, which used to be minimal, has become more than minimal. And so the PRI has ended up weaker and more vulnerable, and the opposition has grown bigger and richer (no small thing). And this time, in Fox, the opposition has found a candidate who is sensational even in his looks.</p>
        <p>For as everyone loves to notice, Vicente Fox, at a rugged 58, is the Marlboro Man. He wears black cowboy boots. His belt buckle, in a slightly ominous touch, touts the oversize letters FOX. His mighty shoulders point like ax blades in either direction. His chin is a steel prow, cutting the air. Every bristly hair of his Dapper Dan mustache expresses impudence. The crown of his head stands a full 6 feet 6 inches above the ground. He is a giant. And that is only half the story.</p>
        <p>Fox wears his big leather boots because, having grown up on a farm, the rancher's manner is his by right. But having studied with the Jesuits, he left the farm behind and took up a career in business. And because some cliches are, in their boundlessness, positively sinister, the Marlboro Man steadily rose in the world until he had become the president of Coca-Cola in its Mexican branch.</p>
        <p>When he shifted over to politics, he enlisted in National Action, the right-wing party. But he also cleverly applied a few soft-drink marketing methods to constructing a parallel organization of his own, the Friends of Fox, in order to keep a distance from the pesky barons and troglodytic ideologues of National Action. He raised money, apparently with no trouble at all (though his enemies complain about foul play). And he has shown that he knows how to work a crowd.</p>
        <p>I rode in his campaign bus into villa isla, a few miles from Minatitlan, where his local organizers had gathered a few thousand people together with a long row of farm tractors. Fox shook a couple of hands. He strode over to the first of those tractors and climbed into the driver's seat. He clapped a straw sombrero on his head. And right away he began, very slowly, to drive.</p>
        <p>The tractor was a big green John Deere with rear wheels five feet tall, and it was surrounded on all sides by the jostling crowd, which made driving a delicate business. But he pushed forward. And with one hand on the wheel, guiding his tractor through the human sea, Fox raised his free hand in the V sign, which is a symbol of his campaign. The crowd roared. And down the street he went, the conquering general, riding in triumph on his white steed, which happened to be a green tractor.</p>
        <p>It was quite a stunt. It was the performance of a man who really might get himself elected president -- cheerful, confident, well organized, efficient with time. And so, as any number of Mexicans have come to believe, in today's election the moment for change on the biggest of scales may finally have arrived. Every single condition for a democratic transition at the national level seems to be at hand: a popular disgust for the PRI, a lust for change, a feeling of freedom, a smaller likelihood of large-scale fraud and an opposition leader who radiates brio with every oversize step he takes.</p>
        <p>There is only one problem. Vicente Fox is not the only well-liked insurgent running for president. Cuauhtemoc Cardenas is also running. No one seriously believes that Cardenas can win, though his supporters sometimes convince themselves otherwise. His poll statistics dropped into single figures just a few months ago. But many millions of people in Mexico will always have a place in their hearts for the wronged and defrauded hero of 1988, and his poll statistics began to rise. He still can't win, short of a miracle. But if his numbers climb high enough, he will guarantee that Fox can't win, either. And the PRI will triumph once again.</p>
        <p>When will Mexico change? This year, the question can be answered with exactitude. Mexico will change when enough people among the opposition democrats, on the right and left, agree to pull together against the PRI. You might imagine that, in our postideological age, a principled alliance of right and left would have been easily enough arranged. In any number of countries around the world during the last dozen years, democratic revolutions have succeeded precisely because of that kind of coalition. In 1990, coalitions of the democratic right and left overthrew the governments of Augusto Pinochet in Chile and the Sandinistas in Nicaragua. It was the same in Eastern Europe in 1989, where some of the anti-Communist dissidents were social democrats and others were free-market Thatcherites.</p>
        <p>In Mexico, Fox and Cardenas did entertain the same idea. Their emissaries negotiated, and in the southern state of Chiapas the two parties managed to come up with a single candidate for governor. But no such luck at the national level. It could even be that by the time you read this article, some 11th-hour maneuver might have taken place, and Cardenas or some of his allies might have thrown their support to Fox. But even if some such alliance did take shape, it is impossible to imagine Cardenas and his allies working up any enthusiasm for Fox. So the real decision will have to be made by the voters themselves, with or without their leaders -- by many thousands of ordinary Mexicans who might normally prefer to vote for Cardenas and the left but who will now have to consider voting, in the name of democracy, for Fox, the right-wing cowboy.</p>
        <p>One day I visited Cuauhtemoc Cardenas in his campaign headquarters. I told him, in all sincerity, that he was the hero of Mexican democracy, due to his race in 1988 and his dignity afterward. And I asked if he didn't worry that by splitting the opposition, he was going to bring his heroic career to a tragic end. My premise was that Fox's victory would represent an obvious forward step for democracy. But Cardenas didn't agree, for reasons that mirror a crucial ambiguity that you find among a lot of people in the Mexican left. If you ask those people to explain why they hate the PRI, sometimes they will say: because the PRI is corrupt and dictatorial. But other times they will fall into an old-fashioned, left-wing style of thinking, which looks on economics as the foundation of life and on politics as secondary. When they slip into that particular mood, Mexico's leftists are likely to say: we despise the PRI because it is the agent of the rich.</p>
        <p>From Cardenas's perspective, the PRI wasn't so bad until the early 1980's, when it began privatizing the old state economy. But from that point of view, Fox's National Action offers very little alternative. National Action is strictly pro-business, and given its druthers, would surely privatize everything in sight. National Action and the PRI disagree on many things, but on macroeconomic issues, their instincts are the same.</p>
        <p>Now, you might suppose that after all these years the Mexican left could tell at a glance the difference between a corrupt, authoritarian octopus like the PRI and an ordinary pro-business party like National Action, even if both parties speak the language of market economics. But the Mexican left has modern moods and antique moods, and when antiquity prevails, the left sees no difference at all. That was Cardenas's position. He said about Fox, ''I don't think he represents the real and deep change that Mexico needs.''</p>
        <p>Cardenas had a deeper worry, too -- a gut belief that, even apart from economic policy, Fox is no democrat at all. It is because of his tempestuousness and because of the crafty shifts in his campaign positions. Cardenas worried about National Action and its old-fashioned Catholic prudery and its line on abortion and other sexual questions.</p>
        <p>And this gut belief of Cardenas's, as I discovered, was by no means his alone. I visited the new mayor of Mexico City, Rosario Robles Berlanga, who took over City Hall after Cardenas resigned to run for president. Robles is a vigorous woman in her mid-40's, a big talent who has made herself tremendously popular in no time flat -- someone with a real possibility of becoming a presidential contender herself six years from now on a left-wing ticket. She told me that in her judgment Fox is an authoritarian-in-waiting. ''There is no difference between him and Fujimori,'' she said, referring to the Peruvian strongman.</p>
        <p>I visited Carmen Boullosa, who is one of Mexico's liveliest literary figures. Fox reminded Boullosa of the macho Catholic authoritarians she knew as a child, against whom she had to rebel -- the kind of figure who has always blocked the door to any kind of modern life. I visited Marta Lamas, Mexico's leading feminist and the editor of ''Debate Feminista.'' Lamas nearly exploded at Fox's name. She saw in him a threat to every forward step that women have taken in Mexico, a threat so large and dangerous that, unlike all the other left-wingers with whom I spoke, she said that six more years of a lamentable PRI dictatorship would suit her better than a wild experiment with Vicente Fox as president.</p>
        <p>The whole attitude was expressed in detail by Carlos Monsivais, the cultural critic, in the weekly magazine Proceso and again over coffee and Coke. Monsivais looked on Fox as the worst sort of Catholic reactionary. He had gathered together an alarming collection of quotations to prove it, too: Fox complaining about the useful laws that long ago defined the secular state; Fox criticizing the lay character of public education; Fox saying he wants the schools to teach religious values, meaning Catholic values. Monsivais observed that on matters of abortion, Fox has expressed a hostility even to the extreme cases, like the rape of a child, where Mexican law does permit the procedure. Fox on homosexuality: ''A degenerate act which goes against human nature.''</p>
        <p>Monsivais saw a dangerous messianism in Fox. It bothered him no end that Fox began his campaign by hoisting the banner of the Virgin of Guadalupe, the ancient symbol of Mexico's Catholic extreme right. But then, for all his hair-raising quotations, Monsivais wouldn't go so far as Lamas, the feminist. He looked on Fox as horrible, and on the PRI as even more horrible. It was just that Monsivais couldn't possibly bring himself to vote for the lesser of two horribles. He told me he was going to vote for Cardenas and hope for the best.</p>
        <p>That sort of reaction has not gone unnoticed among Fox's advisers. And so, in the latter days of the campaign, Fox set out to undo some of his more disastrous gestures to the extreme right. The banner of the Virgin of Guadalupe was quietly put away. In one of his television debates, Fox poured words of praise on the Mexican left for its historic role in opposing the PRI. He praised the student uprising of 1968. He praised Cardenas himself for his battles on behalf of democracy.</p>
        <p>It is true that in trying to soothe the ruffled left, Fox also managed now and then to hurl a few unforgivable personal insults. I watched him stand up in Veracruz and call Cardenas a traitor to his own party for refusing to withdraw from the race. He insulted Cardenas's mother. A bad move! Still, he calmed down and resumed his courtship, with an occasional success. A group of some 30 left-wingers announced that they were endorsing Fox in spite of their philosophical differences. Those were serious radicals -- people from the defunct Mexican Communist Party and from the '68 student rebellion. They held a meeting in Mexico City, and Fox stood on the podium and pushed his courtship even further. In a sober tone, as if swearing an oath to the entire public, he promised not to do any of the scary things, point by point, that he had been accused of wanting to do.</p>
        <p>''I commit myself to maintain the lay character of the Mexican state and public education,'' he said. ''I commit myself to maintain the liberty, diversity and pluralism of Mexican society and never to use the power of the state to impose lifestyles, religious beliefs or codes of personal behavior. To respect the liberty of creation, of culture and of expression of all the groups who form Mexican society.''</p>
        <p>He promised to limit the power of the presidency, which, under the PRI, has been almost monarchical. He promised to make the struggle against poverty and inequality the ''supreme priority'' of his new government. And he absolutely promised not to do what, in the past, he has always been itching to do, which is to privatize Mexico's state oil company, Pemex.</p>
        <p>It was everything he could possibly do to placate the left, short of cutting off a hand. But the response among a good many left-wingers was, I must say, to recoil from Fox even more violently than before -- as if he had now revealed himself to be not just a dangerous reactionary but a dangerous liar too, a man without any principles whatsoever, not even reactionary principles.</p>
        <p>It should be added that Fox's enemies on the left have not been the only people to glance in his direction and worry. Enrique Krauze is Mexico's leading historian and one of its most eloquent defenders of liberal democratic ideas, and in May he published his own estimation of Fox. It was a balanced appraisal, not entirely condemning Fox but fretting about his political background. Krauze reminded his readers that during the 1920's, thousands of peasants in central Mexico rebelled against the anticlerical wing of Mexico's Revolution and in the name of Christ the King went to war. They were known as the Cristeros, from the Spanish for Christ. The war was a calamity.</p>
        <p>Fox, as Krauze saw him, comes out of the fiercest of the Cristero districts and has always nursed a vivid and slightly alarming nostalgia for Cristero values. Then, too, Krauze observed that Fox went to visit Fidel Castro not long ago and came away full of praise. That was not exactly a right-wing thing to do. Krauze found it worrisome, though.</p>
        <p>There is, of course, one other group that has been steadily tossing its own criticisms at Fox. An internal dossier of Francisco Labastida's PRI campaign has fallen into my hands -- a book-length analysis of Fox, part of which appears to have been written by a psychologist, in the grimmest of terms: ''An obsessive character, possibly associated with messianic delirium,'' not to mention misogyny and authoritarianism. And, sure enough, no sooner did I leaf through the PRI dossier than I began to notice attacks of that nature on Fox's character appearing in the press. It was even suggested, somewhat indirectly, that Fox is not only a madman but also a fascist.</p>
        <p>Labastida spoke at a PRI rally in Jalisco. ''Long live liberty and long live tolerance!'' cried the candidate of the world's oldest ruling party. ''Let's not let reaction, intolerance and fascism spread!''</p>
        <p>So is Vicente Fox the hope for Mexican democracy? or, if you will pardon the pun, is Fox a wolf in sheep's clothing? I cannot peer into his head to identify his actual intentions. But I have been able to observe him and chat with him on a number of occasions. And I can offer an impression. His personal values on questions of abortion, homosexuality and the importance of religious education came to him from his Jesuit upbringing, in the conservative environment that Krauze has described. Those ideas are not going to change.</p>
        <p>Even now he collects books on Cristero themes. But business became his passion. When he changed course in life and became a politician for National Action, he had no difficulty in squaring his antique Catholic sentiments with his modern business ideas. National Action has always had its Catholic nostalgias. The party was organized in 1939 to fight against the leftward tilt of the Mexican Revolution, and its early sympathies veered toward Generalissimo Franco in Spain. Franco's Falange wore blue shirts and so did Mexico's National Action. Still, the old fascists in Spain have mostly evolved into democratic conservatives. And in Mexico, National Action, which was never entirely fascist, likewise evolved -- from the party of Christ the King to the Catholic party of business and democracy.</p>
        <p>Fox himself shows the evolution. as soon as he opens his mouth, it becomes obvious that he despises the PRI -- despises it with a quick, hot passion that endears him to ordinary people. He remembers the PRI's murders, massacres and corruption. But mostly he hates the PRI because it has run Mexico's economy badly. He is an outraged businessman. And then, having evolved into a businessman-politician, he adopted one more set of ideas, which you don't find anywhere else in National Action.</p>
        <p>This last set of inspirations came to him from an unhappy experience in his first, unsuccessful race for the governorship of Guanajuato state, back in 1991. The PRI converted that particular election into an obvious fraud. Fox mounted a furious protest. And he found himself standing shoulder to shoulder with a number of activists from the left, Cardenas's supporters, who were campaigning for a modern electoral system. One of those people was Jorge G. Castaneda, a political writer who is well known in the United States as a commentator on Mexican affairs and as a professor at New York University.</p>
        <p>In 1991, Castaneda was an ambitious young man from an elite but slightly peculiar background. His father had been foreign minister for the PRI. He himself had spent a few years in the Mexican Communist Party. By the time he met Fox, though, the young Castaneda had given up on Communism and was hard at work trying to rethink the whole concept of leftism and its goals. His research led him to still another Latin American professor in the United States, Roberto Mangabeira Unger, a Brazilian who teaches at Harvard.</p>
        <p>Mangabeira Unger had soured on the traditional left-wing dream of a giant social-welfare state. He wanted Latin America's left-wing movements to build smaller and more efficient states that would use market methods to improve the condition of the poor -- to harness higher taxes to the methods of the pro-business right, in order to achieve the egalitarian goals of the left. Mangabeira Unger was a Latin American theorist of what only later has come to be known as the Third Way.</p>
        <p>Castaneda picked up on those ideas, and he and Fox began to talk. Castaneda introduced Fox to Mangabeira Unger. And Fox became entranced with the notion of using his Coca-Cola skills to do what the PRI in recent decades has never been able to do: achieve something lasting for the poor.</p>
        <p>Those are the ideas that seem to fire up Fox's imagination. When I spoke with him two years ago, he nattered on about economics, market programs to help the poor, democracy and corruption. Riding around with him on the campaign bus in the last weeks of his campaign, I must have watched Fox deliver a dozen speeches to audiences of every kind, and those speeches, too, hit the same notes. Sometimes he stressed the importance of labor unions -- real unions, run by their own members, instead of the state unions that are run by the PRI.</p>
        <p>Late one night on the bus, when everyone seemed to be nodding off except the driver and the candidate, I took the seat next to him at the front of the bus and asked him about Fidel Castro. Fox told me that he genuinely admired Castro's achievements in public education, in creating ''human capital.'' But what most caught Fox's imagination in Cuba seemed to be how beautifully Castro has restored a portion of downtown Havana. ''That kind of thing is valuable for tourism,'' he explained, as if everything ought to have its business justification. He reflected on Mexico City and its failure to capitalize on the tourist potential.</p>
        <p>The bus was hurtling through darkness, with no cars on the highway and no houses on the side. We pulled up at a toll booth, and Fox interrupted our chat to lean out the window and flash his V sign at the astonished toll collectors and win two more votes.</p>
        <p>Then he wanted to talk about an interesting system for spreading financial credit to the very poor that he has seen in Bangladesh. He is a big fan of what he calls ''microenterprises,'' the tiny businesses of the poor. And he veered into a discussion of the international business of freelance political consultants -- people like Dick Morris, who struck Fox as rather creative, and James Carville, who struck him as less creative (and who has gone to work for the PRI). But can foreign consultants make any sense of Mexican politics? ''I don't think they have a nose for Mexico,'' he said. Fox hired his own consultant from the ranks of Mexico's Coca-Cola. And such was the conversation: business, politics, business and more business.</p>
        <p>In my hearing, he never did harp on what, in the United States, are called ''family values'' or ''Christian values.'' Those were simply not his campaign themes. Still, I did hear him let rip more than once with a slogan from the Cristero fanatics of the 1920's. He said: ''If I advance, follow me! If I hold back, push me! If I retreat, kill me!'' Which does sound a little extreme. And there you have the problem with Vicente Fox. He dreams a businessman's vision of a modern Mexico. But now and then, when the moon comes out, he reverts to his old nostalgias. He can't help himself.</p>
        <p>Most of the people who line up to hear him speak aren't thinking about religious questions or about sexual and cultural controversies. They want him to lambaste the PRI and to lay out his business ideas, which sound so much more inventive and impassioned than anyone else's. But there are any number of historical-minded people whose ears twitch at the sound of those ancient Cristero slogans and who begin to reflect that Fox's National Action does contain a number of genuine fanatics of the old-fashioned Catholic right. Which is true; I've met them.</p>
        <p>And so the worries begin. Fox has only himself to blame. But it must be said that in Mexico's left-wing opposition, he and his National Action have met their counterpart. For the Mexican left is likewise a mix of modern ideas and old-fashioned prejudices. And under the pressure of a desperately close election, Mexico's right-wing party and its left-wing party have, between them, ended up refighting the Cristero War of the 1920's, or perhaps the Spanish Civil War of the 1930's -- the eternal battle of class-struggle left-wingers against the warriors of Christ the King. And they have managed to forget that the largest and most intractable of Mexico's problems today don't come from Catholic fanatics or from anti-Catholic fanatics but from a corrupt authoritarianism whose end could be easily arranged -- if only the right and the left would stop their quarreling.</p>
        <p>What Mexico needs, you might suppose, are some lucid intellectuals, capable of dragging their own political movements into modern times. All over the world in the last dozen years, when authoritarian governments have been overthrown, the intellectuals have been in the forefront, and a few of them have even become political leaders. Vaclav Havel, the Czech hipster, is the supreme example. But Mexico is not like other countries. Mexico's intellectuals can boast of one of the world's most brilliant literary cultures, and they bask in prestige and wield influence and have always received handsome subsidies, in one form or another, from the state, which means, the PRI. The subsidies have not exactly made them slaves either.</p>
        <p>On the contrary, most of Mexico's intellectuals vociferously oppose the PRI. But the greatest number of them do so by supporting C1/3rdenas, even if he can't win. Some of them support an utterly marginal left-wing politician named Gilberto Rincon Gallardo, whose poll statistics hover around 2 percent. And only a handful have supported Fox -- joined in the last days of the campaign by a reluctant and slightly larger number. It is an amazing situation, given how much hangs on this election. But the most striking phenomenon in this campaign has been an outpouring of articles and op-eds supporting democracy in general -- essays so watery and indistinct that you could easily conclude that democracy must be already well established and that the PRI must be no less democratic than any other political organization and that it hardly matters whom you vote for, so long as you vote.</p>
        <p>Carlos Fuentes is the most prestigious of the literary intellectuals, and he has made himself a master of such watery endorsements. ''Vote for yourself,'' he wrote. And so Mexico teeters on the edge of an enormous decision -- teeters on the brink of achieving, through peaceful and legal means, a democratic transition of power in the world's largest Spanish-speaking country. And because Fox is an outsider among the intellectuals and because Fox's background has some worrisome aspects, the overwhelming majority of intellectuals have found all kinds of rhetorically elaborate ways to remain safely on the sidelines.</p>
        <p>When will Mexico change? What can surely be predicted is that in today's election Mexico will undergo either a larger tragedy or a smaller tragedy. The larger tragedy will come about if the Mexicans simply cannot figure out how to escape the only political party they have ever known. The smaller tragedy will come about if, in spite of every obstacle, Vicente Fox does succeed in defeating the PRI. Fox will move into Los Pinos. And he will discover that bringing democracy to Mexico is going to be harder than it ought to be, if only because he and the rest of Mexico's democrats are still caught up in ancient myths and feuds, and people who should be his allies aren't.</p>
        <p>Paul Berman is the author of ''A Tale of Two Utopias: The Political Journey of the Generation of 1968.'' His article on Cuauhtemoc C1/3rdenas appeared in the magazine in August 1998.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Paul Berman is the author of ''A Tale of Two Utopias: The Political Journey of the Generation of 1968.'' His article on Cuauhtemoc C1/3rdenas appeared in the magazine in August 1998.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
