<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Press Baron's Progress</title>
    <meta content="02EVA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212068"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evans, Harold</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nasaw, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hearst, William Randolph Sr (1863-1951)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Chief, The: the Life of William Randolph Hearst (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E4D91E31F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1556" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Press Baron's Progress</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Harold Evans</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Evans, Harold</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harold Evans reviews book The Chief: The Life of William Randolph Hearst by David Nasaw; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE CHIEF</p>
        <p>The Life of William Randolph Hearst.</p>
        <p>By David Nasaw.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 687 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. $35.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE CHIEF</p>
        <p>The Life of William Randolph Hearst.</p>
        <p>By David Nasaw.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 687 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. $35.</p>
        <p>We all know how the publishing tycoon William Randolph Hearst ends his days. He is a hollow hulk of a man entombed in a Charles Addams mausoleum of art. Even his drunken harpy of a mistress has abandoned him. He shuffles toward death through Xanadu's darkened galleries, his impotence mocked by the statuary he has spent a lifetime lifting from the palaces of Europe. That, of course, was Orson Welles in the movie ''Citizen Kane,'' but for most of us Charles Foster Kane and William Randolph Hearst are indistinguishable; they morphed into the archetype of the demagogic press baron who menaces democracy by cynical manipulation and enriches himself in the process.</p>
        <p>''Citizen Kane'' happens to be a distorted portrait of Hearst, but it has for generations suborned our perceptions because Kane was created by an artist. History has more to fear from an artist than a hack. We see Richard III as a ''poisonous hunch-back'd toad,'' though he didn't have a hunchback at all, because Shakespeare's intent was to epitomize evil and its inevitable retribution. Welles, similarly, cannot allow his monster to depart, as he did in truth, amid light and flowers at San Simeon, entertained in his final happy years by the wittiest people in the world, attended to devotedly by Marion Davies, his movie-star companion of 35 years, because that finale would suggest redemption for a man who had betrayed the socialist ideals dear to the young Welles.</p>
        <p>David Nasaw's absorbing and ingeniously organized new biography might finally rescue Hearst from the curse of Kane. ''The Chief'' is not an authorized biography, but the Hearst family and the Hearst Corporation gave Nasaw, a history professor at the City University of New York, the keys to personal papers stored in a Bronx warehouse since the 1920's, and the San Simeon papers secured in a ranch bunkhouse after W. R.'s death in 1951 at the age of 88.</p>
        <p>Nasaw was a good choice. He is a meticulous researcher and a cool analyst. His Hearst is altogether a larger, more sympathetic figure than the vindictive, humorless crypto-fascist seen by the left. He does not exculpate Hearst, the propagandist who signed up Hitler and Mussolini and flayed Franklin D. Roosevelt as a Communist dupe. He explains him and makes him human. We empathize with him as a lover in his 80's writing poems to Davies, whose descent into alcoholism all but broke his heart. We are entertained by paradox. Nasaw shows us a tyrant who is always courteous to his staff, so personally gentle he cannot bring himself to sack the hopelessly incompetent. He spends fastidious millions on his dream homes but instructs his staff to trap mice live so they can be set free on the grounds. He is a pioneer of slash-and-burn assaults on public figures who draws the line at ferreting into private lives.</p>
        <p>Nasaw's new material enables him to answer questions that have intrigued earlier biographers. Why did the politically ambitious George Hearst, his forty-niner father, yield W. R. control of The San Francisco Examiner? W. R. was a party-loving Harvard dropout of 23, a chorus girl on each arm. His approach to scholarship, to the distress of both his parents, was to send customized chamber pots to his professors, each pot elaborately embossed on the inside bottom with the professor's name. Nasaw's convincing answer is that The Examiner was the bribe to break up their son's infatuation with an aspiring actress, Eleanor Calhoun, who they thought was digging for gold through her bedchamber.</p>
        <p>The Examiner was going nowhere, anyway, so how did the boy publisher succeed so brilliantly? Nasaw demonstrates that he did not just buy his way up. In the crucial years, after his father's death in 1891, he had to beg for money from his schoolmarm mother, Phoebe, who inherited every cent of his father's fortune, and he paid a price. Before Phoebe agreed to let him have $150,000 to buy the failing New York Journal in 1895, he had to give up another companion, Tessie Powers, a waitress he'd met in Cambridge and lived with for nearly a decade.</p>
        <p>The measure of Hearst's triumph is that when he takes over The Examiner in 1887 he has 15,000 readers, and by his middle years he has 20 million or more. As the Chief, he was dictating editorial policy and news for 28 newspapers, a wire service and radio stations, producing innovative newsreels, controlling a magazine empire and running the Cosmopolitan film studio as one of the most successful Hollywood movie producers in the 20's. On the way, he invents synergy between print and film, insisting that his magazine short-story writers give him the option on movie rights; produces the first moving picture serials, including ''The Perils of Pauline''; builds fabulous houses, amazing the architects with his ability to carry multiple blueprints in his head; wins the mayoral race in New York, only to be robbed by Tammany Hall fraud; serves two terms in Congress; comes in second in the balloting for president at the 1904 Democratic convention; and has a lot of fun.</p>
        <p>Rupert Murdoch's rise is the only modern parallel. He, too, started with a single inherited newspaper and dared to win in multimedia, though Murdoch has never run for public office -- or, for that matter, written his own columns and interviews. W. R. was a delightful writer and a keen observer. This is how he described his contemporary Lord Northcliffe, the true creator of tabloid journalism: ''Imagine a face that presents a mixture of Napoleon, Edison and the left-hand cherub leaning over the frame of Raphael's Sistine Madonna.'' W. R. had an eye for talent, but he was inventive himself. He was insistent on news as narrative. When there was no news, he made it with campaigns and investigations. He was for three decades flamboyantly on the side of the people, the immigrants and the unions -- against the octopus in California, the Southern Pacific Railroad; against the bosses of Tammany Hall, against the banks and Wall Street, against the trusts and their Republican puppets. How they hated him! As it was said of William Jennings Bryan, his onetime ally, probably no man in civil life has exerted so much terror without taking life.</p>
        <p>Why did the tribune of the people become the crusader for capitalism? It was not just hardening of the arteries. Nasaw suggests that the turning point was the bloodshed in 1934, when the phony peace between capital and labor ended in pitched battles and gunfire across the country. Hearst feared that revolutionary excesses would generate a homegrown fascist movement that would destroy American democracy. Traveling in a fleet of black limousines through southern and central Europe, he saw firsthand how Nazism and Fascism had been spawned as an antidote to Communism. The messages Nasaw examined reveal how relentless Hearst became in enforcing execution of his command to fight Communism. ''It is time to call in the cockroach man,'' he instructed his editorial director. So Hearst reporters, posing as students, set out to entrap ''un-American'' university professors, unleashing in every city with a Hearst newspaper a witch hunt that lasted 20 years.</p>
        <p>Toward the end of his life, Nasaw says, W. R. relented. He was appalled when his papers shared their files with Joe McCarthy. On the eve of his 87th birthday, he directed his editors to back off the anti-Communist campaign because it was irritating people and ''might be arousing war hysteria.'' Typically, he ended: ''This is a must for all the papers. These instructions must be obeyed to the letter.'' Untypically, his empire carried on as before, the twitchings of a dying beast.</p>
        <p>Nasaw's explanation of Hearst's anti-Communism is credible, but it is harder to swallow W. R.'s response to Hitler and Mussolini. It was one thing to commission them as columnists. (It's satisfying to learn that the greedy Musso -- $1,500 a crack, or $15,000 in today's currency -- could not write, and that Hitler always missed his deadlines.) It was another to cable his New York editors to make the Berlin correspondent's coverage of the Nazis more favorable: ''Von Wiegand articles and cables seem too incendiary. Think he should be instructed to send generally interesting news without partisanship.'' The Hearst press did report the Nazi violence, rather more than The Times of London under Geoffrey Dawson, and in a private meeting with Hitler in 1934, Hearst did make a personal appeal for the Jews. But he gravely misjudged his man. It was a singular failure that he was blind to the realities of Nazi rule and Nazi anti-Semitism. His isolationism was one of the key factors in America's fatal hesitation before the world blew up.</p>
        <p>At the end of his examination of all the material, Nasaw confesses that Hearst's confidence in Hitler remains ''baffling.'' The conclusion is symptomatic of the scrupulous honesty that distinguishes this biography of the most powerful publisher America has ever known: Welles got that part right.</p>
        <p>Harold Evans is the former editor of The Sunday Times and The Times of London. His most recent book is ''The American Century.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Harold Evans is the former editor of The Sunday Times and The Times of London. His most recent book is ''The American Century.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
