<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sainthood Quest for Knight of the Church</title>
    <meta content="02SAIN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212164"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beatifications and Canonizations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Knights of Columbus</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'donnell, Gabriel (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgivney, Michael J (Rev) (1852-1890)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beatifications and Canonizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E0DA1130F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1358" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sainthood Quest for Knight of the Church</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CYNTHIA WOLFE BOYNTON</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on efforts by Dominican friar, Rev Gabriel O'Donnell, hired by Knights of Columbus in 1997, to present and defend evidence to Vatican that organization's founder, Rev Michael J McGivney, should be named saint; biographical sketch of McGivney, who was born in Waterbury, Conn, in August 1852; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To his supporters, the Rev. Michael J. McGivney is nothing less than a saint. To get the Vatican to see it that way, now they have to prove it.</p>
        <p>Father McGivney, who was born in Waterbury in 1852 and died in Thomaston in 1890, founded the Knights of Columbus in New Haven in 1882. The Knights, with 1.6 million members worldwide, have been working since 1982 to get Rome to canonize him. In 1997 the organization hired the Rev. Gabriel O'Donnell, a Dominican friar, as postulator of the effort. The postulator is the church official who presents, and defends, to the Vatican evidence of a person's worthiness for sainthood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To his supporters, the Rev. Michael J. McGivney is nothing less than a saint. To get the Vatican to see it that way, now they have to prove it.</p>
        <p>Father McGivney, who was born in Waterbury in 1852 and died in Thomaston in 1890, founded the Knights of Columbus in New Haven in 1882. The Knights, with 1.6 million members worldwide, have been working since 1982 to get Rome to canonize him. In 1997 the organization hired the Rev. Gabriel O'Donnell, a Dominican friar, as postulator of the effort. The postulator is the church official who presents, and defends, to the Vatican evidence of a person's worthiness for sainthood.</p>
        <p>If Father McGivney is canonized by the Pope, he would be only the fourth American ever to be named a saint and the first from Connecticut. The first American given sainthood was Sister Elizabeth Anne Seton in 1988.</p>
        <p>''To say it's an awesome task is an understatement,'' said Father O'Donnell. ''For the past three years, all my energy has been focused on getting to know Father McGivney and spreading the word about his work while at the same time following strict Vatican procedures. To get an idea of how detailed this process is, before I could officially start working as postulator, I had to attend a six-month canonization class conducted by the Congregation for the Causes of Saints in Rome that outlines everything you need to know and do. It's mandatory for all postulators. And I still have years of work ahead of me.''</p>
        <p>The first phase of the canonization process was completed in April, when the Vatican accepted a spiritual biography of Father McGivney. The 760-page document, written by Father O'Donnell, took close to a decade to complete. It contains an almost daily accounting of Father McGivney's activities, from the start of his ministry in 1877 at St. Mary's Church in New Haven, to his death in 1890 in Thomaston. Testimonies from people who believe in his holiness, and today pray to him for divine intercession, are also included, along with journal entries, letters, photographs and newspaper clippings.</p>
        <p>Father O'Donnell hand-delivered to cardinals in Rome three copies of the document. Following Vatican rules, each was publicly wrapped in white paper and red ribbons, and placed in cardboard boxes tied with string. Hot wax was used to seal and secure the packages. Father O'Donnell said it is a ritual that assures the documents are authentic.</p>
        <p>It is also representative of the long and tedious process that canonization requires.</p>
        <p>''To say it's an awesome task is an understatement,'' said Father O'Donnell. ''It's an incredible and exciting time for Catholics and all people here. Father McGivney was an amazing man. He lived what he preached, which was for selfless service to others.''</p>
        <p>The quest to canonize Father McGivney began nearly a century after his death from pneumonia and tuberculosis. It is an effort being led by the 22,000-member Father McGivney Guild, an offshoot of the Knights of Columbus. As part of their mission, guild members regularly pray to Father McGivney, distribute prayer cards that have been touched to a relic of the priest, and share stories about his life.</p>
        <p>''His followers are rightly devoted,'' said the head of the Knights of Columbus, Virgil Dechant from the organization's international headquarters in New Haven. ''Through the Knights,'' he said, ''Father McGivney's vision touches and betters the world.''</p>
        <p>The son of Irish immigrants, Father McGivney was the oldest of 13 siblings, six of whom died in infancy or childhood. At 13 he went to work with his father, making spoons at the Holmes Booth and Haydens Company brass mills in Waterbury. He left the factory when he was 16 to attend college and seminary, and was ordained a priest in 1877.</p>
        <p>While serving at his first parish, St. Mary's, Father McGivney founded the Knights of Columbus in the church's basement as a way for Catholic men to support each other and to provide death benefits for their families. The Knights is now the world's largest Catholic fraternal organization. It annually distributes about $110 million to charities, and members volunteer an average of 55 million hours each year.</p>
        <p>Father McGivney was also dedicated to providing food, clothing and shelter to widows and orphans, as well as to ministering to New Haven prisoners. He gained public attention in the early 1880's for conducting Mass in jail for a man convicted of killing an Ansonia police officer.</p>
        <p>A newspaper clipping from the time quotes the convicted man, James Smith, as saying, ''Father, your saintly administration has enabled me to meet death without a tremor.'' Mr. Smith is described as going to the gallows with Father McGivney at his side. With this and other records of Father McGivney's public acts now in the hands of the Congregation for the Causes of Saints at the Vatican, the second, more difficult, phase of canonization begins: the certification of miracles.</p>
        <p>One miracle performed after his death is needed for beatification, which is the formal recognition of what are called a candidate's ''heroic virtues.'' A second miracle, performed after his death, is needed for sainthood. Father O'Donnell said several miracles throughout the country had already been credited to Father McGivney's intercession and are being investigated. All these miracles are medical in nature, and for any of them to be proved, a panel of doctors, lawyers and church officials, among others, must agree that a complete, spontaneous and unexplainable healing took place without any medical means whatsoever, Father O'Donnell said.</p>
        <p>For fear of invading privacy, or in some way compromising the investigations under way, Father O'Donnell said he would not discuss specifics of any of the miracles. But a visit to the Knights of Columbus Web site shows that people from as far away as Nigeria and the Philippines believe Father McGivney has performed many miracles in their lives: A Woodstock resident said prayer to Father McGivney caused a fellow Knight's brain tumor to vanish. A mother from Ontario, Canada, said she believed Father McGivney helped the police find her mentally disabled daughter, who had wandered away from home. Hundreds of other postings offer thanks for similar events.</p>
        <p>Duane Rogers, a Knight in Virginia for 15 years, said he prays to Father McGivney daily and believes the priest has responded by protecting his wife, who is legally blind; bringing success to his 21-year-daughter away at college, and helping heal his 23-year-old daughter, who has thyroid cancer.</p>
        <p>Father O'Donnell said there was no way to tell how long it would take to complete the next canonization phase. He is moving to Rome in August and will live there for up to three years to answer questions from the Vatican about Father McGivney, and to put together a new document to argue further the reasons the priest should be made a saint.</p>
        <p>''Spreading the word about Father McGivney is essential to our cause,'' Father O'Donnell said. ''And in many ways, it will only benefit people. He was a holy man, for sure. But he was also a simple man who lived a life that we all can follow.''</p>
        <p>More can be learned about Father McGivney by visiting his grave at St. Mary's Church on Hillhouse Avenue in New Haven, visiting the Knights of Columbus Web site at www.kofc.org or joining the Father McGivney Guild. (Guild membership is free.) The number to call for more information is 203 772-2130.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
