<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sorters and Gizmos to Ease the Wash Load</title>
    <meta content="02WASH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212211"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INSIDE/OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Laundries and Laundry Aids</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hodara, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Laundries and Laundry Aids</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E6DA1F30F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sorters and Gizmos to Ease the Wash Load</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN HODARA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hodara, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes some of numerous items to sort clothes and otherwise make washing and ironing clothes easier; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I MUST admit, I do get a small sense of satisfaction from a pile of clean clothes and an empty hamper.</p>
        <p>It's a fleeting victory, though, because laundry is in the same league as dirty dishes and backyard dandelions -- quick to regenerate and relentlessly in need of attention.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I MUST admit, I do get a small sense of satisfaction from a pile of clean clothes and an empty hamper.</p>
        <p>It's a fleeting victory, though, because laundry is in the same league as dirty dishes and backyard dandelions -- quick to regenerate and relentlessly in need of attention.</p>
        <p>Is it any wonder, then, that there are so many products designed to arm us for our battles with our dirty clothes and to make life in the laundry room a little brighter, easier and even fun? Here are a few options:</p>
        <p>Gathering your soiled belongings and getting them to the washing machine are steps that can't be skipped when it comes to laundry.</p>
        <p>Bed, Bath and Beyond stocks an array of items for this task, ranging from simple mesh bags ($6.99) to a three-bin mesh laundry sorter for whites, colors and delicates ($19.99) to a deluxe sorter ($79.99). That upscale version is a chrome model on wheels, with three removable cotton-canvas bags and a shelf on top.</p>
        <p>The Frontgate catalog features a similar sorter, with the addition of a rod for hangables under the shelf ($99). The Frontgate catalog can be ordered by calling (800) 626-6488 or on the Internet: www.frontgate.com. Restoration Hardware in The Westchester features its Desoto laundry basket, a circular number on wheels with a chrome-plated frame and one large canvas bag ($55).</p>
        <p>When it comes to hampers, Bed, Bath and Beyond has two inexpensive mesh versions, one that fits into a corner and one that is oval shaped (both $9.99). For those planning to do laundry when they travel, look for the Pop-Up Hamper ($9.99). It folds to the size of half a breadbox and opens up to a full-size, two-load hamper with handles.</p>
        <p>What about places to put things? Bed, Bath and Beyond has a Rolling Laundry Organizer ($19.99), which is three shelves on wheels and narrow enough to slide between the washer and dryer when it's not being used.</p>
        <p>Frontgate offers a wall-mounted clothes drying rack, which retracts into a chrome-finished cover and can be hidden when not in use ($59 for five rods; $79 for eight rods).</p>
        <p>Fels-Naptha? Gonzo? Oust? You might not pick these oddly named items as cleaning products, but read on. At Restoration Hardware, check out Fels-Naptha, a heavy-duty bar soap (five bars, $8.50) with prewash spot-removing powers (it's also touted as a treatment for poison ivy and a garden pest repellent). Gonzo, as its name suggests, is a highly recommended stain remover, which works on clothes as well as carpets, upholstery and vinyl ($3.95).</p>
        <p>Who would have thought you would need to wash the washing machine? Oust Cleaner ($2.95) cycles through the machine when it is empty of clothes, ridding it of the accumulated build-up you never knew was there but will surely be relieved to know is gone.</p>
        <p>Choosing environmentally safe laundry products can reduce build-up from the start, delivering just-as-clean clothes without the pollutants. Mrs. Green's Natural Market, with stores throughout Westchester, carries environmentally sound laundry detergents from Bio-Kleen, Bio-Pac, Seventh Generation, Ecover and Earth Friendly.</p>
        <p>Shaklee, the California-based mail-order business with several representatives in Westchester, offers its Basic-L line of laundry products, which are hypo-allergenic and free of phosphates, chlorine, borates and nitrates.</p>
        <p>As for the dry cleaner, the problem is that you have to go there. Twice. And you have to wait, sometimes days, before you can pick up your belongings -- unless you decide to do your dry cleaning at home.</p>
        <p>Dryel provides a reusable, plastic clothes bag and dryer-activated cleaning cloths. Your dry-clean-onlys tumble with the cloth in the bag for 30 minutes and come out clean and somehow unwrinkled. (Available at Wal-Mart, Kmart, Target and Sam's Club; 12 cloths for cleaning up to 48 garments are in the kit, $19.99 at Sam's Club). Bed, Bath and Beyond sells its own version, called Custom Cleaner ($8.99 for three loads).</p>
        <p>Sometimes it's not stains that take you to the dry cleaner, but unpleasant, lingering odors from perspiration, smoke or perfume. A lot of time, cost and wear and tear on clothes can be avoided with the Sharper Image Ionic Closet Dry Cleaner. ($89.95; compact model, $49.95). It's a clothes freshener that you put in your closet, hanging on the wall or from the rod, or standing on the floor. It's smaller than a breadbox and runs 24 hours a day, silently circulating natural ozone to neutralize unwanted smells in all kinds of fabrics.</p>
        <p>So, can ironing be made easier? Or is that a contradiction in terms? Perhaps not. Frontgate's European Ironing Board ($149) comes with two shelves, one below to hold items already pressed, the other a side extension to spread out clothes. And if that's not enough, their Ironing Stool ($79) positions you at the perfect height for ironing in comfort.</p>
        <p>INSIDE/OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
