<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Casino Attracts Rockers, Though Not Necessarily High Rollers</title>
    <meta content="02ATLA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212200"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlantic City (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Trump Marina Hotel and Casino (Atlantic City, Nj)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey/Atlantic City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DC1F30F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1175" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Casino Attracts Rockers, Though Not Necessarily High Rollers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTIC CITY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on niche that Trump Marina casino in Atlantic City, NJ, has carved out for itself by booking rock bands; multiband show called United We Funk is set for July 8; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Resorts International opened up the first legal casino here more than two decades ago, president Jack Davis brought in what he figured would be one of the ultimate casino entertainment acts as his first headliners: Steve Lawrence and Eydie Gorme.</p>
        <p>Steve and Eydie were a hit then and they will be back in Atlantic City again this summer, this time Aug. 25 through 27 at Caesar's Atlantic City.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Resorts International opened up the first legal casino here more than two decades ago, president Jack Davis brought in what he figured would be one of the ultimate casino entertainment acts as his first headliners: Steve Lawrence and Eydie Gorme.</p>
        <p>Steve and Eydie were a hit then and they will be back in Atlantic City again this summer, this time Aug. 25 through 27 at Caesar's Atlantic City.</p>
        <p>But the Steve and Eydie fans probably won't be hanging out at the Trump Marina. Already, the Grand Cayman showroom this summer has seen the likes of Big Bad Voodoo Daddy, Little Feat and Ted Nugent. Sometime glam-rockers, The Stone Temple Pilots, appeared at the Marina  June 24 and a multiband show called United We Funk will be there July 8.</p>
        <p>And coming up are such 70's and 80's rockers as George Thorogood and the Destroyers and Foreigner.</p>
        <p>While the occasional rock act shows up in other casinos (Caesar's will feature the Beach Boys and Aretha Franklin at the end of the summer), no one in Atlantic City has decided to do the loud-and-just-past-their-peak acts as the Trump Marina does.</p>
        <p>''They have that niche pretty much to themselves,'' said Michael Pollock, editor of the Atlantic City-based Gaming Industry Observer. Other properties believe that those interested in that music are not prime gambling customers, he said.</p>
        <p>Actually, officials at Trump Marina admit that someone interested in rocking hearty with Ted Nugent, who led the Amboy Dukes (''Journey to the Center of The Mind'') in the 1960's, before going out on his own in the late 1970's (''Cat Scratch Fever''), may not be a high roller.</p>
        <p>''Basically, bringing in these groups creates an image for us,'' said Steve Gietka, vice president of entertainment for Trump Marina and Trump Taj Mahal. ''We are doing an advertising theme that we are welcoming younger customers. We wanted to be controversial. We wanted to be written about. We don't have a volcano on our front lawn, so we figure having a rock sensibility will differentiate us.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gietka said that the rock marketing for the Trump Marina started in 1997 when negotiations to align the casino-hotel, then named Trump's Castle, with the Rank Organization, the owners of the Hard Rock Cafe chain. The Trump Hard Rock never came to be, but the seed of the idea germinated as the Trump Organization started a $5 million renovation and name change.</p>
        <p>''Five million is not a lot for a face lift,'' said Mr. Gietka. ''We recognized that a new music program could add to that. If it didn't work, it could be turned off, as opposed to bricks and mortar, which would cost a lot more to change again.''</p>
        <p>The Trump people knew, from focus groups and marketing studies, all of which said that their customers didn't really care what entertainment was at the Marina.</p>
        <p>''They said they cared about the gaming product, the rooms, the service,'' Mr. Gietka said. ''They were here to gamble and as long as these things were met, as long as they had some kind of entertainment, they pretty much didn't worry about what it was. So we were going to spend millions of dollars on a maintenance program no one cared about.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gietka said his managers, who tended to be under 50, usually thought of as the prime age of most casino gamblers, did care. They wanted a new image and also figured that there was room for at least one casino to attract a younger crowd.</p>
        <p>''To a large degree, the Trump Marina has gone against prevailing wisdom with some success,'' said Mr. Pollock, the gaming newsletter editor. ''Is that a market sufficiently large so that a number of casinos will go after it? Simply, no.''</p>
        <p>If you walk around the Trump Marina, you will hear rock music on the sound system. Rock acts from Philadelphia and New Jersey will be playing in the lounge. Rock memorabilia will show up on the walls at times. Rock, not necessarily all hard and loud, will almost always be in the showroom. The Brian Setzer Orchestra, which does a mix of rock and big band, for instance, will play July 28 and 29. Kenny Loggins and K. C. and the Sunshine Band, who tend to rock a bit more softly, will be there Aug. 4 and Aug. 11, respectively.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gietka said he was committed to actually selling most of the tickets to these concerts, which play in a theater with 1,400 seats, to the general public.</p>
        <p>''Sure, gaming pays the bills in casinos, but no one said that everything has to be given away,'' he said. ''People in Atlantic City actually will pay for some things. But if you want to get into music as a retail business, like we do, you have to be involved with agents, with radio stations, with record promoters, and not every casino wants to do that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gietka also recently took over the entertainment responsibilities at Trump Taj Mahal. While he hasn't made it an out-and-out rock venue, he has made the mix more youthful. Kenny Rogers and Tom Jones play there, but so will Todd Rundgren and the young comic D. L. Hughley.</p>
        <p>And on Aug. 25, the ultimate young act, Britney Spears, will pop and bubble at the Taj Mahal's Mark Etess Arena.</p>
        <p>''Yes, the parents will be milling around and some of them are going to gamble, but we didn't do it for that reason,'' said Mr. Gietka. ''At the Taj, we want to have the image of playing the superstars, and there is little hotter than Britney Spears now.''  ''But the Marina still needs to be a bit on the wilder side,'' he said. ''The Taj is about having acts way too big to play a 1,400-seat ballroom. (The Etess Arena seats 5,200.) But both Sting and Prince have played at the Marina, so it can be really exciting.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pollock said he was enthusiastic about the Marina booking more youthful acts, but he said that the 50-and-over group, changing though it may be, would continue to be the market for casinos and their entertainment choices.</p>
        <p>''Of course, even focusing on that market, you can't look at them the same way as you did their parents,'' Mr. Pollock said. ''Shecky Greene is history. He used to personify the casino act. Now, if you are 50, you look at, say, Dennis Miller or even Chris Rock. That's a completely different kind of entertainment.''</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
