<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nassau Budget Hamstrings Breast Cancer Project</title>
    <meta content="02CANC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Breast Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7DE1E30F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1455" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nassau Budget Hamstrings Breast Cancer Project</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA SASLOW</byline>
      <dateline>HEWLETT</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1998, Nassau County turned over Hewlett House, this village's original homestead, to 1 in 9, the Island's leading breast cancer advocacy coalition. It contracted with Friends for Long Island's Heritage, a preservation group, to manage the conversion of the 290-year-old farmhouse into a breast cancer information clearinghouse and meeting place, and hired Geri Barish, president of 1 in 9, to direct the program.</p>
        <p>The idea was to help ease the burden of breast cancer victims and their families. Then the county budget unraveled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1998, Nassau County turned over Hewlett House, this village's original homestead, to 1 in 9, the Island's leading breast cancer advocacy coalition. It contracted with Friends for Long Island's Heritage, a preservation group, to manage the conversion of the 290-year-old farmhouse into a breast cancer information clearinghouse and meeting place, and hired Geri Barish, president of 1 in 9, to direct the program.</p>
        <p>The idea was to help ease the burden of breast cancer victims and their families. Then the county budget unraveled.</p>
        <p>The restoration project, originally estimated to cost about $900,000, has already spent more than $1,250,000 and still needs an estimated $167,000. But with the county obliged to cut more than $200 million from its budget over the next three years, the money for Hewlett House isn't there. The restoration has been halted, Ms. Barish's job is in jeopardy and Friends for Long Island's Heritage has been accused of mismanaging the project.</p>
        <p>''We have been so delayed and so over-budgeted, and we have to find out why,'' said Jeffrey Toback, the Oceanside Democrat who has scheduled a hearing of his county Legislature government services committee on Thursday to look into the Hewlett House situation.</p>
        <p>''What I'm worried about,'' Mr. Toback said, ''is that some combination of the county and the contractor intentionally understated the numbers so they could get support for this project. Hopefully, we'll find out who, what, when and why, and then what we can do about it.''</p>
        <p>An audit last month by the county comptroller, Frederick E. Parola, described Hewlett House as unsuitable for a breast cancer resource center, saying the site is not centrally located and doesn't provide enough interior space or parking.</p>
        <p>''In retrospect, we could have provided them with three vacant, much larger farmhouses rather than this quaint little building,'' Mr. Parola said last week after a tour of the house's crumbling walls and wobbly staircases. ''We haven't served the people we promised this for, which is a sad commentary on a good idea.''</p>
        <p>The president of Friends for Long Island's Heritage, Jerry Kessler, said that many of Mr. Parola's findings were unjustified.</p>
        <p>''When we started this project in 1998, the county had $250,000 to spend,'' Mr. Kessler said. ''Historic restorations are typically four to six times more costly than normal construction, and we knew, without even taking the house apart, that the estimated cost for restoration would be between $900,000 and $1 million. The county was supposed to get more funding for the project, but it never did. Normally a project like this takes 12 to 14 months to complete, but this project had to be suspended several times because of lack of funds, which has delayed its completion.''</p>
        <p>Bruce Blakeman, who spearheaded the launching of the Hewlett House project as presiding officer of the county Legislature and, after his defeat in the 1999 election, still serves as chairman of the Hewlett House advisory council, also challenged the audit.</p>
        <p>''A glaring omission in the audit was that Hewlett House was acquired for one dollar,'' he said. ''While the renovation has been costly, it's not as bad when you consider that the local school district transferred to the county a property worth a half million dollars, for one dollar.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Barish said that the delays were preventing 1 in 9 from providing the full range of programs envisioned for Hewlett House, including a resource library with computer stations and Internet access, a legal advocacy program, nutrition classes, an exercise program, counseling, workshops in alternative medical therapies and a crisis center for women recently diagnosed with breast cancer. Some programs are already operating from 1 in 9's office  at the Nassau County Medical Center in East Meadow, but most are awaiting the completion of the Hewlett House project.</p>
        <p>''We have received so many donations for Hewlett House, from furnishings and appliances to free labor,'' Ms. Barish said. ''We've also gotten money from grants, private donations and contributions from students at local high schools. And all that money is just sitting in bank accounts, waiting to be used.''</p>
        <p>She said the donations are restricted and may be used only for programs, not for the construction project.</p>
        <p>The project has already been halted several times, Mr. Kessler said.</p>
        <p>''In October of 1998, the job had to be shut down because of lack of funding,'' Mr. Kessler said. ''We owed money to contractors who had done the work, and it was a big problem. It took until February 1999 for Nassau County to come up with another $725,000, but the money was not available until April, which delayed the project for six months. In June of 1998, Hewlett House received a state grant for $375,000, but those funds were also not available for an entire year. By the fall of 1999, I could see that we would be about $150,000 short to complete the job, so in January, because of insufficient funds, we had to shut down the job once again.''</p>
        <p>William Modell, a Hewlett resident and a member of the Hewlett House advisory council, took issue with the management of Friends for Long Island's Heritage. ''We had worked out with county unions that they would supply pro-bono time and labor for this project,'' said Mr. Modell, who is chairman of the Modell's sporting goods chain. ''But Friends wanted to control the job on their own, declined our offer and wanted nothing to do with the unions.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessler insisted that such allegations were inaccurate.</p>
        <p>''We contacted all of the trade unions, looking for volunteer labor,'' he said. ''Everybody said they would do something, but when it came down to it, nobody was standing in line ready to put labor into Hewlett House.''</p>
        <p>A state grant for $150,000 was secured last week by Senator Kemp Hannon, Republican of Garden City, to complete the project. Until the money is received next month, the project will use existing funds that Friends for Long Island's Heritage has left over from another contract, said Mr. Gulotta, so that there will be no further work interruptions. The grant money will then replace any funds used from that account, he said.</p>
        <p>If all goes as planned, Mr. Kessler anticipates that the house can be completed by September. ''Between 80 and 90 percent of the work is already done,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Parola is less confident. ''It appears overly optimistic,'' he said, ''to think that the restoration will be completed with this money, or in the time period they promise.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Barish's salary is another source of contention. Her $65,000 post was originally placed on the county Legislature's payroll. But last November, the Republicans lost their  majority in the Legislature (and Ms. Barish, a Republican, lost her contest for a seat on the body), and the new Democratic majority wants Ms. Barish's salary to be picked up on the county Health Department's budget.</p>
        <p>In January, when the Democrats took control, they agreed to keep Ms. Barish's salary on the Legislature's books only for the first half of the year. The Health Department ''is where it should be,'' said Judith Jacobs, the presiding officer.</p>
        <p>''I have the highest regard for the work Geri Barish has done and don't want to see her job eliminated,'' Ms. Jacobs said. But she added, ''we can't go on spending money from the Legislature's payroll.''</p>
        <p>Rather than see Ms. Barish lose her job, the county executive, Thomas S. Gulotta, is prepared to engage in a little budgetary juggling to make sure her salary is covered.</p>
        <p>''I will not permit Geri Barish to be laid off by the Legislature,'' Mr. Gulotta said. ''Breast cancer transcends all political boundaries. One way or another, even if we have to transfer money at the end of the year into the Health Department, we will secure financing in order to fund her position so that she can assume the operations of Hewlett House on behalf of 1 in 9.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Barish said she is optimistic. ''We're so close, we can't stop now,'' she said. ''There is too much at stake and so many people have worked to make Hewlett House a reality. We owe it to Long Island families with breast cancer to provide them with the resource center that we promised them. We can't walk away from that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
