<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the Millennium, Students Build an Arch of Their Own</title>
    <meta content="02ARCH$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CLASS PROJECT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Thomas Jefferson Elementary School (Yorktown Heights, NY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beller, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE5DA1F30F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="403" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the Millennium, Students Build an Arch of Their Own</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER BELLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beller, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Parents and students at Thomas Jefferson Elementary School in Yorktown Heights, NY, complete and dedicate Millennium Arch; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN parents and students at Thomas Jefferson Elementary School in Yorktown Heights began thinking about an art project to mark the new millennium, someone discovered that the gateway arch in St. Louis was also named for Thomas Jefferson.</p>
        <p>So, almost a year later, with great fanfare the school dedicated its Millennium Arch in a ceremony that included recognition from local officials and the governor, band music and, of course, cake.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN parents and students at Thomas Jefferson Elementary School in Yorktown Heights began thinking about an art project to mark the new millennium, someone discovered that the gateway arch in St. Louis was also named for Thomas Jefferson.</p>
        <p>So, almost a year later, with great fanfare the school dedicated its Millennium Arch in a ceremony that included recognition from local officials and the governor, band music and, of course, cake.</p>
        <p>The arch, 9 feet high from floor to ceiling and 11 feet wide spanning the main corridor of the school, is the culmination of 12 weeks of construction and months of research; classes in all grades studied architecture and the role the arch has played in history.</p>
        <p>The sides of the arch are decorated with wood cutouts representing earth, wind, fire and air, which were designed by students from the fifth and sixth grades; there is also a mural on the underside that illustrates the transition from daytime to night.</p>
        <p>The project was led by the school's art teacher, Pauline Halim, and an artist, Lori Nozick of Crompond, and was financed in part by a grant from the Lakeland Education Foundation.</p>
        <p>The students ''all did sketches with different ideas and then talked about which ones they liked,'' Ms. Halim said. Ms. Nozick, who often works with children and focuses on sculpture, observed that originally the children planned to build the arch out of wood, but to meet fire codes, city workers built the frame out of metal studs and wallboard.</p>
        <p>On a hot Wednesday morning students and parents listened as five students described their experiences and counted down and cheered as the students cut the ribbon in front of the arch.</p>
        <p>''The cutouts have different meanings,'' said Vlora Gjokaj, a student, reading a speech. ''The bottom stands for fire -- meaning we are burning with intelligence.''</p>
        <p>Aaron Rosario, a fifth grader, said: ''We learned about arches because we studied architecture. Also, an arch is a very good structure because it is very famous.''</p>
        <p>Afterward students filed underneath their arch and into the sunlight for Field Day.</p>
        <p>As the children formed teams, Buddy Loeb, the principal, and Susan Isenberg, the head teacher, stood and took in one of the last school days before summer.</p>
        <p>''They wanted to distinguish themselves,'' Ms. Isenberg said. Mr. Loeb agreed that they had.</p>
        <p>PETER BELLER</p>
        <p>CLASS PROJECT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
