<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Physics of Fireworks, From Factory to Sky</title>
    <meta content="02FIRE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212185"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fireworks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fireworks By Grucci (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grucci, Felix J Jr (Supervisor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richter, Allan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fireworks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7DE1E30F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1346" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Physics of Fireworks, From Factory to Sky</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN RICHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richter, Allan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Grucci family of Bellport, Long Island, owners of Fireworks by Grucci, which ranks among top 10 fireworks companies in terms of revenue; president Felix Grucci Jr, in order to finance expansion into new distribution hubs, is weighing whether to take company public; diagram shows setup, launching of Gold Split Comet and anatomy of shell; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOST Sundays around Concetta Grucci's dining-room table in Bellport, business chatter is as much a staple as the pasta and meat dishes that the 82-year-old matriarch serves to 20 members of her fireworks clan.</p>
        <p>''This is how we keep the structure intact. The glue is Concetta, my mother,'' Felix Grucci Jr., the supervisor of Brookhaven Town and president of Fireworks by Grucci, said the other day as Mrs. Grucci scraped the last egg salad from a bowl for another Felix, a nephew.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOST Sundays around Concetta Grucci's dining-room table in Bellport, business chatter is as much a staple as the pasta and meat dishes that the 82-year-old matriarch serves to 20 members of her fireworks clan.</p>
        <p>''This is how we keep the structure intact. The glue is Concetta, my mother,'' Felix Grucci Jr., the supervisor of Brookhaven Town and president of Fireworks by Grucci, said the other day as Mrs. Grucci scraped the last egg salad from a bowl for another Felix, a nephew.</p>
        <p>Attendance around the table will be thin today as the family gears up for the Fourth of July, but recent Sunday dinner conversations have centered on keeping pace with what is, well, a booming fireworks industry.</p>
        <p>American spectators will view the bursts of 160 million pounds of fireworks this year, the American Pyrotechnics Association estimates. And the group, based in Bethesda, Md., says millennial celebrations are propelling revenue to new heights that are not likely to drop off, just as the nation's Bicentennial set enduring records.</p>
        <p>The Gruccis rank among the top 10 companies in terms of revenue. Combined, the 10 account for about a third of the $200 million American market, up from $130 million just two years ago. Fireworks by Grucci, which is privately owned, is not saying exactly where in the top tier it resides, at least for now.</p>
        <p>To finance an expansion that would give the company new distribution hubs, Mr. Grucci said, the family has been talking about offering stock to the public, but bringing outside shareholders into the family fold does not quite sit right.</p>
        <p>''I always thought they should take the company public, particularly after the catastrophe when their factory blew up, but they feel they would lose that tremendous sense of family, which is part of their success,'' said the writer George Plimpton, who chronicled the Gruccis in ''Fireworks: A History and Celebration'' and befriended the family. ''When you go to a big Grucci fireworks show, the entire family is there, Concetta among them.''</p>
        <p>The catastrophe referred to was the explosion in 1983 that leveled the Grucci's enterprise in Bellport and killed two family members, including Jimmy, the oldest son of Concetta and Felix Sr. ''It totally consumed my father-in-law's wealth,'' Phil Butler, the company vice president, said of Felix Sr., who died in 1993. ''He always put all of his earnings back into the business, and was very happy to do it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Butler's wife, Donna Grucci Butler, manages the technical end of the business, like the choreography of the displays, while her brother Felix Jr. handles the finances.</p>
        <p>The Gruccis are signing fewer deals for shows with towns and other public sponsors in favor of more lucrative corporate and private contracts, and the average cost of a Grucci show has hit more than $37,000, Mr. Butler said, versus a national average of $14,000.</p>
        <p>But the cost of painting the night sky is also rising. The market demands splashier displays and the Gruccis have adopted more elaborate safety measures. Manual firing has given way to electronic triggers. And Plexiglas, which is better able to absorb a misfire, is replacing the stiff cardboard gun barrels through which shells are usually fired.</p>
        <p>The company has helped usher the fireworks industry into the computer age. ''They actually have equipment that plays the music as sound waves so you can see the rises and peaks and troughs in the music,'' said John Conkling, the technical director at the fireworks trade association, ''and then you lay your fireworks on top of that so you have peaks and troughs in the fireworks that match the music. They are among the pioneers.''</p>
        <p>While the Gold Split Comet shell illustrated on Page 1 is uniquely Grucci fare displayed at the family's larger shows, the Gruccis make only about a third of the shells they fire. The race among competitors, including a handful of other families with century-old Italian roots, is to splatter the sky not with proprietary shells, but with the widest variety.</p>
        <p>''If your blood pressure doesn't hit 150 over 110, you're not putting on a good show,'' said Dr. Conkling.</p>
        <p>Mr. Butler, whose measured speech marks the careful manner needed in the pyrotechnician's job he held a decade ago, explained: ''We shop the world, every continent. If you go to another fireworks show, you see the same thing over and over again. Their display mode is to blow up the sky and keep firing in the hope that they can disguise that they don't have variety.''</p>
        <p>Despite the drama and applause, the business still attracts some unwelcome gazes, as evidenced by the cancellation this year of what would have been the family's sixth consecutive Fourth of July show at Smith Point County Park. Mr. Grucci is quick to point out, however, that the safety concern expressed by the Suffolk County Police Commissioner, John Gallagher, was over traffic congestion, not the fireworks.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the Grucci factory, in Brookhaven Hamlet, is set in a tightly controlled enclosure that resembles a military test site. Caution signs, two miles of eight-foot-high barbed-wire fence and huge sand-and-gravel barriers surrounding 82 storage tanks accent the premium on safety.</p>
        <p>So do the copper plates on the outside of the assembly buildings, each the size of a mobile home: All who enter must wipe a hand across the plate to discharge static. To minimize risk, no more than four workers at a time are in any one building.</p>
        <p>As he assembled shells recently, Jimmy Grucci, 28, whose father was killed in the 1983 explosion, explained what drew him to the work: ''When my dad was alive, I used to go to the shows with him every weekend. At the time I was 8 or 9 years old. I just felt I had to do this.''</p>
        <p>Or as Mr. Plimpton put it: ''You can't be born in that family without wanting to go back to it. After the explosion, Felix Sr. wanted them to get out of it, but it was the younger generation that wanted to continue.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
