<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fleisher, the Underdog, Seeks to Hold Off Irwin</title>
    <meta content="02SENI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Senior Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arkush, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fleisher, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4D61539F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fleisher, the Underdog, Seeks to Hold Off Irwin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL ARKUSH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arkush, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>BETHLEHEM, Pa., July 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Fleisher leads after three rounds at United States Senior Open golf tournament; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bruce Fleisher's first career in professional golf was not nearly as fruitful as many had anticipated. Fleisher, the 1968 United States Amateur champion, won only one tournament in more than 400 starts on the PGA Tour. But his second career has been the exact opposite. Fleisher, 51, is a star on the Senior Tour. As the third-round leader of this week's United States Senior Open at Saucon Valley Country Club, he has a great chance to pull off his most significant triumph yet.</p>
        <p>It will not, however, be easy. Although Fleisher recorded a four-under-par 67 today, he will square off in Sunday's final twosome against Hale Irwin, his predecessor as the Tour's top player. Irwin, the 1998 winner, is two shots back after a 65 that included six birdies during a seven-hole stretch on the front nine. Also in contention is the Senior Tour rookie Tom Kite, who followed Friday's 65 with a 66 and trails by three shots. Kite, the 1992 United States Open champion, has already captured one Senior major this year, the Tradition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bruce Fleisher's first career in professional golf was not nearly as fruitful as many had anticipated. Fleisher, the 1968 United States Amateur champion, won only one tournament in more than 400 starts on the PGA Tour. But his second career has been the exact opposite. Fleisher, 51, is a star on the Senior Tour. As the third-round leader of this week's United States Senior Open at Saucon Valley Country Club, he has a great chance to pull off his most significant triumph yet.</p>
        <p>It will not, however, be easy. Although Fleisher recorded a four-under-par 67 today, he will square off in Sunday's final twosome against Hale Irwin, his predecessor as the Tour's top player. Irwin, the 1998 winner, is two shots back after a 65 that included six birdies during a seven-hole stretch on the front nine. Also in contention is the Senior Tour rookie Tom Kite, who followed Friday's 65 with a 66 and trails by three shots. Kite, the 1992 United States Open champion, has already captured one Senior major this year, the Tradition.</p>
        <p>Despite Fleisher's advantage, he did not waste time after the round today putting himself in the more comfortable position of underdog.</p>
        <p>''I think he is going to be the one to beat,'' Fleisher said of Irwin after bogeying two of his final five holes today and wiping out half of a four-stroke lead. ''Hale is a champion.''</p>
        <p>Irwin said of Fleisher: ''He has been the guy that has been on top and doing the thing that we all had hoped to do. The difference may be that I have been in that position before, and this is the first time Bruce has.''</p>
        <p>Irwin is correct. Despite 10 victories since joining the Senior Tour in 1999, Fleisher has yet to secure a major, the game's most important barometer of success.</p>
        <p>All the pressure Sunday will be on him, and he knows it. It is one thing to win the Royal Caribbean Classic; it is quite another to capture the most prestigious title in senior golf. Nonetheless, he seems ready for the challenge.</p>
        <p>''Maybe this is my time,'' said Fleisher, who has won three times in 2000 and has earned more than $1.1 million. ''I am not going to back off, I can tell you that.''</p>
        <p>For Fleisher, the key will be patience.</p>
        <p>''I am just going to try to do the same thing I have been doing,'' he said. ''Keeping the ball in play, keep my rhythm, hopefully make a few putts and don't get too excited.''</p>
        <p>Patience, however, may not be enough. That is because the par-71 course, softened by heavy rains earlier in the week, has been very vulnerable, a highly unusual situation for an Open test. A 65, or even a 64, is not out of the question, which means that pursuers like Hubert Green (four back) and Allen Doyle (five behind) have a legitimate chance. Today, for example, Fleisher, Irwin and Kite, despite some difficult pin placements, recorded a total of 22 birdies.</p>
        <p>''I guess the scores are probably going to go low again tomorrow unless the greens dry out significantly,'' Kite said. ''I think all the players are just shocked at how low it is. This is a heck of a golf course.''</p>
        <p>Not everyone, however, could tame Saucon Valley. Jack Nicklaus, who had shot a 67 Thursday to raise the chance that he might contend this week, followed Friday's 75 with a lackluster 73 and was 15 strokes back. Nicklaus, plagued by poor putting, also pulled a rib muscle when hitting out of the rough on No. 6. He has made only one birdie over his last 36 holes.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
