<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 1927 Building of Full-Floor Duplexes and a Triplex</title>
    <meta content="02SCAP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212124"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="STREETSCAPES/820 PARK AVENUE, AT 75TH STREET"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gray, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Streetscapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EED71330F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1177" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 1927 Building of Full-Floor Duplexes and a Triplex</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER GRAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gray, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Streetscapes article describes apartment building at 820 Park Ave at 75th St; it had duplex, full-floor apartments when it was built in 1927; in recent years, some residents have retured their homes to duplex glory; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MANY people consider a Park Avenue building with full-floor apartments something devoutly to be desired. But at 820 Park Avenue, built in 1927 at 75th Street, the full-floor apartments are comparatively small reminders of a more glorious past -- they were originally twice the size. In recent years, though, some residents have been able to return their homes to duplex glory.</p>
        <p>Albert J. Kobler, who put up the building, started out in business around 1910 by selling newspaper ads. He proved so able that in 1917 William Randolph Hearst appointed him head of Hearst's American Weekly syndicated Sunday magazine supplement.  Kobler later claimed to have increased the supplement's circulation from 2 million to 25 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MANY people consider a Park Avenue building with full-floor apartments something devoutly to be desired. But at 820 Park Avenue, built in 1927 at 75th Street, the full-floor apartments are comparatively small reminders of a more glorious past -- they were originally twice the size. In recent years, though, some residents have been able to return their homes to duplex glory.</p>
        <p>Albert J. Kobler, who put up the building, started out in business around 1910 by selling newspaper ads. He proved so able that in 1917 William Randolph Hearst appointed him head of Hearst's American Weekly syndicated Sunday magazine supplement.  Kobler later claimed to have increased the supplement's circulation from 2 million to 25 million.</p>
        <p>In 1923, Kobler bought a severe stone mansion at the northwest corner of 75th and Park for his own use, filling it with art treasures and antiques. In 1925 the magazine Arts &amp; Decoration said that Kobler's ''priceless art collection'' made the house reminiscent ''of the baronial castles of England.''</p>
        <p>But in 1926 Kobler demolished the house for a dramatically new kind of dwelling. He retained the architect Harry Allan Jacobs to design a 14-story building with duplexes above the ground floor for five tenants -- and with the top three floors as Kobler's triplex.</p>
        <p>Jacobs predicted in a 1925 article in The New York Times that soon ''the private house will be forgotten and a thing of the past,'' because of taxes, problems with servants, and the construction of other tall apartment buildings in elite neighborhoods, most of which ''are rather barrack-like and unattractive.''</p>
        <p>Jacobs's design remains unusual: above a two-story stone base rises a facade of mottled amber brick with windows arranged in vertical bays. These terminate at the Kobler apartment, marked by bands of plum-colored terra cotta and, on the north end, a three-story slate-shingled roof arranged as a mock-mansard roof.</p>
        <p>The base is a delicious orange and yellow Ohio sandstone from the Mississippian era, 3 million years old, according to Sidney Horenstein, a geologist at the American Museum of Natural History.</p>
        <p>The ironwork at the entryway is some of the most unusual on Park Avenue: dark, hammered shapes worked in medieval designs, including the shapes of blades and a knight. William J. Whitaker, collections manager at the architectural archives of the University of Pennsylvania, said that records in their collection indicate that the work was done by Samuel Yellin, one of the most prominent American metalworkers.</p>
        <p>KOBLER owned the building and leased the duplexes for $25,000 to $40,000 a year. The typical 20-room duplex had a 22-by-38-foot living room, a 19-by-23-foot dining room, a library and five master bedrooms, with six servants' rooms.  Kobler's triplex, decorated by French &amp; Company, had a 37-by-39-foot living room with a 20-foot ceiling and a great stone arch.  Arts &amp; Decoration visited the apartment in 1928 and noted that ''bewildered New York sunlight filters through the splendor and ancient stained glass.''</p>
        <p>The magazine said that Kobler had tapestry once owned by King Henry VIII of England, an early Gothic carved frieze, a table from the Strozzi palace in Florence, chairs from the Barberini palace in Rome, and walnut doors leading to the butler's pantry with scenes of 15th-century Flanders and 20th-century Park Avenue -- designed by Kobler himself. ''Home-making is no less a significant art than music, sculpture, poetry; in fact it involves them all,'' the magazine said.</p>
        <p>Kobler's 820 Park Avenue was not the only high-rise palace built by Hearst executives: Hearst himself created a five-level apartment in a building he bought in 1913 at 137 Riverside Drive, at 86th Street. And Arthur Brisbane, one of Hearst's assistants, built two buildings incorporating apartments for his own use: the 1926 Ritz Tower, at 57th &amp; Park, with a duplex, and the 1929 apartment house at 1215 Fifth Avenue, at 102nd Street, with a triplex penthouse.</p>
        <p>Kobler's new neighbors included Herbert Lehman, governor of New York from 1932 to 1942 and United States senator from 1949 to 1957. Another tenant was Herbert S. Martin, a vice president at the investment bank of S. W. Straus &amp; Company. Martin, his wife and their three young sons lived in the eighth and ninth floor duplex, from which Martin fell or jumped in January 1930, not long after the stock market crash of 1929. He had previously had a nervous breakdown, and was getting ready to go on a three-month vacation in Egypt and Europe.</p>
        <p>IN 1928 Kobler became publisher of The New York Daily Mirror, which Hearst had founded in 1924. Sometime before Kobler's death in 1937 at age 60, he leased  his custom-built apartment to the automobile manufacturer Walter Chrysler. The Kobler/Chrysler triplex was subdivided into six apartments in 1941, and the other duplexes in the building were gradually split up.</p>
        <p>The building is now a co-op. One shareholder, Denise LeFrak Calicchio, a broker with Sotheby's International Realty, said that two of the old duplexes, on the sixth and seventh floor and the eighth and ninth, have been rejoined in recent years.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Calicchio said that she has the 10th and 11th floors -- the late Governor Lehman's former apartment -- but that she has not actually recombined them.</p>
        <p>''People seem to need lots of space now,'' she said, adding that if a recombined duplex were to sell today it would probably go for about $15 million or $20 million.</p>
        <p>The co-op is now working with JMA Consultants, an engineering firm, on a complete exterior repair job. Eugene Ferrara, the owner of the firm, said that the work is fairly routine, except for the mock-mansard slate roof, but that they found only a few loose pieces there.</p>
        <p>Alfred Kobler's son, John, still lives in New York, on the West Side. He said that he does not recall much about his father's role in the building but that his father had left him a large photographic album showing the rooms of the family apartment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kobler said that about 30 years ago, ''I took it over to the doorman, and asked for him to send it up to the people on the top floor, with a note asking if they would like to have it; but I never heard another word, and they never returned it.''</p>
        <p>STREETSCAPES/820 PARK AVENUE, AT 75TH STREET</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
