<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Blues for This Bowling Alley</title>
    <meta content="02BOWL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212183"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bowling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Alley, The (Hartford, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stowe, Stacey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bowling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E7DE1E30F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1605" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Blues for This Bowling Alley</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STACEY STOWE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stowe, Stacey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on group of families who have purchased 16-lane duckpin bowling alley in West End section of Hartford, Conn; lanes, which has reopened as The Alley, was neighborhood landmark threatened with closure; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a bygone era, someone might have made a musical about it: neighborhood families buy a 60-year-old bowling alley for $20,000 and fix it up by chipping in money and elbow grease.</p>
        <p>A stockbroker figures out a business plan and a lawyer checks legal issues. A pair of architects orchestrate renovations. A mother of three decides to return to the workforce as manager. Teenagers volunteer to paint and ask for part-time jobs. In this kind of plot, Mickey Rooney and Judy Garland could pop up at the shoe rental counter and break into song.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a bygone era, someone might have made a musical about it: neighborhood families buy a 60-year-old bowling alley for $20,000 and fix it up by chipping in money and elbow grease.</p>
        <p>A stockbroker figures out a business plan and a lawyer checks legal issues. A pair of architects orchestrate renovations. A mother of three decides to return to the workforce as manager. Teenagers volunteer to paint and ask for part-time jobs. In this kind of plot, Mickey Rooney and Judy Garland could pop up at the shoe rental counter and break into song.</p>
        <p>But those fresh-faced youngsters would be upstaged. It's the twinkly-eyed grown-ups who sing the praises of owning a 16-lane duckpin alley in the West End section of Hartford.</p>
        <p>''The first thing I hear when I tell people about buying it is, 'What a cool thing to do with a mid-life crisis','' said Christine Palm. Ms. Palm, the mother of four boys and the editor of a local paper, The West End News, said she heard through the grapevine that the alley was to close. She and her husband, James Baker, a graphic artist, considered buying it to prevent another neighborhood business from closing. Phone calls to five other couples confirmed their sentiment.</p>
        <p>Not only did those first few friends want in, within several weeks the number of interested families climbed. Over the period of a few months, 23 families committed to the purchase. The initial cost of $20,000 was split 23 ways, but the families also raised an extra $44,000 for renovations. Although revenue from the bowling alley isn't the source of their primary income, the families formed a limited-liability corporation to protect their assets. The corporation is managed by three partners: Ms. Palm; John Gale, a lawyer; and Avery Buell, a stockbroker, all long-time West Enders.</p>
        <p>''Our biggest concern was liability,'' said Susan Russell, who stepped forward to manage the lanes now known as the Alley. ''We wondered, if it goes under will we lose our first-born child?'' Yet the idea of a communally owned alley was so popular, would-be investors had to be turned away; a week before its May 27 grand opening, a neighborhood businessman stepped among the paint cans and asked if he could become an owner.</p>
        <p>Serendipity also stepped in. The landlord, Steven Neiditz, whose father and uncle owned the building for longer than he could remember, offered things like a month-to-month lease. The alley purchase coincides with the publication of a book by a Harvard professor that asserts Americans need to join clubs, specifically bowling leagues. ''Bowling Alone: The Collapse and Revival of Community in America'' (Simon &amp; Schuster), by Robert D. Putnam, makes a case that belonging to clubs like bowling leagues increases ''human connectedness,'' and the trickle-down effect is improved relations within families and between people of different race, culture and economic levels. ''One of them dropped me a note, and when I found out about what they were doing, I thought it was the kind of grass-roots initiative that if it were emulated in other communities around the country, could significantly increase social connectedness,'' Mr. Putnam said in a telephone interview from his home in New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putnam's words echo what these mostly middle-aged professionals say they hope to accomplish.</p>
        <p>They have plans to sponsor events in conjunction with their neighborhood elementary school. On a recent weekday, Ms. Palm was fielding calls from a shelter for homeless young women about a trip to the bowling alley. The Mayor of Hartford, Mike Peters, bought $500 worth of tickets that are kept at the alley for children who wander in to bowl, but don't have enough money.</p>
        <p>Hank Murray, a labor lawyer who has lived in the West End with his family since 1977, said many residents were drawn to the area because of its racial and cultural diversity, not likely to be found in suburban neighborhoods. It was Mr. Murray who contacted Mr. Putnam.</p>
        <p>Buying the Alley, opened 60 years ago as Mark Twain Lanes after the city's favorite son, was a way to keep the neighborhood alive, and the active social network was the means to the purchase, Mr. Murray said. ''We weren't going to have one more neighborhood business bite the dust,'' he said. ''We were still smarting from the closing of Cheese &amp; Stuff,'' added Ms. Russell.</p>
        <p>Cheese &amp; Stuff was a grocery store specializing in organic foods that was emblematic of the funky style so dear to West Enders. It sold bulk flour and cereal as well as pricey prepared fare, organic produce and bath soaps. The staff was racially diverse and likely to dress in tie-dyed clothes and Birkenstock sandals. In the last decade, it was what remained of a corner that once included a shop that sold crystals as well as a feminist bookstore and restaurant.</p>
        <p>Earlier this spring, the owners of Cheese &amp; Stuff, the Wild Oats grocery store chain, announced it was closing the Farmington Avenue store and relocating to tonier West Hartford. West Enders wrote letters to the editor and picketed, saying they were promised by the store's owners that the market would stay put. In the end, it moved and the site is still empty.</p>
        <p>Residents described the West End as a place where people meet on the sidewalk, walking dogs or following children on bicycles. On warm summer nights, someone is usually having a neighborhood cook-out. Most blocks have a book club. There is a mixture of multi-  and single-family houses, most of them from the Victorian era or early 1900's. Most of the yards are well-tended, but some boast a charming lack of perfection.</p>
        <p>The Alley purchase is not the neighborhood's first foray into business. Fifteen years ago, neighbors stepped forward when Mo's Midtown, a small and immensely popular diner near the Alley, was scheduled to close. A few families bought it and held it for six months, until a Mo's waitress raised the money to buy it herself.</p>
        <p>The 23 families bought the bowling alley from an East Granby couple, Nancy and Jim Gesuelle, who owned it for more than 10 years and had spent close to $100,000 renovating and replacing the machinery and lanes. Mr. and Mrs. Gesuelle each work full time at the Cigna Insurance Company. They said they sold the business, formerly known as Farmington Avenue Duckpin to spend more time with their two school-aged daughters.</p>
        <p>The Gesuelles said there were offers to buy the alley for the pin-setting machines, but that would have meant ending its 60-year streak as a bowling alley.</p>
        <p>''It was a love of the sport that caused us to buy it in the first place,'' Mrs. Gesuelle said. ''I'm happy we found people who will keep it going.''</p>
        <p>''There's also selfish impulse here,'' said Lindsey Karl, the architect who with her husband, Michael Cannon, led the renovations. ''We want a place for our kids to go.'' The couple have two teenagers.</p>
        <p>To this end, the Alley will be smoke-free, but the owners are divided over whether to have a liquor license. Although the sale of liquor means higher profits, it also makes the atmosphere less family-friendly, owners said. Many of the owners place a premium on this quality.</p>
        <p>''I don't put up with what I call trash talk,'' said Ms. Russell, who as manager will be stalking the lanes to insure teenagers behave. There won't be computerized bowling either, bucking a growing trend at 10-pin lanes. The Alley owners want their children to add scores the old-fashioned way, to hone their math skills.</p>
        <p>Nostalgia for things past, however, was ultimately trumped by taste when it came to the Alley's interior. Dark paneling was taken down. Walls were repainted. A soda fountain and cafe were built. Laser bowling with its glow-in-the-dark lights was installed to lure teenagers. Four lanes of anchored chairs were ripped out to make room for a dance area where salsa and tango lessons are planned.</p>
        <p>For maintenance and repair of the pin-setting machines, the owners turned to John Gorman, a professional bowler who has worked at the lanes for many years.</p>
        <p>There is a growing sense that the endeavor, initiated to keep a neighborhood business afloat, could turn profitable. ''I think it's going to make money,'' said Mr. Buell, the stockbroker who wrote the business plan. ''There's enough people in this neighborhood and the extended neighborhood and a fair number of leagues are interested.'' (Owners said the Alley is one of just three public duckpin lanes in the greater Hartford area.)</p>
        <p>In a move that would please Robert Putnam, welcomes are being extended to bowling leagues. So far, five are on board.</p>
        <p>''Susan held meetings with them and baked them banana bread,'' Ms. Palm said.</p>
        <p>''It was really a cheese basket,'' Ms. Russell interjected.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, but banana bread sounds better,'' Ms. Palm said. ''More homespun.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
