<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A One-Time Prodigy With All-Star Mentors</title>
    <meta content="02ALEX$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212135"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Budd, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alexander, Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4DC1030F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A One-Time Prodigy With All-Star Mentors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL ALEXANDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alexander, Paul</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTIC CITY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paul Alexander article on singer Julie Budd, 46, whose career spans more than 30 years, who has worked with almost every major star and who is about to wrap up three-week engagement at Algonquin Hotel in Manhattan and move on to Resorts Hotel in Atlantic City; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BACKSTAGE at the Resorts Hotel here, the sign on the dressing room reads ''Miss Julie Budd.'' Inside, Julie Budd sits in front of a large mirror putting on make-up. It's less than an hour before show time and she's alone. No make-up artist, no hair stylist, no vocal coach. She doesn't need a vocal coach because, while she has a voice that's nothing short of thrilling, she barely warms up. ''La-la-la-la-la-la-la-la,'' she sings, her voice gliding the scales, as she dabs on mascara. ''La-la-la-la-la-la-la-la.'' During her shows she routinely belts out thunderous notes worthy of Ethel Merman, which itself is a feat since she's 5-foot-2 and asthmatic, but she hardly raises her voice above a whisper when she's vocalizing.</p>
        <p>She has no hair stylist and no make-up artist because she does her own hair and make-up. For that matter, before every show, she also sets her sound levels, adjusts her stage lighting and picks out all of her wardrobe, usually from her own closet. At a time when stars, even those who aren't superstars, travel with entourages of assistants, Ms. Budd is a throwback to a generation who believed if you wanted something done right you did it yourself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BACKSTAGE at the Resorts Hotel here, the sign on the dressing room reads ''Miss Julie Budd.'' Inside, Julie Budd sits in front of a large mirror putting on make-up. It's less than an hour before show time and she's alone. No make-up artist, no hair stylist, no vocal coach. She doesn't need a vocal coach because, while she has a voice that's nothing short of thrilling, she barely warms up. ''La-la-la-la-la-la-la-la,'' she sings, her voice gliding the scales, as she dabs on mascara. ''La-la-la-la-la-la-la-la.'' During her shows she routinely belts out thunderous notes worthy of Ethel Merman, which itself is a feat since she's 5-foot-2 and asthmatic, but she hardly raises her voice above a whisper when she's vocalizing.</p>
        <p>She has no hair stylist and no make-up artist because she does her own hair and make-up. For that matter, before every show, she also sets her sound levels, adjusts her stage lighting and picks out all of her wardrobe, usually from her own closet. At a time when stars, even those who aren't superstars, travel with entourages of assistants, Ms. Budd is a throwback to a generation who believed if you wanted something done right you did it yourself.</p>
        <p>Actually, Ms. Budd, 46, is more than a throwback. She's that generation's prize pupil. For in a career that's spanned more than 30 years -- she was discovered at age 12 -- she has worked with almost every major star of the generation before hers -- Johnny Carson, George Burns, Bob Hope, Jack Benny, Jimmy Durante, Carol Burnett, Bill Cosby, Danny Thomas, Milton Berle, Liberace and, as she calls him, ''Mr. Sinatra.''</p>
        <p>''To me, these performers are all descendants of the vaudevillian performer, '' Ms. Budd says, her voice quiet with emotion. ''The closest thing to that is the Broadway star, but that's different because the vaudevillian doesn't have a director telling him what to do. He has to find it himself. He has to do everything himself. Jimmy Durante once said to me, 'You've got to learn the business to stay in it.' I learned from people who learned the same way they taught me.''</p>
        <p>All the years of training have turned Ms. Budd into a consummate performer. This night, she shares top billing with Regis Philbin. She has also just released ''If You Could See Me Now,'' her follow-up to the 1997 album ''Pure Imagination.'' Ms. Budd's producer is Lisa Schiff. On Saturday, Ms. Budd will wrap up a three-week solo run in the Oak Room at the Algonquin Hotel in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>To a generation who watched her grow up on television variety shows -- and to their parents -- Ms. Budd is so familiar that her name was once the punchline to an entire episode of ''The Nanny.'' But with her new CD, Ms. Schiff, hopes to expand Ms. Budd's appeal to a younger audience. ''With that voice, I believe she can achieve anything she wants,'' Ms. Schiff says.</p>
        <p>Ms. Budd coats her lips with layers of red lipstick -- bold enough to be seen by the audience from the stage. It's a vaudevillian's touch. ''I caught the end of an era,'' she says. ''I was a part of something we'll never see again.''</p>
        <p>Energetic, precocious, Edie Erdman was summering with her parents at the Tamarac Lodge in the Catskills in 1966 -- just the sort of thing upper-middle-class Jewish families from Brooklyn did in the mid-60's. Telling her parents she was going to bed early one night, she sneaked off to a talent show. At the end of the show, Edie sang ''Who Can I Turn To?'' Even at 12, she could hit the ''money'' notes, and the instant she finished, the audience sprang to its feet. ''I thought they were leaving,'' Ms. Budd recalls. ''When I realized they weren't, I did another song -- 'Moon River.' ''</p>
        <p>Walking off stage, she was met in the wings by Herb Bernstein, a producer and arranger who had recorded singers like Dusty Springfield, Lesley Gore and Tina Turner. Becoming Ms. Budd's manager, Mr. Bernstein had her sing for a friend of his, Merv Griffin.</p>
        <p>''The next day, I was on Merv Griffin's live TV show but only after Merv changed my name from Edie Erdman to Julie Budd,'' she says. ''I went out and did 'Chasing Rainbows' and again the people stood up. Only this time I knew they weren't leaving. And while the show was actually on the air, Ed Sullivan's office called to book me on his show.''</p>
        <p>Over the next two years, Ms. Budd appeared on ''The Merv Griffin Show'' 50 times. In her career, she was on ''The Ed Sullivan Show'' nine times. In the late 60's and early 70's, she would also make regular appearances on ''The Mike Douglas Show,''  ''The Tonight Show,''  ''The Carol Burnett Show'' and ''The Jim Nabors Show,'' among others.</p>
        <p>She also started working the hotels and casinos in Atlantic City, Las Vegas, Lake Tahoe and Reno -- any venue that would let a minor perform, since she didn't turn 21 until 1975. It was during the decade between the late 60's and the late 70's that she ''worked with them all,'' as she put it: Liberace ('' 'When you go onstage, don't dress like you're going to the A &amp; P,' Lee used to tell me''), Carol Burnett (''She taught me the importance of creating a real sense of theater about yourself''), Jimmy Durante (''Of all of them, he was the toughest''), and, of course, Sinatra (''He taught me never to take rehearsals for granted''). In these years there was one performer she did not work with -- Barbra Streisand. In the early part of Ms. Budd's career, she was often compared to Ms. Streisand. Indeed, industry insiders believe that early on Ms. Budd did not become as successful a recording artist as she was a live performer (she cut just one record) because critics and fans felt she sounded too much like Ms. Streisand. Some listeners even confused her with Ms. Streisand's sister, Rosalyn Kind, who tried to start a singing career during these years.</p>
        <p>Both Ms. Budd and Ms. Streisand felt they didn't sound the same, which they discussed the first time they met after one of Ms. Streisand's shows at the International Hotel in Las Vegas in 1970. ''Herbie and Marty Erlichman, Barbra's manager, grew up together in Brooklyn,'' Ms. Budd recalls. ''Barbra was playing the International and I was getting ready to go in there, so Marty invited Herbie and me to come to Barbra's last show. When we went backstage afterward, Barbra extended her hand to me. There was a mirror on the wall so I pulled her over to it and said, 'And you're taller than me, too.' Barbra started laughing. 'And you have a much wider jaw bone than me.' So I looked at her and said: 'What's the deal? We're not anything alike.' And she said, 'I don't know what the deal is, but I wish it would stop.' That night, we sat and talked until 3 in the morning.''</p>
        <p>In 1980, Disney cast Ms. Budd as the female lead in ''The Devil and Max Devlin,'' a picture starring Mr. Cosby and, in a perverse move, Elliot Gould, who had been married to Ms. Streisand from 1964 until 1968. The picture was successful, though not enough to launch a career for Ms. Budd in Hollywood. But she had bigger problems. By the early 80's, most of the variety shows she had been appearing on for years had gone off the air. During the rest of the 80's, she worked mostly as a live entertainer.</p>
        <p>Then, in 1990, her career entered what she calls ''a blah period.'' She was still working, but she wasn't playing the gigs she wanted. By 1995, she didn't know what to do except call on an old friend, Frank Military, the producer and record executive, and tell him she needed a record deal. Mr. Military phoned Ms. Schiff,  who signed her on.</p>
        <p>S OMEONE once told me,'' Ms. Budd says as she checks her make-up in the mirror one last time, ''if you stay in this business long enough, everything that can happen to you probably will.'' It's only minutes before show time and, as she has been for most of the last hour, she is still alone. These days, she's happy. With the recording career she has thanks to Ms. Schiff, she's again playing the gigs she wants to play and working with entertainers she admires, like Mr. Philbin. ''You can always live again in this business if you have what it takes to survive it,'' she says. ''It's the one business that forgives a lot -- and gives you a second chance. If you have talent. Talent is the final word in any contract.''</p>
        <p>So what does she think about as she stands backstage waiting to go on? ''I often have in my head all of the voices of all my teachers. Tonight, one of them will be shouting, 'Get in your light, you fool.' And one will say, 'Put on a sweater, Julie.' That will be Mr. Sinatra. Lee will probably yell, 'That dress -- what were you thinking?' And then George Burns will say: 'Leave her alone. She'll sit on the edge of the stage and sing and all will be forgiven.' And then Jack Benny will say, 'How does she remember all those words?' ''</p>
        <p>The stage manager shouts from the hallway that it's time for places. She leaves her dressing room, walks down the hall, enters the stage door, and weaves her way through the semi-dark until she finds her place in the wings. She takes a deep breath, then stands erect. Her entrance music starts. Then, over the public address system, the announcer says, ''Ladies and gentlemen, Miss Julie Budd!''</p>
        <p>MUSIC Paul Alexander, who writes a political column for bloomberg.com, is the author of biographies of Sylvia Plath and J. D. Salinger.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Paul Alexander, who writes a political column for bloomberg.com, is the author of biographies of Sylvia Plath and J. D. Salinger.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
