<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Again Alters Day to Meet on Middle East</title>
    <meta content="Y14GOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/politics/14GORE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238598"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arab-Americans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DE133FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="570" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Again Alters Day to Meet on Middle East</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>CEDAR RAPIDS, Iowa, Oct. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Gore alters campaign schedule for second day to attend White House meeting on Mideast; cancels meeting with Arab-Americans in Detroit, although aides promise quick rescheduling (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the second consecutive day, Vice President Al Gore altered his campaign schedule today to return to Washington for a White House meeting concerning the instability in the Middle East.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore canceled a scheduled private meeting with 30 to 40 Arab-Americans in Detroit, a city where Arabs hold considerable political sway. Mr. Gore's aides said the cancellation was logistical, not political. Indeed, Mr. Gore planned to meet tonight in Washington with several of those who were to have attended the Detroit session, and his staff pledged to reschedule the full meeting quickly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the second consecutive day, Vice President Al Gore altered his campaign schedule today to return to Washington for a White House meeting concerning the instability in the Middle East.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore canceled a scheduled private meeting with 30 to 40 Arab-Americans in Detroit, a city where Arabs hold considerable political sway. Mr. Gore's aides said the cancellation was logistical, not political. Indeed, Mr. Gore planned to meet tonight in Washington with several of those who were to have attended the Detroit session, and his staff pledged to reschedule the full meeting quickly.</p>
        <p>''We've met with Arab-American leaders in the past and will continue to do so in the future,'' said Chris Lehane, Mr. Gore's press secretary.</p>
        <p>Greg Simon, an adviser to the Gore campaign who is of Lebanese descent, said there was no awkwardness in meeting with Arab-Americans at a time of such tension in the Middle East. On Thursday, 17 American sailors were killed in a suspected terrorist attack on a United States destroyer in Yemen, while on the West Bank a Palestinian mob killed two Israeli soldiers and prompted an Israeli missile attack on Ramallah and Gaza City.</p>
        <p>While Arab-Americans may play a role in the election in pivotal states like Michigan, a heavy turnout by Jewish voters is expected to be even more critical to Mr. Gore's chances in Florida.</p>
        <p>''Our role as honest broker is crucial to peace in the Middle East,'' Mr. Simon said, ''and regardless of where your interests lie and which side you sympathize with, everybody wants to see peace in the region. That means you need to keep open lines of communication. These meetings are about peace, not about taking sides.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore campaigned today before a modest crowd in this city in northeastern Iowa, delivering virtually the same attack on George W. Bush's record on health care as governor of Texas that he did in Milwaukee on Thursday.</p>
        <p>''At a time like this, it is just unacceptable to have millions of parents worry themselves sick about how they're going to get health care for their children,'' Mr. Gore said.</p>
        <p>The vice president repeated his pledge to provide health coverage to every child in America by 2005. That plan relies on his ability to provide $95 billion over 10 years to expand the federal Children's Health Insurance Program.</p>
        <p>''My opponent doesn't have that as a priority,'' Mr. Gore said. ''He has very different priorities, because he has proposed a massive tax cut, almost half of which goes to the top 1 percent.''</p>
        <p>There was one notable change in Mr. Gore's remarks today: He lost the ''lockbox.'' After ''Saturday Night Live'' parodied his frequent use of that term to refer to his promise to protect Medicare and Social Security surpluses from raids by Congress, Mr. Gore avoided the metaphor today.</p>
        <p>''I believe,'' he said, ''that we should put Medicare and Social Security in a special category where the money can't be used for anything else.''</p>
        <p>In a year of few cross-party endorsements, Mr. Gore received the backing today of the Republican mayor of Cedar Rapids, Lee Clancey. In remarks before Mr. Gore's address, Ms. Clancey leveled a blistering critique of Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>''I wanted a president who has the intelligence to understand the issues,'' she said, ''who has the ability to articulate those issues, who has the wisdom to make good decisions on those issues.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
