<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; It's a Very Long Way From Japan to Shea</title>
    <meta content="14ARAT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/sports/14ARAT-EARLY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez, Timo</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E7D6133FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; It's a Very Long Way From Japan to Shea</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times column discusses play of New York Mets outfielder Timo Perez in playoffs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEGEND has it that Omar Minaya signed Timo Perez. ''He deserves the bulk of the credit because he took the ball and ran with it,'' Bobby Valentine said of the Mets' senior assistant general manager. First, however, came a handoff from the man sitting in Valentine's office yesterday, the manager's guest, invited over for the playoffs from Chiba, Japan.</p>
        <p>''There was a connection,'' Valentine said obsequiously before the Mets prepared for Game 3 of the National League Championship Series today, leading St. Louis, 2-0, and seemingly working more with wands than with bats, starting with their Dominican speedster by way of Japan at the top of the order.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEGEND has it that Omar Minaya signed Timo Perez. ''He deserves the bulk of the credit because he took the ball and ran with it,'' Bobby Valentine said of the Mets' senior assistant general manager. First, however, came a handoff from the man sitting in Valentine's office yesterday, the manager's guest, invited over for the playoffs from Chiba, Japan.</p>
        <p>''There was a connection,'' Valentine said obsequiously before the Mets prepared for Game 3 of the National League Championship Series today, leading St. Louis, 2-0, and seemingly working more with wands than with bats, starting with their Dominican speedster by way of Japan at the top of the order.</p>
        <p>By the end of the month, Valentine may want to remember his one season of managing abroad as more than a fascinating professional excursion. He may look back upon his year with Chiba Lotte as a well-timed flirtation with fate. There, an American whose job it was to communicate daily with players and reporters hired a translator, a retired catcher from the Japanese leagues named Isao O'Jimi.</p>
        <p>''I play four years,'' O'Jimi said. ''But not a very good player.''</p>
        <p>''You must have been pretty good to make the Japanese majors,'' he was told.</p>
        <p>''No,'' he insisted. ''Not very good.''</p>
        <p>Well, maybe that does explain how O'Jimi wound up as Valentine's translator, and later on the Mets' international scouting staff. That left the former backstop in perfect position during the 1998 season to catch an eyeful of a pint-size outfielder who had taken the unorthodox trail from the Dominican Republic to the Hiroshima Carp, arriving there at the almost unheard age of 18.</p>
        <p>''I see that he run very fast and make good contact,'' O'Jimi said. ''I watch him close in B.P. and then in the game. Usually he make contact, and you know, maybe four pitchers on each Japanese team can pitch here, so he's facing very good pitchers. I call Omar Minaya and say, 'This player hit the ball and run very fast.' ''</p>
        <p>But to go from being a Japanese bench player to Class A ball in Florida to Class AAA ball in Norfolk to the crucible of the major league postseason, in one year?</p>
        <p>''In Japanese Central League, he play against the Tokyo Giants and there is always 55,000 people,'' O'Jimi said. ''He is used to the pressure.''</p>
        <p>This kind of pressure?</p>
        <p>''Of course,'' O'Jimi said, smiling. Then, pointing to his head, he said: ''I can only know that now, watching him play so good for the Mets.''</p>
        <p>It is still all a little difficult to believe, this Timo Perez story, this contemporary remake of ''Damn Yankees.'' Was there a soul for sale somewhere in the vicinity of Shea Stadium? The incredulous expression of Al Leiter, hands on the sides of his cap, as Perez ran down a drive to the right-field corner for a backhand catch against the wall in St. Louis on Thursday night, said it all. Is this really happening? Is this guy who 90 days ago no one even heard of really this good? Is he really doing this now?</p>
        <p>''He's a very good player who has helped us win games,'' Valentine said.</p>
        <p>Asked to say pretty much the same thing in Spanish for a Spanish-language sports report, Valentine for that rare occasion abstained, apparently not wanting to push his luck.</p>
        <p>''I would not do him justice speaking in Spanish,'' he said.</p>
        <p>I have to admit, my first day home upon returning from the Olympics in Australia, when the caller on sports talk radio was asking about Timo, I thought he meant Tino. We didn't hear much about Timo Perez on the streets of Sydney, only about the Mets not hitting and failing again to catch the Braves. All summer, they didn't have a genuine leadoff hitter or any speed. So I sat down for Game 2 of the division series in San Francisco to watch this little fellow lace base hits all over Pac-Bell, and my reaction was: ''Did I miss something?''</p>
        <p>What I learned yesterday is that Perez comes from San Cristobal in the Dominican Republic, that he speaks more Japanese than he does English. That he's listed at 5 feet 9 inches, but is shorter than I am, at 5-8. That he snickered when he said he weighed about 165 pounds. That the translator that Jay Horwitz of the Mets' staff sent over didn't want to upset Perez by inquiring about the rumor out of Japan that he is 31, not 23. That Perez would not reveal the contents of the mysterious cardboard boxes piled near his dressing stall.</p>
        <p>He wore a gold chain around his neck and said that his mother, Maria Luisa, is with him here in New York, and a cousin lives here as well.</p>
        <p>Maybe that's all we need to know for now because something strange and mysterious may be developing around the Mets, the way it happened in 1969 and 1986. Timo Perez seems to be in the process of fitting into Mets lore. We know how he got here. Two victories short of the World Series, we still can't be certain of why.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
