<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>School Aide Is Arrested in Assault on 12-Year-Old Student</title>
    <meta content="14SCHO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/nyregion/14SCHO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">McMillan, Clarence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rashbaum, William K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sinclair, Lamar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sinclair, Judette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph E (School Principal)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DA133FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>School Aide Is Arrested in Assault on 12-Year-Old Student</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. RASHBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rashbaum, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Police arrest Clarence McMillan, aide at Brooklyn special-education school, for allegedly punching student Lamar Sinclair, 12, in chest several times, causing boy, who suffers from heart murmur, to pass out; boy's mother, Judette Sinclair, police school safety officer, says she will sue city, news conference; her lawyer scores failure of principal, Rudolph E Giuliani, mayor's cousin, to seek immediate medical aid (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The police arrested an aide at a special-education school in Brooklyn yesterday on charges that he punched a 12-year-old student several times in the chest, causing the boy, who the authorities said suffers from a heart murmur, to pass out.</p>
        <p>The boy fell to the floor and struck his chin during the incident, on Thursday about 1:30 p.m. in the cafeteria at Public School 369 on State Street. He suffered an injury to his chin that required 14 stitches, the police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The police arrested an aide at a special-education school in Brooklyn yesterday on charges that he punched a 12-year-old student several times in the chest, causing the boy, who the authorities said suffers from a heart murmur, to pass out.</p>
        <p>The boy fell to the floor and struck his chin during the incident, on Thursday about 1:30 p.m. in the cafeteria at Public School 369 on State Street. He suffered an injury to his chin that required 14 stitches, the police said.</p>
        <p>The school aide, Clarence McMillan, 39, of 42-53 157th Street in Queens, was arrested yesterday about 3:30 p.m. and charged with third-degree assault. The police said Mr. McMillan was a former boxer who works as a fight trainer. He has worked at P.S. 369 for nine years, according to the Board of Education. He was suspended without pay.</p>
        <p>School officials said they could not explain what caused the assault. The boy, Lamar Sinclair, said that the school aide became angry because he had eaten a friend's french fries.</p>
        <p>Pam McDonnell, a spokeswoman for the Board of Education, said, ''It sounds like the child was not out of control.'' She added, '' Nothing warrants this reaction.''</p>
        <p>The student's mother, Judette Sinclair, 38, a New York Police Department school safety officer, appeared at a news conference yesterday afternoon with her son and her lawyer, Sanford A. Rubenstein, who said he had submitted court papers notifying the city of his intention to file a lawsuit charging negligence in the hiring, training and supervision of Mr. McMillan.</p>
        <p>''This is outrageous, unacceptable conduct by an employee of a school whose job it is to help children and not injure them,'' Mr. Rubenstein said, adding that the Board of Education should review its hiring and training practices for school aides.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rubenstein said the lawsuit would also accuse the principal, Rudolph E. Giuliani, a cousin of the mayor, with failing to get immediate medical assistance for the child. Ms. Sinclair said that instead of calling 911, the principal told her to pick up her son. She said she believed he had sought to avoid calling 911 because a response by Emergency Medical Service paramedics would have led to a police report. She accused the school of failing to report the incident to the police, and said that she called the police herself after her son was treated for his injuries.</p>
        <p>Reached at P.S. 369 after school yesterday, Mr. Giuliani declined to comment. Ms. McDonnell, the Board spokeswoman, said that Mr. Giuliani had offered to call 911, but that she believed Ms. Sinclair had chosen to pick up her son instead to make sure that he would be taken to the Brooklyn Hospital Center rather than Long Island Jewish Medical Center, which is closer to P.S. 369.</p>
        <p>Ms. McDonnell said that the principal had notified the Board of Education's Office of Special Investigations, which she said routinely notifies the police in such incidents.</p>
        <p>Lamar said that the confrontation started when he and a friend were eating lunch. After the other student stopped eating, Mr. McMillan, who was monitoring students in the lunchroom, told the student to throw out his leftovers. Before he did so, Lamar asked for his french fries and the other child agreed. But Mr. McMillan called Lamar over to upbraid him for taking the food. Lamar said the aide punched him in the chest five times, once saying, ''I'll break you,'' and told him to return to his seat. As he turned to walk back to his table, he said, he became dizzy, lost consciousness and collapsed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
