<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y14CAM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/politics/14CAMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238621"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giordano, Philip A (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herszenhorn, David M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E6DB133FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Presidential nominee Sen Joseph Lieberman is still running for re-election in Connecticut, but will not debate Republican opponent Philip A Giordano (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE RUNNING MATES</p>
        <p>LIEBERMAN BOWS OUT OF SENATE DEBATE  Senator Joseph I. Lieberman is still running for re-election in Connecticut, but he will not be debating his opponent for United States Senate, Mayor Philip A. Giordano of Waterbury. Mr. Lieberman had agreed to participate in a debate before becoming Vice President Al Gore's running mate, but had put the event on hold since joining the big ticket.</p>
        <p>Late last month, he said that voters who wanted to see him debate could watch him with Dick Cheney, the Republican vice-presidential candidate. Yesterday, an aide said that Mr. Lieberman would not participate in any debate in the Connecticut race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE RUNNING MATES</p>
        <p>LIEBERMAN BOWS OUT OF SENATE DEBATE  Senator Joseph I. Lieberman is still running for re-election in Connecticut, but he will not be debating his opponent for United States Senate, Mayor Philip A. Giordano of Waterbury. Mr. Lieberman had agreed to participate in a debate before becoming Vice President Al Gore's running mate, but had put the event on hold since joining the big ticket.</p>
        <p>Late last month, he said that voters who wanted to see him debate could watch him with Dick Cheney, the Republican vice-presidential candidate. Yesterday, an aide said that Mr. Lieberman would not participate in any debate in the Connecticut race.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman has two more weeks to decide whether to drop from the Senate race and allow another Democrat to run. Should he stay and win both, he would have to give up his Senate seat and a successor would be chosen by Gov. John G. Rowland, a Republican.</p>
        <p>At a news conference last night, Mr. Giordano said Mr. Lieberman should drop out. ''If you don't have an hour and a half to spend with the constituents of Connecticut, then get out of the race,'' he said.</p>
        <p>David M. Herszenhorn (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE COURTS</p>
        <p>RULING ON PUERTO RICO VOTING IS OVERTURNED  A federal appeals court ruled yesterday that residents of Puerto Rico could not vote in presidential elections unless the island territory became a state or the Constitution was amended. The ruling overturns a lower court decision that said Puerto Rico's 2.4 million voters had the right to cast presidential ballots.  (AP)</p>
        <p>THE CANDIDATES</p>
        <p>BUSH CRITICIZES GORE IN CAR COUNTRY  Gov. George W. Bush strongly criticized Vice President Al Gore in Pontiac, Mich., yesterday as an enemy of the automobile whose concern for the environment trumped the economic interests of many people in Michigan, a crucial swing state. Mr. Bush rummaged through Mr. Gore's voting record and his 1992 book on the environment, ''Earth in the Balance,'' to make his points, and noted the vice president's tie-breaking vote in the Senate in 1993 to raise gasoline taxes.</p>
        <p>''In speeches, he calls auto workers his friends,'' Mr. Bush said. ''But in his book, he declares that the engines that power your cars are his enemy.'' Mr. Bush went on: ''The internal combustion engine, Mr. Gore wrote, is, and I quote, 'a mortal threat to the security of every nation that is more deadly than that of any military enemy we're ever likely to confront.' Unlike Al Gore, I don't consider the internal combustion engine a threat to the future of mankind. I consider it a remarkable testimony to American ingenuity.''</p>
        <p>Kym Spell, a spokeswoman for the Gore campaign, said that accusation was wholly unfounded. Mr. Gore's campaign proposals included no new energy taxes, Ms. Spell said, and the incentives he had outlined for the manufacture of vehicles not powered solely by gasoline were meant to benefit, not punish, the auto industry.</p>
        <p>Frank Bruni (NYT)</p>
        <p>TRAVEL LOGS</p>
        <p>BY THE NUMBERS  Both candidates ended the week in closely contested states, George W. Bush in Michigan and Vice President Al Gore in Iowa.</p>
        <p>The stats:</p>
        <p>Length of official day: Gore, 14 hours; Bush, 11 hours</p>
        <p>States visited: Gore, 2; Bush, 1</p>
        <p>Towns/Cities visited: Gore, 1; Bush, 2</p>
        <p>Official Events: Gore, 2; Bush, 2</p>
        <p>Diners visited/drop-bys: Gore, 0; Bush, 0</p>
        <p>Press conferences: Gore, 0; Bush, 1 (editorial board meeting)</p>
        <p>Press interviews (includes newspapers and television): Gore, 2; Bush, 9</p>
        <p>Main message: Gore, Preserving proserity; Bush, commitment to the ''greatest generation'' and energy conservation</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
