<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Devils Can't Shake The Rust, Falling Short in Ottowa</title>
    <meta content="14DEVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/sports/14DEVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238654"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ottawa Senators</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Ottawa Senators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E7D8133FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="849" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Devils Can't Shake The Rust, Falling Short in Ottowa</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>KANATA, Ontario, Oct. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ottawa Senators defeat New Jersey Devils, 3-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There comes a point when rest turns to rust. The Devils, idle since their season-opening victory last Friday, demonstrated their sluggishness from the long layoff tonight with a flat-footed first period as they fell behind the Ottawa Senators by a goal at the Corel Center.</p>
        <p>Although they performed respectably for the rest of the game and showed some flash and flair, they scored no more goals and the Senators earned a 3-1 victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There comes a point when rest turns to rust. The Devils, idle since their season-opening victory last Friday, demonstrated their sluggishness from the long layoff tonight with a flat-footed first period as they fell behind the Ottawa Senators by a goal at the Corel Center.</p>
        <p>Although they performed respectably for the rest of the game and showed some flash and flair, they scored no more goals and the Senators earned a 3-1 victory.</p>
        <p>The Devils, the defending Stanley Cup champions, won't wait so long for their next action. They play host to Anaheim on Saturday night at the Meadowlands.</p>
        <p>''We were a little sluggish,'' said Scott Stevens, the Devils' captain, referring to the first period. ''Hopefully, we'll feel better tomorrow night and get a couple points.''</p>
        <p>Larry Robinson, the Devils' coach, shook his head when asked if his team was rusty. ''We're not going to make excuses,'' he said, adding that the Devils overstayed some shifts, failed to get the puck in deep and failed to create commotion in front of the Ottawa net. He also pointed out that the Senators had not played since last Saturday.</p>
        <p>Robinson, however, did not seem distraught about the game in which his team outshot the Senators, 31-25.</p>
        <p>''We had enough chances to win,'' Robinson said.</p>
        <p>The Senators (2-0-1-0), who struggled through most of the 1990's as an expansion team, have ripened into what could be a championship contender. Their roster is stocked with young talent, much of it European, and many of their players perform with elan. Their skill level is bolstered this season by the return of Aleksei Yashin, a first-rate center who missed last season in a contract dispute.</p>
        <p>But the fans here resent Yashin's bargaining stance, which failed, and they boo him whenever he touches the puck.</p>
        <p>The Devils scored first tonight, 8 minutes 18 seconds into the game, when Sergei Brylin and Alexander Mogilny dashed into the Ottawa zone, exchanged a series of passes around defenseman Karel Rachunek and worked the puck past goalie Patrick Lalime.</p>
        <p>Brylin got the last tap, from the corner of the cage, after Lalime was maneuvered to the other side. Scott Gomez got the other assist.</p>
        <p>But the Senators tied it at 1-1 at 14:35. Although Shawn McEachern took the shot, the play was fashioned by Yashin, who opened space to the left of Devils goalie Martin Brodeur by enticing defenseman Brian Rafalski to chase him behind the goal line. No Devil picked up coverage on McEachern, who had lots of net to shoot toward because Brodeur had moved to the other side in mistaken anticipation of the flow.</p>
        <p>The fans who had booed Yashin for most of the sequence paused to cheer the goal, then booed his name when it was announced on the public-address system.</p>
        <p>The Senators made it 2-1 at 16:40 on a goal by Ricard Persson, whose wrist shot hit Brodeur on its way in. Moments before, Brodeur had made a save on Marian Hossa but was unable to control the long rebound. Magnus Arvedson beat the Devils to the loose puck and set up the goal with a pass to the slot.</p>
        <p>Brodeur said: ''Personally, I didn't feel too good in the first period with the atmosphere of the game and the excitement of it. When they scored those two quick goals, everybody came out of the rust we were in. We responded really well.''</p>
        <p>In the third period, the Devils forced their will and their skill, taking most of the shots and keeping the Senators away from Brodeur. Gomez, Brylin and Mogilny moved like whippets, coming close several times, but were stymied. This frustration led to Mogilny's roughing penalty at 11:44 for an altercation with Chris Phillips, an Ottawa defenseman.</p>
        <p>When they returned to even strength, the Devils came close a couple more times but could not convert, and their momentum waned. With Brodeur out for an extra attacker, Gomez fanned on a moving puck in the slot and the Senators carried down and scored into the empty net, Rob Zamuner finishing the play.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>The Devils played again without center JASON ARNOTT and defenseman SCOTT NIEDERMAYER, who are not signed to contracts. A team spokesman said there was nothing to announce regarding their negotiations. . . . PATRIK ELIAS led the Devils with four shots on goal. Defenseman BRIAN RAFALSKI was a minus-3. . . . ALEKSEI YASHIN turned the boos to gasps late in the third period when he performed a spin move, perhaps inadvertently, in the Devils' zone while avoiding a check and controlling the puck.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
