<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Former Republican Stronghold Has Divided Loyalties These Days</title>
    <meta content="Y14VOT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/politics/14VOTE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238655"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: IMPRESSIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Santa Ana (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E5D8133FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Former Republican Stronghold Has Divided Loyalties These Days</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <dateline>SANTA ANA, Calif., Oct. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Voters in Santa Ana, California, veer from traditional conservatism as they flip-flop between Al Gore and George W Bush; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like his neighbors in the Floral Park section of this old Orange County city, Pete Suica, a wholesale burglar-alarm salesman, worries about the little things: how to keep his well-tended street of 1920's and 30's bungalows safe and tidy for himself and his wife, Jennifer Proctor, a nurse. But he worries about the big things, too, like the economy.</p>
        <p>''Before the first debate, I was saying, 'You know, Gore might not be a bad choice, the way the economy's going,' '' said Mr. Suica, a 42-year-old Republican with two Bush-Cheney signs in his front yard. ''You say, 'Maybe . . . ' '' he added, his voice trailing off. ''But then I saw the debate and Gore turned me off and Bush started to impress me again.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like his neighbors in the Floral Park section of this old Orange County city, Pete Suica, a wholesale burglar-alarm salesman, worries about the little things: how to keep his well-tended street of 1920's and 30's bungalows safe and tidy for himself and his wife, Jennifer Proctor, a nurse. But he worries about the big things, too, like the economy.</p>
        <p>''Before the first debate, I was saying, 'You know, Gore might not be a bad choice, the way the economy's going,' '' said Mr. Suica, a 42-year-old Republican with two Bush-Cheney signs in his front yard. ''You say, 'Maybe . . . ' '' he added, his voice trailing off. ''But then I saw the debate and Gore turned me off and Bush started to impress me again.''</p>
        <p>After the second debate, Ms. Proctor felt that way even more. ''I thought Bush did much better,'' she said. ''He seemed more in command, in control, and Gore is just so darn irritating. I thought, if I have to listen to that man for four years, I'll go crazy. You know, it's one thing for a politician to get caught in a smart lie. But in a stupid lie, that's another thing.''</p>
        <p>A few blocks away, Samuel Romero, owner of St. Teresa's Catholic Gift Shop on Fourth Street, in a stretch of shops and food stalls catering to the city's large Hispanic population, said he was leaning the opposite way.</p>
        <p>''I'm one of those guys that flip-flops from one party to another,'' said Mr. Romero, 66, who backed Ronald Reagan but four years ago voted Democratic in frustration over  the California Republican Party's campaigns against illegal immigration and affirmative action, a stance that deeply troubled Mr. Romero, a proud son of immigrants from Mexico. ''I said, what am I doing voting Republican? I'm not wanted. And here I am, a former Marine, all for the flag, and I'm not welcome.''</p>
        <p>This year, Mr. Romero was open to suggestion. In the summer, Gov. George W. Bush's nephew George P. Bush, who is also Mexican-American, made a campaign stop at Mr. Romero's store full of prayer books  and devotional objects, and Mr. Romero was impressed. He watched both debates closely, and in the second one, on Wednesday, had a flash.</p>
        <p>''They kept agreeing with each other,'' he said. ''I thought maybe what we ought to do is not make a change. I like Bush. I like his easy manner. But right now, after what I watched, it's like a friendly game of badminton, and the economy is great. So why make a change?''</p>
        <p>Evenly divided is how the conversation went this week in interviews up and down the streets of Santa Ana, smack in the heart of a county that was once a Republican stronghold. Eight years ago, this Congressional district, long represented by the fiery conservative Robert K. Dornan, voted for George Bush. But its demographics have been steadily changing, and now nearly half its residents are of Hispanic origin.</p>
        <p>In 1996, President Clinton not only beat Bob Dole here by eight percentage points, but Loretta Sanchez, a former financial analyst from nearby Anaheim, defeated Mr. Dornan by 984 votes.</p>
        <p>Now, Democratic and Republican lawn signs seem to sprout in rough parity amid the white iceberg roses and spindly purple-flowering sage of the solid middle-class streets of Floral Park, and many voters expressed ambivalence about both candidates.</p>
        <p>Even Gore supporters had some doubts about his demeanor. And even Bush supporters had some doubts about his experience and readiness for the presidency.</p>
        <p>''Did either one of them really burst out of their shell?'' asked Clarin Cheek, 30, speaking of the performances of Mr. Bush and Vice President Al Gore in the debate.  ''No.''</p>
        <p>Still, Ms. Cheek, a paralegal, and her husband, Chris, 30, who works in his family's metal-stamping business in nearby Tustin, said they were ''tending to lean towards Gore,'' as Mr. Cheek put it while they walked their yellow mutt, Zoe, at twilight.</p>
        <p>''There are some things I like Bush better on,'' Mr. Cheek said. ''I thought he'd be more judicious about intervening in situations around the world than Gore. We can't just go off everywhere.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Cheek added, ''Since these events in the Middle East, I feel a little bit more confident with Gore having international experience.''</p>
        <p>And, her husband chimed in, ''I don't think we need a huge tax cut. I think it would just take away from other programs we need.''</p>
        <p>Just across the street, Thomas Hunsaker, 38, a tile contractor renovating a house, called himself ''a moderate conservative'' and confessed that after he watched part of this week's debate, ''Gore scares me, where he'd take the country.''</p>
        <p>''I'm a wild one,'' said Mr. Hunsaker, a former commuter airline pilot and Army veteran who said he had sown his share of wild oats. ''And yet I think this White House has been less than moral. The nontruths, the lying. And even now, every time there's a fund-raising controversy, they act like they don't know anything about it.</p>
        <p>''Let me just say, I was brought up with conservative values, and there's  things that you do when you know you're not going to get caught, and then there are things you just know you shouldn't do,'' he added. ''The Clinton administration just disgusts me.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Hunsaker said, ''I do think Bush would do more to support the military, and I think he'd take a stronger foreign policy role without sticking his neck out everywhere. I don't think the economy's got any correlation with Clinton and Gore and their staff. A lot of it is from things that happened six, seven, eight years before.''</p>
        <p>Hector De La Torre, a 40-something elementary school teacher who usually votes Democratic, used exactly the same word as Mr. Hunsaker, except to describe Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>''Bush really scares me,'' Mr. De La Torre said as he stopped on Fourth Street to chat. ''He doesn't know his facts in his own state. He didn't know and he could defend himself and his tax plan when Gore attacked him. He said, 'I care about the environment,' but he couldn't explain the smog in Houston.''</p>
        <p>A few blocks away, outside the Bowers art museum on Main Street, Dick Hartman, a retired safety director for a trucking company, and his wife, Mary, stopped to talk as they left a belated Columbus Day reception. Mr. Hartman is a Republican and his wife, the daughter of Italian immigrants who describes herself as ''still a bleeding heart at heart,'' agreed that the second debate, and the whole presidential race, seemed very close.</p>
        <p>''I thought that in this debate, Bush did edge Gore out,'' said Mr. Hartman, a Navy veteran of World War II. ''He seemed more relaxed. But right now we're into this very bad situation in the Middle East, and how would he handle that if he doesn't have experience?'' But moments later he added, ''I think either way we're going to have a good president, but I think I'd feel better if it were Bush.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Hartman said she voted for Mr. Clinton four years ago, and liked much of what Mr. Gore had to say in the debates.</p>
        <p>''But then I think of these, what do they call them, exaggerations, and some of these faux pas,'' she said of Mr. Gore. ''And I've heard people say that's not just an exaggeration, but part of his character, so how do you really know? I don't.''</p>
        <p>Greg Joslyn, 46, an executive with the Orange County Foundation for Medical Care, a nonprofit organization that administers health insurance plans for businesses, was heading into the museum for another reception, this one for St. Joseph Hospital. Asked what struck him about the second debate, he replied instantly: ''Gore's complete character change. He seemed totally different from the first one. I think George is just who he says he is and what you see is what you get.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Joslyn is a Republican and a Bush supporter, but he said neither candidate was adequately addressing the burden that aging baby boomers would place on the Medicare and Social Security systems. ''I don't think either candidate, quite frankly, is really honest about the impact of that demographic boom. Something has got to be done.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Joslyn also said he liked Mr. Bush's overall attitude, and thought he would be cooperative with Democrats to get things done.</p>
        <p>''My sister lives in Texas, and she's a single-issue voter for whom a women's right to choose is really most important,'' he said. ''But even she says that as governor, Bush really has reached out across the aisle.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: IMPRESSIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
