<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Overturns Lead-Paint Control Law, Citing 'Perfunctory' Review by City Council</title>
    <meta content="14PAIN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/nyregion/14PAIN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238630"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lead</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paints and Painting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">York, Louis B (Justice)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lead</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5DA133FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Overturns Lead-Paint Control Law, Citing 'Perfunctory' Review by City Council</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Stat5</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The lead-paint control law that New York City enacted last year has been overturned by a judge who faulted the City Council for not making a required review of the law's environmental impact.</p>
        <p>The decision, by Justice Louis B. York of State Supreme Court in Manhattan, said that although state and city procedures require an environmental study, ''the Council's entire legislative review process was mostly perfunctory, only occasionally rising to the level of cursory, with the operative word being alacrity rather than analysis.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The lead-paint control law that New York City enacted last year has been overturned by a judge who faulted the City Council for not making a required review of the law's environmental impact.</p>
        <p>The decision, by Justice Louis B. York of State Supreme Court in Manhattan, said that although state and city procedures require an environmental study, ''the Council's entire legislative review process was mostly perfunctory, only occasionally rising to the level of cursory, with the operative word being alacrity rather than analysis.''</p>
        <p>The case was first reported yesterday in the New York Law Journal.</p>
        <p>The overturned law, which replaced a stricter statute, required landlords to visually inspect apartments built before 1960 when a child under 6 lived there, and specified that the city would take over repairs if a landlord failed to make them.</p>
        <p>But it allowed landlords to supervise and certify their own repairs, and made tenants responsible for reporting suspected hazards.</p>
        <p>Lead is highly toxic, especially for fetuses and young children. Exposure can cause severe and permanent physical, mental and emotional impairment.</p>
        <p>The Council speaker, Peter F. Vallone, a Democrat from Queens, issued a statement yesterday, saying:  ''It is disappointing to learn that this law has been overturned. Since the Council passed this bill, the number of children the city tests has gone up, and the number of reported cases of lead poisoning is down.''</p>
        <p>The city's lawyers said they would appeal Justice York's decision.</p>
        <p>The ruling, however, increased the pressure on the Council to again reopen the lead-paint issue, which has been debated for two decades.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Vallone did not say whether he would try to re-enact the law with proper environmental reviews, seek a new law or simply await the appeal.</p>
        <p>The original law the Council passed in 1982 was never fully enforced, but it set stricter work regulations for landlords during the removal of lead paint and required repairs to be made more quickly.</p>
        <p>The Council adopted the new law in June 1999 in an unusual split vote, over the protests of health, tenant, environmental and community groups that said it removed major protections. Some critics then challenged the law in court.</p>
        <p>Last month the federal Environmental Protection Agency told city officials that the new law was critically flawed and likely to result in more lead poisoning of children. The agency called on the city to close the loopholes.</p>
        <p>Environmental review is crucial, said Matthew J. Chachere, a lawyer for the New York City Coalition to End Lead Poisoning, the alliance that has been suing the city over lead-paint issues since 1985.</p>
        <p>''There's no way, if the Council really did a proper review, that they could come up with a law as bad as this,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Critics objected to the provisions of the law that reduced the age of children to be protected to 6 years old from 7, raised the level of lead permitted and allowed landlords to satisfy their obligations with annual visual inspections.</p>
        <p>Critics also say that the law encouraged landlords to do quick lead-control projects without strict rules and eliminated requirements for specially trained crews to do the work and for follow-up testing to detect residual lead dust.</p>
        <p>The advocacy groups had supported a different bill, sponsored by Councilman Stanley E. Michels, a Democrat from Manhattan, that would have been much stricter. Mr. Michels led the opposition that voted against the new law.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the overturned law accused Mr. Vallone of pushing it through at the behest of major campaign donors from the real estate industry.</p>
        <p>The associate director of the New York State Tenants and Neighbors Coalition, Michael McKee, praised the court ruling, saying: ''It's a slam dunk. Peter Vallone and the landlords lost, and children won.''</p>
        <p>The court ruling's immediate effect is unclear.</p>
        <p>In striking down the new law, the judge said that his action reinstated the stricter original statute, along with earlier court findings holding the city in contempt for failing to enforce that law.</p>
        <p>But the city contended that its appeal triggered a stay keeping the new law in effect. That was disputed, however, by Mr. Chachere, who said that the city was not entitled to an automatic stay.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
