<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suddenly, a Chatty Bartok And an Inexorable Liszt</title>
    <meta content="14POLL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/arts/14POLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Emerson String Quartet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollini, Maurizio</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E2DA123FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="550" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suddenly, a Chatty Bartok And an Inexorable Liszt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Tommasini reviews concert by pianist Maurizio Pollini and Emerson String Quartet, part of Pollini's concert series examining links between music from 14th century to present (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some concert hall or performing institution somewhere should try to persuade Maurizio Pollini to become its artistic director, for this great Italian pianist has demonstrated a knack for inspired programming through Carnegie Hall's Perspectives series. Last season, working with other soloists, ensembles and orchestras, Mr. Pollini began his examination of connections between music from the 14th century to  the present. When the series is completed next year, he will have performed in and planned nearly 30 programs.</p>
        <p>This season's offerings began on Thursday night with another fascinating program, this time shared by Mr. Pollini and the Emerson String Quartet. In the first half, the Emerson played the Romanian composer Gyorgy Kurtag's ''Officium Breve in Memoriam Andreae Szervanszky'' (1989). This affecting memorial work to a composer colleague is structurally daring: a series of elliptical mini-movements compressed into 12 minutes that pays homage to the radical concision of Webern. Bits of themes appear and are decisively aborted; pungent harmonies shimmer and drift away without a trace; almost as soon as they begin, pugnacious outbursts of grating chords get counter-punched cold: you never know what is going to happen next.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some concert hall or performing institution somewhere should try to persuade Maurizio Pollini to become its artistic director, for this great Italian pianist has demonstrated a knack for inspired programming through Carnegie Hall's Perspectives series. Last season, working with other soloists, ensembles and orchestras, Mr. Pollini began his examination of connections between music from the 14th century to  the present. When the series is completed next year, he will have performed in and planned nearly 30 programs.</p>
        <p>This season's offerings began on Thursday night with another fascinating program, this time shared by Mr. Pollini and the Emerson String Quartet. In the first half, the Emerson played the Romanian composer Gyorgy Kurtag's ''Officium Breve in Memoriam Andreae Szervanszky'' (1989). This affecting memorial work to a composer colleague is structurally daring: a series of elliptical mini-movements compressed into 12 minutes that pays homage to the radical concision of Webern. Bits of themes appear and are decisively aborted; pungent harmonies shimmer and drift away without a trace; almost as soon as they begin, pugnacious outbursts of grating chords get counter-punched cold: you never know what is going to happen next.</p>
        <p>Bartok, an earlier Eastern European master, is also known for his sometimes brusquely compact compositional style. But coming after the ''Officium Breve,'' Bartok's String Quartet No. 4 (1928) seemed positively loquacious. Here were complete phrases laid out with the logic of a well-constructed paragraph. The Emerson Quartet gave typically compelling accounts of both works, though in the Bartok the violinist Eugene Drucker had to tend to a broken string, which stopped the performance just minutes into the first movement. Once the problem was fixed, the musicians just started over.</p>
        <p>To begin the second half of the program, Mr. Pollini played Chopin's Prelude in C sharp minor (Op. 45) with such sensitivity to its wayward chromatic harmony and elusive structure that Chopin seemed like yet another cutting-edge Eastern European composer. This was, no doubt, the idea. Mr. Pollini brought the same exploratory quality to one of Chopin's most experimental works, the ''Polonaise Fantaisie,'' which sounded like some dreamy, halting and captivating memory of a stirring Polish dance.</p>
        <p>He then played two short late works of Liszt, ''Nuages Gris'' and ''La Lugubre Gondola,'' with such an accentuated sense of the music's radical harmony that Liszt seemed for a moment the most modern composer on the program. In Mr. Pollini's noble performance, Liszt's great Sonata in B minor, which is more a fantastical than many works called fantasies, sounded organic and inexorable. That said, for all the insight, elegance and brilliance of Mr. Pollini's playing, his well-known expressive reticence was very much present. The intellectual rigor of his playing is not always matched by rhythmic rigor. He seemed freer in three generous encores by Chopin: the Preludes in D minor and D flat from Opus 28 and the Ballade in G minor.</p>
        <p>But reservations do not count much next to Mr. Pollini's artistry and vision, both fully present in this entire Perspectives project.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
