<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Producer Prices Jumped 0.9% in September, Mostly Because of Oil</title>
    <meta content="Y14ECO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/business/14ECON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238599"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Producer Price Index</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonhardt, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Producer Price Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E3DE133FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Producer Prices Jumped 0.9% in September, Mostly Because of Oil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leonhardt, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bureau of Labor Statistics reports that producer price index of finished goods rose 0.9 percent in September, its largest increase since February; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American manufacturers were able to charge surprisingly high prices for their goods in September, the government reported yesterday, but most analysts said the increases were probably not a harbinger of broader inflation. Investors seemed to agree, as major stock indexes rose.</p>
        <p>The data on pricing and a report showing strong retail sales point to the resilience of the American economy, despite two years of rising oil prices and a six-week spell of declining stock prices, economists said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American manufacturers were able to charge surprisingly high prices for their goods in September, the government reported yesterday, but most analysts said the increases were probably not a harbinger of broader inflation. Investors seemed to agree, as major stock indexes rose.</p>
        <p>The data on pricing and a report showing strong retail sales point to the resilience of the American economy, despite two years of rising oil prices and a six-week spell of declining stock prices, economists said.</p>
        <p>The Producer Price Index of finished goods -- a measure of what American buyers, be they consumers or companies, pay for domestically made products -- rose 0.9 percent last month, its largest increase since February, according to the Bureau of Labor Statistics.</p>
        <p>About two-thirds of the rise came from the energy sector, in which prices tend to be driven by a global market and do not generally reflect month-to-month shifts in American consumer demand. An increase in car and truck prices was the second most important cause for the unexpected jump in the index, and initial data for October suggest that vehicle prices are likely to decline.</p>
        <p>As a result, the report, said James F. O'Sullivan, an economist at J. P. Morgan, ''is not as alarming as the headline number -- the general trends are still pretty tame.''</p>
        <p>Edward Yardeni, the chief economist at Deutsche Banc Alex. Brown, added, ''I think the bottom line is that inflation is going to stay close to zero.''</p>
        <p>Prices for food, alcoholic beverages and cleaning products also rose, when compared with August and adjusted for normal seasonal variations, according to the report. The cost of glassware, electronic equipment and women's clothing fell.</p>
        <p>Economists pay particular attention to the so-called core index, which excludes volatile energy and food prices. It rose 0.3 percent last month -- also higher than expectations.</p>
        <p>Analysts said, however, that the price index and the 0.9 percent increase in retail sales in September were unlikely to alter the Federal Reserve's policy. At its last meeting, the Federal Open Market Committee kept interest rates at their current level but noted that the risk of inflation remained higher than the risk of a downturn. Since that meeting, import prices have dropped and some high-profile companies, have warned of earnings shortfalls.</p>
        <p>Investors seemed to see little in the reports to suggest an impending rate increase, and many stocks finished higher for the first time since last week. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index, after having fallen 7 percent since Oct. 6, regained about half of its losses yesterday, closing at 1,374.17, up 44.39 points.</p>
        <p>In part, the lack of inflation fears stems from a belief that consumer spending will slow in the final months of the year, thanks to high oil prices and tepid stock market gains.</p>
        <p>So far, though, there is little evidence that people are pulling back. Retail sales also rose at their fastest pace since February and roughly 50 percent more than analysts had expected. Nearly every sector saw an increase, according to the Department of Commerce.</p>
        <p>Consumer surveys, like the University of Michigan's, have shown that many Americans expect gas prices to come down from their current level, which are the highest in a decade but still lower than they were in the late 1970's and early 1980's, when adjusted for inflation.</p>
        <p>Last month gasoline prices rose 9 percent from their August level in the producer index. Most other energy costs continued to jump as well.</p>
        <p>The biggest surprise in the report was the increase in the cost of passenger vehicles, even though many automakers have recently announced rebates. But analysts said the rise of about 1.5 percent appears be to a statistical blip.</p>
        <p>For starters, prices had fallen in previous months despite growing sales, and this month's increase simply brings vehicle costs closer to the level of earlier this year, said Dean Baker, the co-director for the Center for Economic Policy and Research in Washington.</p>
        <p>In addition, Ford Motor and General Motors, the world's two largest car companies, have offered many new rebates in the first half of October, according to Deutsche Banc. That suggests that vehicle costs will not rise again this month.</p>
        <p>The Producer Price Index, which includes many goods bought by distributors, is often a leading indicator of the more closely watched Consumer Price Index. The comparison is imperfect, however, because the consumer index also covers services. It will be released next week.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
