<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High Hopes for Seton Hall, but First Up, a Little Fun</title>
    <meta content="14SETO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/sports/14SETO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seton Hall University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E4D7133FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High Hopes for Seton Hall, but First Up, a Little Fun</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>SOUTH ORANGE, N.J., Oct. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses outlook for Seton Hall basketball team this season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Tommy Amaker was hired to rebuild Seton Hall three years ago, he refused to play host to Midnight Madness, instead choosing to begin the preseason in a low-key manner.</p>
        <p>Now, after the Pirates' surprising surge into the Round of 16 last season, and armed with the most highly-acclaimed recruiting class in school history, Amaker decided to dim the lights tonight at Walsh Gymnasium and let the spotlight shine on the Pirates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Tommy Amaker was hired to rebuild Seton Hall three years ago, he refused to play host to Midnight Madness, instead choosing to begin the preseason in a low-key manner.</p>
        <p>Now, after the Pirates' surprising surge into the Round of 16 last season, and armed with the most highly-acclaimed recruiting class in school history, Amaker decided to dim the lights tonight at Walsh Gymnasium and let the spotlight shine on the Pirates.</p>
        <p>Seton Hall was the host of its first Midnight Madness since 1996, thus giving students their first glimpse of a team that has high expectations.</p>
        <p>Amaker's recruiting class of Eddie Griffin of Roman Catholic High School (Philadelphia), regarded by some as the top freshman in the country; Seton Hall Prep's Marcus Toney-El; Andre Barrett of Rice High School; and Damion Fray of Walt Whitman High School (Huntington Station, N.Y.) is considered by many to be the best one in the nation.</p>
        <p>St. John's, meanwhile, decided not to hold Midnight Madness. Instead, Coach Mike Jarvis will simply push the newcomers Omar Cook, Kyle Cuffe and Willie Shaw in practice at midnight.</p>
        <p>In Bloomington, Ind., there will be Midnight Madness, but for the first time in 29 years it will be without Bob Knight.</p>
        <p>Amaker said: ''When I got here my first year, I just thought that it had been done and we should try something different. I want our guys to earn things. It's a fun thing, but I wanted them to earn it. If they want something for the program, I want to provide it because we deserve it.''</p>
        <p>Amaker conceded that he was outnumbered in his opinion, with excitement growing over the prospect of this team.</p>
        <p>''It was the kids' idea and the students', too,'' Amaker said. ''The students on campus have missed it. I've kind of became the villain around here not having it. Maybe I'll move back into their good graces.''</p>
        <p>The Pirates, 22-10 last season, advanced to the Round of 16 with two dramatic victories. They slipped past Oregon in the opening round, 72-71, when Shaheen Holloway drove the length of the court for a layup with 1.9 seconds left in overtime. In the next game they upset Temple, 67-65, also in overtime, when Ty Shine, playing for the injured Holloway, scored a career-high 26 points, including the decisive 3-point field goal with 18 seconds to play.</p>
        <p>The magic ran out with a 68-66 loss to Oklahoma State.</p>
        <p>Holloway and Rimas Kaukenas are gone, but with Samuel Dalembert, Shine and Darius Lane returning, the Pirates have a solid base to challenge for the Big East crown.</p>
        <p>While Amaker will let the students and players have their fun tonight, he is looking forward to Saturday morning, when the Pirates will really begin to try to work the new talent in with a solid returning core.</p>
        <p>One of the team's most notable returning players, Samuel Dalembert, was not allowed to participate in the Midnight Madness because of a violation of team rules. He will join the team Saturday.</p>
        <p>Amaker said: ''We want to start teaching and working. Certainly, Midnight Madness is not an environment to teach and work.</p>
        <p>''I think it's going to be a process, a journey. The sure thing we, as coaches, have to remember is that they are very young and it's a long horse race. We have tough opponents early in our schedule. We go on the road. These kids need to get thrown to the fire, thrown to the wolves. It's going to be a process, and as long as we remember that these kids are young, we'll be all right.''</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Casting a Spell at UConn  STORRS, Conn., Oct. 13  AP</p>
        <p>A hypnotist was scheduled to be part of the prepractice festivities at Gampel Pavilion tonight as Connecticut kicked off the 2000-1 season with Midnight Madness. But he will have a tough time snapping the fans from the time-honored trance that has become Huskymania.</p>
        <p>After all, the fans have just been treated to the most successful three-year run in the school's history. During that span, Jim Calhoun's Huskies were 91-17 and won the national championship in 1999.</p>
        <p>The 2000-1 squad is without the core of that successful group because of graduation and early jumps to the National Basketball Association. With the departures of Khalid El-Amin, Jake Voskuhl and Kevin Freeman, Calhoun must find the next leader, someone who can either start or finish the Huskies' familiar fast-break offense.</p>
        <p>His choices range from the soft-spoken Albert Mouring, a 3-point specialist, to the emotional power forward Edmund Saunders. Mouring is the only player returning who averaged double figures last season with 13.9 points a game. Saunders averaged 4.8 rebounds and 6.8 points.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
