<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Riding the Cosmic Line, The Last Stop Is Death</title>
    <meta content="14LINE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/arts/14LINE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238573"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Primary Stages Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruckner, D J R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alfaro, Luis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Straight as a Line (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E5D8123FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Riding the Cosmic Line, The Last Stop Is Death</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By D. J. R. BRUCKNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruckner, D J R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>theater review: riding the cosmic7</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Think of ''Straight as a Line,'' Luis Alfaro's 70-minute one-act, as a poem; it will save sorting out a lot of confusion that can come of expecting a play-as-we-know-it. Even though a man dies of AIDS onstage, it is not necessarily a work about AIDS; almost any irreversibly degenerative disease would have served. In Mr. Alfaro's poems, stories and performance pieces, wasting is a deep theme; if there were a literary laureate of the second law of thermodynamics, he would have a good claim on the title.</p>
        <p>The play is about migration, in a cosmic sense. In the production by Primary Stages, its characters, Paulie (James Sie) and his ''Mum'' (Natsuko Ohama), are British immigrants. That they are strikingly Asian in appearance only makes the point more insistent: they could be from anywhere; we are all migrants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Think of ''Straight as a Line,'' Luis Alfaro's 70-minute one-act, as a poem; it will save sorting out a lot of confusion that can come of expecting a play-as-we-know-it. Even though a man dies of AIDS onstage, it is not necessarily a work about AIDS; almost any irreversibly degenerative disease would have served. In Mr. Alfaro's poems, stories and performance pieces, wasting is a deep theme; if there were a literary laureate of the second law of thermodynamics, he would have a good claim on the title.</p>
        <p>The play is about migration, in a cosmic sense. In the production by Primary Stages, its characters, Paulie (James Sie) and his ''Mum'' (Natsuko Ohama), are British immigrants. That they are strikingly Asian in appearance only makes the point more insistent: they could be from anywhere; we are all migrants.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alfaro, who in performance and writing has brilliantly evoked the Chicano experience in Los Angeles, is acutely sensitive to the many layers of satisfying self-deception in the casual American formula ''a nation of immigrants,'' which, to everyone of the second generation or beyond, means ''all those other people.''</p>
        <p>That Paulie and his mother are British and definitely not upper-class calls up a meaningful echo, however; a Joe Orton shadow of tragic meanness falls on these people. The underlying question here, as in much of Mr. Alfaro's work, is what, in a universe of migrants, draws any of us together; in this case dying does, but in a way so tentative it makes you apprehensive about the weakness, perhaps the exhaustion, of death itself. After all, if death isn't final, what is? Mr. Alfaro's attitude invites you to go ask someone else.</p>
        <p>Mum, a onetime prostitute who is now makes change at a Las Vegas casino, had thrown Paulie into the streets when he was 12 on the puritanical principle that ''if you're old enough to drink beer, you are old enough to make a living.'' Paulie, a male prostitute until disease made him undesirable, invites Mum to New York to witness his throwing himself in front of a subway train. At least that's the ruse; it is a way of getting reconnected. In fact, he goes back to Las Vegas with her to die, his condition simply a personal metaphor for inexorable dessication by the desert everyone lives in, which all the glittery pretense of the Vegas strip cannot conceal.</p>
        <p>Not that Mr. Alfaro allows Paulie and Mum to say anything directly about all that. In fact, much of their dialogue is quite funny, if often abrasive and sometimes cruel, until the last short scene. I suspect most viewers will think the playwright has made a striking mistake by separating scenes with quick blackouts that are variations on crude jokes about doctors euphemistically delivering death sentences, but even those missteps are not uninteresting examples of the chances this writer will take. A bigger gamble that does not pay off in ''Straight as a Line'' is his extreme distance from the characters and the secret fears they share, which fester into something close to despair. There is an icy feeling to this play that makes the Quentin Tarantino of ''Pulp Fiction,'' by comparison, seem positively sticky with warm compassion.</p>
        <p>So, the play's effect depends to an unusual extent on the director and actors, and, as difficult as this work can be to take at times, I would be content to be in their company for much longer than their hour or so.</p>
        <p>Jon Lawrence Rivera, the founder of Playwrights' Arena in Los Angeles, directs with a conductor's sense of timing; the suggestion of musical movements and of variations on themes that culminate in an aching silence is very powerful. And since Mr. Alfaro has entrusted so many of his dramatic efforts first to Mr. Rivera, one might assume that this conception of the play is authentic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sie has performed Paulie in several places since he first appeared in the role under Mr. Rivera's direction at Playwrights' Arena a year ago, but he still manages to make Paulie cringe from any insight into who he is. He may be dying, but he's still an annoying little twit whose insouciance is much more repulsive than all his cancerous lesions. And Ms. Ohama turns Mum from an ignorant and delightful comic figure into a woman beaten down by knowledge she can no longer deny with such subtlety that her transformation comes as a shock when you realize what has happened.</p>
        <p>''Straight as a Line'' is not neat. It sets loose all kinds of emotions and provides no container at all to take them home in.</p>
        <p>STRAIGHT AS A LINE  By Luis Alfaro; directed by Jon Lawrence Rivera; sets by Bob Phillips; lighting by Deborah Constantine; sound by Eric Shim; production manager, Joshua Helman; stage manager, Renee Lutz; associate producer, Seth Gordon; managing director, Margaret Chandler. Presented by Primary Stages, Casey Childs, artistic director. At 354 West 45th Street, Clinton.</p>
        <p>WITH: James Sie (Paulie) and Natsuko Ohama (Mum).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
