<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore's Brother-in-Law Plays Crucial Role in the Campaign</title>
    <meta content="14BROT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/politics/14BROT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238634"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE GORE FAMILY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hunger, Frank W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905EFDA133FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore's Brother-in-Law Plays Crucial Role in the Campaign</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>MILWAUKEE, Oct. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank W Hunger, who was married to Vice Pres Al Gore's late sister, is perhaps Gore's best friend and among his most valued advisers; is discreet and offers much of his advice in private, making his influence hard to quantify; has taken leave from law firm to travel with Gore, serving as intermediary between campaign staff and candidate; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As soon as the first presidential debate ended last week, Vice President Al Gore's wife, three daughters and son-in-law joined him on stage, creating a handsome family portrait for the cameras. But Mr. Gore thought the picture was incomplete. He motioned to the audience, summoning an older man with a weathered face and a shock of white hair, who bounded up, giving Mr. Gore a hearty hug and a slap on the back.</p>
        <p>For Al Gore, there is no question that the man, Frank W. Hunger, is family, and then some. Though not related by blood, they share more than four decades of history. Some memories are jubilant, like their constant companionship during Mr. Gore's successful campaigns for the Senate and the vice presidency. Others are heartbreaking, like the 1984 death of Nancy Hunger -- Mr. Hunger's vivacious wife and Mr. Gore's beloved only sibling -- after a prolonged battle with lung cancer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As soon as the first presidential debate ended last week, Vice President Al Gore's wife, three daughters and son-in-law joined him on stage, creating a handsome family portrait for the cameras. But Mr. Gore thought the picture was incomplete. He motioned to the audience, summoning an older man with a weathered face and a shock of white hair, who bounded up, giving Mr. Gore a hearty hug and a slap on the back.</p>
        <p>For Al Gore, there is no question that the man, Frank W. Hunger, is family, and then some. Though not related by blood, they share more than four decades of history. Some memories are jubilant, like their constant companionship during Mr. Gore's successful campaigns for the Senate and the vice presidency. Others are heartbreaking, like the 1984 death of Nancy Hunger -- Mr. Hunger's vivacious wife and Mr. Gore's beloved only sibling -- after a prolonged battle with lung cancer.</p>
        <p>Sixteen years later, Mr. Hunger is  perhaps the vice president's closest friend. And in this campaign, as in Gore campaigns past, he is also among Mr. Gore's most valued advisers, a man whose counsel is treasured because he has no agenda other than the advancement of Al Gore.</p>
        <p>''He is the only one traveling with Al Gore,'' said the campaign manager, Donna Brazile, ''who can look him eye to eye and keep his day job.''</p>
        <p>A successful corporate litigator and former top Justice Department official, Mr. Hunger, 64, is sometimes mentioned as a potential attorney general in a Gore administration, a Robert Kennedy to Mr. Gore's John. Such nepotism would probably be politically untenable today. But if Mr. Gore wins, Mr. Hunger will clearly be one of the most influential people in the White House, whether he works there or not.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Hunger is discreet and offers much of his advice in private, even Mr. Gore's top strategists say his influence is hard to quantify. But they know that it is there, and that his reach as a minister without portfolio stretches from the profound to the trivial, from the choice of a running mate to the selection of beer on Air Force Two.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunger was among the few in a Nashville hotel room when Mr. Gore winnowed his list of potential running mates to Senator Joseph I. Lieberman. When one aide asked whether the country was ready for a Jewish vice president, Mr. Hunger silenced the discussion. ''If it's not,'' he said, ''it damn well should be.''</p>
        <p>Since taking unpaid leave from a Washington law office on June 30, Mr. Hunger, often in his campaign uniform of dungarees and running shoes, has traveled with Mr. Gore virtually every day, as he did today  here in Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>Of the many voices that Mr. Gore hears on strategic issues, Mr. Hunger's redolent Mississippi drawl is often the last. He serves as an intermediary between the campaign staff and the candidate, delivering difficult messages and gauging the correct moment to approach Mr. Gore for thorny decisions.</p>
        <p>His politics, Mr. Hunger said, are similar to Mr. Gore's, but he generally avoids discussions of government policy, feeling it is not his place. He  helps Mr. Gore prepare for debates, however, sometimes simply by buffering him from a deluge of advice. He served as a sounding board for Mr. Gore's convention speech. He will also get people hired to the campaign staff. And at the vice president's request, he investigated why the campaign was hemorrhaging money last year, and as a result recommended moving the headquarters from Washington to less expensive Nashville.</p>
        <p>''I don't have a title, and I don't have any responsibilities,'' Mr. Hunger said. ''It's the best of all worlds. Whenever anything comes up that he wants done, I do it. And I try to keep my mouth shut and my ears open.''</p>
        <p>He did rail at Gore aides, however, when the vice president took what Mr. Hunger considered a boneheaded position on Elian Gonzalez and when the campaign did not move quickly to quash the furor over Mr. Gore's claims about the price of drugs for his dog. Known for a sense of connection to typical Americans,  he took an early interest in the rising price of gasoline and advised Mr. Gore to get out in front of the issue.</p>
        <p>And yet less weighty matters are not beneath his concern. When Mr. Gore strolled barefoot along a Florida beach last week while being interviewed by two reporters, Mr. Hunger walked alongside and issued constant alerts -- ''Watch your foot!'' -- about sharp shells in the sand.</p>
        <p>But perhaps Mr. Hunger's most significant role is as Mr. Gore's fun-loving alter ego. Mischievous and slightly irreverent, he is the crazy uncle of both the Gore family and the Gore campaign, and it falls to him to keep the famously disciplined candidate loose and relaxed. He is easy to laugh, eager to dance and ready with a Rebel whoop at any sign of good news. On Mr. Gore's post-convention riverboat trip down the Mississippi, he walked the decks in bare feet, shorts and a Hawaiian shirt.</p>
        <p>With no children of his own, he is devoted to the four Gore children; he has attended their ballgames, been to their graduations and slipped them sips of his beer. Even the campaign staff calls him Uncle Frank. For years, he had Mr. Gore's eldest daughter, Karenna, believing that he had shared a bunk with Elvis Presley in the military (though Presley served in the Army and Mr. Hunger in the Air Force). On his 60th birthday, at Kristin Gore's urging, he jumped from an airplane at 11,000 feet. The free fall, he says, ''scared the bejesus out of me.''</p>
        <p>Tipper Gore, who shares her own friendship with Mr. Hunger, calls him the Auntie Mame of the family.  ''He gets Al to have fun,'' she said. ''He'll say: 'Enough of that. Let's have a beer.' With Frank around, Al's more prone to laugh, cut up, think of jokes, play. I think Frank lightens him up and loosens him up, most definitely.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunger is also the Gores' tenant, living in the Tudor house in Arlington, Va., that they vacated in 1993 to move into the vice president's official residence in Washington.  The house once belonged to the grandparents of Mrs. Gore, who moved there as a child with her mother after her parents divorced.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunger has only grown closer to his brother-in-law since the death of Nancy Hunger, Mr. Gore's older sister, who was a longtime smoker. The bond was forged in part during the two agonizing years when the men researched her lung-cancer treatment and consoled each other through her deterioration. Mr. Hunger encouraged Mr. Gore to speak about her death in his anti-tobacco speech at the 1996 Democratic National Convention, not anticipating the cynical reaction following news accounts that Mr. Gore had boasted, while in tobacco country during previous campaigns, that he had farmed the crop. ''Might have been one of the dumber things I've done,'' Mr. Hunger said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore says he values Mr. Hunger for his integrity, his experience and his judgment, which the vice president says is ''the best of practically anybody I know.''</p>
        <p>''He's the closest thing I have to a brother,'' said Mr. Gore, 52, pausing before appending one of the good-natured barbs that characterize their friendship. ''An older brother, I might add.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunger, 12 years the vice president's senior, chuckled when told of Mr. Gore's aside, then said, ''I have no better or closer friend in the world.''</p>
        <p>The son of a dry cleaner, Mr. Hunger was born in Winona, Miss., roughly midway between Memphis and Jackson, and attended the University of Mississippi as an undergraduate and for one year of law school before finishing his legal education at Duke. His law school roommate in Oxford was Thad Cochran, now one of Mississippi's two Republican senators. Despite their political differences, they remain fast friends, and Mr. Hunger has enthusiastically supported Mr. Cochran's campaigns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunger left Ole Miss after the ugliness of 1961, when riots accompanied the desegregation of the university. ''I was very upset at the way my state behaved,'' he said. Mr. Hunger, friends say, always had progressive views on race, and that qualified him as a liberal by the standards of the place and time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunger met Nancy Gore while visiting a longtime friend from Winona at Vanderbilt, where she was an undergraduate. Gregarious, smart and sophisticated, she captivated him as she did most all who knew her. ''She was one of the most attractive women I'd ever seen in my life,'' he said. They began dating several years later and married in 1966.</p>
        <p>The Hungers lived in Greenville, Miss., an oasis of progressive politics in the heart of the Delta, and quickly became part of its eclectic intellectual fabric. They befriended both Hodding Carter 3d, the editor of the city's crusading integrationist newspaper, and Clark Reed, a pioneer of the state's Republican Party. On weekends, Mr. Hunger and his friend Billy Percy, a nephew of the novelist Walker Percy, would go duck hunting on Mississippi River sandbars.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunger became a successful corporate litigator for Lake Tindall, Greenville's most prominent firm. He specialized in defending oil companies like Shell and Exxon in toxicity cases and vehicle manufacturers in product liability matters like those arising from rollovers of Honda's all-terrain vehicles.</p>
        <p>It was lucrative work. The last financial disclosure report that Mr. Hunger filed with the Justice Department, in 1999, showed he had assets of at least $4 million. Among them were significant holdings in the companies that Mr. Gore now derides as ''big oil'' and ''big drug companies.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunger had become assistant attorney general in charge of the Justice Department's immense civil division, with nearly 700 lawyers handling 22,000 cases, after the 1992 election. Mr. Gore helped him get the appointment, but in his six years at Justice he won widespread admiration for his judgment in a broad variety of cases, including the government's ultimately unsuccessful defense of the Food and Drug Administration's efforts to regulate tobacco.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunger enthusiastically backed that government stand but thought that court precedent could not support a government suit seeking damages from the tobacco companies to recover costs of treating smoking-related illnesses. That suit  was not filed until after he left the Justice Department in January 1999 to become a partner with the Washington office of an Atlanta-based law firm, Long Aldridge &amp; Norman, from which he has been on leave since early summer.</p>
        <p>Those who worked with Mr. Hunger at Justice say he never overtly played the Gore card.</p>
        <p>''In my four years with Frank at the Department of Justice, not once did I ever hear him mention the vice president, in a meeting or any other conversation,'' said former Solicitor General Walter Dellinger, who adds that his friend is ''easy to underestimate.''</p>
        <p>But others say Mr. Hunger's relationship clearly gave him influence,  and the backbone to resist outside pressures.</p>
        <p>''He'd get a lot of calls saying the White House wants this, that or the other,'' recalled George J. Phillips, Mr. Hunger's chief of staff at the department. ''He'd say: 'The White House is just a building. You tell me who in the White House wants that.' ''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE GORE FAMILY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
