<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abroad at Home; But There Is No Peace</title>
    <meta content="14LEWI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/opinion/14LEWI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEED7123FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="757" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abroad at Home; But There Is No Peace</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Anthony</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Lewis Op-Ed column observes that particular pain of latest Palestinian violence is that negotiated settlement seemed so near; explains that fundamental logic of human and geographic situation points to solution something like that proposed by Prime Min Ehud Barak at Camp David (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In April 1993, as South Africans were negotiating an end to the apartheid system, white extremists assassinated a popular black leader, Chris Hani. Black anger brought riots that threatened to derail the negotiations. Nelson Mandela, asked by the white government to speak on state television, called for calm. The negotiations went on, and succeeded.</p>
        <p>But there is no Palestinian Mandela. The shattering events of the last two weeks have made clear that Yasir Arafat is unwilling or unable to play that role. He played a great part in putting the Palestinian cause on the world's agenda. But he does not have the vision, or the serenity, to turn his people toward the difficult compromises of peace and democracy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In April 1993, as South Africans were negotiating an end to the apartheid system, white extremists assassinated a popular black leader, Chris Hani. Black anger brought riots that threatened to derail the negotiations. Nelson Mandela, asked by the white government to speak on state television, called for calm. The negotiations went on, and succeeded.</p>
        <p>But there is no Palestinian Mandela. The shattering events of the last two weeks have made clear that Yasir Arafat is unwilling or unable to play that role. He played a great part in putting the Palestinian cause on the world's agenda. But he does not have the vision, or the serenity, to turn his people toward the difficult compromises of peace and democracy.</p>
        <p>Palestinians say that Ariel Sharon's visit to the Temple Mount was a deliberate provocation for his own political purposes, and that is true. They say that their violent protests reflect deeply felt grievances, and that also is true. Their land has been seized, settlements planted in their midst by force -- and expanded even now.</p>
        <p>But black South Africans had grievances at least as profound. They had lived under white domination for centuries, their land taken from them, their status reduced to virtual serfdom. Yet under the leadership of Nelson Mandela and his colleagues they understood that patience and negotiation were the best way to vindicate their rights.</p>
        <p>The particular pain of these last days is that a negotiated settlement of the Israeli-Palestinian conflict seemed so near. At Camp David, Prime Minister Ehud Barak had offered concessions that were surely a basis for agreement. But Mr. Arafat did not respond with any show of flexibility. He evidently decided that it was time to move from the negotiating table to the streets.</p>
        <p>Once let loose, violence is hard to stop. It has led to the lynching of Israeli soldiers. Israel's weapons have taken nearly 100 Palestinian lives. On both sides hearts have hardened. Bitterness -- and fear -- mock the very idea of negotiation.</p>
        <p>''I have been eternally optimistic,'' an Israeli friend who was a founder of the Peace Now movement said to me on the telephone. ''But right now it's hard to see a way out.''</p>
        <p>The first step has to be an end to the violence. That means a clear signal from Chairman Arafat -- the opposite of the signal he sent the other day by releasing some Hamas members from prison. It also requires restraint on the Israeli side.</p>
        <p>In the end the fundamental logic of the situation, human and geographical, points toward a solution something like the Barak proposals at Camp David. Before the recent events, more and more Israelis had come to understand that peace for them required allowing the Palestinians to have a political expression of their national feeling: a state in most of the West Bank and Gaza with its capital in East Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>It will be difficult to return to the negotiating process that had come close to that end. If Prime Minister Barak brings the right-wing Likud Party and its leader, Mr. Sharon, into an emergency government, that will be a further obstacle. Mr. Sharon is a symbol, to Palestinians, of disregard for their humanity.</p>
        <p>But I would not write off the possibility of some progress if and when calm is restored. Mr. Sharon, for all his jingoism and arrogance, has an interest in reducing the level of tension. And the only way to do that is to take practical steps on the ground.</p>
        <p>There could be another interim agreement giving the Palestinians political control over more of the West Bank. It could ease their lives by reducing the number of Israeli checkpoints they must pass to travel between their own cities and towns. Israel could impose a true freeze at last on all settlement activity. Of course all this would depend on a credible end to Palestinian violence.</p>
        <p>''The Palestinians are our neighbors forever,'' Prime Minister Barak said Thursday in an interview with Christiane Amanpour of CNN. ''We will never lose hope of peace.''</p>
        <p>Yes, the presence of the Palestinians is the inescapable reality of Israel's existence. But there is an alternative to peace: endless conflict, swelling now and again to cruel bloodshed. The horror of that alternative is what should eventually turn both sides back to the search for peace.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
