<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Price of America's Naivete</title>
    <meta content="14GERE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/opinion/14GERE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238629"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cole (USS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yemen</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gerecht, Reuel Marc</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DA133FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Price of America's Naivete</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Reuel Marc Gerecht</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gerecht, Reuel Marc</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reuel Marc Gerecht Op-Ed article on long and merciless history in Middle East explains bombing of USS Cole in Yemen and turmoil in Israel and West Bank as violent expressions of age-old confrontation between Islam and the West; points out that US foriegn policy usually ignores fact that US walks in footsteps of Europe in region (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>History is long and merciless in the Middle East. The suicide boat-bombing of the U.S.S. Cole in the port of Aden, Yemen, and the turmoil in Israel, Gaza and the West Bank are, above all else, violent expressions of the age-old confrontation between Islam and the West. America, no less than Israel, is inextricably tied to the Muslim-Christian tug-of-war that began in the seventh century when Arab armies first conquered Palestine.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, America's foreign policy has usually ignored, if not denied, the fact that the United States walks in the footsteps of Europe in the Middle East. We are the region's pre-eminent Western power, the successor to Great Britain, but we see ourselves as of the new world, not the old: able to be ''friends'' with anybody, regardless of race, creed, or religion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>History is long and merciless in the Middle East. The suicide boat-bombing of the U.S.S. Cole in the port of Aden, Yemen, and the turmoil in Israel, Gaza and the West Bank are, above all else, violent expressions of the age-old confrontation between Islam and the West. America, no less than Israel, is inextricably tied to the Muslim-Christian tug-of-war that began in the seventh century when Arab armies first conquered Palestine.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, America's foreign policy has usually ignored, if not denied, the fact that the United States walks in the footsteps of Europe in the Middle East. We are the region's pre-eminent Western power, the successor to Great Britain, but we see ourselves as of the new world, not the old: able to be ''friends'' with anybody, regardless of race, creed, or religion.</p>
        <p>American exceptionalism -- the ironclad belief that our secular tradition of toleration, moderation and compromise can transcend the religions and animosities of older societies -- has led us to see others as we would want them to see themselves. This naivete, complemented by the naivete of many on the Israeli left, who also downplay and deride religion as the defining feature of people's lives, has provoked the Middle East's present strife far more than Ariel Sharon's visit to the Temple Mount.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration has tenaciously pursued a peace process that Muslims regard as an insult to their pride. Muslims from Tangiers to Tehran may be willing to concede that Israel exists because, as the Soviets used to say, the correlation of forces allows no other alternative. But they rebel against the idea that Jews have a legitimate, historic right to a state west of the Jordan river, which is, after all, the ultimate objective of the peace process. For decades, the State Department has operated under the assumption that with the right batch of Israeli concessions the Arab world would tire, cut a deal, and recognize the legitimacy of the Jewish state.</p>
        <p>There is no doubt that the Middle East is no longer a hotbed of competing virulently anti-Israeli Arab nationalisms. Pan-Arabism, Ba'athism and Nasserism have all given way to new national identities, in which the Muslim component has regained considerable ground. And for a Muslim, who views Islam as God's final revelation and can recall with vividness and understandable pride nearly a thousand years of Muslim triumph and superiority over Christendom (that is, the West), the presence and strength of Israel is a painful reminder of Islam's long fall from power. Though esteemed for their knowledge, Jews are usually characterized in Islamic tradition as cowardly and weak. Losing to Christians over the last 300 years has been bad enough; losing to Jews since 1947 has been especially galling.</p>
        <p>A quick read of the Arabic press, particularly the Palestinian press, with its calls to holy war and slogans of ''Death to the Jews,'' ought to give pause to those who still believe that with just one more Israeli concession -- East Jerusalem -- the Arab world would convert what it calls ''Jewish Crusaders'' into legitimate neighbors. Palestinian Arab nationalism is younger than its Israeli Jewish counterpart, but the Muslim reluctance to concede that ''Muslim lands'' can ever legitimately be relinquished to infidels is age-old, imbedded into Islamic law and custom.</p>
        <p>Palestinian Arab nationalism, born through conflict with Palestinian Jewish nationalism and intellectually nourished since 1948 by virulent, Western-imported anti-Semitism, reinforces the religious tendency to see Israel as an alien power and Jews as unrelenting hostile to the Islamic faith.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration, like the Bush administration before it, unwisely chose to advance the ''peace process'' as quickly as possible, attempting in effect to force the Palestinians and those Arabs allied to their cause to make de facto recognition of Israel de jure. We have in essence been demanding that they in broad daylight forsake their history and their faith as they have come to understand them. They quite naturally have declined.</p>
        <p>The Americans and the Israelis have managed to make happen in only 10 years what America's enemies in the Middle East could only have dreamed of doing. Laid low by two decades of miscalculation, Yasir Arafat and the Palestinian Liberation Organization were then revived by secret and then open diplomacy with Jerusalem and Washington.</p>
        <p>Washington encouraged -- and Jerusalem delivered -- concession after concession to Mr. Arafat, even though Mr. Arafat, when speaking Arabic to the Arab world, never abandoned the claims that the Palestinian Arabs have always made to all of Israel.</p>
        <p>Further east, Saddam Hussein has turned the tables on the United States in the public opinion wars. Mr. Hussein may not yet have rebuilt his army, but he has made immense progress in demonstrating that Arab radicals, if not Arab monarchs, still know how to stand up against the West.</p>
        <p>When Israel precipitously withdrew from Lebanon, abandoning the allied South Lebanese Army to the mercy of Hezbollah, a wave of pride rippled through the Middle East. When Israeli Prime Minister Ehud Barak made concessions at Camp David touching on East Jerusalem and the Temple Mount, the people of the ''Arab street,'' to which Yasir Arafat is connected at the navel, saw Israel and America on the run. From that moment, violence in Israel, the West Bank, Gaza and Jordan was inevitable.</p>
        <p>If the United States had moved its embassy from Tel Aviv to Jerusalem at the end of the Gulf War, we would have sent a crystal-clear signal to both our enemies and our friends that America's writ and Israel's legitimacy are non-negotiable and indomitable. We went in the other direction, toward the peace process and what we called even-handedness.</p>
        <p>For both our Arab friends and our Arab enemies -- and especially for the Israelis who, despite their faults, remain the only liberal democracy in the region -- we should realize that the peace process will not change the anti-Western fundamentals of the Middle East. Both Washington and Jerusalem will have to live in an imperfect, sometimes violent world, where peace is found in heaven, not on earth.</p>
        <p>Reuel Marc Gerecht, a former Middle East specialist in the Central Intelligence Agency, is the author (under the pseudonym Edward Shirley) of ''Know Thine Enemy: A Spy's Journey into Revolutionary Iran.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Reuel Marc Gerecht, a former Middle East specialist in the Central Intelligence Agency, is the author (under the pseudonym Edward Shirley) of ''Know Thine Enemy: A Spy's Journey into Revolutionary Iran.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
