<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Safeco, Mariners' Offense Fizzles</title>
    <meta content="14SEAT$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/sports/14SEAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238694"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="2000 PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spousta, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E7DF103FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Safeco, Mariners' Offense Fizzles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM SPOUSTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Spousta, Tom</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, Oct. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses New York Yankees victory over Seattle Mariners in Game 3 of American League Championship Series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They collected enough hits to hold a garage sale, but the scoring funk continued for the Seattle Mariners tonight as fizzled rallies and the frustrated superstars Alex Rodriguez and Edgar Martinez highlighted an 8-2 loss to the Yankees.</p>
        <p>The Yankees took a 2-1 lead in the four-of-seven-game American League Championship Series, with Game 4 here on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They collected enough hits to hold a garage sale, but the scoring funk continued for the Seattle Mariners tonight as fizzled rallies and the frustrated superstars Alex Rodriguez and Edgar Martinez highlighted an 8-2 loss to the Yankees.</p>
        <p>The Yankees took a 2-1 lead in the four-of-seven-game American League Championship Series, with Game 4 here on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Heads bowed and bats broken, the Mariners were not sure why runs were so scarce and clutch hits so elusive. Despite 10 hits and several momentum swings in their favor, they managed only one run in the first inning and another in the fifth.</p>
        <p>''I don't know how it happens,'' Rodriguez said. He said the Yankee starter Andy Pettitte, ''pitched out of some jams and we just couldn't get the big hit.</p>
        <p>''The intensity has been there for the most part,'' Rodriguez added. ''We just haven't had the breaks. You have to take advantage of all your opportunities against Pettitte and those guys. They come few and far between. And when you don't, you're giving them a huge boost.''</p>
        <p>The Mariners got 10 hits, and Rodriguez and Martinez were each 2 for 4, but neither could spark an offense that has only 5 runs to show for 22 hits against the Yankees.</p>
        <p>''Every time we got something going, he made the pitches to get out of the inning,'' Martinez said. ''We thought we had him in the first couple innings, but he changed speeds very well after that.''</p>
        <p>Martinez added that the slump ''has put the pressure on our pitchers. We thought it would change today, but it didn't. . . . It's not over. This was a pivotal game, but we feel we can still win.''</p>
        <p>Seattle managed a run in the fifth inning on Rickey Henderson's double and Mike Cameron's single, but could not solve the Yankee relief pitchers, either.</p>
        <p>''There's no answer for it,'' Cameron said. ''No magic reason. It's simple. We just haven't gotten any big hits against any of their pitchers. We just have to stay aggressive, make some adjustments and turn this thing around.''</p>
        <p>The Mariners threatened in the eighth inning. Rodriguez reached on an infield hit and stole second base. But Martinez struck out for the second time, the pinch-hitter Stan Javier grounded out and John Olerud flied out to left field.</p>
        <p>Indeed, five of their first eight batters hit singles, but the awakening of the Mariners' offense was a mirage. They squandered nearly every scoring chance, especially early, when they stranded runners on first and second base in the first and second innings.</p>
        <p>Opportunities lost were never regained. In the third inning, the heart of the Mariners' order suffered an attack of sorts while trying to peck away at Pettitte. Rodriguez led off the inning and watched a curveball nick the plate for a called third strike. Martinez followed with a single to left for his second hit, but Pettitte's retaliation was swift. The Yankees' starter caught Martinez with his weight shifted toward second base and easily picked him off for the second out.</p>
        <p>Jay Buhner then struck out swinging to end the threat.</p>
        <p>The fourth inning again typified the Mariners' scoring problems. John Olerud led off with a single, but David Bell flew out to center field. Trailing by 3-1, Joe Oliver grounded into a double play.</p>
        <p>The Mariners' punchless offense dates to Game 3 of their A.L. division series sweep of the Chicago White Sox. Including that 2-1 victory, the Mariners have only 7 runs to show for 28 hits in 36 postseason innings.</p>
        <p>''We had our chances there in the first two innings,'' Mariners Manager Lou Piniella said. ''We had the right people up at the plate and just didn't get the hit. But I just have a feeling we're going to start hitting the ball pretty good in the series, I really do.''</p>
        <p>Martinez said about the slump: ''It has put the pressure on our pitchers. We thought it would change today, but it didn't.''</p>
        <p>Since moving to Safeco Field during last season, the Mariners have evolved into more of a finesse team, with the departure of Ken Griffey Jr. to Cincinnati completing the process. Gone are the double-digit scores of the Kingdome, replaced by Safeco Field and its retractable roof.</p>
        <p>After several years of batting .276 or better, the Mariners dropped to .269 the past two seasons. In their first full season at Safeco, they were the third-worst hitting team in the A.L., although they hit only five fewer home runs than 1999.</p>
        <p>2000 PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
