<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Toll Rises to 17 in Ship Blast, as U.S. Hunts Suspects</title>
    <meta content="14SHIP$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/14/world/14SHIP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE WARSHIP EXPLOSION: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cole (USS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yemen</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Aden (Yemen)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burns, John F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E5D6133FF937A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1824" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Toll Rises to 17 in Ship Blast, as U.S. Hunts Suspects</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burns, John F</byline>
      <dateline>ADEN, Yemen, Oct. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States Navy says 17 sailors were killed and 38 hurt in blast on destroyer Cole, Aden, Yemen; divers search harbor bed for bodies and clues to explosion's cause; witnesses say Cole was attacked by two men in small harbor boat that exploded as it drew alongside ship, in port to refuel; worldwide hunt begins to track down group responsible for attack, although US officials stop short of publicly using word terrorism; senior officials say US got unspecified warning last month of possible attack on warship; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seventeen sailors were killed in the blast on the destroyer Cole on Thursday, the United States Navy announced tonight, after divers spent the day searching the harbor bed for bodies and for clues to the explosion's cause.</p>
        <p>Thirty-eight sailors were wounded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seventeen sailors were killed in the blast on the destroyer Cole on Thursday, the United States Navy announced tonight, after divers spent the day searching the harbor bed for bodies and for clues to the explosion's cause.</p>
        <p>Thirty-eight sailors were wounded.</p>
        <p>The toll makes the attack the worst on the American armed forces since the bombing of an Air Force barracks in Saudi Arabia in 1996 that killed 19 people.</p>
        <p>Diving operations were suspended for the night, more than 32 hours after the blast, which blew a 40-by-40-foot hole in the Cole's port side, somewhat larger than first reported.</p>
        <p>Witnesses said the Cole, which is outfitted with guided missiles and advanced electronic equipment, was attacked by two men in a small harbor boat. It exploded as it drew alongside the American vessel, which had stopped at this port to refuel.</p>
        <p>While American energies in Aden focused on the recovery effort, a worldwide hunt began in earnest today to track down the group responsible for what had every appearance of a terrorist attack, though American officials stopped short of publicly using the word terrorism.</p>
        <p>There were reports that two Islamic groups had claimed responsibility, but these could not be verified, and American officials said their investigation had produced no firm leads so far.</p>
        <p>Two senior military officials said that the United States had received an unspecific warning of a possible attack on an American warship last month, but that it lacked detail and did not mention the country where the attack was expected.</p>
        <p>''It was a question of how directly you could tie it to a certain place,'' one official said. Since the warning, reported by an intelligence source in the Arab world, was not specific enough, ''it got put on the shelf.'' It was not clear that the warning could have stopped what some officials described today as a skillful suicide bombing.</p>
        <p>While the Cole's crew had extensive training in repelling an overt attack by a small boat and even had extra sailors on watch on Thursday, the attack had been so meticulously disguised and carried out that the officials said there was little the crew could have done to stop it.</p>
        <p>Immediate suspicion fell on Islamic radical groups that have used Yemen as a base for terrorist attacks in the past, but there was no concrete evidence to support this.</p>
        <p>Despite the reports that two Islamic groups claimed to have attacked the Cole, it was not ruled out that the claims might have been false, made by groups seeking publicity.</p>
        <p>In London, where he lives in self-exile, a Syrian-born Islamic radical, Sheik Omar Bakri, was reported as saying he had received a phone call from a group calling itself Muhammad's Army, which said it had attacked the Cole and the British Embassy in Sana, the Yemeni capital, 190 miles north of Aden. The group said it intended to take hostages and to continue bombing all American and British embassies, according to news reports</p>
        <p>Later in the day a previously unknown organization said in Beirut that it had carried out the attack.</p>
        <p>Terrorism experts mulled various theories today, among them the possibility that the ship was attacked in retaliation for events in the Gaza Strip and the West Bank. Two weeks of confrontations there between Israelis and Palestinians have produced a wave of anger across the Arab world directed at Israel, and to some extent at the United States.</p>
        <p>Experts also weighed other possibilities, including a group sympathetic to Iraq. The Cole had been scheduled to join an American flotilla enforcing trade sanctions on Iraq that were imposed after its invasion of Kuwait in 1990.</p>
        <p>Western terrorism specialists also said it was possible that the attack had nothing to do with the recent hostilities in the Middle East because it appeared to be an assault that would have required substantial time to plan.</p>
        <p>It was also not clear, these experts said, that any Islamic group in Yemen could have had sufficient notice of the arrival of the Cole, whose refueling stop here, the 13th made by an American Navy ship in the last two years, was not announced in advance.</p>
        <p>During the day, fears of a wider terror campaign were stirred when an explosive device believed to have been a bomb was thrown over the wall at the British Embassy in Sana. The device, which exploded shortly after dawn atop a diesel generator in the embassy courtyard, damaged the building, but caused no casualties.</p>
        <p>American efforts in Aden today concentrated on the search for the missing and on efforts at what a Navy spokesman described as ''stabilizing'' the crippled destroyer, which lay listing at its mooring point in a broad channel that leads into the inner harbor from the Gulf of Aden. Reporters were kept far away from the vessel, and were even prevented by American and Yemeni officials from photographing it. The huge hole on the vessel's port side was at first plainly visible, but later was covered by what appeared to be large white tarpaulins.</p>
        <p>But a Navy spokesman, Lt. Terrence Dudley, who flew in with scores of other Navy personnel from the Fifth Fleet's headquarters in the Persian Gulf state of Bahrain, said the recovery effort had succeeded to the point where there was no danger of the Cole's going to the bottom of Aden's deep harbor. ''The ship is not in any danger of sinking,'' he said, adding that Navy officials had been ''evacuating water'' from the engine room and other compartments at the water line, which he said had been ''extensively damaged'' by the blast.</p>
        <p>Fleet commanders overseeing the operation have decided for now not to try to move the Cole from its mooring point about a mile off the crowded harbor front.</p>
        <p>Viewed through binoculars, the ship appeared to be listing gently on its port side, and throughout the day teams of Navy men gathered aboard a smaller vessel with a flat platform that was moored beside the gaping hole. The platform appeared to be used for efforts to probe inside the damaged compartments, and possibly to lower divers onto the seabed.</p>
        <p>Apart from the dead and wounded, who accounted for more than a sixth of the 293-member crew, the rest of the ship's complement remained aboard, many of them forced to spend the night in sleeping bags under awnings stretched over the open decks.</p>
        <p>Details that Navy officials disclosed during the day suggested that the attackers might have come close to sinking the vessel, or at least of so damaging it that the toll could have been far higher.</p>
        <p>Lieutenant Dudley told reporters that the destroyer had sustained ''a lot of internal damage.'' There was extensive flooding of many lower compartments, as well as the engine room, and the flooding was complicating efforts to search for the missing and to look for clues in the attack.</p>
        <p>He said the tentative plan was to pump the water out of the damaged compartments, make some temporary repairs in Aden and then tow the Cole back to the United States for permanent repairs.</p>
        <p>He turned away questions about the identity of the attackers, saying it was an issue for the team of about 100 specialists from the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the Central Intelligence Agency and the Navy who began arriving here from Washington, Europe and the Persian Gulf late  Thursday.</p>
        <p>Among the F.B.I. agents were several from a squad that has focused exclusively on Osama Bin Laden, who has been charged in the attacks in 1998 on two American embassies in Africa that killed hundreds of people.</p>
        <p>An edge of impatience crept into Navy officers' remarks when they were asked about the assertions on Thursday by Yemen's president, Ali Abdullah Saleh, that the Cole explosion appeared to have been an accident on board the ship.</p>
        <p>It remained unclear whether Yemeni investigators, who appeared to be playing no direct part in the activities around the Cole today, would have any enthusiasm for investigating any terrorist aspects of the affair in the light of Mr. Saleh's insistence that the explosion was an accident.</p>
        <p>When the Yemeni assertions were put to Lieutenant Dudley, the Navy spokesman, he replied with apparent acerbity: ''We do know that a small boat approached our vessel, that there was a large explosion that was external to our vessel, and that it left our ship with fairly extensive damage of a kind that clearly was inflicted from outside. The evidence we have seen clearly shows that the explosion occurred outside our vessel.''</p>
        <p>Lieutenant Dudley, offering a more detailed account of the attack than the sketchy version relayed through the Pentagon on Thursday, said the Cole entered the Aden harbor and began to tie up to a mooring point near the fuel depot at 8:45 a.m. local time Thursday, which was 1:45 a.m. Eastern time.</p>
        <p>About 45 minutes later, the Cole was circled by several smaller boats, some of which were involved in the mooring and refueling operations and others which were dedicated to clearing garbage and other refuse from the Cole. Then another small boat approached from across the harbor, he said, and this approachwas immediately followed by the blast.</p>
        <p>The small boat in question appeared to be the motorized rubber dinghy described on Thursday by witnesses, including several Aden citizens, who said the two men aboard it were standing erect at the moment of the blast, as if in some kind of salute.</p>
        <p>Yemeni officials said today that as far as they knew, the operations around the Cole had produced no remains identifiable as those of the men on the dinghy.</p>
        <p>For Aden, the blast was a major setback, striking as it did at an operation, United States Navy refueling, that was agreed to in 1999 as a gesture of American confidence in President Saleh. The American hope was that the plan, in the face of widespread concerns about past terrorist activities in Yemen, would help Mr. Saleh in his effort to lead Yemen away from its reputation as an often violent, anti-Western, former Soviet satellite state, in favor of warm ties with the United States.</p>
        <p>THE WARSHIP EXPLOSION: THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
