<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Company Enrolling Poor in Health Care Plans Is Criticized</title>
    <meta content="30MAXI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Maximus Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipton, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5D81639F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Company Enrolling Poor in Health Care Plans Is Criticized</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maximus Inc comes under criticism for its work in telephoning Medicaid recipients to get them to enroll in health insurance plans; Virginia-based company has $24-million contract to help poor New York City residents select family doctors and one of 18 health insurance programs, rather than relying on emergency rooms for basic medical care; company and state officials defend record of getting voluntary enrollments; photo of office where enrollment brokers handle calls in 18 languages (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the 19th floor of an office tower just two doors down from the New York Stock Exchange, brokers at a sprawling telephone dispatch center field a steady stream of calls from jittery clients, handling the requests in 18 different languages.</p>
        <p>The conversations have nothing to do with the ups and downs of the financial market next door. Instead, staff members at this Broad Street dispatch center -- speaking in English, Spanish, Haitian Creole, Urdu, Russian and Chinese, among other tongues -- are at the forefront of a revolution under way in New York City that, at least in theory, is fundamentally changing the way health care is delivered to the poor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the 19th floor of an office tower just two doors down from the New York Stock Exchange, brokers at a sprawling telephone dispatch center field a steady stream of calls from jittery clients, handling the requests in 18 different languages.</p>
        <p>The conversations have nothing to do with the ups and downs of the financial market next door. Instead, staff members at this Broad Street dispatch center -- speaking in English, Spanish, Haitian Creole, Urdu, Russian and Chinese, among other tongues -- are at the forefront of a revolution under way in New York City that, at least in theory, is fundamentally changing the way health care is delivered to the poor.</p>
        <p>They are known as enrollment brokers, working under a $24 million state and city contract to help poor city residents, many of whom have long relied on emergency rooms for basic care, to sign up with their own family doctors. These brokers provide no direct medical care. Instead, by working on the phone, through mailings and at hundreds of community meetings a month, they answer questions and urge the poor to pick their doctors and one of 18 health insurance programs.</p>
        <p>But as the state contemplates a $40 million expansion and two-year extension of this enrollment effort, some state and local officials as well as advocates for the poor are questioning the results so far. Critics contend that some of the one million Medicaid recipients in New York City gradually being moved into health care plans have been misinformed about their choices, repeatedly sent enrollment forms in languages they do not understand and, in some cases, encountered mistakes that have forced delays in needed medical care.</p>
        <p>The contractor is Maximus Inc., the same McLean, Va., company that bid on the city's welfare-to-work contracts last year, only to have its $104 million in winning bids suspended after a State Supreme Court justice concluded this spring that the selection process was ''corrupted.'' The Giuliani administration is appealing the ruling, but the Manhattan district attorney and federal authorities are investigating the matter.</p>
        <p>The state comptroller, H. Carl McCall, has until today to decide whether to approve the contract extension, and he is expected to do so, his office indicated yesterday. But he plans to conduct a separate audit to monitor the program's progress.</p>
        <p>Demands placed on Maximus are only set to expand, as the city rolls out the mandatory enrollment effort to more neighborhoods and Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani intensifies his effort to sign up more uninsured city residents for health coverage. The state also wants Maximus to help enroll the poor in managed care plans in Nassau and Suffolk Counties.</p>
        <p>Maximus and the state health officials defended the company's record this week, noting that of the 79,326 Medicaid recipients enrolled through May in areas of New York City where managed care is now mandatory, 81 percent picked their plans voluntarily. That exceeds the contract guideline of 60 percent. A soon-to-be released study of programs in nine states by researchers at George Washington University found an average voluntary enrollment of 63 percent, although it was as high as 100 percent in Oregon and 90 percent in Connecticut. Under the rules, Medicaid recipients have 60 days to choose a health plan or else they will be assigned to one.</p>
        <p>Maximus officials acknowledged some start-up problems, but both they and the State Health Department said they were proud of the program now in place.</p>
        <p>''We are not in a process of total denial,'' said Daniel Walsky, deputy director of Maximus's Broad Street office. ''Any issue that comes up, whether we think it is supported or not, we will go back and train our staff.''</p>
        <p>Advocates for health care and the poor -- in groups like the Gay Men's Health Crisis and Children's Defense Fund -- are urging Mr. McCall to reject a request by the State Health Department for the two-year extension and expansion, and instead are urging the state to approve only a month-to-month renewal of the contract, until the concerns about Maximus's performance are addressed.</p>
        <p>''The state and city are paying good taxpayers' dollars for an effort that is falling far short and hurting the health care of low-income New Yorkers,'' said Susan M. Dooha, director of health policy at Gay Men's Health Crisis and co-chairwoman of the New York City Task Force on Medicaid Managed Care.</p>
        <p>In theory, the switch to managed care is supposed to benefit everyone involved. Nationally, nearly 54 percent of Medicaid recipients were in managed care programs by the latest count in 1998, up from 10 percent in 1991. The goal is to improve care, because once a family has a regular doctor, they are more likely to get regular checkups, perhaps avoiding serious ailments. It can also save money, by reducing emergency room use and repetitive tests that result when a patient sees a new doctor each time.</p>
        <p>But the transition, in New York and other states, has not always gone smoothly. So far, mandatory enrollment is occurring only on Staten Island, in Lower Manhattan and in southwest Brooklyn, although it is set to reach more neighborhoods soon. Complications have been outlined in a series of complaints filed with the federal government by the Legal Aid Society.</p>
        <p>Among those noted in the complaints was a 63-year-old Russian-speaking man with diabetes and other medical complications who was repeatedly sent information in English, which he could not understand, had his medical insurance briefly canceled and then was automatically assigned to a doctor's office where no one spoke Russian. When he became ill recently, he had to pay for a doctor with his own money, and then had to wait several weeks before he could get an emergency test the doctor had recommended, the complaint says, collectively blaming Maximus, the state and the city.</p>
        <p>In a second case, a 62-year-old Spanish-speaking woman with degenerative joint disease had to delay surgery after complications that resulted from her not being able to read forms Maximus had sent her in English, even though she had requested them in Spanish, the complaint says. Officials from Maximus and the state said they were looking into these allegations.</p>
        <p>An investigation released earlier this year by Mark Green, the New York City public advocate, found similar problems. The Broad Street telephone center, where Maximus operates what it calls the Medicaid Choice Hotline, frequently gave out incorrect or misleading answers, says Mr. Green's report, released in February. Staff members leading some of the approximately 450 neighborhood presentations about the options available sometimes showed up late or not at all, the report says.</p>
        <p>Mr. Green also said that the state database of doctors who participate in the Medicaid managed care program was ''grossly inaccurate,'' complicating the selection process.</p>
        <p>The city Human Resources Administration has also been criticized, for denying hundreds of requests made by Medicaid clients to drop out of the program. People with AIDS or  serious mental illness, or those needing doctors who speak their language are allowed to receive waivers. But, for example, the Legal Aid complaint notes that of the 242 people requesting language-based exemptions, only one was granted, for a young girl who is both deaf and Russian speaking.</p>
        <p>''I was very scared,'' said a 61-year-old Russian-speaking woman from Brooklyn, explaining through a translator about the confrontations she said she had with Maximus operators as she tried to apply for a waiver, based on a mental illness, physical disability and a language barrier. The state overruled the city and granted her waiver. ''I was very upset and I felt like my face was burning up with embarrassment,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Tom McGraw, the project manager of Maximus's Broad Street office, said staff training had been intensified, and he disputed suggestions that the call center operators were at times rude or incorrect. But the company has also dropped 4 of the approximately 50 community groups it used for educational sessions, acknowledging some problems. And it has increased advertising for these sessions, with multilingual signs in churches, check-cashing stores, barbershops and other places, Mr. McGraw said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
