<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>True Love and a Crisis at Christmas (When Else)?</title>
    <meta content="30ZONE0AD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rattlestick Theater</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Buddy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Crumple Zone, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E0D61F30F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1059" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>True Love and a Crisis at Christmas (When Else)?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Weber reviews play The Crumple Zone by Buddy Thomas, at Rattlestick Theater; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''The Crumple Zone,'' a new play by Buddy Thomas at the Rattlestick Theater in Greenwich Village, has a lot going for it. It has a nicely structured plot about a gay household with a love triangle coming to a crisis at Christmastime; sequences of physical comedy directed by Jason Moore to be antic without being overblown into slapstick; and an effective set by Dawn Robyn Petrlik that evokes a pleasantly chintzy holiday atmosphere in a two-bedroom rental apartment on Staten Island.</p>
        <p>Most of all, it has a bristling, funny performance by Mario Cantone, who plays the squeaky wheel, a clamorously lonely man on the outside of the triangle looking in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''The Crumple Zone,'' a new play by Buddy Thomas at the Rattlestick Theater in Greenwich Village, has a lot going for it. It has a nicely structured plot about a gay household with a love triangle coming to a crisis at Christmastime; sequences of physical comedy directed by Jason Moore to be antic without being overblown into slapstick; and an effective set by Dawn Robyn Petrlik that evokes a pleasantly chintzy holiday atmosphere in a two-bedroom rental apartment on Staten Island.</p>
        <p>Most of all, it has a bristling, funny performance by Mario Cantone, who plays the squeaky wheel, a clamorously lonely man on the outside of the triangle looking in.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cantone has ample stage credits (he replaced Nathan Lane in ''Love! Valour! Compassion!'' on Broadway) but is probably best known for his high-pitched stand-up comedy work, and he knows how to take over a room. In this case the room is a tiny apartment, but he works it like a diva. He is the kind of actor who seems most in control when he's in a tizzy, and he has a voice that easily and naturally runs up to shrill and a jittery pestiness that calls for throttling. Indeed, at one point in the play, he is the recipient of a realistic punch in the nose.</p>
        <p>But this is not a shrill performance. Even in high dudgeon there's no tension in Mr. Cantone's face or his body language, no sense of method acting when he's working up to a fever pitch, just the wicked glee of a man who loves to seize the spotlight. The magnitude of his neurotic charisma in such a small space gives his character, Terry, an out-of-work actor (which gives license to his home theatrics), the hilariously keening pathos that makes the play work.</p>
        <p>Terry is in love with Buck (Gerald Downey), a good-looking though rather bland fellow who works at the Staten Island Mall, but Buck, alas, is carrying on an impassioned affair with Terry's roommate, Alex (Joshua Biton). At the start of the second act, when Terry serenades Buck by lip-synching a recording of ''Nevertheless (I'm in Love With You)'' by  Debbie Shapiro-Gravitte, climbing over the furniture and appropriating the Christmas-tree tinsel in place of a feather boa, the hopelessness of the gesture is wrenching, but Mr. Cantone makes Terry so comfortably self-revelatory that his rendition of the song is side-splitting.</p>
        <p>Buck's affair with Alex, being conducted mostly in the apartment right under Terry's nose, is only one of the things driving him nuts. Another is that with Buck, Alex is cheating on his long-term boyfriend, Matt (Paul Pecorino), who has been on tour with a shlocky musical. Terry, a bit of a conventional moralist, finds the infidelity offensive.</p>
        <p>Most of this is revealed in the opening scene -- it takes a while to get the names and the characters matched up -- in which Terry and Buck are waiting for Alex to return from his temporary job as a Santa Claus at the mall as Matt is leaving long, anguished love messages on the answering machine. By the end of the first act, Terry, in desperation, has picked up Roger (Steve Mateo) on the Staten Island ferry. Roger's main attraction is a sculptured torso, but he couldn't provide Terry with a more inappropriate liaison. The lunacy that erupts as the lights go down -- and as, of course, Matt pops in the door for a surprise Christmas visit -- is beautifully staged. The physical jokes are precisely timed, and as chaotic as the scene is, the play is never allowed to devolve into a cartoon.</p>
        <p>In its close quarters and its dialogue that frequently relies on repartee, ''The Crumple Zone'' is the kind of domestic comedy that might have been written by Neil Simon if Mr. Simon were gay and 40 years younger. As Mr. Simon's plays often do, it presents, with affection, the conflicts of close-knit people, people who essentially love one another, as they come to cross purposes. And the playwright, Mr. Thomas, has provided some good gags (the best involves the delivery of several flower arrangements) and has set the scene and situation with a sure hand. The apartment here works well as the crucible for his simmering plot.</p>
        <p>What the play lacks is a sharpness of language. The jokes don't often enough land squarely, especially in the second act, in which the characters have a lot of confession and anguish to get off their chests, and the talk of love and heartbreak is rather familiar. As a result the characters, aside from Terry, have an interchangeable quality; they're distinguished by their plot points rather than their personalities.</p>
        <p>This is all a burden for the younger actors here. Mr. Cantone gets most of the best lines, but even so, the  other cast members have a hard time sustaining the energy he provides, and none have found the idiosyncrasies that would make their characters distinct. The most evident example is Alex's long monologue in the opening act, when he arrives home from the mall with a story about how a bunch of brats and  their angry mothers have cost him his job as Santa Claus.</p>
        <p>It's written as a set piece, and it's an opportunity for the character to rise, but the story itself is not funny enough or awful enough to be the pivotal moment the play wants it to be. Mr. Biton, making his Off Broadway debut, doesn't yet have the chops to make it so; you can see him cranking up the machinery. This is an unfair comparison, perhaps, but where Mr. Biton grows agitated as his character does, Mr. Cantone grows more at ease. It's a valuable acting lesson.</p>
        <p>THE CRUMPLE ZONE</p>
        <p>By Buddy Thomas; directed by Jason Moore; sets by Dawn Robyn Petrlik; costumes by David Mills; sound by Laura Grace Brown; lighting by Ed McCarthy; choreography by Peter Kapetan; fight consultant, B. H. Barry; production stage manager, Gail Eve Malatesta; assistant stage manager, Michael Biondi; technical director, Jeff Duer. Presented by Marcus Kettles Productions. At the Rattlestick Theater, 224 Waverly Place, Greenwich Village.</p>
        <p>WITH: Mario Cantone (Terry), Joshua Biton (Alex), Steve Mateo (Roger), Gerald Downey (Buck) and Paul Pecorino (Matt).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
