<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israeli Armorer in a Global Arena; Aircraft Maker Runs Afoul of U.S. With China Radar Contract</title>
    <meta content="Y30PLA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211392"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Sales Abroad</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radar</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Defense Contracts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Taiwan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Israel Aircraft Industries</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Orme, William A Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Keret, Moshe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Sales Abroad</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Defense Contracts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E1DA1639F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2274" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israeli Armorer in a Global Arena; Aircraft Maker Runs Afoul of U.S. With China Radar Contract</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM A. ORME Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Orme, William A Jr</byline>
      <dateline>LOD, Israel, June 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israel Aircraft Industries is encountering US opposition to sale of Phalcon early-warning radar system that will be used on Chinese planes; Pres Clinton reiterates concern that China could use radar system against American forces in Taiwan; House Appropriations Committee this week called on Israel to terminate deal, with many members pledging to cut Israel's aid if it does not; dispute to foreign policy analysts is illustration of how Israeli-American strategic ties are still often frayed by miscommunication and mistrust on both sides--as well as by rare but deep divergences in each country's conception of its national interest; China contract has opened first significant rift between Clinton administration and government of Prime Miun Ehud Barak; Israel Aircraft Industries' president Moshe Keret says conflict is also potential business catastrophe, one that he thinks directly threatens his company's prospects for survival in increasingly competitive and consolidated arms industry; company is centerpiece of domestic arms and aeronautics industry that Israel considers key to its defense; graph; chart; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Behind a tarpaulin-covered fence at the far edge of the Israel Aircraft Industries complex at Ben-Gurion International Airport here sits a refurbished Russian transport, its saucer-like radar pod temporarily removed for fine-tuning.</p>
        <p>Within weeks, company officials say, the pod will be back, the radar switched on, and the distinctive droop-winged jet ready for its final test flights. The plane, a transformed Ilyushin-76, will be able to monitor air and telecommunications traffic more than 200 miles away -- the specifications ordered by the plane's owner, the People's Republic of China.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Behind a tarpaulin-covered fence at the far edge of the Israel Aircraft Industries complex at Ben-Gurion International Airport here sits a refurbished Russian transport, its saucer-like radar pod temporarily removed for fine-tuning.</p>
        <p>Within weeks, company officials say, the pod will be back, the radar switched on, and the distinctive droop-winged jet ready for its final test flights. The plane, a transformed Ilyushin-76, will be able to monitor air and telecommunications traffic more than 200 miles away -- the specifications ordered by the plane's owner, the People's Republic of China.</p>
        <p>For Israel Aircraft Industries' president, Moshe Keret, who over the last 15 years has built a virtually bankrupt military contractor into Israel's biggest exporter, the sale was to have been one of his greatest achievements. The Phalcon early-warning radar system installed on the Chinese plane showcased all the strengths of I.A.I. -- as the state-owned company is known -- its technological prowess and its success in developing new markets abroad to help pay for Israel's weapons.</p>
        <p>But if the Pentagon has its way, and the betting here is that it will, the converted Ilyushin will never reach China, which long ago gave Israel Aircraft the down payment on the $250 million spy plane.</p>
        <p>Today, President Clinton reiterated Washington's concern that China could use the radar system against American forces in the Taiwan Strait. Earlier in the week, the House Appropriations Committee called on Israel to terminate the deal, with many members pledging to cut Israel's aid if it does not.</p>
        <p>''We signed a contract,'' a top official of Israel Aircraft said. ''We have their money. Now we say, 'No, sorry?' ''</p>
        <p>To foreign policy analysts, the Phalcon dispute is an illustration of how Israeli-American strategic ties are still often frayed by miscommunication and mistrust on both sides -- as well as by rare but deep divergences in each country's conception of its national interest. The China contract has opened the first significant rift between the Clinton administration and the government of Prime Minister Ehud Barak, just as both governments are trying to persuade the Palestinians to join them in Washington for a conclusive round of peace talks.</p>
        <p>But to Mr. Keret, 65, who has worked at Israel Aircraft his entire adult life, the conflict is also a potential business catastrophe, one that he thinks directly threatens his company's prospects for survival in an increasingly competitive and consolidated global arms industry.</p>
        <p>A threat to Israel Aircraft's future is seen by many Israeli leaders as a threat to the nation, both militarily and economically. The company, founded in 1953, is the centerpiece of a domestic arms and aeronautics industry that Israel considers the key to its defense.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to talk about the Phalcon per se,'' Mr. Keret, who has been asked by the government not to comment on the deal, said at I.A.I. headquarters here. ''But what is the environment in which we are operating? It is very competitive. Although we are a state-owned company, we get no subsidy, and no favoritism from the defense ministry.''</p>
        <p>Compared with Boeing and other behemoths of the global defense trade, Israel Aircraft is no giant: its $1 billion in foreign military sales puts it about 30th among major arms sellers abroad, according to independent assessments. Overall sales reached $2 billion last year, two-thirds from military contracts and the rest from commercial aircraft production and maintenance.</p>
        <p>But it is difficult to overstate the company's importance to Israel. With 14,000 skilled workers, Israel Aircraft is by far the country's biggest industrial employer, comparable in American terms to General Motors and General Electric combined. A further 15,000 Israeli jobs are indirectly dependent on the company. And its $1.6 billion in military and commercial sales abroad make it the biggest exporter.</p>
        <p>''If there is a disaster in I.A.I. for one reason or another,'' Mr. Keret said, ''its effects would be felt throughout the country.''</p>
        <p>A certain disaster for the company would be any significant erosion of American aid. I.A.I. has been the biggest beneficiary of American rules permitting a quarter of military assistance to be spent in Israel -- for purchases of arms produced in this country. Yet Moshe Arens, a three-time former defense minister, whose views are widely shared here, said this week that $2 billion in annual military aid is ''not sufficient to make us start accepting U.S. control over defense industry exports.''</p>
        <p>American officials seem mystified that Israel would jeopardize its critical international alliance by pursuing what appears to be a marginal weapons deal. Last fall, as the China controversy broke into the open, the same Israeli officials who were defending the Phalcon sale were presenting Washington with a $17 billion wish list of arms they said the country needed to compensate for the expected turnover of the Golan Heights to Syria. Now the Israelis are discussing a similar military aid package to safeguard a peace pact with the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>''I have tried to explain to Israelis that Americans cannot understand why Israel was refusing to give up $250 million when it was asking the United States for $17 billion,'' said David Makovsky, who has been an Israeli analyst at the Washington Institute for Near East Policy.</p>
        <p>But far more than $250 million is at stake, leaders of this country say. ''We'll do our utmost to act sensitively and to be attentive to U.S. interests,'' Mr. Barak, who appoints Israel Aircraft's board, said. ''At the same time, there's a contract with China, signed during the incumbency of the previous government. The state doesn't call off contracts to which it is a signatory just like that.''</p>
        <p>Even seen narrowly, the contract with China is potentially a $2 billion deal, huge by Israel Aircraft standards. Under terms negotiated three years ago, Beijing has options to buy seven more Phalcon-equipped Ilyushins. Fulfilling such a contract would catapult the company into an elite fraternity of major contractors in bidding for such systems -- and it would subsidize further technological advances at home. Though Israel Aircraft lost to Boeing in a recent bid to supply early-warning planes to Australia, it is competing for a $2 billion contract in Turkey.</p>
        <p>Worse, executives say, the cancellation of the contract would be a signal to potential customers that no deal with Israel Aircraft is final, as the United States could effectively veto a promised delivery.</p>
        <p>''Better to buy from the Europeans,'' a gloomy executive said. Or perhaps from the Russians, who supplied destroyers, cruise missiles and other heavy weaponry to the Chinese over the last decade with few protests from Washington.</p>
        <p>Or, as others here cynically suggest, from the Americans themselves. Israelis point to the continuing export of advanced military technology to China by the United States in the last decade: since the ban by Congress in 1989 on military sales to Beijing, after the crackdown on pro-democracy protests in Tiananmen Square, the White House has issued waivers for some $300 million in exports of satellite and encryption equipment to the country.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the United States did not renege on its own deals, Israelis note, fulfilling $36 million in orders placed by China before the ban, including anti-artillery radar systems.</p>
        <p>In an editorial last week, the newspaper Maariv decried what it called ''Washington's attempts to torpedo the deal and sabotage Israel's defense exports, perhaps out of the desire to protect the interests of giant U.S. corporations.''</p>
        <p>Yet Maariv, like other leading media voices here, concluded that Israel would have little choice but to renege on the contract. Until the dispute is resolved, another daily, Haaretz, said, ''The Phalcon will continue to be a sword of Damocles hanging over Israel's head.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Keret seems surprised by the furor in Washington over the Phalcon deal. Until newspapers here published photos of the plane late last year, setting off the American outcry, company executives say they considered the contract old news.</p>
        <p>When the company bid for the contract in 1996, Israel officially notified the United States that the Phalcon system did not incorporate protected American technology, a contention the Pentagon has never challenged. Though Washington officials say they objected to the sale on strategic and human rights grounds, there were no public complaints.</p>
        <p>The deal, calling for delivery beginning in 2000, was concluded in highly publicized trips to Moscow and Beijing by Benjamin Netanyahu, then the prime minister, and Yitzhak Mordechai, the defense minister. In April 1998, the Phalcon sale was reported to Congress in a General Accounting Office review of recent Chinese arms purchases.</p>
        <p>Again, there were no public American protests, though officials did say they tried to dissuade Israel from signing.</p>
        <p>''As the deal went forward, they weren't hearing us anymore,'' a senior State Department official said.</p>
        <p>Though American companies were prohibited from selling radar planes to China after the events there in June 1989, Israel Aircraft considered this a commercial opportunity. In the first foreign sale of its airborne radar, it sent a Phalcon-equipped Boeing 767 to Chile, which was then prohibited by Congressional strictures from buying Boeing Awacs surveillance planes. Washington raised no objections, Mr. Keret said.</p>
        <p>From Central America in the 1980's to Turkey in the 1990's, the company provided other military equipment to countries where United States exports were constrained by human rights considerations.</p>
        <p>And in China, Israel Aircraft was hardly alone. Competitors in Italy and Britain were offering advanced airborne radar systems to Beijing.</p>
        <p>But the United States has since become more worried by Beijing's conflict with Taiwan, and officials are telling the Israeli contractor that no company so dependent on American trade and aid can consider itself geopolitically autonomous.</p>
        <p>By design, Mr. Keret has made Israel Aircraft increasingly reliant on the United States as a market,  supplier and business partner, creating joint ventures with all the major aerospace companies. And through its own American subsidiaries -- including its Galaxy corporate jet business, based in Fort Worth -- the company says it spends about $400 million yearly in the United States.</p>
        <p>With such partners, the company specializes in upgrading American aircraft for foreign air forces -- and even for the United States Air Force, which recently awarded Israel Aircraft and Boeing a $400 million contract to revamp 450 of its T-38 Talon trainers. The small unmanned planes, an I.A.I. specialty, proved a crucial reconnaissance weapon for the United States Army in Kosovo, prompting other NATO orders.</p>
        <p>In its most ambitious American joint venture, Israel Aircraft is the principal contractor on the Arrow, a $2 billion antiballistic-missile system deployed here this year.</p>
        <p>American support has been critical to the company's turnaround. After weathering a worldwide plunge in military sales in the mid-1990's, it has stayed in the black for 14 consecutive quarters. Net profit last year rose to $70 million.</p>
        <p>But just as Boeing and Lockheed Martin heed the Pentagon before pursuing foreign arms deals, so now must Israel Aircraft, many officials of this country reluctantly conclude.</p>
        <p>The last time Israel Aircraft tried to buck the Pentagon and its military contractors, Mr. Keret painfully recalls, it almost destroyed the company. The project was his baby: I.A.I.'s own jet fighter, the Lavi, envisioned as a successor -- and competitor -- to the Air Force's F-16. The increasingly expensive project was canceled under pressure from Washington in 1987, just a year after the Lavi's maiden flight. The move wiped out 5,000 jobs and nearly propelled Israel Aircraft into receivership.</p>
        <p>Mr. Keret is credited with rescuing the company from the Lavi debacle. The radar and navigation and missile-guidance systems developed for the Lavi were refined into independent products, many of them now installed on I.A.I.-refurbished F-16's.</p>
        <p>But as he sits in his corporate offices here, which are still decorated with models and photographs of the extinct Israeli fighter, Mr. Keret says he regrets the loss of corporate and national independence that the Lavi symbolized. ''It was a good plane,'' he said. ''I'm sure we could have sold a lot of them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
