<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lawmakers Pass $21.5 Billion Budget; Action Delayed on Road and School Plans</title>
    <meta content="30JERS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christine Todd (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E3DE1739F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1474" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lawmakers Pass $21.5 Billion Budget; Action Delayed on Road and School Plans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, June 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Legislature approves $21.5-billion budget, takes action on dozens of other bills, but fails to enact key capital spending programs for roads and schools; budget increases spending almost ten percent, reflecting steadily rising income tax receipts; Gov Christine Whitman says she will use line-item veto to cut at least $25 million, so that surplus is at least $850 million; budget highlights; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a daylong burst of lawmaking before its summer recess, the New Jersey Legislature easily approved a $21.5 billion budget today and took action on dozens of lesser bills.</p>
        <p>The Legislature failed, however, to enact the two capital spending programs that have dominated its agenda for months: $12 billion to build new schools and $3.75 billion to rebuild roads and bridges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a daylong burst of lawmaking before its summer recess, the New Jersey Legislature easily approved a $21.5 billion budget today and took action on dozens of lesser bills.</p>
        <p>The Legislature failed, however, to enact the two capital spending programs that have dominated its agenda for months: $12 billion to build new schools and $3.75 billion to rebuild roads and bridges.</p>
        <p>With a new fiscal year beginning on Saturday, both houses overwhelmingly passed a boom-time budget that calls for spending increases of nearly 10 percent, far outstripping the rate of inflation but reflecting steadily rising income tax receipts.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Gov. Christine Todd Whitman said the governor would use her line-item veto to cut at least $25 million from the budget on Friday to ensure that it contains a surplus of no less than $850 million, another record.</p>
        <p>But Assembly leaders balked at both the school construction bill and the refinancing of the Transportation Trust Fund.</p>
        <p>The school construction effort, which would be the most ambitious in the nation, appeared close to passage before today, after months of arduous negotiations between Governor Whitman and the leaders of both houses, all three of whom are Republicans.</p>
        <p>In broad strokes, it calls for $8.6 billion in state spending for school projects. This includes $6 billion for needy districts, mainly in cities, to comply with a 1998 court order; the rest is for mainly suburban districts, on a sliding scale according to their wealth. Another $3.4 billion would be raised through local taxes. Interest payments over time could actually bring the total cost to $15 billion.</p>
        <p>The outline of a deal was, in fact, disclosed today, when the Senate passed an Assembly bill, prompting Governor Whitman to issue a ''conditional veto,'' detailing more than a dozen changes she would require before signing it.</p>
        <p>For example, she raised the cost allowance for school projects to $138 per square foot, but insisted that professional fees and site acquisition costs be included in that figure, contrary to the Assembly's wishes. The governor also put the New Jersey Economic Development Authority in charge of the entire construction effort, rather than leaving the financing of projects in the hands of the state's Educational Facilities Authority, as some senators had wished.</p>
        <p>In addition, Governor Whitman rejected an Assembly-created provision that would have given lawmakers a veto over projects entirely paid for by the state.</p>
        <p>Senators unanimously agreed to the governor's changes today. But the Assembly speaker, Jack Collins,  postponed a vote until a special session on July 13, saying that members needed more than just a few hours to digest the governor's changes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Collins said he expected that the Assembly eventually would approve the governor's changes, although he suggested that Republicans who had supported earlier versions might now defect. Some, including Leonard Lance, the chairman of the Assembly Budget Committee, have argued that the state Constitution requires that such an expensive bond issue be put before the voters for approval.</p>
        <p>Today's session, the last before lawmakers recessed for the summer, was only the latest in a series of deadlines for an agreement on school construction that have passed without a deal. But Mr. Collins, who is likely to be a candidate in next year's governor's race, refused to call the latest delay a delay. He alluded to the more than $120 million included in the new budget for preliminary work on school projects and said that in any case, legislators would have been criticized if they rushed into a ''$15 billion project,'' as he repeatedly and loudly referred to it.</p>
        <p>''This will be the biggest building project in the history of the state,'' Mr. Collins said. ''Thinking people want to make sure we do it right.''</p>
        <p>Assembly leaders used a similar rationale in postponing final passage of the refinancing of the Transportation Trust Fund, which pays for the construction of roads and bridges.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers in both houses had agreed on a compromise plan to replenish the fund with $3.75 billion in receipts from the 11.5-cent-a-gallon gas tax over the next four years, while capping the amount of debt that can be raised for transportation projects at $650 million a year.</p>
        <p>When the governor conditionally vetoed the bill late today -- lifting a cap that lawmakers had imposed on the amount of money that could be used for salaries and overhead instead of actual construction expenses -- the Senate agreed to her changes but Assembly leaders in both parties refused to comply, deferring a vote to July 13.</p>
        <p>The minority leader, Joseph Doria, said that he objected to the changes, saying capital dollars should not be wasted on the salaries of ''bureaucrats,'' but added that he and other Assembly members felt sandbagged by the governor and the Senate. ''We thought that this was a bipartisan, bicameral bill,'' he said. ''Nobody spoke to me about this conditional veto.''</p>
        <p>The $21.5 billion state budget, meanwhile, sailed through both houses, although some lawmakers raised concerns about the size of the spending increase. In the Senate, the vote was 38 to 1, with Senator John A. Lynch, a Democrat from Middlesex County, casting the lone no vote.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lynch, who has frequently attacked the state's rising debt burden under Governor Whitman, said the budget lacked a plan for paying off that debt, as well as an effective redevelopment plan for Newark and other urban centers. ''It's great to throw money around when there's plenty of it, but I think the theme of this budget cycle is one of missed opportunities,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Senate also gave final approval to the governor's proposal for an earned income tax credit, which is modeled after a federal tax credit. The program, which would cost $48 million, would provide checks of up to $400 to about 280,000 lower-income working families, many of which earn too little to pay any taxes now.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
