<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Selling Clothes by Upstaging Them</title>
    <meta content="30BOXE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PHOTOGRAPHY REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harper's Bazaar (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fashion Institute of Technology</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dahl-Wolfe, Louise (d1989)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bacall, Lauren</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boxer, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Fashion Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D61F30F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1164" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Selling Clothes by Upstaging Them</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH BOXER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Boxer, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sarah Boxer reviews Louise Dahl-Wolfe's fashion photographs for Harper's Bazaar, exhibited at FIT museum and at Staley-Wise gallery; photo of Lauren Bacall on 1943 cover photo M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is hard to think of a single article of clothing photographed by Louise Dahl-Wolfe that is half as memorable as the outfits she made with her camera: the shadow worn like a swimsuit by a naked sunbather in ''Dappled Nude'' and the bubbles and water worn by a nude diver in ''Nude in Pool.'' The best fashions, Dahl-Wolfe seems to say, are shadows and bubbles.</p>
        <p>You might think fashion designers would have bristled at the visual upstagings that Dahl-Wolfe dished out for two decades. They didn't. Dahl-Wolfe, who died in 1989 at 94, was the queen photographer of Harper's Bazaar under the editor Carmel Snow, the art director Alexey Brodovitch and the fashion editor Diana Vreeland, from 1936 until 1958. Trained as a painter in San Francisco, Dahl-Wolfe brought American fashion into the great and colorful outdoors. She is credited with creating the look for the independent American woman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is hard to think of a single article of clothing photographed by Louise Dahl-Wolfe that is half as memorable as the outfits she made with her camera: the shadow worn like a swimsuit by a naked sunbather in ''Dappled Nude'' and the bubbles and water worn by a nude diver in ''Nude in Pool.'' The best fashions, Dahl-Wolfe seems to say, are shadows and bubbles.</p>
        <p>You might think fashion designers would have bristled at the visual upstagings that Dahl-Wolfe dished out for two decades. They didn't. Dahl-Wolfe, who died in 1989 at 94, was the queen photographer of Harper's Bazaar under the editor Carmel Snow, the art director Alexey Brodovitch and the fashion editor Diana Vreeland, from 1936 until 1958. Trained as a painter in San Francisco, Dahl-Wolfe brought American fashion into the great and colorful outdoors. She is credited with creating the look for the independent American woman.</p>
        <p>But a curious thing happens when you look at the two exhibitions ''Louise Dahl-Wolfe: The American Image,'' a retrospective at the Museum at the Fashion Institute of Technology in Chelsea, which includes 43 black-and-white fashion photographs and portraits, 100 color tear sheets from Harper's Bazaar and some scrapbooks, and ''Louise Dahl-Wolfe: Another Look,'' 33 black-and-white prints at the Staley-Wise gallery in SoHo. (Although Dahl-Wolfe was a great colorist, the tear sheets are shown instead of the original color prints because the film she used was unstable and has faded.)</p>
        <p>It is hard to focus on the clothes. You notice the architecture, the furniture, the patterns on the floors and walls, the shapes made by the models' limbs long before you see the fashions. As Etheleen Staley said in a short movie about Dahl-Wolfe that runs continually at the Fashion Institute exhibition, her nudes always look clothed and her clothed women always look a little nude. You notice their anatomies. It is the clothes that recede.</p>
        <p>Take a simple example, the black-and-white photograph ''Twins at the Beach'' (1955), a paean to synchronized sunbathing. Two women laze on a white wooden beach bench with their eyes shut. Their heads, fitted with identical white swimming caps, incline toward each other, and their elbows stick up behind their heads. One woman's palms are showing, the other's fingers are bent to show her dark fingernail polish. The setting is memorable, too. The shoreline, splitting the dark foamy sea from the white sand, almost seems like a horizon line, splitting dark sky from white earth. The scene is so absorbing that the black bathing suits, one ruffly, the other plain, are lost in the shuffle.</p>
        <p>The same is true of Miggie Minnegerode modeling a bathing suit by Mabs in 1939. In the middle of the night, in the middle of a shallow pool,  is a sculpture of Venus, slightly out of focus and obscured by shadow. Her competition has just arrived on deck. In clear focus and in light (provided by an unseen car's headlamps) is a live Venus. She has the same hair bun and roughly the same pose, but her reproachful expression suggests that she might devour the Venus in the pool. Oh, yes, and she is wearing a swimsuit that is glistening but utterly forgettable.</p>
        <p>Why didn't fashion designers mind? Maybe because Dahl-Wolfe's sleight of hand, and her slight of fashion, generated just what they wanted: a crucial transfer of envy. In these photographs, you can envy the models' bodies and their surroundings. But the only things you can actually buy are the clothes. Envy is thus transferred onto the saleable item. This is the stuff that ads are made on.</p>
        <p>The March 1943 cover of Harper's Bazaar shows how feelings about one thing can bleed into another. The photograph shows Lauren Bacall standing in front of an American Red Cross door. (By the way, Ms. Bacall owes her career to some photographs by Dahl-Wolfe that were sent to Hollywood.) She has red lipstick and a red bag that match the red cross, a tight-fitting white cap, a smoky look and a scary black coat, with a bat collar. Despite the vamp outfit, Ms. Bacall appears benign, even a healing presence. Where did this feeling come from? Behind the frosted glass door is the blurry figure of a nurse whose head is crossed out by the red cross painted on the door. Her kindness has been transferred to Ms. Bacall.</p>
        <p>Enviability is an even more mobile quantity. And Dahl-Wolfe was a master of the transfer of envy, particularly when she photographed her subjects outdoors. Her best portraits were shot outdoors, and her best fashion shots feature women in wide-open spaces wearing very few saleable clothes. The less clothing Dahl-Wolfe had to work with, the better she was.</p>
        <p>She was not the first (and certainly not the last) to think of selling clothes by selling a setting. The photographer George Hoyningen-Huene may have started the game in the 1930 Vogue photograph ''Swimwear by Izod,'' which depicts two swimmers out on a diving platform. But Dahl-Wolfe refined it.</p>
        <p>Out of her photographs emerges a curious inverse law. The less clothing there is to sell, the more acreage is required to sell it. To sell a swimsuit you need an ocean or an estate or a sand dune. To sell casual clothes you might need a county fair or a table in a resort. But to sell couture, a drawing room or even a hole in the wall will do.</p>
        <p>Take Bijou Barrington modeling an ordinary halter top and skirt. She stands outdoors. Indeed, she appears to be holding up part of Taliesen West, Frank Lloyd Wright's compound in Phoenix. The model's outfit is entirely forgettable. But who cares? She seems to own the place.</p>
        <p>To sell a suit, less real estate is required. Take the photograph of Betty Threat modeling a gray Hattie Carnegie suit with a floating collar. She seems to have climbed through a hole in the wall and is ready to pass through another, as if she were some kind of Alice in Wonderland.</p>
        <p>What happens with a Dior gown of gray net, embroidered with jeweled scales and topped with a brown velvet ribbon around the bosom? In a photograph called ''Plan de Paris,'' which ran in Harper's Bazaar in 1951, Mary Jane Russell models the gown standing like a conquerer in front of a giant map of Paris. The question the photograph raises is, which is mightier -- the gown or the town? At first the town seems dominant. But the model in the gown, whose hand spans the Seine, ultimately conquers.</p>
        <p>PHOTOGRAPHY REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
