<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES: FOR CHILDREN</title>
    <meta content="30KIDS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D61F30F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES: FOR CHILDREN</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the Fourth</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK CONSERVANCY. Independence Day Weekend workshops, tomorrow from 1 to 2:30 p.m.: at the Henry Luce Nature Observatory at Belvedere Castle, midpark at 79th Street. Flag making and a historical overview of the Stars and Stripes. Information: (212) 772-0210. At the Charles A. Dana Discovery Center, 110th Street near Fifth Avenue, a printmaker will introduce the art of paper- and fabric-rubbing. For ages 6 and up. Free, but call to register: (212) 860-1370.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the Fourth</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK CONSERVANCY. Independence Day Weekend workshops, tomorrow from 1 to 2:30 p.m.: at the Henry Luce Nature Observatory at Belvedere Castle, midpark at 79th Street. Flag making and a historical overview of the Stars and Stripes. Information: (212) 772-0210. At the Charles A. Dana Discovery Center, 110th Street near Fifth Avenue, a printmaker will introduce the art of paper- and fabric-rubbing. For ages 6 and up. Free, but call to register: (212) 860-1370.</p>
        <p>EAGLE WEEKEND. In keeping with the spirit of the Fourth of July, the Queens Zoo, 53-51 111th Street, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, will celebrate the beauty and grace of the bald eagles Claire and Mel, inhabitants of the zoo. There will also be eagle-related activities tomorrow and Sunday from 11 a.m. to 5 p.m., including crafts, discussions, storytelling and face painting. Free with admission: $2.50; the elderly, $1.25; children 3 to 12, 50 cents; 2 and under, free. Information: (718) 271-1500.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>''THE TORTOISE AND THE HARE'' and other Aesop's fables, presented by Puppetworks, 338 Sixth Avenue, at Fourth Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, Saturdays at 12:30 and 2:30 p.m. (through Aug. 26). For ages 3 and up. Admission: $7; $5 for children; $4.25 for groups of 20 or more. Reservations suggested: (718) 965-3391.</p>
        <p>''UNWANTED: THE VERY UGLY DUCKLING,'' a New Age version of the Hans Christian Andersen story, in which the hero discovers both his inner beauty and his birth mother, tomorrow at 12:30 p.m. at 432 West 42nd Street, Clinton. Tickets: $10. Reservations advised. Information: (212) 592-4508.</p>
        <p>''THE WIND IN THE WILLOWS,'' a musical adaptation by Douglas Post based on the book by Kenneth Grahame. Presented by Pied Piper Children's Theater, a troupe of children ages 5 to 12, tomorrow and July 8 at 3 and 7 p.m.; Sunday and July 9 at 3 p.m.; Monday and Wednesday at 10 a.m. Holy Trinity Episcopal Church, 20 Cumming Street, Inwood, Upper Manhattan. Tickets: $6; $3 for children under 16. Information: (212) 567-2329.</p>
        <p>Zoos</p>
        <p>''BUTTERFLY ZONE,'' at the Bronx Zoo, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, Fordham. Zebra longwings, tiger swallowtails, variegated fritillary, luna moths and other beautiful species have returned to the ''Butterfly Zone'' through Oct. 1, weather permitting. Children can also view the metamorphosis of the occupants of chrysalises, as they transform inside eclosion boxes and emerge as butterflies or moths. Admission to the Butterfly Zone is $2. Hours: daily, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., until 5:30 P.M. on weekends and holidays. Zoo admission: $9; ages 2 to 12, $5; under 2, free, and free for everyone on Wednesdays. Parking, $6. Information: (718) 367-1010.</p>
        <p>SEA LION KEEPER WEEKEND, at Prospect Park Zoo, 450 Flatbush Avenue, near Empire Boulevard, Prospect Heights, Brooklyn, tomorrow and Sunday from 1 to 4:30 p.m. Youngsters can join zoo experts to learn about the popular marine mammals both days at 3 p.m. at the sea lion pool. Other activities include crafts workshops, playing Sea Lion Simon Says or joining in the Bucket of Fish Relay.Sea Lion shows at 11:30 a.m. and 2 and 4 p.m. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; weekends, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Admission: $2.50; the elderly, $1.25; children 3 to 12, 50 cents; 2 and under, free. Information: (718) 399-7339.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>''BATTLE FOR THE PLANET OF THE APES,'' the 1973 film directed by J. Lee Thompson in which mankind is decimated by nuclear war and the apes are in command, tomorrow and Sunday at 2 p.m. at Walter Reade Theater, Lincoln Center, 165 West 65th Street. Tickets: $3. Information: (212) 875-5601.</p>
        <p>''BATTERY BOOKWORMS,'' storytelling by Cecilia Carson, tomorrow from 11 a.m. to 12:30 p.m. at the World Financial Center Winter Garden, on the Grand Staircase, West Street, between Liberty and Vesey Streets. Free. Information: (212) 945-2600.</p>
        <p>''BEADS, BODY AND SOUL: ART AND LIGHT IN THE YORUBA UNIVERSE,'' an exhibition presented jointly by the Studio Museum in Harlem (through Sept. 17) and the Museum for African Art (through Aug. 27) explores 1,000 years of beaded arts in the Yoruba culture. The Museum for African Art will present a workshop tomorrow at 1 p.m. with the Yoruba drummer Folorunsho (Foley) Kolade, who will teach children the different drum tones and their meaning, perform with the children and tell stories of his Nigerian childhood. Limited to 30. For ages 5 and up. 593 Broadway, SoHo. Free with museum admission: $5; $2.50 for children, students and the elderly. Participants should call to reserve space for all activities. Information (212) 966-1313), Extension 125.</p>
        <p>RAIN FOREST LIFE, a tropical adventure via a live video teleconference with the Cleveland Metroparks Zoo, today at 3:30 p.m. at the Windsor Park Branch of the Queens Library, 79-50 Bell Boulevard, Bayside. For children 6 to 11. Free. Information: (718) 468-8300.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BOTANICAL GARDEN, 200th Street and Southern Boulevard, Bedford Park, the Bronx, will present its Summer Train Show, tomorrow through Sept. 10, featuring colorful model engines chugging along the wooded hillsides, miniature evergreens and summer flowers of the Everett Children's Adventure Garden's fantasy landscape of streams, bridges, a castle, and homes of American artists and writers from an earlier age. Throughout July in the Ruth Rea Howell Family Garden, ''Cool Off!,'' Tuesdays through Sundays 1 to 6 p.m., green and shady getaways for children, including the Bean Tunnel and Sunflower House, a child-size Reflection Garden and a Plant Petting Zoo. Garden and Children's Adventure Garden hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Grounds admission free for all on Wednesdays and from 10 a.m. to noon on Saturdays. Adventure garden admission: $3; students and the elderly, $2; children 2 to 12, $1; under 2, free. The best way to see the garden is with a ''garden passport'' combination ticket, which grants admission to the entire grounds, with a tram tour: adults, $10; students and the elderly, $7.50; children 2 to 12, $4; under 2, free. Parking: $5. Information: (718) 817-8700.</p>
        <p>TRIX CIRCO MUNDIAL, a single-ring circus in which stunts, trapeze acts and acrobatics are presented with Latin-flavored music and costumes and most of the performers are from Spanish-speaking countries or Hispanic-American communites. Tonight at 7:30; tomorrow and Sunday, noon, 3:30 and 7:30 p.m. at Macombs Dam Park, 40 East 164th Street, across from Yankee Stadium in the Bronx. For updated schedule information, depending on the weather, call (888) 959-0595. Tickets: $16 to 25; for ages under 10, $14 to $22.50.</p>
        <p>Exhibitions</p>
        <p>''ANIMALS AS ARCHITECTS'' AND ''PIGTAILS AND HARD HATS,'' two interactive exhibitions at the Staten Island Children's Museum, Snug Harbor Cultural Center, 1000 Richmond Terrace, Livingston. ''Animals as Architects,'' through Sept. 3, featuring a home with walls of recyclable material and another with a secret tunnel, demonstrates that animals are concerned with human interests like energy efficiency and comfort. Next door, ''Pigtails and Hard Hats,'' which may remind youngsters of the three little pigs, uses the storybook characters to teach about the construction industry. Through Aug. 28. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Admission: $4; under 2 and members, free. Information: (718) 273-2060.</p>
        <p>''REPTILES: REAL AND ROBOTIC,'' including an alligator snapping turtle 10 times life size and a Western diamondback rattlesnake 36 feet long, is part of the exhibition (through Sept. 17) at the New York Hall of Science, 47-01 111th Street, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Queens. Although those are robots, the real ones are no less impressive, including gila monsters, bearded dragons and blue-tongued skinks. Children will enjoy ''Reptiles Revealed'' shows each day in the hall at 1 and 3 p.m., and at noon and 2 p.m. they can see demonstrations of NASA's use of robotics. They can also take a reptile home -- as a craft, that is -- by making a gecko glider or a snake mobile. (There is a $1 materials fee.) And beginning tomorrow (through Aug. 26), the museum will offer shows of live reptiles every Saturday at 2 p.m. for $2. Hours in July and August: Mondays from 9:30 a.m. to 2 p.m.; Tuesdays through Sundays, 9:30 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $7.50; $5 for ages 4 to 17 and the elderly; free for ages 3 and under. Information: (718) 699-0005.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
