<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Salute to the Fourth; Down to the Sea Again, in Ships Tall and Fleet</title>
    <meta content="30RALP$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Independence Day (US) (July 4)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opsail 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Niagara (Brig)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Eagle (USS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">John F Kennedy (USS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York Harbor</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Ralph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Independence Day (US) (July 4)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D71F30F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1904" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Salute to the Fourth; Down to the Sea Again, in Ships Tall and Fleet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blumenthal, Ralph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Operation Sail 2000 in New York harbor will begin on July Fourth with parade of tall ships up Hudson River, blessing of the fleet, and review by Pres Clinton from deck of aircraft carrier John F Kennedy; other events during holiday period noted; photos of US brig Niagara, built during War of 1812 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WE were heaving to and definitely not giving up the ship as the United States brig Niagara weathered stormy skies in Long Island Sound before mustering in New York Harbor for Operation Sail 2000 over the coming July 4 holiday.</p>
        <p>The spanker sail at the stern trailed a puff of patriotic color: a 15-star Old Glory from the War of 1812. And atop the foremast fluttered a replica of Commodore Oliver Hazard Perry's proud blue banner, ''Don't Give Up the Ship.'' After vanquishing the British in the original Niagara on Lake Erie in 1813, Perry retired to his cabin and penned his eloquent report: ''We have met the enemy and they are ours.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WE were heaving to and definitely not giving up the ship as the United States brig Niagara weathered stormy skies in Long Island Sound before mustering in New York Harbor for Operation Sail 2000 over the coming July 4 holiday.</p>
        <p>The spanker sail at the stern trailed a puff of patriotic color: a 15-star Old Glory from the War of 1812. And atop the foremast fluttered a replica of Commodore Oliver Hazard Perry's proud blue banner, ''Don't Give Up the Ship.'' After vanquishing the British in the original Niagara on Lake Erie in 1813, Perry retired to his cabin and penned his eloquent report: ''We have met the enemy and they are ours.''</p>
        <p>The air rang with commands shouted and repeated: ''Avast!,'' ''Brace up three points!'' and -- my favorite -- ''O.K., hear the news: Port watch eats!'' Even a clueless landsman knew that spelled lunch.</p>
        <p>The Niagara has been assigned a leading spot in the parade of sail on Tuesday, behind the flagship, the United States Coast Guard bark Eagle; the full-rigged Danish training ship Danmark; and the Pogoria of Poland.</p>
        <p>An estimated five million spectators are expected to throng New York City's shores next week for what may be the greatest nautical spectacle of all time -- an event drawing well over 120 tall ships, some 42 warships from the United States and 25 other nations and 50,000 to 70,000 small pleasure craft.</p>
        <p>President Clinton will review the July 4 spectacle from the deck of the aircraft carrier the John F. Kennedy, anchored near the Statue of Liberty, as some 70 planes soar overhead in an international flyover. The festivities will culminate at 9 p.m. with what is being called the largest pyrotechnic display in history: a Macy's fireworks bombardment shooting off more than 2,000 shells a minute -- more than 60,000 in all -- in New York Harbor.</p>
        <p>Between the arrival of the armada on Monday and its departure on July 9 there will be gun salutes and a blessing of the fleet, a national bell-ringing, military band concerts and a concert by the New York Pops, with a guest appearance on the podium by Walter Cronkite, the event's honorary chairman.</p>
        <p>Ships moored around Manhattan, Brooklyn, Staten Island, Liberty State Park and Bayonne, N.J., will be open to visitors. Also scheduled are demonstrations of military and sportive prowess by many of the 28,000 or so visiting seamen. After the events in New York, many of the ships will sail on to Boston for another assemblage.</p>
        <p>''We think this is the most magnificent and important tall-ship event in history anywhere in the world,'' said Charles A. Robertson, chairman of Op Sail 2000. A longtime yachtsman and businessman, Mr. Robertson was instrumental in the last Operation Sail, in 1992, which commemorated the 500th anniversary of Columbus's landing in the New World. Add the military component, said Capt. Woody Berzins, the Navy spokesman for the ''gray hull'' or warship event, officially called the International Naval Review, and you are looking at ''the greatest maritime event in history,'' in the unabashed words of the Op Sail 2000 slogan.</p>
        <p>Op Sails of Yesteryear</p>
        <p>Next week's extravaganza will be the fifth Operation Sail, a tradition established in 1961 by another old salt, President John F. Kennedy, who did not live to see its actual debut in celebration of the New York World's Fair in 1964. Subsequent Op Sails celebrated the nation's bicentennial (1976) and the centennial of the Statue of Liberty (1986). Future Op Sails are already being planned, Mr. Robertson said, for the West Coast in 2004 or 2005 and back again on the East Coast in 2008 or 2009.</p>
        <p>The International Naval Reviews go back to 1893, when the warships of 10 nations sailed from Hampton Roads, Va., into New York Harbor past President Grover Cleveland to commemorate Columbus's second voyage. In 1907 American and foreign warships again convened in Hampton Roads to mark the tercentennial of the Jamestown Colony, a salute reprised there in 1957 for Jamestown's 350th anniversary. A fourth naval review, the largest to date, drew warships from more than 40 countries to New York for the 1976 bicentennial, and a smaller fleet converged in 1986 for the relighting of the renovated Statue of Liberty's torch. Next week's International Naval Review, the sixth, was mandated by Congress in 1996 as an observance of the millennium and the nation's 224th birthday.</p>
        <p>With the focus on anniversaries, the submarine service, in its centennial this year (the inventor John Holland sold his prototype submersible to the Navy for $150,000 in 1900), celebrates with a visit by the Jacksonville, one of the nation's 50 nuclear-powered fast-attack submarines.</p>
        <p>But once again it is the wind-powered craft, throwbacks to a storied wooden world, that are likely to steal the show. They go from the largest of the tall ships, 27 Class A vessels starting with the Esmeralda, a four-masted Chilean barkentine of 371 feet, to 25 Class B ships of 161 to 100 feet, to 61 Class C Vessels of 90 to 18 feet.</p>
        <p>Recreational craft that are not part of the official group with assigned berths are also expected to swarm New York's waters in record numbers, possibly as many as 70,000 by Coast Guard estimates.</p>
        <p>A majority of the windjammers, despite their antique look, are actually modern-day re-creations, built as training vessels for foreign navies. ''Sailing vessels like these teach them things they wouldn't ordinarily know,'' said Paul A. Welling, a retired Coast Guard Vice Admiral who skippered the Eagle for four years, training 600 cadets a summer. He now serves as chief operating officer of Op Sail 2000. ''If you're on a screw-driven vessel you wouldn't be so concerned about weather and wind-shifts.''</p>
        <p>Authenticity on the Wavertree</p>
        <p>Among the more authentic entries is the Wavertree, called the world's oldest iron sailing ship, built in 1885. A pillar of the British merchant fleet hauling jute from India to Scotland, it was demasted in a storm off Cape Horn in 1910, faced junking for scrap and was finally rediscovered in 1968 by the South Street Seaport Museum, which is turning it into a floating museum and training vessel.</p>
        <p>The Niagara, which I joined recently in New London, Conn., for a sopping day sail before it headed off to Newport, Philadelphia and New York for the festivities, is on the light side for a Class A vessel and ranks about midway in length, at 198 feet. But it is surpassing in loftiness: its two masts top out at 118 and 113 feet.</p>
        <p>Both masts are square-rigged (the defining characteristics of a brig), which means that the yards, the horizontal spars from which the sails are set, can be set square to the centerline of the ship as well as angled, or ''braced up sharp,'' to sail closer to the wind. The 15 sails consume almost 13,000 square feet of canvas and can propel the ship along at up to 13.5 knots, or more than 16 miles an hour, very speedy for a square-rigger of this size. Once the Niagara bristled with 18 32-pounder carronades and two 12-pounder long guns that could hurl a cannonball more than a mile; now only four replica 32-pounder Scottish cannons and two long guns poke through the gun ports.</p>
        <p>The Niagara, which makes regular cruises out of the Erie Maritime Museum in Erie, Pa., comes freighted with history, although with the exception of a few precious original timbers, it is a re-creation.</p>
        <p>With the immature young republic and its recently dislodged British overlords having stumbled into war again in 1812 over simmering resentments and insults, Perry, commanding nine ships, confronted six of the enemy's at Put-in-Bay on Lake Erie on Sept. 10, 1813. The beginning of the battle went badly for the Americans. Perry, aboard his flagship, the Lawrence, miraculously escaped when 80 percent of the crew was felled by British fire. Striking her banner, ''Don't Give Up the Ship'' -- and then doing precisely that -- Perry evacuated to the Niagara, hauled up the banner and went on to capture the British fleet (''Two Ships, two Brigs, one Schooner, &amp; one Sloop''), a victory that prepared the way for peace in 1814 and the nation's westward expansion.</p>
        <p>The Niagara was ignominiously scuttled in 1820 and raised and rebuilt nearly a century later, in 1913, for the centennial of the battle. Renovation dragged on through the Depression and World War II. But by the 1980's severe decay required its dismantling, with some original timbers salvaged for a full reconstruction, completed in 1990.</p>
        <p>The ship surely seemed authentic enough, though, as I stepped aboard in a downpour, seeking shelter under the canvas-covered main hatch and enviously eyeing the crew in waterproof orange and yellow foul-weather gear. In 1813 a crew of 155 manned the ship, about 100 of them on the guns. Today it sails with 16 professionals, including the master, Capt. Walter Rybka, plus 24 volunteers who sign on for at least three weeks at a time. Visitors are encouraged to pitch in on the two watches, port and starboard, and even, with proper safety harnesses, high up on the sails.</p>
        <p>Life Below Decks</p>
        <p>''Give them tasks, belt them up if they want to play,'' Captain Rybka told the crew. But he cautioned, ''Do not belt up someone who doesn't want to go.''</p>
        <p>Among the special guests on board was Cmdr. William F. Foster Jr. of the Constitution, the granddaddy of tall ships. Known as ''Old Ironsides,'' it was commissioned in 1797 as one of the nation's first six warships and is now restored and permanently berthed as a museum in Charlestown Navy Yard in Boston.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the biggest revelation for a nonseaman was how much brawn and know-how a tall ship requires to remain, well, shipshape. There are sails to loose and set, halyards to haul away on and make fast, line to coil, yards to brace up and brace in, watches to stand and the tiller to steer. Below deck, where the clearance is too low to stand upright, hot meals are cooked on a wood stove; the crew is unceremoniously bunked in hammocks hanging like clusters of cocooned caterpillars, and even the heads require manual pumping.</p>
        <p>That's all authentic, too (except that there are no more floggings and no grog issue). ''They always kept them busy so they wouldn't discover those sailorly vices,'' said John Beebe-Center, the sun-bronzed Chief Mate, who learned sailing while growing up in Salem, Mass.</p>
        <p>If the spaghetti tangle of rigging seemed impossibly intricate, it was perhaps only the 19th-century equivalent of today's computer innards: to the people whose business it was to sail the ship, it all made perfect sense. So, too, the laboriously loaded and fired guns, which Captain Rybka and his crew demonstrated to thunderous effect.</p>
        <p>In the sudden silence after the concussive blast, somewhere on deck a cell phone trilled. Clearly, we were back in the 21st century.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
