<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senate Backs Bill Allowing Safe Havens For Infants</title>
    <meta content="30BABY$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211436"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abandonment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kocieniewski, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E2DF1739F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senate Backs Bill Allowing Safe Havens For Infants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kocieniewski, David</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, June 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Senate gives final approval to bill that would allow parents to abandon newborn infants at hospital or police station without facing criminal penalties (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hoping to spare the lives of newborn babies whose mothers are too desperate to care for them, the New Jersey State Senate gave final legislative approval today to a bill that would allow parents to abandon an infant at a hospital or police station without facing criminal penalties.</p>
        <p>The so-called Safe Haven Bill, which was passed by the Assembly on Monday, will change the state's legal code, which currently treats the abandonment of any child as a crime punishable by up to 10 years in prison. Gov. Christine Todd Whitman is expected to sign the bill into law, said Jayne O'Connor, a spokeswoman for the governor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hoping to spare the lives of newborn babies whose mothers are too desperate to care for them, the New Jersey State Senate gave final legislative approval today to a bill that would allow parents to abandon an infant at a hospital or police station without facing criminal penalties.</p>
        <p>The so-called Safe Haven Bill, which was passed by the Assembly on Monday, will change the state's legal code, which currently treats the abandonment of any child as a crime punishable by up to 10 years in prison. Gov. Christine Todd Whitman is expected to sign the bill into law, said Jayne O'Connor, a spokeswoman for the governor.</p>
        <p>Texas became the first state to enact a safe haven law last year. Legislatures in 11 other states, including New York, have approved similar measures this year.</p>
        <p>One of the Trenton bill's sponsors, Senator Gerald Cardinale, said he thought such legislation could have prevented several recent incidents in which New Jersey infants died after their parents abandoned them.</p>
        <p>So far this year, five infants have been abandoned in New Jersey, one of whom died. In 1996, a teenage couple, Amy S. Grossberg and Brian C. Peterson, made national headlines when they threw their newborn son into a trash bin outside a motel in Delaware, killing the child.</p>
        <p>''Women who find themselves with an unwanted pregnancy will know that if they carry the baby to term, they can surrender custody of the baby without having to go through all sorts of legal hoops,'' said Mr. Cardinale, a Republican of Bergen County. ''They won't have to reveal who the father is. They won't have a social worker trying to change their mind. And they won't have to involve their parents or relatives in the decision-making process.''</p>
        <p>Some child advocates contend that state-sanctioned drop-off centers for infants could hinder the process of  placing abandoned newborns in adoptive homes by complicating the legal child custody issues because an abandoned child has no identifiable guardian.</p>
        <p>Nina Williams-Mbengue, a policy analyst for the National Conference of State Legislatures, said it was unclear whether the laws would work. During the first four months the Texas law was in effect, nine babies were abandoned across the state, none of them at a hospital or police station.</p>
        <p>But supporters of the Texas law said that the disappointing response resulted from their failure to publicize the new law and that they were now raising money to start a statewide advertising campaign.</p>
        <p>New Jersey's law will allocate $500,000 for a public awareness campaign and will establish a 24-hour toll-free phone line to inform prospective parents about the law, said  Diane Allen, a Republican state senator from Edgewater Park.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
