<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Gains a Compromise On War Crimes Tribunal</title>
    <meta content="Y30COU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Criminal Court</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E4D81639F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="960" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Gains a Compromise On War Crimes Tribunal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, June 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States wins agreement to keep door open to further talks on its demand that no American official or soldier be surrendered to world's first permanent court for war crimes as long as US has not signed treaty creating International Criminal Court (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States won an agreement today to keep the door open to further talks on its demand that no American official or soldier be surrendered to the world's first permanent court for war crimes as long as Washington has not signed the treaty creating the court.</p>
        <p>European and other nations are determined to keep the United States from being frozen out of the biggest change in international law in decades. With their help, the Clinton administration's ambassador at large for war crimes, David Scheffer, won an agreement letting his delegation return to the final round of negotiations on the form and functions of the court, in November. Without the deal today, the United States' participation would have ended.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States won an agreement today to keep the door open to further talks on its demand that no American official or soldier be surrendered to the world's first permanent court for war crimes as long as Washington has not signed the treaty creating the court.</p>
        <p>European and other nations are determined to keep the United States from being frozen out of the biggest change in international law in decades. With their help, the Clinton administration's ambassador at large for war crimes, David Scheffer, won an agreement letting his delegation return to the final round of negotiations on the form and functions of the court, in November. Without the deal today, the United States' participation would have ended.</p>
        <p>The deal was immediately criticized by many independent legal experts and official delegates here, who say that no exceptions should be made for the United States. Exempting Americans, they argue, only opens the way for officials of other nations -- some of them ruled by dictators -- to avoid prosecution.</p>
        <p>The United States voted against the creation of the tribunal, the International Criminal Court, two years ago because the Pentagon and a Republican-controlled Congress opposed it.</p>
        <p>The court will deal with war crimes, crimes against humanity and genocide. In principle, the court will have universal jurisdiction, regardless of which individual countries voted for the treaty to form it. That power makes Washington nervous, feeling it would be vulnerable to unfair or frivolous prosecution.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scheffer said the United States would take the criticism into account and would try to devise safeguards as it prepares for further negotiations. In the meantime, he said, it is important for the United States to stay involved with the court as it comes into operation over the next few years.</p>
        <p>''The world needs a permanent international criminal court,'' he said in an interview with several reporters today. ''We need it because the perpetrators of these heinous crimes must be brought to justice, and we need it as a deterrent over the generations that follow. The international system simply cannot continue to deal with these problems in an ad hoc manner indefinitely.</p>
        <p>''This court has tremendous potential for being a vehicle for international justice, and we want to be able to see that potential,'' he said. ''We should be able to assist the court and cooperate with it when it's in our  national interest to do so.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Scheffer, who helped create war crimes tribunals for the Balkans and Rwanda, is in danger of being hamstrung over the next few months by a bill recently introduced in the Senate by Jesse Helms, Republican of North Carolina, and John W. Warner, Republican of Virginia, that seeks to block any American cooperation with the International Criminal Court as long as the United States does not sign and ratify the treaty. Mr. Helms, chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, has vowed never to allow ratification.</p>
        <p>''It is clearly a locomotive coming down on us,'' Mr. Scheffer said of the bill today. ''But I would hope that the locomotive stops, because it's recognized that we are making progress in these negotiations to achieve the very objective that is behind this legislation. It is a counterintuitive piece of legislation because it is undermining the very negotiating efforts that we are undertaking to achieve the objective that we all agree must be achieved.''</p>
        <p>On Friday, delegates from more than 100 nations who have been meeting here for three weeks are expected to approve two main components of the court's business, the rules of procedure and a document called ''the elements of crimes.'' These elements are a compendium of legal definitions that Mr. Scheffer called a checklist for prosecutors considering indictments.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration, which once spoke more forcefully for membership in the court, was instrumental in calling for more specific criteria for war crimes, genocide and crimes against humanity.</p>
        <p>''Never before have war crimes and crimes against humanity and genocide been defined with such precision as we now have in the elements of crimes,'' Mr. Scheffer said. ''This will be the document that guides prosecutors not only in the I.C.C. but also in national and military courts for decades to come.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''And defense counsel will look at this document to determine where exactly their rights are in the defense of their clients with respect to any particular crime. It's a truly historic document. We invested a tremendous amount of our talent in it.''</p>
        <p>In a November-December session, the last at which countries that do not sign the treaty establishing the court will have the right to participate in its affairs, the United States will argue for a provision that allows specifically for an exemption from prosecution. The accord today generally paved the way for that debate by raising the general question of international agreements outside the court's treaty.</p>
        <p>In Washington, another American official was more cautious than Mr. Scheffer in welcoming the move today. ''Proponents of the court are certainly not speaking for the American people,'' the official said. ''It is inconceivable that the American people would support the hauling of an American official before a court that is not accountable to the American government when we are not party to the underlying treaty. Ultimately we're going to have to address this more fundamental question.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
