<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Forget Sosa: Yanks Trade for Justice</title>
    <meta content="30JUST$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Cubs</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleveland Indians</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sosa, Sammy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Justice, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ledee, Ricky</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EEDF1739F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1245" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Forget Sosa: Yanks Trade for Justice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, June 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees, refusing to make high-priced trade for Sammy Sosa of Chicago Cubs, instead acquire outfielder David Justice from Cleveland Indians, first substantial move to bolster their sagging team; Yankees swap outfielder Ricky Ledee and two minor league players to be named in return for Justice, who is expected to join the team on June 30; chart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Refusing to make a high-priced trade for Sammy Sosa, the Yankees instead acquired outfielder David Justice from Cleveland tonight, the first substantial move to bolster their sagging team.</p>
        <p>The Yankees swapped outfielder Ricky Ledee and two minor league players to be named in return for the 34-year-old Justice, who has 21 homers and 58 runs batted in this year -- more homers than any Yankee. Justice, expected to join the Yankees on Friday, developed into Plan C for the Yankees in the last three days, after they failed to complete a conditional trade for Detroit's Juan Gonzalez last week and then haggled without success for Sosa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Refusing to make a high-priced trade for Sammy Sosa, the Yankees instead acquired outfielder David Justice from Cleveland tonight, the first substantial move to bolster their sagging team.</p>
        <p>The Yankees swapped outfielder Ricky Ledee and two minor league players to be named in return for the 34-year-old Justice, who has 21 homers and 58 runs batted in this year -- more homers than any Yankee. Justice, expected to join the Yankees on Friday, developed into Plan C for the Yankees in the last three days, after they failed to complete a conditional trade for Detroit's Juan Gonzalez last week and then haggled without success for Sosa.</p>
        <p>After the Yankees informed the Cubs of their impending trade for Justice, Chicago's general manager, Ed Lynch, passed on the word to a disappointed Sosa, who was playing in Pittsburgh tonight. The Sosa talks, Yankees General Manager Brian Cashman said, ''are shut down.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees and Indians have agreed on a list of about a half-dozen minor leaguers from which the two unnamed players will be selected by Aug. 1. Baseball officials say no one on the list is a front-line prospect, such as Drew Henson or Alfonso Soriano. The Indians are starved for pitching, making it possible that the right-handers Jake Westbrook and Ryan Bradley are among those being considered.</p>
        <p>Joe Torre, the Yankees' manager, seems to be leaning toward using Justice as his designated hitter, with occasional appearances in left or right field. Shane Spencer, perhaps the Yankees' best outfielder this year, will get more time in left field now.</p>
        <p>Torre may shake up the lineup in a big way. Tino Martinez, who has been the Yankees' No. 5 hitter behind Bernie Williams, is struggling, batting .263 with 7 homers and 41 R.B.I. Justice, batting .265, could move into the No. 5 spot, with catcher Jorge Posada hitting sixth and Martinez dropping to seventh, ahead of Spencer and Scott Brosius in the last two spots.</p>
        <p>Torre would not reveal his plans for the lineup. ''I'm not going to talk about it until I talk to the people involved,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Justice will be a long-term investment for the Yankees: He is making $7 million this year and each of the next two years, and has an option for 2003 for $7 million. That's about $10 million to $13 million less than the Yankees might have had to pay Sosa in a contract extension. It was the potential cost in salary and prospects that made Yankees' executives extremely leery of dealing for Sosa and ultimately scuttled the trade proposal.</p>
        <p>The Yankees offered Ledee, Westbrook, outfielder Jackson Melian and a choice of Soriano or D'Angelo Jimenez for Sosa; the Cubs insisted on five players, including Melian, Westbrook, Ledee and two players from a group of three that included Soriano, Jimenez and Alex Graman, a Class A pitcher. The Yankees also knew that if they agreed to a trade for Sosa, they would then have to negotiate a contract extension of almost $100 million with the slugger -- an agreement that would revamp their salary structure and change the dynamics of their forthcoming negotiations with Derek Jeter, their 26-year-old shortstop, and Mariano Rivera, their closer.</p>
        <p>George Steinbrenner, the Yankees' principal owner, was enticed by the idea of getting Sosa's power and marquee presence; his executives were frightened by how such a trade would affect the organization.</p>
        <p>The Cubs and Yankees reached a stalemate on Tuesday, and the Yankees explored other options. They talked with the Baltimore Orioles about B. J. Surhoff, and exchanged proposals for Oakland's John Jaha (offering Allen Watson) and San Diego's Ed Sprague. The Yankees still might try to acquire Jaha or Sprague.</p>
        <p>Cashman called Mark Shapiro, Cleveland's assistant general manager, on a matter unrelated to Justice, and in the course of their conversation, Shapiro indicated that Justice was available. The Indians, like the Yankees, are a struggling American League power. Last week Justice infuriated club officials by suggesting the Indians' best years might be behind them. ''There comes a time when you say, 'Hey, maybe the window of opportunity is closing for them,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>So with the Sosa talks at an impasse, Cashman began bartering with Cleveland General Manager John Hart. There were only three instances of brief contact between the Yankees and Cubs on Wednesday and Thursday, and in all three instances, it was Andy MacPhail, the Cubs' president, who made the call, reaching out to the Yankees. Each time, MacPhail was told that Yankees officials were having trouble reaching Steinbrenner. The Yankees were stalling, and the Sosa deal was dying.</p>
        <p>Hart and Cashman settled on a deal about 5 p.m. today, and Cashman called the Orioles to call off the Surhoff talks, while Yankees President Randy Levine phoned MacPhail to end the Sosa discussions.</p>
        <p>About a half-hour before tonight's game, Torre summoned Ledee into his office and told the outfielder -- who signed with the Yankees 10 years ago, when he was 16 -- that he was being traded.</p>
        <p>Ledee said goodbye to Jeter, Posada and a few others, but could not face the rest of the team, fearing he would be unable to contain his emotions. His eyes were puffy and welled with tears when he spoke to reporters. ''It's sad,'' he said. ''It's very, very sad. I'm just sad I couldn't put it together with the Yankees, the team I wanted to be with.''</p>
        <p>Justice was part of another shocking trade, in 1997, when the Atlanta Braves swapped him to the Cleveland Indians in a deal that also included Kenny Lofton and Marquis Grissom. But Justice was still incredulous when he was told this evening.</p>
        <p>''I'm stunned,'' he said, ''but business is business. That's the game we play. I don't know any of the guys there except for Mike Stanton, but I make friends wherever I go. I wanted to end my career in Cleveland but I didn't think it would happen because stuff like this always happens in baseball. But I'll go to New York and play hard.''</p>
        <p>Cashman said: ''We're getting a professional hitter who has been in every postseason but one since 1991. His makeup is built for New York. No question, it's an upgrade.''</p>
        <p>Jeter said: ''He's an established star. He's been around for a while, and he'll fit right in.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees' next goal will be to improve their pitching staff. Roger Clemens and Orlando Hernandez are expected to return to the rotation sometime in the next week, but Yankees scouts are scouring the majors for possible candidates, such as Pittsburgh's Francisco Cordova and Philadelphia's Andy Ashby. A scout from the Minnesota Twins will be following the Yankees for the next few days, and although there were no discussions about the right-hander Brad Radke, the Yankees will pursue him if he becomes available before the July 31 trading deadline.</p>
        <p>''I've got the impression this is not over,'' Williams said. ''We've got a couple of more things to do.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
