<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Cityscape So Wondrous Strange</title>
    <meta content="30DREA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pilobolus Dance Theater</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tracy, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunning, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EED81F30F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Cityscape So Wondrous Strange</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jennifer Dunning reviews Michael Tracy's new work Sweet Dreams, performed by Pilobolus Dance Theater; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Metaphorical worlds are seldom created through acrobatic movement and visual effects of the body. But Michael Tracy's new ''Sweet Dreams'' succeeded in creating an enveloping, larger other world in a program presented by Pilobolus Dance Theater on Wednesday night at the Joyce Theater. Nothing much happened once that world had been posited. But that is the way of luscious, mysterious dreams like the one created by Mr. Tracy and his collaborators.</p>
        <p>Much of the impact of ''Sweet Dreams'' comes from its eerie set, designed, with the costumes, by Angelina Avallone. Ms. Avallone hits just the right balance between de Chirico and Edward Hopper. A glowing moonlike egg hangs over a corner of what appears to be a walled  city. The wall is thick and impenetrable, but there is an opening beyond which is visible a distant, equally unyielding totem of a building with a crudely shaped window. A small egg balances on top of the wall. Just below, the tiny silhouette of a figure may be glimpsed in a lighted window that, like the figure, is a modern-day urban conceit that contributes to the sense of dreaming illogic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Metaphorical worlds are seldom created through acrobatic movement and visual effects of the body. But Michael Tracy's new ''Sweet Dreams'' succeeded in creating an enveloping, larger other world in a program presented by Pilobolus Dance Theater on Wednesday night at the Joyce Theater. Nothing much happened once that world had been posited. But that is the way of luscious, mysterious dreams like the one created by Mr. Tracy and his collaborators.</p>
        <p>Much of the impact of ''Sweet Dreams'' comes from its eerie set, designed, with the costumes, by Angelina Avallone. Ms. Avallone hits just the right balance between de Chirico and Edward Hopper. A glowing moonlike egg hangs over a corner of what appears to be a walled  city. The wall is thick and impenetrable, but there is an opening beyond which is visible a distant, equally unyielding totem of a building with a crudely shaped window. A small egg balances on top of the wall. Just below, the tiny silhouette of a figure may be glimpsed in a lighted window that, like the figure, is a modern-day urban conceit that contributes to the sense of dreaming illogic.</p>
        <p>Paul Sullivan's thickly textured, often witty score adds to the feeling of imbalance, with an aural landscape that is mysterious yet spotted with cheerful musical allusions. The odd mortals who inhabit ''Sweet Dreams'' are recognizably Pilobolian outcasts. Rebecca Anderson is the central dream figure, a woman in a poppy-red shift with white-blond hair that flies like a flag through her journeys across the stage, usually lifted high and manipulated by three pairs of raised hands. Matt Kent is her sweetly dopey lover or guide in a strange world inhabited by Otis Cook and Benjamin Pring, a pair of pliable bodies without much personality.</p>
        <p>Ms. Anderson curls up at the start and end of the new work, drawn into sweet sleep. Wrapped in a blanket of warm light, designed by Steven Strawbridge, she snuggles into a bed made of the arched bodies of Mr. Cook and Mr. Pring. Those moments have the satisfying rightness of a fairy tale's start and finish.</p>
        <p>Ms. Anderson figured prominently in the evening's other highlight, ''Pseudopodia,'' created in 1974 by Jonathan Wolken and set to a score by Mr. Wolken and Moses Pendleton. The solo is a tour de force of sustained motion for a tightly rolled-up body that occasionally rises then quickly falls back. Never quite settling into a move, Ms. Anderson seemed to be borne through the dance by the subtle spring and push of some airy extra-physical momentum.</p>
        <p>The program, the second of three to be presented through July 22 at the Joyce (175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea), also included two signature Pilobolus works, the 1990 ''Particle Zoo'' and the 1980 ''Day Two.'' Mr. Pring was a somewhat cute outsider in ''Particle Zoo,'' which added more of a sense of narrative but diluted the quartet's brute physicality. ''Day Two,'' a topless romp through sensual tribal rituals and across a wet floor, was gloriously performed by Ms. Anderson, Mr. Cook, Josie Coyoc, Mr. Kent, Gaspard Louis and Mr. Pring.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
