<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>12 of 19 Dodgers' Suspensions Overturned</title>
    <meta content="30SUSP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wrigley Field (Chicago)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Dodgers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Cubs</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beeston, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robinson, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kreuter, Chad</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dempsey, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shelby, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez, Carlos</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sheffield, Gary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santangelo, F P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fetters, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffman, Glenn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hundley, Todd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Karros, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Shawn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berroa, Geronimo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chan Ho Park</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dreifort, Darren</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gagne, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Adams, Terry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mills, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Osuna, Antonio</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Masaoka, Onan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE0D81639F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>12 of 19 Dodgers' Suspensions Overturned</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Major League Baseball's new appellate judge of disciplinary action overturns 12 of suspensions imposed against 19 members of Los Angeles Dodgers by game's new dean of discipline for brawl with fans at Wrigley Field in Chicago on May 16; decision by Paul Beeston, baseball's chief operating officer, on action taken by Frank Robinson, vice president for on-field operations, is a first because this is first year in which same official who levies suspensions and fines for on-field incidents has not heard and decided appeals as well; Beeston upholds eight-game suspensions of Dodgers' pitcher Chad Kreuter and coaches Rick Dempsey and John Shelby and five-game suspensions of pitcher Carlos Perez and outfielders Gary Sheffield and F P Santangelo; he reduces from four games to one suspension of pitcher Mike Fetters; also upholds fines Robinson levied against all 16 players and 3 coaches (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In what for Major League Baseball is a stunning development, its new appellate judge of disciplinary action yesterday overturned 12 of the suspensions imposed against 19 members of the Los Angeles Dodgers by the game's new dean of discipline for a brawl with fans at Wrigley Field in Chicago.</p>
        <p>The decision by Paul Beeston, baseball's chief operating officer, on action taken by Frank Robinson, vice president for on-field operations, was a first because this is the first year in which the same official who levies suspensions and fines for on-field incidents has not heard and decided appeals as well. In previous years, the league presidents performed those duties, but the office of league president has been eradicated with the centralization of league functions in the commissioner's office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In what for Major League Baseball is a stunning development, its new appellate judge of disciplinary action yesterday overturned 12 of the suspensions imposed against 19 members of the Los Angeles Dodgers by the game's new dean of discipline for a brawl with fans at Wrigley Field in Chicago.</p>
        <p>The decision by Paul Beeston, baseball's chief operating officer, on action taken by Frank Robinson, vice president for on-field operations, was a first because this is the first year in which the same official who levies suspensions and fines for on-field incidents has not heard and decided appeals as well. In previous years, the league presidents performed those duties, but the office of league president has been eradicated with the centralization of league functions in the commissioner's office.</p>
        <p>The players association long criticized the practice of having the same person decide the penalty and hear the appeal of that penalty. At most, under that format, a president would reduce the suspension by a game or two, depending on its length.</p>
        <p>Beeston acted on the penalties Robinson imposed for an incident in a May 16 game against the Cubs. A fan precipitated the incident by hitting Chad Kreuter in the head, the catcher said, and snatching his cap. Kreuter at the time was in the Dodgers' bullpen next to the stands.</p>
        <p>Kreuter went into the stands after the fan, and other members of the team followed. A brawl ensued, delaying the game for nearly 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>Beeston upheld the eight-game suspensions of Kreuter and the coaches Rick Dempsey and John Shelby and the five-game suspensions of pitcher Carlos Perez and outfielders Gary Sheffield and F. P. Santangelo. He reduced from four games to one the suspension of pitcher Mike Fetters. Beeston also upheld the fines Robinson levied against all 16 players and 3 coaches.</p>
        <p>Overturned were the eight-game suspension of the coach Glenn Hoffman and the three-game suspensions of catcher Todd Hundley, first baseman Eric Karros, outfielders Shawn Green and Geronimo Berroa and pitchers Chan Ho Park, Darren Dreifort, Eric Gagne, Terry Adams, Alan Mills, Antonio Osuna and Onan Masaoka.</p>
        <p>Kreuter and Shelby were ordered to begin their suspensions last night. The other suspensions will be staggered. The Dodgers cannot replace suspended players on the roster, and they had complained that their chances in the National League West race could be affected by the string of suspensions.</p>
        <p>The suspensions, totaling 84 games, were believed to be the most resulting from a single incident.</p>
        <p>Beeston did not return telephone calls seeking an explanation for his decision, but Commissioner Bud Selig said: ''There's an appeals process in place. This was part of the process.''</p>
        <p>Robinson, at Shea Stadium last night for the Mets' game with the Atlanta Braves, said he did not have a problem with Beeston's decision and did not believe it undermined his position.</p>
        <p>''No, not at all,'' Robinson said. ''This is the way the appeals process works. Any time you go in with an appeal, there's a possibility of it being overturned or the possibility of it being reduced. You have to accept the final say because that is it.''</p>
        <p>Robinson added that Beeston's decision would not affect his rulings in future cases. ''I look at each incident on a case-by-case basis,'' he said. ''I'll continue to do my job.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
