<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Light Fare For the Fall</title>
    <meta content="30BROA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211348"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON STAGE AND OFF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Drama Dept (Theater Company)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Signature Theater Co (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Noth, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simon, Neil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vidal, Gore</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dinner Party, The (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Best Man, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/On Stage and Off</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Signature Theater Co</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Drama Dept</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E2DF1639F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1022" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Light Fare For the Fall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jesse McKinley</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Stage and Off column; light fare in view for fall season includes Neil Simon's Dinner Party and revival of Gore Vidal's The Best Man, with Chris Noth making Broadway debut; photo; Drama Dept and Signature Company plans also noted (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maybe it was the prospect of the long holiday weekend or just the summer heat, but this has been a sizzling week for deal makers on and off Broadway, giving shape to the coming season and a sense of security to newly hired actors, playwrights and myriad theater populi.</p>
        <p>First, some trend spotting. After several seasons packed with serious fare, the fall is looking considerably lighter. The latest indication is Neil Simon's ''Dinner Party,'' which opened last week at the Kennedy Center in Washington. The Washington Post called the play, which stars Henry Winkler, John Ritter and Len Cariou, ''laugh out-loud funny,'' adding that it was Mr. Simon's ''emotionally richest play.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Maybe it was the prospect of the long holiday weekend or just the summer heat, but this has been a sizzling week for deal makers on and off Broadway, giving shape to the coming season and a sense of security to newly hired actors, playwrights and myriad theater populi.</p>
        <p>First, some trend spotting. After several seasons packed with serious fare, the fall is looking considerably lighter. The latest indication is Neil Simon's ''Dinner Party,'' which opened last week at the Kennedy Center in Washington. The Washington Post called the play, which stars Henry Winkler, John Ritter and Len Cariou, ''laugh out-loud funny,'' adding that it was Mr. Simon's ''emotionally richest play.''</p>
        <p>Emanuel Azenberg, Mr. Simon's longtime producer, said he would bring the play to Broadway in October, in association with Ira Pittelman and Gordon Davidson, artistic director of Mark Taper Forum in Los Angeles, where the play had its premiere last year.</p>
        <p>Industry gossip suggests that ''The Dinner Party'' will land at the Walter Kerr Theater. That house, however, has also been mentioned for ''Proof,'' David Auburn's drama, now at the Manhattan Theater Club. There's no definite word on that play's future, but this week brought word that Mary-Louise Parker, the star of ''Proof,'' has apparently opted out of the Roundabout Theater Company's fall production of ''Desire Under the Elms.'' That production has now been canceled, to be replaced by another play directed by David Leveaux.</p>
        <p>As for ''Dinner Party,'' it joins another comedy, ''The Tale of the Allergist's Wife'' by Charles Busch, and a couple of revivals that mix sugar and salt: Jane Wagner's ''Search for Signs of Intelligent Life in the Universe'' from 1985 and Gore Vidal's 1960 political satire ''The Best Man.'' (More on that guy later.)</p>
        <p>Other transfers were in the works. From London via California is ''Lifegame,'' an improvisational piece from the Improbable Theater, the British troupe behind mind-bending works like ''70 Hill Lane'' (a metaphysical magic show) and ''Shockheaded Peter'' (a morbidly hilarious children's operetta).</p>
        <p>This time the work is even less predictable: each night, an audience member is picked at random (and in advance) to share his or her life story, portions of which are then re-enacted by the cast of eight.</p>
        <p>The show is currently at the La Jolla Playhouse in California. David Stone, who has done very nicely with ''The Vagina Monologues'' and ''Fully Committed,'' heads the New York producing team.</p>
        <p>And after a brief run at Dance Theater Workshop in Chelsea, producers of the Foundry Theater's ''And God Created Great Whales'' confirmed a move even farther downtown. This surreal exploration of ''Moby-Dick'' begins a monthlong run at the Salon at 45 Bleecker Street in Greenwich Village on Aug. 3.</p>
        <p>Something New</p>
        <p>There was also action in the nonprofit realm, where the trend is running headlong toward new plays. At the Drama Dept. the new season will include three New York premieres:  ''The Dazzle,'' a play by Richard Greenberg; an untitled play ''about racism and sweet potatoes,'' written by and starring the quirky comic siblings Amy and David Sedaris; and ''The Big Time,'' the first musical by the company's artistic director, Douglas Carter Beane.</p>
        <p>At the Signature Company, meanwhile, the next two seasons will be filled by new works, each by one of the company's guest playwrights from the last decade. (The company devotes each season to a single playwright, often choosing lesser-known works from the writer's canon.)</p>
        <p>For the fall the Signature plans to present ''A Lesson Before Dying,'' a new adaptation of the Ernest J. Gaines novel by Romulus Linney (1991-92 season), as well as the ''The Last of the Thorntons,'' a premiere from Horton Foote (1994-95) that is already cast with Mason Adams, Estelle Parsons and Hallie Foote, the playwright's daughter.</p>
        <p>The final entry of the season, ''Urban Zulu Mambo,'' is a tribute to Adrienne Kennedy, who was the Signature's writer in residence in 1995-96. ''Mambo'' was written by a quartet of African-American women -- Regina Taylor, Ntozake Shange, Kia Corthron and Suzan-Lori Parks -- and is performed by Ms. Taylor.</p>
        <p>Two of the ''Mambo'' writers will also be represented elsewhere. Ms. Parks's new play, ''Topdog/Underdog,'' is on next season's roster at the Public Theater, along with ''Kit Marlowe,'' a new play by David Grimm; ''Book of the Dead,'' a music theater piece by John Moran; and ''Dog eaters,'' a play about 1980's Manila by Jessica Hagedorn.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile a new play by Ms. Corthron, ''Force Continuum,'' is part of the Atlantic Theater Company's 2000-01 season, along with Tom Donaghy's ''Beginning of August,'' directed by Neil Pepe.</p>
        <p>Primary Choice</p>
        <p>''The Best Man'' has found its best man, and it's Mr. Big.</p>
        <p>Translation: Chris Noth, best known for playing Mr. Big, Sarah Jessica Parker's elusive paramour on HBO's ''Sex and the City,'' will be making his Broadway debut in September in ''The Best Man.'' Mr. Noth will play Joe Cantwell, a consummate politician (think J. F. K.) in the revival, which opens on Sept. 17 at the Virginia Theater.</p>
        <p>Mr. Noth, a Yale Drama graduate and a veteran of NBC's ''Law and Order,'' said he was yearning to be back onstage but was surprised by  the opportunity.</p>
        <p>''I was shocked that they're actually doing drama on Broadway,'' he said on the set of ''Sex and the City.'' ''I thought: 'Wow, they're doing this? I gotta be there.' ''</p>
        <p>Along the Way</p>
        <p>*Few details yet, but it looks as if the master magician Ricky Jay will return to Broadway next spring in a new show directed by David Mamet.</p>
        <p>*''A Moon for the Misbegotten,'' with Gabriel Byrne, Roy Dotrice and Cherry Jones, closes on Broadway on Sunday, but there is talk of a London run in late winter. There are a couple of potential snags, however. Mr. Byrne and Mr. Dotrice have a new ABC series in the works, ''Madigan Men.'' Mr. Byrne has also been entertaining another Broadway engagement, for spring 2001.</p>
        <p>ON STAGE AND OFF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
