<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Stage, A Lesson In Endurance</title>
    <meta content="30NYC.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211484"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hull, Bryan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haberman, Clyde</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fantasticks, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EEDE1739F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Stage, A Lesson In Endurance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Clyde Haberman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haberman, Clyde</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NYC column interviews Bryan Hull, 62-year-old actor who has appeared in 7,895 performances of The Fantasticks; Off-Broadway institution opened in May 1960, and has now been performed 16,627 times (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE'S an old Jewish joke (it's written somewhere that you must never begin: There's a new Jewish joke) about a poor man in Poland who goes to his rabbi saying he desperately needs a job.</p>
        <p>''Tell you what,'' the rabbi says. ''We'll give you work standing outside the town gates, watching for the Messiah. You're to alert us when you see him coming. And for that, we'll pay you two zlotys a month.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE'S an old Jewish joke (it's written somewhere that you must never begin: There's a new Jewish joke) about a poor man in Poland who goes to his rabbi saying he desperately needs a job.</p>
        <p>''Tell you what,'' the rabbi says. ''We'll give you work standing outside the town gates, watching for the Messiah. You're to alert us when you see him coming. And for that, we'll pay you two zlotys a month.''</p>
        <p>This, the poor man complains, is a pittance.</p>
        <p>''True,'' the rabbi replies. ''But think of the job security.''</p>
        <p>Fiddle with a few words, and you could tell pretty much the same joke about New York actors. Many of them would give up a lot, including a fat paycheck, for steady work, especially for a role deemed worthwhile. Those lucky souls tend to be in short supply.</p>
        <p>That brings us to Bryan Hull, one of those souls, who came to mind because this was supposed to be the week that we were rid of ''Cats'' once and for all.</p>
        <p>The longest-running musical in Broadway history was scheduled to close last Sunday. But it seems it's true about cats having multiple lives. The play's run at the Winter Garden, which began in 1982, has been extended to September because of a surge in demand for tickets. These, the theater marquee promises, are the ''final weeks!'' The exclamation point is presumably the producers' way of saying that they mean it, that this isn't one of those ''going out of business'' sales that manage to drag on for years.</p>
        <p>But even if ''Cats'' does purr on, it will remain an arriviste compared with Mr. Hull and his fellow performers, who have kept quite a different musical going, far from Broadway, for an extraordinary four decades.</p>
        <p>''The Fantasticks,'' at the Sullivan Street Playhouse in Greenwich Village, opened on May 3, 1960, and has been there ever since. Try to remember a time when it wasn't around. It is such a New York institution that most New Yorkers overlook it, much the way they give the Empire State Building or the Statue of Liberty a pass.</p>
        <p>Yet the show sets a record for endurance with every performance. Last night's was No. 16,627. Mr. Hull, 62, has been around for nearly half the play's life, making him the longest-running performer in the modern history of New York theater.</p>
        <p>For the 7,895th time, he stepped onto the tiny stage last night, playing an over-the-hill actor, a wig of wispy white hair covering his own thick graying hair. ''Sir, the players have arrived,'' the character announced. With that, Mr. Hull was off and running, as he has been since May 20, 1980.</p>
        <p>Through that long stretch, he has not missed a show, aside from his allotted two weeks of vacation each year and a three-month absence in 1998 because of a broken leg. He has never missed a performance because of a cold or other routine illness.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes, people ask me, 'Why are you doing this for 20 years?' '' Mr. Hull said, his voice radio announcer deep. '' 'Well,' I say, 'I have a job.' ''</p>
        <p>As every actor in this city knows, there may be no more magical words than those: I have a job. For Mr. Hull, who auditioned for the part six times before getting it, a steady paycheck for 18 minutes of work a night is ample reward.</p>
        <p>IF you are unfamiliar with the play, it is an uncomplicated tale of a boy and a girl, of fathers who scheme to bring the young lovers together, of lost innocence and faded dreams, of learning that ''without a hurt, the heart is hollow.''</p>
        <p>It is the sort of show that draws disdainful sniffs from New York sophisticates (the sort of people who would also probably never be caught dead at the Statue of Liberty or the Empire State Building). The writer Vivian Gornick once nuked the play in this newspaper. Sometimes, Mr. Hull said, you can see the audience sitting there stone-faced, as if to say, ''O.K., show us why you've been here 40 years.''</p>
        <p>But enough people turn up each night to keep the play going, though they typically are student groups and Japanese tourists.</p>
        <p>Maybe there is a lesson in that. Maybe some of us in this city are too sophisticated for our own good. Maybe an unadorned fantasy about love is a necessary antidote to the graphic sex, crude language and overdone pyrotechnics that usually pass for entertainment these days.</p>
        <p>''The charm and the pleasure of it,'' Mr. Hull said, ''is that it is what it is: a simple show.''</p>
        <p>Which may be why it has outlasted the likes of ''Cats'' to become a New York fixture that, for all anyone knows, will still be around whenever the Messiah does show up.</p>
        <p>NYC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
