<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All Reserve Is Lost as Unruliness Takes the Stage</title>
    <meta content="30WIMB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211428"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Women's Tennis Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Alexandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dokic, Jelena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EFD61639F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All Reserve Is Lost as Unruliness Takes the Stage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>WIMBLEDON, England, June 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Unaccustomed unruliness erupts at Wimbledon tournament as Jelena Dokic's father is led away for unruly behavior and Alexandra Stevenson charges hazing and racial slur by players jealous of her 'big spash' during rookie year; photo; WTA says allegations were investigated and were not substantiated (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The All England Club's genteel image was shattered today when Jelena Dokic's father was led away by a police officer after unruly behavior on the grounds, and Alexandra Stevenson ended her run at Wimbledon by describing the hazing she endured during her rookie season, which, she said, included a profane racial slur recently directed at her.</p>
        <p>Moments after losing to Patricia Wartusch in the second round, Stevenson spoke about how tough it was to deal with the jealousy she has encountered since gaining celebrity status last year. In her Wimbledon debut, she was the object of attention. She was the first female qualifier to reach the semifinals and it was disclosed that Julius Erving was her biological father. An interview with Barbara Walters quickly followed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The All England Club's genteel image was shattered today when Jelena Dokic's father was led away by a police officer after unruly behavior on the grounds, and Alexandra Stevenson ended her run at Wimbledon by describing the hazing she endured during her rookie season, which, she said, included a profane racial slur recently directed at her.</p>
        <p>Moments after losing to Patricia Wartusch in the second round, Stevenson spoke about how tough it was to deal with the jealousy she has encountered since gaining celebrity status last year. In her Wimbledon debut, she was the object of attention. She was the first female qualifier to reach the semifinals and it was disclosed that Julius Erving was her biological father. An interview with Barbara Walters quickly followed.</p>
        <p>''I kind of made a big splash,'' Stevenson said. ''I don't think a lot of girls appreciated it. They have to grow up and have bigger minds, not be so petty.''</p>
        <p>Stevenson said that at a tournament in Strasbourg, France, last month, a French player, Amelie Cocheteux, hurled a racial slur at her during every changeover of their match. The next day, she said, another French player, Anne-Gaelle Sidot, pushed her mother, Samantha Stevenson, and pulled down her hat.</p>
        <p>''Cocheteux called me the names, and Sidot hit my mom,'' Stevenson said. ''In the French Open, Cocheteux came up and hit me, kind of bumped into me in the locker room.''</p>
        <p>Sidot was not available for comment early this evening, but Cocheteux was reached by a French reporter and denied all of Stevenson's accusations.</p>
        <p>The chief executive officer of the Women's Tennis Association, Bart McGuire, said the allegations were investigated.</p>
        <p>''It was determined that Ms. Sidot did not physically strike Ms. Stevenson but did tip her hat during a conversation regarding use of a practice court,'' McGuire said, referring to Samantha Stevenson. ''Ms. Sidot also alleged that Ms. Stevenson used verbally abusive language. The tour determined no disciplinary action was warranted.''</p>
        <p>McGuire said that no proof could be found of a racial slur directed at Alexandra Stevenson by Amelie Cocheteux. Tour officials found no witnesses to substantiate the allegation of the bumping in the locker room.</p>
        <p>Today, Damir Dokic spun out of control. About 20 minutes after Jelena Dokic defeated Gala-Leone Garcia on Court 5, he was seen walking unsteadily through the grounds, waving the flag of St. George. As he entered the third floor of the press center, witnesses heard him ranting ''the Queen's side of the country is beautiful, the other side is fascist.''</p>
        <p>He also began criticizing the WTA for its treatment of his daughter, who was fined for being four hours late for an interview at the Australian Open. Mark Saggers, a sports reporter for Britain's Sky Sports, said that Dokic smashed his cell phone into three pieces after that. A police officer led Dokic away. Saggers gave a statement to the police, but said he would not press charges. Inspector Andrew Freestone of the Metropolitan Police Service said that Dokic came to the police room voluntarily,  that the Dokic family chose to leave the grounds and that no further action would be taken.</p>
        <p>At a tune-up for Wimbledon in Birmingham last June, Dokic began shouting at spectators during his daughter's match and was ejected. Later, he was picked up by the police when he was spotted lying in the middle of a road. They said he was cautioned for drunken and disorderly behavior and released without being charged.</p>
        <p>Today, Damir Dokic's outburst coincided with a WTA statement concerning a new policy to help eliminate distractions created by parents, friends and coaches. The players' council voted to restrict access to locker rooms at all tour events to players only. Alexandra Stevenson said she believed the rule was ''silly'' and that it was aimed at her mother and the mother of Martina Hingis. The WTA denied that the rule was directed specifically at mothers.</p>
        <p>''I think the rule is fair,'' said Chris Evert, who is at Wimbledon as an analyst for NBC. ''Players need a place to be alone.''</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
