<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fight Over Cuban Boy Leaves Scars in Miami</title>
    <meta content="Y30MIA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cuban-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Custody and Support</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Miami (Fla)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bragg, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzalez, Elian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzalez, Juan Miguel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cuban-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Custody and Support</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4D81639F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1203" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fight Over Cuban Boy Leaves Scars in Miami</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK BRAGG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bragg, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, June 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Emotional battle over Elian Gonzalez has united Miami's exile community but has also widened division with other Miamians and cost Cuban-Americans prestige and credibility in eyes of much of nation; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>She was 19 when she came here from Colombia 43 years ago, but even working with a mop in her hand, Maria Hernandez believed she had found paradise. Then Elian Gonzalez came, and in the seven months of speeches, marches and conflict that followed, her Miami changed.</p>
        <p>She was driving to work recently when a pickup flying American flags pulled up beside her. ''I looked over, in that way people glance over at each other at stoplights,'' said Mrs. Hernandez, who now owns a cleaning service.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>She was 19 when she came here from Colombia 43 years ago, but even working with a mop in her hand, Maria Hernandez believed she had found paradise. Then Elian Gonzalez came, and in the seven months of speeches, marches and conflict that followed, her Miami changed.</p>
        <p>She was driving to work recently when a pickup flying American flags pulled up beside her. ''I looked over, in that way people glance over at each other at stoplights,'' said Mrs. Hernandez, who now owns a cleaning service.</p>
        <p>The man in the truck rolled down a window and made an obscene gesture at her, because he thought she was Cuban-American, she believes. She was not flying the American flag upside-down, the way angry Cuban-Americans had, in protest. She was just going to work.</p>
        <p>''He looked at me with these mean eyes,'' she said, and she knew her paradise was gone.</p>
        <p>''I went to Eckerd's to buy some things, and two cashiers were fighting about Elian right in front of their customers,'' said Ms. Hernandez, who is married to a Cuban-American and wanted Elian to stay here.</p>
        <p>But the cost has been high. ''This is not the city I grew to love. I have neighbors who do not speak to each other. People's personalities have completely changed. I never knew there was so much hate in this city.''</p>
        <p>Elian -- the battle to keep him, the armed federal raid that took him from Miami, and the courtroom decisions that sent him home to Cuba -- widened racial and ethnic divisions that are part of this city's history.</p>
        <p>It is perhaps the saddest legacy of Elian, say experts on Cuban exile history, immigration and international politics, but it is hardly the only one.</p>
        <p>The fight to keep Elian in the United States became an all-or-nothing battle for many Cuban-Americans, the dominant culture in Miami, and it has cost them prestige and power. It has changed the way that others around the country see them and their cause, say experts on the community, and may even lead to a loosening of American relations with  President Fidel Castro.</p>
        <p>''It was not handled intelligently,'' said Lisandro Perez, director of the Cuban Research Institute at Florida International University. ''It was driven by emotions and passions, and you don't act intelligently when you are driven by emotions and passions.''</p>
        <p>But Cuban-American leaders said the fight was necessary, and moral. And while it may have colored the way people view them, it also drew younger people to an old cause.</p>
        <p>''It has united the exile community,'' said Jose Basulto, the president of Brothers to the Rescue, a group of Cuban-American pilots who search the Florida Straits for rafters.</p>
        <p>As for its cost, Mr. Basulto said, ''I could care less what the American people think about the Cuban exile community.''</p>
        <p>But it does matter, political experts said.</p>
        <p>The Elian experience ''has weakened the Cuban-American position'' in many ways, Mr. Perez said. ''The anti-embargo position has been strengthened and it's not because Americans suddenly realized Fidel Castro is a good guy. It's because the Elian case has made Cuban-Americans lose a lot of credibility.''</p>
        <p>As most of the nation seemed to believe that a 6-year-old boy should be with his father, and the courts said that he should, too, Cuban-Americans could not see beyond their hatred of Mr. Castro, political and immigration experts say.</p>
        <p>''This became a bizarre experience where family, flag and police -- all parts of the Republican trinity -- were attacked by Cuban-Americans,'' said David Abraham, a professor of immigration law at the University of Miami. ''There was the firing of the police chief because he kept public order, and the desecration of the flag, and it was very disconcerting to middle Americans.''</p>
        <p>In Miami, it has ruined friendships and brought a strained politeness to relationships.</p>
        <p>For years, Ann-Sofi Truby and a Cuban-American who does maintenance at her house in South Miami had talked, ''about our families, different things,'' said Ms. Truby, who has lived here nearly 30 years.</p>
        <p>They stopped talking during the Elian situation.</p>
        <p>''I would stay inside while he was here,'' she said, because talk would end in argument.</p>
        <p>In the past several months, Ms. Truby, who is in her 60's, bought an American flag. She waved it from her Volvo whenever she saw people demonstrating for Elian's remaining here.</p>
        <p>No apologies are being offered on either side.</p>
        <p>''All of us should feel extremely satisfied,'' said Ninoska Perez, a spokeswoman for the Cuban American National Foundation, by far the most powerful of the exile groups.</p>
        <p>''Castro had to wait until the judicial process came to an end'' to  claim Elian, Ms. Perez said. ''For someone who has not respected any laws during the last 41 years, that should be a loss.''</p>
        <p>But the way the Cuban-American power structure conducted itself left many in Miami feeling alienated.</p>
        <p>Mayor Alex Penelas of Miami-Dade County and Mayor Joe Carollo of Miami made it clear that they sided with Cuban-Americans against the federal government, drawing a backlash from around the country. Then, Mr. Carollo fired his city manager and forced the resignation of his police chief -- both non-Cuban whites -- and Cuban-Americans filled both posts.</p>
        <p>''The Cuban exiles have shown such arrogance,'' said Garth Reeves, the publisher emeritus of the city's black newspaper, The Miami Times. ''They're saying, 'This is our town now, and, damn it, we run it. We make the decisions' '' to the exclusion of everyone else.</p>
        <p>To Mr. Reeves, and to many other black Miamians, Cuban-Americans are a pampered minority that became a pampered majority, and now -- at the first major setback for them in recent history -- they denigrate the country that gave them a haven.</p>
        <p>Gov. Jeb Bush, a Republican who has enjoyed the support of Cuban-Americans in Miami, blamed the media for what he called a misunderstanding of the situation.</p>
        <p>''I think it's damaged -- incorrectly so -- the nature of Cuban-Americans in Miami,'' Governor Bush said. ''It breaks my heart to see the national press depict people who have been lovers of freedom the way that this has all played out.''</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Bush spoke, Cuban-Americans here continued to vent their anger at a government that they feel has betrayed them, at best, and, at worst, is in league with Mr. Castro.</p>
        <p>''I am never going to vote again,'' said Magaly Lima, 58, who came to Miami 38 years ago.</p>
        <p>The long-term impact may be economic. Social instability, economics experts said, seldom leads to a strong economy.</p>
        <p>''These recent events have made Miami less attractive,'' said Michael Connolly, chairman of the economics department at the University of Miami School of Business. ''People are moving away if they live here and aren't coming down here if they don't.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
