<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police Take Rocker Out to Ballgame</title>
    <meta content="30ROCK$15" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211478"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rocker, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Jayson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E2DE1739F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police Take Rocker Out to Ballgame</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blair, Jayson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City police and Mets management take precautions to prevent outbursts against Atlanta Braves pitcher John Rocker, who angered some New Yorkers with his comments about various minority groups; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Rocker walked out of a side entrance of the Atlanta Braves' midtown hotel yesterday afternoon and was quickly escorted into an unmarked police van that would take him first to the players association headquarters and later to Shea Stadium. So began the pitcher's first day in the city he so notoriously insulted in a magazine article last December, a day that ended without any ugly incidents and with Rocker contributing to the Braves' 6-4 victory over the Mets.</p>
        <p>The use of the police van was one of dozens of measures that New York police officials and Mets management took yesterday in the hopes of keeping Rocker's presence from leading to any incidents outside the stadium or in it. Police officers were stationed outside the Braves' hotel, the Grand Hyatt, on East 42nd Street, from the moment the Braves arrived in a bus from the airport early yesterday morning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Rocker walked out of a side entrance of the Atlanta Braves' midtown hotel yesterday afternoon and was quickly escorted into an unmarked police van that would take him first to the players association headquarters and later to Shea Stadium. So began the pitcher's first day in the city he so notoriously insulted in a magazine article last December, a day that ended without any ugly incidents and with Rocker contributing to the Braves' 6-4 victory over the Mets.</p>
        <p>The use of the police van was one of dozens of measures that New York police officials and Mets management took yesterday in the hopes of keeping Rocker's presence from leading to any incidents outside the stadium or in it. Police officers were stationed outside the Braves' hotel, the Grand Hyatt, on East 42nd Street, from the moment the Braves arrived in a bus from the airport early yesterday morning.</p>
        <p>They were part of a contingent of more than 700 officers deployed at the team hotel, along the Flushing subway line and at Shea Stadium because of concerns about Rocker's safety, New York officials said. City officials were relieved on Wednesday when baseball officials sent assurances that Rocker would back down from his vow to ride the No. 7 train -- the one Rocker had singled out for verbal abuse in Sports Illustrated in December -- to last night's game against the Mets. But those assurances did not mute the police presence.</p>
        <p>The department's bomb squad arrived at Shea about 2:30 p.m., followed by police officers carrying bags with sharp-shooting rifles. Officers on horseback were in the stadium's parking lot, while others in plainclothes mingled around the stadium. A unit of officers with video cameras took positions in case of mayhem. It seemed as if the Police Department was preparing for the arrival of the president, and not the presence of a 25-year-old reliever who has alienated many of his teammates with the uproar he has created with his derogatory comments toward gays and immigrants and just about anyone not like Rocker.</p>
        <p>The heavy police presence seemed to work. Rocker was booed when he first came on the field before the game and again when the Mets played a videotape, on the scoreboard, of an apologetic statement he made at a brief press gathering about 50 minutes before the game. But there were no ugly incidents -- before the game or during it. Rocker himself took part in the Braves' pregame warm-up on the field and even autographed a few baseballs. Some insults were hurled his way, but nothing more. By 8 p.m., an hour into the game, the police had sent 100 officers home.</p>
        <p>Still, as the game proceeded, the police made sure their presence was known. Between half-innings, about eight police officers stood on each foul line, facing the crowd. Police officers were visible in the back of the newly barricaded visitors' bullpen, where Rocker was situated, and in the left-field bleachers next to the bullpen. There were fears the bullpen would be bombarded with objects, but peace generally prevailed.</p>
        <p>And finally, in the eighth inning, Rocker entered the game, with some objects being thrown his way, but none hitting him. Amid derisive chants, he proceeded to strike out Robin Ventura and retire Todd Zeile and Jay Payton on ground balls. He walked off the field with his head up, seeming to fight the urge to flash the smirk that was so familiar when he clashed with Mets fans in last year's postseason.</p>
        <p>During his pregame statement, Rocker seemed to make an effort to be humble, flashed a grin or two, said that most New Yorkers were ''extremely charismatic, although a bit spirited'' and apologized several times for all the negative remarks he has made. Braves officials said that Rocker had written the statement himself, scribbling it on a piece of paper in his hotel room at 2 a.m.</p>
        <p>Rocker spent the early part of his day in the hotel. About 12:30 p.m. he took an unmarked police van to the players' union headquarters. Hours later, he returned to the hotel, and about 4:30 p.m. -- back in the van -- he arrived at Shea. Rocker is being shadowed by an Atlanta police lieutenant, and the police want to limit his itinerary while he is here.</p>
        <p>Whether they are successful remains to be seen. Before the game, several dozen fans took part in an anti-Rocker rally outside Shea, but hundreds of other fans walked right past, with any number saying the whole Rocker situation had been blown out of proportion. After the game, the police reported four arrests, with only one directly related to Rocker's presence. Bruce A. Barnett, 31, of Hicksville, N.Y., was charged with throwing a beer bottle at the Braves' bullpen while Rocker was stretching during the seventh inning.</p>
        <p>However, the police also said that 63 people were issued summonses for having open containers of alcohol outside the stadium, a reflection of the desire of the police to keep things under control. They hope to do so three more times.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
