<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Davenport Survives and Sampras Gears Up</title>
    <meta content="30TENN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Alexandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dokic, Jelena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Agassi, Andre</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Serna, Magui</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pierce, Mary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davenport, Lindsay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Likhovtseva, Yelena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sampras, Pete</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE6DF1739F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1170" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Davenport Survives and Sampras Gears Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>WIMBLEDON, England, June 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Various mishaps of day at Wimbledon tournament described; photos of Andre Agassi slipping on rain-soaked court and Mary Pierce lamenting her play during loss to Magui Serna; day also sees father of Jelena Dokic hustled away by policeman for unruly behavior and Alexandra Stevenson accusing fellow player of racial slur; Pete Sampras is diagnosed with acute tendinitis in leg; Lindsay Davenport slips by Yelena Likhovtseva (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At least Pete Sampras was safe. With his sore left shin packed like a champagne bottle in ice, he spent his off day on the schedule healing in a villa well outside the vine-covered walls of the All England Club.</p>
        <p>Inside, chaos was exploding with the rapid-fire of popcorn. The father of Jelena Dokic was being hustled away by a policeman for unruly behavior. Alexandra Stevenson was starting a firestorm after accusing a fellow player of hurling a racial slur at her during a recent tournament. The French Open champion Mary Pierce's powerful game was short-circuiting during a surprise second-round exit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At least Pete Sampras was safe. With his sore left shin packed like a champagne bottle in ice, he spent his off day on the schedule healing in a villa well outside the vine-covered walls of the All England Club.</p>
        <p>Inside, chaos was exploding with the rapid-fire of popcorn. The father of Jelena Dokic was being hustled away by a policeman for unruly behavior. Alexandra Stevenson was starting a firestorm after accusing a fellow player of hurling a racial slur at her during a recent tournament. The French Open champion Mary Pierce's powerful game was short-circuiting during a surprise second-round exit.</p>
        <p>And on Center Court, as the parting distress signal of the day, Andre Agassi was throwing up his arms in anger when Referee Alan Mills waited until after Agassi slipped on the grass to suspend his intense match with Todd Martin because of rain. On Friday, the second-seeded Agassi will pick up his match ahead by two sets to one, but down a break after the first game of the fourth set.</p>
        <p>''Why did you wait for a fall?'' Agassi yelled at Mills. ''It's not right.''</p>
        <p>Agassi gathered his things in a huff, and stalked off the court to end a frantic fourth day of Wimbledon. It began with Sampras's latest malady. With his 28-year-old body already as tortured as a voodoo doll, the results of an M.R.I. test he underwent Wednesday night after his second-round victory were unveiled today: acute tendinitis in the lower left shin.</p>
        <p>Sampras, the top-seeded player, is expected to play his third-round match against 99th-ranked Justin Gimelstob on Friday. Over the next 10 days, if Sampras can grit his teeth through his half of the draw -- which is light on danger, with only No. 9 Thomas Enqvist remaining as a seeded player -- he would still have a shot at winning his 13th Grand Slam title and breaking the record he shares with Roy Emerson.</p>
        <p>''He is resilient, so it's a matter of doing the best he can,'' said Sampras's coach, Paul Annacone, who has watched Sampras endure back and leg problems through the last few years. ''He could sit around and say: 'Why me? Why has it been like this lately?' You just try to figure out what happened, and try to deal with it.</p>
        <p>''When he plays here, and he feels well, I think, historically, we've seen what happens. So it's a matter of trying to do it another way.''</p>
        <p>As a six-time winner at Wimbledon, Sampras will press on, using his serve as a peg leg to stand on. Sampras still has his trusty howitzer.</p>
        <p>But today proved that power players are vulnerable.</p>
        <p>With her ground strokes spraying the grass well outside the lines, the third-seeded Pierce could not find enough control on the big points to hold off 49th-ranked Magui Serna, losing by 7-6 (5), 7-6 (4) in her attempt at an encore to her French Open title.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't meant to be,'' said Pierce, who came cruising into Wimbledon with a 25-9 record this year. ''She played well, served great. There were a few chances -- not very many -- in the first set and the second set. It was just close. It just wasn't there all together for me today.''</p>
        <p>Out of sorts, Lindsay Davenport could sympathize. Still trying to find the compass to her swift strokes after a six-week absence with a back injury this spring, she gamely slipped by Yelena Likhovtseva, 3-6, 6-3, 6-3.</p>
        <p>It was a drop shot, of all weapons, that turned what looked like an upset into a relief. With Likhovtseva serving to go ahead, 4-0, in the third set, Davenport slipped in the drop shot. From there, Davenport ran off six straight games.</p>
        <p>''It's always tough when you have injuries,'' she said. ''You don't really think about things when you're playing well. All of a sudden when I was out for almost two months, your tennis just starts to hurt a little bit.</p>
        <p>''Finally, I loosened up a bit and started hitting out a little bit more, and thought I forced a few more errors. That gave me a little bit more confidence to keep going for some more shots. Obviously, she got a little nervous and started missing.''</p>
        <p>By avoiding the upset, Davenport ducked the mayhem today. After a boisterous romp around the grounds, Damir Dokic celebrated his daughter Jelena's second-round victory by popping off in the press center and smashing a reporter's cell phone. Two hours later, Stevenson's attempt to recreate her trip fantastic through Wimbledon last year -- during which she became the first woman qualifier to land in the semifinals -- ended with a 7-6 (6), 6-3 loss to Patricia Wartusch.</p>
        <p>''The good thing is my rookie year is over,'' said Stevenson, whose biological father was disclosed to be Julius Erving at Wimbledon last year. ''There was a lot of hazing going on.''</p>
        <p>Stevenson said one incident had occurred at a tournament last month when a French player, Amelie Cocheteux, referred to her with a racial slur on the court. When questioned about the accusation by a French reporter, Cocheteux denied making such a remark.</p>
        <p>Throughout the day, there were more barbs ricocheting around the grounds than volleys. Out of harm's way, Sampras was recovering quietly, icing his shin and taking anti-inflammatory drugs. In his absence, Annacone was left to confront the prickly issues concerning Sampras's increased fragility. The question of toughness was raised.</p>
        <p>''It's a subjective thing,'' Annacone said. ''I can tell you my body feels awful 90 percent of the time when I wake up in the morning. I played 10 years on the tour. I've had a herniated disk in my back. I've got all kinds of things. I don't know what he physically feels like.</p>
        <p>''But compared to certain people, his tolerance is very high. Probably compared to a football player, they're saying, 'What's the big deal?' I think everything is relative, but unfortunately for people like Pete, I think things like that tend to make a lot of news. But, yeah, if you give me five minutes, I could probably argue both sides.''</p>
        <p>On Friday, a strong return by Sampras could help bring peace to the argument -- and, perhaps, to the grounds of Wimbledon.</p>
        <p>MATCH POINTS</p>
        <p>Fifth-seeded YEVGENY KAFELNIKOV was upset by THOMAS JOHANSSON, 6-1, 7-6 (0), 6-4; and 15th-seeded MARAT SAFIN went down to MARTIN DAMM, 7-5, 7-6 (4), 6-3.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
