<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Modern Will Take Refuge In Queens, Starting in 2002</title>
    <meta content="30MOMA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211529"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Museum of Modern Art (NYC)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E6D61F30F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Modern Will Take Refuge In Queens, Starting in 2002</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Museum of Modern Art will close for renovations in spring 2002 and move to temporary exhibition space in Long Island City (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Museum of Modern Art will close its doors in the spring of 2002, in the thick of construction to expand its Midtown Manhattan campus, and move to an exhibition space in Long Island City, Queens, for a little over two years, the museum's director said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Until then, the Modern will continue to present exhibitions at its 53rd Street location, said the director, Glenn D. Lowry. The museum's film program will also remain in Midtown until spring 2002; the film department is looking for another screening location.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Museum of Modern Art will close its doors in the spring of 2002, in the thick of construction to expand its Midtown Manhattan campus, and move to an exhibition space in Long Island City, Queens, for a little over two years, the museum's director said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Until then, the Modern will continue to present exhibitions at its 53rd Street location, said the director, Glenn D. Lowry. The museum's film program will also remain in Midtown until spring 2002; the film department is looking for another screening location.</p>
        <p>The temporary museum, a 140,000-square-foot, two-story building formerly owned by Swingline, the maker of staplers and other office supplies, will house much of the museum's permanent collection and provide space for exhibitions, storage and offices. The Modern acquired the building at 45-20 33rd Street, off Queens Boulevard, last August as a study and storage center. It is near P.S. 1, the alternative art space that made an alliance with the Modern in February 1999.</p>
        <p>Michael Maltzan Architecture of Los Angeles has been selected to design the spaces of the Queens building, including the entrance and exhibition areas. Mr. Maltzan, who formerly worked for Frank O. Gehry, is designing an expansion of the Armand Hammer Museum of Art and Cultural Center in Los Angeles. Cooper, Robertson &amp; Partners, a New York firm, has been hired as executive architect for the overall project, including the building's eventual reconversion into offices, study center, workshops and storage space.</p>
        <p>The Modern's $650 million expansion, designed by Yoshio Taniguchi of Tokyo, will increase museum space to about 630,000 square feet from its current 378,330 square feet. The first phase, the demolition of the Dorset Hotel on West 54th Street, is to take place next month. In August the Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Sculpture Garden will close to the public and become a staging area. Construction is to begin next spring and continue through late 2004, the Modern's 75th-anniversary year, when all exhibitions are to return to Midtown. The Swingline property will then become a permanent art study and storage center.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
