<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From Supreme Court Opinions on Nebraska's Abortion Law</title>
    <meta content="Y30STE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211423"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE SUPREME COURT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nebraska</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, John Paul (Assoc Justice)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Connor, Sandra Day (Assoc Justice)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ginsburg, Ruth Bader (Assoc Justice)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rehnquist, William H (Chief Justice)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scalia, Antonin (Assoc Justice)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Anthony M (Assoc Justice)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Nebraska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nebraska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E6D61639F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="7305" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From Supreme Court Opinions on Nebraska's Abortion Law</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from opinions on Supreme Court abortion decision written by Justices John Paul Stevens, Sandra Day O'Connor, Ruth Bader Ginsburg, William H Rehnquist, Antonin Scalia and Anthony M Kennedy (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a Supreme Court decision on Wednesday overturning a Nebraska law dealing with abortion. The vote in the case, Stenberg v. Carhart was 5 to 4. With the continuation of a front-page article on Thursday, The Times published excerpts from the majority opinion by Justice Stephen G. Breyer and a dissent by Justice Clarence Thomas. But six other justices -- John Paul Stevens, Sanda Day O'Connor, Ruth Bader Ginsburg, William H. Rehnquist, Antonin Scalia and Anthony M. Kennedy -- also wrote opinions. The excerpts below provide a fuller range of views on the court on this case.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a Supreme Court decision on Wednesday overturning a Nebraska law dealing with abortion. The vote in the case, Stenberg v. Carhart was 5 to 4. With the continuation of a front-page article on Thursday, The Times published excerpts from the majority opinion by Justice Stephen G. Breyer and a dissent by Justice Clarence Thomas. But six other justices -- John Paul Stevens, Sanda Day O'Connor, Ruth Bader Ginsburg, William H. Rehnquist, Antonin Scalia and Anthony M. Kennedy -- also wrote opinions. The excerpts below provide a fuller range of views on the court on this case.</p>
        <p>FROM THE DECISION  By Justice Breyer</p>
        <p>We again consider the right to an abortion. We understand the controversial nature of the problem. Millions of Americans believe that life begins at conception and consequently that an abortion is akin to causing the death of an innocent child; they recoil at the thought of a law that would permit it. Other millions fear that a law that forbids abortion would condemn many American women to lives that lack dignity, depriving them of equal liberty and leading those with least resources to undergo illegal abortions with the attendant risks of death and suffering.</p>
        <p>Taking account of these virtually irreconcilable points of view, aware that constitutional law must govern a society whose different members sincerely hold directly opposing views, and considering the matter in light of the Constitution's guarantees of fundamental individual liberty, this court, in the course of a generation, has determined and then redetermined that the Constitution offers basic protection to the woman's right to choose. We shall not revisit those legal principles. Rather, we apply them to the circumstances of this case.</p>
        <p>Three established principles determine the issue before us. We shall set them forth in the language of the joint opinion in ''Casey.''</p>
        <p>First, before ''viability the woman has a right to choose to terminate her pregnancy.''</p>
        <p>Second, ''a law designed to further the state's interest in fetal life which imposes an undue burden on the woman's decision before fetal viability'' is unconstitutional. An ''undue burden is shorthand for the conclusion that a state regulation has the purpose or effect of placing a substantial obstacle in the path of a woman seeking an abortion of a nonviable fetus.''</p>
        <p>Third, ''subsequent to viability, the state in promoting its interest in the potentiality of human life may, if it chooses, regulate, and even proscribe, abortion except where it is necessary, in appropriate medical judgment, for the preservation of the life or health of the mother.''</p>
        <p>We apply these principles to a Nebraska law banning ''partial birth abortion.'' The statute reads as follows:</p>
        <p>''No partial birth abortion shall be performed in this state, unless such procedure is necessary to save the life of the mother whose life is endangered by a physical disorder, physical illness, or physical injury, including a life-endangering physical condition caused by or arising from the pregnancy itself.''</p>
        <p>The statute defines ''partial birth abortion'' as: ''an abortion procedure in which the person performing the abortion partially delivers vaginally a living unborn child before killing the unborn child and completing the delivery.''</p>
        <p>It further defines ''partially delivers vaginally a living unborn child before killing the unborn child'' to mean: ''deliberately and intentionally delivering into the vagina a living unborn child, or a substantial portion thereof, for the purpose of performing a procedure that the person performing such procedure knows will kill the unborn child and does kill the unborn child.''</p>
        <p>The law classifies violation of the statute as a ''Class III felony'' carrying a prison term of up to 20 years, and a fine of up to $25,000. It also provides for the automatic revocation of a doctor's license to practice medicine in Nebraska. . . .</p>
        <p>The question before us is whether Nebraska's statute, making criminal the performance of a ''partial birth abortion,'' violates the federal Constitution, as interpreted in Planned Parenthood of Southeastern Pa. v. Casey (1992) and Roe v. Wade (1973). We conclude that it does for at least two independent reasons. First, the law lacks any exception ''for the preservation of the  health of the mother.'' Second, it ''imposes an undue burden on a woman's ability'' to choose a D&amp;E [dilation and evacuation] abortion, thereby unduly burdening the right to choose abortion itself. We shall discuss each of these reasons in turn.</p>
        <p>The Casey joint opinion reiterated what the court held in Roe; that ''subsequent to viability, the state in promoting its interest in the potentiality of human life may, if it chooses, regulate, and even proscribe, abortion except where it is necessary, in appropriate medical judgment, for the preservation of the life or health of the mother.''</p>
        <p>The fact that Nebraska's law applies both pre- and postviability aggravates the constitutional problem presented. The state's interest in regulating abortion previability is considerably weaker than postviability.  Since the law requires a health exception in order to validate even a postviability abortion regulation, it at a minimum requires the same in respect to previability regulation.</p>
        <p>The quoted standard also depends on the state regulations ''promoting [the state's] interest in the potentiality of human life.''  The Nebraska law, of course, does not directly further an interest ''in the potentiality of human life'' by saving the fetus in question from destruction, as it regulates only a method of performing abortion. Nebraska describes its interests differently. It says the law ''shows concern for the life of the unborn,'' ''prevents cruelty to partially born children,'' and ''preserves the integrity of the medical profession.'' But we cannot see how the interest-related differences could make any difference to the question at hand, namely, the application of the ''health'' requirement.</p>
        <p>Consequently, the governing standard requires an exception ''where it is necessary, in appropriate medical judgment for the preservation of the life or health of the mother,'' for this court has made clear that a state may promote but not endanger a woman's health when it regulates the methods of abortion: Thornburgh v. American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists,  Colautti v. Franklin, Danforth, Doe v. Bolton.</p>
        <p>Justice Thomas says that the cases just cited limit this principle to situations where the pregnancy itself creates a threat to health. He is wrong. The cited cases, reaffirmed in Casey, recognize that a state cannot subject women's health to significant risks both in that context, and also where state regulations force women to use riskier methods of abortion. Our cases have repeatedly invalidated statutes that in the process of regulating the methods of abortion, imposed significant health risks. They make clear that a risk to a women's health is the same whether it happens to arise from regulating a particular method of abortion, or from barring abortion entirely. Our holding does not go beyond those cases, as ratified in Casey.</p>
        <p>Nebraska responds that the law does not require a health exception unless there is a need for such an exception. And here there is no such need, it says. It argues that ''safe alternatives remain available'' and ''a ban on partial-birth abortion/D&amp;X [dilation and extraction] would create no risk to the health of women.'' The problem for Nebraska is that the parties strongly contested this factual question in the trial court below; and the findings and evidence support Dr. Carhart. The state fails to demonstrate that banning D&amp;X without a health exception may not create significant health risks for women, because the record shows that significant medical authority supports the proposition that in some circumstances, D&amp;X would be the safest procedure.</p>
        <p>We shall reiterate in summary form the relevant findings and evidence. On the basis of medical testimony the District Court concluded that Carhart's D&amp;X procedure is  . . . safer than the D&amp;E and other abortion procedures used during the relevant gestational period in the 10 to 20 cases a year that present to Dr. Carhart. It found that the D&amp;X procedure permits the fetus to pass through the cervix with a minimum of instrumentation. It thereby reduces operating time, blood loss and risk of infection; reduces complications from bony fragments; reduces instrument-inflicted damage to the uterus and cervix; prevents the most common causes of maternal mortality (DIC and amniotic fluid embolus); and eliminates the possibility of 'horrible complications' arising from retained fetal parts.'' . . .</p>
        <p>Nebraska, along with supporting amici, replies that these findings are irrelevant, wrong, or applicable only in a tiny number of instances. It says (1) that the D&amp;X procedure is little-used, (2) by only a handful of doctors. It argues (3) that D&amp;E and labor induction are at all times safe alternative procedures. It refers to the testimony of petitioners medical expert, who testified (4) that the ban would not increase a woman's risk of several rare abortion complications (disseminated intravascular coagulopathy and amniotic fluid embolus).</p>
        <p>The Association of American Physicians and Surgeons et al., amici supporting Nebraska, argue (5) that elements of the D&amp;X procedure may create special risks, including cervical incompetence caused by overdilitation, injury caused by conversion of the fetal presentation, and dangers arising from the blind use of instrumentation to pierce the fetal skull while lodged in the birth canal. Nebraska further emphasizes (6) that there are no medical studies ''establishing the safety of the partial-birth abortion/D&amp;X procedure,'' and ''no medical studies comparing the safety of partial-birth abortion/D&amp;X to other abortion procedures. It points to (7) an American Medical Association policy statement that there does not appear to be any identified situation in which intact D&amp;X is the only appropriate procedure to induce abortion. And it points out (8) that the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists qualified its statement that D&amp;X ''may be the best or most appropriate procedure,'' by adding that the panel ''could identify no circumstances under which the [D&amp;X] procedure would be the only option to save the life or preserve the health of the woman.''</p>
        <p>We find these eight arguments insufficient to demonstrate that Nebraska's law needs no health exception. For one thing, certain of the arguments are beside the point. The D&amp;X procedure's relative rarity (argument 1) is not highly relevant. The D&amp;X is an infrequently used abortion procedure; but the health exception question is whether protecting women's health requires an exception for those infrequent occasions. A rarely used treatment might be necessary to treat a rarely occurring disease that could strike anyone; the state cannot prohibit a person from obtaining treatment simply by pointing out that most people do not need it. Nor can we know whether the fact that only a handful of doctors use the procedure (argument 2) reflects the comparative rarity of late second term abortions, the procedure's recent development, the controversy surrounding it, or, as Nebraska suggests, the procedure's lack of utility.</p>
        <p>For another thing, the record responds to Nebraska's (and amici's) medically based arguments. In respect to argument 3, for example, the District Court agreed that alternatives, such as D&amp;E and induced labor, are safe but found that the D&amp;X method was significantly safer in certain circumstances. In respect to argument 4, the District Court simply relied on different expert testimony stating that another advantage of the Intact D&amp;E is that it eliminates the risk of embolism of cerebral tissue into the woman's blood stream.</p>
        <p>In response to amici's argument (5), the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, in its own amici brief, denies that D&amp;X generally poses risks greater than the alternatives. It says that the suggested alternative procedures involve similar or greater risks of cervical and uterine injury, for D&amp;E procedures, involve similar amounts of dilitation and of course childbirth involves even greater cervical dilitation. The College points out that Dr. Carhart does not reposition the fetus, thereby avoiding any risks stemming from conversion to breech presentation, and that, as compared with D&amp;X, D&amp;E involves the same, if not greater, blind use of sharp instruments in the uterine cavity.</p>
        <p>We do not quarrel with Nebraska's argument (6), for Nebraska is right. There are no general medical studies documenting comparative safety. Neither do we deny the import of the American Medical Associations statement (argument 7) even though the state does omit the remainder of that statement: The A.M.A. recommends that the procedure not be used unless alternative procedures pose materially greater risk to the woman.</p>
        <p>We cannot, however, read the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists panel's qualification (that it could not identify a circumstance where D&amp;X was the only life- or health-preserving option) as if, according to Nebraska's argument, (8) it denied the potential health-related need for D&amp;X. That is because the College writes the following in its amici brief:</p>
        <p>''Depending on the physician's skill and experience, the D&amp;X procedure can be the most appropriate abortion procedure for some women in some circumstances. D&amp;X presents a variety of potential safety advantages over other abortion procedures used during the same gestational period. Compared to D&amp;E's involving dismemberment, D&amp;X involves less risk of uterine perforation or cervical laceration because it requires the physician to make fewer passes into the uterus with sharp instruments and reduces the presence of sharp fetal bone fragments that can injure the uterus and cervix.'' . . .</p>
        <p>Using this law, some present prosecutors and future attorneys general may choose to pursue physicians who use D&amp;E procedures, the most commonly used method for performing previability second trimester abortions. All those who perform abortion procedures using that method must fear prosecution, conviction and imprisonment. The result is an undue burden upon a woman's right to make an abortion decision.  We must consequently find the statute unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>JUSTICE O'CONNOR,  Concurring</p>
        <p>The issue of abortion is one of the most contentious and controversial in contemporary American society. It presents extraordinarily difficult questions that, as the court recognizes, involve ''virtually irreconcilable points of view.'' The specific question we face today is whether Nebraska's attempt to proscribe a particular method of abortion, commonly known as ''partial-birth abortion,'' is constitutional. For the reasons stated in the court's opinion, I agree that Nebraska's statute cannot be reconciled with our decision in Planned Parenthood of Southeastern Pa. v. Casey, and is therefore unconstitutional. I write separately to emphasize the following points.</p>
        <p>First, the Nebraska statute is inconsistent with Casey because it lacks an exception for those instances when the banned procedure is necessary to preserve the health of the mother. Importantly, Nebraska's own statutory scheme underscores this constitutional infirmity. As we held in Casey, prior to viability ''the woman has a right to choose to terminate her pregnancy.'' After the fetus has become viable, states may substantially regulate and even proscribe abortion, but any such regulation or proscription must contain an exception for instances ''where it is necessary, in appropriate medical judgment, for the preservation of the life or health of the mother.'' Nebraska has recognized this constitutional limitation in its separate statute generally proscribing postviability abortions. That statute provides that ''no abortion shall be performed after the time at which, in the sound medical judgment of the attending physician, the unborn child clearly appears to have reached viability, except when necessary to preserve the life or health of the mother.''  Because even a postviability proscription of abortion would be invalid absent a health exception, Nebraska's ban on previability partial-birth abortions, under the circumstances presented here, must include a health exception as well, since the state's interest in regulating abortions before viability is ''considerably weaker'' than after viability. The statute at issue here, however, only excepts those procedures ''necessary to save the life of the mother whose life is endangered by a physical disorder, physical illness, or physical injury.'' This lack of a health exception necessarily renders the statute unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>Contrary to the assertions of Justice Kennedy and Justice Thomas, the need for a health exception does not arise from ''the individual views of Dr. Carhart and his supporters.'' Rather, as the majority explains, where, as here, ''a significant body of medical opinion believes a procedure may bring with it greater safety for some patients and explains the medical reasons supporting that view,'' then Nebraska cannot say that the procedure will not, in some circumstances, be ''necessary to preserve the life or health of the mother.'' Accordingly, our precedent requires that the statute include a health exception.</p>
        <p>Second, Nebraska's statute is unconstitutional on the alternative and independent ground that it imposes an undue burden on a woman's right to choose to terminate her pregnancy before viability. Nebraska's ban covers not just the dilation and extraction (D&amp;X) procedure, but also the dilation an evacuation (D&amp;E) procedure, ''the most commonly used method for performing previability second trimester abortions.'' The statute defines the banned procedure as ''deliberately and intentionally delivering into the vagina a living unborn child, or a substantial portion thereof, for the purpose of performing a procedure that the person performing such procedure knows will kill the unborn child and does kill the unborn child.'' As the court explains, the medical evidence establishes that the D&amp;E procedure is included in this definition. Thus, it is not possible to interpret the statute's language as applying only to the D&amp;X procedure. We have stated on several occasions that we ordinarily defer to the construction of a state statute given it by the lower federal courts unless such a construction amounts to plain error. Such deference is not unique to the abortion context, but applies generally to state statutes addressing all areas of the law. Given this construction, the statute is impermissible. Indeed, Nebraska conceded at oral argument that ''the state could not prohibit the D&amp;E procedure.'' By proscribing the most commonly used method for previability second trimester abortions, the statute creates a ''substantial obstacle to a woman seeking an abortion,'' and therefore imposes an undue burden on a woman's right to terminate her pregnancy prior to viability.</p>
        <p>It is important to note that, unlike Nebraska, some other states have enacted statutes more narrowly tailored to proscribing the D&amp;X procedure alone. Some of those statutes have done so by specifically excluding from their coverage the most common methods of abortion, such as the D&amp;E and vacuum aspiration procedures. For example, the Kansas statute states that its ban does not apply to the ''(A) suction curettage abortion procedure; (B) suction aspiration abortion procedure; or (C) dilation and evacuation abortion procedure involving dismemberment of the fetus prior to removal from the body of the pregnant woman. The Utah statute similarly provides that its prohibition ''does not include the dilation and evacuation procedure involving dismemberment prior to removal, the suction curettage procedure, or the suction aspiration procedure for abortion.'' Likewise, the Montana statute defines the banned procedure as one in which ''(A) the living fetus is removed intact from the uterus until only the head remains in the uterus; (B) all or a part of the intracranial contents of the fetus are evacuated; (C) the head of the fetus is compressed; and (D) following fetal demise, the fetus is removed from the birth canal.'' By restricting their prohibitions to the D&amp;X procedure exclusively, the Kansas, Utah, and Montana statutes avoid a principal defect of the Nebraska law.</p>
        <p>If Nebraska's statute limited its application to the D&amp;X procedure and included an exception for the life and health of the mother, the question presented would be quite different than the one we face today. As we held in Casey, an abortion regulation constitutes an undue burden if it ''has the purpose or effect of placing a substantial obstacle in the path of a woman seeking an abortion of a nonviable fetus.'' If there were adequate alternative methods for a woman safely to obtain an abortion before viability, it is unlikely that prohibiting the D&amp;X procedure alone would ''amount in practical terms to a substantial obstacle to a woman seeking an abortion.'' Thus, a ban on partial-birth abortion that only proscribed the D&amp;X method of abortion and that included an exception to preserve the life and health of the mother would be constitutional in my view.</p>
        <p>Nebraska's statute, however, does not meet these criteria. It contains no exception for when the procedure, in appropriate medical judgment, is necessary to preserve the health of the mother; and it proscribes not only the D&amp;X procedure but also the D&amp;E procedure, the most commonly used method for previability second trimester abortions, thus making it an undue burden on a woman's right to terminate her pregnancy. For these reasons, I agree with the court that Nebraska's law is unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>JUSTICE STEVENS, CONCURRING,  With Justice Ginsburg</p>
        <p>Although much ink is spilled today describing the gruesome nature of late-term abortion procedures, that rhetoric does not provide me a reason to believe that the procedure Nebraska here claims it seeks to ban is more brutal, more gruesome, or less respectful of ''potential life'' than the equally gruesome procedure Nebraska claims it still allows. Justice Ginsburg and Judge Posner have, I believe, correctly diagnosed the underlying reason for the enactment of this legislation a reason that also explains much of the court's rhetoric directed at an objective that extends well beyond the narrow issue that this case presents. The rhetoric is almost, but not quite, loud enough to obscure the quiet fact that during the past 27 years, the central holding of Roe v. Wade,  has been endorsed by all but 4 of the 17 Justices who have addressed the issue. That holding that the word ''liberty'' in the Fourteenth Amendment includes a woman's right to make this difficult and extremely personal decision makes it impossible for me to understand how a state has any legitimate interest in requiring a doctor to follow any procedure other than the one that he or she reasonably believes will best protect the woman in her exercise of this constitutional liberty. But one need not even approach this view today to conclude that Nebraska's law must fall. For the notion that either of these two equally gruesome procedures performed at this late stage of gestation is more akin to infanticide than the other, or that the state furthers any legitimate interest by banning one but not the other, is simply irrational.</p>
        <p>FROM A DISSENT  By Justice Thomas  With Justice Scalia  And Chief Justice Rehnquist</p>
        <p>In 1973, this court struck down an act of the Texas Legislature that had been in effect since 1857, thereby rendering unconstitutional abortion statutes in dozens of states. As some of my colleagues on the court, past and present, ably demonstrated, that decision was grievously wrong . . .</p>
        <p>Abortion is a unique act, in which a woman's exercise of control over her own body ends, depending on one's view, human life or potential human life. Nothing in our federal Constitution deprives the people of this country of the right to determine whether the consequences of abortion to the fetus and to society outweigh the burden of an unwanted pregnancy on the mother. Although a state may permit abortion, nothing in the Constitution dictates that a state must do so. . . .</p>
        <p>In the years following Roe, this court applied, and, worse, extended, that decision to strike down numerous state statutes that purportedly threatened a woman's ability to obtain an abortion. The court voided parental consent laws, legislation requiring that second-trimester abortions take place in hospitals, and even a requirement that both parents of a minor be notified before their child has an abortion. It was only a slight exaggeration when this court described, in 1976, a right to abortion ''without interference from the state.'' The court's expansive application of Roe in this period, even more than Roe itself, was fairly described as the ''unrestrained imposition of [the court's] own, extraconstitutional value preferences'' on the American people.</p>
        <p>It appeared that this era of court-mandated abortion on demand had come to an end, first with our decision in Webster v. Reproductive Health Services, and then finally (or so we were told) in our decision in Planned Parenthood of Southeastern Pa. v. Casey. Although in Casey the separate opinions of the chief justice and Justice Scalia urging the court to overrule Roe did not command a majority, seven members of that court, including six members sitting today, acknowledged that states have a legitimate role in regulating abortion and recognized the states' interest in respecting fetal life at all stages of development. The joint opinion authored by Justices O'Connor, Kennedy and Souter concluded that prior case law ''went too far'' in ''undervaluing the state's interest in potential life'' and in ''striking down some abortion regulations which in no real sense deprived women of the ultimate decision.'' Roe and subsequent cases, according to the joint opinion, had wrongly ''treated all governmental attempts to influence a woman's decision on behalf of the potential life within her as unwarranted,'' a treatment that was ''incompatible with the recognition that there is a substantial state interest in potential life throughout pregnancy.'' Accordingly, the joint opinion held that so long as state regulation of abortion furthers legitimate interests, that is, interests not designed to strike at the right itself, the regulation is invalid only if it imposes an undue burden on a woman's ability to obtain an abortion, meaning that it places a substantial obstacle in the woman's path. . . .</p>
        <p>The standard set forth in the Casey joint opinion has no historical or doctrinal pedigree. The standard is a product of its authors' own philosophical views about abortion, and it should go without saying that it has no origins in or relationship to the Constitution and is, consequently, as illegitimate as the standard it purported to replace. Even assuming, however, as I will for the remainder of this dissent, that Casey's fabricated undue-burden standard merits adherence (which it does not), today's decision is extraordinary. Today, the court inexplicably holds that the states cannot constitutionally prohibit a method of abortion that millions find hard to distinguish from infanticide and that the court hesitates even to describe. . . . In striking down this statute, which expresses a profound and legitimate respect for fetal life and which leaves unimpeded several other safe forms of abortion, the majority opinion gives the lie to the promise of Casey that regulations that do no more than ''express profound respect for the life of the unborn are permitted, if they are not a substantial obstacle to the woman's exercise of the right to choose'' whether or not to have an abortion. . . .</p>
        <p>In the almost 30 years since Roe, this court has never described the various methods of aborting a second- or third-trimester fetus. From reading the majority's sanitized description, one would think that this case involves state regulation of a widely accepted routine medical procedure. Nothing could be further from the truth. The most widely used method of abortion during this stage of pregnancy is so gruesome that its use can be traumatic even for the physicians and medical staff who perform it. And the particular procedure at issue in this case, ''partial birth abortion,'' so closely borders on infanticide that 30 states have attempted to ban it. . . .</p>
        <p>There is no question that the state of Nebraska has a valid interest, one not designed to strike at the right itself, in prohibiting partial birth abortion. Casey itself noted that states may ''express profound respect for the life of the unborn.'' States may, without a doubt, express this profound respect by prohibiting a procedure that approaches infanticide, and thereby dehumanizes the fetus and trivializes human life. The A.M.A. has recognized that this procedure is ''ethically different from other destructive abortion techniques because the fetus, normally 20 weeks or longer in gestation, is killed outside the womb.</p>
        <p>The ''partial birth'' gives the fetus an autonomy which separates it from the right of the woman to choose treatments for her own body. . . . The next question, therefore, is whether the Nebraska statute is unconstitutional because it does not contain an exception that would allow use of the procedure whenever ''necessary in appropriate medical judgment, for the preservation of the health of the mother.''</p>
        <p>In Roe and Casey, the court stated that the state may ''regulate, and even proscribe, abortion except where it is necessary, in appropriate medical judgment, for the preservation of the life or health of the mother.'' Casey said that a health exception must be available if ''continuing her pregnancy would constitute a threat'' to the woman. Under these cases, if a state seeks to prohibit abortion, even if only temporarily or under particular circumstances, as Casey says that it may, the state must make an exception for cases in which the life or health of the mother is endangered by continuing the pregnancy. These cases addressed only the situation in which a woman must obtain an abortion because of some threat to her health from continued pregnancy. But Roe and Casey say nothing at all about cases in which a physician considers one prohibited method of abortion to be preferable to permissible methods. Today's majority and Justice O'Connor twist Roe and Casey to apply to the situation in which a woman desires for whatever reason an abortion and wishes to obtain the abortion by some particular method.</p>
        <p>FROM A DISSENT  By Justice Kennedy With Chief Justice Rehnquist</p>
        <p>For close to two decades after Roe v. Wade, the court gave but slight weight to the interests of the separate states when their legislatures sought to address persisting concerns raised by the existence of a woman's right to elect an abortion in defined circumstances. When the court reaffirmed the essential holding of Roe, a central premise was that the states retain a critical and legitimate role in legislating on the subject of abortion, as limited by the woman's right the court restated and again guaranteed.  The political processes of the state are not to be foreclosed from enacting laws to promote the life of the unborn and to ensure respect for all human life and its potential. The state's constitutional authority is a vital means for citizens to address these grave and serious issues, as they must if we are to progress in knowledge and understanding and in the attainment of some degree of consensus.</p>
        <p>The court's decision today, in my submission, repudiates this understanding by invalidating a statute advancing critical state interests, even though the law denies no woman the right to choose an abortion and places no undue burden upon the right. The legislation is well within the state's competence to enact. Having concluded Nebraska's law survives the scrutiny dictated by a proper understanding of Casey, I dissent from the judgment invalidating it.</p>
        <p>The court's failure to accord any weight to Nebraska's interest in prohibiting partial-birth abortion is erroneous and undermines its discussion and holding. The court's approach in this regard is revealed by its description of the abortion methods at issue, which the court is correct to describe as clinically cold or callous. The majority views the procedures from the perspective of the abortionist, rather than from the perspective of a society shocked when confronted with a new method of ending human life. Words invoked by the majority, such as transcervical procedures, osmotic dilators,  instrumental disarticulation, and paracervical block, may be accurate and are to some extent necessary, but for citizens who seek to know why laws on this subject have been enacted across the nation, the words are insufficient. Repeated references to sources understandable only to a trained physician may obscure matters for persons not trained in medical terminology. Thus it seems necessary at the outset to set forth what may happen during an abortion.</p>
        <p>The person challenging Nebraska's law is Dr. Leroy Carhart, a physician. . .</p>
        <p>As described by Dr. Carhart, the D&amp;E procedure requires the abortionist to use instruments to grasp a portion (such as a foot or hand) of a developed and living fetus and drag the grasped portion out of the uterus into the vagina. Dr. Carhart uses the traction created by the opening between the uterus and vagina to dismember the fetus, tearing the grasped portion away from the remainder of the body. . . .</p>
        <p>The other procedure implicated today is called partial-birth abortion or the D&amp;X. The D&amp;X can be used, as a general matter, after 19 weeks' gestation because the fetus has become so developed that it may survive intact partial delivery from the uterus into the vagina. In the D&amp;X, the abortionist initiates the woman's natural delivery process by causing the cervix of the woman to be dilated, sometimes over a sequence of days. The fetus arms and legs are delivered outside the uterus while the fetus is alive; witnesses to the procedure report seeing the body of the fetus moving outside the woman's body. At this point, the abortion procedure has the appearance of a live birth. As stated by one group of physicians, as the physician manually performs breech extraction of the body of a live fetus, excepting the head, she continues in the apparent role of an obstetrician delivering a child. With only the head of the fetus remaining in utero, the abortionist tears open the skull. According to Dr. Martin Haskell, a leading proponent of the procedure, the appropriate instrument to be used at this stage of the abortion is a pair of scissors. . . . Of the two described procedures, Nebraska seeks only to ban the D&amp;X. In light of the description of the D&amp;X procedure, it should go without saying that Nebraska's ban on partial-birth abortion furthers purposes states are entitled to pursue. Dr. Carhart nevertheless maintains the state has no legitimate interest in forbidding the D&amp;X. As he interprets the controlling cases in this court, the only two interests the state may advance through regulation of abortion are in the health of the woman who is considering the procedure and in the life of the fetus she carries. The court, as I read its opinion, accedes to his views, misunderstanding Casey and the authorities it confirmed.</p>
        <p>Casey held that cases decided in the wake of Roe v. Wade had given [state interests] too little acknowledgment and implementation. The decision turned aside any contention that a person has the right to decide whether to have an abortion without interference from the state, and rejected a strict scrutiny standard of review as incompatible with the recognition that there is a substantial state interest in potential life throughout pregnancy. The very notion that the state has a substantial interest in potential life leads to the conclusion that not all regulations must be deemed unwarranted. We held it was inappropriate for the judicial branch to provide an exhaustive list of state interests implicated by abortion.</p>
        <p>Casey is premised on the states having an important constitutional role in defining their interests in the abortion debate. It is only with this principle in mind that Nebraska's interests can be given proper weight. The states brief describes its interests as including concern for the life of the unborn and for the partially-born, in preserving the integrity of the medical profession, and in erecting a barrier to infanticide. A review of Casey demonstrates the legitimacy of these policies. The court should say so.</p>
        <p>States may take sides in the abortion debate and come down on the side of life, even life in the unborn Even in the earliest stages of pregnancy, the state may enact rules and regulations designed to encourage [a woman] to know that there are philosophic and social arguments of great weight that can be brought to bear in favor of continuing the pregnancy to full term and that there are procedures and institutions to allow adoption of unwanted children as well as a certain degree of state assistance if the mother chooses to raise the child herself. . . .  Abortion, Casey held, has consequences beyond the woman and her fetus. The states interests in regulating are of concomitant extension. Casey recognized that abortion is, fraught with consequences for the persons who perform and assist in the procedure [and for] society which must confront the knowledge that these procedures exist, procedures some deem nothing short of an act of violence against innocent human life. . . .</p>
        <p>Casey demonstrates that the interests asserted by the state are legitimate and recognized by law. It is argued, however, that a ban on the D&amp;X does not further these interests. This is because, the reasoning continues, the D&amp;E method, which Nebraska claims to be beyond its intent to regulate, can still be used to abort a fetus and is no less dehumanizing than the D&amp;X method.</p>
        <p>While not adopting the argument in express terms, the court indicates tacit approval of it by refusing to reject it in a forthright manner. Rendering express what is only implicit in the majority opinion, Justice Stevens and Justice Ginsburg are forthright in declaring that the two procedures are indistinguishable and that Nebraska has acted both irrationally and without a proper purpose in enacting the law. The issue is not whether members of the judiciary can see a difference between the two procedures. It is whether Nebraska can. The court's refusal to recognize Nebraska's right to declare a moral difference between the procedure is a dispiriting disclosure of the illogic and illegitimacy of the court's approach to the entire case.</p>
        <p>Nebraska was entitled to find the existence of a consequential moral difference between the procedures. We are referred to substantial medical authority that D&amp;X perverts the natural birth process to a greater degree than D&amp;E, commandeering the live birth process until the skull is pierced. American Medical Association (A.M.A.) publications describe the D&amp;X abortion method as ethically wrong. The D&amp;X differs from the D&amp;E because in the D&amp;X the fetus is killed outside of the womb where the fetus has an autonomy which separates it from the right of the woman to choose treatments for her own body. Witnesses to the procedure relate that the fingers and feet of the fetus are moving prior to the piercing of the skull; when the scissors are inserted in the back of the head, the fetus body, wholly outside the woman's body and alive, reacts as though startled and goes limp. D&amp;X's stronger resemblance to infanticide means Nebraska could conclude the procedure presents a greater risk of disrespect for life and a consequent greater risk to the profession and society, which depend for their sustenance upon reciprocal recognition of dignity and respect. The court is without authority to second-guess this conclusion.</p>
        <p>FROM A DISSENT  By Justice Scalia</p>
        <p>I am optimistic enough to believe that, one day, Stenberg v. Carhart will be assigned its rightful place in the history of this court's jurisprudence beside Korematsu and Dred Scott. The method of killing a human child -- one cannot even accurately say an entirely unborn human child -- proscribed by this statute is so horrible that the most clinical description of it evokes a shudder of revulsion. And the court must know (as most state legislatures banning this procedure have concluded) that demanding a ''health exception'' which requires the abortionist to assure himself that, in his expert medical judgment, this method is, in the case at hand, marginally safer than others (how can one prove the contrary beyond a reasonable doubt?) is to give live-birth abortion free rein. . . .</p>
        <p>The two lengthy dissents in this case have, appropriately enough, set out to establish that today's result does not follow from this court's most recent pronouncement on the matter of abortion, Planned Parenthood of Southeastern Pa. v. Casey, It would be unfortunate, however, if those who disagree with the result were induced to regard it as merely a regrettable misapplication of Casey. It is not that, but is Casey's logical and entirely predictable consequence. To be sure, the court's construction of this statute so as to make it include procedures other than live-birth abortion involves not only a disregard of fair meaning, but an abandonment of the principle that even ambiguous statutes should be interpreted in such fashion as to render them valid rather than void.  Casey does not permit that jurisprudential novelty which must be chalked up to the court's inclination to bend the rules when any effort to limit abortion, or even to speak in opposition to abortion, is at issue. It is of a piece, in other words, with Hill v. Colorado, also decided today.</p>
        <p>But the court gives a second and independent reason for invalidating this humane (not to say anti-barbarian) law: That it fails to allow an exception for the situation in which the abortionist believes that this live-birth method of destroying the child might be safer for the woman. (As pointed out by Justice Thomas, and elaborated upon by Justice Kennedy, there is no good reason to believe this is ever the case, but who knows? It sometime might be.)</p>
        <p>I have joined Justice Thomas's dissent because I agree that today's decision is an ''unprecedented expansion'' of our prior cases, ''is not mandated'' by Casey's ''undue burden'' test, and can even be called (though this pushes me to the limit of my belief) ''obviously irreconcilable with Casey's explication of what its undue-burden standard requires.'' But I never put much stock in Casey's explication of the inexplicable. In the last analysis, my judgment that Casey does not support today's tragic result can be traced to the fact that what I consider to be an ''undue burden'' is different from what the majority considers to be an ''undue burden,'' a conclusion that cannot be demonstrated true or false by factual inquiry or legal reasoning. It is a value judgment, dependent upon how much one respects (or believes society ought to respect) the life of a partially delivered fetus, and how much one respects (or believes society ought to respect) the freedom of the woman who gave it life to kill it. Evidently, the five Justices in today's majority value the former less, or the latter more, (or both), than the four of us in dissent. Case closed. There is no cause for anyone who believes in Casey to feel betrayed by this outcome. It has been arrived at by precisely the process Casey promised a democratic vote by nine lawyers, not on the question whether the text of the Constitution has anything to say about this subject (it obviously does not); nor even on the question (also appropriate for lawyers) whether the legal traditions of the American people would have sustained such a limitation upon abortion (they obviously would); but upon the pure policy question whether this limitation upon abortion is ''undue'' i.e., goes too far.</p>
        <p>In my dissent in Casey, I wrote that the ''undue burden'' test made law by the joint opinion created a standard that was ''as doubtful in application as it is unprincipled in origin,'' ''hopelessly unworkable in practice,'' ''ultimately standardless.'' Today's decision is the proof. As long as we are debating this issue of necessity for a health-of-the-mother exception on the basis of Casey, it is really quite impossible for us dissenters to contend that the majority is wrong on the law any more than it could be said that one is wrong in law to support or oppose the death penalty, or to support or oppose mandatory minimum sentences. The most that we can honestly say is that we disagree with the majority on their policy-judgment-couched-as-law. And those who believe that a 5-to-4 vote on a policy matter by unelected lawyers should not overcome the judgment of 30 state legislatures have a problem, not with the application of Casey, but with its existence. Casey must be overruled.</p>
        <p>THE SUPREME COURT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
