<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOES OF ABORTION START NEW EFFORT AFTER COURT LOSS</title>
    <meta content="30ABOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE SUPREME COURT: THE COURSE AHEAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nebraska</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glaberson, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Nebraska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nebraska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E0D71639F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1389" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOES OF ABORTION START NEW EFFORT AFTER COURT LOSS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glaberson, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Day after Supreme Court effectively struck down bans on medical procedure its opponents call partial-birth abortion, supporters of those bans say they are already planning new generation of laws intended to withstand further legal challenge; court ruled that state laws must specify type of procedure barred and must permit use of procedures when necessary to health of woman; decision came in Nebraska case, but legal experts say it will likely invalidate similar law around the country; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A day after the Supreme Court effectively struck down bans on a medical procedure its opponents call partial-birth abortion, supporters of those bans said they were already planning a new generation of laws intended to withstand further legal challenges.</p>
        <p>In its 5-to-4 decision on Wednesday, the Supreme Court ruled that to  be constitutionally acceptable, state laws that ban the procedure must specify the type of procedure barred. The court also found that the state laws must permit use of that procedure if it is considered necessary to preserve the health of the mother. The laws exist in some 30 states.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A day after the Supreme Court effectively struck down bans on a medical procedure its opponents call partial-birth abortion, supporters of those bans said they were already planning a new generation of laws intended to withstand further legal challenges.</p>
        <p>In its 5-to-4 decision on Wednesday, the Supreme Court ruled that to  be constitutionally acceptable, state laws that ban the procedure must specify the type of procedure barred. The court also found that the state laws must permit use of that procedure if it is considered necessary to preserve the health of the mother. The laws exist in some 30 states.</p>
        <p>''One of our state senators has already contacted our office to get assistance to draft a new law that could withstand constitutional scrutiny,'' said L. Steven Grasz, the chief deputy attorney general of Nebraska.</p>
        <p>Nebraska's ban was the only one the Supreme Court considered in the case decided on Wednesday. But legal experts said the court's decision was likely to invalidate similar laws around the country and would spur efforts to pass new bans.</p>
        <p>''There will be a rush back to the drawing boards,'' said Laurence H. Tribe, an expert on constitutional law at Harvard Law School. Professor Tribe and other legal experts said that the court's ruling had left little maneuvering room for the proponents of the bans.</p>
        <p>''Partial-birth abortion'' is the term opponents of abortion use to describe one of several methods doctors use to terminate pregnancies after about 16 weeks.</p>
        <p>Anti-abortion forces use graphic descriptions of the procedure in hopes of undermining public support for abortion.</p>
        <p>Roger Hunt, the speaker of South Dakota's House of Representatives, said yesterday that efforts were already underway to analyze that state's ban and ''to see what, if anything, we may need to do to amend our statute so that we meet constitutional muster as far as the Supreme Court is concerned.''</p>
        <p>In Indiana, State Senator Patricia Miller, who sponsored the ban there four years ago, said she would propose legislation if necessary to meet the new requirements laid out by the court.</p>
        <p>''I still very much believe that states have the right to restrict partial-birth abortion,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Besides the legal fight over Nebraska's ban, other bans have been challenged in state and federal courts, and judges across the country have permanently or temporarily barred the enforcement of many of them, often using some of the same reasons cited in the Supreme Court decision.</p>
        <p>So, even before Wednesday's ruling, supporters of the bans had been working on strategies to rewrite the laws.</p>
        <p>Some of these revised bans are already on the books. Because of court challenges, however, only eight  bans are now in full force across the country, said the National Right to Life Committee, which drafted a model law on which the Nebraska statute and many others were based.</p>
        <p>Legal experts said that proponents of a ban might be able to comply relatively easily with the finding that laws must describe more specifically what is being banned. But they said that revised laws could still falter concerning the ''health of the mother'' exception.</p>
        <p>In Ohio, for example, an early ban was struck down by a federal appeals court and the legislature enacted a new law that its supporters say should meet some of the Supreme Court's new requirements. That law is to take effect next month. The new Ohio law is more specific in defining what is considered an illegal partial-birth abortion.</p>
        <p>Simon Heller, the litigation director of the Center for Reproductive Law and Policy, which opposes the bans, called the Ohio law an example of what he said would be new efforts to better describe the prohibited abortion methods.</p>
        <p>Publicly, supporters of the bans often say they want to ban a procedure known as a D &amp; X abortion, for intact dilation and extraction.</p>
        <p>In that procedure, used starting at about 16 weeks of pregnancy when the fetus's head has grown too big to pass safely through an undilated cervix, doctors trying to keep the fetus as intact as possible for various reasons extract it feet first and then use a sharp instrument to collapse the fetal skull.</p>
        <p>But critics of the bans say they are often so broadly worded that they seem to also ban so-called D &amp; E abortions, for dilation and evacuation. In this procedure, which is used much more commonly for abortions after the first trimester of pregnancy, the fetus is dismembered during the abortion.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the Supreme Court opinion, written by Justice Stephen G. Breyer, agreed that that had been a flaw in the Nebraska law.</p>
        <p>Justice Breyer's decision said that Nebraska, because of its broad phrasing, imposed an ''undue burden'' on a woman's right to choose a D &amp; E abortion.</p>
        <p>Critics have said that state legislation creating a ban was often written in very general terms because its supporters are trying to discourage all abortions, not just those they describe as partial-birth abortions.</p>
        <p>In revised laws across the country, Mr. Heller said, ban proponents ''will now try to come up with different language that they will claim is limited to this one specific procedure, but that really isn't.''</p>
        <p>His group, which has challenged many bans nationally, is preparing to challenge the Ohio law, which, he said, remains so broadly worded that it could be read as banning more than the D &amp; X abortions.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the bans denied they intended to limit women's rights to other methods of abortion. Mr. Grasz, the Nebraska deputy attorney general, said that abortion-rights groups make that claim to motivate their supporters with the fear that all abortion rights are at stake, not just a limitation on a particular method of abortion.</p>
        <p>''The only thing the states were trying to do,'' he said, ''was ban partial-birth abortion.''</p>
        <p>Those efforts, he said, would continue.</p>
        <p>People on both sides of the abortion issue were also divided yesterday regarding the Supreme Court's requirement that any ban, to be constitutional, must permit the use of the D &amp; X procedure if it is deemed necessary to preserve the health of the mother.</p>
        <p>The life of the woman is not at issue: all state laws banning the procedure -- including Nebraska's -- made allowances for its use should the pregnant woman's life be otherwise threatened.</p>
        <p>But Wednesday's ruling addressed the issue of the mother's health, a lower medical threshold -- and one more open to broad interpretation.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the bans said that rule was needed to preserve a meaningful right to choice guaranteed by the landmark 1973 abortion decision, Roe v. Wade.</p>
        <p>But proponents of the bans said they regarded that part of Wednesday's opinion as a trap for them.</p>
        <p>On the one hand, they said, if new laws are too narrow in defining the health of the mother, they will be struck down like the Nebraska law, which did not include a health exception.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, they continued, if the health exception written into new laws is too broad, the bans would be ineffective because doctors could invoke the exception routinely to use the banned procedures.</p>
        <p>In a companion suit to Roe v. Wade, the Supreme Court defined  ''the health of the mother'' broadly, including factors like a woman's age, and physical, psychological or emotional condition.</p>
        <p>Dorinda C. Bordlee, a special assistant attorney general in Louisiana who has defended the state's 1997 ''partial birth'' ban, said she was considering advising the Louisiana legislature to amend its law to define the mother's health strictly as ''significant long-term physical risks.''</p>
        <p>Such a law would surely be challenged in court.</p>
        <p>''That would force the Supreme Court to reconsider what it considers 'health,'  '' Ms. Bordlee said.</p>
        <p>THE SUPREME COURT: THE COURSE AHEAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
