<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y30BRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211376"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E4DB1639F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>UKRAINE: PRESIDENTIAL POWERS  A constitutional court ruled that President Leonid Kuchma's plan to strengthen his powers over Parliament do not violate the Constitution. The ruling paves the way for Mr. Kuchma to submit the changes to Parliament, which must pass them by a two-thirds majority. Some opposition leaders want to water down the proposals, fearing Mr. Kuchma's executive powers will too easily override the legislature. Ever since Mr. Kuchma won re-election last November, he has been campaigning for stronger powers to break the many deadlocks that have snarled economic reform plans.</p>
        <p>Patrick E. Tyler (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>UKRAINE: PRESIDENTIAL POWERS  A constitutional court ruled that President Leonid Kuchma's plan to strengthen his powers over Parliament do not violate the Constitution. The ruling paves the way for Mr. Kuchma to submit the changes to Parliament, which must pass them by a two-thirds majority. Some opposition leaders want to water down the proposals, fearing Mr. Kuchma's executive powers will too easily override the legislature. Ever since Mr. Kuchma won re-election last November, he has been campaigning for stronger powers to break the many deadlocks that have snarled economic reform plans.</p>
        <p>Patrick E. Tyler (NYT)</p>
        <p>AUSTRIA: RIGHTS MONITORS  Austria said it was willing to cooperate with a panel asked to examine its human rights records. The European Court of Human Rights in Strasbourg, France, will appoint three monitors, who will send their findings to the other 14 European Union governments. Analysts believe this could be a first step toward ending Austria's political isolation within the Union, which froze political relations with Vienna on Feb. 4 after Jorg Haider's far-right Freedom Party joined Austria's coalition government.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>TURKEY: ARMENIANS EXPELLED  Four Armenians invited to a meeting in the eastern city of Kars were expelled by Turkish security agents. Local authorities had invited the four as part of an effort to improve relations between the two countries, which would greatly help the economy in Kars and other border areas. But the Foreign Ministry said that since Armenia is occupying territory that belongs to Azerbaijan, Turkey's ally, and is promoting hostility toward Turkey, the ministry is ''not promoting such contacts.''</p>
        <p>Stephen Kinzer (NYT)</p>
        <p>IRELAND: PREMIER TESTIFIES  Prime Minister Bertie Ahern told a tribunal investigating improper payments to politicians that he had no knowledge of a donation of $91,000 that disappeared in 1989. A Fianna Fail party supporter donated $121,000 to former Prime Minister Charles Haughey, of which only $30,000 reached the party account. Mr. Ahern, who handled party finances at the time, said he was aware of only the $30,000 donation, and he accepted blame for not sending a receipt for that amount.</p>
        <p>Brian F. Lavery (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>ARGENTINA: SUING BRITAIN  Relatives of more than 300 sailors who were killed when the cruiser General Belgrano was sunk by the Royal Navy during the Falklands war in 1982 announced that they plan to sue Britain for damages next week in the European Court of Human Rights in Strasbourg, France. Lawyers for the relatives, who have been preparing the case for five years, will argue that since the ship's sinking was outside the theater of operations, it violated international wartime conventions.</p>
        <p>Clifford Krauss (NYT)</p>
        <p>COLOMBIA: REBEL TALKS  Delegations representing 21 nations, including European and United Nations diplomats, began two days of meetings with the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia, the country's main left-wing guerrilla group, in a demilitarized area controlled by the rebels. The topic of the conference is drug trafficking: the guerrillas are heavily involved in the cocaine trade but say they would favor alternative crop-substitution programs. The United States did not take part because of a ban on official contacts with the group.</p>
        <p>Larry Rohter (NYT)</p>
        <p>CANADA: JAILED AGAIN  An upstate New York judge has jailed a Vancouver man who fled a penal work camp 29 years ago while serving up to 4 years for selling $20 worth of LSD to an undercover agent. Allen Richardson told the Rochester judge he fled in 1971 because a guard told him he was about to be returned to Attica prison, where a deadly riot had just occurred. The case was a cause celebre in Canada.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>KOREAS: TALKS PROGRESS  North and South Korea appeared close to a landmark agreement on the issues of the repatriation of former prisoners and family reunions. The North Korean Red Cross has agreed to hold reunions in August for families who were separated in the Korean War, and South Korea would repatriate former North Korean prisoners in September, reports from both sides said. Talks between the two, being held in North Korea, are scheduled to wind up today.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: PALESTINIANS COMPLAIN  Saeb Erekat, a senior peace negotiator, said the Palestinians had lodged complaints with the Americans and the Europeans about increasing Israeli reinforcements of settlements in Gaza and the West Bank. Palestinians report seeing tanks moving into certain settlement areas, which they say is creating panic among Palestinians.</p>
        <p>Deborah Sontag (NYT)</p>
        <p>IRAQ: SECURITY STEPPED UP  The United Nations is tightening security in Iraq after the shooting deaths of two of its staff members at an office in Baghdad, a United Nations official in Baghdad said. She said these procedures included checking again that all United Nations employees had their identity cards and that a thorough verification of visitors' identities should be made before they enter United Nations offices. According to officials, Fowad Hussein Haydar, above, opened fire after entering the building and demanding an end to sanctions against Iraq.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>SIERRA LEONE: PEACEKEEPERS FREED  Liberia said rebels in Sierra Leone had freed 21 Indian United Nations peacekeepers and handed them over to the Liberian authorities. The statement did not make clear whether the 21 were a group seized in Kuiva on June 5 or came from a separate contingent surrounded in nearby Kailahun since early in May.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
