<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Privatization and Failing Schools</title>
    <meta content="30FRI3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211386"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Charter Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O (Chancellor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Charter Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E4DA1639F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Privatization and Failing Schools</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial on suggestion by schools chancellor Harold Levy that he would consider turning some failing New York City schools into charter schools run by private companies or not-for-profit groups; says charter option should not be ruled out, as long as schools remain open to all and are held to rigorous performance and financial standards; says any privatization effort should begin slowly</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City's schools chancellor, Harold Levy, raised eyebrows this week when he said that he would consider turning some failing schools into charter schools that would be run by private companies or not-for-profit groups. The charter option should not be ruled out -- as long as schools developed under its rubric remain open to all citizens and are held accountable to rigorous performance standards and taxpayer scrutiny, and provided that privatization is not a cover for channeling money from public education to parochial schools. In addition, City Hall, which has long pushed for privatization, needs to understand that there is nothing magical about privatization and that rebuilding failing schools requires the same grit, determination and patience no matter who undertakes the job.</p>
        <p>City Hall has been sharply critical of how the Board of Education deals with failing schools, when in fact the system has made important strides in this area. About half of the city schools that are put on the state's list of failing institutions for poor performance are turned around within three years, providing evidence that the system is learning at last to deal with one of its most difficult problems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City's schools chancellor, Harold Levy, raised eyebrows this week when he said that he would consider turning some failing schools into charter schools that would be run by private companies or not-for-profit groups. The charter option should not be ruled out -- as long as schools developed under its rubric remain open to all citizens and are held accountable to rigorous performance standards and taxpayer scrutiny, and provided that privatization is not a cover for channeling money from public education to parochial schools. In addition, City Hall, which has long pushed for privatization, needs to understand that there is nothing magical about privatization and that rebuilding failing schools requires the same grit, determination and patience no matter who undertakes the job.</p>
        <p>City Hall has been sharply critical of how the Board of Education deals with failing schools, when in fact the system has made important strides in this area. About half of the city schools that are put on the state's list of failing institutions for poor performance are turned around within three years, providing evidence that the system is learning at last to deal with one of its most difficult problems.</p>
        <p>A recent study of schools that got off the list shows that they did so by forcing out teachers who  were resistant to change. The teachers' union has gone along with this process, bending rules to ease transfers and creating a peer intervention program that retrains failing teachers and sometimes advises them to seek new careers. Under tough new rules, if a school does not improve in three years, it can be closed, its staff dispersed and new staff brought in.</p>
        <p>There are certainly some rock-bottom schools where nothing has worked and where the communities are desperate to try anything. But private companies have been fired in cities like Baltimore and Hartford. In Albany, New York State's most heralded effort, the New Covenant Charter School, severed its relationship with a private management company after months of dismal performance.</p>
        <p>The evidence suggests that any privatization effort should begin slowly, with just a few schools and with close scrutiny from city and state education officials. Companies that succeed by objective criteria -- using the same resources as the public schools -- should be allowed to continue. Those that fail should not.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
