<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y30CAM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211429"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chicago (Ill)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Reform Party</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fleetwood Mac (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perot, Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EED61639F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1286" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by B. Drummond Ayres Jr.</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reform Party gathers enough signatures to put Ross Perot on ballot for party's primary, which will be conducted by mail and over Internet; Los Angeles City Council reconsiders setting aside Pershing Square as gathering place for protesters during Democratic national convention; acts on concerns of police and merchants about violence; George W Bush campaign seeks 'real-looking people,' particularly 'Hispanic and Caucasian' for 'nonunion commercial'; Al Gore campaign event in Chicago features recordings by Fleetwood Mac (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE REFORM PARTY</p>
        <p>PEROT MAY FACE OFF WITH BUCHANAN  If Ross Perot wants to run for president again, now he can. An effort to collect the required number of signatures to qualify him for the Reform Party primary has succeeded, said Ira Goodman, a party official from New Jersey who has been leading a campaign to draft Mr. Perot as an alternative to the two other candidates who are seeking the party nomination: Patrick J. Buchanan, the former television commentator, and John Hagelin, a physicist. Mr. Perot, the Reform Party founder and two-time presidential nominee, now has until Saturday to notify party officials by letter that he intends to run, if that is his decision. Russell Verney, one his close associates, said yesterday that he would speak to Mr. Perot as soon as possible to review the options. Mr. Verney added that a decision on whether to try to undercut the other two candidates, especially Mr. Buchanan, whom many Reform Party members consider too conservative, could come as early as today. The balloting for the primary, which is conducted by mail and over the Internet, begins on July 5 and ends on Aug. 9.</p>
        <p>Michael Janofsky (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE REFORM PARTY</p>
        <p>PEROT MAY FACE OFF WITH BUCHANAN  If Ross Perot wants to run for president again, now he can. An effort to collect the required number of signatures to qualify him for the Reform Party primary has succeeded, said Ira Goodman, a party official from New Jersey who has been leading a campaign to draft Mr. Perot as an alternative to the two other candidates who are seeking the party nomination: Patrick J. Buchanan, the former television commentator, and John Hagelin, a physicist. Mr. Perot, the Reform Party founder and two-time presidential nominee, now has until Saturday to notify party officials by letter that he intends to run, if that is his decision. Russell Verney, one his close associates, said yesterday that he would speak to Mr. Perot as soon as possible to review the options. Mr. Verney added that a decision on whether to try to undercut the other two candidates, especially Mr. Buchanan, whom many Reform Party members consider too conservative, could come as early as today. The balloting for the primary, which is conducted by mail and over the Internet, begins on July 5 and ends on Aug. 9.</p>
        <p>Michael Janofsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE CONVENTIONS</p>
        <p>CONCERNS ABOUT PROTESTS  Less than a week after voting to set aside Pershing Square in downtown Los Angeles as a gathering place for protesters at the Democratic National Convention, the Los Angeles City Council is reconsidering the move under pressure from the police and merchants' groups worried about violence or disruptions at convention hotels and the jewelry mart near the square. The police have proposed putting demonstrators in a fenced-off parking lot near the convention site. The council approved the new plan as part of a $4 million bailout of the convention's local organizing committee, at the insistence of one member, Jackie Goldberg, a liberal Democrat representing Hollywood, who held the decisive vote. The Secret Service has now decided not to have Vice President Al Gore stay at the Royal Biltmore Hotel, opposite the square, citing safety concerns. After a sometimes impassioned debate on Wednesday, the council referred the matter to a committee; a final vote is expected next week.</p>
        <p>Todd Purdum (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS</p>
        <p>REALITY-BASED AD FOR BUSH  The Bush campaign is searching for real people, or at least actors who look like them. In a casting notice sent to talent agents this week, a company representing the campaign said it was looking for ''a wide range of assorted, real-looking people'' to appear in a spot for Gov. George W. Bush that is to be filmed in July. Describing the spot as a ''nonunion commercial,'' the memorandum asked for ''everyday people on the street'' with a ''strong emphasis on Hispanic and Caucasian.'' The notice was a surprise to officials of the Screen Actors Guild, which is on strike against the advertising industry. Guild officials said they thought they had a signed agreement that gave the Bush campaign permission to hire union actors. But Mark McKinnon, Mr. Bush's media consultant, said that while two members of the campaign's advertising team who are partners in a separate agency had signed such an agreement, the Bush campaign's agency, Maverick Media, had not.</p>
        <p>Peter Marks (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS</p>
        <p>IT'S IN THE MUSIC  Vice President Al Gore's ''progress and prosperity'' tour carries an implicit argument for four more years of the current administration, and at a campaign event in Chicago yesterday, the recorded music made the same case. It was by Fleetwood Mac, the band that played at President Clinton's inauguration festivities in 1993, and it even included the song ''Don't Stop (Thinking About Tomorrow),'' Mr. Clinton's theme. The other tunes had their own strange relevance. There was ''The Chain,'' a plea for continuity that includes a declaration -- ''if you don't love me now, you will never love me again'' -- with disturbing implications for a candidate trailing in many polls. And there was ''Tusk,'' which seemed to capture the uncertainty of Mr. Gore's future in Washington with its opening lines: ''Why don't you ask him if he's going to stay? Why don't you ask him if he's going away?''</p>
        <p>Frank Bruni (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
