<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Girlfriend Testifies Against Murder Suspect</title>
    <meta content="30KO.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211461"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kim, Diane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seong, Claudia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ko, Edmund</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finkelstein, Katherine E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E6DE1739F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="546" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Girlfriend Testifies Against Murder Suspect</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHERINE E. FINKELSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finkelstein, Katherine E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Diane Kim testifies that former boyfriend, Edmund Ko, restrained her on deserted road in November 1997 while his girlfriend Claudia Seong viciously slashed her face, scalp and legs in jealous rage; Ko is on trial in New York City for murder of Columbia law student Lynda Hong, another former girlfriend, four months later; Ko is on trial but case has also focused on Seong, whom both sides acknowledge is violently jealous (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former girlfriend of the man on trial in the murder of a Columbia law student testified yesterday that he had restrained her on a barren New Jersey road while his girlfriend viciously slashed her face, scalp and legs in a jealous rage.</p>
        <p>The woman, Diane Kim, 26, wept as she testified in Manhattan Criminal Court that the man, Edmund Ko, 26, held her arms while his girlfriend, Claudia Seong, 34, slashed her scalp so deeply that the knife entered her skull. Ms. Seong's sister sat on her knees to pin her down, Ms. Kim said. The two have been charged in the attack and freed on bail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A former girlfriend of the man on trial in the murder of a Columbia law student testified yesterday that he had restrained her on a barren New Jersey road while his girlfriend viciously slashed her face, scalp and legs in a jealous rage.</p>
        <p>The woman, Diane Kim, 26, wept as she testified in Manhattan Criminal Court that the man, Edmund Ko, 26, held her arms while his girlfriend, Claudia Seong, 34, slashed her scalp so deeply that the knife entered her skull. Ms. Seong's sister sat on her knees to pin her down, Ms. Kim said. The two have been charged in the attack and freed on bail.</p>
        <p>The attack, on Nov. 18, 1997, was four months before another former girlfriend of Mr. Ko's, Hyeseung Lynda Hong, 26, was found dead in her apartment near Columbia University, where she studied law.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Ko, 25, of Cliffside Park, N.J., is being tried for Ms. Hong's murder, testimony in this case has repeatedly focused on Ms. Seong, who in her appearance in the courtroom refused to answer any questions. Both sides have acknowledged that she is violently jealous.</p>
        <p>In June 1997, shortly after their two-month relationship ended, Ms. Kim said, Mr. Ko called her and said she was among the former girlfriends he was telling not to contact him or acknowledge him in public because he was in a new relationship. Ms. Hong had been similarly warned by a friend of Ms. Seong's, according to court testimony.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ko did not contact Ms. Kim again, she said, until Nov. 17 at midnight, when he called and asked to see her immediately. At first she declined, she said. But at 3 a.m., after he had called several more times and promised that two women would accompany them so that her new boyfriend would not be jealous, she said, she agreed to meet him. Mr. Ko, Ms. Seong and her younger sister, Young Joo, picked her up, drove half a mile to a deserted stretch of road and got out, Ms. Kim said.</p>
        <p>''What's going on?'' she recalled asking. Mr. Ko pushed and hit her, Ms. Kim said, and then he shoved her backward over a barricade. Young Joo Seong sat on her knees and Mr. Ko held her arms, she added.</p>
        <p>Claudia Seong took out a long knife and cut her right thigh through her blue jeans, Ms. Kim said, crying. ''I kept asking, 'Why are you doing this to me?' and Claudia said, 'You know why,' '' she testified, adding that Claudia Seong drew the knife from her nose to her cheek as Mr. Ko held her.</p>
        <p>After the attack, blood covered her ''from head to toe,'' she said. ''My eyes were covered with blood.''</p>
        <p>She said the three left her in that condition, and she walked home before going to a hospital. .</p>
        <p>Jack Litman, Mr. Ko's lawyer, asked her during cross-examination, ''One thing we can agree on, the only person who slashed you is Claudia Seong?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Kim said yes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
