<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Residential Real Estate; Smaller Building With Bigger Apartments</title>
    <meta content="30REAL$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garbarine, Rachelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6DE1739F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Residential Real Estate; Smaller Building With Bigger Apartments</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHELLE GARBARINE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Garbarine, Rachelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residential Real Estate column on Montrose luxury rental apartment building on East 38th Street in Manhattan; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By the standards of current Manhattan construction, the Montrose, with 97 luxury rental apartments on 20 stories, is a small building. But when leasing begins next month, its developers are betting that the combination of a smaller building and large units -- 60 percent of the apartments are two-bedrooms -- and a location in a residential neighborhood in eastern Murray Hill will be attractive to prospective tenants.</p>
        <p>The building, at 306-308 East 38th Street, between First and Second Avenues, will offer studio to two-bedroom units, including nine duplex apartments, with 650 to 1,259 square feet each. And because low-rise apartment houses stand to the south and west of the Montrose, its units above the third floor will offer unobstructed views of the East River.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By the standards of current Manhattan construction, the Montrose, with 97 luxury rental apartments on 20 stories, is a small building. But when leasing begins next month, its developers are betting that the combination of a smaller building and large units -- 60 percent of the apartments are two-bedrooms -- and a location in a residential neighborhood in eastern Murray Hill will be attractive to prospective tenants.</p>
        <p>The building, at 306-308 East 38th Street, between First and Second Avenues, will offer studio to two-bedroom units, including nine duplex apartments, with 650 to 1,259 square feet each. And because low-rise apartment houses stand to the south and west of the Montrose, its units above the third floor will offer unobstructed views of the East River.</p>
        <p>A huddle of low-slung commercial structures was demolished less than a year ago to make way for the $35 million building, which is being developed by the Clarett Group of Manhattan with the Fidelity Management Trust Company of Boston as an equity partner. Fleet Bank and HSBC Bank provided construction financing.</p>
        <p>''Not everyone wants to live in a big building, and there is a tremendous demand for large apartments in established residential neighborhoods,'' said Nancy Packes, president of Feathered Nest, a rental brokerage in Manhattan and the exclusive leasing agent for the Montrose.</p>
        <p>The market for the Montrose, Ms. Packes said, ''is not so much families with children, but more established professional couples and empty nesters.''</p>
        <p>Rents will range from $2,500 to $8,500 a month, or an average of $52 a square foot. That is on par with buildings east of Second Avenue in the 30's, where rents increased by 10 percent over the last year to an average of $53 a square foot, according to Benjamin James Associates, another Manhattan residential brokerage firm, which specializes in rentals downtown.</p>
        <p>''Up until a year and a half ago, this was a sleepy neighborhood of low-rise prewar apartments,'' said Douglas A. Wagner, president of Benjamin James, pointing out that for much of the last decade, the development activity was centered on and west of Third Avenue. Since mid-1998, when the 50-story Paramount Tower rental building opened, the activity ''has been moving east,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That building, at 240 East 39th Street, between Second and Third Avenues, was developed by the Glenwood Management Corporation of New Hyde Park, N.Y., an active Manhattan developer. It brought to the neighborhood 446 rental apartments, 20 percent of them rented to low-income tenants. Gary Jacob, executive vice president at Glenwood, said new leases for the market-rate units were averaging ''north of $50 a square foot.''</p>
        <p>Now, in addition to the Montrose, the Related Companies, another large Manhattan developer, is building a 260-unit mixed-income rental tower at 39th Street and Second Avenue. It is a convenient, walk-to-work location, said David J. Wine, Related's vice chairman, adding that ''it's also attractive when you look at the stores and movie theaters along Second Avenue.''</p>
        <p>Monthly rents for those units, which are expected to start leasing in November, have not been determined, he said.</p>
        <p>The Clarett Group bought the site for the Montrose in the summer of 1999 from a development group that had assembled the five parcels as well as bought the air rights above a five-story walk-up to the west, but could not obtain financing, said Neil Klarfeld, a company principal. He said he and his partner, Veronica Hackett, secured the financing and last October proceeded to build the project alone.</p>
        <p>''We liked the site and the views and felt renters were looking for and could relate to a high-end boutique building,'' Mr. Klarfeld said. That the project could be constructed as of right -- meaning no special permits were needed -- was also appealing, he said.</p>
        <p>The project is the initial foray into the Manhattan residential market for the partners. Separately, he said, they developed about 8 million square feet of commercial space in New York City, mostly in Manhattan, including 60 Wall Street, the 1.6-million-square-foot world headquarters for J. P. Morgan. He said that in January of this year, his company joined with Post Properties, a development company in Atlanta, to develop residential projects in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The partners, who are wine aficionados, took the inspiration for the name of their company, as well as the Montrose, from terms associated with Bordeaux.</p>
        <p>The building, designed by Marvin H. Meltzer of the Manhattan architectural firm of Meltzer/Mandl, rises 20 stories from a two-story stone-and-glass base and cantilevers at the ninth floor for 12 stories over the adjacent smaller building. The entire building steps back at the 15th floor.</p>
        <p>To create its facade, Mr. Meltzer chose factory-built panels of silver and greenish-blue aluminum and reddish-brown brick tiles, which were manufactured by Eastern Exterior Wall Systems in Bethlehem Pa., and trucked to the site, where they were lifted and welded into place. ''The panels not only helped speed the construction but gave us a greater palette to work with,'' said Mr. Meltzer, who described the Montrose as a ''modern, sculptured building.''</p>
        <p>Inside, all of the apartments have features like open floor plans, a generous number of windows, marble and slate finishes, a washer and dryer, and direct Internet access. The duplex units also have terraces.</p>
        <p>Amenities in the building include a health club and a common landscaped sun deck on the roof. There are also private locked storage areas, which residents could use as wine cellars.</p>
        <p>Occupancy is to start in September, Mr. Klarfeld said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
