<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lamoriello to Stay In Charge for Devils</title>
    <meta content="30DEVI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211366"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yankeenets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lamoriello, Lou</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E3DC1639F933A05755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lamoriello to Stay In Charge for Devils</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lou Lamoriello agrees to remain as New Jersey Devils president with mandate to run team for new owner, YankeeNets; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lou Lamoriello is not leaving East Rutherford. He is not taking a hockey sabbatical. He is not leaving the Devils to run another franchise.</p>
        <p>Lamoriello agreed yesterday to stay as the Devils' president and general manager for an unspecified number of years, with a mandate to run things for the YankeeNets, the team's new owner, with the same authority he had for 13 years and two Stanley Cups under the previous owner, John McMullen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lou Lamoriello is not leaving East Rutherford. He is not taking a hockey sabbatical. He is not leaving the Devils to run another franchise.</p>
        <p>Lamoriello agreed yesterday to stay as the Devils' president and general manager for an unspecified number of years, with a mandate to run things for the YankeeNets, the team's new owner, with the same authority he had for 13 years and two Stanley Cups under the previous owner, John McMullen.</p>
        <p>Lamoriello said he had never contemplated taking a break from hockey. He declined to say if he would have run the Colorado Avalanche had McMullen succeeded in his bid to buy the team. Lamoriello also refused to say how much he will receive of the $175 million the YankeeNets are paying for the Devils, although his share is said to be at least $8 million.</p>
        <p>The YankeeNets have pursued Lamoriello since agreeing to buy the team last February, but negotiations awaited the end of the season, which concluded with New Jersey's second Stanley Cup in the Lamoriello era.</p>
        <p>''It was just my understanding of the direction the YankeeNets conglomeration was going in,'' he said during a conference call yesterday, ''and I wanted a level of comfortability that the success of the Devils and the way we've run the Devils would be manageable. Everything was focused this past week and it took very little time in the past few days.''</p>
        <p>Harvey Schiller, the chairman of YankeeNets, said, ''Lou, probably, and he may not like me saying this, but on the open market financially, Lou was a very valuable property.''</p>
        <p>If Lamoriello had spurned the YankeeNets, Schiller said, hiring both a new president and a new general manager ''would have been costlier to the franchise.'' Schiller said the YankeeNets never contacted another candidate.</p>
        <p>Lamoriello made it clear that his priority is to re-sign Devils Coach Larry Robinson, who replaced Robbie Ftorek with eight games left in the season.</p>
        <p>Lamoriello said he planned to start negotiating with Robinson last night and expected no serious obstacles to signing him. ''We certainly have had conversations, nothing specific,'' Lamoriello said. ''I'd hope nothing has changed. There will be no arm-twisting. He'll come back because he feels good about it.''</p>
        <p>At the Devils' Stanley Cup victory rally two weeks ago, Robinson vowed, ''If Lou Lamoriello is the manager, Larry Robinson will be the coach.''</p>
        <p>Lamoriello's authority over Devils players and business decisions will remain the same as it was under McMullen, although the team has long had a reputation of not zealously marketing its players. He will report to Schiller and to a Devils' board of directors.</p>
        <p>''I feel comfortable I will have 100 percent final say, as I have in the past,'' Lamoriello said.</p>
        <p>But Lamoriello's role will expand because of the integration of some Devils and Nets operations, as the YankeeNets plan to move the teams to a proposed arena in Newark.</p>
        <p>''We want Lou to be involved in working with our sports properties at a variety of levels,'' Schiller said.</p>
        <p>But when asked if he would have input into the Yankees' pursuit of Sammy Sosa, Lamoriello quickly responded, ''Next question.''</p>
        <p>Lamoriello brings his reputation for fiscal efficiency to a company whose teams are renowned for hefty player spending, to great success with the Yankees, to no success with the Nets. The Devils won the Stanley Cup with a $37.6 million payroll, well below the Rangers' $61.2 million payroll.</p>
        <p>The YankeeNets, despite coping with heavy debt, holds out the promise of being in a position of letting Lamoriello spend more lavishly than in the past.</p>
        <p>''Money, and spending unlimited money, doesn't necessarily mean you'll have success,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Lamoriello's success has inextricably been linked with McMullen's. The two occasionally prickly personalities seemed well suited atop the Devils' hierarchy.</p>
        <p>''Dr. McMullen always gave me the responsibility,'' said Lamoriello, who yesterday added the title of chief executive officer. ''He became a fan of hockey, and an admirer of the type of players who played the game. He enjoyed the relationships with the players in a way that never overlapped into the operations. He never interfered.''</p>
        <p>When asked if he expected such freedom in his new job, or if he expected future pressure from powerful YankeeNets directors like George Steinbrenner to enliven a slumping squad with a big-name player, Lamoriello said, ''Nothing's going to change.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
