<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anti-Eviction Programs Pushed by City Hall Are in Disarray</title>
    <meta content="18HRA.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/nyregion/18HRA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231682"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Evictions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Community Law Advocates</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipton, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollock, Deborah J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E7D7163BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anti-Eviction Programs Pushed by City Hall Are in Disarray</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses problems facing Giuliani administration's anti-eviction programs; storefront office of Community Law Advocates, group in South Bronx that was established to keep poor families from being evicted into homelessness, has been shuttered since July, when state criminal investigators seized everything from its desktop computers to records on center's welfare clients; office at city's Human Resources Administration in lower Manhattan that had been set aside for agency's coordinator of 'new initiatives' has sat vacant since ity too was searched by investigators and collaborative effort by Deborah J Pollock, founder of Community Law Advocates, and Giuliani administration to change way city helps poor families facing eviction is months behind schedule (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The storefront office of Community Law Advocates, a group in the South Bronx that was established to keep poor families from being evicted into homelessness, has been shuttered since July, when state criminal investigators seized everything from its desktop computers to records on the center's welfare clients.</p>
        <p>An office at the city's Human Resources Administration in Lower Manhattan that had been set aside for the agency's coordinator of ''new initiatives'' has sat vacant since it, too, was searched by investigators. And across the city, a collaborative effort by the founder of Community Law Advocates and the Giuliani administration to change the way New York City helps poor families facing eviction is months behind schedule.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The storefront office of Community Law Advocates, a group in the South Bronx that was established to keep poor families from being evicted into homelessness, has been shuttered since July, when state criminal investigators seized everything from its desktop computers to records on the center's welfare clients.</p>
        <p>An office at the city's Human Resources Administration in Lower Manhattan that had been set aside for the agency's coordinator of ''new initiatives'' has sat vacant since it, too, was searched by investigators. And across the city, a collaborative effort by the founder of Community Law Advocates and the Giuliani administration to change the way New York City helps poor families facing eviction is months behind schedule.</p>
        <p>It is far from the situation envisioned by Jason A. Turner, the city's human resources commissioner, and Deborah J. Pollock, the founder of Community Law, after they met in 1998 at a Bronx housing court.</p>
        <p>Ms. Pollock, 42, had spent 10 years at the Legal Aid Society as a housing court advocate when she and Mr. Turner decided to team up. Their approach was to encourage poor families about to be evicted to move to more affordable apartments or to persuade landlords to cut claims of past-due rent, as a way to reduce the reliance on government to pay off large debts on behalf of these desperate families.</p>
        <p>But like other major components of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's high-profile campaign to change the city's welfare system, the eviction-prevention program has turned out to be far more complicated -- and controversial -- than expected.</p>
        <p>Community Law and Ms. Pollock, who set up the organization in 1998, are now the subject of a criminal investigation by the state attorney general's office and other law enforcement officials, who are examining rental assistance applications submitted by the group on behalf of poor city residents to determine whether mistakes were made or information was falsified, officials close to the investigation said.</p>
        <p>The investigators are trying to determine if Community Law, in collaboration with some landlords, falsified applications to the state to arrange extra welfare payments to landlords to cover recipients' past-due rent, two officials close to the inquiry said.</p>
        <p>Investigators are also looking into Community Law's fund-raising methods.</p>
        <p>A Community Law official told a reporter that in the last two years, the organization had asked about 20 landlords to donate to Community Law 10 percent of any past-due rent it had collected on their behalf. Some legal advocates for the poor have questioned the practice, asking how Community Law could demand necessary repairs to run-down apartments at the same time it was soliciting donations.</p>
        <p>''There is an inherent conflict between being paid by the landlord and representing the tenant,'' said Steven Banks, deputy attorney in charge for the Legal Aid Society.</p>
        <p>The Human Resources Administration has been pulled into the inquiry at least superficially because it hired Ms. Pollock last year as a consultant. And before the criminal investigation began, Ms. Pollock was offered an executive-level post at Human Resources, as its coordinator of new initiatives, and Community Law also bid unsuccessfully on a large Human Resources contract. Those moves are now the subject of a separate conflict-of-interest inquiry by the city's Department of Investigation, a city official said. Ms. Pollock did not take the job.</p>
        <p>Vincent L. Briccetti, a lawyer representing Community Law, did not dismiss the possibility that factual errors had been made on applications submitted to the state. ''But I am certainly not aware of and do not believe that there was any fraud committed by Community Law Advocates or its employees,'' Mr. Briccetti said.</p>
        <p>Ronald Kliegerman, a Manhattan lawyer representing Ms. Pollock, said he had ''not heard anything of a concrete nature that anyone has committed a crime.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Turner, the human resources commissioner, said the criminal inquiry into Community Law had nothing to do with his agency. And as far as he is concerned, the new approach to eviction prevention is a success, despite the delay in expanding it to all of the city's welfare centers. ''We are rolling it out citywide,'' Mr. Turner said.</p>
        <p>Advocates for the poor say it is no surprise that the anti-eviction initiative, which has received little public notice, is the subject of so much scrutiny. ''It's directly as a result of the arrogant, ideologically inspired way they are doing this,'' said Glenn Pasanen, of City Project, a nonprofit social services advocacy group.</p>
        <p>Community Law officials say all scrutiny and the questions about their operations are unjustified; they attribute the impetus for the inquiry in part to groups that oppose the innovations. These include some groups of lawyers and traditional social service agencies that would see their caseloads, and fees, reduced if the innovations were successful.</p>
        <p>''Community Law Advocates was under scrutiny from the moment of inception because we represented a threat to the status quo,'' said one person associated with the organization, who asked not to be identified because of the investigation.</p>
        <p>The initiative has its origins in a  belief shared by Mr. Turner and Ms. Pollock that the government approach to helping welfare recipients threatened with homelessness was too slow and too expensive. At times, Mr. Turner said in a speech in November 1998, the old approach had  ''an inadvertently negative influence on tenants' responsibilities about paying their rent.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Turner, who joined the Giuliani administration in early 1998, has moved to reorganize city welfare intake centers and has hired private  companies to put more emphasis on helping people find jobs, instead of just signing them up for benefits.</p>
        <p>But both initiatives have been stymied by legal challenges, with advocates for the poor claiming that the city has wrongly turned away people who need assistance or has broken rules when hiring contractors.</p>
        <p>Preventing homelessness was another area that the administration had hoped to reorganize and, at least partly, turn over to private groups. For years, the administration had tried to find a way to eliminate or reduce the $10 million a year it allocates to nonprofit legal groups that fight evictions for about 10,000 families. The cases typically entailed a request to the state to pay off delinquent rent and increase a monthly housing allowance, with the lawyers arguing that the basic subsidy of $312 for a family of four is far too low.</p>
        <p>Under Ms. Pollock's program, intervention typically came before landlords took the tenants to court. It tried to get their landlord to reduce delinquent-rent claims in return for an accelerated payment from the city, or encourage the tenant to find a new, less expensive place to live.</p>
        <p>Each case settled without going to court would mean one less $1,080 legal fee for tenant lawyers, which, for critics of the system, was in itself a victory. The approach also emphasized self-sufficiency, something Mr. Turner had pushed since his arrival.</p>
        <p>''The existing system has not insisted that both tenants and landlords take responsibility for working out their differences because the Human Resources Administration, in the form of the taxpayer, has been bailing the tenants out,'' Mr. Turner said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Pollock and Community Law at first worked independently of city government, helping about 1,800 families negotiate deals with landlords, a Community Law official said. Several welfare recipients interviewed who turned to the group for help had no complaints.</p>
        <p>''They did everything good for me and my mom,'' said Luz Ortiz, 31, of the Bronx, who said her rent troubles were resolved in part through Community Law's work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Turner hired Ms. Pollock as a city consultant in January 1999. The intent was to introduce her eviction-prevention techniques to all the city's welfare intake centers by the end of 1999, city documents show. Then the city, like Community Law, would try to negotiate settlements with landlords or encourage tenants to move, trying whenever possible to avoid housing court.</p>
        <p>Simultaneously, the city moved to revise rules governing the nonprofit legal groups, prohibiting organizations that had filed or intended to file class-action lawsuits, like Legal Aid, from getting anti-eviction compensation. These lawsuits -- on behalf of the homeless and regarding the city's efforts to revamp welfare -- had infuriated the Giuliani administration, which intended the new rules to block the lawsuits. Mr. Turner spoke with Ms. Pollock and another group with close ties to the administration about jointly bidding to take some of these eviction cases, two participants said.</p>
        <p>''The city wanted to open it up to a group with a different philosophy  that believed in personal responsibility,'' said Dennis Saffran, executive director of the Center for the Community Interest, a conservative advocacy group that is a strong supporter of Mr. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>Mr. Turner's plan to roll out the new eviction-prevention technique citywide has been repeatedly delayed. Instead of reaching 29 welfare centers by the end of 1999, as the administration has said was its goal, it has been in only 5 since December, when Ms. Pollock's $20,000 consulting contract ended. City officials said that even with this modest start, the program helped 2,500 families to maintain housing or move to new apartments.</p>
        <p>But the effort to bring new legal aid groups into the pool of contractors that defend tenants in housing court failed. Ultimately, the city backed down on its ban on any class-action lawsuits, and Legal Aid, along with all the other groups that had long defended welfare clients, won contracts again. The bid submitted by Community Law was rejected in late July.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
