<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bessies, Performance Awards, Honor Innovative Efforts</title>
    <meta content="18BESS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/arts/18BESS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Dance and Performance Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bessie Awards</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dance Theater Workshop</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E6DF163BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="490" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bessies, Performance Awards, Honor Innovative Efforts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dance Theater Workshop presents annual New York Dance and Performance Awards (Bessies); photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 16th annual New York Dance and Performance Awards, familiarly known as the Bessies in honor of Bessie Schonberg, a noted teacher of dance composition, were given on Friday night at the Joyce Theater. This year's awards, presented by Dance Theater Workshop, celebrated both innovation and continuity.</p>
        <p>One of three special citations went to Micki Wesson, an administrator and consultant for many cultural organizations. She championed new choreography in her acceptance speech, but also remarked, ''I'm so grateful for being old enough to have seen so many of the dancers who've been mentioned tonight.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 16th annual New York Dance and Performance Awards, familiarly known as the Bessies in honor of Bessie Schonberg, a noted teacher of dance composition, were given on Friday night at the Joyce Theater. This year's awards, presented by Dance Theater Workshop, celebrated both innovation and continuity.</p>
        <p>One of three special citations went to Micki Wesson, an administrator and consultant for many cultural organizations. She championed new choreography in her acceptance speech, but also remarked, ''I'm so grateful for being old enough to have seen so many of the dancers who've been mentioned tonight.''</p>
        <p>Other special citations were awarded to the International Association of Blacks in Dance, which is devoted to promoting and preserving dances by people of African ancestry, and to Francis Mason, a critic and editor who has served as chairman of the Martha Graham Center of Contemporary Dance.</p>
        <p>Speaking of the adminstratively troubled Graham organization, he said, ''The question now is how to save Graham's dances.'' But, noting the Graham dancers' desire to continue, he promised, ''We'll be back.''</p>
        <p>A sense of determination was also evident at the start of the program when present and former members of the Martha Graham Dance Company and Martha Graham Ensemble crossed the stage in a solemn processional.</p>
        <p>For the first time cash awards of either $500 or $1,000, made possible by the magazine Time Out New York and other donors, went to the winners, who were chosen by a committee.</p>
        <p>These were the categories and winners of the awards:</p>
        <p>Choreographers and creators: Marie Chouinard, Sarah East Johnson, Stephan Koplowitz, Inbal Pinto, Yvonne Rainer, Herbin Van Cayseele (Tamango), David Rousseve, Gus Solomons Jr. and Merian Soto.</p>
        <p>Performance installation and new media: Seiji Shimoda.</p>
        <p>Performers: Peter Boal, Stacy Dawson, Carmen DeLavallade, Francie Huber, Gwen Welliver and Greg Zuccolo.</p>
        <p>Composers: Robert Een and Straylight (a trio made up of Jason Finkelman, Charles Cohen and Geoff Gersh).</p>
        <p>Lighting and visual design: Matayo Wumni Olaiya, Paul Kaiser, Shelly Eshkar, Suzanne Gallo (posthumously), Aaron Copp, Nadia Lauro and Atsushi Kitagawara.</p>
        <p>The masters of ceremonies were David Dorfman and David Neumann, a replacement for Dan Froot, who remained with his wife in Los Angeles to await the impending birth of twins. Assisted by Ms. Dawson, they provided comic banter throughout the three-hour program, which began with greetings by David R. White, executive director and producer of Dance Theater Workshop, and Laurie Uprichard, executive director of the Danspace Project at St. Mark's Church.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
