<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.B.I. Is Under Scrutiny For Conduct in Lee Case</title>
    <meta content="Y18FBI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/national/18FBI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">China-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Alamos National Laboratory</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeh, Louis J (Dir)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Wen Ho</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E6D7163BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.B.I. Is Under Scrutiny For Conduct in Lee Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Critics of Federal Bureau of Investigation say agency's handling of Wen Ho Lee case, in which agents tracked nuclear scientist for years and at times pressed him to confess, revived memories of era of J Edgar Hoover era when FBI was accused of intimidating and abusive tactics; director, Louis J Freeh, defends investigation, but begins formal review of agency's conduct; says evidence remains uncontradicted that Lee copied large amounts of sensitive data without explanation onto 10 computer tapes, only three of which have been found; says Lee's willingness to explain what he did with tapes justifies settlement; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To critics of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the Wen Ho Lee case, in which agents tracked the nuclear scientist for years and at times pressed him to confess, revived memories of the J. Edgar Hoover era when the F.B.I. was accused of intimidating and abusive tactics.</p>
        <p>Louis J. Freeh, the F.B.I. director, has defended the agency's investigation, but he has also begun a formal review of the F.B.I.'s conduct, agency officials said. Mr. Freeh is likely to face critical scrutiny in Congressional hearings next week after James A. Parker, the federal district judge in the case, called it a national embarrassment and President Clinton said he was ''quite troubled.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To critics of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the Wen Ho Lee case, in which agents tracked the nuclear scientist for years and at times pressed him to confess, revived memories of the J. Edgar Hoover era when the F.B.I. was accused of intimidating and abusive tactics.</p>
        <p>Louis J. Freeh, the F.B.I. director, has defended the agency's investigation, but he has also begun a formal review of the F.B.I.'s conduct, agency officials said. Mr. Freeh is likely to face critical scrutiny in Congressional hearings next week after James A. Parker, the federal district judge in the case, called it a national embarrassment and President Clinton said he was ''quite troubled.''</p>
        <p>The uproar followed a decision by federal authorities to settle the case after charging Dr. Lee in a 59-count felony indictment in December 1999. The indictment, accusing Dr. Lee of transferring huge amounts of secret atomic research data from the classified computer system at Los Alamos weapons lab, came after authorities had spent years investigating him.</p>
        <p>In the end, Dr. Lee pleaded guilty only to a single count of mishandling classified material.</p>
        <p>Mr. Freeh defended the settlement in a statement Wednesday in which he made no mention of the criticism. He said the evidence remained uncontradicted that Dr. Lee had copied large amounts of sensitive data without explanation onto 10 computer tapes, only three of which had been found.</p>
        <p>Mr. Freeh said Dr. Lee's willingness, as part of the plea, to explain what he did with the tapes justified the settlement. ''In this case, as has happened often in the past, national security and criminal justice needs intersect,'' Mr. Freeh said. ''In some instances, prosecution must be forgone in favor of national security interests. In this case, both are served.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Freeh is out of the country until midweek, and F.B.I. officials have rallied to defend him, pointing out that other agencies were involved. The F.B.I. investigation was based on a referral from the Energy Department, which first raised suspicions about Dr. Lee. The decision to charge Dr. Lee with multiple counts was approved by Attorney General Janet Reno.</p>
        <p>But other law enforcement officials in the government said the F.B.I. was largely responsible. They said it was the F.B.I. that identified Dr. Lee as the prime suspect and remained fixed on him -- even as the inquiry went on for years without turning up any evidence of spying.</p>
        <p>Moreover, they said, Mr. Freeh, whose views about criminal cases are widely respected at the Justice Department, influenced others in the government to go along. One official said after the guilty plea, ''The F.B.I. sold Janet Reno a bill of goods.''</p>
        <p>Several former and current F.B.I. officials acknowledged that the Lee case was flawed.</p>
        <p>They said counterintelligence investigations were almost never solved quickly, but often required years of painstaking work. The Lee case proved nearly impenetrable, involving an accusation of a theft of nuclear secrets that supposedly occurred in the 1980's, but was not suspected until the 1990's.</p>
        <p>Some officials said institutional problems at the F.B.I. contributed to the breakdown of the Lee case -- an inquiry that remained a relatively low priority for nearly two years, until 1998, when Mr. Freeh, facing criticism in Congress over the government's failure to plug security leaks at weapons labs, ordered the investigation put on a fast track.</p>
        <p>Some officials said the case fell through the cracks of changing post-cold-war counterintelligence assumptions and priorities. China espionage had never been a top priority at the F.B.I. as it focused on the Soviet Union and East Bloc countries. But after the collapse of the Soviet empire in 1991, counterintelligence no longer seemed as important. Many top agents were transferred out of spy-catching units.</p>
        <p>In the swirl of change, the Lee case seemed to get lost, assigned not to one of the F.B.I.'s large offices in New York, Washington or Los Angeles, but to the Albuquerque office.</p>
        <p>In mid-1997, when Ms. Reno turned down a request by the F.B.I. to seek a special intelligence warrant to allow electronic surveillance of  Dr. Lee in an effort to jump-start the inquiry, F.B.I. officials protested, but did not alert Mr. Freeh. And he, in turn, did not appeal to Ms. Reno.</p>
        <p>Ms. Reno had ruled that the evidence against Dr. Lee was too fragmentary and dated to justify a surveillance warrant.</p>
        <p>The debate over the warrant still divides F.B.I. and Justice Department officials. Some argue that a last chance was lost to establish Dr. Lee's guilt or prove his innocence.</p>
        <p>Without electronic eavesdropping, agents were stymied. But they seemed determined to show that Dr. Lee was the key to Chinese espionage at Los Alamos.</p>
        <p>Two agents interrogated Dr. Lee at the Los Alamos lab on March 7, 1999, and adopted a bullying approach. An edited transcript of the interrogation shows that the agents asked him repeatedly to explain why he had failed a polygraph examination administered a month earlier.</p>
        <p>''But Wen Ho, I'm telling you,'' one of the agents said, ''the facts are right here! The facts are, if you're saying you didn't do anything, that's not what this shows. All of the polygraphs that you're taking, and all the stuff you're telling everybody, you're failing! Why are you failing your polygraphs?''</p>
        <p>''I don't know,'' Dr. Lee replied. ''I, I, I, I don't know why I fail, but I do know I have not done anything, I have not done anything.'' Dr. Lee added: ''I never give classified information to Chinese people. I never tell them anything relating to nuclear weapons, uh, data or design or whatever, I have never done anything like that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
