<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Romanian Lifters Fail Their Drug Test</title>
    <meta content="18OLYM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weight Lifting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nandrolone (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Romania</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Norway</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Olympic Committee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pound, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cihareau, Traian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mateas, Adrian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimseth, Stian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Weight Lifting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight Lifting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E1D7163BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Romanian Lifters Fail Their Drug Test</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Monday, Sept. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>International Olympic Committee's top anti-doping official Dick Pound says that he is cautiously optimistic about new resolve to catch athletes who are using illicit performance-enhancing substances; Romanian weight lifters Traian Cihareau and Adrian Mateas test positive for steroid nandrolone; Norweigan weight lifter Stian Grimseth is also banned for drug use (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The International Olympic Committee's top anti-doping official said today that he was cautiously optimistic about a new resolve to catch athletes who are using illicit performance-enhancing substances.</p>
        <p>Weight lifting, rife with doping scandals through the years, has been embarrassed again at these Games. The entire Romanian weight lifting team was expelled from the Olympics on Sunday after two of its members -- Traian Cihareau and Adrain Mateas -- tested positive for the steroid nandrolone. However, weight lifting's international governing body today lifted a ban on the four members who had not tested positive in the Games. Romania will instead pay a $50,000 fine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The International Olympic Committee's top anti-doping official said today that he was cautiously optimistic about a new resolve to catch athletes who are using illicit performance-enhancing substances.</p>
        <p>Weight lifting, rife with doping scandals through the years, has been embarrassed again at these Games. The entire Romanian weight lifting team was expelled from the Olympics on Sunday after two of its members -- Traian Cihareau and Adrain Mateas -- tested positive for the steroid nandrolone. However, weight lifting's international governing body today lifted a ban on the four members who had not tested positive in the Games. Romania will instead pay a $50,000 fine.</p>
        <p>Also today, Stian Grimseth, a Norwegian weight lifter, was expelled from the Games after testing positive for banned drugs, a Norwegian team official said.</p>
        <p>China removed 27 athletes from its Olympic team before the Games began, saying later that many of them had recorded suspicious blood tests indicating use of the endurance drug EPO. Seventeen other athletes, including four weight lifters, were removed from their teams for doping infractions discovered before the Games.</p>
        <p>And Dieter Baumann of Germany, the 1992 5,000-meter champion, had his two-year suspension upheld today by an arbitration panel of track and field's international governing body. Baumann tested positive for the steroid nandrolone last Oct. 19 and Nov. 12. He had appealed the suspension, contending he was the victim of a plot when traces of the drug were found in toothpaste he supposedly used. He had hoped to be reinstated in time to compete in the 5,000 preliminaries on Sept. 27.</p>
        <p>The number of drug suspensions related to the Sydney Games is now approaching 50 -- only 48 athletes had previously been punished for doping violations at the Summer Games since drug testing was introduced in 1968.</p>
        <p>''There are people in this business who think a positive drug test is a failure; I'm of the opposite view,'' said Dick Pound, an I.O.C. vice president from Montreal and the head of the World Anti-Doping Agency. ''It's a sign that things are working. Whether it's short of perfection is hardly material. It's keeping people away who might otherwise have competed and it's catching people here who might not otherwise have been caught. It's a work in progress, but for the first time I'm starting to feel cautiously optimistic about this.''</p>
        <p>The entire Romanian lifting team had been expelled under a ''three strikes'' rule that calls for the removal of a team if three members test positive in one year. The $50,000 fine prevents a complete ban, in accordance with the rules of the International Weightlifting Federation.</p>
        <p>SWIMMING  Malchow Continues Record Run</p>
        <p>Tom Malchow set an Olympic record today in preliminaries for the 200-meter butterfly. The 24-year-old Malchow, who holds the world record, cut 0.01 seconds off the mark set by the American Melvin Stewart in winning the 1992 gold medal. He finished in 1 minute 56.25 seconds.</p>
        <p>Malchow qualified for the semifinals, along with 15-year-old Michael Phelps, the youngest member of the American men's team since 1932. Phelps qualified third fastest in 1:57.30. (AP)</p>
        <p>BOXING  Juarez Wins Easily</p>
        <p>Ricardo Rocky Juarez, the 125-pound world champion from Houston, blasted his way past Bijan Batmani of Iran, stopping him today in the third round on the 15-point rule.</p>
        <p>Juarez boxed cautiously in the first round. He stepped up the pace, landing crunching rights to the head for a 12-0 lead after two rounds and finished the match with a right uppercut that made it 15-0. Jeff Lacy followed with a second dominating performance, stopping Cleiton Conceicao of Brazil, 17-2, at 165 pounds. (AP)</p>
        <p>ROWING  U.S. and Britain Suffer Setback</p>
        <p>The United States men's eights, the world champions, and their main gold medal rival, Britain, suffered surprising defeats today in heats at the rowing regatta.</p>
        <p>The Americans, world champions for the past three years, finished second to Croatia by more than two seconds and now face the elimination repechage on Wednesday in a bid to qualify for Sunday's final. The same task faces the British after they lost to Australia, beaten by nearly two seconds. (Reuters)</p>
        <p>SHOOTING  China Wins Gold in Air Rifle</p>
        <p>Cai Yalin of China won the gold medal in 10-meter air rifle today with an Olympic-record score of 696.4. He broke the mark of 695.7 set in 1996 by this year's silver medalist, Artem Khadjibekov of Russia, who scored 695.1 today. Russia's Yevgeny Aleinikov had 693.8 points to earn the bronze.</p>
        <p>Cai had 594 points in the qualifying to top Khadjibekov and Aleinikov, who were tied for second with 592 points. Jason Parker, of Omaha, finished fifth with 693.1 points. (AP)</p>
        <p>TRACK AND FIELD  Jamaicans May Protest Relays</p>
        <p>Members of Jamaica's track team threatened to boycott Olympic relay events to protest Merlene Ottey being given a spot on the Jamaican team in the 100 meters. The men are among the favorites in the 4x100 relay, and the women are expected to challenge the United States in the 4x400 relay.</p>
        <p>Danny McFarlane, a 400 runner, said that team officials had announced that Ottey would compete in the 100 in place of Peta-Gaye Dowdie, who beat Ottey in the Olympic trials. He said he would bow out of the 4x400 relay but run in his individual event.</p>
        <p>Ottey, 40, is returning from a one-year ban from international competition after traces of the steroid nandrolone were found in her system. She placed fourth in the 100 at the Jamaican trials in July, behind Dowdie, Beverley McDonald and Tanya Lawrence. The four were picked to run in the 4x100 relay. (AP)</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
