<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kicking Unit Is Criticized</title>
    <meta content="18BLUE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/sports/18BLUE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: EXTRA POINTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Bears</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Chicago Bears</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E1D8163BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="519" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kicking Unit Is Criticized</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giants victory over Chicago Bears discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Giants Coach Jim Fassel called the field-goal unit atrocious following the game, and he wasn't exaggerating. The Giants missed three field-goal attempts that could have turned a tight 14-7 victory into an easier afternoon.</p>
        <p>Brad Daluiso had a 34-yard field- goal attempt in the second quarter go wide left and later received no help from his teammates. On the next possession, Daluiso attempted a 41-yarder, but the ball barely left the ground and went straight into the offensive line. The holder Brad Maynard, also the Giants' punter, said he was unable to hold a low snap from center Jason Whittle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Giants Coach Jim Fassel called the field-goal unit atrocious following the game, and he wasn't exaggerating. The Giants missed three field-goal attempts that could have turned a tight 14-7 victory into an easier afternoon.</p>
        <p>Brad Daluiso had a 34-yard field- goal attempt in the second quarter go wide left and later received no help from his teammates. On the next possession, Daluiso attempted a 41-yarder, but the ball barely left the ground and went straight into the offensive line. The holder Brad Maynard, also the Giants' punter, said he was unable to hold a low snap from center Jason Whittle.</p>
        <p>Chicago's Mike Wells was credited for pushing a Giants player into the ball. The Bears recovered at their 26-yard line and scored with 18 seconds left in the half for a 7-7 tie.</p>
        <p>The field-goal unit's last and potentially most costly mistake was not blocking on Daluiso's 31-yard attempt with 1 minute 8 seconds left in the game. The Giants led 14-7 and were trying to seal the victory. But Chicago's Mike Brown dove for and blocked the ball.</p>
        <p>''The only thing that's frustrating for me is, as a kicker, you're based 100 percent on your stats and today's statistically is a terrible day,'' Daluiso said. ''I didn't kick any better or worse than I ever kick.''</p>
        <p>Daluiso had made his first four field goal attempts this season.</p>
        <p>Time Ran Out</p>
        <p>Officials could not make a decision on a video replay within the allotted 90-second limit, so they upheld a second-quarter call. Marcus Robinson caught a 37-yard pass in the end zone, but was ruled out of bounds. Because the play occurred in the final two minutes, officials decided to review their own call but couldn't decide, so the play stood. Three plays later, Chicago scored for a 7-7 tie.</p>
        <p>A Clean Play</p>
        <p>Quarterback Kerry Collins appeared to have his face mask grabbed by Bears defensive end Troy Wilson with three minutes left, but Collins later told Coach Jim Fassel that Wilson cleanly grabbed his helmet. . . . Fassel challenged a second-quarter play and lost. On a flea flicker, Giants receiver Ike Hilliard lost control of a sinking pass from Collins as he rolled on the ground in the end zone. . . . The Bears rookie linebacker Brian Urlacher, starting his first game, had 13 tackles and one sack. . . . Joe Montgomery, last year's second-round pick, was inactive for the third time in as many games. Montgomery has been unable to make the active roster as he tries to adjust to playing fullback and special teams. . . . The Giants rookie cornerback Ralph Brown remained in Chicago last night for observation of a bruised kidney. Brown took a knee to the abdomen in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>RAFAEL HERMOSO</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL: EXTRA POINTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
