<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="18MBRF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/nyregion/18MBRF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231668"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E5D8163BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: HEATING OIL WARNING -- Senator Charles E. Schumer yesterday said the price of home heating oil in the New York area could reach $3 a gallon by winter, nearly double last week's price of $1.59 in New York City and $1.61 on Long Island. At a Manhattan news conference, Senator Schumer again called on President Clinton to release 30 million barrels of oil from the government's 570 million barrel strategic petroleum reserve to ensure supply and help curb price increases. The senator based his projections on a study from Fimat USA, an energy market analysis firm. The Oil Heat Institute of Long Island, a trade group, has also said prices exceeding last year's peak of $2.40 a gallon were possible.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: MASS HELD FOR WORKERS -- A Roman Catholic Mass was held in Brooklyn over the weekend for several hundred workers on strike for 15 months against the Domino Sugar refinery here. The workers have complained that organized labor and elected officials have shown them scant support. But Ted H. Jacobsen, secretary of the New York City Central Labor Council, said yesterday that representatives of 40 local unions attended the Mass on Saturday at Our Lady of Mount Carmel Church in Brooklyn and Peter Vallone, the City Council speaker, and other officials spoke at it.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: HEATING OIL WARNING -- Senator Charles E. Schumer yesterday said the price of home heating oil in the New York area could reach $3 a gallon by winter, nearly double last week's price of $1.59 in New York City and $1.61 on Long Island. At a Manhattan news conference, Senator Schumer again called on President Clinton to release 30 million barrels of oil from the government's 570 million barrel strategic petroleum reserve to ensure supply and help curb price increases. The senator based his projections on a study from Fimat USA, an energy market analysis firm. The Oil Heat Institute of Long Island, a trade group, has also said prices exceeding last year's peak of $2.40 a gallon were possible.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: MASS HELD FOR WORKERS -- A Roman Catholic Mass was held in Brooklyn over the weekend for several hundred workers on strike for 15 months against the Domino Sugar refinery here. The workers have complained that organized labor and elected officials have shown them scant support. But Ted H. Jacobsen, secretary of the New York City Central Labor Council, said yesterday that representatives of 40 local unions attended the Mass on Saturday at Our Lady of Mount Carmel Church in Brooklyn and Peter Vallone, the City Council speaker, and other officials spoke at it.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>ELLENVILLE: FIRE AT CATSKILL HOTEL -- A smoky fire at the Nevele Grande Hotel led to the evacuation of nearly 200 guests in a wing of the resort in the Catskill Mountains. The fire caused no major injuries but several guests and two firefighters were treated at the scene. Reza Razzazan, the hotel's general manager, said yesterday that the fire began Saturday in a first-floor closet but that inspectors were unable to determine the cause immediately. ''Everything was fine by the evening,'' Mr. Razzazan said. ''We had a barbecue.''</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>UTICA: CONGRESSIONAL RACE NARROWS -- Tensions over an Indian land claim have helped cloud the re-election bid of Representative Sherwood Boehlert, a Republican. Mr. Boehlert, 63, is seeking his 10th term in the House of Representatives. In last week's primary, he won 56 percent to 44 percent against David Vickers, who will run in the general election on the Conservative and Right to Life lines. A dairy farmer and political rookie, Richard Engelbrecht, is the Democratic nominee for the 23rd District seat. The pollster John Zogby predicted that Mr. Boehlert will win but said voters were attracted to Mr. Vickers in part because he opposes the Oneida Indian tribe's seeking compensation for 250,000 acres in Oneida and Madison Counties.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC CITY: CROSSING THE TIME LINE -- If gamblers saw clocks while they were gambling, according to an unspoken casino taboo, they might realize how long they had been gambling and leave. Now, a new casino room is breaking that taboo. Coyote Kate's Slot Parlor, part of the Wild, Wild West casino at Bally's Park Place, has a clock at the top of a 30-foot tower. It is the only clock in any of Atlantic City's 12 casinos, not counting those in restaurants, stores and public spaces. The clock taboo is ''strictly old-school casino thinking,'' said Wallace Barr, executive vice president of Park Place Entertainment Corporation, the casino's owner.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>TRENTON: TEACHER TENURE OPPOSED -- A majority of New Jersey residents think public school teachers should not have tenure, according to a Gannett New Jersey poll released yesterday. When asked if tenure should be retained or abolished, 59 percent of those responding said it should be scrapped, while 30 percent favored keeping it. Meanwhile, 7 out of 10 of those surveyed said teachers' pay should be based on performance. Lynn Maher, a New Jersey Education Association spokeswoman, said many people do not understand that tenure simply requires hearings for teachers before they can be fired.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>MONTVILLE: GIRL DIES FROM E. COLI -- Lauren Mansel, 12, became the third person in the state this year to be killed by an E. coli infection when she died on Thursday at Connecticut Children's Medical Center in Hartford. She was brought to the hospital after exhibiting symptoms more than two weeks ago. Family members say they do not know how Lauren ingested the bacteria. Health officials say they believe Lauren's case is an isolated one and say there is no public health threat. An epidemiologist from the Department of Public Health is to investigate the death.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CALENDAR  Today</p>
        <p>PRETRIAL HEARING FOR BIERENBAUM -- A pretrial hearing in State Supreme Court in Manhattan is scheduled to continue today in the murder case against Dr. Robert Bierenbaum, accused of killing his wife, Gail Katz-Bierenbaum, who disappeared in 1985.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
