<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bucking the Swing-State Trend, Ohio Holding Steady, Polls Show</title>
    <meta content="18OHIO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/politics/18OHIO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000919T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="BATTLEGROUNDS" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VOTERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ohio</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Midwestern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Apple, R W Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E2D8163BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1931" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bucking the Swing-State Trend, Ohio Holding Steady, Polls Show</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Apple, R W Jr</byline>
      <dateline>COLUMBUS, Ohio, Sept. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Battlegrounds, second article in series on four states likely to be critical to outcome of presidential race, finds Gov George W Bush holding reasonably steady lead in Ohio, bucking trend in which Pennsylvania and several other swing states may have shifted toward Vice Pres Al Gore; polls indicate candidates have both built solid partisan bases within state, considered political microcosm since Civil War, and are fighting over perhaps 5 to 6 percent of electorate, composed largely of independents, suburban residents and women; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pennsylvania and several other swing states may have shifted toward Vice President Al Gore in the presidential race in the last three weeks, but so far Ohio has more or less stayed put, if surveys of voters are to be believed.</p>
        <p>In polls by various organizations starting in May, Mr. Gore's main rival, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, has held a reasonably steady lead. A recent survey, completed before Labor Day by The Columbus Dispatch, gave him a lead of six percentage points, 49 to 43, with a margin of sampling error of 2 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pennsylvania and several other swing states may have shifted toward Vice President Al Gore in the presidential race in the last three weeks, but so far Ohio has more or less stayed put, if surveys of voters are to be believed.</p>
        <p>In polls by various organizations starting in May, Mr. Gore's main rival, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, has held a reasonably steady lead. A recent survey, completed before Labor Day by The Columbus Dispatch, gave him a lead of six percentage points, 49 to 43, with a margin of sampling error of 2 percent.</p>
        <p>One of the state's leading academic pollsters said, ''This race hasn't changed a lick in Ohio in the last six months.'' Some politicians see progress for Mr. Gore, but they think that he still has ground to make up.</p>
        <p>Which is a bit odd, because this Midwestern state has been considered a political microcosm since the Civil War. Bill Clinton carried it twice (albeit by fewer than 100,000 votes in 1992). Jimmy Carter, Ronald Reagan and George Bush took it in the three elections before that, and in 1984, 1988 and 1996, the voting breakdown here almost exactly matched the national pattern.</p>
        <p>The last time Ohio voted against the grain was 1960; although he drew  big crowds, John F. Kennedy lost here; he said the state broke his heart.</p>
        <p>It may be that Ohio, never a very trendy place, is a bit slower to react to changes in the national campaign than are the other big battleground states. It may be that the state Democratic Party's striking lack of recent electoral successes is beginning to take a toll in the party's organization. Or it may be that demographic changes are making Ohio less typical.</p>
        <p>Whatever the explanation may be, Mr. Bush's continued strength here is very good news for a campaign that has been short of good news lately -- and no Republican has ever been elected president without carrying Ohio.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's strategists insist that he can catch Mr. Bush here. With nine paid field operatives already in the state, the Gore campaign decided this week to send in 15 more. And the vice president shows no sign of reducing his campaigning or his television spending in the state, even in the heavily and ancestrally Republican Cincinnati area. He has been there four times this year, and he unveiled his $500 billion tax-cut plan there this summer.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Mr. Gore and his running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut, rode school buses from the Dayton area through Middletown to Cincinnati, trailed by a procession of limousines, regular buses, vans and motorcycles. The idea was to draw attention to the Democrats' prescriptions for education.</p>
        <p>Representative Tom Sawyer of Akron, a Democrat, conceded that ''Gore had trouble getting traction here, and a month ago people in our own party were saying he was on his last legs.'' But he said Mr. Gore's emphasis on issues in his speech at the Democratic convention had made a big difference.</p>
        <p>''At least this is a contested state now,'' Mr. Sawyer said. ''We have a decent chance to carry it.''</p>
        <p>Party officials here estimated that the two campaigns and two major parties have already spent $11 million on television commercials in Ohio. It is a costly state, which includes all or part of 12 media markets, including big ones centered on Cleveland, Columbus, Cincinnati, Dayton and Toledo.</p>
        <p>William A. Burga, president of the Ohio A.F.L.-C.I.O., which has more than 800,000 members, said he thought Mr. Gore was spending far too much time in Cincinnati and needed to go ''where his base is -- the northern, northeastern, southeastern parts of Ohio.''</p>
        <p>Still, all the available evidence suggests that Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore have both built solid partisan bases here, and that they are fighting over perhaps 5 to 6 percent of the electorate, composed largely of independents, suburban residents and women.</p>
        <p>Few swing voters in Ohio are white, working-class ethnics like such voters in other states, said Dean Lacey, an assistant professor of political science at Ohio State University.</p>
        <p>Instead, Mr. Lacey said, they are mostly suburban women -- ''soccer moms'' -- as well as former supporters of Ross Perot who would have liked the chance to vote for Gov. Jesse Ventura of Minnesota, and a fair number of middle-class African-Americans attracted by the Republicans' support for school vouchers. Mr. Perot took 21 percent of the Ohio vote in 1992, although his total fell back to 11 percent four years later.</p>
        <p>Kelly Craiglow, 33, who describes herself as a ''stay-at-home mom'' and lives in Lancaster, a small city southeast of here, is just the sort of voter Mr. Gore needs to win over if he is to carry Ohio. She leans to Mr. Bush because she is a Republican, she said in an interview, but having worked for a time in a pharmacy, she is very worried about the cost of prescription drugs.</p>
        <p>''Old people came in there and spent all their money on prescriptions,'' Ms. Craiglow said. ''It was sad, and then they ran completely out of money and had to rely on the government.''</p>
        <p>Although aware that both Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore had plans to deal with the problem, she acknowledged that she had not taken the time to study and compare them. But she said she would watch the debates and ''probably vote for whichever one sounds as if he is going to be able to help those people a little.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore may have more trouble reaching voters like Elaine Medsker, 71, who works part time at a hospital near her home in Geauga County, east of Cleveland. Her comments dealt with character, not policy questions.</p>
        <p>''I've been very depressed by Mr. Clinton. He's a sleazy person, and Gore's not far behind,'' said Mrs. Medsker, a Republican who has voted for Democrats for president in the past. ''Gore makes so many promises, one after another, and you know he can't deliver on them. Now, President Bush was a good man, an honest man, and I think he has a good influence on his son.''</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Sawyer, Mr. Burga said he had detected some recent movement toward Mr. Gore, whether or not it had been reflected in the polls.  People were beginning to volunteer in larger numbers, he said, ''as the vice president starts to focus on the issues our members think about, like prescription drugs, education and Social Security.''</p>
        <p>Labor has changed its tactics for this campaign, Mr. Burga said. It is putting new emphasis on getting campaign materials into the hands of every local union official in the state. He said he hoped that workers would respond more enthusiastically to the urging of their elected leaders than ''to what some bunch of guys in Washington or Columbus tells them that they ought to do.''</p>
        <p>How much the state Democratic Party will be able to contribute to the Gore effort is questionable. The Republicans have a strong organization, built up over many decades by chairmen like Ray C. Bliss, who went on to head the Republican National Committee, and the incumbent, Robert T. Bennett.</p>
        <p>At the moment, the Republicans here, led by Gov. Bob Taft, hold every statewide constitutional office and both Senate seats, plus solid margins in the Congressional delegation (11-8), the State Senate (21-12) and the State House of Representatives (59-40). The Democrats have been having trouble recruiting strong candidates; as a result, Senator Michael DeWine, no political superman, is expected to win easily this fall over the untested Ted Celeste, a Democrat who is the brother of former Gov. Richard F. Celeste. If so, Mr. DeWine would be the first Republican senator from Ohio to win re-election since John W. Bricker did it in 1952.</p>
        <p>Representative John R. Kasich, the Columbus Republican who made a brief run for the Republican presidential nomination last year, argued that the State Democratic Party would be of little help to Mr. Gore in November.</p>
        <p>''Gore will pay a price for the Democrats' weakened condition,'' Mr. Kasich said. ''They're in a shambles. The only thing I can compare it to is the lousy condition of our own party in the 1970's as a result of Watergate.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kasich is retiring. His district, once considered marginal, is now leaning slightly toward the Republican nominee, Pat Tiberi, the majority leader in the State House. But Mr. Tiberi has been distancing himself from Mr. Bush's 10-year, $1.3 trillion tax-cut proposal, focusing instead on more modest measures, like eliminating the inheritance tax.</p>
        <p>''Insurance,'' an Ohio Republican consultant said. ''If Gore demolishes Bush's tax plan in the debates next month, Tiberi doesn't want to pay.''</p>
        <p>Big industrial unions like the steelworkers, in Cleveland and Youngstown; the automobile workers, in the Cleveland area; and the rubber workers, in Akron, used to be strong in Ohio. But now the dominant unions are those for teachers (the Ohio Education Association has 120,000 members) and the state, county and municipal workers, with 105,000.</p>
        <p>The Kasich district exemplifies the demographic changes that are transforming Ohio. Columbus is now the largest city (though not the largest metropolitan area) in the state, supplanting Cleveland. Its growth is in white-collar jobs at Ohio State, insurance companies like Nationwide and banks like Bank One, rather than the industrial jobs on which the state once depended.</p>
        <p>Delaware County, which forms the northern part of the district, used to be a bucolic place. The town of Delaware, the county seat and the home of Ohio Wesleyan University, still plays host to one of harness racing's main events, the Little Brown Jug, each September. (Brown jug banners were hanging from lamp poles there this week.) But the county is fast filling up with new, prosperous, Republican-leaning suburbs.</p>
        <p>Despite the large number of liberal-arts colleges, Ohio stands in the bottom quarter of states in the percentage of residents who are college graduates. And according to one recent survey, Ohio ranks in the bottom third in number of technology-driven businesses.</p>
        <p>''Our demographics are slowly drifting away from the national norms,'' said Mike Curtin, the associate publisher of The Dispatch, who has been watching elections in Ohio for decades. ''We're aging; we're exporting our college graduates; and we're not very involved in the new economy. We're not going to be the barometer we have been.</p>
        <p>''The state's still in play, of course, but the hill Democratic candidates have to climb gets a degree or two steeper every four years or so.''</p>
        <p>Battlegrounds</p>
        <p>This is the second article in a series about four swing states that are likely to be critical to the outcome of the presidential race. Later articles will look at Wisconsin and Michigan. An earlier article looked at Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VOTERS  Correction:  September 19, 2000, Tuesday  One map yesterday in a grouping with an article about the importance of Ohio in the presidential race showed erroneous calculations of population density by county. Here is a corrected version.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 19, 2000, Tuesday  One map yesterday in a grouping with an article about the importance of Ohio in the presidential race showed erroneous calculations of population density by county. A corrected version appears today, on Page A20.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 19, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>One map yesterday in a grouping with an article about the importance of Ohio in the presidential race showed erroneous calculations of population density by county. Here is a corrected version.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>Correction: September 19, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>One map yesterday in a grouping with an article about the importance of Ohio in the presidential race showed erroneous calculations of population density by county. A corrected version appears today, on Page A20.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
