<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Forsakes Effort to Curb Poppy Growth By Afghans</title>
    <meta content="Y18AFG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/world/18AFGH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Taliban (Afghan Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wren, Christopher S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E4DD163BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="707" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Forsakes Effort to Curb Poppy Growth By Afghans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER S. WREN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wren, Christopher S</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Sept. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>UN winds down efforts to persuade farmers in Afghanistan, world's largest producer of opium, to switch to alternative legal crops out of frustration with declining support from Western donors and indifference of ruling Taliban (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Frustrated by declining support from Western donors and the indifference of the ruling Taliban, the United Nations is winding down efforts to persuade farmers in Afghanistan, the world's largest producer of opium, to switch to alternative legal crops.</p>
        <p>Ghorak, Khakrez and Maiwand, three districts of Kandahar province where the United Nations set up pilot programs promoting alternative crops, have recorded decreases in poppy cultivation of at least 50 percent, according to the latest annual survey of the United Nations International Drug Control Program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Frustrated by declining support from Western donors and the indifference of the ruling Taliban, the United Nations is winding down efforts to persuade farmers in Afghanistan, the world's largest producer of opium, to switch to alternative legal crops.</p>
        <p>Ghorak, Khakrez and Maiwand, three districts of Kandahar province where the United Nations set up pilot programs promoting alternative crops, have recorded decreases in poppy cultivation of at least 50 percent, according to the latest annual survey of the United Nations International Drug Control Program.</p>
        <p>''This demonstrates that the alternative development projects work very well,'' the program's executive director, Under Secretary General Pino Arlacchi, said here. Similar programs in Bolivia and Peru, he noted, led to sharp declines there in the cultivation of coca, the plant used to make cocaine.</p>
        <p>Despite United Nations efforts to convince Afghan farmers to switch to wheat and other food crops in return for compensation, Mr. Arlacchi said, ''Afghanistan remains by far the largest opium supplier in the world.''</p>
        <p>Now, with United Nations funding running out and opium still Afghanistan's leading cash crop, the pilot projects will end this year, Mr. Arlacchi said, ''given lack of financial and political support.''</p>
        <p>Afghanistan's production of opium, the essential raw ingredient of heroin, was estimated at just over 3,600 tons this year, a decline from the record 5,100 tons in 1999.</p>
        <p>But the drop was caused mainly by a severe drought in southern Afghanistan and not by any effort by the Taliban to make peasants grow something other than opium poppies. A previous decree that farmers reduce their areas under opium cultivation by one-third has been widely ignored by the farmers and the Taliban authorities.</p>
        <p>Half of Afghanistan's opium is consumed as heroin by addicts in neighboring Pakistan and Iran, Mr. Arlacchi said. The rest is smuggled out to heroin markets in Europe, usually via Turkey and the Balkans.</p>
        <p>Afghanistan planted nearly 203,000 acres in opium poppies this year, a slight decline from last year, again apparently because of bad weather. United Nations officials hoped that the drought might encourage some farmers to revert to traditional crops. But the poor harvest may leave indebted farmers with no choice but to keep raising opium.</p>
        <p>Opium growing is encouraged by Afghanistan's rugged, often remote terrain and a long-running civil war that has bred lawlessness and defiance of authority.</p>
        <p>Afghan farmers can earn about $14 per pound of opium, considerably more than they do from other crops, United Nations officials say. Roughly 10 pounds of raw opium are used to produce 1 pound of heroin. At the consuming end, the cost of a pound of uncut heroin in Europe or the United States can exceed $40,000.</p>
        <p>Opium poppies are grown in 22 of Afghanistan's 32 provinces, but 6 provinces in the south account for 92 percent of the opium producing area. Moreover, 97 percent of this land is irrigated, proof that precious water is diverted to opium poppies at the expense of other crops.</p>
        <p>The Taliban, a militant Islamic movement that fought its way into power, controls an estimated 91 percent of the Afghan villages visited by United Nations surveyors, compared with 9 percent controlled by opposition forces in the north. But the Taliban's territory contains 96 percent of the country's opium poppy fields, up from about 90 percent last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arlacchi visited Afghanistan three years ago and secured assurances of cooperation from the Taliban, which considers drug use contrary to Islamic precepts, at least in theory. Since then, he said, ''There was no substantial improvement in our relationship.''</p>
        <p>The United Nations drug control office will continue its annual survey of Afghanistan's opium cultivation and harvest yield, conducted by Afghan nationals who have been able to move about the country and interview opium growers and local officials.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
