<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patents; Training ligaments and heart valves in the laboratory, so they perform well after transplants.</title>
    <meta content="18PATE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/business/18PATE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231587"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Advance Tissue Sciences</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Institutes of Health</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chartrand, Sabra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Naughton, Gail (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Watson, John (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE6D61F38F93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patents; Training ligaments and heart valves in the laboratory, so they perform well after transplants.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sabra Chartrand</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chartrand, Sabra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Gail Nughton, president of Advance Tissue Sciences, and Dr John Watson, who heads National Institutes of Health tissue engineering coordinating committee, comment on advances in field of growing tissue outside body for transplants; Naughton, who holds 27 patents in field, has patented device that mimics physical conditions tissue will encounter when implanted in body and prompts tissue to develop needed strength and elasticity (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN her laboratory, Gail Naughton grows body parts. She nurtures cells until they divide and grow into heart valves, blood vessels, ligaments and tendons that she says look like they ''would have grown in your own body.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Naughton is a cell biologist and president of Advanced Tissue Sciences in La Jolla, Calif. In July, she was named inventor of the year for 2000 by the Intellectual Property Owners association for her work in growing tissue outside the body, a process known as tissue engineering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN her laboratory, Gail Naughton grows body parts. She nurtures cells until they divide and grow into heart valves, blood vessels, ligaments and tendons that she says look like they ''would have grown in your own body.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Naughton is a cell biologist and president of Advanced Tissue Sciences in La Jolla, Calif. In July, she was named inventor of the year for 2000 by the Intellectual Property Owners association for her work in growing tissue outside the body, a process known as tissue engineering.</p>
        <p>She owns 27 patents in the field. Her most recent covers a device that mimics the physical conditions the tissue will encounter when implanted in the body. Under those artificial conditions, the device prompts the tissue to develop the strength and elasticity it will need to do its job in the body.</p>
        <p>As a field, tissue engineering is only about 15 years old. But it has advanced so quickly that its scientists and researchers are also working on growing organs. They are closer, however, to the creation of ligaments, cartilage, valves and other tissue that perform less complex functions in the body.</p>
        <p>Nearly every major university and medical research institution has scientists at work on tissue engineering, and many other researchers and organizations hold patents for the technology. The National Institutes of  Health has awarded about a hundred grants related to tissue engineering, said Dr. John Watson, chairman of the tissue engineering coordinating committee at the N.I.H.</p>
        <p>''The beginning of this field held out the promise and the prospects, but now we are where the rubber hits the road,'' Dr. Watson said, ''and the development of tissue and organs that can be used clinically is a much greater challenge. But we all think those things are doable. The prospects are good. I think five years out, we'll begin to see it.''</p>
        <p>At the heart of tissue engineering, Dr. Naughton said, is a process that places a human cell on a degradable polymer ''and puts it within a bioreactor that simulates the conditions of the body.'' Within two to four weeks, the cell divides and secretes growth factors, along with collagen, elastins and other proteins, ''until all together it forms a functional living tissue.''</p>
        <p>That technology has led Advanced Tissue Sciences to animal studies of skin, ligament, cartilage and blood vessels grown in a laboratory. The company plans to begin human trials of cartilage and blood vessels next year. It has also done work in growing small pieces of liver, and recently won a federal grant for a 10-year project to ''grow a heart in a box,'' Dr. Naughton said, referring to the bioreactor.</p>
        <p>''We and others have already grown cardiac muscle in small pieces that when you put an electrical stimulus to it, it actually pulses,'' Dr. Naughton said. Creating a whole heart would theoretically involve growing more muscle, and adding the valves and blood vessels that her company is already working on. ''In our minds it's much easier to do that than to grow a whole liver, which is not only structurally complex but does so many complex functions in the body.''</p>
        <p>Growing ligament, cartilage, cardiac muscle, blood vessels and heart valves outside the body will rely on technology in Dr. Naughton's newest patent. It covers a container that is designed to push, pull and stress the growing tissue with the same force it will eventually encounter in the body.</p>
        <p>Ligaments grown under passive conditions like a petri dish have not been strong enough to do their job in the body, she said. So she developed a bioreactor with more invigorating growing conditions. Cells are placed on a scaffold housed at body temperature in a container the size of a table top.</p>
        <p>''It's made so that it mechanically pulls the edge of the tissue, literally pulls the scaffolding with increasing force during the growth period,'' Dr. Naughton said. ''As they're pulled, the cells get a signal that makes them secrete a denser protein, making them more dense and more elastic. So what you end up with is stronger and much more able to withstand  forces the ligament will see once in the body.''</p>
        <p>A similar process is used to grow heart valves.</p>
        <p>''Valves need to be able to withstand the tremendous pressure from blood pulsing through them as the heart beats,'' Dr. Naughton said. ''To create a live valve, we put the cells on the scaffold and gradually increase an amount of pulsing. But instead of pulsing blood, we pulse the liquid nutrient we feed the valve. Over time, with more force and frequency added, the valve sees the same force, the same opening and closing, that it's going to see in the body after implementation.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Watson from the N.I.H. said Dr. Naughton's patent for the bioreactor was important. ''Tissue engineering is now about active tissues, tissues that secrete growth factors, tissues that have to have a good knowledge of the biological rules in the body, so that they have the desired effect and don't have the undesired effect,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Naughton said the bioreactors like hers increased quality control in tissue engineering.</p>
        <p>''There are a couple of really important benefits of bioreactors,'' she said. ''First, the process can be automated, so pumps automatically feed nutritional fluid to the tissues for three or four weeks.</p>
        <p>''Second, because it's a closed system, it remains sterile,'' she continued. ''With a petri dish, every time you open it to feed the tissue, there's a potential for contamination. And last, it makes the process far more reproducible because you can make sure the same forces act on the tissue whether you're growing five at a time or a thousand at a time.''</p>
        <p>The Advanced Tissue Sciences bioreactor received patent 6,121,042.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
