<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Should Forget a Year Ago</title>
    <meta content="Y18CHAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/sports/18CHAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231630"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E6DC163BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="931" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Should Forget a Year Ago</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Murray Chass</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Baseball column discusses outlook for 3 game series between New York Mets and Atlanta Braves; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Well, here they go again, but is there any reason to think the ending will be any different this time? After all, a film buff can watch ''Casablanca'' over and over, and each time Ingrid Bergman will leave Humphrey Bogart at the airport.</p>
        <p>In this case, the Atlanta Braves always leave the Mets -- in second place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Well, here they go again, but is there any reason to think the ending will be any different this time? After all, a film buff can watch ''Casablanca'' over and over, and each time Ingrid Bergman will leave Humphrey Bogart at the airport.</p>
        <p>In this case, the Atlanta Braves always leave the Mets -- in second place.</p>
        <p>Sure, Tom Glavine, Atlanta's ranking veteran, said recently that the Braves are ''not going to win forever; we're not going to win our division for the rest of baseball.'' But is this the first season of the rest of baseball?</p>
        <p>As they did almost one year ago to the day, the Mets and the Braves open a three-game series in Atlanta tonight, then play another three-game series in New York next week. A Mets visit to Philadelphia and a Braves trip to Montreal separate the home-and-home series. Talk about deja vu, Yogi.</p>
        <p>The Mets, on the other hand, can do without the part of the deja vu that arose from their trip to Atlanta last year. Only one game behind the Braves when they arrived, they lost each game of the three-game series there, then lost their next four and what had been their three-and-a-half-game lead in the wild-card standing.</p>
        <p>Going into this series, the Mets lag three games behind the Braves and are five games ahead of the Arizona Diamondbacks in the race for the wild-card slot. The way the Mets have played this month, winning only 6 of 16 games, they can thank the Diamondbacks for allowing them to retain the wild-card lead.</p>
        <p>Typical of the Diamondbacks' disappointing play the past month was a situation in their game against the Braves yesterday. Behind, 2-1, they had the bases loaded with one out in the fourth inning when Matt Williams, who is supposed to be their big run producer, grounded into an inning-ending double play.</p>
        <p>But the Mets behaved just as meekly in Montreal yesterday, collecting all of four hits in a 5-0 loss that represented the 14th time in their last 21 games that they have scored three runs or fewer.</p>
        <p>The Mets haven't played well enough to overtake Atlanta, despite the Braves' uncharacteristically mediocre play during the past six weeks or so. Since the beginning of August, the Braves have been basically a .500 team. The Mets actually supplanted the Braves in first place during that stretch, but Atlanta's hiatus turned out to be brief, only two days.</p>
        <p>The most noticeable difference in the Braves has been the absence of the injured John Smoltz and the inability of any pitcher to replace him as No. 3 in the starting rotation, behind Greg Maddux and Tom Glavine.</p>
        <p>Kevin Millwood, who in his first two full seasons with the Braves compiled a 35-15 record, had been expected to step up to No. 3, not just in position but in production. But his victory over the Diamondbacks yesterday gave him a 10-11 record.</p>
        <p>The 7-1 victory left the Braves with an 88-61 record after 149 games, which vividly reflects the struggles they have seen. The record matches the worst they've had at this stage of the season since 1991, the season in which they began their string of eight consecutive division championships.</p>
        <p>That season their record was 85-64, and they were half a game from first place. In 1996 they also had an 88-61 record. In every other season they have ranged from 90 to 95 victories. With 92 victories last season, they won their next eight games, including four against the Mets, and emerged from the streak as division champions once more.</p>
        <p>When Maddux and Glavine pitched against the Mets in Atlanta a year ago, they had a combined 29-19 record. They go into this series -- Maddux is scheduled to pitch against Mike Hampton tonight, Glavine against Al Leiter on Wednesday night -- with a combined 36-15 record.</p>
        <p>When the teams played last year, John Rocker had not yet declared himself Mr. Misfit. Just a hard-throwing kid from Georgia, the relief pitcher gained saves in all three games in Atlanta. Now he's notorious and not as reliable, although his consistency has improved since the Mets faced him in late June and early July.</p>
        <p>Rocker has allowed no runs in his last eight appearances and has a 1.32 earned run average in his last 30 games. The Braves once again seem to be calling on him as their closer, letting Mike Remlinger and Kerry Ligtenberg serve as his setup relievers.</p>
        <p>But even more than having Rocker as a reminder of their disastrous September visit last year, the Mets have visions of Chipper Jones and the destruction he unloaded on them in that series. Jones slugged four home runs in the three games, each one a critical blow in the series sweep.</p>
        <p>His performance clinched the National League Most Valuable Player award for Jones. He's not a leading contender for the award this season, but if the Mets are looking for omens, they should be wary of one involving Jones.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, on Sept. 5, Jones hit two home runs against Randy Johnson. On that same date last season, Jones hit two home runs against the same Randy Johnson.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
