<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Old Ties to Serbia Still Bind Many in Montenegro</title>
    <meta content="Y18MON$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/world/18MONT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231627"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Independence Movements and Secession</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Montenegro</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Djukanovic, Milo (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/San Marino</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DD163BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Old Ties to Serbia Still Bind Many in Montenegro</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>KOLASIN, Montenegro</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Montenegrans are divided over moves toward independence by Pres Milo Djukanovic, who broke with Serbian Pres Slobodan Milosevic in 1997 and is now regarded by many as traitor to centuries of Montenegrin-Serbian brotherhood; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here in the stirring, ragged mountains of northern Montenegro, the Yugoslav Army patrols from the Breza barracks on one side of town, while the Montenegrin special police, dressed in army fatigues and carrying automatic weapons, roam from their barracks in a resort hotel, the Bjelasica, that once catered to skiers.</p>
        <p>They follow each other on the narrow roads with Balkan braggadocio, but neither side appears eager to fight. ''We keep an eye on each other,'' said one policeman. ''But everyone's tired of blood.'' Fatigue may be an insufficient tourniquet, however.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here in the stirring, ragged mountains of northern Montenegro, the Yugoslav Army patrols from the Breza barracks on one side of town, while the Montenegrin special police, dressed in army fatigues and carrying automatic weapons, roam from their barracks in a resort hotel, the Bjelasica, that once catered to skiers.</p>
        <p>They follow each other on the narrow roads with Balkan braggadocio, but neither side appears eager to fight. ''We keep an eye on each other,'' said one policeman. ''But everyone's tired of blood.'' Fatigue may be an insufficient tourniquet, however.</p>
        <p>Tiny Montenegro is the last remaining republic with Serbia in what is left of Yugoslavia, but under President Milo Djukanovic it is moving gingerly toward independence. Mr. Djukanovic has decided to boycott the elections called for Sept. 24 by the Yugoslav president, Slobodan Milosevic, who changed the Constitution to win another term.</p>
        <p>Here in Kolasin, a stronghold of pro-Yugoslav feeling, Montenegrins will go to vote anyway, casting their ballots for unity. Mr. Djukanovic, who broke away from Mr. Milosevic in 1997 and split Montenegro's governing party, is regarded as a traitor to centuries of Montenegrin-Serbian brotherhood. Mr. Milosevic's brother, Borislav, now the Yugoslav ambassador in Moscow, was born here, and their father is buried nearby; President Milosevic is not just a native son, but a fixture in the cosmos.</p>
        <p>''Until Milosevic dies he will be president of Yugoslavia,'' Dragomir Bulatovic said with fervor. ''It wouldn't be Yugoslavia unless Milosevic were president. We'd be like San Marino and controlled by the United States.''</p>
        <p>His friend, Milan Bulatovic, concurred. ''What Milosevic accomplished last year in Serbia, rebuilding the country, couldn't be done anywhere else in the world,'' he said. ''Here, Djukanovic just wants to sell the country to foreigners.''</p>
        <p>Major complaints here center on Mr. Djukanovic's management of the economy: dumping the Yugoslav dinar for the German mark, closing former state-owned enterprises, like a wood factory and a department store, swapping the management of another firm and laying off most of its workers, albeit -- for the moment -- at 70 percent of their pay.</p>
        <p>Along the chilly streets of low wooden houses and crumbling, angular public buildings constructed in the modernist-socialist style, skeptical citizens emerged from coffee houses to interrogate a foreigner, riled by the presence of an American whose government bombed Yugoslavia last year.</p>
        <p>''You killed our children!'' one man shouted, but Drasko Popovic told him to calm down, then apologized. This is a pro-Milosevic town, he said, run by the pro-Milosevic Socialist People's Party of Momir Bulatovic, and most people in this part of Montenegro, closest to Serbia, will vote in the elections.</p>
        <p>Most of the 5,000 people in town, and some 9,000 more in surrounding villages, want to stay united with Serbia, Mr. Popovic said. ''We don't like those people who are trying to push us apart to make money for themselves.''</p>
        <p>About 35 percent to 40 percent of Montenegro's 650,000 people support the union with Serbia, too large a minority for Mr. Djukanovic to ignore or idly antagonize. There are fears in the capital, Podgorica, that Mr. Milosevic will manipulate pro-Serbian feelings in this region and use the army -- and a special paramilitary grouping called the Seventh Battalion, some of whose members are also billeted here -- to foment what could look like a civil war.</p>
        <p>Mr. Popovic was chatting with his friend, Branko Kukovic, who has just published a book of patriotic poems about Serbs in Montenegro and Herzegovina called ''The Guardians of Freedom.'' The book's preface is some 15 pages of intricate historical data about the undying bond between Serbia and Montenegro.</p>
        <p>Some of Mr. Djukanovic's special police sped up in their new white Land Rovers and then slammed on the brakes. ''The police are Milo's army, and he's doing what the Croats and the others did before they broke away,'' said Mr. Kukovic. ''But here it just helps Milosevic with the Serbs who support his cause. It makes people angry.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kukovic seemed especially agitated that the Montenegrin authorities were even splitting the Serbian Orthodox Church, setting up a Montenegrin Orthodox Church, and he said that would be the subject of his next book.</p>
        <p>But he is not a pessimist. ''We'll find enough clever people not to have a civil war,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Still, attitudes are not uniform. In a dark little coffee shop, Djuro Bojic, 18, sported a sweatshirt that read: ''Montenegro Independent.''</p>
        <p>Kolasin is a center of pro-Milosevic feeling, he said, ''but some people are changing their minds -- they begin to think that Milosevic may be finished.'' This election ''is very, very touchy,'' he said, and there is little affection for Mr. Milosevic's main challenger, the Serbian opposition candidate, Vojislav Kostunica.</p>
        <p>''This town is very, very tense,'' Mr. Bojic said. ''People get drunk, and there are a lot of fights over political issues. It's so stupid, but it's very, very deep. I know examples of fathers sending sons away, because the son was for Milo and he was for Momir,'' referring to Mr. Djukanovic and Mr. Bulatovic, as usual in Montenegro, by their first names.</p>
        <p>Yugoslav soldiers act like bullies, he said. ''They're pushing hard,'' he added. The Seventh Battalion, he said, is hot-tempered and recently broke up a friendly soccer match in nearby Bijelo Polje by taking out  guns and shooting in the air.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bojic is no great fan of Mr. Djukanovic, favoring instead a smaller pro-independence party. But in the elections, he will be rooting for Mr. Milosevic. ''I never supported him more,'' Mr. Bojic said, grinning widely. ''Because if Milosevic wins, we'll definitely have independence here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
