<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Torre and Fans Try to Make the Most of an Awful Day at the Park</title>
    <meta content="Y18YAN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/sports/18YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleveland Indians</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D8163BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1116" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Torre and Fans Try to Make the Most of an Awful Day at the Park</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cleveland Indians defeat New York Yankees, 15-4; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yankee Stadium patrons graded on the curve yesterday, contrary to their notorious reputation. They saw the Indians pummel Denny Neagle and Randy Keisler for 10 runs before there was anybody out in the fourth inning, and when Craig Dingman struck out the first Cleveland batter he faced, fans stood to cheer, some with sarcasm, some in sincere appreciation.</p>
        <p>The defensively challenged Jose Canseco was applauded for getting within yards of a fly ball in right field after misplaying a couple of others. Yankee fans warmly embraced Ryan Thompson's cheap, rolling single in the fifth inning, because it was the Yankees' first hit against Chuck Finley.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Yankee Stadium patrons graded on the curve yesterday, contrary to their notorious reputation. They saw the Indians pummel Denny Neagle and Randy Keisler for 10 runs before there was anybody out in the fourth inning, and when Craig Dingman struck out the first Cleveland batter he faced, fans stood to cheer, some with sarcasm, some in sincere appreciation.</p>
        <p>The defensively challenged Jose Canseco was applauded for getting within yards of a fly ball in right field after misplaying a couple of others. Yankee fans warmly embraced Ryan Thompson's cheap, rolling single in the fifth inning, because it was the Yankees' first hit against Chuck Finley.</p>
        <p>It was a beautiful fall-like afternoon, and the crowd of 50,174 refused to allow the Indians to completely ruin the day with their 15-4 rout.</p>
        <p>The Yankees have drawn 3,045,103 fans this season, the second consecutive year in which the team's attendance has surpassed three million. The team will probably fall just short of last year's attendance, 3,292,736; it had 81 home dates last year, and it is expected to finish this year with 80.</p>
        <p>On the pennant front, the Yankees progressed, passively. The Boston Red Sox lost to the Detroit Tigers by 5-4 and that shaved the Yankees' clinching number in the American League East to eight. And Manager Joe Torre made the best of a really bad game, giving work to a handful of relievers contending for the last couple of spots on the Yankees' postseason roster.</p>
        <p>The rest of it was a mess. Neagle (7-5) had no command and, by his own admission, deserved to be booed. He faced 15 batters in two and a third  innings and allowed eight hits, including two doubles and two homers.</p>
        <p>Neagle fell behind Manny Ramirez, three balls and no strikes, in the first inning and Ramirez bashed a fastball for an upper-deck home run. Travis Fryman smashed a two-run homer two innings later, and Neagle was relieved; Cleveland led, 14-0, in the fourth inning. Building demolition is more picturesque.</p>
        <p>But later, as Neagle explained to reporters why he was so bad, Canseco walked over and said aloud: ''All right, leave him alone. It's my turn now.''</p>
        <p>Long beyond his days as a regular outfielder, Canseco volunteered to play right field yesterday in place of the injured Paul O'Neill and was a disaster. ''I may not volunteer anymore,'' Canseco said.</p>
        <p>He chased down a line drive to open the game and felt his confidence growing. ''Then reality set in,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Canseco fumbled a hit in the third inning as it caromed off a wall for his first error, then was fooled by the winds of Yankee Stadium and allowed an easy fly to drop for his second error. He was booed, but when the next batter hit a fly ball in his direction, center fielder Bernie Williams raced over and waved off Canseco demonstratively, the crowd roaring.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think they were as bad as they possibly could've been,'' Canseco said.</p>
        <p>Once Thompson singled to end Finley's no-hit bid, both managers emptied their benches; Cleveland's Charlie Manuel did so to prepare for the grueling schedule that faces the Indians in the next two weeks, while Torre rested Williams and Derek Jeter, and tested a couple of his relievers.</p>
        <p>Barring injury, all but a few pieces of the Yankees' postseason roster is in place. Roger Clemens, Andy Pettitte and Orlando Hernandez will most likely make up three-fourths of the playoff rotation, and unless Neagle -- 15-7 with the Reds and Yankees this year -- completely falls apart in his final three starts, he will probably be the No. 4 starter.</p>
        <p>The Yankees are expected to carry six relievers, including the closer, Mariano Rivera, the setup men Mike Stanton and Jeff Nelson, and the middle reliever Dwight Gooden. That means four or five candidates are vying for the last two places -- the veteran David Cone, the left-handers Randy Choate and Ted Lilly, and the right-handers Dingman and Jason Grimsley.</p>
        <p>In Torre's perfect world, Grimsley would win a job, especially with Ramiro Mendoza out for the year. The right-hander is durable, versatile, experienced and imminently capable of pitching effectively against left-handers, but there is a caveat:  Grimsley has got to throw strikes,  and lately he has had a lot of trouble doing that.</p>
        <p>Grimsley took over for the seventh and eighth innings yesterday, implemented a mechanical adjustment he made over the weekend and got back to throwing sinkers for strikes. He retired six of the seven batters he faced, four on ground balls and two on strikeouts.</p>
        <p>''It was important for us to get Grimsley some work, to get his confidence back,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Grimsley has dealt with control problems his entire career. He was encouraged by what he did yesterday but was not assuming it would happen again. ''The next true test is when I go back out there,'' Grimsley said, ''to see how I react.''</p>
        <p>Cone is the most experienced of the roster contenders, and he has pitched better in the last six weeks after winning only one of his first 11 decisions. But if Cone is on the roster but not in the starting rotation and if Gooden fills the role of long reliever, there is a question of how useful Cone will be. The Yankees may decide it will be better to carry a second left-hander, to face hitters like Cleveland's Jim Thome and Roberto Alomar, or Oakland's Jason Giambi.</p>
        <p>Choate, a rookie, has served as the Yankees' left-handed specialist this month, but he allowed two runs in the 11th inning to Toronto last Thursday and was tagged with the loss, and the Yankees have been concerned about his ability to hold runners on base.</p>
        <p>Now another left-hander, Lilly, is being considered. Torre seemed intrigued when talking about Lilly before yesterday's game, and that was before he allowed one unearned run over two innings (Lilly was on the mound when Canseco made his second error).</p>
        <p>Lilly has been a starting pitcher most of his career, and Torre may make a point of using him on consecutive days in the last two weeks of the season to see how he responds. Because in the playoffs, there will be no second chances, no forgiving, no grading on the curve.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
