<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Matters; It's Showtime On Financing Campaigns</title>
    <meta content="18MATT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/nyregion/18MATT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purnick, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DC163BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Matters; It's Showtime On Financing Campaigns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE PURNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purnick, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joyce Purnick Metro Matters column asks question that if both Senate candidates Hillary Rodham Clinton and Representative Rick A Lazio want to limit campaign spending, why don't they? (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TIME for a new installment in the ''Let's Get Real'' column series, aimed at clearing the political air.</p>
        <p>Today's question: if both Hillary Rodham Clinton and Representative Rick A. Lazio want to limit campaign spending, why don't they?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TIME for a new installment in the ''Let's Get Real'' column series, aimed at clearing the political air.</p>
        <p>Today's question: if both Hillary Rodham Clinton and Representative Rick A. Lazio want to limit campaign spending, why don't they?</p>
        <p>In that now infamous scene of Mr. Lazio confronting Mrs. Clinton at the end of last Wednesday's debate in Buffalo, he nearly knocked her off balance demanding she sign a pledge banning soft money in the campaign. She said he had to get outside supporters to agree to stop spending independent money bashing her. Which complicates matters because, note well, independent money is not soft money, nor is issues money. Nor do candidates have the authority to stop supporters from spending whatever they want.</p>
        <p>So in effect, Mrs. Clinton said, ''No thanks.'' As did Mr. Lazio last spring, when he called her campaign's proposal to limit soft money ''ridiculous'' and ''incredible,'' because she had already spent lavishly and he was just getting into the Senate race.  And both Mr. Lazio and Mrs. Clinton claim devotion to campaign finance reform.</p>
        <p>What goes on here? Political theater. Given a system centered on costly television ads and laws loaded with loopholes, neither candidate can afford to give up a penny of soft, hard or medium-well money. So each postures, knowing the bluffs won't be called.</p>
        <p>A mutual ban, reached early in the campaign and diligently monitored, might have succeeded. But voluntary limits are very difficult to enforce. People have a constitutional right to spend for or against candidates. Organizations like unions can spend unlimited ''issues money,'' too. Candidates can try, but have no right to stop them.</p>
        <p>Even Senator Russell D. Feingold, Democrat of Wisconsin and co-author of the McCain-Feingold bill on campaign finance reform, said it was tough maintaining a self-imposed ban on soft money when he ran for re-election two years ago. ''I couldn't literally force independent groups to stop, but I went through hoops asking them not to,'' Mr. Feingold said Friday over the phone. In his view it was worth it, and may well have been why he won. But, he cautioned, ''It wasn't easy.''</p>
        <p>Political money that wants to be spent gets spent. Over the weekend, the American Conservative Union, in Virginia, denied Mr. Lazio's request to cancel an anti-Clinton ad. Mrs. Clinton's campaign says there are many such groups out to thwart her. Mr. Lazio says he will ask them to stop if she signs the pledge, and will denounce those that don't. But to what effect?</p>
        <p>Technically, the American Conservative Union money isn't soft money anyway. Soft money is the unlimited and largely unregulated donations to political parties, intended to evade limits on direct donations to candidates. They are supposed to be independent of any campaign. But distinctions blur. How, for instance, to distinguish the new Conservative Party television ad attacking Mrs. Clinton's failed health care proposal from a Lazio campaign ad? But  because it's a Conservative Party commercial, money that paid for it is not subject to any limits.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton has long been raising soft money and is said to have helped the Democrats raise a generous horde of it (total unknown). Mr. Lazio has not raised soft money, but is obviously benefiting from party expenditures anyway, as well as from independent spending.</p>
        <p>AS of Sept. 1, Mr. Lazio had more hard money on hand than his opponent did -- $10.2 million to her $7.1 million. Hard money in federal campaigns is regulated and limited -- $1,000 per donor in the primary, $1,000 in the general election. Mr. Lazio's advantage has Mrs. Clinton ''panicked,'' a Clinton adviser told The New York Times last week, so surely she isn't eager to sacrifice her soft money.</p>
        <p>''She's been aggressively raising soft money from the beginning,'' said Fred Wertheimer, a longtime advocate in Washington for campaign finance reform. ''And his offer is just not the kind of commitment  sufficiently binding that anyone could rely on.'' Mr. Wertheimer concludes: ''We have people who are looking for political advantage. We do not have people looking to achieve some campaign finance goal.''</p>
        <p>So the country's leading proponent of  campaign finance reform questions the seriousness of the Lazio pledge, Mrs. Clinton has all but dismissed it, and as for Mr. Lazio, maybe he'd better call the people at the state Conservative Party and tell them that they are undermining him. Imagine sabotaging a candidate trying, as the congressman said in last week's debate, to make ''a huge statement about character and trust to the rest of the country.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
