<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tycoon Takes to the Road With Media-vs.-Moscow Wars</title>
    <meta content="Y18GUS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/world/18GUSI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231628"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of the Press</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Russian Jewish Congress</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barringer, Felicity</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gusinsky, Vladimir V</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of the Press</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E7DC163BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tycoon Takes to the Road With Media-vs.-Moscow Wars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICITY BARRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barringer, Felicity</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on recent visit of Russian media tycoon Vladimir V Gusinsky to New York, where he cast himself as protector of free Russian press under siege by government of Pres Vladimir V Putin; his brief arrest in June on corruption charges put harsh spotlight on Russian government's blunt use of its powers against media critics; visited city in capacity as president of Russian Jewish Congress (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vladimir V. Gusinsky, the Russian media tycoon whose brief arrest in June on corruption charges put a harsh spotlight on the Russian government's blunt use of its powers against media critics, came to New York last week and urged journalists and politicians not to let the spotlight go out.</p>
        <p>If his quick tour sometimes seemed at cross-purposes with itself -- Mr. Gusinsky wanted to raise the visibility of his cause but insisted that conversations be off the record -- he still made his case to everyone from President Clinton to Mike Wallace of CBS, from senators and congressmen to Lou Boccardi, the president of The Associated Press, and to editors of The Wall Street Journal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vladimir V. Gusinsky, the Russian media tycoon whose brief arrest in June on corruption charges put a harsh spotlight on the Russian government's blunt use of its powers against media critics, came to New York last week and urged journalists and politicians not to let the spotlight go out.</p>
        <p>If his quick tour sometimes seemed at cross-purposes with itself -- Mr. Gusinsky wanted to raise the visibility of his cause but insisted that conversations be off the record -- he still made his case to everyone from President Clinton to Mike Wallace of CBS, from senators and congressmen to Lou Boccardi, the president of The Associated Press, and to editors of The Wall Street Journal.</p>
        <p>While it is hardly unusual for prominent Russians to seek succor and financial support in New York and Washington, it was still surprising to see Mr. Gusinsky take Russia's government-media wars on the road, casting himself as the protector of a free Russian press under siege by the government of President Vladimir V. Putin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gusinsky was in New York in his capacity as president of the Russian Jewish Congress; he met Mr. Clinton briefly at a dinner of the World Jewish Congress last Monday.</p>
        <p>And true to his roots as a banker and -- though he dislikes the term -- as one of Russia's oligarchs, he also met with potential investors in his financially fragile conglomerate, Media-Most, one of his aides said.</p>
        <p>For some, Mr. Gusinsky, with his close ties to the former government and his opulent living, is a problematic spokesman for press freedom.</p>
        <p>His television network, NTV, has an aggressive news department, has provided biting coverage of the war in Chechnya and was a sharp opponent of Mr. Putin's candidacy last year. But in 1996, when President Boris N. Yeltsin's candidacy for a second term seemed threatened by his Communist opponents, the Communists were virtually shut out by NTV, which reaches 100 million viewers, clustered in Russia's large and medium-sized cities.</p>
        <p>Like Boris A. Berezovsky, who owns ORT, the network with the largest audience, Mr. Gusinsky has not shied from using his media properties as weapons in Russia's intricate and cutthroat political and financial battles.</p>
        <p>William H. Luers, a former ambassador to Czechoslovakia, said in an interview after a dinner with Mr. Gusinsky that Mr. Gusinsky's earlier actions ''don't diminish the basic argument that he is making for press freedom.''</p>
        <p>In light of Mr. Gusinsky's willingness to use his media properties as blunt instruments in national elections, his campaign to preserve press freedom in Russia ''is a little ironic,'' Mr. Luers said. ''But it is true that his television and radio stations are among the few left to say what needs saying. That he's not the perfect messenger doesn't mean that his case is not important.''</p>
        <p>Since early this year, Mr. Putin's government has proved to be increasingly willing to move against opposition journalists -- or not to stop military officers, federal prosecutors or other officials who take punitive measures against media critics. The trend began with the detention of Andrei Babitsky, a Radio Liberty journalist covering the Chechnya war, and continued with Mr. Gusinsky's arrest and the recent decision of ORT executives to pull the plug on Sergei Dorenko, that network's most caustic commentator.</p>
        <p>Media-Most has also made itself vulnerable to government pressure by making a deal during the Yeltsin era that gave Gazprom, the state-controlled gas monopoly, an equity stake in Media-Most worth about $234 million, and had Gazprom guarantee a $211 million loan from Credit Suisse First Boston.</p>
        <p>Gazprom paid the loan when it fell due, and is now arguing that its various interests in Media-Most amount, in effect, to a controlling stake in the media conglomerate. Mr. Gusinsky argues that Gazprom officials are grossly undervaluing his enterprise, to squeeze him financially until he cedes control of his media to the state.</p>
        <p>Appearing on the CNN program ''Larry King Live'' on Sept. 8, Mr. Putin brushed off a question about muzzling the press, saying, ''I believe that when they are talking about the need to protect the freedom of expression, that's only a pretext to be able to cover their own commercial interests in some quarters.''</p>
        <p>A few days later, in a meeting with members of Parliament, Mr. Putin said he would not nationalize NTV, according to a report on the news agency Interfax.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gusinsky's most influential broadcaster, Yevgeny Kiselyov, scoffed at Mr. Putin's statements. ''I live in this country,'' he said in an interview in Moscow, and Mr. Putin's statement ''does not have anything to do with the truth.''</p>
        <p>In New York, Mr. Gusinsky met  with about 40 journalists at a dinner  arranged by Global American Television, a Massachusetts concern that supplies programs like ''JAG'' to NTV.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Gusinsky went to Washington to meet with a group of members of Congress, including Representative Tom Lantos, Democrat of California, and with Senator Gordon H. Smith, Republican of Oregon. The meeting was arranged by a group championing the cause of Jews in the former Soviet Union.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
