<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>China Troupe Overcomes, As Did Man Behind It</title>
    <meta content="18DENG$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000920T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">China Disabled People's Performing Arts Troupe</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bohlen, Celestine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deng Pufang</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE3DD143BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1345" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>China Troupe Overcomes, As Did Man Behind It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELESTINE BOHLEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bohlen, Celestine</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Deng Pufang, who is touring United States with 39 members of China Disabled People's Performing Arts Troupe; performance is collection of songs, dances, operas and musical compositions drawn from ancient and modern Chinese culture; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 1968, at the height of China's Cultural Revolution, Deng Pufang, then a student of physics at Beijing University, fell, jumped or was pushed from a fourth-floor window after being savaged by Red Guards who had singled him out as the son of a ''capitalist roader.''</p>
        <p>The ''capitalist roader'' was Deng Xiaoping, who was later to be China's highest-ranking leader until his death in 1987. And Deng Pufang, his eldest son, who broke his back in that fall and lost the use of both legs, became in due course the chairman of China's Disabled Persons Federation and a visible and vigorous champion of China's 60 million disabled citizens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 1968, at the height of China's Cultural Revolution, Deng Pufang, then a student of physics at Beijing University, fell, jumped or was pushed from a fourth-floor window after being savaged by Red Guards who had singled him out as the son of a ''capitalist roader.''</p>
        <p>The ''capitalist roader'' was Deng Xiaoping, who was later to be China's highest-ranking leader until his death in 1987. And Deng Pufang, his eldest son, who broke his back in that fall and lost the use of both legs, became in due course the chairman of China's Disabled Persons Federation and a visible and vigorous champion of China's 60 million disabled citizens.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Deng is in the United States on a six-city tour with 39 members of the China Disabled People's Performing Arts Troupe, whose dazzling performances -- including one on Monday night at Carnegie Hall -- are proof that in China today, being blind, deaf, mentally retarded or confined to a wheelchair is no barrier to artistic self-realization.</p>
        <p>''Even for us working in this area, we are very much surprised to see that so many disabled people are so gifted and talented,'' said Mr. Deng, speaking through an interpreter. ''And we believe many people in the society have no knowledge of their talents.''</p>
        <p>''In China the troupe has been traveling across the country and every performance was a sensation,'' he said. ''The audiences are moved by their talent but, more important, they are touched by the spirit demonstrated on the stage, their unyielding efforts and their pursuit of development.''</p>
        <p>The performance is a collection of songs and dances, operas and musical compositions drawn from ancient and modern Chinese culture. Among the stars are deaf dancers performing the ''Thousand-Hand Bodhisattva''; Qiu Erming, the deaf son of the founder of the Qiu School of Beijing Opera, who in an excerpt from ''Stealing the Royal Horse'' uses his father's recorded voice; and Guan Yongfen, a singer who performs from her wheelchair.</p>
        <p>One of the most striking numbers is ''The Wings of Life,'' in which five amputees, using their crutches, present a lively and moving dance. The concert's last number is a medley by the orchestra conducted by Hu Yyishou, a 22-year-old mentally retarded man whose ability to make music is not impaired by an I.Q. of less than 30.</p>
        <p>Interviewed in his hotel room in Washington, where the troupe had come for a Sunday performance at the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, Mr. Deng was eager to talk about China's disabled people, with one exception: himself. He demurred when asked to clear up the conflicting accounts of how he came to fall from the fourth-story window, and referred to a 1995 biography of his father, written by his sister Xiao Rong.</p>
        <p>''She wrote a lot about my father's experience during the Cultural Revolution,'' he said. ''You should check that book. That would be the right answer.''</p>
        <p>And when asked to retell the version in the book, he again demurred, this time with a coy chuckle. ''There are a lot of rumors and different things said about that,'' he said. ''But I can tell you that the book has the right answer. But that would not be an answer directly from me.''</p>
        <p>[In the book Ms. Xiao wrote that Deng Pufang, after being beaten, could no longer bear the agony, wrote a suicide note and jumped out of the window. Another version of the incident, cited in a June 1989 article in The New York Times by Harrison Salisbury, said Deng Pufang never knew exactly what happened to him. After the fall, Mr. Salisbury wrote, Mr. Deng was left on his own in a hostel north of Beijing, where he had to weave wire baskets for a living. His father later managed to move his son to the military compound where he himself was being held.)</p>
        <p>Such caution about personal experiences would come naturally to the son of a leader as powerful as Deng Xiaoping. In the final years of their father's life, Mr. Deng and his siblings were viewed by many as prime examples of China's ''princeling'' caste, heirs of high-ranking officials who took advantage of their access and privilege to make their own personal fortunes. According to one published report, Deng Xiaoping openly chided his eldest son for his association with the Kanghua Development Corporation, a private company many suspected of being corrupt; Mr. Deng ultimately resigned.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Deng rebuffs any suggestion that he personally benefited from his father's position. ''I do not know where you got information that my family is connected to a privileged group,'' he said, as always answering with a benign smile and a slightly surprised look in his eyes. ''I believe such privileges might exist. I had a very great man as my father, but I never believe that I have privileges because I have such a father. I went to school with ordinary children, my classmates were from ordinary families.''</p>
        <p>''Even though I had access and opportunities to meet many top leaders,'' he said, ''yet I myself would prefer life as an ordinary man and to serve the needs of people with most difficulties.''</p>
        <p>Since his father's death Mr. Deng has maintained his high-profile position. He was elected an alternate member of the Communist Party's Central Committee and maintains good relations with President Jiang Zemin, who recently attended a performance in Beijing of the disabled people's arts troupe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deng is credited at home and abroad with playing an important role in putting the needs of the disabled onto China's political agenda. He proudly lists the results. Twenty years ago only 6 percent of disabled children had access to education; today 70 to 80 percent are in school. Employment rates among disabled people have also risen from 50 percent to more than 70 percent. In 1990 a law was passed guaranteeing rights for the handicapped. ''People are moving out of the isolation of their homes into society,'' Mr. Deng said.</p>
        <p>When he first began to work in behalf of disabled people Mr. Deng discovered that they were not only poor but also were treated with prejudice and contempt. Some of this he came to attribute to China's low level of economic development, but some he saw as the result of a culture that had never cared for the weak.</p>
        <p>''In the beginning I encountered many difficult questions: no access to rehabilitation, schools, employments,'' he said. ''There was an invisible barrier because China had a very weak foundation for morality. It was not like Western countries where you have several centuries of education of humanitarianism.''</p>
        <p>''Part of my work was to give broad publicity to the subject of humanitarianism, to teach that disabled people should be regarded as human beings in the first place, rather than putting the emphasis on their disabilities.'' he said. ''I was telling society that disabled people were entitled to rights, so in this way I gradually changed the social environment.''</p>
        <p>The concerted drive to improve life for the disabled coincided with his father's policy of economic reform, which has produced a sharp rise in living standards in China. But Mr. Deng continues to dwell on the need to raise the level of ''humanitarianism,'' which he defines as a belief in equal rights, equal opportunities and equal dignity for all citizens.</p>
        <p>''I want to make people not only accept the philosophy,'' he said, ''but to make the theory deep rooted in their hearts and to make it the basic normal of social life, to make this theory something very natural from childhood.''</p>
        <p>Once ''a humanitarian environment'' was created, ''not only disabled people but everybody would benefit,'' he said, adding, ''In China, this is a very important subject.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 20, 2000, Wednesday  An article on Monday about the China Disabled People's Performing Arts Troupe and its chairman, Deng Pufang, who are touring the United States, misstated the year of the death of Mr. Deng's father, the Chinese leader Deng Xiaoping. It was 1997, not 1987.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 20, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on Monday about the China Disabled People's Performing Arts Troupe and its chairman, Deng Pufang, who are touring the United States, misstated the year of the death of Mr. Deng's father, the Chinese leader Deng Xiaoping. It was 1997, not 1987.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
