<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Patients in Hospice Care, But for Far Fewer Final Days</title>
    <meta content="Y18HOS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/national/18HOSP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hospice Care</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Accounting Office</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospice Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E3DC163BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="732" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Patients in Hospice Care, But for Far Fewer Final Days</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New General Accounting Office report finds number of Medicare patients receiving hospice care more than doubled in last decade, but that they are not getting full value of services because they often sign up for hospice benefits just few days or weeks before they die; findings discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The number of Medicare patients receiving hospice care more than doubled in the last decade, but they are not getting the full value of the services because they often sign up for hospice benefits just a few days or weeks before they die, federal investigators said today.</p>
        <p>In a new report, the General Accounting Office, an investigative arm of Congress, said that 28 percent of all Medicare beneficiaries in the hospice program received hospice care for one week or less.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The number of Medicare patients receiving hospice care more than doubled in the last decade, but they are not getting the full value of the services because they often sign up for hospice benefits just a few days or weeks before they die, federal investigators said today.</p>
        <p>In a new report, the General Accounting Office, an investigative arm of Congress, said that 28 percent of all Medicare beneficiaries in the hospice program received hospice care for one week or less.</p>
        <p>William J. Scanlon, director of health care studies at the General Accounting Office, said, ''Although more Medicare beneficiaries are receiving hospice services, they are, on the average, receiving fewer days of care than did beneficiaries in the past.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Scanlon said Medicare patients in the hospice program received an average of 59 days of hospice care in 1998, down 20 percent from an average of 74 days in 1992.</p>
        <p>The Senate Special Committee on Aging plans to hold a hearing on Monday to investigate the decline. Senator Charles E. Grassley, the Iowa Republican who is chairman of the committee, said: ''Too few people use the hospice benefit for too little time. That has to change.''</p>
        <p>Hospice care provides a humane alternative for patients who are dying. It emphasizes efforts to relieve pain and suffering, avoids aggressive efforts to cure a disease and may allow patients to die at home. Under Medicare, a hospice typically provides doctors' services, nursing care, the services of home health aides, medical supplies and equipment, and pain-control medications.</p>
        <p>Medicare finances health care for 39 million people who are elderly or disabled. The number receiving hospice care increased to 358,949 in 1998 from 143,110 in 1992, the accounting office said.</p>
        <p>In 1992, more than 75 percent of Medicare hospice patients had cancer. But the number with other chronic illnesses -- heart and lung disease, stroke, Alzheimer's -- has increased rapidly. Those patients now account for 43 percent of Medicare beneficiaries receiving hospice care.</p>
        <p>Under Medicare, patients can qualify for hospice care only if their doctors certify that they are expected to live for six months or less, assuming their illnesses run the normal course. When some patients lived longer than six months, the government tried to force their hospices to pay back some of the money they had received from Medicare. The Clinton administration investigated other hospices suspected of taking in patients who did not meet the eligibility criteria.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scanlon said, ''Patient advocacy groups and the hospice industry assert that this federal scrutiny of compliance with the six-month eligibility rule has had a chilling effect on entry into the hospice program.'' It is often difficult for doctors to know if a patient will die within six months, Mr. Scanlon said, and this is particularly true for patients suffering from illnesses other than cancer.</p>
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the Republican candidate for president, recently cited enforcement of the six-month rule as evidence that Medicare was run by heavy-handed bureaucrats with little compassion for beneficiaries.</p>
        <p>Nancy-Ann Min DeParle, administrator of the Health Care Financing Administration, the federal agency that runs Medicare, said there was ''a disturbing misperception that hospices and beneficiaries will be penalized if a patient lives longer than six months.''</p>
        <p>To correct that misperception, Ms. DeParle sent letters last week to the 2,200 hospices that participate in Medicare.</p>
        <p>''In no way are hospice beneficiaries restricted to six months of coverage,'' Ms. DeParle said in the letters. ''There is no limit on how long an individual beneficiary can receive hospice services, as long as they meet the eligibility criteria. As long as a physician continues to properly and conscientiously recertify the six-month prognosis, a beneficiary can continue to receive the hospice benefit.''</p>
        <p>Senator Grassley said this clarification was overdue. But he also suggested that Congress might want to replace the six-month rule with other, more flexible criteria for eligibility. And he said Medicare should increase payments to hospices because current payment rates were inadequate to cover their costs, which have increased sharply, in part because of drug costs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
