<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Six Events That Show a Brutal Century Wasn't All Bad</title>
    <meta content="18SALA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/arts/18SALA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salamon, Julie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Force More Powerful, A (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E5DF163BF93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1108" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Six Events That Show a Brutal Century Wasn't All Bad</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE SALAMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salamon, Julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Julie Salamon reviews two-part PBS documentary A Force More Powerful: A Century of Nonviolent Conflict; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''A Force More Powerful,'' a new two-part PBS documentary, wants to clean up the nasty record the 20th century left behind. Yes, it was a brutal hundred years, marked by horrendous destruction. But the project's filmmakers (led by the writer, producer and director Steve York) point out that morality sometimes prevailed over evil without violence, that righteousness could flatten the enemy as effectively as a tank.</p>
        <p>It is fascinating to observe situations in which political movements find their flash points and ordinary people find the will, without weapons, to confront dictatorial bullies. There is undeniable power in images of unarmed citizens marching bravely toward policemen and soldiers, knowing they could be arrested, beaten and even killed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''A Force More Powerful,'' a new two-part PBS documentary, wants to clean up the nasty record the 20th century left behind. Yes, it was a brutal hundred years, marked by horrendous destruction. But the project's filmmakers (led by the writer, producer and director Steve York) point out that morality sometimes prevailed over evil without violence, that righteousness could flatten the enemy as effectively as a tank.</p>
        <p>It is fascinating to observe situations in which political movements find their flash points and ordinary people find the will, without weapons, to confront dictatorial bullies. There is undeniable power in images of unarmed citizens marching bravely toward policemen and soldiers, knowing they could be arrested, beaten and even killed.</p>
        <p>The documentary covers six peaceable uprisings that took place in different decades and very diverse cultures: Indian protest against British rule, desegregation in the American South, anti-apartheid action in South Africa, the Solidarity movement in Poland, the defeat of Gen. Augusto Pinochet in Chile and the Danish resistance against the Nazis in World War II.</p>
        <p>That's a huge landscape to squeeze into a little screen, even in three hours. So the filmmakers have compressed each of these complex situations into a half-hour homily, extolling the virtues of nonviolent action. While reference is made to the economic and political circumstances surrounding these historic moments, the documentary often fails to supply context and analysis. Its missionary zeal to promote peaceful resolution of conflict often undercuts the great subject at its core: what inspires ordinary people to succumb to the force of moral authority? Sometimes it may be desperation; sometimes it may be a calculation that the time is right to be on the side of the angels.</p>
        <p>The documentary's aura of saintliness is enhanced by the narrator's contemplative voice, which belongs to the actor Ben Kingsley, who played the title role in ''Gandhi,'' Richard Attenborough's 1982 cinematic beatification. Gandhi's story (or a brief chapter of it) is told here, and his name is invoked often, to explain the influence of his methods on various nonviolent protests throughout the century.</p>
        <p>Certainly Gandhi was the godfather to these crusades, which used his strategies and capitalized on the romantic nobility of his legacy. But in most of these cases the peaceful protests were given a boost by economic chaos or guerrilla warfare or both. In South Africa armed struggle predated the economic boycotts and sanctions that ultimately led to the end of apartheid. General Pinochet's willingness to allow a plebiscite followed an attempted assassination (which left five of his bodyguards dead), and the discovery of a guerrilla group's arms cache in the desert. The Danes hid Jews and carried on shipyard strikes to slow the Nazi war effort, but also blew up factories and railroad tracks.</p>
        <p>The documentary is best when it examines specific tactics of these nonviolent protests, which required leaders to have media savvy and an ability to gauge the oppressor's tolerance for being publicly shamed (or, in the case of the Danish strikers, the oppressor's need for their services). It wasn't enough for the British police in India to attack Gandhi's volunteers with steel-tipped clubs. The action had political resonance when the horrible image was transmitted to the world by a United Press reporter, who described the ''sickening whacks of the clubs on unprotected skulls.''</p>
        <p>It's impressive to watch black students from Fisk University in Nashville attend workshops in nonviolent action in 1960 intended to prepare them for the consequences of ordering lunch at segregated lunch counters. After grounding them in religious and Gandhian philosophy, their leader turns practical. He asks white volunteers to come into the classroom to curse at the black students and hit them, to instill the required stoicism.</p>
        <p>Without analyzing the phenomenon, the documentary shows that, as the century progressed, the manipulation of imagery -- especially on television -- became more and more important to pacifist movements. (It doesn't deal at all, however, with the ways in which marches have become a cliche and protest a performance art.)</p>
        <p>At Lech Walesa's first meeting with Poland's deputy prime minister in 1980, the documentary says, this 37-year-old union leader had little experience with microphones and cameras. A year later we see him as a seasoned on-camera persona, arguing angrily with the opposition on the telephone as he is being filmed. It's a canned intimate moment, and Mr. Walesa is going along as smoothly as a professional television personality.</p>
        <p>In Chile, before the vote in 1988 that led to General Pinochet's defeat, he allowed his opposition 15 minutes nightly of state-owned television time. That was his downfall. These broadcasts, some of them as bizarrely cheerful as fast-food commercials, dealt bluntly with issues of torture and poverty, and became required viewing in Santiago and beyond.</p>
        <p>Peter Ackerman and Jack DuVall, authors of a book being published in tandem with ''A Force More Powerful,'' provide much more analysis than the documentary, including the proposition that advances in technology promise a good future for nonviolent protests. With cameras and computers connecting the remotest places, it's not easy to hide atrocities these days. As the world's economies become more intertwined, they argue, authoritarian regimes may be more vulnerable to international public opinion. It's a nice, hopeful theory.</p>
        <p>DARING TO RESIST</p>
        <p>Channel 13, New York, Thursday night at 10.</p>
        <p>The three Jewish women featured in ''Daring to Resist,'' a Holocaust documentary, decided as teenagers that surviving genocide was a form of moral superiority, even if it required picking up a gun. This one-hour film by Barbara Attie and Martha Goell Lubell, which will be shown later on other PBS stations, lets these vibrant old women tell what happened to them when they were young and marked for death by the Nazis because they were Jews.</p>
        <p>By now, such stories may seem familiar, but through poignant interviews and photographs, the filmmakers -- and of course their subjects -- evoke a fresh stab of sorrow for the terrible losses, and admiration for those lucky and brave enough to endure.</p>
        <p>A FORCE MORE POWERFUL  A Century of Nonviolent Conflict  PBS, tonight and next Monday night at 9  (Channel 13 in New York)</p>
        <p>Written and produced by Steve York; Peter Ackerman, series editor and principal content adviser; Miriam A. Zimmerman, managing producer; Joseph Wiedenmayer and David Ewing, editors; Tom Weidlinger, Denmark and Poland sequence producer; original music composed and conducted by John Keltonic. Jack DuVall, executive producer; Dalton Delan, executive in charge of production. A co-production of York Zimmerman Inc. and WETA, Washington. Ben Kingsley, narrator.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
