<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Moving From New Jersey to the Ivy League, Wryly</title>
    <meta content="18MASL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/18/arts/18MASL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231584"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maslin, Janet</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perrotta, Tom</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Joe College (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EED71F38F93BA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Moving From New Jersey to the Ivy League, Wryly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maslin, Janet</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Janet Maslin reviews Joe College by Tom Perrotta; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JOE COLLEGE  By Tom Perrotta  306 pages. St. Martin's Press. $23.95.</p>
        <p>Danny, the appealingly wry and candid hero of Tom Perrotta's new novel, finds himself musing in italics one day about the dreamy typesetters of the Garden State, smelling of sleepy love and the first cigarette of the mad romantic morning. Danny is experiencing a certain aesthetic and economic confusion. A Yale junior with working-class New Jersey origins, he finds himself besotted by Jack Kerouac even as he tends to the mundane details of his father's business, which is visiting offices and factories in a snack-vending vehicle that is nicknamed the Roach Coach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JOE COLLEGE  By Tom Perrotta  306 pages. St. Martin's Press. $23.95.</p>
        <p>Danny, the appealingly wry and candid hero of Tom Perrotta's new novel, finds himself musing in italics one day about the dreamy typesetters of the Garden State, smelling of sleepy love and the first cigarette of the mad romantic morning. Danny is experiencing a certain aesthetic and economic confusion. A Yale junior with working-class New Jersey origins, he finds himself besotted by Jack Kerouac even as he tends to the mundane details of his father's business, which is visiting offices and factories in a snack-vending vehicle that is nicknamed the Roach Coach.</p>
        <p>''Wow,'' says Cindy, the home-town girl who runs into Danny outside the manufacturing plant where she works and is awed by his Ivy League status. ''I guess I don't have to count my change.''</p>
        <p>''You better,'' Danny tells her. ''I'm an English major.''</p>
        <p>With Joe College as his mocking nickname in the blue-collar world, and with the kinds of Yale friends who argue that deodorant is a needless product foisted on the public by big corporations (''Believe me,'' says Danny's mother on that point, ''no one was ever sorry they put on deodorant,''), Danny vacillates interestingly between two worlds. ''It didn't sound right in this context,'' Danny thinks about one of Bruce Springsteen's New Jersey anthems, ''played for the enjoyment of people who were going to end up being the bosses of the people the Boss was singing about.'' As to where he himself may wind up on this spectrum, that's what this ingratiatingly told story is about.</p>
        <p>It takes a sharp eye and a light touch, not to mention a fine memory for embarrassment (this book is set in the early 1980's, and at one point Danny dances a la John Travolta), to take on the back-to-school genre as knowingly as Mr. Perrotta has. His earlier ''Election'' (a novel several shades less caustic than Alexander Payne's film version) dipped effortlessly into the cauldron of high school political scheming. And his first and still best book, the unassumingly brilliant 1994 short story collection ''Bad Haircut,'' managed to invest offhanded coming-of-age tales with surprisingly deep resonance.</p>
        <p>Like Cameron Crowe slipping incognito into Ridgemont High or even Peter Farrelly (yes, of the gross-out Farrellys) affectingly infiltrating prep school in the autobiographical ''Outside Providence,'' Mr. Perrotta shows an uncanny aptitude for stepping right into an academic past. His new book's authenticity is doubtless helped by the facts that he attended Yale just when Danny did and currently teaches writing at Harvard.</p>
        <p>''Joe College'' tells what happens as Danny works at the Yale cafeteria, hangs around colorfully with his friends (''You ever try to read George Eliot stoned?'') and engages in the predictable fling with Cindy, which yields the predictable procreative problem. Meanwhile he soaks up campus atmosphere (''She was the kind of woman you could imagine walking through the streets of revolutionary Iran in her usual attire and not upsetting the ayatollahs'') and finds himself falling for the polar opposite of the unsophisticated, overeager Cindy.</p>
        <p>Polly Wells is deputy assistant literary editor for poetry at a Yale magazine whose first cover depicts a defecating dog and whose avowed purpose is bringing grit and realism to the students' lives. Polly, who is cuter than this suggests, one day announces that she would like to try painting for the express purpose of wearing paint-spattered jeans. ''It wouldn't be fair,'' Danny tells her. ''You're too cool already.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile back at the Roach Coach, where Danny fills in for his father during vacation, Staten Island mobsters threaten to impinge on business. They also threaten to compromise the author's storytelling skills. Having sold to the movies not only ''Election'' but also ''The Wishbones,'' a breezy novel about a band that plays weddings (pace, Adam Sandler), he now shows a dangerous taste for standard plot add-ons like gangsters with snappy nicknames (Vito Meatballs) or the faculty member who is having an affair with Polly. There is also an 11th-hour plagiarism problem to give the story a convenient turning point and save Mr. Perrotta the trouble of digging deeper to find one. And, when it comes to Danny's crisis with Cindy, there's an awfully convenient resolution.</p>
        <p>But these are minor failings in an overwhelmingly pleasing book, one that relies for little of its appeal on plot devices anyhow. Mr. Perrotta's strengths are writing quick-witted, engaging talk that draws readers right into Danny's collegiate experience and in pinpointing the nostalgic hallmarks of his Yale years with a gimlet eye.</p>
        <p>There are the singing Whiffenpoofs, delivering ''a version of 'Help Me, Rhonda' that made the Beach Boys look like a bunch of swinging anarchists by comparison.'' There is the classmate who is studying the death of President William McKinley and taking a harsh look at his administration, which prompts Danny to worry about his own parents' reaction to such talk. ''Was this what they'd scrimped and sacrificed for all those years?'' he wonders. ''So their son could spend his Tuesday nights drinking beer, smoking dope, eating weird food and learning to see the assassin's side of the story?''</p>
        <p>Most valuably for the success of this book, there is Mr. Perrotta's keen, inviting evocation of the process of undergraduate self-discovery. Dressing to go out one night, Danny looks in the mirror and finds that ''a powerful sense of wholeness and well-being descended upon me as I pondered my reflection, as if life were an endless costume party, and I'd finally figured out a way to come as myself.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
