<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Prewar Beauty? Oh, the Thrill of the Chase</title>
    <meta content="04BOOK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219875"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garber, Marjorie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sex and Real Estate: Why We Love Houses (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD6163CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="790" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Prewar Beauty? Oh, the Thrill of the Chase</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani reviews Marjorie Garber's Sex and Real Esate: Why We Love Houses; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEX AND REAL ESTATE</p>
        <p>Why We Love Houses</p>
        <p>By Marjorie Garber</p>
        <p>243 pages. Pantheon Books. $23.</p>
        <p>Sex and real estate? For many aging baby boomers, the scholar Marjorie Garber argues in her new book, real estate now occupies the place in their brains once reserved for sex: they fantasize not about the perfect mate, but about parquet floors and 12-foot ceilings, and kitchens with Viking stoves; their favorite pornography consists of Architectural Digest and House and Garden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEX AND REAL ESTATE</p>
        <p>Why We Love Houses</p>
        <p>By Marjorie Garber</p>
        <p>243 pages. Pantheon Books. $23.</p>
        <p>Sex and real estate? For many aging baby boomers, the scholar Marjorie Garber argues in her new book, real estate now occupies the place in their brains once reserved for sex: they fantasize not about the perfect mate, but about parquet floors and 12-foot ceilings, and kitchens with Viking stoves; their favorite pornography consists of Architectural Digest and House and Garden.</p>
        <p>Buying and selling a house, she says, ''is a lot like dating'': ''the same emotional overinvestment; the same daydreaming; the same quickening of the pulse; the lingering around the phone, willing it to ring.'' She points out that the vocabulary of real estate ads is ''flirty, seductive, a come-on'' (''Prewar Beauty,'' ''Light &amp; Lovely on West End Avenue''), and that buyers use similar language in contemplating a purchase: they talk about making ''an offer'' -- a proposal -- for a property or wanting ''to see it again.'' Open houses play the role of mixers for prospective buyers; and sellers, having had their properties rejected once too often, speak of getting them ''face-lifts'' or ''makeovers.''</p>
        <p>Despite such entertaining asides, Ms. Garber's book turns out to have little to do with sex and real estate. It's really a hodgepodge of essays -- some better than others -- about houses and the role that houses play in our cultural imagination. Although the book retraces much of the ground covered by Witold Rybczynski's classic 1986 book, ''Home: A Short History of an Idea,'' it does so with considerably less coherence and charm. It also lacks the cogency and sociological depth of Ms. Garber's 1992 study of cross-dressing (''Vested Interests: Cross-Dressing and Cultural Anxiety''), substituting anecdotes and assertions for sustained analysis.</p>
        <p>By far the strongest sections of ''Sex and Real Estate'' are those that are grounded in detailed social observation and the familiarity of the author, a professor of English at Harvard University, with American literature. Ms. Garber points out that the phenomenon of the ''trophy house'' is not something new that started with the likes of Donald Trump or Bill Gates, but something as old as the American dream.</p>
        <p>She observes that William Dean Howells's novel ''The Rise of Silas Lapham'' depicts an upwardly mobile Boston businessman whose plans to build an expensive house have the object of making good marriages for his daughters. And she notes that ''The Great Gatsby'' includes some ''unerringly apt descriptions of vernacular architecture as the sign and symbol of cultural desire.''</p>
        <p>Concurrent with Americans' mania for bigger and better houses, Ms. Garber argues, is a nostalgia for history and the vanished past. In earlier decades, William Randolph Hearst and Isabella Stewart Gardner stocked their mansions with expensive treasures imported from Europe, while the slightly less wealthy settled for living in Elizabethan-style manors and castlelike mansions. Today the aura of history is available to just about anybody with access to catalogs from Pottery Barn or Restoration Hardware, which sell everything from antique-style hardware to lightly distressed furniture to folk-art reproductions.</p>
        <p>In some communities, Ms. Garber writes, a battle has emerged between individuality and authenticity. In the historical district of Cambridge, Mass., she reports, homeowners must get a ''certificate of appropriateness'' for any significant changes to their houses, and on Nantucket, local hardware stores display placards showing the half-dozen or so historically correct colors that people are permitted to paint their homes.</p>
        <p>It is in the chapters where Ms. Garber strays from the world of observation into the realm of philosophical speculation that this book begins to run aground. Her efforts to explore the metaphorical connection between the notions of ''home'' and ''motherhood'' (i.e. the house as womb, as a refuge of safety and comfort) feel vague and pretentious, as do her attempts to explicate the metaphor of the ''house as body'' or container for the soul.</p>
        <p>''If 'the house' is a major internalized image,'' Ms. Garber writes in one particularly labored passage, ''it is a second-order image, derived from myth, art, folklore, psychology and phenomenology -- and from the concurrent development of what might be called the consumer unconscious, that is, the strategies of advertisement and merchandising that accompany or anticipate expansion in real estate and in the selling of high-end household goods and services.''</p>
        <p>These sorts of remarks, representing the worst kind of academic pontification, do nothing to illuminate Ms. Garber's subject. Rather, they obscure the more interesting and valid points she wants to make in this lumpy and uneven book.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
