<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>S.E.C. Rule On Disclosure Still Unsettled</title>
    <meta content="Y04DIS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219972"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDF143CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>S.E.C. Rule On Disclosure Still Unsettled</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Securities and Exchange Commission is still scrambling to revise proposed rule against selective disclosure of corporate information before it comes up for vote within week; new rule is intended to prevent corporate officials from sharing important information with only limited groups of big investors or Wall Street analysts; is supported by consumer groups and individual investors and opposed by investment banks and brokerage firms (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite an outpouring of support from individual investors and consumer groups, federal securities regulators are still scrambling to revise a proposed rule against selective disclosure of corporate information before it comes up for a vote next week.</p>
        <p>The Securities and Exchange Commission is scheduled to vote next Thursday on the new rule, intended to prevent corporate officials from sharing important information only with limited groups of big investors or Wall Street analysts. People close to the commission said they expected the rule, a pet project of Arthur Levitt, the chairman of the commission, to be passed over the vocal opposition of investment banks and brokerage firms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite an outpouring of support from individual investors and consumer groups, federal securities regulators are still scrambling to revise a proposed rule against selective disclosure of corporate information before it comes up for a vote next week.</p>
        <p>The Securities and Exchange Commission is scheduled to vote next Thursday on the new rule, intended to prevent corporate officials from sharing important information only with limited groups of big investors or Wall Street analysts. People close to the commission said they expected the rule, a pet project of Arthur Levitt, the chairman of the commission, to be passed over the vocal opposition of investment banks and brokerage firms.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levitt has repeatedly said that by ''feeding'' information to analysts before the rest of the investing public, some corporations have put ''a stain on our markets.'' Two of the three other commissioners have expressed concerns about particular aspects of the proposed rule. Three commissioners must agree for a rule to be adopted.</p>
        <p>To ensure passage, these people said, the commission is rewriting the rule to make clear that senior executives will not be punished for sharing information with reporters and bond-rating agencies and that lower-level employees will remain as free as they are now to talk to people outside their companies. The commission also is making changes to protect executives from civil lawsuits over public disclosures of corporate information.</p>
        <p>The commission is exempting information gathered by reporters in response to complaints from the media, including Dow Jones &amp; Company, the publisher of The Wall Street Journal. Dow Jones objected to the rule, arguing that it could restrict the ability of reporters to gather information from company executives.</p>
        <p>Peter G. Skinner, executive vice president and general counsel for Dow Jones, said yesterday that he had heard that the company's concerns had been addressed, but he declined to comment before seeing a revised version of the proposal.</p>
        <p>The commission has received thousands of letters and e-mail messages expressing support for the rule from individual investors, as well as the Consumer Federation of America, the Council of Institutional Investors and the Financial Executives Institute. Yesterday, the AFL-CIO said its investment officers supported the rule.</p>
        <p>One group that has not been appeased is the Securities Industry Association, the main trade group for Wall Street firms. Yesterday, the association reiterated its strong opposition to the proposed rule.</p>
        <p>''The fundamental problem with this is that, with the best of intentions, it will end up hurting investors,'' said Stuart Kaswell, general counsel for the association. ''They're taking a swing at Wall Street and they're going to hit investors.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaswell said that the rule would do more harm than good because it would sharply curtail communications between company executives and analysts and, in turn, the investors those analysts advise. Analysts no longer will be able to meet privately with corporate executives and try to ''ferret out'' information that may be useful to investors.</p>
        <p>''You will have what amount to presidential-style press conferences where corporate officials will be able to answer as much or as little as they care to answer,'' Mr. Kaswell said. ''The chance to ask hard-hitting questions in private will go away.''</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Kaswell, Joseph McLaughlin, a securities lawyer at Brown &amp; Wood in New York, argues that the rule will put a chill on corporate communications. ''The natural thing to do is to be extremely careful,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But groups representing major corporations have not stood in the commission's way. ''We talked a lot about whether there would be a chilling effect,'' said Philip Livingston, chief executive of Financial Executives Institute. ''We didn't really think so.''</p>
        <p>To protect reporters' ability to gather news, the commission plans to spell out who cannot receive material information from corporate officials that is not available to the general public. That group of recipients will be limited to include securities analysts, brokers, mutual fund managers and other shareholders. The association opposes that change, Mr. Kaswell said, because brokerage firms regard news reporters as competitors in a race to gather valuable information about companies.</p>
        <p>Still, it is standard practice at most companies to hold separate meetings and conference calls for analysts and for reporters. Privately, some securities regulators say the Wall Street firms are fighting to maintain the advantage they have in gathering information from companies whose stocks they rate.</p>
        <p>''Right now the fear is that information is being given out selectively as a way of keeping analysts in check,'' said Harvey Goldschmid, a law professor at Columbia University who helped draft the proposed rule when he was the commission's general counsel. ''Fundamentally, for the average person, there will be a sense of the markets being fairer.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
