<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beyond Asian Stereotypes, This Comic Settles Scores</title>
    <meta content="04WANT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cho, Margaret</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coleman, Lionel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">I'm the One That I Want (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E4DF173CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beyond Asian Stereotypes, This Comic Settles Scores</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews film of Margaret Cho's one-woman show, I'm the One That I Want, directed by Lionel Coleman; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are moments in the filmed concert of Margaret Cho's successful and hilarious one-woman show, ''I'm the One That I Want,'' when her cheeks puff up, her eyes crinkle, her mouth curls into a wicked little smirk and she swings out at the injustices of the world like an Asian-American Roseanne.</p>
        <p>Like her feisty forerunner in stand-up comedy, Ms. Cho, who is Korean-American and grew up in a bohemian section of San Francisco, has a hefty stash of volatile personal baggage to unload. Much of it has to do with body image and the pressure on women (especially in show business) to be fashion-model slim. Add to that the media stereotyping of Asians as humble, polite, bowing-and-scraping servants and you have a full arsenal of accumulated resentments ripe for comic detonation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are moments in the filmed concert of Margaret Cho's successful and hilarious one-woman show, ''I'm the One That I Want,'' when her cheeks puff up, her eyes crinkle, her mouth curls into a wicked little smirk and she swings out at the injustices of the world like an Asian-American Roseanne.</p>
        <p>Like her feisty forerunner in stand-up comedy, Ms. Cho, who is Korean-American and grew up in a bohemian section of San Francisco, has a hefty stash of volatile personal baggage to unload. Much of it has to do with body image and the pressure on women (especially in show business) to be fashion-model slim. Add to that the media stereotyping of Asians as humble, polite, bowing-and-scraping servants and you have a full arsenal of accumulated resentments ripe for comic detonation.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cho is a superb mimic of body language, and her show is strung with killingly funny parodies of Asian women as meek, supplicating flower girls. Ms. Cho is anything but meek. She is a lusty, full-figured 31-year-old dynamo whose outrage is tempered by an empathetic sweetness. A major figure who runs through her show is her all-knowing Buddha-like mother, whom she impersonates with a complicated mixture of love and ridicule that tilts just enough toward love to make us care about her.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cho's experiences in mainstream show business are a chilling lesson in ethnic stereotyping. As she discovered first hand, ludicrous, patronizing preconceptions about Asians and Asian-Americans still extend to the heart of America's popular myth-making machine. The spine of the show, filmed at the Warfield Theater in San Francisco, is Ms. Cho's appalling true story of her experiences starring in the short-lived ABC sitcom ''All-American Girl,'' the first mainstream television comedy built around an Asian-American family.</p>
        <p>Initially, Ms. Cho recalls, she believed that all her dreams had come true and she had found acceptance for the first time in her life. But those dreams were quickly dashed. No sooner had she won the role of a character loosely based on herself than the network tried to revamp her appearance and her personality. Although much of Ms. Cho's stand-up comedy had involved the affectionate ridicule of her parents, such jokes became taboo on the show. Insisting she lose weight, the producers hired a personal trainer and nutritionist to slim her down quickly.</p>
        <p>The immediate result of being forced to lose 30 pounds in two weeks was having her kidneys collapse. But even more damaging was the loss of personal identity as she dutifully acceded to her bosses' market-tested notions of who she should be. At one point, she says, she became so obsessed with slimming down that all she could think about when watching ''Jesus Christ Superstar'' was the effectiveness of cross-carrying as a weight-loss regime. The crowning humiliation was the network's hiring of a special consultant to instruct Ms. Cho on how to seem ''more Asian.''</p>
        <p>Ultimately Ms. Cho's sense of herself was so thoroughly undermined that she went into a suicidal tailspin and became addicted to alcohol and drugs. She is even able to make this miserable chapter of her life funny in a bit in which she parodies two drunks unsuccessfully trying to have sex.</p>
        <p>And speaking of sex, Ms. Cho is refreshingly, uproariously raunchy. A self-proclaimed ''fag hag,'' ''trash talker'' and ''hetero-phobe'' who was ''raised by drag queens,'' Ms. Cho muses loudly, profanely and at length on gay and lesbian mating habits, oral sex and pornography, both gay and straight. (She has particularly nasty things to say about the men in straight porn, who she believes are selected for their unattractiveness so they won't threaten male viewers.) As enamored of gay men as she is, Ms. Cho is hardly intimidated by them and has some tart things to say about their manners in bars. Discussing the Proustian moments that transport us back to childhood, her most vivid, she says, isn't the Christmasy fragrance of evergreens but the scent of men in pantyhose.</p>
        <p>How funny is ''I'm the One That I Want?'' Several times while watching the movie, which opens today at the Quad Cinema, I laughed until the tears were running down my face.</p>
        <p>I'M THE ONE THAT I WANT</p>
        <p>Directed by Lionel Coleman; written by Margaret Cho; edited by Robyn T. Migel; music by Joan Jett and the Blackhearts; produced by Lorene Machado. At the Quad Cinema, 13th Street, west of Fifth Avenue, Greenwich Village. Running time: 96 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Margaret Cho.</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
