<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Puerto Rican Parade May Ban Some Rap</title>
    <meta content="04PARA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puerto Rican Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rap Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puerto Ricans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Central Park (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forero, Juan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez, Federico</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rap Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DC143CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Puerto Rican Parade May Ban Some Rap</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUAN FORERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Forero, Juan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Puerto Rican Day parade in New York City may ban some floats carrying rap performers whose music glorifies violence and attracts unruly throngs; photo; Federico Perez says parade officials are not accusing rappers of inciting rampage that erupted at edge of Central Park this June, but says obscene lyrics blaring from floats do not promote traditional Latin image; 30 men are charge so far in attacks on dozens of women (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two months after the violent aftermath of the National Puerto Rican Day Parade, the parade's directors are considering a ban on some floats carrying rap performers whose music, they say, glorifies violence and attracts unruly throngs that tarnish the march's image, a leading board member said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Federico Perez, a board member since the 1960's and a former city councilman from the Bronx, said he and his colleagues were not accusing rappers of having incited the rampage that erupted on the southern fringe of Central Park after the parade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two months after the violent aftermath of the National Puerto Rican Day Parade, the parade's directors are considering a ban on some floats carrying rap performers whose music, they say, glorifies violence and attracts unruly throngs that tarnish the march's image, a leading board member said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Federico Perez, a board member since the 1960's and a former city councilman from the Bronx, said he and his colleagues were not accusing rappers of having incited the rampage that erupted on the southern fringe of Central Park after the parade.</p>
        <p>But in an interview, Mr. Perez said board members were concerned that many rap lyrics blaring from floats in recent years had been obscene and did not blend in with the traditional Latin image parade organizers wanted to project.</p>
        <p>''If we can prevent music that is conducive to these acts that are outside the norm, well, we'll have to do that,'' said Mr. Perez, who serves as spokesman for the 18-member board, a private organization that oversees the event. ''We are responding to a problem that occurred, a problem with our image. We know it happened after the parade, but we can't put our head in the sand.''</p>
        <p>The events that happened early in the evening of June 11 after the parade ended on Fifth Avenue have caused consternation among the board members, Mr. Perez said. In frenzied attacks that attracted nationwide attention, hordes of young men, many of whom had attended the parade, groped about 60 women in the southeast corner of the park near 59th Street.</p>
        <p>The police have charged 30 men in the attacks and are searching for 17 others.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perez and other board members said they had not discussed which rap stars might be banned. But he said the board would, in all likelihood, enact far-reaching changes in September when it gathers to plan next year's festivities.</p>
        <p>''We will prohibit some groups from participating,'' Mr. Perez said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perez said that some of the rap music had ''negative connotations,'' attracting youths who take their shirts off and degenerate into raucous mobs. ''We want music that is representative of us,'' he said, ''that is representative of the Hispanic.''</p>
        <p>Hip-hop industry insiders, rap fans and Assemblyman Ruben Diaz of the Bronx, whose district includes the Bronx River Houses where rap was born, said they thought Mr. Perez's contentions were misguided.</p>
        <p>''I love rap music, and I didn't grow up hassling women,'' said Mr. Diaz, a regular parade participant whose parents were born in Puerto Rico. ''Somebody who says rap music or hip-hop is not a part of Puerto Rican culture would be sadly mistaken.''</p>
        <p>Rap's energy and street-wise message, supporters said, resonates deeply among Puerto Rican youth, just as it does among young African-Americans. And Puerto Rican performers like Fat Joe, Noriega and the late Big Pun have become mainstream stars in rap.</p>
        <p>''As far as saying hip-hop artists are not part of the Puerto Rican tradition, they're crazy,'' said Vee Bravo, an editor of Stress, a Queens-based rap magazine that has had a parade float carrying rap artists since 1996.</p>
        <p>''I think it's censorship if they go ahead and do this,'' said Mr. Bravo, who is of Chilean descent. ''I would be disappointed if it happens, and I would seek to mobilize the young people they're attacking to boycott the parade.''</p>
        <p>Fat Joe, whose given name is Joseph Cartagena, said he and other rappers have long believed that parade organizers fail to embrace them, despite their popularity among young Puerto Ricans.</p>
        <p>''The problem with the board of directors is that everyone is very old, and even without this problem happening this year we always have different problems with them each year,'' he said. ''It seems like our money is good, and the attention we bring to the Puerto Rican Day Parade is good, but our cause is not really accepted.''</p>
        <p>The National Puerto Rican Day Parade, a New York institution since 1958, is embraced by hundreds of thousands of Puerto Ricans who enjoy the annual chance to express pride in their cultural contributions.</p>
        <p>This year, the high-spirited celebration, which moved up a 42-block stretch of Fifth Avenue to 86th Street, included tributes to notable Puerto Ricans like Pedro Albizu Campos, a figure in the island's separatist movement, and Tito Puente, the beloved mambo king, who died in May. Fans lined up to cheer competing salsa bands and the colorful floats sponsored by villages in Puerto Rico.</p>
        <p>But the parade, for many, is also about advertising and promotion, attracting politicians like Hillary Rodham Clinton and Representative Rick A. Lazio, corporations selling everything from Internet sites to coffee to corn oil, and musicians looking to connect with Puerto Rican youth. So for years, the parade has attracted rappers and hip-hop D.J.'s, Latin and African-American, who pay for their own floats or are sponsored by radio stations.</p>
        <p>Artists have included Latin stars like Fat Joe; Angie Martinez, a popular radio D.J.; and the rapper Porto Rok, and black artists like Busta Rhymes's Flipmode Squad and Puffy Combs.</p>
        <p>Not all of the parade's board members said they foresaw a ban on rappers. Carlos Velasquez, who oversees marketing for the board, said old rules might be dusted off to prohibit obscenities in lyrics and the practice of throwing T-shirts and other merchandise from rap floats, which promotes rowdy behavior.</p>
        <p>''We don't believe in discrimination against any group, but we ask that they have a certain healthy respect,'' he said. ''And many of the lyrics don't go along accordingly.''</p>
        <p>Board members said they were concerned that large numbers of unruly young fans of certain hip-hop stars tended to flood the parade and give off a negative image. ''By the time they get to 86th Street, it's a huge group,'' said Sydnia Buchanan, a board member. ''We cannot disband the group while they're marching. If people get too close to the group while they're marching, that's something we have to work with.''</p>
        <p>Another board member, Madelyn Lugo, said policies should be established to ensure that Puerto Rican culture is evident among parade participants. ''If they play music, they can play something in rap,'' she said, ''but they should identity at least with the Puerto Rican culture.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
