<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Iconoclast to Whom the Personal Is Always Political</title>
    <meta content="04COTT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219905"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Center of Photography (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Museum of Contemporary Art (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosler, Martha</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotter, Holland</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EEDD173CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Iconoclast to Whom the Personal Is Always Political</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOLLAND COTTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotter, Holland</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Holland Cotter reviews retrospective of the work of American artist Martha Rosler at New Museum of Contemporary Art in SoHo and International Center of Photography on Upper East Side; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you happen to be on basically O.K. terms with the world, meaning that the world is doing all right by you, the alert, irritated, combative work of the American artist Martha Rosler may not be your cup of tea.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, if you find yourself nagged by a few social questions that just won't go away -- like, why the ''haves'' have so much, or why race and class dictate where people live and how they die -- then her art of ideas-that-lead-to-actions is well worth getting to know.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you happen to be on basically O.K. terms with the world, meaning that the world is doing all right by you, the alert, irritated, combative work of the American artist Martha Rosler may not be your cup of tea.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, if you find yourself nagged by a few social questions that just won't go away -- like, why the ''haves'' have so much, or why race and class dictate where people live and how they die -- then her art of ideas-that-lead-to-actions is well worth getting to know.</p>
        <p>There's no better chance to make its acquaintance than in ''Martha Rosler: Positions in the Life World,'' a career retrospective of more than 30 years that is also the artist's first major museum show and is divided between the New Museum of Contemporary Art in SoHo and the International Center of Photography on the Upper East Side.</p>
        <p>Despite the split in venues and Ms. Rosler's long-standing habit of dividing her energies among several media at once, the show is of a piece. It is crowded, garrulous, agitated and funny -- the subway ride uptown from the New Museum feels like an extension of it -- and all but inseparable from the urban landscape that is Ms. Rosler's native milieu.</p>
        <p>She was born in Brooklyn and went to school there in the 1950's and 60's, first to a yeshiva, then to Brooklyn College, where she earned a degree in English and studied art with Ad Reinhardt. She painted in an Abstract Expressionist vein but also took photographs of city streets, inspired partly by socially conscious artists like Walter Rosenblum, who was teaching in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Equally important -- Ms. Rosler  says so in the show's excellent catalog, which was edited by Catherine de Zegher and looks like a textbook, right down to the scuff-proof binding -- was her youthful involvement in New York's experimental poetry scene, then in the middle of the so-called mimeograph revolution. From this, one guesses, she learned how art could be produced outside both the market and academia, and she got a sense of the loaded, slippery power of language, which plays a crucial role in her work.</p>
        <p>She moved to California to study linguistics in 1968, a mind-boggling moment in American culture, equally idealistic and bummed out. Ms. Rosler became involved in the peace movement and feminism. She abandoned painting for other forms, to which she brought two very American attitudes: a candid, hey-what's-going-on-here moral brashness and a TV-generation sense of the absurd.</p>
        <p>The multifarious art that resulted was based on some simple guidelines. Aware of the co-opting power of the market, she chose mediums that were either ephemeral (installation, performance) or easily reproduced and distributed (video, photography). She also opted out of developing a signature style, a decision that makes her retrospective, organized by Elizabeth A. Macgregor of the Ikon Gallery in Birmingham, England, and Sabine Breitwieser of the Generali Foundation in Vienna, look less like a solo exhibition than a lively collaborative effort.</p>
        <p>The show mixes all kinds of things together, with the bulk of photography and video uptown and the large-scale installations at the New Museum. The installations are Ms. Rosler's most didactic works, and she continues to produce them. Each has homed in on a specific topic -- atomic weapon production in the United States, the military dictatorship in Chile -- and fleshes it out with a wealth of research materials:  news clips, maps and political documents attached directly to the gallery wall or available in handouts.</p>
        <p>The result is a total immersion in concentrated information, though one with little visual allure. This may not have been a problem in the alternative spaces for which some of these installations were originally created. But in museums -- institutions that prefer seductive objects, foster short attention spans and have a temperamental intolerance for most conceptually based art -- it is. On two visits, I saw people giving text collages only the briefest scan before moving on, which is too bad: the daily news, Ms. Rosler's greatest resource, is the weirdest, saddest, scariest story ever told.</p>
        <p>By contrast, people did linger over the installation titled ''Monumental Garage Sale,'' which fills the museum's basement gallery. First presented in 1973, it's just what it says it is: a sprawling cash-and carry bazaar of the castoff contents of innumerable household attics and closets, including the artist's own. (Everything is for sale, cheap. The proceeds will go to a local charity.)</p>
        <p>Although it's not apparent at first, the items have been carefully arranged. The ''best,'' most attractive objects are at the front of the room, while at the back, which is dimly lighted, one finds a stash of odd, disconcerting things: old underwear, soft-core pornography, family snapshots and other abject, embarrassing, unpresentable items; their presence undermines the fragile barrier between private and public space, home and the world.</p>
        <p>The intersection of these spheres -- the personal and the political is another way to define them -- is at the core of much of Ms. Rosler's most trenchant and innovative work, beginning with two interrelated series of photomontages, ''Bringing the War Home: House Beautiful'' and ''Bringing the War Home: In Vietnam,'' at the I.C.P.</p>
        <p>Both series were made between 1967 and 1972, and each combines images lifted from popular magazines: interiors from House Beautiful and Vietnam combat pictures from Life. In one montage, a wounded Southeast Asian child limps, as if dazed, through a chic modern living room; in another, a suburban picture window looks out on a battlefield. Ms. Rosler designed all the work for reproduction in alternative journals, not for gallery display.</p>
        <p>She uses the same cut-and-paste technique in the feminist series ''Beauty Knows No Pain, or Body Beautiful'' (1966-72), at the New Museum. Here she packs female body parts snipped from Playboy magazines into ads for top-of-the-line refrigerators. She makes the sex-sells strategy of lingerie ads explicit by pasting in genitals and breasts, and in the piece ''Untitled (Cargo Cult)'' (1974), she shows faces of fashion models being crated for shipping: a Western ideal of beauty sent abroad.</p>
        <p>Despite her self-description as a ''ham-fisted'' artist with an anti-style, anti-mastery aesthetic, Ms. Rosler's photomontages are full of subtle touches. In one of the war series, a skeletal Giacometti sculpture, an icon of 1950's existentialist despair, seems to be striding out of the living room into the battle beyond. And in a ''Body Beautiful'' piece about domestic entrapment, one finds, hanging on a hallway wall, a Robert Indiana poster for Virgil Thomson's opera ''The Mother of Us All,'' which is based on the life of Susan B. Anthony and has a libretto by Gertrude Stein.</p>
        <p>Nowhere does Ms. Rosler tackle feminist themes with more imaginative panache than in her videos, several of which are on continuous view in a gallery at the International Center of Photography. One of the earliest is ''Semiotics of the Kitchen'' (1975), a deadpan cross between a Julia Childs demonstration and a ''Saturday Night Live'' skit, with the artist dressed in an apron and robotically wielding cooking utensils as if they were weapons. It's six minutes long and it's great.</p>
        <p>A piece like this, widely influential  over the last 25 years, has naturally begun to acquire a period feel. After all, it emerged from a time when feminist art and the video medium were both in a start-up phase. A text-and-photo installation completed at the same time, however, looks as fresh today as when it was made and seems to point the way to what Ms. Rosler is doing now.</p>
        <p>Titled ''The Bowery in Two Inadequate Descriptive Systems'' (1974-75), it is composed of black-and-white unpeopled shots of Manhattan's skid row, alternating with typed lists of slang words for drunkenness. Simple as it sounds, it has a lot going on. The piece is historically erudite, with its references to Minimalist grids and the American tradition of Social Realist photography. The single words in irregular stacks have the abstract insistence of concrete poetry but also interact with  the words on shop signs and liquor bottles in the pictures. The themes are ones this artist has dealt with repeatedly: consumption and its hazards, and the intersection of private and public in social space. For many Bowery residents, the doorways Ms. Rosler photographed were home.</p>
        <p>But far from nailing down a hard-and-fast message, the piece stays oblique, suggestive, open-ended. The same is true of the most recent photographs, a series of color images of shop windows and street posters titled ''Transitions and Digressions'' (1997). All the elements that have fascinated Ms. Rosler for decades are here -- the female body, language, absurdist comedy and the economics of acquisition -- but are given a haunted, poetic resonance.</p>
        <p>In short, Ms. Rosler has sustained her political focus and pushed her art ahead, neither of which is easy. This doesn't make her a prime candidate for mainstream stardom. True, she's joined a New York gallery (Gorney, Bravin &amp; Lee in Chelsea), a move she resisted for decades. But most of her work will probably still have little to say to the viewer for whom taste, style and beauty are the essential building blocks of art.</p>
        <p>That's probably fine with Ms. Rosler, who, one suspects, has an opinion or two about the present New York scene, with its big bucks, big spaces and slightly desperate glamour fixations. (Check out her 1978 deconstruction of the fashion industry in the video ''Martha Rosler Reads Vogue.'') At the same time, this mid-career summary coincides with a diffuse, anything-can-happen interlude of germination in contemporary art, one in which her practical and deeply skeptical utopianism has an important place.</p>
        <p>''Martha Rosler: Positions in the Life World'' is on view at the New Museum of Contemporary Art, 583 Broadway, near Prince Street, SoHo, (212) 219-1222, through Oct. 8 and at the International Center of Photography, Fifth Avenue at 94th Street, (212) 860-1777, through Oct. 1.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
