<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shares End Broadly Higher To Recover From Early Skid</title>
    <meta content="Y04STO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Standard &amp; Poor's Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershey, Robert D Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE3D7173CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shares End Broadly Higher To Recover From Early Skid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershey, Robert D Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stocks prices finish broadly higher on New York stock exchanges on August 3; Dow Jones industrial average gained 19.05 points, closing at 10,706.58; Nasdaq Composite Index gained 101.41, to 3,759.88; S&amp;P 500 advanced 13.86 points, to 1,452.56; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stocks pulled out of an early skid and rallied to finish broadly higher yesterday, with the technology-dominated Nasdaq composite index posting a hefty 2.8 percent gain after being down as much as 3.8 percent in the first half hour.</p>
        <p>The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index and Dow Jones industrial average traced similar but less pronounced patterns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stocks pulled out of an early skid and rallied to finish broadly higher yesterday, with the technology-dominated Nasdaq composite index posting a hefty 2.8 percent gain after being down as much as 3.8 percent in the first half hour.</p>
        <p>The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index and Dow Jones industrial average traced similar but less pronounced patterns.</p>
        <p>Analysts attributed the sharp reversal to a combination of bargain-hunting, Motorola's denial of a report that it had cut its estimate of cellular telephone production and a surge of confidence that the government's monthly report on jobs and pay, to be released this morning, would make the Federal Reserve less likely to raise short-term interest rates when it meets on Aug. 22.</p>
        <p>''Money is still searching for technological investment,'' said Ned Riley Jr., chief investment officer at State Street Advisors in Boston. He cautioned, however, that the Federal Reserve will sooner or later succeed in curbing economic growth and that when it does, high-technology businesses will be hurt as well as traditional, more cyclical, companies.</p>
        <p>Semiconductor stocks were under particular selling pressure yesterday morning after Kulicke &amp; Soffa, a top maker of equipment for assembling chips, warned of deferred orders. Its shares slumped to 13 9/16 and recovered only to 16 5/8, down 5 1/2. Credence Systems was among other industry losers, falling 9 49/64, to 39.</p>
        <p>But other technology stocks regained all their lost ground and then some, with Cisco Systems, the most highly valued company after General Electric, slipping to 58 1/2 before rallying to close at 64 3/8, up 3 7/16. Cisco is to report its quarterly results on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq composite index ended the day with a gain of 101.42 points, at 3,759.88. This shrank its loss so far this year to 7.6 percent.</p>
        <p>The S.&amp; P. 500 advanced 13.86 points, or nearly 1 percent, to 1,452.56, paced by Cisco, Oracle, Intel, Sun Microsystems, EMC and Nortel Networks.</p>
        <p>The blue-chip Dow Jones industrial average, many of whose components have been recent havens for investors fleeing technology, rose  19.05 points, or 0.2 percent, to  10,706.58. The Dow is down 6.9 percent so far this year.</p>
        <p>Banks and brokerage firm stocks joined technology among the day's biggest winning sectors. J. P. Morgan, up 3, to 135, was the best-performing Dow stock, accounting for 17 points of the 19-point rise in the blue-chip average.</p>
        <p>Clorox reported a big profit gain but cautioned about prospects and its stock slipped 3 11/16, to 39 11/16.</p>
        <p>Gap's profits disappointed Wall Street and the shares fell 7 11/16, to 30 1/4.</p>
        <p>But Viacom beat expectations and rose 2 3/16, to 71 9/16, while Disney, reporting after the 4 p.m. close of the market, gained 2 points in late trading. The UnitedHealth Group also gained after reporting results. It closed regular trading at 84 15/16, up 15/16.</p>
        <p>Motorola, which changed hands for as little as 33 1/2, ended at 36 1/8, down 11/16, while AT&amp;T touched a 52-week low before finishing at 30 9/16, down  1/2.</p>
        <p>Hilton Hotels eased  1/2, to 9 9/16, after announcing higher second-quarter profits.</p>
        <p>Joseph Battipaglia, chief market strategist at Gruntal, was among analysts saying the Federal Reserve can still refrain from raising rates at this month's meeting despite mixed evidence that the economy's blistering pace has appreciably slackened. He predicted it would decide that the series of six increases since mid-1999 ''is all we have to do for now.''</p>
        <p>Joe Sundeman, an analyst at Schaeffer's Investment Research, said that the market had rallied sharply on recent job reports that suggested inflation remained largely in check.</p>
        <p>Volume on the New York Stock Exchange rose yesterday to 1.1 billion shares from 994.6 million as 74 issues made new highs, compared with 57 new lows. But declines outnumbered advancing issues by 1,545 to 1,338, roughly reversing Wednesday's performance.</p>
        <p>Nasdaq turnover was 1.83 billion shares.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
