<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out of Her Dreams and Into a Dive</title>
    <meta content="04COYO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219897"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">McNally, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Coyote Ugly (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Elvis Mitchell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E4DE173CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out of Her Dreams and Into a Dive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell reviews Coyote Ugly, film directed by David McNally; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In ''Coyote Ugly,'' three of the supermodel bartenders -- Zoe (Tyra Banks), Rachel (Bridget Moynahan) and Cammie (Izabella Miko) -- are poring over an issue of Playboy and making fun of the Playmate's favorite movie, ''Saving Private Ryan.'' At this point, there's a cosmic shift in the universe, a rumbling that disrupts the plates of karma. Those same women leap on a bar and douse themselves with water -- presumably so their leather pants can get even tighter around their slender hips -- for a bunch of leering drunks. So having a movie as superficial as ''Coyote Ugly'' make fun of someone's shallowness is like having Ronald McDonald criticize your taste in clothes.</p>
        <p>''Coyote Ugly'' combines the showier elements of ''Flashdance,'' a movie whose follow-your-dream simple-mindedness it seeks to duplicate, and ''Cocktail,'' in which Tom Cruise flipped bottles of liquor for a clientele apparently uninterested in drinking. It looks like a big-budget version of a Miller's Genuine Draft commercial. (After extolling the fun of alcohol, the movie is lacking only the somber tagline ''Drink Responsibly,'' which actually makes the Miller television spots morally superior.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In ''Coyote Ugly,'' three of the supermodel bartenders -- Zoe (Tyra Banks), Rachel (Bridget Moynahan) and Cammie (Izabella Miko) -- are poring over an issue of Playboy and making fun of the Playmate's favorite movie, ''Saving Private Ryan.'' At this point, there's a cosmic shift in the universe, a rumbling that disrupts the plates of karma. Those same women leap on a bar and douse themselves with water -- presumably so their leather pants can get even tighter around their slender hips -- for a bunch of leering drunks. So having a movie as superficial as ''Coyote Ugly'' make fun of someone's shallowness is like having Ronald McDonald criticize your taste in clothes.</p>
        <p>''Coyote Ugly'' combines the showier elements of ''Flashdance,'' a movie whose follow-your-dream simple-mindedness it seeks to duplicate, and ''Cocktail,'' in which Tom Cruise flipped bottles of liquor for a clientele apparently uninterested in drinking. It looks like a big-budget version of a Miller's Genuine Draft commercial. (After extolling the fun of alcohol, the movie is lacking only the somber tagline ''Drink Responsibly,'' which actually makes the Miller television spots morally superior.)</p>
        <p>Piper Perabo, a young actress with worried eyes and clean hair, is Violet, a Jersey girl who moves to New York City in hopes of realizing her dream of becoming a songwriter. The ambition to entertain is in her blood: Violet's mother was a singer and songwriter who never got to see her dream come true. As Violet trundles from record company to talent agency to drop off her demo tape and get rebuffed, EMF's ''Unbelievable'' cranks along on the soundtrack.</p>
        <p>The song is probably meant to draw attention to the walls of indifference that Violet meets, but it functions more as a comment on the willful naivete of Gina Wendkos's script. It seems that Violet has never even seen MTV, where videos on this same subject turn up all the time. It also seems they don't have credit cards in New Jersey; when Violet goes shopping for a computer to use when she's composing, she asks if the store has a payment plan.</p>
        <p>''Coyote Ugly'' seems to take place in 1989, since most of the songs -- ''Need You Tonight,'' ''All She Wants to Do Is Dance,'' ''I Will Survive,'' ''One Way or Another'' -- are from roughly that year or before. Violet gets a job at Coyote Ugly, the East Village bar, after she watches Cammie, Rachel and Zoe show their sensitivity when they ridicule the Playmate. The bar, run by the tough and tart Lil (Maria Bello), encourages its female barkeeps, clad in snug halter tops, to stoke the libidos of its howling customers by flirting with them -- Hooters as a mom-and-pop operation -- while a tape loop repeatedly plays the same verse from the Charlie Daniels Band's ''Devil Went Down to Georgia.'' (Maybe all that stomping is causing the jukebox to stick.) The place is a brightly colored dreamsicle for every frat boy in the metropolitan area.</p>
        <p>The producer Jerry Bruckheimer (''Flashdance,'' ''Top Gun,'' ''Armageddon'') and the director, David McNally, traffick in the lamest of soft core. This kind of teasing lacks even the complications of the escapades in ''Where the Boys Are,'' which in its Jurassic era way suggested that there might be repercussions to such actions. Violet has to find the courage to follow her dream, conquer her stage fright and get the man she desires (Adam Garcia) to commit. Will she accomplish all of those things? Those who've never seen ''Flashdance'' or heard its Oscar-winning title song may be surprised by this film's ending (re-shot a few weeks ago), which features an epic lip-sync.</p>
        <p>In a brief appearance in ''White Boys'' as a sullen hip-hop kid in the Farm Belt, Ms. Perabo showed that she has enough going for her to survive ''Coyote Ugly,'' but here can show only her spunk and her confident voice. John Goodman plays her worried dad; he gets his laughs and almost gives the picture a heart.</p>
        <p>Each of the other women in the cast is given a single trait for definition. Zoe, for example, left the bar to study law -- perhaps at the Donatella Versace Law School, where you have to work both torts and leather fittings into your schedule. She pops back into Coyote Ugly as a customer, and soon enough she is dragged kicking and screaming away from her books and back onto the bar.</p>
        <p>Whatever else can be said about ''Flashdance,'' its cutting, cinematography and use of music were brand new back in 1983. ''Coyote Ugly'' continues the tradition of integrity set by ''Flashdance,'' in which a dancer doubled for the star, Jennifer Beals. Here the actresses have body doubles and dance doubles, and one of them even has a ''fire leg double.'' At one point, when Violet and her bartender associates -- or their body doubles -- are driving the drunken patrons wild, Lou the bouncer (Del Pentecost) starts heaving troublemakers out. Lou grabs a guy with a camera, who screams, ''Hey, man! I'm a reporter for The Voice.'' Maybe his article will show up in the director's cut on DVD.</p>
        <p>Someone needs to warn the bartenders at the real Coyote Ugly bar that now is a good time to start shopping around for doubles and extra pairs of leather pants. They'll need them for the onslaught of customers the movie will bring in.</p>
        <p>''Coyote Ugly'' is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It includes sexual situations and much alcohol consumption.</p>
        <p>COYOTE UGLY</p>
        <p>Directed by David McNally; written by Gina Wendkos; director of photography, Amir Mokri; edited by William Goldenberg; music by Trevor Horn; production designer, Jon Hutman; produced by Jerry Bruckheimer and Chad Oman; released by Touchstone Pictures. Running time: 94 minutes. This film is rated PG-13.</p>
        <p>WITH: Piper Perabo (Violet Sanford), Adam Garcia (Kevin O'Donnell), Maria Bello (Lil), Melanie Lynskey (Gloria), Izabella Miko (Cammie), Bridget Moynahan (Rachel), Tyra Banks (Zoe), Del Pentecost (Lou), Michael Weston (Danny) and John Goodman (Bill).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
