<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Around the World</title>
    <meta content="04EATI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="42" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="EATING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E3D91F3DF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1524" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Around the World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Capsule reviews of 12 New York restaurants featuring 12 different world cuisines; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whether you're a world traveler or a homebody, you can sample the world's foods without leaving New York City. These possibilities represent 12 cuisines. (These summaries are taken from dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times by William Grimes, Eric Asimov and others.)</p>
        <p>1. Brawta Caribbean Cafe</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(718) 855-5515</p>
        <p>347 Atlantic Avenue, at Hoyt Street</p>
        <p>Boerum Hill, Brooklyn</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Brawta, which is Jamaican patois for ''something extra,'' offers top-flight Jamaican food in a relaxed, colorful dining room. Rotis -- peppery stews of chicken or mellow goat rolled up in huge, soft flatbreads -- are superb, as is the spicy jerk chicken. Coco shrimp is an unusual and generous shrimp curry made with coconut milk. Don't miss the traditional Caribbean beverages, like sweet sorrel, and the thick sea moss.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Whether you're a world traveler or a homebody, you can sample the world's foods without leaving New York City. These possibilities represent 12 cuisines. (These summaries are taken from dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times by William Grimes, Eric Asimov and others.)</p>
        <p>1. Brawta Caribbean Cafe</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(718) 855-5515</p>
        <p>347 Atlantic Avenue, at Hoyt Street</p>
        <p>Boerum Hill, Brooklyn</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Brawta, which is Jamaican patois for ''something extra,'' offers top-flight Jamaican food in a relaxed, colorful dining room. Rotis -- peppery stews of chicken or mellow goat rolled up in huge, soft flatbreads -- are superb, as is the spicy jerk chicken. Coco shrimp is an unusual and generous shrimp curry made with coconut milk. Don't miss the traditional Caribbean beverages, like sweet sorrel, and the thick sea moss.</p>
        <p>2. Chola  **  [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 688-4619</p>
        <p>232 East 58th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Chola does not look very different from dozens of modest Indian restaurants in New York City until you pick up the menu, which is large and fascinating, with many vegetarian specialties from southern India, some intriguing British-Indian offerings, even a small group of dishes from the Jews of Calcutta. The appetizers are especially appealing, like masala dosa, a crisp crepe so large the ends hang off the plate. Folded inside is a delightful mixture of spicy potatoes and peas. Hyderabadi korma, a mixture of vegetables cooked in coconut milk with curry leaves and mustard seeds, is delicious, and phall, lamb cooked with abundant fresh green chilies, is exciting and very hot.</p>
        <p>3. Circus  **  [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 223-2566</p>
        <p>808 Lexington Avenue, at 62nd Street</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>With the kind of food your mother might cook if you grew up in Sao Paulo or Bahia, Circus is usually packed with Brazilians eager for a taste of home. That taste includes empanadas, pretty ovals of pastry stuffed with chicken, and many other hearty dishes, like camarao na moranga, a heap of tiny, tender rock shrimp sauteed with fresh corn, hearts of palm, shallots, peas and coconut milk, mixed with cheese and baked in an acorn squash; and picadinho, beef sauteed with wine and thyme, topped with a poached egg and accompanied by rice, beans and cooked bananas. The food is not the only lively thing here; Brazilians eat late, and as the night gets older, the restaurant takes on the air of a party.</p>
        <p>4. Cyclo</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(212) 673-3975</p>
        <p>203 First Avenue, near 12th Street East Village</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Cyclo stands out among New York's Vietnamese restaurants because the food is so light, fresh and balanced. Delicate, greaseless spring rolls cry out to be eaten the Vietnamese way, wrapped in a lettuce leaf with some mint or cilantro and marinated carrot and dipped in nuoc cham, the tangy sweet-and-sour sauce. Among other outstanding dishes are ca bam, chopped monkfish that you spoon up with a crisp sesame-rice cracker, and chicken roasted with lemon grass and lime juice. Chao tom, grilled shrimp paste wrapped around sugar cane, is served traditionally with soft rice wrappers.</p>
        <p>5. Deniz Lounge And Restaurant  **  [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 486-2255</p>
        <p>400 East 57th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Deniz (the name means ocean in Turkish) calls itself a Mediterranean seafood restaurant, which is only partly true. It is really a Turkish restaurant, and the menu has many dishes to please people who don't eat fish. It does especially well with cold dishes, like an eggplant salad that is smooth, creamy and smoky, and salty little rolls of phyllo-wrapped feta cheese that are crunchy and delicious enough to disappear in two bites. If you do like seafood, the choices include wonderful sardines wrapped in grape leaves and topped with thinly sliced rounds of lemon; the chewy, oniony octopus salad; and the rich taramosalata, fish roe whipped with olive oil and lemon.</p>
        <p>6. Eight Mile Creek  **  [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 431-4635</p>
        <p>240 Mulberry Street, at Prince Street</p>
        <p>Little Italy</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>When a restaurant announces that it will serve Australian cuisine, you expect good comic material, not good food, but the joke stops when the seared kangaroo arrives. Appetizers include chilled avocado-cucumber soup with yabby (crayfish) meat; warm oyster ''meat pie'' with leeks, salsify and tarragon; and seared sushi-grade tuna over a salad of poached squid and seaweed noodles. Entrees include black sea bass with duck confit, mashed potatoes and black vinegar reduction; Australian lamb loin served over herbed polenta with maitake mushrooms; and mountain-pepper-roasted tomato with orzo, mousseron mushrooms and goat cheese.</p>
        <p>7. Firebird  **  [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 586-0244</p>
        <p>365 West 46th Street</p>
        <p>Clinton</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Firebird has an ornate, lavish air of czarist aristocracy. Both the sumptuous dining rooms downstairs and the cozy parlor upstairs enhance the illusion of old-fashioned elegance. Champagne and caviar help, of course. Caviar arrives with a covered pot of blini, a dish of sour cream, a pitcher of butter and its own private waiter, who turns the service into a distinctly Russian performance. Caviar is just the beginning of the selection. The menu also features exceptional grilled sturgeon and fine grilled marinated lamb loin. The wine selection is not nearly as impressive as the vodka list.</p>
        <p>8. Habib's Place</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(212) 979-2243</p>
        <p>438 East Ninth Street</p>
        <p>East Village</p>
        <p>$ Cash only</p>
        <p>This tiny restaurant serves superb Middle Eastern and North African fare, courtesy of Habib Belkadi, a smiling jazz lover whose welcoming manner has made Habib's a neighborhood favorite. His couscous is terrific, as are falafel and lamb kebabs, and if Mr. Belkadi's sister made any of the desserts, try them. Everybody who has ever carried a guitar in the East Village, it seems, is a friend of Mr. Belkadi. Diners generally leave happy and well fed.</p>
        <p>9. Maya  **  [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 585-1818</p>
        <p>1191 First Avenue, at 65th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Richard Sandoval, the chef and owner, has put his heart into Maya to showcase the food of his native Mexico. While Maya is attractive and colorful, the food is what's most memorable, with unusual dishes like roasted corn soup with a dumpling made of huitlacoche, a corn fungus that is a time-honored Mexican ingredient. Even a familiar selection like chili relleno is given a twist: Mr. Sandoval stuffs his with seafood and cheese. Chicken in a mole poblano sauce is truly complex, while pipian de puerco, grilled pork in a pumpkin seed sauce, is also satisfying.</p>
        <p>10. Meigas  **  [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 627-5800</p>
        <p>350 Hudson Street, at King Street</p>
        <p>South Village</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Meigas, a new Spanish restaurant in a former industrial building, is very large with high ceilings and a light, beachy color scheme dominated by sand and aqua, which gives it the feel of a giant bathhouse. The flavors sing clearly. Ingredients taste exactly like what they are, and in combination they interact without getting lost. This sense of clarity and definition helps elevate rustic dishes like rabbit loin wrapped in bacon and surrounded by sauteed scallops, pearl onions, scallions and garlic confit; and the juicy and flavorful rib-eye steak, served with potatoes and piquillo peppers.</p>
        <p>11. Ping's Restaurant  **  [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(718) 396-1238</p>
        <p>83-02 Queens Boulevard</p>
        <p>Elmhurst, Queens</p>
        <p>$$ American Express</p>
        <p>If you look closely at the bank of fish tanks near the back of Ping's, you can see how extraordinary the food may be at this Chinese restaurant. In addition to the usual lobsters and sea bass, there can be two types of live shrimp, three kinds of crab, freshwater and saltwater eels, and other fish, like cod, rarely seen swimming in restaurants. The superb starters include sweet little scallops in the shell served in a special Hong Kong condiment made with soy, sugar and fermented fish sauce, and fried giant prawns filled with roe and served with little sweet-potato dumplings. Dungeness crab is irresistible, and pea shoots are wonderful, served with bits of pork and eggs.</p>
        <p>12. Silver Swan</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(212) 254-3611</p>
        <p>41 East 20th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>The excellent selection of beers and ales is reason enough to enjoy Silver Swan's solid German fare. The beer list includes Rauchbier, or smoked beer, made with smoked malt; and a dozen Bavarian wheat beers, dry, quenching brews made with a high proportion of wheat malt rather than barley malt, that are just right with weisswurst, mild veal sausage, or bratwurst, juicy pork sausage. The menu also includes five varieties of schnitzel and a satisfying sauerbraten.</p>
        <p>Summaries taken from reviews use the star ratings. Others are taken from the $25 and Under column (+) and articles (++), and capsule revies from New York Today: www.nytoday.com (+++).</p>
        <p>What the Stars Mean</p>
        <p>**** -- Extraordinary  *** -- Excellent  ** -- Very Good  * -- Good  None Poor to Satisfactory</p>
        <p>Price Range  Based on the cost of a three-course dinner, per person, tax, tip and drinks not included.</p>
        <p>$ -- $25 and under  $$ -- $25 to $40  $$$ -- $40 to $55  $$$$ -- $55 and over</p>
        <p>Past Reviews -- Good Eating columns back to June 1998, along with reviews from The Times and capsule reviews by Times critics of additional restaurants not reviewed in the newspaper, are available on New York Today.</p>
        <p>EATING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
