<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.B.A. Coach Finds Joy in Women's League</title>
    <meta content="04PROF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219953"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Richie Adubato</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Liberty</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Adubato, Richie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffman, Jan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E3D7173CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.B.A. Coach Finds Joy in Women's League</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN HOFFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoffman, Jan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former NBA coach Richie Adubato reflects on coaching New York Liberty women's team; interview; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BACK then, he coached the greats, from Bob Lanier to Shaquille O'Neal. He traveled on the Orlando Magic's private jet, stocked with lobster, steak and Shaq's very own seven-foot bed.</p>
        <p>Now? His greats have names like Teresa Witherspoon, Vickie Johnson. Luxury? Even the coach has flown coach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BACK then, he coached the greats, from Bob Lanier to Shaquille O'Neal. He traveled on the Orlando Magic's private jet, stocked with lobster, steak and Shaq's very own seven-foot bed.</p>
        <p>Now? His greats have names like Teresa Witherspoon, Vickie Johnson. Luxury? Even the coach has flown coach.</p>
        <p>Back then, guy talk.</p>
        <p>Now?</p>
        <p>''The women cry at everything,'' says Richie Adubato, 62, the coach for the New York Liberty, who, with four games until playoffs, are the top team in the Eastern Conference of the Women's National Basketball Association. ''They cry if we lose! They cry if we win!''</p>
        <p>He's throwing up his hands as he strides off the court after practice at Madison Square Garden. ''Tari Phillips!'' he says, on a tear about his sojourn in this strange new country. ''It takes her an hour to put on her makeup -- and that's if she can find it!''</p>
        <p>What's a coach who spent nearly 40 years around sweaty guys to do?</p>
        <p>It happens that Mr. Adubato is thrilled to be here. After 19 years as an up-and-down coach in the National Basketball Association, he has been as rejuvenated by this gutsy team of women -- many started this season green, injured or overweight -- as they have been by him. Referring to last summer, his first with the Liberty and with coaching women, he adds, sitting in his office, ''I tell you, I never had so many hugs and kisses in one season.''</p>
        <p>If you've ever chanted with the sweet, exuberant Liberty crowds of 14,000 at the Garden or seen a game on TV -- Lifetime carries the big one tonight against the Orlando Miracle, former team of Tari Phillips, the Liberty's center -- you know Mr. Adubato. He's the ginger-headed man (Jersey Italian dad, Jersey Irish mom) in a natty suit, running along the sidelines, frantically signaling the girls (his term), working the refs, hard:</p>
        <p>''Aw look, she's an actor! Did you see that? Right there! That's an Academy Award! That was a nasty, hard foul! Wow. Now that -- that is a new trick! I've never seen that before! Look, she did it again!''</p>
        <p>Although one year he was fined 27 times -- What? Just for defending his team? -- Mr. Adubato has calmed down. Being hired and fired a lot, divorced and remarried, having a granddaughter, can have that effect on a person. He was an assistant in Detroit, Dallas, Cleveland, New York and Orlando; head coach in Detroit, Dallas and Orlando.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, when Blaze -- Carol Blazejowski, the Hall of Fame guard and Liberty general manager -- had a meeting with Mr. Adubato in a Route 3 diner, Mr. Adubato was just consulting for the Celtics' Rick Pitino. He was courtsick for a team of his own.</p>
        <p>She was skeptical about hiring someone who was older, a guy and  who had never coached women. (He wondered: ''Do I have to say woman-to-woman defense or can I still say man-to-man?'')</p>
        <p>She didn't know Mr. Adubato, son of a Cincinnati Reds scout, elected  basketball over baseball, on the theory that even if your team is short and can't shoot, there are a thousand other ways to win. That he loved basketball so much that for 18 years, while a junior high classroom teacher in inner-city Paterson, N.J., he coached at local Catholic schools and colleges (when, fans, he befriended Jersey coaches like Dick Vitale and Hubie Brown).</p>
        <p>Nor that his worst moment was not being fired after his first two years coaching in the N.B.A., but having to walk back into that eighth-grade classroom as a teacher again.</p>
        <p>IN spite of her concerns, Ms. Blazejowski liked him. What's not to like? He's funny, kind, pumped-up, demanding, a natural teacher, a storyteller, not a screamer and a basketballholic.</p>
        <p>As his wife, Carol, says, he may not be able to remember bread and milk, but he can recite plays from 40 years ago. He relaxes watching eight N.B.A. games a night, taking notes. Orlando, you better believe that at practice, he was teaching your moves: he watched four tapes and had a scout's reports.</p>
        <p>He is also astute:</p>
        <p>In a tight game with Orlando,  Crystal Robinson, his prize shooter, fouled a player on a three-point shot with 20 seconds left. She looked devastated. During timeout, he soothed her. You didn't foul. Bad call. You can shut them down. Buoyed, she did the job and then some.</p>
        <p>''Who's coming to dinner?'' he will shout into the locker room.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Adubato is still on a learning curve with this woman thing. If the women are more coachable, more eager, more grateful, more team-spirited and harder-working than the men, they are also ''more emotional.'' He'll often ask a co-captain to deliver his stern message. As for personal stuff?</p>
        <p>''The guys could talk to me about marriage and divorce,'' he says. ''None of the women are even married; they don't have those kinds of problems.'' They turn to the co-captains or Patty Coyle, an assistant coach, with personal issues. ''They come to me about basketball.''</p>
        <p>He never won an N.B.A. championship. In the W.N.B.A., the Liberty have to clinch the conference title, win the playoffs, face down mighty Los Angeles or Houston.</p>
        <p>Who knows? His team surprised everyone this season. He always fantasized about a Manhattan ticker tape parade. ''But I never dreamed,'' he says in wonderment, ''it might be for women.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
