<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Sidesteps Senate to Fill Civil Rights Enforcement Job</title>
    <meta content="04RECE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219962"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marquis, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Bill Lann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Diversity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE7DF143CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Sidesteps Senate to Fill Civil Rights Enforcement Job</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER MARQUIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marquis, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton appoints Bill Lann Lee to become Justice Department's chief enforcer of civil rights laws; recess appointment, procedural step around Senate confirmation process, is blunt challenge to Republicans; Senate Judiciary Committee refused to confirm Lee, a Chinese-American lawyer, because of his support for affirmative action; Lee photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton today appointed Bill Lann Lee to become the Justice Department's chief enforcer of civil rights laws, in a blunt challenge to Republicans who have criticized Mr. Lee, a Chinese-American lawyer, but who are eager to portray themselves as more welcoming to minorities.</p>
        <p>With Republican leaders celebrating their national convention in Philadelphia with appeals to minority voters, Mr. Clinton named Mr. Lee the new assistant attorney for civil rights by virtue of a recess appointment, a procedural step around the Senate confirmation process.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton today appointed Bill Lann Lee to become the Justice Department's chief enforcer of civil rights laws, in a blunt challenge to Republicans who have criticized Mr. Lee, a Chinese-American lawyer, but who are eager to portray themselves as more welcoming to minorities.</p>
        <p>With Republican leaders celebrating their national convention in Philadelphia with appeals to minority voters, Mr. Clinton named Mr. Lee the new assistant attorney for civil rights by virtue of a recess appointment, a procedural step around the Senate confirmation process.</p>
        <p>The president's move was largely symbolic, since Mr. Lee has been at that job in an acting capacity for two and a half years. Mr. Clinton -- who in 1993 withdrew the name of another nominee for the civil rights job, Lani Guinier -- has stood by Mr. Lee and twice renominated him.</p>
        <p>The Senate Judiciary Committee has refused to confirm Mr. Lee, largely voicing the same concerns it had about Ms. Guinier.</p>
        <p>Republican committee members say Mr. Lee, during his tenure as a counsel for the NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund, promoted affirmative action programs that the Republicans oppose, like school busing and racial and gender preferences in cities and corporations.</p>
        <p>White House aides acknowledged that the recess appointment, which would have the effect of allowing Mr. Lee to serve through the end of Mr. Clinton's term without the need for Senate confirmation, was partly a rebuke to the Republican Party's drive for racial inclusiveness under the leadership of its presidential nominee, Gov. George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>''It's one thing to put on a show of diversity,'' said Elliot Diringer, a White House spokesman. ''It's another thing to support vigorous civil rights enforcement, and that's what we are doing here.''</p>
        <p>''The kinder, gentler Republican mood is either a myth, or maybe that memo never made it to the Republican Senate,'' said Senator Patrick J. Leahy, a Vermont Democrat.</p>
        <p>Denouncing the handling of Mr. Lee's nomination as ''steeped in partisan vinegar,'' Mr. Leahy said it was ''part of a pattern dating back four years now, in which dozens of judicial nominees and others -- especially women and minorities -- have been subjected to anonymous and humiliating delays before they get a vote, if they ever get a vote at all.''</p>
        <p>Senate Republicans privately accused the White House of seeking to bolster the campaign prospects of Vice President Al Gore by driving a wedge between their party and minority voters.</p>
        <p>Publicly, Republicans were restrained in their criticism, and Senator Orrin G. Hatch, who has opposed Mr. Lee's appointment, observed that he liked the nominee ''on a personal level'' and ''would support him in any number of positions.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Mr. Hatch chided the president for backing a nominee who, he said, failed to ''bring all sides together in our efforts to advance the cause of civil rights.'' Mr. Hatch added that ''the timing of this decision serves as further evidence of what we have come to know is true: The Clinton-Gore White House is intent on dividing our people rather than uniting us for the common good.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
