<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Briefing</title>
    <meta content="04MBRF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219975"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Influenza</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Visiting Nurse Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bahrampour, Tara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E5DE143CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Visiting Nurse Assn advises Brooklyn community groups to request flu vaccine now because of anticipated shortage this fall (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: FLU VACCINE -- Fearing a severe shortage of influenza vaccine in October, a home health care organization is asking Brooklyn community groups to request the vaccine now, two months before the start of the flu season. The Visiting Nurse Association of Brooklyn cited an advisory from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention that vaccine manufacturers expect shipment delays and supply cuts in October and November. Susan Wyant, a spokeswoman for the nurses, said the association would accept requests from community groups and businesses that want immunization clinics in their areas.</p>
        <p>Tara Bahrampour (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: FLU VACCINE -- Fearing a severe shortage of influenza vaccine in October, a home health care organization is asking Brooklyn community groups to request the vaccine now, two months before the start of the flu season. The Visiting Nurse Association of Brooklyn cited an advisory from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention that vaccine manufacturers expect shipment delays and supply cuts in October and November. Susan Wyant, a spokeswoman for the nurses, said the association would accept requests from community groups and businesses that want immunization clinics in their areas.</p>
        <p>Tara Bahrampour (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: TRADER SENTENCED -- James J. McDermott Jr., the former chairman and chief executive of Keefe Bruyette &amp; Woods, the Manhattan investment brokerage house, was sentenced yesterday to eight months in federal prison for leaking confidential financial information. Mr. McDermott was convicted in April of leaking information about bank deals. Prosecutors charged that he shared the insider information with Kathryn B. Gannon, a friend and adult film star who has also been charged but has not yet been tried. She is a Canadian citizen and is believed to be in Canada. Prosecutors are seeking her extradition.</p>
        <p>John Sullivan (NYT)</p>
        <p>GLENS FALLS: MAN GIVES $1 MILLION -- After three visits to the Crandall Public Library, a man decided to donate $1 million to the library's $10 million expansion. The man, Charles R. Wood, who made his fortune in the amusement-park industry, said he liked what he saw at the library. ''Older people were reading papers over here and youngsters were milling around reading books and working on computers,'' he said. ''It was like their home away from home.'' Glens Falls is 50 miles north of Albany.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CALVERTON: FIRECRACKER ACCIDENT -- A 42-year-old Long Island woman lost a hand yesterday when she lighted something before dawn that appeared to be a candle but was actually a powerful firecracker, the Suffolk County police said. The woman, Anna Capasso, had borrowed the candle-like explosive from a neighbor after she fell behind in her payments to the electric company and lost her service, the police said. She was listed in satisfactory condition at the University Medical Center at Stony Brook.</p>
        <p>Michael Cooper (NYT)</p>
        <p>ALBANY: INDIAN TAX-FREE GOODS -- Motor fuel and cigarettes can remain free of state tax on Indian reservations even when sold by Indian vendors to non-Indian customers, an appeals court decided yesterday. The five-member panel rejected arguments that by not charging state sales taxes on reservation purchases, the state is hurting non-Indian businesses. For example, Indian vendors can sell a carton of cigarettes for $13.50 less than vendors who collect state taxes. Indians argue that 19th-century treaties make their reservations immune to state taxation.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: MINISTER PLEADS NOT GUILTY -- A Hartford minister and civic activist pleaded not guilty Wednesday to charges that he promoted prostitution and assaulted a prostitute allegedly pregnant with his baby. The minister, the Rev. Henry Price, demanded sexual favors from prostitutes, got them jobs at a massage parlor and took much of the money they earned as prostitutes, the police said. Mr. Price left the courthouse Wednesday without comment.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>VERNON: MAN RULED INSANE -- A Superior Court judge ruled yesterday that a man who opened fire on three state troopers responding to a 1998 vandalism call was legally insane. Judge Jonathan J. Kaplan of Rockville Superior Court ruled that the man, Edward Premo, had a ''severe mental illness'' and ordered him committed for further evaluation. He is to return to court Sept. 21, when he could be sentenced to more than 100 years in some sort of confinement, Judge Kaplan said.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>PARSIPPANY: E. COLI DEATH -- A 20-month-old boy has died of complications caused by E. coli bacteria, state health officials confirmed yesterday. The boy, identified by The Daily Record of Morristown as Nicolaus Arthur Brayton, fell ill on July 23 and died on Tuesday, said Dennis McGowan, a spokesman for the State Health Department. The boy's sister was also sick. She was treated at Schneider Children's Hospital in New Hyde Park, N.Y., officials there said, for what The Daily Record said was also E. coli poisoning. It was not clear how the boy was infected with E. coli, usually associated with contaminated meat.</p>
        <p>Andy Newman (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW BRUNSWICK: U.S. TO STUDY CHEMICAL SITE -- A federal health agency will conduct a study to determine whether some New Brunswick residents are endangered by toxins that have seeped from a chemical company into a brook that runs through its property. The Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry, based in Atlanta, has said it will begin a months-long study of the Rhodia Inc. site, The Star-Ledger reported yesterday. The study was requested by the Edison Wetlands Association, which has sued both Rhodia and the State Department of Environmental Protection. Officials at Rhodia said its current operations were clean.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>TRENTON: FINANCIER PLEADS -- Robert E. Brennan, the former penny-stock tycoon, pleaded not guilty yesterday to bankruptcy fraud charges at his arraignment in federal court. Mr. Brennan, 56, is charged with hiding from creditors more than $500,000 he allegedly got from cashing in casino chips less than a month after he filed for bankruptcy in 1995. Bill Parcells, the former New York Jets football coach, put up $150,000 of Mr. Brennan's $500,000 bail amount, according to a legal source who spoke on the condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CALENDAR</p>
        <p>Today</p>
        <p>LAND DEVELOPMENT HEARING -- The East Hampton Town Board plans to hold a public hearing on two moratoriums on land development. East Hampton Town Hall, 159 Pantigo Rd, East Hampton. 10 a.m. Information: 631-324-4140</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
