<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Silicon Valley's Primal Spirit Lives On, in a Part of Beijing</title>
    <meta content="04VALL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/04/business/04VALL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entrepreneurship</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Beijing (China)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Silicon Valley (Calif)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Qinghua University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Beijing East Doctors Information Technology (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markoff, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Beijing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entrepreneurship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EFDF143CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1507" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Silicon Valley's Primal Spirit Lives On, in a Part of Beijing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Markoff, John</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Computer technology entrepreneurship in China is being led by university students, with spirit akin to start-ups that created and continue to fuel Silicon Valley; Beijing's chaotic Zhongguancun neighborhood, site of some of nation's best universities and government's designated high-technology zone, is home to a fledgling Internet industry as well as better-known Chinese computer companies; startup Internet company called Beijing East Doctors Information Technology is run by six doctoral students in Qinghua University dormitory; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anyone searching for the soul of China's Silicon Valley can find it here, up four flights of concrete stairs, past walls with peeling paint and ledges strewn with beer bottles, down a darkened hallway and inside what was once the student activity room at Qinghua University Dormitory No. 20.</p>
        <p>It is here that a visitor will find the makeshift research and development offices of the fledgling company called Beijing East Doctors Information Technology (''doctors'' as in Ph.D.'s, not medical doctors).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anyone searching for the soul of China's Silicon Valley can find it here, up four flights of concrete stairs, past walls with peeling paint and ledges strewn with beer bottles, down a darkened hallway and inside what was once the student activity room at Qinghua University Dormitory No. 20.</p>
        <p>It is here that a visitor will find the makeshift research and development offices of the fledgling company called Beijing East Doctors Information Technology (''doctors'' as in Ph.D.'s, not medical doctors).</p>
        <p>With the blessing of the administrators at Qinghua, China's leading technical university, six graduate students are sharing their pursuit of a legend borrowed from the opposite side of the Pacific Ocean, in the original Silicon Valley -- the birthplace of companies like Hewlett-Packard and Yahoo, whose roots lie deep in the student life of Stanford University.</p>
        <p>As Yang Diange, a 27-year-old computer science student who is the chief executive of Beijing East, put it: ''That is our dream -- to be just like a Cisco or a Sun Microsystems.''</p>
        <p>Like many of the best and brightest technology companies in Silicon Valley, Hewlett-Packard, Sun and Cisco were founded by students, faculty and staff members at Stanford.</p>
        <p>Today, Beijing East, which is developing a Web site that will match technology experts with Internet users, is one of perhaps 500 or 600 recent home-grown Internet start-ups in Zhongguancun, a chaotic Beijing neighborhood that is both the site of some of the nation's best universities and the Chinese government's designated high-technology industrial zone.</p>
        <p>Zhongguancun, in the Haidian district in northwest Beijing, is home to a fledgling Internet industry as well as better-known Chinese computer and telecommunications companies like Legend Computer Systems, Founder Computer Systems and Huawei Technology.</p>
        <p>Although the Internet arrived in China only in 1997, Beijing students, when their experience is measured in ''Internet years,'' have already weathered a boom-and-bust cycle. Many tiny start-ups here have gone out of business since the April decline of the Nasdaq stock market.</p>
        <p>For the young founders of Beijing East, however, Zhongguancun is the perfect incubator. Next year the company plans to move off campus and commercialize its Internet computer support Web site.</p>
        <p>And though they work half a world away from the world's better-known high-technology mecca, this group of graduate students is in many ways closer to the authentic entrepreneurial spirit that drives Silicon Valley than many of the ersatz Silicon Deserts, Mountains, Glens and Forests, which are most frequently the public relations products of overzealous economic development agencies.</p>
        <p>''It has been remarkable to me how similar the entrepreneurial high-tech Chinese are to their American counterparts,'' said Kai-Fu Lee, an American-educated computer scientist who is director of a research laboratory that Microsoft has established in Zhongguancun.</p>
        <p>Despite the oppressive humidity that visits Beijing each summer, the Qinghua students spend 15 to 18 hours a day packed into their dormitory room with six personal computers hooked to their campus network.</p>
        <p>So far, the students have drawn no salaries and have raised about $36,000 from friends and family that was spent mostly on computers and the wages paid to some undergraduate students for programming help.</p>
        <p>They are now adding the finishing touches to their Web site, which is intended to take advantage of the latest Internet trend, a peer-to-peer service and support network. In their case, it is meant to bring together China's best technology experts with what they hope will be tens of thousands of Internet and PC novices hungry for online help in everything from surfing the Web to questions about both the Windows and Linux operating systems.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, Mr. Yang expects the company to need as much as $500,000 to start its business. Despite some concerns about a recent cooling in venture capital investment in China, he foresees no difficulties in raising the funds. Indeed, he feels the group needs to be picky even in choosing its investors.</p>
        <p>''It is not very difficult for us to find an investor for our next stage,'' he said. ''But we don't want to cooperate with common investors. We will grow faster with the help of famous investors such as International Data Group, Softbank, CMGI, etc.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Yang's confidence is echoed by other Zhongguancun start-ups.</p>
        <p>''We have venture capitalists coming to our door every week,'' said Jia En Chen, general manager of eefind .com, a Chinese-language search-engine technology development company in an office park just south of the Qinghua campus.</p>
        <p>Like Beijing East, eefind is a clear example of why the Chinese start-ups should be taken seriously.</p>
        <p>Both companies have access to sophisticated software technology and bright programmers, and they are operating on a shoestring compared with their Silicon Valley counterparts.</p>
        <p>Although eefind's extremely cramped two-room office on the top floor of the 10-story Qinghua Pioneer Park building makes even the most crowded Silicon Valley office or garage look spacious, the company has spent only about $130,000 so far in developing its search engine.</p>
        <p>Moreover, eefind.com exemplifies a second significant aspect of the Chinese technology boom. Many entrepreneurs who are founding companies are technologists who are moving here because they see the Internet boom here as real. A sense seems to prevail that in the 21st century the Internet will increasingly be dominated by the Chinese.</p>
        <p>Eefind's founder, Ming-Jer Lee, is a computer science graduate student from Taiwan who moved to Beijing to found the company.</p>
        <p>''This is where the Internet market will be,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the recent growth of the Chinese Internet suggests that he may even be understating the future. July survey statistics reported by the China Internet Network Information Center show that the number of Chinese Internet users has almost doubled, to 16.9 million from 8.9 million, in just seven months. By one estimate, the annual value of e-commerce could pass $1 billion by 2002.</p>
        <p>That the Internet is catching hold in urban China can be seen by even a casual visitor to Beijing. Many billboards that bracket the city's freeways now come equipped with Internet addresses.</p>
        <p>One of the first American companies to realize that the spirit of the Zhongguancun Internet boom was a resource to be exploited was Microsoft. Nearly two years ago, it set up a research laboratory here and tapped as its director Kai-Fu Lee, who had previously served as a vice president at both Apple Computer and Silicon Graphics, where he worked on voice recognition and 3-D software.</p>
        <p>The Microsoft laboratory, now well established, is beginning to contribute to Microsoft products under development. Mr. Lee has recruited a number of American-trained computer experts to lead the laboratory's research teams and has hired leading Chinese scientists, programmers and mathematicians.</p>
        <p>Many of his research group leaders are ethnic Chinese who agreed to return from the West, or to move from Taiwan, to build the lab.</p>
        <p>In summer, the laboratory, which occupies a single floor of a new office building in the Zhongguancun zone, plays host to 180 student interns who are developing software programs for Microsoft. The laboratory is scheduled to expand to a second floor of the building in August.</p>
        <p>Yet, despite his optimism about the potential Chinese technologists, Mr. Lee is still cautious about the possibility that Zhongguancun could rival Silicon Valley for sheer entrepreneurial innovation. In a recent article in People's Daily, he asserted that cultural differences remain.</p>
        <p>''I believe the 'real' differences between Silicon Valley and Zhongguancun are: culture, different types of talent, different definitions of innovation, different types of venture capital and different involvement of academic institutions,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>Silicon Valley has evolved a culture that is tuned to market-driven innovation, Mr. Lee noted, while in China, innovation is still largely driven by technology.</p>
        <p>He also wrote that venture capital is not playing the same role in China that it plays in Silicon Valley, where investors are frequently an integral part of a company's day-to-day operations. Things are changing in China, but until recently investors had been used only as a source of financing.</p>
        <p>There may be another crucial difference as well. Despite an intensifying housing shortage, highway traffic problems and declining quality of life in Silicon Valley, it still seems like an earthly paradise compared with the rapidly industrializing Beijing, with its chronic pollution.</p>
        <p>At a recent lunchtime meeting at the Microsoft lab here, a visitor asked seven of the American-trained computer experts recruited by Mr. Lee what they missed most about the United States. In unison the group answered, ''Fresh air!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
