<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>49ers' Rookie Hopes Time Is on His Side</title>
    <meta content="04NFLL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219942"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco 49ers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carmazzi, Giovanni</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/San Francisco 49ers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7D8173CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1235" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>49ers' Rookie Hopes Time Is on His Side</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Thomas George</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas George column on rookie quarterback Giovanni Carmazzi's disappointing preseason debut with San Francisco 49ers, team badly in need of solid and exciting quarterback; table; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The San Francisco 49ers' rebuilding task starts at quarterback. This can be brutal.</p>
        <p>It is one thing to be the Dallas Cowboys of the late 1980's, rebuilding around Troy Aikman. Or the current model, the Cleveland Browns, building around Tim Couch. But not only are the 49ers weak at too many starting positions and bare in backups behind those slots, they are also saddled with the task of finding a permanent, solid and exciting quarterback.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The San Francisco 49ers' rebuilding task starts at quarterback. This can be brutal.</p>
        <p>It is one thing to be the Dallas Cowboys of the late 1980's, rebuilding around Troy Aikman. Or the current model, the Cleveland Browns, building around Tim Couch. But not only are the 49ers weak at too many starting positions and bare in backups behind those slots, they are also saddled with the task of finding a permanent, solid and exciting quarterback.</p>
        <p>The current candidates read like a list of who's who among your most nondescript, unknown passers. Jeff Garcia is the starter for now. He showed a touch of ability last year filling in for the injured Steve Young. Now that Young has retired, Garcia -- quick feet, decent arm, courageous but limited -- is the immediate answer.</p>
        <p>Tim Rattay, drafted from Louisiana Tech this year (seventh round, 212th overall selection), has big-game collegiate experience. But at barely 6 feet tall, he lacks ideal size. Rick Mirer has tossed his hat into the ring, but the eight-year veteran suffered miserably last year as a Jet.</p>
        <p>And then there is Giovanni Carmazzi.</p>
        <p>They call him Gio. A big, strapping quarterback (6-3, 224 pounds) who was a third-round selection of the 49ers in last April's draft, the 65th player selected over all. He is from Hofstra University, where he set 11 school passing records and threw 71 career touchdown passes. Smart guy (valedictorian of his high school near Sacramento). Strong arm. Mobile enough.</p>
        <p>Last Monday night, like the rest of the 49ers' 36 rookies, Carmazzi gained an opportunity to show what he could do against the New England Patriots in the annual Hall of Fame preseason game in Canton, Ohio. What a chance! Your National Football League debut on national television after a weekend when three 49ers, led by Joe Montana, the essence of quarterbacking, entered the Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>In his rosiest dreams, Carmazzi would torch the field. He would fire the football to receivers left and right and short and long. Show command of the offense. Lead with poise and flair. Give the 49ers hope that not only was a star born, but a long-term answer to their quarterback problems unveiled.</p>
        <p>But Gio blew up.</p>
        <p>He looked anxious, nervous and overwhelmed in a quarter of work. He exhibited happy feet in the pocket. He bailed out when the pass-rushing surge neared him. He threw passes too high, too low and too hard. He called a wrong audible. He was sacked twice. He completed only 3 of 7 passes.</p>
        <p>He looked like a rookie. An awfully green one.</p>
        <p>It was easy to see on the faces of the 49ers' players, coaches and management that they were roundly disappointed. The hope was that Carmazzi would somehow immediately hit the ground sprinting and shock them and the N.F.L. That he would be so good so fast that there was no way the 49ers could keep him out of the starting lineup. That maybe he would be a rookie version of the St. Louis Rams' Kurt Warner. And, indeed, all of that could still happen.</p>
        <p>But after one preseason game, and let us emphasize the one, reality set in. Carmazzi will need time and grooming, just like nearly every rookie quarterback in N.F.L. history.</p>
        <p>''I thought I would be more nervous in the game than I was, but actually I was most nervous earlier in the day,'' Carmazzi said.</p>
        <p>That is a scary thought, indeed, because he looked shellshocked on Monday night.</p>
        <p>''I had fun but it was obvious I have a lot to learn and a lot of adjustments that need to be made,'' Carmazzi said. ''In college we used about five or six formations. Here I've got 50 to 100. Everything out there was new from the setting to my teammates to the opponent. I definitely felt like a rookie. I was a little wound up. I didn't feel comfortable. But I'm a tense guy and that's kind of what I look like even when I'm comfortable and successful.''</p>
        <p>That trait has some 49ers wondering just what they have in Carmazzi, and it has caused a definitive split on the team. Some see a strong potential answer for the future, so smart and strong and big, and a kid who will learn on the run. Others see him as lacking the traits essential to good quarterbacking -- a calm presence, a coolness exuded in the toughest situations.</p>
        <p>''What you saw in that game is some of what we have seen in practices, but we know he has ability,'' said Bill Walsh, the 49ers' vice president and general manager. ''He has got to find a way to relax so that he can compete. Sometimes he looks fearful of what's happening around him. In this game he looked at the Patriots' pass rush and took his eyes off receivers, and that's the last thing a quarterback can do. He has no chance if he continues to do that. We're all optimistic.''</p>
        <p>Carmazzi gets another chance tomorrow when San Diego plays at San Francisco. And then more chances through the preseason and perhaps in N.F.L. Europe next year.</p>
        <p>''It was his first pro game ever, so some of what happened was to be expected,'' said 49ers receiver Jerry Rice. ''He was a little tense and he wanted so badly to do all of the right things. Pressure situations are how you build. It is hard to say just what is going to happen with Gio. But as a rookie you take the good with the bad. He reminded me of my first year.''</p>
        <p>A year when Rice dropped passes and was hounded as people wondered if he could cut it.</p>
        <p>Joe Gardi, Carmazzi's coach at Hofstra, was at the Hall of Fame game.</p>
        <p>''I saw Gio let the ball get away from him a little bit,'' he said. ''It reminded me of how he started his career here. He was benched for a while. But we found that Gio was a late comer, that he won games in the third and fourth quarter. Everything with him is correctable. He's got to get the cobwebs out and get more experience. He just has to fit all of the pieces together. It was one game, one preseason game at that. I know it would be a mistake to ever give up on Gio.''</p>
        <p>Give up? Heck, the kid just got started. Brett Favre was shipped from Atlanta because the Falcons gave up on him. Even Montana in his first season with the 49ers watched as a backup to Steve DeBerg.</p>
        <p>For Carmazzi, for the 49ers, school is in. Expect hard knocks.</p>
        <p>''I've always been a guy who took the road less traveled, it seems,'' Carmazzi said. ''I need to continue to work on the things that got me to the 49ers, especially my drops, making precise reads and executing plays. I'd like to be a 49er for a very long time. I know this game is very fleeting. You see it every day in the N.F.L.''</p>
        <p>ON PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
