<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Freezing Is Pleasing</title>
    <meta content="04FAMI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219869"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FAMILY FARE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Zoos</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Central Park Wildlife Center/zoo (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graeber, Laurel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3D81F3DF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="981" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Freezing Is Pleasing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Laurel Graeber</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Graeber, Laurel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Events for the whole family coming up in New York include Chill Out! Weekend at Central Park Zoo, Hambletonian Day at Meadowlands Racetrack and Aah-Pootee! That's Snow, a play at Theater of the Riverside Church; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gus, Ida and Lily are like any teenagers during the summer: they love their frozen treats. Don't offer them anything as mundane as ice cream, though. They prefer honey and chocolate on something really tempting, like red snapper or frozen mackerel.</p>
        <p>Sound disgusting? That's because you don't understand polar bears' tastes. But you will if you visit the Central Park Zoo tomorrow or Sunday for Chill Out! Weekend, where experts will compete each day at 1 p.m. at concocting bear-friendly feasts. The contest's format will be similar to that of the popular television show ''The Iron Chef.'' Two of the zoo's keepers will try to outdo ''the ice chef,'' a professional.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gus, Ida and Lily are like any teenagers during the summer: they love their frozen treats. Don't offer them anything as mundane as ice cream, though. They prefer honey and chocolate on something really tempting, like red snapper or frozen mackerel.</p>
        <p>Sound disgusting? That's because you don't understand polar bears' tastes. But you will if you visit the Central Park Zoo tomorrow or Sunday for Chill Out! Weekend, where experts will compete each day at 1 p.m. at concocting bear-friendly feasts. The contest's format will be similar to that of the popular television show ''The Iron Chef.'' Two of the zoo's keepers will try to outdo ''the ice chef,'' a professional.</p>
        <p>''Each chef will have the same ingredients and have 10 minutes to come up with an interesting creation,'' said Diana Heide, a zoo spokeswoman. ''Ray Riffe, the main keeper for the polar bears, has made cakes for them for years. It will be fun to see if that is an advantage or if fresh ideas are the determining factor.'' (The bears will judge.)</p>
        <p>Children can also enjoy friendly competition based on the other featured species, the penguin. They will put elastic bands around their ankles, pair off and see who can waddle faster. They will also have 30 seconds to build penguin nests from rocks.</p>
        <p>Those with an artistic bent can make polar bear fans and watch Ice Fantasies, a Brooklyn company, carve ice sculptures. Radio Disney will visit the event, the Cat in the Hat will be at the Tisch Children's Zoo, and the Wildlife Theater will present ''Polar Bear and the Beat.''</p>
        <p>''What's cool about our penguin exhibit is that we've had eight chicks born since June 27,'' Ms. Heide said. ''You can see the parents feeding them, and it's adorable.''</p>
        <p>Chill Out! Weekend, tomorrow and Sunday from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. at the Central Park Zoo, Fifth Avenue at 64th Street, (212) 861-6030. Free with admission: $3.50; the elderly, $1.25; ages 3 to 12, 50 cents.</p>
        <p>A Day at the Races</p>
        <p>Most children aren't interested in racing unless it involves engines, especially their own. But today and tomorrow the Meadowlands Racetrack will give them reasons to appreciate another kind of horsepower.</p>
        <p>The fun is the 75th anniversary of the Hambletonian, an annual trotting race. From 9 a.m. to noon today, families can enjoy an open house that includes breakfast and tours of the track's barns, horse hospital and blacksmith shop.</p>
        <p>''It's great for the kids, because they get to be up close and personal with the horses,'' said Glenn Cademartori, the Meadowlands' director of marketing and development. ''They get to pet them, and we bring giant carrots so they can feed them.''</p>
        <p>Children can also touch other animals at a petting zoo, as well as decorate and take home horseshoes, enjoy amusement rides and see racing exhibits. They can even get into the saddle themselves: pony rides will be offered all morning and evening.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow Hambletonian Day will feature the petting zoo, a reptile display, face painters, clowns and costumed characters.</p>
        <p>Oh, and by the way, ''we're also racing for a million dollars,'' Mr. Cademartori said.</p>
        <p>Hambletonian Open House, today from 9 a.m. to noon at the Meadowlands Racetrack, 50 State Route 120, East Rutherford, N.J., (201) 843-2446. Free. Pony and amusement rides tonight from 6 to 10; free. Hambletonian Day, tomorrow from 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Admission: $1.</p>
        <p>An Icy Adventure</p>
        <p>''Aah-Pootee! That's Snow'' begins with what must be, at one time or another, every small child's fantasy: not only running away, but also finding an obliging monster who will gobble up an oblivious, harried, too-busy-for-play mother. (My 5-year-old son seemed suspiciously discomfited by the idea that such a quest might actually be fulfilled.)</p>
        <p>Not to worry. ''Aah-Pootee,'' the final event of the New York Family Arts Festival at the Theater of the Riverside Church in Manhattan, is a children's musical, so mommy-devouring is banned. But the heroine, called O.K. Okay (this, she explains, is how her mother addresses her), still seems likely to get her wish: her home turf is the tundra, where all kinds of creatures roam.</p>
        <p>O.K. (Michelle Luchese) encounters several, including an avuncular moose (Michael Givens), a workaholic sled dog (Alex Keomurjian), a doting polar bear (Kendall March), the bear's cubs (Adeline Lee and Blaine Morris), fashion-victim seals (Megan G. Jones and Kelly Boczek) and a lion longing for a throne (Raphael Peacock). None qualify as monsters, except for the aspiring lion king, whose role model would appear to be Scar rather than Simba.</p>
        <p>May Ebbitt Cutler, the founder and former head of Tundra Books, a Canadian publisher, wrote the book and lyrics for the musical, whose title is an Inuit word for snow. Andrew Svoboda composed the score, which ranges delightfully from lullabylike melodies to jazzy tunes.</p>
        <p>The dialogue has some cute jokes, although at two hours (including an intermission), the play is far too long for preschoolers. Fortunately, the second act includes a through-the-audience chase scene, a hilarious number (''Time to Think'') and a parent-and-child reunion that will leave youngsters satisfied -- and busy mothers feeling a little less guilty.</p>
        <p>''Aah-Pootee! That's Snow!'' at the Theater of the Riverside Church, 91 Claremont Avenue, at 120th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 870-6784. Today at 7 p.m., tomorrow at 1 and 7 p.m.; Sunday at 2 p.m. Tickets: $18; the elderly, $12; children, $10. Family discounts.</p>
        <p>FAMILY FARE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
