<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Canada Goes Aboard Ship To Retrieve Its Weapons</title>
    <meta content="Y04CAN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/04/world/04cana.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219969"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Katie (Ship)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E0DF143CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="745" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Canada Goes Aboard Ship To Retrieve Its Weapons</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <dateline>MONTREAL, Aug. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Canadian troops swing down from a helicopter to board American merchant ship Katie, which for almost three weeks has held three Canadian soldiers and 10 percent of Canada's armored might hostage on high seas over nonpayment of shipping bill; incident spotlighted logistical weakness of Canada's military; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ending a naval wrangle that highlighted the logistical weakness of the Canadian military, Canadian troops swung down from a helicopter today to board an American merchant ship that for almost three weeks had held three Canadian soldiers and 10 percent of Canada's armored might hostage on the high seas over nonpayment of a shipping bill.</p>
        <p>Without any sea-lift capacity of its own, Canada moves its personnel and materiel either by private freighter or by arranging rides to wars and peacekeeping assignments aboard the ships of other NATO countries. This afternoon, with the money owed by a Montreal shipping company still unpaid, Canada's defense minister, Art Eggleton, ordered soldiers from a Canadian naval vessel, the Athabaskan, to board the merchant ship, the Katie, which had been anchored in international waters off the southeast coast of Newfoundland.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ending a naval wrangle that highlighted the logistical weakness of the Canadian military, Canadian troops swung down from a helicopter today to board an American merchant ship that for almost three weeks had held three Canadian soldiers and 10 percent of Canada's armored might hostage on the high seas over nonpayment of a shipping bill.</p>
        <p>Without any sea-lift capacity of its own, Canada moves its personnel and materiel either by private freighter or by arranging rides to wars and peacekeeping assignments aboard the ships of other NATO countries. This afternoon, with the money owed by a Montreal shipping company still unpaid, Canada's defense minister, Art Eggleton, ordered soldiers from a Canadian naval vessel, the Athabaskan, to board the merchant ship, the Katie, which had been anchored in international waters off the southeast coast of Newfoundland.</p>
        <p>The boarding of the ship, which flies the flag of St. Vincent and the Grenadines, took place without injuries, although Reuters reported that the Ukrainian captain, Vitaly Khlebnikov, ''engaged the ship in violent maneuvers'' as a Canadian Sea King helicopter lowered the soldiers by cable. After the boarding, the freighter, escorted by a Canadian frigate and destroyer, resumed course to its original destination, Becancour, a port downriver on the St. Lawrence.</p>
        <p>''Boarding this vessel became necessary after all other reasonable solutions were exhausted,'' Mr. Eggleton said at a news conference after the incident this afternoon. Referring to the billing standoff, which was almost a month old, he added: ''There was no end in sight to this dispute. No responsible government can allow interference with its military personnel or equipment.''</p>
        <p>For Canadians, the spectacle of $150 million worth of tanks and munitions held hostage over a $100,000 bill was either a joke or a sad commentary on how Ottawa has starved successive military budgets.</p>
        <p>Looking at the ''amusing'' side, The Globe and Mail in Toronto editorialized today, saying, ''The Ukrainian crew of a Soviet-era ship flying the flag of that great naval power, St. Vincent and the Grenadines, holds hostage Canadian military equipment because of a financial dispute that does not even involve the Canadian government.''</p>
        <p>But The National Post, Canada's conservative national newspaper, saw the deep-sea standoff as a national humiliation.</p>
        <p>''It is hard to decide which is the most pitiful part of this story,'' the newspaper said today, before the boarding. ''Is it that Canada's navy, which in 1946 was the third largest in the world, today doesn't even have the ability to transport our army to battle? ''Is it that a key element of our national security was delegated to a foreign company? Is it that fully 10 percent of Canada's armored force can fit on a single ship?''</p>
        <p>Returning from a Canadian peacekeeping mission in Kosovo, the cargo included 580 tanks, armored personnel carriers and reconnaissance vehicles as well as 390 sea containers loaded with 500 tons of weapons, ammunition and electronic gear.</p>
        <p>''Exposure to salt and humidity are decidedly bad for tanks, vehicles and high-tech equipment, no matter how well wrapped they may be,'' The Globe and Mail said today. ''National Defense must get the equipment back as quickly as possible.''</p>
        <p>Under international maritime law, a boarding may occur if permission is granted by the captain, by the owner or by the country of registry. St. Vincent and the Grenadines told Canada that it did not object to the boarding.</p>
        <p>''We still regard it as a commercial dispute,'' Mary Ellen Gilroy, public affairs officer for the United States Embassy, said this evening.</p>
        <p>Peter Margan, president of the company that owns the freighter, Third Ocean Marine Navigation of Annapolis, Md., has said that halting the Katie in international waters was the only leverage he had over the delinquent company, Andromeda Navigation of Montreal. Andromeda stopped payment to Mr. Margan's company on July 5 because of counterclaims against it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
