<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Split Over Bangladeshi Event Believed to Prompt Threats</title>
    <meta content="04THRE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000812T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219976"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Threats and Threatening Messages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bangladeshi-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bangladesh</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewan, Shaila K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Bangladesh</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Threats and Threatening Messages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E5DE143CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Split Over Bangladeshi Event Believed to Prompt Threats</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHAILA K. DEWAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dewan, Shaila K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Five Bangladeshi-American newspapers in New York City receive threatening letters and mysterious powder, prompting investigation by anti-terrorism task force; letters referred to Fobana, name of annual Bangladeshi convention in New York over Labor Day weekend; squabbling over rights to run event linked (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For almost all of New York's handful of Bengali-language newspapers, Tuesday was a harrowing day involving the city police, the postal police, F.B.I. agents, hazardous materials experts and, for some, showers in tents set up outside their evacuated offices. Yesterday, they were left wondering what the fuss had been about.</p>
        <p>The excitement came after five Bangladeshi-American newspapers, one in Manhattan and the rest in Queens, and one cultural organization, also in Queens, received envelopes containing threatening letters and a mysterious brown or white powder, prompting an investigation by the city's joint task force on terrorism, which includes police officers and federal agents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For almost all of New York's handful of Bengali-language newspapers, Tuesday was a harrowing day involving the city police, the postal police, F.B.I. agents, hazardous materials experts and, for some, showers in tents set up outside their evacuated offices. Yesterday, they were left wondering what the fuss had been about.</p>
        <p>The excitement came after five Bangladeshi-American newspapers, one in Manhattan and the rest in Queens, and one cultural organization, also in Queens, received envelopes containing threatening letters and a mysterious brown or white powder, prompting an investigation by the city's joint task force on terrorism, which includes police officers and federal agents.</p>
        <p>As best Abu Taher, the executive editor of Weekly Bangla Patrika, could remember, the letter he received began ''Fobana Alert: Take the sweet taste of nerve gas.''</p>
        <p>Fobana, which stands for Federation of Bangladeshi Associations of North America, is the name of an annual Bangladeshi convention to be held in New York on Labor Day weekend.</p>
        <p>Kowshik Ahmed, the editor of The Weekly Bangalee , said an employee had opened a similar letter and placed it in another envelope. Shortly afterward, he arrived in the office and got a call from the police. They asked him if he had received a suspicious letter, and when he said yes, they told him to drop it on the floor and leave the building.</p>
        <p>No one who came into contact with the powder was injured or became ill, said James Margolin, a spokesman for the Federal Bureau of Investigation. He said the powder was being analyzed at a lab. But, he said, sending the letters could have been a criminal act no matter what the powder contained, and no matter what the intention of the sender.</p>
        <p>''The use of the federal mail to transmit a threat is illegal whether the threat is terrorist or not,'' Mr. Margolin said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taher said he had no idea what could have prompted the threats. But he and others who received the letters suspected that they had less to do with the machinations of international terrorists, and more to do with a controversy within the Bangladeshi-American community over Fobana 2000.</p>
        <p>The annual convention, which includes seminars and cultural events by artists from Bangladesh, has long been troubled by splits and factions. This year, there will be three Fobanas.</p>
        <p>The squabbling over who has the rights to the official Fobana began last year, when two Fobanas were held in Atlanta. One convention designated a Bangladeshi organization in Toronto to be the host of this year's Fobana, which it plans to do. Then, the other convention designated a New York organization to handle this year's convention. Two organizations are claiming that honor. One will hold Fobana 2000 at the Pier 92 convention center on Sept. 1, 2, and 3. The other will hold Fobana 2000 at Madison Square Garden the same weekend. The organizers of both conventions said they believed the letters were connected to the dueling conventions. Both condemned the threats.</p>
        <p>''It is a very sad thing such a nasty thing can happen,'' said Shelley A. Mubdi, the organizer of the Pier 92 convention. ''It shocks us. I have a hunch why it is happening.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mubdi went on to explain that the Atlanta convention had designated his organization, the Bangla Desh League of America, to be the host of this year's Fobana. But because he was not present, another New Yorker, Saidur Rab, the owner of The Weekly Thikana, had accepted on his behalf. Then, according to Mr. Mubdi, Mr. Rab incorporated his own organization, the Bangladesh League of America, New York, and proceeded to organize his own convention.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rab said he had been involved in his organization for 17 years. But according to state records, his organization was not incorporated until after the Atlanta convention, while Mr. Mubdi's was incorporated in 1947. He added that most of the newspapers that received the letters, except Mr. Taher's, were sponsors of his convention.</p>
        <p>Muhammad Alam, a staff reporter at The Weekly Bangladesh in Jamaica, Queens, which did not receive a letter, said the fight over the biggest convention in a small community -- there are an estimated 200,000 Bangladeshi-Americans in New York -- was one of egos, not politics or ideology.</p>
        <p>''There is some ego problem in people,'' he said. ''That's terrible.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 12, 2000, Saturday  An article on Aug. 4 about threatening letters that were sent to several Bengali-language newspapers and a Bangladeshi organization in New York, referring to two competing conventions planned for the Labor Day weekend, both named Fobana 2000, misstated the day the letters were received. It was Aug. 2, not Aug. 1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 12, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Aug. 4 about threatening letters that were sent to several Bengali-language newspapers and a Bangladeshi organization in New York, referring to two competing conventions planned for the Labor Day weekend, both named Fobana 2000, misstated the day the letters were received. It was Aug. 2, not Aug. 1.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
