<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CABARET GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="04CABA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219874"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EFD6163CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CABARET GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing of new or noteworthy cabaret shows in Manhattan this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>CHARLES CERMELE, Arci's Place, 450 Park Avenue South, at 30th Street, (212) 532-4370. A friendly, big-voiced baritone, Mr. Cermele has apparently never met a popular standard he didn't like. Even the gloomiest ballad is given an upbeat tilt by this affable singer, whose presentation of songs at times recalls Bert Parks introducing the latest Miss America. His fascination with vintage pop is all wrapped up with his devotion to his Italian-American family, and the songs are interspersed with funny anecdotes about his childhood in a New Jersey suburb. Tomorrow night at 8:30 and 11. Other performers: Cabaret Festival through Aug. 21, with Stan Martin, host, and Jill Corey, Lynn diMenna and Joan Crowe, singers, on Sunday night at 8; Carolyn Montgomery, Heather Gilchrist, Julie Reyburn, Marnie Baumer and Julie Corbett Leon, singers, Monday night at 8. In a salute to the Manhattan Association of Cabarets and Clubs, the Accidentals, vocal group, and Joyce Breach, jazz singer, Tuesday night at 9; Carlos Martin and Natalie Gamsu, singers, Wednesday night at 9; Thomas, singer, and Georga Osborn, female musical comedy group, Thursday night at 9. Cover: $25; $15 minimum (Stephen Holden).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing of new or noteworthy cabaret shows in Manhattan this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>CHARLES CERMELE, Arci's Place, 450 Park Avenue South, at 30th Street, (212) 532-4370. A friendly, big-voiced baritone, Mr. Cermele has apparently never met a popular standard he didn't like. Even the gloomiest ballad is given an upbeat tilt by this affable singer, whose presentation of songs at times recalls Bert Parks introducing the latest Miss America. His fascination with vintage pop is all wrapped up with his devotion to his Italian-American family, and the songs are interspersed with funny anecdotes about his childhood in a New Jersey suburb. Tomorrow night at 8:30 and 11. Other performers: Cabaret Festival through Aug. 21, with Stan Martin, host, and Jill Corey, Lynn diMenna and Joan Crowe, singers, on Sunday night at 8; Carolyn Montgomery, Heather Gilchrist, Julie Reyburn, Marnie Baumer and Julie Corbett Leon, singers, Monday night at 8. In a salute to the Manhattan Association of Cabarets and Clubs, the Accidentals, vocal group, and Joyce Breach, jazz singer, Tuesday night at 9; Carlos Martin and Natalie Gamsu, singers, Wednesday night at 9; Thomas, singer, and Georga Osborn, female musical comedy group, Thursday night at 9. Cover: $25; $15 minimum (Stephen Holden).</p>
        <p>MARC SALEM, Feinstein's, at the Regency, 540 Park Avenue, at 61st Street, (212) 339-4095. Marc Salem is the mental magician who dazzled audiences at the Westside Theater in Midtown with his 1997 show ''Mind Games.'' Now, Mr. Salem, accompanied by a bass, piano and percussion trio, is in residence at Feinstein's through Sept. 2 with ''Mind Games and All That Jazz.'' But handsome as it is, Feinstein's at the Regency may not be the ideal setting for the display of Mr. Salem's enjoyable bag of tricks. The intimacy of Feinstein's, where Mr. Salem seems to be working with a smaller palette than at the Westside Theater, detracts from the the aura of magic that can surround, say, a wristwatch that suddenly changes the time it displays. The jazz trio Vibrations, as pleasant and talented as it is, provides little more than a few attractive introductory numbers and a bit of musical commentary of the ''Twilight Zone'' sort. Nevertheless, Mr. Salem and his wizardry provide cool fun for hot summer nights. Fridays and Saturdays at 8:30 and 11 p.m.; Sunday at 1:30; Wednesday and Thursday at 8:30 p.m.. Cover: $40 for weekends; no cover on weekdays; dinner required for early show on weekends, with seating beginning at 6; a la carte supper menu with $20 minimum for late show; $35 for early show; Sunday brunch is $30 and cover is $30. Through Sept. 2 (Lawrence Van Gelder).</p>
        <p>* ''OUR SINATRA,'' Blue Angel Theater, 323 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. The rising young cabaret star Eric Comstock is the mastermind behind this utterly winning tribute to Ol' Blue Eyes, which focuses on what Mr. Comstock calls the hidden gems and orphan songs that Sinatra made popular. Joined by Christopher Gines, a creamy baritone who echoes Dick Haymes and Steve Lawrence in their prime, and Hilary Kole, a perky swinger, Mr. Comstock conducts a witty and knowledgeable survey of the Sinatra canon. Mr. Comstock concentrates on the mature Sinatra and Mr. Gines on the dreamy 1940's balladeer, with Ms. Kole bridging the gap. The memorable show proves there are still young singers good enough to keep the tradition alive. Today and Monday through Wednesday at 8 p.m.; tomorrow at 2:30 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $50 and $55; premium ringside seating, $75 and $80 (Holden).</p>
        <p>BEMELMANS BAR, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, (212) 744-1600. The pianist Peter Mintun. Tuesdays through Saturdays, beginning at 9:30. Through Oct. 14. No cover for early show; cover for late show: $10. No minimum; $5 cover at the bar.</p>
        <p>CARNEGIE CLUB, 156 West 56th Street, (212) 957-9676. Cary Hoffman, with the 11-piece Carnegie Club Orchestra, plays music made famous by Frank Sinatra in the 1950's, featuring the original arrangements by Nelson Riddle. Fridays and Saturdays at 9:30 and 11 p.m. The cover is $20; two-drink ($15) minimum.</p>
        <p>DANNY'S SKYLIGHT ROOM, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133. Tonight from 9 to 1 in the piano bar, Jerry Scott. Tomorrow evening from 5 to 9, Chuck Musone; from 9 to 1, in the piano bar, Mr. Scott; at 9:15, Nikayah Blackman, singer. Sunday night from 7 to 11, Sol Yaged and friends. Monday night at 7, ''Not Just Davyd,'' with Davyd Dean, and Bill Zeffiro, pianist; from 8 to midnight, Chris Barrett. Cover: free to $12; $10 minimum.</p>
        <p>DON'T TELL MAMA, 343 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 757-0788. Tonight at 8, ''A Midsummer Night's Sing,'' variety show; at 8:30, ''Poole Party!,'' comedy variety show, with Ron Poole; at 10, Richard Skipper, impersonator, as Carol Channing; at 11, Ron Seykell, Broadway singer, with Lenny Babbish, pianist. Tomorrow night at 6, Danielle Eddo, singer, with Michael McFrederick, pianist; at 6:30, ''The Stand-Up Comedy Experience''; at 8, Victoria Bundonis, singer, with Gregory Toroian, pianist; at 8:30, ''Poole Party!''; at 11, Tommy Femia impersonates Judy Garland. Sunday at 3 p.m., Sue Matsuki, singer, with Gerry Dieffenbach, pianist; at 5, ''An Afternoon in the Spotlight,'' talent showcase; at 6, Stephen Cornine, singer, songwriter and pianist. Cover: Free to $18. Two-drink minimum. No credit cards.</p>
        <p>FIREBIRD CAFE, Firebird Cafe, 363 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 586-0244. Billy Stritch, singer and pianist, Friday nights at 9 and 11; Thursday nights at 9 (through Aug. 18). Cover: $30; $15 minimum. Tomorrow night at 9, Natalie Douglas, singer. Cover: $20; $15 minimum. Tomorrow night at 11, Alton F. White, singer, in ''How Do I Feel.'' Cover: $30; $15 minimum. Sunday at 7 p.m., Carol McCann, part of Songwriter's series; at 9, David Friedman, singer. Cover: $20; $15 minimum.</p>
        <p>HUDSON RIVER PARK'S MOONDANCE SERIES, Pier 25, North Moore Street, near West Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 533-7275. Sunday night, dancing and music begin at 6:30; swing music with Blue Saracens. Free.</p>
        <p>JOE'S PUB, Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778 or (212) 239-6200. Tonight through Sunday night at 8:30, Sandra Bernhard, singer and comedian, in ''Songs I Sang on the Kibbutz,'' with a five-piece band. Tickets: $30. Tomorrow night at 11:30, Da Lata, dance group. Tickets: $15.</p>
        <p>UPSTAIRS AT ROSE'S TURN, 55 Grove Street, West Village, (212) 366-5438. Tonight and tomorrow night at 11, ''Candy Comedy Hour.'' Tomorrow night at 7, Jorge Luis Altamirano, singer; at 9, Corito, singer. Cover: $5 to $7; two-drink minimum. No credit cards.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
