<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEW VIDEO RELEASES</title>
    <meta content="04VIDB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219884"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E4DF173CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEW VIDEO RELEASES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter M. Nichols</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roundup of new home video releases; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Holy Smoke</p>
        <p>''Thank God it's Quantas!'' cries Ruth Barron's mother (Julie Hamilton), on her way to Sydney from India with her headstrong daughter, Ruth (Kate Winslet, left), whom she has been trying to extract from her guru. Back home Ruth is turned over to a tough ''cult exiter'' named P. J. Waters (Harvey Keitel), but gradually he is overmatched. Though it has sensual allure, Jane Campion's film isn't helped by a screenplay that, Janet Maslin wrote in The New York Times, ''threatens to become heavy-handedly ideological beneath its outward whimsy.''</p>
        <p>1999. Miramax. $104.16; DVD, $29.99. 114 minutes. Closed captioned. R. Release date: Aug. 8.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Holy Smoke</p>
        <p>''Thank God it's Quantas!'' cries Ruth Barron's mother (Julie Hamilton), on her way to Sydney from India with her headstrong daughter, Ruth (Kate Winslet, left), whom she has been trying to extract from her guru. Back home Ruth is turned over to a tough ''cult exiter'' named P. J. Waters (Harvey Keitel), but gradually he is overmatched. Though it has sensual allure, Jane Campion's film isn't helped by a screenplay that, Janet Maslin wrote in The New York Times, ''threatens to become heavy-handedly ideological beneath its outward whimsy.''</p>
        <p>1999. Miramax. $104.16; DVD, $29.99. 114 minutes. Closed captioned. R. Release date: Aug. 8.</p>
        <p>Reindeer Games</p>
        <p>In Michigan in the dead of slate-gray winter a dimple-chinned convict named Rudy (Ben Affleck) gets out of prison and goes home to romance Ashley (Charlize Theron), with whom a recently deceased prisoner has been corresponding. Ashley has never seen her pen pal or his picture, so Rudy slides by on that front, but he has trouble when Ashley's lowlife brother (Gary Sinise) wants to use his expertise to rob a casino on an Indian reservation. John Frankenheimer's film reflects his bent for swift, scary violence, but at the end ''a needlessly complicated mechanism is a blow to the breakneck wiliness that has come before'' (Elvis Mitchell).</p>
        <p>2000. Dimension. $107.37; DVD, $29.99. 104 minutes. Closed captioned. R. Release date: Aug. 8.</p>
        <p>Bedrooms and Hallways</p>
        <p>Rose Troche's comedy reaches for Noel Coward, but without the sharp class distinctions and with a lot more sex. A love-starved gay artisan named Leo (Kevin McKidd) has an affair with Brendan (James Purefoy). But then there is Sally (Jennifer Ehle), Leo's high school sweetheart, who is breaking up with Brendan. Does Leo tell her he's sleeping with her former boyfriend? Having begun to explore the ins and outs of bisexuality, the film then ''loses its nerve and turns into a shallow sitcom in which everyone is abruptly and mechanically paired off'' (Stephen Holden).</p>
        <p>1999. First Run Features. $79.95. 96 minutes. Release date: Aug 8.</p>
        <p>The Grandfather</p>
        <p>Now impoverished, Rodrigo, Count of Albrit (Fernando Fernan-Gomez), determines to discover which of his granddaughters (Cristina Cruz and Alicia Rozas) is of his blood. Complicating that question, their mother, Lucrecia (Cayetana Guillen Cuervo), who was unfaithful to Don Rodrigo's son when he was alive and now profits from a liaison with a government minister, uses her influence to throw the old man off the track. Part paean to the genuine riches of life, Jose Luis Garcia's film ''brims with understandings of the complexities of relationships, the frailties of humankind and the possibilities of joy'' (Lawrence Van Gelder).</p>
        <p>1999. Miramax. $104.16; DVD, $29.99. 147 minutes. Spanish with English subtitles. PG. Release date: Aug. 8.</p>
        <p>Straight to Video</p>
        <p>Other new titles of interest, some of which may have had a theater release, appeared on television or been on videocassette in earlier editions.</p>
        <p>THE BEATLES COLLECTION. Four DVD's, slickly packaged, include ''Help!'' (90 minutes), with a mad scientist and demented mystics chasing the boys around the world after the ring on Ringo's finger; ''Magical Mystery Tour'' (50 minutes), a psychedelic gambol through the countryside; ''The First U.S. Visit'' (83 minutes), with three performances on the Ed Sullivan Show, and ''You Can't Do That! The Making of 'A Hard Day's Night' '' (60 minutes), with Phil Collins reflecting on the evolution of Richard Lester's movie about an imaginary day in the life of the group. 2000. M.P.I. $79.99. Release date: Aug. 8.</p>
        <p>ROSETTA. Tired of being poor, a desperate 17-year-old Belgian girl (Emilie Dequenne) is determined to land work at any cost. Foraging for her existence, she scratches for sustenance and covets a friend's position as a cook at a waffle stand, to the extent that she hesitates to rescue him when he falls into a river. Luc and Jean-Pierre Dardenne's stoically drab film won the top prize at last year's Cannes Film Festival, with Ms. Dequenne named best actress, and the Darwinian struggle to survive makes a great subject. But ''this time the Dardenne brothers pushed too hard,'' Stephen Holden wrote in The New York Times. ''Instead of feeling universal, the movie feels claustrophobic.'' 1999. USA. $56.49. 95 minutes. French with English subtitles. R.</p>
        <p>STRANGE IMPERSONATION. An interesting piece of 40's noir, Anthony Mann's film involves a lab accident, a scarred face, swapped identities and revenge on former lovers and enemies. 1946. Kino. $24.95. 68 minutes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
