<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="04DIGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219966"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DF143CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bessemer Trust to Acquire Two Units of a Rival Firm  Bessemer Trust, one of the oldest firms in the business of managing money for wealthy families, will announce today that it is buying the private client and institutional equity groups of a rival, Brundage, Story &amp; Rose.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bessemer Trust to Acquire Two Units of a Rival Firm  Bessemer Trust, one of the oldest firms in the business of managing money for wealthy families, will announce today that it is buying the private client and institutional equity groups of a rival, Brundage, Story &amp; Rose.</p>
        <p>Terms of the deal were not disclosed. But executives said the deal would add $4.5 billion in assets under management and about 800 clients to Bessemer, which has $33 billion under management and 1,300 clients. Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette is buying Brundage, Story's institutional fixed-income division. [Page C2.]</p>
        <p>Spirit of Silicon Valley Lives in China  Zhongguancun, a chaotic Beijing neighborhood, is both the site of some of China's best universities and the government's designated high-technology industrial zone -- its Silicon Valley -- where there are 500 to 600 recent home-grown Internet start-ups. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Walt Disney Profit Increases 48%  Walt Disney reported a 48 percent rise in third-quarter profit, citing strong advertising sales at its ABC television network. The strong advertising market, buoyed by hit show ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire,'' kept Disney well ahead of Wall Street's expectations. Before Disney announced its results, its shares closed at $42.3125, up $2.1875. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Viacom said second-quarter profit fell because of good-will expenses for its purchase of CBS, but the results still beat expectations. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Reverse Slide and Close Up  Stocks pulled out of an early skid and rallied to finish broadly higher. The Nasdaq composite index gained 101.42 points, or 2.8 percent, to 3,759.88. The Dow Jones industrial average edged up 19.05 points, to 10,706.58, while the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index rose 13.86 points, or 1 percent, to 1,452.56. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Tom Clancy Defects to Michael Ovitz  In another sign of Michael Ovitz's return to power as a Hollywood deal maker, Mr. Ovitz has persuaded the thriller writer Tom Clancy to defect from his longtime agent, Robert Gottlieb at the William Morris Agency. [C4.]</p>
        <p>No Gene-Altered Food for Novartis  Novartis, one of the world's leading agricultural biotechnology companies, said that it had eliminated genetically engineered ingredients from all of its food products. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Rival Emerges to N.T.T. in Japan  Japan Telecom, one of this nation's largest telecommunications companies, plans to offer local phone service, which would put it into direct competition with Nippon Telegraph and Telephone, the former government phone monopoly. Haruo Murakami, president of Japan Telecom, said that his company had applied to N.T.T. for the right to tap into its local network. Japan Telecom could offer the new service in 2001. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Law Firm Mergers Cross Borders  Pushed by globalization and a boom in corporate law involving mergers and acquisitions, law firms in Europe are undergoing combinations of their own. The changes are also affecting law firms in the United States, as links are forged across the Atlantic. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Group Invests in Supercomputer  The National Science Foundation said it had made a $45 million award to the Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center to buy from Compaq what the computer maker says will be the world's fastest nonmilitary supercomputer when it is completely installed next year. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Retail Sales Gained 3.7% in July  Sales in stores open more than a year, a crucial figure for measuring the health of the retail industry, rose 3.7 percent in July. [C18.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
