<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yugoslavs Hold 4 Westerners in Arms Case</title>
    <meta content="04YUGO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/04/world/04yugo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220032"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Netherlands</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Montenegro</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DA143CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yugoslavs Hold 4 Westerners in Arms Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <dateline>PRAGUE, Aug. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Yugoslav Army says it has arrested two Britons and two Canadians in Montenegro, accusing them of possessing weapons and explosives, in what appears to be another effort to stimulate fears of NATO encirclement before elections next month; arrest comes on heels of detention of four Dutch citizens earlier in week and days of Serbian and Yugoslav Army statements about need to preserve unity of Yugoslavia, which is made up of Serbia and Montenegro (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yugoslav Army said today that it had arrested two Britons and two Canadians in Montenegro, accusing them of possessing weapons and explosives, in what appeared to be another effort to stimulate fears of Western encirclement before elections next month.</p>
        <p>It was the second arrest of four foreigners reported this week by Yugoslav authorities. Four Dutchmen whose detention was disclosed on Monday were seized last month on Serbia's border with Montenegro, reportedly because they were trying to kill President Slobodan Milosevic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yugoslav Army said today that it had arrested two Britons and two Canadians in Montenegro, accusing them of possessing weapons and explosives, in what appeared to be another effort to stimulate fears of Western encirclement before elections next month.</p>
        <p>It was the second arrest of four foreigners reported this week by Yugoslav authorities. Four Dutchmen whose detention was disclosed on Monday were seized last month on Serbia's border with Montenegro, reportedly because they were trying to kill President Slobodan Milosevic.</p>
        <p>The army said today that the Britons and Canadians were employees of the NATO-led forces in Kosovo and were suspected of training pro-Western secessionists in Montenegro, Serbia's tiny sister republic, to commit ''terrorist actions.''</p>
        <p>The charges were rejected by British and Canadian forces, who said the four were simply returning from a weekend vacation in Montenegro to nearby Kosovo, the Serbian province that NATO-led forces now control, and were not carrying arms or explosives.</p>
        <p>The arrest follows days of Serbian and Yugoslav Army statements about the need to preserve Yugoslavia, which is made up of Serbia and Montenegro. Belgrade has accused the West of training the Montenegrin police in preparation for Montenegro's secession, and the charges today appear to fit that pattern.</p>
        <p>President Milo Djukanovic of Montenegro has broken with Mr. Milosevic, talks of an independent Montenegro and is openly supported by the West. Mr. Milosevic controls the Yugoslav Army in Montenegro, while Mr. Djukanovic controls the police, which he has built up with Western help.</p>
        <p>Western diplomats fear that Mr. Milosevic is not merely creating a sense of threat to help his election campaign, but may also be laying the groundwork for military or police action in Montenegro to bring down Mr. Djukanovic.</p>
        <p>NATO provided Montenegro a security guarantee in its air war against Serbia last year. But that guarantee is no longer in place. NATO and Western officials regularly warn Mr. Milosevic not to move against Montenegro. But they do not specify what NATO might do about it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic has called federal, local and presidential elections for Sept. 24. Mr. Djukanovic has resisted calls by the Clinton administration to participate in them and, together with the Serbian opposition, try to defeat Mr. Milosevic. Mr. Djukanovic argues that to participate after recent constitutional changes forced through by Mr. Milosevic would only legitimize the elections, which Mr. Milosevic is widely expected to rig.</p>
        <p>Washington has also been unable to persuade Vuk Draskovic, leader of the Serbian Renewal Movement, the single largest opposition party in Serbia, to participate in the elections. But Mr. Draskovic appears to be willing to have his party run for local offices and at least support a unified opposition candidate for the presidency, if one can be agreed on.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic presents himself as the best defender of Serbs against outside enemies and paints his opposition as traitors in the pay of the Western countries that bombed Yugoslavia last year and took over Kosovo.</p>
        <p>Western diplomats regard the arrest of the four men near the Montenegro-Kosovo border sometime between Monday night and Tuesday morning as a ploy for domestic purposes. In a statement faxed to news agencies in Belgrade, the Yugoslav Army said, ''There are indications the foreign citizens arrested trained special units of the Interior Ministry in the Republic of Montenegro and are specialists in demolition and performing terrorist actions.''</p>
        <p>The two Britons -- Adrian Pragnell, 41, and John Yore, 31 -- work in Kosovo training police officers at the police academy, said their employer, the Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe, which is based in Vienna. A spokeswoman for the organization, Melissa Fleming, said in a telephone interview that the two men were unarmed, and that they had been taking a ''weekend excursion'' to Montenegro and were to return to England on Sept. 4, after a year in Kosovo. Ms. Fleming said descriptions of the men as experts on explosives were ''absolutely absurd.''</p>
        <p>The office of the Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe in Kosovo has warned its employees not to travel to Montenegro, but it is not clear that all employees received the warning, Ms. Fleming said. It is possible that the four arrested men do not have visas for Yugoslavia, she said, ''but probably that's the extent of their wrongdoing.'' The organization does not know where the men are being held, she added.</p>
        <p>The Canadians -- Shaun Going, 45, and his nephew Liam Hall, 19 -- had also gone to Montenegro from Kosovo for a weekend break, employees told Agence France-Presse in Pristina. Mr. Going owns Meridian Resources, a construction company with headquarters in Calgary, Alberta. For a year, he has been running its office in Pristina, where the company has 20 contracts, mostly with the NATO-led forces. Mr. Going was said to be friendly with the Britons and was traveling with them.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Yugoslav authorities played a videotape at a news conference that showed the Dutchmen arrested last month confessing to the charges of plotting to kidnap or assassinate Mr. Milosevic and the former Bosnian Serb leader, Radovan Karadzic.</p>
        <p>Other suspects have previously been arrested on charges of acting as mercenaries for NATO who were seeking to kidnap fugitive war-crimes suspects from Bosnia taking refuge in Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>Dutch demands for access to the men have not been granted yet.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
