<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Props Talk Back: Young Performers Mix Bush's Message With Their Own</title>
    <meta content="Y04DIA$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000805T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PHILADELPHIA DIARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuczynski, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdy, Matthew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E3DB143CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1293" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Props Talk Back: Young Performers Mix Bush's Message With Their Own</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alex Kuczynski and Matthew Purdy</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdy, Matthew; Kuczynski, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vignettes of happenings at Republican National Convention; photo (Philadelphia Diary) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Republican audiences this week have been prosperous and mostly white and the stage always a Gap ad of vivid ethnicity. But sometimes, the models have thoughts of their own.</p>
        <p>Monday night, a group of children sat at school desks on the convention-hall podium behind Laura Bush as she addressed the delegates. Yesterday, at a ''Tribute to Laura Bush'' luncheon, young performers from Philadelphia's Rainbow Company were Mrs. Bush's backdrop in a packed hotel ballroom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Republican audiences this week have been prosperous and mostly white and the stage always a Gap ad of vivid ethnicity. But sometimes, the models have thoughts of their own.</p>
        <p>Monday night, a group of children sat at school desks on the convention-hall podium behind Laura Bush as she addressed the delegates. Yesterday, at a ''Tribute to Laura Bush'' luncheon, young performers from Philadelphia's Rainbow Company were Mrs. Bush's backdrop in a packed hotel ballroom.</p>
        <p>The children were excited, but some members of the troupe, a musical theater group, seemed to feel more like props for the Republican's message of inclusion.</p>
        <p>''I don't understand how male presidents can understand about abortion and pregnancy,'' said Katie Gould, 15, before the company performed for the Bushes, who oppose abortion. ''Like they say they're not for welfare and they're not for abortion. They've never experienced it -- not that I have,'' Katie said.</p>
        <p>''It's a show,'' said Will Brock, 27, who plays keyboards for the group. ''But they've got to do some things to get some votes they don't usually get, some black and Hispanic votes.''</p>
        <p>Ricardo Martin, the director of the theater, said he liked the exposure and money from the event and being part of what he called history. ''I'm certainly not doing it because I believe in the Republican ideal.''</p>
        <p>Some on stage were more coy. Asked if she supported Mr. Bush, Lauren Brown, who just turned 18, smiled politely and said ''I know who I'm voting for, but it's a secret.''</p>
        <p>Rachel Brooks left the stage thrilled that Governor Bush had spoken to her, and she said ''I tend to favor Republicans.''</p>
        <p>As the performers ended their program with a rousing ''God Bless America,'' the Bushes moved to the middle of the group so they were surrounded by the children.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brock, the keyboard player, shrugged, ''It's a gig, man.''</p>
        <p>The Tale of Two Dans</p>
        <p>Pop political quiz: Which Dan is at the Republican National Convention, Quayle or Rostenkowski?</p>
        <p>Guess again. Rosty, the once-powerful Democratic House-leader-turned-convict in House Post Office check scandal-turned corporate consultant, is offering convention commentary for Fox's Chicago television station.</p>
        <p>Dan Quayle, the once-youthful vice president and surrogate son of President George Bush-turned national amusement-turned political orphan when a real Bush son emerged, is home in Arizona.</p>
        <p>Through his office in Phoenix, Mr. Quayle, who made a brief and ill-fated bid for the Republican presidential nomination, said he was making himself scarce to allow the light to shine on George W.</p>
        <p>Let's ask a veteran commentator. ''I hate to say this about him, because he was vice president,'' Mr. Rostenkowski said. ''Dan Quayle was never taken seriously.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rostenkowski once was, but at the convention, he said, people looked at him quizzically. ''I'm just doing a job here,'' he growled.</p>
        <p>For Republican Women Who Rock</p>
        <p>Representative Mary Bono's new women's organization -- in a play on the name of the women's group more typically affiliated with another political party -- is called Right Now. It made its national debut with a party Wednesday night at a nightclub called The Five Spot.</p>
        <p>The party was pretty tame: The club typically has a burlesque show with some nudity every Wednesday, but it canceled that show and hired a swing band in deference to the Republican women.</p>
        <p>Representative Bono said she and a couple of friends were sitting around having a beer last year when they came up with the idea for Right Now. ''We were just talking  about how there were young women in the Republican Party who don't really have a place to go. They needed someplace hipper than the Republican Women's Federation.''</p>
        <p>One of Ms. Bono's aides described that venerable group as ''the blue-hairs.''</p>
        <p>''Yeah, we're rock-and-roll Republicans,'' Ms. Bono said, sipping a vanilla martini. Then she made a whooping sound, like the exuberant exhalation of a teenager at a rock concert, holding a lighter aloft:</p>
        <p>Whooooo!</p>
        <p>Ms. Bono said that she decided to call the group Right Now because feminists like Gloria Steinem and Patricia Ireland, the president of the National Organization for Women, had defended Bill Clinton.</p>
        <p>For its part, NOW is extremely ticked off at the abuse of its name. Ms. Ireland said: ''I think they will be as successful in starting a grass-roots organization as they will in holding on to our name. I have sent a notice to our general counsel.''</p>
        <p>A Star Is Born (Again)</p>
        <p>It's something of a tradition at political conventions to trot out a promising -- or at least telegenic -- member of the younger generation and try him out before a national audience.</p>
        <p>Robert F. Kennedy's performance in 1964 in Atlantic City was a hallmark, and his nephew John F. Kennedy Jr. got rave reviews in 1988. This year's star turn went to George P. Bush -- grandson of a president, son of a governor and nephew of a presidential nominee. After being interviewed on seemingly every talk show, he was rolled out last night in prime-time to celebrate Uncle George. Surprising no one who had watched more than five minutes of this Benetton ad convention, he mixed English and Spanish and highlighted his Mexican-American heritage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, a 23-year-old pre-law student, displayed not a flicker of nervousness as he strolled across the stage to a wave of excited applause.</p>
        <p>The bestowing of the slot on the young Mr. Bush, one of three children of Jeb Bush, the governor of Florida, and his Mexican wife, Columba, suggested that the Bush family had some distinct ideas about the way it would like its political legacy to proceed.</p>
        <p>But on a more immediate level, the presence of the young Mr. Bush on the stage tonight served two very current needs of his uncle's campaign for president: his appeal to Hispanic voters and his effort, which has been recurrent this week, to present the Republican Party as more ethnically diverse than the delegates here might suggest.</p>
        <p>Soggy Scenes of Summer</p>
        <p>Don't take it as a sign from God that it rained every day of the Republican convention.</p>
        <p>But the weather in Philadelphia sure did contribute to sodden energy levels by the final day of the Republican convention yesterday. California delegates were popping gingko-biloba capsules to stay alert. Donors and delegates on their way into yet another PAC party began to complain of gout. On ''Good Morning America,'' Charles Gibson stood on the floor of the convention hall and pointed out a flashing sign to Diane Sawyer, who was in New York. It read: We need fresh laundry, Diane!</p>
        <p>Before last night's grand finale, Joey Stanton, a Kentucky delegate, was dragging himself to the final happy hour sponsored by the House whip Tom DeLay's political action committee, aboard a V.I.P. train car parked outside the convention hall.</p>
        <p>''My back hurts,'' he complained, ''My toenails hurt. My bellybutton hurts.''</p>
        <p>Bill Borden of Texas said that friends had e-mailed him saying he had looked asleep on C-Span.</p>
        <p>''I e-mailed them back saying, 'well, you dopes, I should have looked asleep because I was asleep,' '' he said. ''I am dying for sleep.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps it takes a grizzled professional to negotiate the grueling party schedule.</p>
        <p>Steve Forbes, the former presidential candidate, looked spry and expertly made-up on his way into the PAC party caboose. ''Having been on the campaign trail, this is duck soup,'' Mr. Forbes said.</p>
        <p>PHILADELPHIA DIARY  Correction:  August 5, 2000, Saturday  A report in the Philadelphia Diary column about a speech by Jeb Bush's son, George P. Bush, misstated his age. It is 24, not 23.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 5, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>A report in the Philadelphia Diary column about a speech by Jeb Bush's son, George P. Bush, misstated his age. It is 24, not 23.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
