<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Monsanto Plans to Offer Rights To Its Altered-Rice Technology</title>
    <meta content="04MONT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220036"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vitamins</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Monsanto Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marquis, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Vitamins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vitamins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5DA143CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Monsanto Plans to Offer Rights To Its Altered-Rice Technology</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER MARQUIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marquis, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Monsanto Corp says it will make available patent rights to genetically altered rice that could help stave off malnutrition in poor nations; so-called 'golden rice' is rich in beta carotene, a source of Vitamin A (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a bid to foster support for biotechnology and save lives, the Monsanto Corporation will make available patent rights to genetically altered rice that could help stave off malnutrition in poor nations, the company's president said tonight.</p>
        <p>Hendrik A. Verfaillie, the president and chief executive of the St. Louis-based company, said Monsanto will forgo licensing fees for using its technology to make ''golden rice,'' a modified strain that is rich in beta carotene, a source of Vitamin A.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a bid to foster support for biotechnology and save lives, the Monsanto Corporation will make available patent rights to genetically altered rice that could help stave off malnutrition in poor nations, the company's president said tonight.</p>
        <p>Hendrik A. Verfaillie, the president and chief executive of the St. Louis-based company, said Monsanto will forgo licensing fees for using its technology to make ''golden rice,'' a modified strain that is rich in beta carotene, a source of Vitamin A.</p>
        <p>''The purpose of golden rice is to bring Vitamin A where people suffer,'' Mr. Verfaillie said in a telephone interview. The development of the rice, he added, ''clearly demonstrates that biotechnology can help not only countries in the West, but in the developing world as well.''</p>
        <p>Worldwide, about two hundred million children suffer from Vitamin A deficiencies, and about a million children succumb to diseases partly caused by a lack of adequate defenses. Hundreds of thousands more go blind each year, experts say.</p>
        <p>Monsanto's unusual offer, which was first reported in Friday's issue of The Washington Post, will cost the corporation financially, Mr. Verfaillie said.</p>
        <p>But it appeared aimed in part at countering a tide of negative publicity over the proliferation of genetically altered crops. Skepticism toward such products is especially acute in Western Europe, whose market is coveted by American producers.</p>
        <p>The company's offer was applauded by the developer of golden rice, Ingo Potrykus, a Swiss professor. In remarks to reporters, Mr. Potrykus said he would seek to persuade other companies to follow Monsanto's lead and provide life-saving biotechnology to poor nations free of charge.</p>
        <p>Beta carotene is the same substance that give carrots their color. The body converts it into Vitamin A, which becomes an essential nutrient that boosts the immune system and wards off disease.</p>
        <p>Monsanto, a large agricultural biotechnology company that is a unit of the Pharmacia Corporation, announced in April that it had decoded the genes of rice, described at the time as the most complex plant decoded to date. Company spokesmen said they hoped the findings would lead to rice with greater yields.</p>
        <p>The company and its competitors have come under criticism from environmentalists and some science groups for their work on genetically modified crops, which the critics say could damage the environment and prove dangerous for consumption. The announcement today could help blunt some of the criticism if the move lives up to its promise of saving the lives of otherwise malnourished children around the world.</p>
        <p>Some groups that have been critical of biotechnology companies have questioned whether the widespread distribution of golden rice is a good idea.</p>
        <p>In a recent statement quoted in The Post, the Rural Advancement Foundation said that ''critics are concerned that the advent of golden rice's 'quick fix' for Vitamin A deficiency could kneecap other low-tech and more cost-effective initiatives --  among them, to reintroduce the many vital-rich food plants that were once cheap and available.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
