<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'The First Decade'</title>
    <meta content="RV005010" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220040"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Ken</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E3DA143CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="509" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'The First Decade'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Ken</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ken Johnson reviews exhibition of 20th-century American art at Michael Rosenfeld Gallery; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michael Rosenfeld Gallery</p>
        <p>24 West 57th Street</p>
        <p>Through Thursday</p>
        <p>Organized to celebrate the Michael Rosenfeld Gallery's 10th anniversary, this densely populated show offers a fine hodgepodge of 20th-century American art. No particular criteria for inclusion are discernible: it looks as if the gallery simply took anything of interest out of storage and put it on view, letting the profusion of almost 60 works spill over into its offices.</p>
        <p>The show boasts only a few first-rank names. There is a small but wild and rather goofy ''Dancing Head'' from the 1940's by Jackson Pollock and an unintentionally hokey, surrealistic mural design by Willem de Kooning, a nautical vision of the artist himself shirtless and in cut-off pants on a wharf with netting, rope, an oar and a sea gull that hovers like a divine portent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Michael Rosenfeld Gallery</p>
        <p>24 West 57th Street</p>
        <p>Through Thursday</p>
        <p>Organized to celebrate the Michael Rosenfeld Gallery's 10th anniversary, this densely populated show offers a fine hodgepodge of 20th-century American art. No particular criteria for inclusion are discernible: it looks as if the gallery simply took anything of interest out of storage and put it on view, letting the profusion of almost 60 works spill over into its offices.</p>
        <p>The show boasts only a few first-rank names. There is a small but wild and rather goofy ''Dancing Head'' from the 1940's by Jackson Pollock and an unintentionally hokey, surrealistic mural design by Willem de Kooning, a nautical vision of the artist himself shirtless and in cut-off pants on a wharf with netting, rope, an oar and a sea gull that hovers like a divine portent.</p>
        <p>That most of the other works are by more marginal figures is a plus, however: this is not just another gathering of the usual, overexposed suspects. Among the more compelling works are, for example, a misty Magic Realist painting of an urn entangled by Christmas tree lights, painted in 1945 by the underappreciated Walter Murch; a diminutive vision of draped figures and a bizarre dog in a dreamy room by Dorothea Tanning that is all Surrealist cliches yet painted with an unusual sensitivity; and a semiabstract picture of swooping bulbous forms drawn and painted with rich physicality by the West Coast beatnik Jay DeFeo.</p>
        <p>The show ranges freely across the spectrum of styles, from the old-time academic realism of a boy in a sideways hat tenderly modeled by Augusta Savage to the boogie-woogie Mondrianism of a grid painting by Charmion von Weigand. And such a broad and motley selection makes a good mirror for modern art, after all, reflecting as it does an invigorating diversity that Modernist theoreticians from Roger Fry to Clement Greenberg wanted to edit away.</p>
        <p>Other highlights include one of the best Fairfield Porters you are ever likely to encounter, a small, radiant painting of a bouquet of buttercups; John Flannagan's fat, coiled snake, carved with rough, primitivistic craft from black sandstone; a zaftig, gilded dancer with dainty feet modeled in relief by Gaston Lachaise; a vibrantly colored, esoteric grid painting by the eccentric polymath Alfred Jensen; and one of Charles Seliger's spacey, fanatically detailed abstractions. There are dull spots, to be sure, but not enough to spoil the show.</p>
        <p>KEN JOHNSON</p>
        <p>ART IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
