<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After a Long Process, Bush Gets to the Point With Words That Fit His Style</title>
    <meta content="Y04BUS$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220039"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gerson, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E3DA143CF937A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1427" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After a Long Process, Bush Gets to the Point With Words That Fit His Style</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Aug. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush's acceptance speech at Republican National Convention went through 17 drafts and condensation to less than 4,000 words; speech is in many ways a glimpse into way Bush thinks and feels; chief speechwriter, Michael Gerson, and other aides say Bush tended to elect simple, clear statements with which he felt comfortable and only campaign insiders helped write speech or listen to practice readings; convention photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If it had been up to his speechwriter, Gov. George W. Bush would have opened his remarks tonight by thanking the delegates here for ''the honor of this hour.''</p>
        <p>But that felt too lofty to the Texas governor, too fancy and formal. And so, as he scribbled in margins, sounded out sentences and ushered the most important address of his political career through 17 drafts, Mr. Bush deleted the last three words of that phrase, ending the sentence with ''honor.'' It was closer to the way he normally spoke, and closer to the way he felt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If it had been up to his speechwriter, Gov. George W. Bush would have opened his remarks tonight by thanking the delegates here for ''the honor of this hour.''</p>
        <p>But that felt too lofty to the Texas governor, too fancy and formal. And so, as he scribbled in margins, sounded out sentences and ushered the most important address of his political career through 17 drafts, Mr. Bush deleted the last three words of that phrase, ending the sentence with ''honor.'' It was closer to the way he normally spoke, and closer to the way he felt.</p>
        <p>He used the last few weeks before his big moment to nip, tuck and condense the speech from about 4,300 words to about 3,900, even though the former length was well within the range of convention tradition. Mr. Bush believed that shorter was better, and truer to who he was. He also exhibited a bit of prescience, because his methodical delivery and the frequent applause extended his appearance on stage beyond what he and his aides had originally estimated.</p>
        <p>Beyond the generally worded proposals and beneath the emphatically stated priorities, Mr. Bush's speech tonight was in many ways a glimpse into the way he thinks and feels. According to the campaign's chief speechwriter, Michael Gerson, and other aides who worked with Mr. Bush on the remarks, he tended to elect simple statements over ornate locutions, the epigrammatic over the elongated, words he felt comfortable saying over words that challenged him, clarity over ambiguity.</p>
        <p>''He wanted images, he wanted things shorter, he wanted things more concrete,'' said Mr. Gerson, who has been writing Mr. Bush's biggest speeches for nearly a year and a half. The campaign did not, as is sometimes the case, recruit outside help for this address. Like most endeavors in Mr. Bush's political world, this process was kept close to home, among the tried and trusted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush did not practice the speech in front of focus groups or strangers, advisers said, although he did practice it often over the last two weeks.</p>
        <p>He read it aloud in front of senior campaign officials, taking pointers from Karen P. Hughes, his communications director, and Mark McKinnon and Stuart Stevens, who make the commercials for the campaign. He toted a teleprompter into the living room of a private house in Cincinnati and then into the dining room of the Pennsylvania governor's mansion in Harrisburg, subjecting friends in both places to his trial runs.</p>
        <p>Tonight's speech may well be a hallmark of Mr. Bush's maturation as a candidate, in that it reflects a degree of diligence and level of preparation not always evident on the campaign trail over the last year.</p>
        <p>He looked at the first draft two months ago, and ordered changes and more changes until the end. He pestered aides well outside of office hours with his latest thoughts. As Mr. Gerson spoke with a New York Times reporter over breakfast early last week, his cell phone rang, and it was the boss.</p>
        <p>''Thirteen is just spelling errors and punctuation,'' Mr. Gerson told Mr. Bush, explaining what had been corrected and amended since the 12th draft. ''We'll make sure that we get 14 ready for the teleprompter.''</p>
        <p>After hanging up, Mr. Gerson said Mr. Bush, who had called from his Texas ranch, wanted the reporter to know that ''he's been thinking so hard, the deer have started talking to him.''</p>
        <p>They apparently were urging concision, simplicity, ''making our eloquence more direct,'' as Mr. Gerson said. What Mr. Bush and his campaign strategists wanted was something that balanced the formality of the occasion with the informality of his personal style, and the difficulty of that task was made apparent in Mr. Bush's delivery tonight, which was not as natural as he undoubtedly wanted it to be, and which tested the limits of his abilities as an orator.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Bush was very much a part of the production.</p>
        <p>He pruned an array of phrases near the top. At the end of a sentence that began ''together, we will,'' Mr. Gerson attached a lengthy litany of goals. Mr. Bush distilled them into a single phrase ''renew America's purpose'' that echoed existing slogans from his campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gerson offered several paragraphs of examples of the sacrifices of the World War II generation, which Mr. Bush had wanted to honor. Mr. Bush was not content until the tribute had been boiled down to a few sentences and a central sentiment: that these brave men had ''stormed beaches, liberated concentration camps and delivered us from evil.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gerson, trying to make the case that good times are as crucial as bad, wrote that ''a time of crisis is a test of strength, a time of prosperity is a test of vision.'' But that was neither active nor specific enough for Mr. Bush, who kept pressing and pressing until Mr. Gerson came up with this: ''Prosperity can be a tool in our hands, used to build and better our country, or it can be a drug in our system, dulling our sense of urgency, of empathy, of duty.''</p>
        <p>Although the theme that the baby boom generation had squandered some of its opportunities and surrendered to irresponsible impulses was present from the first draft, Mr. Bush wanted that notion turned into a motif, with recurring allusions to a privileged generation's unrealized obligation to give something back.</p>
        <p>Inasmuch as Mr. Bush can be said to have intellectual obsessions, this had always been one, but there was another reason to hammer home this argument. It represented an implicit indictment of President Clinton, and an implicit pitch to start anew in the White House.</p>
        <p>Although tonight's speech was much more than a culling and cobbling together of Mr. Bush's stump speeches to date, the candidate did revert to familiar phrases.</p>
        <p>An early draft by Mr. Gerson included the sentiment that ''congregations are responsible not only to worship, but to serve.'' Mr. Bush was not accustomed to using that first word, and one of the first times he read a version of the speech aloud he spontaneously changed it to ''synagogues, churches and mosques,'' words he had used in dozens of previous remarks. Aides duly inserted the change.</p>
        <p>''He needs to be able to say the words in a comfortable way,'' said Ms. Hughes, who provided extensive help with the editing. Ms. Hughes, who has worked with Mr. Bush since 1994, knew his voice as well as he did, and often came to Mr. Gerson to single out the same passage the governor had as something that did not sound like him.</p>
        <p>But as involved as the governor was, he did not let the gravity of the task eclipse the levity to which he is perpetually inclined.</p>
        <p>When he walked onto the convention stage on Wednesday to check out where he would be standing for his big moment, he made a widely grinning, grandly gesticulating show of pointing to ushers, waving to supporters and calling out familiar names, even as his straight-faced entourage busily went about checking the lighting and sound.</p>
        <p>Early this afternoon, when reporters asked about Mr. Bush's latest thoughts on the speech, he said he had given a more important speech ''when I asked my wife to marry me.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. Gerson, who is short, bookish, given to conversing in finely rendered sentences and self-effacing to a fault, has a seriousness that makes him a ripe target for Mr. Bush's kidding.</p>
        <p>One of the governor's advisers said that Mr. Bush, in reviewing those drafts of Mr. Gerson's speeches over time, would try to guess what Mr. Gerson's favorite line was, instantly point it out and say that it had to go. Only after Mr. Gerson's face had lost all color would the governor let him know that it was all a joke.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gerson, 36, is a philosophical man who studied theology in college, calls himself a born-again Christian and is conversant in the work of a wide array of political philosophers and poets.</p>
        <p>Although fundamentally conservative, Mr. Gerson was an early convert to compassionate conservatism.</p>
        <p>In the Bush campaign, he plays an unusual dual role, sitting in on not just the communications staff's meetings but also on the policy staff's as well.</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
