<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Intimate View of the Death House; Exhibition on Sing Sing Tells of Last Meals and Final Moments</title>
    <meta content="21DEAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209055"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Time and Space Limited (Hudson, NY)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sing Sing Correctional Facility (Ossining, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Dinitia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFDA1331F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Intimate View of the Death House; Exhibition on Sing Sing Tells of Last Meals and Final Moments</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DINITIA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Dinitia</byline>
      <dateline>HUDSON, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Exhibition at Time and Space Limited, Hudson, NY, arts center, offers unusually intimate and powerful view of Sing Sing's death row; includes mug shots of 130 of 614 people executed at prison, 1891-1963; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Our children are the apple of our eye, our pride and most precious fortune, love them with all your heart and always protect them,'' Julius Rosenberg, convicted of espionage and condemned to death, wrote in a letter to one of his lawyers from Sing Sing on June 19, 1953, just hours before his execution. The handwriting is shaky with frantic crossings out.</p>
        <p>He also paid tribute to his wife, Ethel, who was to be executed along with him. ''Words fail me when I attempt to tell of the nobility and grandeur of my life's companion, my sweet and devoted wife. Ours is a great love and wonderful relationship, it has made my life full and rich.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Our children are the apple of our eye, our pride and most precious fortune, love them with all your heart and always protect them,'' Julius Rosenberg, convicted of espionage and condemned to death, wrote in a letter to one of his lawyers from Sing Sing on June 19, 1953, just hours before his execution. The handwriting is shaky with frantic crossings out.</p>
        <p>He also paid tribute to his wife, Ethel, who was to be executed along with him. ''Words fail me when I attempt to tell of the nobility and grandeur of my life's companion, my sweet and devoted wife. Ours is a great love and wonderful relationship, it has made my life full and rich.''</p>
        <p>A photograph of Rosenberg's letter is on view in ''Condemned,'' an unusually intimate and powerful exhibition about Sing Sing's death row that recently opened at Time and Space Limited, an arts center in Hudson, in Columbia County about 75 miles north of the prison site at Ossining.</p>
        <p>There is an inventory of Ethel's possessions at the time of her death: dainty, feminine things; deodorant; stockings; a shoebox of letters from her children. And there is her last letter to the children: ''Dearest Sweethearts, my most precious children,'' she writes. ''We press you close and kiss you with all our strength, lovingly Daddy and Mommy.''</p>
        <p>Lining the stark white walls of the exhibition at Time and Space are mug shots of some 130 people who were executed at Sing Sing Correctional Facility, photocopies of their final letters to loved ones, autopsy reports, the menu for a last meal, and other memorabilia. Between1891 and 1963, the year of the last legal execution in New York State, more people -- 614 -- were executed at Sing Sing than at any other prison. For years hence there were no executions because of legal challenges and the opposition of two governors, Hugh L. Carey and Mario M. Cuomo. In 1995, Gov. George E. Pataki signed legislation reinstating capital punishment, but no one has yet been executed under that law.</p>
        <p>Sing Sing has long held an almost mythological place in American culture. Many books have been written about the prison and many movies have been set there, including  ''20,000 Years in Sing Sing'' and ''Each Dawn I Die.''</p>
        <p>Among the notorious people who met death there were Louis (Lepke) Buchalter, the boss of the Brooklyn gang Murder Inc., which was believed to be responsible for more than 20 murders. He was convicted of ordering the shooting of a garment trucker.</p>
        <p>Also executed there were Martha Beck and Raymond Fernandez, the so-called Lonely Hearts Killers. Fernandez met Beck, a nurse, through a pen pal club for the lovelorn, the exhibition notes. During the 1940's and 50's, the pair made headlines for swindling lonely women, and they were eventually condemned for murdering a woman with a hammer.  Beck told prison officials when she arrived at Sing Sing that crime was ''something I got into. I had no control.''</p>
        <p>Many of the crimes are particularly gruesome. Arthur Johnson, 21, was convicted of strangling and raping a 15-year-old girl. Edward Haight was convicted of murdering two girls, 6 and 8. It is recounted under his mug shot that he told prison officials, ''I don't know why I did it.'' Frederick Wood, a salesman, was accused of killing one man with a bottle, another with a shovel. A prison official noted, the exhibition label relates, that Wood said ''he hates homosexuals.''</p>
        <p>During sentencing procedures, the relatives of crime victims are often given an opportunity to describe their loss to the court in emotionally gripping ways. But this exhibition focuses on the private emotions of some who were sent to the chair at Sing Sing decades ago.</p>
        <p>The exhibition was organized by Scott Christianson, former deputy director of parole operations for New York State, who resigned from his job in 1995 in opposition to reinstitution of the death penalty. He is now director of the New York Death Penalty Documentation Project, an effort to gather the official record regarding the state's administration of capital punishment. In assembling the show, Mr. Christian drew on research for his book ''Condemned,'' published in March by New York University Press.</p>
        <p>The records on which the exhibition is based were stored at Sing Sing and inaccessible to outsiders until 1977, when they went to the New York State Archives in Albany. After being catalogued, they were made available to Mr. Christianson in 1997 under the state's Freedom of Information law. Now that the death penalty is legal again in New York,  Mr. Christianson said, ''I thought it was even more important for people to have an opportunity to view this reality they've ignored or not gotten access to.''</p>
        <p>Many letters in the exhibition are intimate, almost naked in their emotion. ''There is no definition in the law as to what constitutes an unwarranted invasion of privacy,'' said  James D. Folts, supervisor of reference services for the New York State Archives, in explaining why the records were released to Mr. Christianson.</p>
        <p>The exhibition includes details about executions written by prison officials in a matter-of-fact style.</p>
        <p>After the Rosenbergs went to the electric chair, the executioner penciled in the time and the duration of the event on an index card, a photograph of which is also in the exhibit: ''Julius Rosenberg, SSP #110-649. Time in: 8:04, Time Out: 8:06 3/4. Amps 8.'' And a record of Ethel's death: '' Time In: 8:11 1/2, Time Out 8:16.'' Ethel required 6 1/2 amps. But tt took several doses of electricity to kill her.</p>
        <p>The exhibition continues through July 16.</p>
        <p>The records cover roughly 20 percent of the executions at Sing Sing. ''I would hope the state could provide detailed records that could be a basis for a challenge in the Supreme Court, if it is shown that the death penalty was administered in an arbitrary or capricious or racist way,'' Mr. Christianson said.</p>
        <p>He said he hoped that the documents could be used to challenge the death penalty in court by substantiating the argument that a disproportionate number of blacks are executed.</p>
        <p>Sing Sing prison was built in 1825. The name comes from a Native American tribe known as ''Sint Sinck,'' or ''stone upon stone,'' referring to the rocky terrain. An engraving from Harper's magazine from the 1870's shows an idealized view of the prison as a self-contained universe, with a hospital and sanitation facilities, a nursery and a women's prison. There is a photograph of the ornate warden's office with its wood paneling and coffered ceiling.</p>
        <p>Another photograph shows a ''torture chair,'' as some convicts referred to it, with a blindfolded and shackled prisoner. Sitting upon it, the inmate was doused with water. Some drowned or died from exposure, Mr. Christianson said. By the 1830's whippings were so common at the prison that Sing Sing became known as a ''catocracy,'' after the cat o' nine tails.</p>
        <p>The first electric chair was built around 1889 and was designed in the laboratory of Thomas Edison. Edison, an advocate of direct current, was competing with George Westinghouse, who favored alternating current. Edison suggested using Westinghouse's alternating current for the electric chair to dramatize how dangerous his rival's method could be for everyday use.</p>
        <p>The first execution by electric chair at Sing Sing took place in 1891.  From 1920 to 1941, the prison's warden was Lewis E. Lawes, who was an opponent of capital punishment. But he presided over 303 executions. The exhibition the well-known photograph of the execution of Ruth Snyder in 1928, taken by a Daily News reporter with a hidden camera, in which her body seems to shake with a tremendous force.</p>
        <p>Death was not always instantaneous, Mr. Christianson pointed out, and it sometimes required repeated administrations of electricity. Sometimes the condemned person caught fire. There was debate about whether death was caused by the electricity or by the autopsy that quickly followed.</p>
        <p>One autopsy report from 1951 in the exhibition notes: ''The cerebellum seen from the posterior surfaces is opaque and grayish in color. It has a boiled appearance. The whole brain is uncomfortably warm to the touch.''</p>
        <p>''It is my contention that one of the reasons legal autopsies were made a requirement was not only an attempt to determine the nature of death, but also to insure death,'' Mr. Christianson said.</p>
        <p>After a series of escapes from death row, a new death house was built in 1920. It was called by The New York Times ''the most impregnable penal institution in the world,'' and it began executions in 1922. The death house had cells, an execution chamber, a hospital, and an office for the ''Lunacy Commission,'' where prisoners were examined to see if they were sane when they committed their crime. Radiating out from the execution chamber were six staging areas, known as ''the Dance Hall.'' Adjoining the chamber was a room where the executioner was concealed.</p>
        <p>The mug shots at Time and Space were taken when the condemned arrived at the prison. Many prisoners wear the suits and ties they had on for their sentencing in court. There is a mix of expressions on the faces:  panic, defiance, bewilderment. Most are young, some only 17, like Norman Roye, a smooth-faced black youth with a sorrowful look. Under the photo is his date of birth and the crime of which he was convicted, strangling an old woman. He claimed innocence and was executed on Jan. 9, 1956.</p>
        <p>There are letters from prisoners begging for mercy. Helen Fowler, 37 and a mother of five, convicted of murder, wrote a rambling letter to Lieutenant-Governor Hanley: ''I have a little boy, 10; one, 5; a girl of 14; one, 18; one, 20; a grandchild.''  She could not hear the testimony at her trial, she said, because she was partly deaf. According to the prosecutor, someone else actually killed the victim. Fowler was convicted because she helped dispose of the body. She was executed in November 1944.</p>
        <p>In one case a man was executed despite the last-minute plea of his co-defendant that he was innocent. Two Chinese men, Lew York Hing and Yun Tieh Li, were accused of killing a woman during a robbery. But in a letter to Chief Justice Lehman, Yun Tieh Li wrote that Lew York Hing ''had nothing to do with this murder.  The one who Do the killing in this case is 'me and Eddie,' '' a reference to an unknown third person. Still, both Yun Tieh Li and Lew York Hing were executed in August 1944.</p>
        <p>Some prisoners were mentally disabled or illiterate. A psychiatrist described Oliver Little, 19, a laborer, convicted of stabbing a man to death, as ''mentally defective, borderline level.'' Yet the execution was legal.</p>
        <p>As the hour of death approached, the prisoners were entitled to choose their final meal.Prisoner No. 123-881, Henry Flakes, asked for barbecued chicken and strawberry shortcake with whipped cream. Many prisoners sat down to write a last letter. For some it appeared to be a psychological imperative, a spiritual ritual that had a cleansing effect.  Frank Newman, convicted of murdering his wife, had claimed temporary insanity and acute alcoholism.  ''I do not believe I could describe how much I despise myself for this terrible thing,'' he wrote to his sons in August 1956, the day before he died. ''I loved Mother. I pray to God to forgive me and that my boys will try to soften the terrible hatred you have for me.''</p>
        <p>In another letter, from Jan. 14, 1960, Ivory Mason, convicted of shooting a woman, wrote to his mother: ''Just a few lines to let you hear from me as this will be my last letter to you.'' When Mason arrived at Sing Sing, he was illiterate but later learned to read and write. ''I must tarry on to my maker from which I come. But don't worry mother. I have made my peace with God.''</p>
        <p>''And mother since you did not come to see me,'' he continued, ''I forgive you. I understand.''</p>
        <p>Mason ended with a plea for forgiveness: ''Sorry if I cause you any heart ache and pains if so please forgive me. So I will close and until we meet beyond the river it is well remembered I were your Son.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
