<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE OTHER ECONOMY: A Plan, a Canal Town; A Canal Town's Existential Crisis</title>
    <meta content="21CLYD$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Clyde (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Erie Canal (NYS)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eaton, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E5D91031F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2246" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE OTHER ECONOMY: A Plan, a Canal Town; A Canal Town's Existential Crisis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE EATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eaton, Leslie</byline>
      <dateline>CLYDE, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses status of plans for economic revival of Clyde, NY; town, located in central New York State, is counting on traffic from nearby Erie Canal to play large part in rebirth; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sitting in Pete's Diner, talking about his beloved hometown, Kenneth DiSanto makes the plan sounds plausible, even probable. Of course this forlorn little village will transform itself from plain old Clyde, smack in the middle of nowhere, to Clyde-on-the-Erie, historic site and tourist magnet.</p>
        <p>Step outside onto Glasgow Street, however, and the obstacles to that plan become plain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sitting in Pete's Diner, talking about his beloved hometown, Kenneth DiSanto makes the plan sounds plausible, even probable. Of course this forlorn little village will transform itself from plain old Clyde, smack in the middle of nowhere, to Clyde-on-the-Erie, historic site and tourist magnet.</p>
        <p>Step outside onto Glasgow Street, however, and the obstacles to that plan become plain.</p>
        <p>Just for starters, you cannot actually get to the Erie Canal from three-block-long downtown Clyde. Railroad tracks run between the water and the village; freight cars rumble through every 20 minutes or so. Nor can you get from the canal into Clyde; the only dock, on the far side of a big, ugly bridge, cannot accommodate anything much bigger than a rowboat.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Clyde, halfway between Rochester and Syracuse, is pinning its hopes for the future on the canal that first gave it life back in the 1820's.</p>
        <p>So are dozens of other communities in upstate New York. They are being egged on by the federal government, which since 1996 has been pushing a ''canal corridor initiative'' to redevelop the historic canal for tourism and recreation -- and has given out almost $240 million in grants and loans to help pay for the efforts.</p>
        <p>''Nobody wants to live in a chapter in a history book,'' said Andrew Cuomo, the secretary of housing and urban development (and a possible future candidate for governor of New York). But, he said, remaking and marketing the canal will promote ''tourism, jobs, energy and optimism, and the quality of life of the locale.''</p>
        <p>Across New York State, there are hundreds of villages and towns of 1,000 or 2,000 or 3,000 souls, stranded in history as well as geography. Places that once had a reason for being -- a railroad stop, a turnpike gate, a waterfall to drive a mill -- are struggling to survive in the age of the Internet.</p>
        <p>In Clyde, ''our game plan has been to find a reason for existence,'' said Mr. DiSanto, who is, among other things, chairman of the village's Industrial Development Corporation.</p>
        <p>That makes Clyde similar to many upstate communities, said Susan Christopherson, a professor of urban planning at Cornell University who has studied the canal redevelopment program. So does its separation from the canal itself. ''In many cases, it ran adjacent to the downtown business district,'' she said. ''It wasn't directly connected to downtown.''</p>
        <p>Some communities along the canal are more prosperous than Clyde, and more urban; many in western Wayne County, for example, where Clyde is located, have become suburbs of Rochester. But ''Clyde is fairly typical of most rural downtowns'' in central New York, said Barbara Harper, director of the Wayne County Economic Development Authority.</p>
        <p>Which means that there is not a whole lot here: Pete's, of course, and the Trackside Deli, a Key Bank branch, antiques shops and a cute little flower shop. For shopping there's a hardware store, the Clyde Bargain Center and Messinger's Variety Store, an old-fashioned five-and-dime that sells housedresses and hairnets when its 91-year-old proprietor can make it to the cash register.</p>
        <p>Clyde has a leafy little town green, too, with a bandstand and fountain. You have to look closely to realize that the statue of George Washington has lost its nose, or that the fancy little roof on wooden supports labeled ''Clyde's Famous Mineral Spring'' covers only a pipe with a soda can smashed into it.</p>
        <p>It's hard to say exactly how many people still live in Clyde. Locals put the population at 2,400, but last year's Census Bureau estimate is about half that. In any event, Clyde is so small it has only one telephone exchange, and people tend to identify themselves by the year they graduated from Clyde-Savannah High.</p>
        <p>And for some of those people, the canal remains a real part of life, even today. Take Brian Howell, who worked on the last steam-powered vessel to ply the Erie. That was only 15 years ago -- and Mr. Howell, who works for the State Canal Corporation, is only 34 (class of 1984).</p>
        <p>At one time, the canal was all the reason Clyde needed for being. When the canal opened in 1825, it provided for the first time transportation through the spine of mountains that runs down the eastern United States -- and that today seems such an insignificant barrier. Wheat could come east, widgets could go west, and people could move both ways, on barges drawn by mules.</p>
        <p>Clyde was the first stop for westbound barges that had pushed for hours through the malaria-infested Montezuma Swamp. Not surprisingly, mule drivers got off to have a drink in one of Clyde's taverns.</p>
        <p>There were shoe shops and clothing shops, and, in time, a fancy hotel, a racetrack, two newspapers, two train stations, three graveyards, at least four churches and a home-grown marching band. The biggest house in town belonged to the owner of the glass factory, which turned out handmade Mason jars.</p>
        <p>The railroad brought Abraham Lincoln, who in 1861 spoke a few sentences to a crowd gathered in Clyde. In the 1880's, it brought the Italian workers whose names are now borne by almost everyone in town.</p>
        <p>Throughout the first half of the 20th century, Clyde continued to prosper. ''If I had to be transported back in time, it would be to the 1930's,'' said R. Hugh Miner, the town historian and publisher of the monthly Crossroads Advocate. In this agricultural area, even the Great Depression was not so bad, he said, ''and this was a very close-knit community.''</p>
        <p>Just ask George L. Storto, who says he is related to everyone in town (his father owned an ice cream parlor). A member of the Clyde-Savannah High class of 1948, Mr. Storto left Clyde in 1957 and ended up in Arizona, working for a big insurance company. And he married a woman from Tennessee.</p>
        <p>''She said, 'Someday you have to show me that little town you're from, because you talk about it and dream about it,' '' Mr. Storto said. In 1995, he and his wife came back to Clyde. ''And I know I'm staying here,'' he said, ''because my wife said we need to buy a couple of plots at the cemetery.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Storto is part of what may be Clyde's secret weapon: a group of well-traveled, well-to-do retirees who are determined to save the place they still love. They include Mr. Di Santo and Richard DeVito, who both retired from Xerox, and Rudolph A. DeLisio, who retired from General Electric (classes of '56, '51 and '41, respectively).</p>
        <p>They knew Clyde before the G.E. plant closed and eliminated 350 jobs in the early 1960's. Even though some other businesses have moved in -- Parker Hannifin, which makes industrial hydraulic equipment, and Thomas Electronics each employ well over 100 people -- Clyde seemed to lose something, they said.</p>
        <p>Property values fell, absentee landlords moved in, and so did a lot of people receiving welfare or disability payments. There is not much for poor or young people to do in Clyde, especially if they don't have cars.</p>
        <p>''They really do need to lighten this town up, put in a movie house or a skating rink,'' said Albert Austin, who lives on Glasgow Street and gets by on Social Security and the money he makes collecting cans and bottles for recycling.</p>
        <p>Next door, Tammy Simcerbeaux, an 18-year-old with two small children, agreed. What does she do for fun? ''Nothing, really,'' she said. ''It's boring.''</p>
        <p>Over the years, drugs became a problem. The Chamber of Commerce and other civic organizations dwindled; in 1989, the village even stopped holding its Christmas decoration competition, a staple of small-town life.</p>
        <p>But in 1996, things began to change. By a narrow margin, Clyde elected a new mayor, Steven J. Groat, a photographer, who shared many of the retirees' ideas and frustrations. Mr. DeLisio started to revive the Chamber of Commerce, in part by allowing anyone to join.</p>
        <p>The retirees formed a sort of Save Clyde Committee, and with Mr. Groat they persuaded a class of landscape architecture students at Cornell to draw up a plan to renovate downtown Clyde. And it began to seem possible that Clyde could serve as an antiques center, a place where people floating down the canal or visiting Montezuma (now a wildlife refuge popular with bird watchers) could browse and buy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Groat began applying for government grants and loans, and has brought more than $1 million into Clyde. Some of the money has gone to a new water system; some was to be spent on a new park and dock on the far side of the Erie, which have not yet been started because the bids came in too high.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the residents of Clyde did a little boot-strapping; 75 of them kicked in $1,000 each toward a limited partnership. The money has gone to buy what the retirees describe as the three worst buildings in town, all on Glasgow Street, and now they are trying to find the cash to renovate the buildings.</p>
        <p>Its buildings will help determine whether Clyde succeeds as a Cinderella -- and under all the layers of plastic and aluminum ''improvements,'' they are beautiful. (And cheap.)</p>
        <p>Fantastically ornate tin covers 14-foot ceilings in an old drugstore that Kevin Sipple is turning into an elegant antiques shop (''no junk,'' he said firmly). A 50-year-old retired police officer from outside Rochester, Mr. Sipple is pulling up the tile floor of his 1853 building to expose the tongue-and-groove maple. Upstairs, he has installed a new kitchen and bathroom in a one-bedroom apartment he hopes to rent out.</p>
        <p>Down the block, in a building Mr. DiSanto owns, is a similar tin ceiling, as well as an elaborately paneled and mirrored wall dating to the days when the place was Wood's barbershop. For the past year, Darrell Marriott, a 35-year-old former quarterback at Clyde-Savannah High, has been running the Olde Erie Hair Shoppe there, giving $8 haircuts.</p>
        <p>Mr. DiSanto owns another building, the old Stoetzel's bakery, and has restored the huge brick oven in the back room, hoping to turn the place into a restaurant. The upper two floors (which would make even Brooklyn brownstone dwellers envious) may someday become a bed and breakfast. Right now, Clyde lacks even a motel.</p>
        <p>Another construction project may soon begin a few blocks away, where the town historical society plans to turn the old Baptist church facing the park into a new museum and meeting hall. (The old museum, a former feed mill by the railroad tracks, is open only two afternoons a week in July and August, and in any event looks like someone's attic).</p>
        <p>These developments may seem minor, but they have not been embraced by everyone. Mr. Groat, 48,  gave up the mayor's office to run for county legislator but lost; his efforts to enforce zoning and building codes made him unpopular in some quarters. And he admits that he and the retirees may have tried to change too much, too soon. ''Trying to do something here is difficult,'' he said. ''I don't want to say that I shoved it down their throats, but I did.''</p>
        <p>Thomas Caprilla, the new mayor -- who was also mayor before Mr. Groat -- said residents were not opposed to the redevelopment plan, but worried that it might increase their taxes, or change the nature of the village. ''As much as people want to see the canal improved,'' he said, ''they're afraid of a flock of tourists coming to Clyde.''</p>
        <p>That does not seem to be a looming problem. More pleasure boats are using the lock near Clyde -- traffic rose by 8 percent between 1997 and 1999 -- but fewer than 1,100 cruised through last year. And while Mr. DiSanto's Industrial Development Corporation has lured several small businesses -- and about 30 jobs -- to Clyde in the last four years, they are in manufacturing, not tourism.</p>
        <p>But those job gains may not be unrelated to Clyde's improvements. Professor Christopherson is working on a new study for the federal government that suggests that improving amenities for tourists may also draw other kinds of businesses looking for good recreational opportunities for their employees.</p>
        <p>In Clyde, anyway, jobs sometime seem beside the point. What people keep coming back to is the search for a reason for being. As Mr. Miner, the historian, puts it, ''The whole idea of the Erie Canal for us is that we're hoping to regain some identity.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
