<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Moves to restrict cell phones reflect a growing reaction against a vocal minority of users.</title>
    <meta content="Y21TRAV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209082"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TRAVEL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharkey, Joe</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Business Travel (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E3D61331F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="999" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Moves to restrict cell phones reflect a growing reaction against a vocal minority of users.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joe Sharkey</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sharkey, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Moves to restrict cell phones on airplanes reflect growing reaction against vocal minority of users; while airlines and federal regulators still insist that in-flight cell phone use is safety hazard that can interfere with complex cockpit communications and navigation technology, some experts and cell phone industry officials have been publicly arguing that science supporting ban is questionable because cell phone use is routine on board private corporate aircraft; given general level of annoyance that many people show toward being subjected to someone else's cell phone conversation, airline industry might be willing to maintain status quo; airlines make money when passengers place expensive calls on existing on-board phones (Market Place column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THANKS to a lucky One-Pass upgrade, I was sitting in first class on a Continental Airlines flight to Florida one sunny morning last week waiting for takeoff. The flight attendant was passing out those steaming face towels and taking drink orders. What a swell flight so far, I thought. But then that dreaded telltale chirp sounded from the row behind me.</p>
        <p>Sure enough, a cell phone idiot began braying into the morning's serenity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THANKS to a lucky One-Pass upgrade, I was sitting in first class on a Continental Airlines flight to Florida one sunny morning last week waiting for takeoff. The flight attendant was passing out those steaming face towels and taking drink orders. What a swell flight so far, I thought. But then that dreaded telltale chirp sounded from the row behind me.</p>
        <p>Sure enough, a cell phone idiot began braying into the morning's serenity.</p>
        <p>''I'm on the plane,'' he declared in a voice as loud as a cattle auctioneer's. ''We're going to take off in a couple of minutes. Listen, did you put on the air-conditioner? What? What? Nah, you got to hit the reset button. What? Hit the reset! It's on the left! What? Listen.''</p>
        <p>It went on like this for several long minutes. Then he barked goodbye and snapped the phone lid shut. But before a sigh of relief had time to form, he made another call. In the seat beside me, a woman who looked like a very nice person muttered a single word, softly, but with feeling.</p>
        <p>''Die,'' she said.</p>
        <p>We've come a long way in the cell phone culture since last summer. Then, after years of resistance, several airlines decided to relax strict prohibitions against using cell phones. Motivated both by public demand and by a realization that passengers ducking away to make last-minute phone calls at the gate were delaying boarding and affecting on-time performance, most airlines began allowing passengers to use cell phones until the pilot started taxiing. The development was generally applauded by passengers.</p>
        <p>In the year since this change, however, there has been a remarkable shift in general attitude toward cell phone use in public, thanks to a minority of users who make the rest of us cringe whenever we see them cracking that cell phone. And while the airlines and federal regulators still insist that in-flight cell phone use is a safety hazard that can interfere with complex cockpit communications and navigation technology, some experts and cell phone industry officials have been publicly arguing that the science supporting the ban is questionable. After all, they say, cell phone use is routine on board private corporate aircraft.</p>
        <p>Assuming that the obvious market potential causes the safety problems to be adequately addressed, will we be arriving at a point where passengers gabbing incessantly into cell phones might be a steady part of the airline experience, just as they are on other public conveyances like trains and buses?</p>
        <p>Oddly enough, there doesn't seem to be any discernible rush to forge ahead into that particular segment of the brave new technological world. Many experts point to rapid technological innovations and say that live Internet and e-mail service will be available on some airplanes within a year. But no one is predicting a cell phone breakout in the clouds.</p>
        <p>''I don't think in the foreseeable future you'll be able to use them, because the testing has just not been done to prove that they are not harmful,'' said Kathryn Creedy, a spokeswoman for the Federal Aviation Administration.</p>
        <p>''So at this point, the syllogism still exists,'' Ms. Creedy said. ''We require that testing be done by the airlines or the industry in order to prove that it is not harmful. And since that testing has not been done, therefore they are banned.''</p>
        <p>Still, Ms. Creedy declined to speculate on whether, given the general level of annoyance that many people now show toward being subjected to someone else's cell phone conversation, the airline industry might now be willing to maintain the status quo. After all, airlines make money when passengers place expensive calls on existing on-board phones.</p>
        <p>But several academic authorities in telephone communications agree  that perhaps the public is now ready to weigh the cultural, rather than just the scientific, argument against encouraging cell phones in the skies -- especially on long, crowded flights where people are already tense and often uncomfortable.</p>
        <p>Growing moves across the country to restrict annoying cell phones on other forms of pubic transportation reflect a swelling reaction against a vocal minority of cell phone users, said Thomas I. White, a professor of business ethics at Loyola Marymount University in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>''The people who get on everyone's nerves, they're coming from a sense that no one else matters. They're totally self-absorbed, and they seem to think that the impact of their actions on other people are absolutely inconsequential,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''This plays itself out in two ways. One, it is seen as an eroding of civility or a disruption of civil discourse. This is what we are seeing in San Francisco where cell phones are being banned from many restaurants. And two, the self-absorption can also be seen as a safety issue, such as in Los Angeles, where there are moves to restrict cell phone use in cars.''</p>
        <p>Dr. White said he wouldn't be surprised to see the move to restrict public use of cell phones grow, especially if it became apparent that they might be allowed on airplane flights.</p>
        <p>Ms. Creedy acknowledged that passengers might well welcome the respite from cell phone annoyances provided by the ban, but stressed that safety was the F.A.A.'s only concern in the matter.</p>
        <p>Dr. White, meanwhile, said: ''I'm assuming the only way the airlines can get away with continuing to ban cell phones is because they say, that's going to mess up the radar or the communications. And the only reason people respect the ban is we're all scared to pull out our cell phones and make a call because it might make the plane go down.''</p>
        <p>Hey, whatever works.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS TRAVEL Business Travel appears each Wednesday. Joe Sharkey's e-mail address is jsharkey@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Business Travel appears each Wednesday. Joe Sharkey's e-mail address is jsharkey@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
