<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Flying The Coop, With Plenty Of Yolks</title>
    <meta content="21CHIC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Park, Nick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lord, Peter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Chicken Run (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Elvis Mitchell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DB1331F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Flying The Coop, With Plenty Of Yolks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell reviews animated film Chicken Run, directed by Nick Park and Peter Lord; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Chicken Run,'' the first full-length feature from Aardman Animation, makes brainy use of Mel Gibson. It parodies Mr. Gibson's inane heroics in giving him a loud loose-cannon entrance.</p>
        <p>He's the voice of Rocky the Flying Rooster, and he comes soaring into Tweedy's farm, where a grim set of henhouses look just like barracks and the residents, led by the . . . well, plucky Ginger (Julia Sawalha), are constantly trying to escape. Ginger is, anyway, and she has just been released again from the Tweedy version of solitary confinement when Rocky, arms flailing and screaming in an unusually uncomfortable version of flight, hits the yard.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Chicken Run,'' the first full-length feature from Aardman Animation, makes brainy use of Mel Gibson. It parodies Mr. Gibson's inane heroics in giving him a loud loose-cannon entrance.</p>
        <p>He's the voice of Rocky the Flying Rooster, and he comes soaring into Tweedy's farm, where a grim set of henhouses look just like barracks and the residents, led by the . . . well, plucky Ginger (Julia Sawalha), are constantly trying to escape. Ginger is, anyway, and she has just been released again from the Tweedy version of solitary confinement when Rocky, arms flailing and screaming in an unusually uncomfortable version of flight, hits the yard.</p>
        <p>He promises Ginger and her friends that he'll teach them to fly and save them from a life of squeezing out eggs for the awful Mrs. Tweedy (Miranda Richardson).</p>
        <p>Based on the sympathy that ''Chicken Run'' will engender for chickens, it's probably good that McDonald's doesn't have a promotional tie-in. The sight of youngsters sobbing over Chicken McNuggets in a Happy Meal while their parents try to explain the food chain wouldn't be good for anybody. ''Chicken Run'' is, though, because like other efforts from the directors Nick Park (''Wallace and Gromit'' and ''Creature Comforts,'' the 1989 Academy Award-winning short) and Peter Lord, who also produced this film, it flies in the face of brightly colored, blandly energetic song-filled animated features.</p>
        <p>There's one forgettable song sequence, but like the other Aardman pieces that Mr. Park has directed, '''Chicken Run'' has that yearning for home that's at the heart of all good fables. There's a wistful calm in the gray skies of England, where all of Mr. Park's work is set, and his characters just want a comfortable place to rest their heads. Ginger dreams of lounging on grass instead of digging in the dirt in the Tweedy yards. (In the Wallace and Gromit shorts, Gromit, the poor thinking man's pooch, is constantly in danger of being tossed out of his home.)</p>
        <p>Visually as depressively earth-toned as ''Stalag 17'' (which is also parodied in the film), the world created by Mr. Park and Mr. Lord will hypnotize the young who may have had a full dose of antic full-length cartoons. (It assumes that children are up for animation a little darker in spirit than what they're usually fed.) The movie rewards them for their rapt, quiet attention, and its use of modeled latex figures instead of drawn animation makes ''Chicken Run''  more realistic and far more vigorously dramatic.</p>
        <p>The film is packed with the kind of detail that adults will like, too, with visual and verbal jokes that make references ranging from ''Modern Times'' to ''Star Trek.'' When the hens, following Rocky's daft flight instructions, are launched into the air, Fetcher (Phil Daniels), one of the farm's hustler mice, moans, ''It's raining hen.''</p>
        <p>There aren't many directors of animation who make such effective use of a Dickensian landscape and have Mr. Park's ability to wrest laughs from situations that lean toward the tragic. Mr. Park and Mr. Lord use several motifs of the Wallace and Gromit shorts, including some unwieldy, potentially deadly machinery: Mrs. Tweedy has installed a chicken pie machine because egg production isn't bringing in the kind of revenue stream she wants.</p>
        <p>Those expecting a breakthrough in animation storytelling may be a little disappointed, though. The Dreamworks influence has made ''Chicken Run'' a little safe; the Wallace and Gromit pictures provided more of an emotional roller coaster. And the presence of Mr. Gibson, even though he lends himself to satirizing his persona, provides comfort.</p>
        <p>If it's the more subversive Nick Park you want or are unfamiliar with, seek out the Wallace and Gromit films, all of which are available and should be seen. There are other notable Aardman projects as well,  including the fabulous and rambunctious ''Rex the Runt'' shorts, which can be found on the Atomfilms.com Web site.</p>
        <p>But ''Chicken Run'' is by no means a letdown. It's immensely satisfying, a divinely relaxed and confident film. Mr. Park and Mr. Lord brilliantly integrate everyday objects into the story.</p>
        <p>And this briskly paced epic -- not a minute is wasted -- uses their satirical take on British modesty and balmy superiority, exemplified here in a cranky former R.A.F. rooster,  Fowler (Benjamin Whitrow). The directors have transferred all the deftness and talent of their shorter films into an artful big screen realization.</p>
        <p>Ginger is ingenious and ambitious,  and for a change the movie gives children a quick-thinking heroine who eventually realizes that she's responsible for her future.</p>
        <p>More important, ''Chicken Run'' doesn't try to cram messages of uplift down its audience's gullet. It's a great eggscape from banality.</p>
        <p>CHICKEN RUN</p>
        <p>Directed by Peter Lord and Nick Park; written by Karey Kirkpatrick, based on a story by Mr. Lord and Mr. Park; director of photography, Dave Alex Riddett; edited by Mark Solomon; music by John Powell and Harry Gregson-Williams; produced by Mr. Lord, David Sproxton and Mr. Park; released by DreamWorks Pictures. Running time: 86 minutes. This film is rated G.</p>
        <p>WITH THE VOICES OF: Phil Daniels (Fetcher), Lynn Ferguson (Mac), Mel Gibson (Rocky), Tony Haygarth (Mr. Tweedy), Jane Horrocks (Babs), Miranda Richardson (Mrs. Tweedy), Julia Sawalha (Ginger), Timothy Spall (Nick), Imelda Staunton (Bunty) and Benjamin Whitrow (Fowler).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
