<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playing Hooky, Working Hooky</title>
    <meta content="21WCOL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Workplace" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209048"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LIFE'S WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belkin, Lisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E3DB1331F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playing Hooky, Working Hooky</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA BELKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belkin, Lisa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lisa Belkin's Life's Work column on playing 'hooky' in middle of the day from her job to do something entertaining like go to the movies; says growing number of companies are allowing employees to play occasional hooky; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I'M thinking of turning off my computer, silencing my cell phone and going to the movies. I have no idea what film I'll see, but that isn't the point. What matters is that the theater will be dark and cool and virtually empty -- because it will be the middle of the day, when I should really be at work.</p>
        <p>I never once played hooky as a child. I'm somewhat embarrassed to admit that I never even thought of it. Maybe I am compensating for that as an adult (or maybe this comes up on days when I don't necessarily want to be an adult), but I get the periodic urge to sneak out once in a while.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I'M thinking of turning off my computer, silencing my cell phone and going to the movies. I have no idea what film I'll see, but that isn't the point. What matters is that the theater will be dark and cool and virtually empty -- because it will be the middle of the day, when I should really be at work.</p>
        <p>I never once played hooky as a child. I'm somewhat embarrassed to admit that I never even thought of it. Maybe I am compensating for that as an adult (or maybe this comes up on days when I don't necessarily want to be an adult), but I get the periodic urge to sneak out once in a while.</p>
        <p>I don't do it often. Maybe once or twice a year, if that -- usually when the weather turns warm. And I am very specific about what I define as ''hooky.'' It does not include time off to visit the accountant or take the car to the insurance adjuster or even to attend the kindergarten year-end picnic. To count, it has to be a minirebellion, a few delicious hours at a place where I know I really am not supposed to be. The movies are a particular favorite. When I emerge after the final credits, blinking in the afternoon glare, I usually go home and concentrate more completely than I could have done before.</p>
        <p>The restorative power of forbidden fruit has not been lost on enlightened employers. Some companies go further still. Morningstar, the financial services company in Chicago, gives workers unlimited time off, no questions asked. (So far, Morningstar says, no one has abused this privilege.) Strategy Associates, a Silicon Valley consulting firm, has an employee-run ''Culture Club'' that schedules monthly hooky sessions for activities like bowling, ice skating, ultimate Frisbee and, yes, an afternoon at the movies.</p>
        <p>Karen Posner, the president and chief executive of COMM2 Inc., a seven-person advertising agency in Chicago, never takes time off. ''The sun and the moon will not rise and set if I stop working,'' she says. Yet, she insists that her employees play occasional hooky. Every so often she hands out coupons that can be traded for rewards as free-form as a day off or as specific as an afternoon at a ballgame. The most cherished coupon, she says, is the one that reads, ''Today it is too cold to go to work and I can't face getting out of bed.''</p>
        <p>Just about the only thing her staff may not do, she says, is lie about why they are not at work. ''I warn them: 'If you lie, you're gonna get caught and I'm never going to trust you,' '' she says.</p>
        <p>Carol Fass, who runs a five-person public-relations firm in Manhattan, agrees. ''I would be unhappy, and would even feel I was an unsuccessful, insensitive boss, if people sneaked out,'' she says. ''I would resent that a good deal. It's a terrific perk to let them take a 'mental health day.' Sneaking out -- I think you have trouble on your hands.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Fass and Ms. Posner say they are trying to pre-empt employees like Kerry Spreckman, who became so good at lying that she wrote and published herself ''The Hooky Book,'' which lists 200 excuses to tell a gullible boss. Among her favorites are ''My garage door won't go up, so I can't get my car out,'' ''My key broke off in the front door, and I have to wait for the locksmith'' and, she says, ''anything disgusting and medical because your boss just doesn't want to hear about it.'' When all else fails, she suggests watching the Weather Channel for natural disasters and then calling (from home) and saying: ''I'm in Kansas; I came for the weekend to see my cousin, and I'm sure you've heard about that tornado.''</p>
        <p>The grown-up part of me certainly understands why a boss values trust, but the not- quite-grown-up part, the part that wants to play hooky in the first place, thinks lying is such a harsh word. Half the point of this, maybe even more than half, is that you aren't supposed to be doing it. Having the boss's permission takes that frisson of naughtiness away.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth McRae Smith understands all that. She is head of the McRae Agency, which specializes in publicity for Internet start-ups, and she has made it policy to play hooky with her office staffs in San Diego and San Francisco. On a whim, she will close business for the afternoon and take everyone antique shopping or clothes shopping or on a drive along the coast for margaritas. ''It's probably a little less exciting because it's not forbidden,'' she says, but to offset that she often ''contributes'' $100 or so to her employees' purchases.</p>
        <p>''If the boss is buying,'' she says, ''no one seems to mind that the boss knows.''</p>
        <p>LIFE'S WORK This column about the intersection of jobs and personal lives appears every other week. Lisa Belkin's e-mail address is Belkin@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">This column about the intersection of jobs and personal lives appears every other week. Lisa Belkin's e-mail address is Belkin@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
