<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Britain, The Kitchen Dervish</title>
    <meta content="21AINS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BY THE BOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harriott, Ainsley</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fabricant, Florence</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Means in Minutes (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/By the Book</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EEDF1331F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Britain, The Kitchen Dervish</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabricant, Florence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Florence Fabricant reviews Ainsley Harriott's Meals in Minutes cookbook; recipe; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TACKLING the recipes in ''Ainsley Harriott's Meals in Minutes'' (Dorling Kindersley, $19.95) calls for energy, concentration and dexterity. It often means doing two, three or even four things at the same time. I am highly organized in the kitchen, but this book put me to the test.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harriott, who has one television program in Britain and another filmed in New York and shown in the United States, is a chef in high gear, enlisting audience and celebrity assistants to work on salads, whip up a marinade, sear chicken and somehow assemble a dish while keeping up a steady, energetic patter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TACKLING the recipes in ''Ainsley Harriott's Meals in Minutes'' (Dorling Kindersley, $19.95) calls for energy, concentration and dexterity. It often means doing two, three or even four things at the same time. I am highly organized in the kitchen, but this book put me to the test.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harriott, who has one television program in Britain and another filmed in New York and shown in the United States, is a chef in high gear, enlisting audience and celebrity assistants to work on salads, whip up a marinade, sear chicken and somehow assemble a dish while keeping up a steady, energetic patter.</p>
        <p>The big surprise is that this culinary sprint is mostly worth it. Occasionally, a recipe like spicy Indian ground lamb skewers takes 10 to 15 minutes longer than Mr. Harriott's E.T.A. On the other hand, I made his pan-fried pizza in 30 minutes, not 40, as the recipe stated.</p>
        <p>That pizza is made with a simple dough of flour, water and baking powder, which is rolled out in a circle and put in a big oiled skillet over medium heat. While the underside browns, the toppings are arranged on it. The whole thing is then run under the broiler. I've never made a pizza like that, and it was terrific.</p>
        <p>Spicy wine-steamed mussels, fish in a Thai curry sauce, broiled cod on couscous and even an oddly appealing onion ''tarte Tatin'' to cut in wedges all worked. Chicken in a spicy cream and yogurt sauce needed more chicken or less sauce, but it was tasty and easy.</p>
        <p>Noodle dishes, quick casseroles and stir-fries, some of which would be good with leftovers, dominate. Aside from some worthwhile crumbles and an apricot rice pudding, the dessert chapter is weak. What I found admirable is how seldom Mr. Harriott uses canned or packaged convenience foods. The purist could go further, as I did for the pizza, using a tablespoon of tomato paste from a tube instead of ketchup.</p>
        <p>There is no mistaking Mr. Harriott's English tastes: ''mash,'' as mashed potatoes are called, reigns; so does cod. There are also clever Asian, Mexican and Cajun touches. He gives a good tip: freeze chunks of peeled ginger for easy grating.</p>
        <p>A 20-minute Peking duck was that fast and excellent. But there was no crispy skin, so I fried strips of duck skin to tuck into the pancakes. It added less than five minutes.</p>
        <p>QUICK PEKING DUCK  Adapted from ''Ainsley Harriott's Meals in Minutes''  Time: 30 minutes</p>
        <p>12 ounces skinless, boneless duck breast  2 tablespoons dark soy sauce  2 tablespoons honey  1 teaspoon Chinese five-spice powder</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon coarse black pepper  1 teaspoon toasted sesame oil  1 garlic clove, crushed  1 tablespoon white wine vinegar  3 tablespoons plum jam or hoisin sauce  Pinch dried chili flakes  8 Chinese wheat-flour pancakes  1 tablespoon sunflower or peanut oil  4 scallions, trimmed and slivered</p>
        <p>1/2 cucumber, peeled, seeded and cut in matchsticks  1 tablespoon fresh cilantro leaves plus sprigs for garnish.</p>
        <p>1. Halve duck breast horizontally. Then cut with the grain in thin slivers. Mix 1 tablespoon soy sauce with honey, five-spice powder and pepper, toss with duck, and set aside.</p>
        <p>2. Heat sesame oil in small saucepan, add garlic, cook briefly, then stir in vinegar, jam, chili flakes and remaining soy sauce. Cook 2 minutes over medium heat to blend, then strain through a sieve, mashing the garlic. Set sauce aside.</p>
        <p>3. Place pancakes on a heat-proof plate. Cover with foil. Set them on top of pan of simmering water to warm.</p>
        <p>4. Heat sunflower or peanut oil in wok or skillet. Drain duck in sieve to remove excess marinade, add to wok, and stir-fry over high heat 2 to 3 minutes, until browned. Remove from heat.</p>
        <p>5. Spread warm pancakes with sauce mixture. Top with strips of duck, scallion and cucumber, sprinkle with cilantro, and roll up. Garnish with cilantro sprigs, and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 2 to 4 servings.</p>
        <p>BY THE BOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
