<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On ABC, Coverage Of Football Tops Politics</title>
    <meta content="Y21CON$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209123"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7DC1031F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="539" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On ABC, Coverage Of Football Tops Politics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the television battle between the Republicans and the Democrats this summer, the winner is: the San Francisco 49ers.</p>
        <p>Well, one of the winners, anyway. In a further downshifting of convention coverage in prime time, ABC News announced yesterday that it would not pre-empt two preseason football games scheduled for the opening nights of the Republican and Democratic national conventions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the television battle between the Republicans and the Democrats this summer, the winner is: the San Francisco 49ers.</p>
        <p>Well, one of the winners, anyway. In a further downshifting of convention coverage in prime time, ABC News announced yesterday that it would not pre-empt two preseason football games scheduled for the opening nights of the Republican and Democratic national conventions.</p>
        <p>But the network will not completely abandon politics in prime time when the Republicans convene in Philadelphia on Monday, July 31, and the Democrats in Los Angeles on Monday, Aug. 14. David Westin, the president of ABC News, said the network will provide coverage during halftime of the games, one on July 31, when the 49ers play the New England Patriots, and the other on Aug. 14, when the St. Louis Rams face the Tennessee Titans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Westin said yesterday that ABC News was planning an hour of coverage on the second and third nights and two hours on the final night of both conventions, with additional exposure on ''Nightline'' with Ted Koppel. ABC officials said that was slightly less than the network provided four years ago, when football did not intrude on the coverage.</p>
        <p>Still, ABC News may as yet provide more prime-time coverage than either of its rivals. CBS News and NBC News have yet to announce their plans, but the two networks are considering scaling back. (Neither party has announced its lineup of convention speakers.) NBC News, however, will have a presence each night through its all-news cable station, MSNBC, which will offer gavel-to-gavel coverage.</p>
        <p>Advocates for maintaining a strong prime-time presence by the networks were disappointed by ABC News's announcement.</p>
        <p>''The presidential campaign merits a halftime report in an N.F.L. preseason game,'' said Paul Taylor, executive director the Alliance for Better Campaigns, which monitors network coverage of politics. ''What has broadcast television come to in terms of commitment?''</p>
        <p>Network officials say the lack of a contest for the nominations, and the parties' desire to turn the gatherings into tightly managed, four-day-long advertisements has diminished their value as news events.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor, a former political reporter, said the parties' decision to present the conventions as feel-good commercials contributes to the receding coverage on the networks, which still draw vastly larger audiences than cable. But he added, ''By any modicum of news judgment it's an important occasion, even if it's a frustrating occasion.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Westin said ABC News had also invited Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas to face each other sometime after the conventions in an hourlong televised discussion, without a moderator, and that the initial reaction from the campaigns had been positive. He added that the network also wanted to produce hourlong biographical specials in prime time of the two.  The project's fate was uncertain, he said, because the network might be required under the fairness doctrine to also devote that amount to third-party candidates.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
