<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>School Board Approval Expected for Plan to Put Disabled Students in Regular Classes</title>
    <meta content="21SPEC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Education (Handicapped)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodnough, Abby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Special Education (Handicapped)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE7DB1031F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>School Board Approval Expected for Plan to Put Disabled Students in Regular Classes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodnough, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City's Board of Education is expected to approve plan that would move thousands of students classified as disabled into regular classrooms over next three to five years; plan, which would require intensive training for hundreds of classroom teachers, outlined (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City's Board of Education is expected to approve a plan today that would move thousands of students classified as disabled into regular classrooms over the next three to five years.</p>
        <p>The plan, which would require intensive training for hundreds of classroom teachers, would also significantly reduce the number of children who are classified as disabled in the first place, board officials said yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City's Board of Education is expected to approve a plan today that would move thousands of students classified as disabled into regular classrooms over the next three to five years.</p>
        <p>The plan, which would require intensive training for hundreds of classroom teachers, would also significantly reduce the number of children who are classified as disabled in the first place, board officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Under the plan, the board would eliminate its decades-old system of placing every disabled student into one of 20 highly specific special education categories and having separate classes for each category of disability. Instead, as many children as possible would be assigned to regular classrooms based on their age and academic ability.</p>
        <p>Schools would have to exhaust every option for helping children in regular classrooms before classifying them as disabled and moving them into special education classes, the board officials said.</p>
        <p>Students who could not be placed in regular classrooms would be grouped into six new categories, based not on their disability but on which class size was most appropriate for them. At the elementary level, the maximum class size would be reduced to 12, from 15.</p>
        <p>''This is a monumental change,'' Francine Goldstein, the board's director of student support services, said in an interview. ''Special education has always been seen as a place kids are sent to, and now it's going to be seen as a service they can get, ideally in a general education setting.''</p>
        <p>The board did not provide precise estimates of how many of the 140,000 students currently in special education it hoped to move, or how much the program would cost. Nor has the board worked out the details of how it would put the plan into effect, a problem that several advocates for special education students complained about yesterday.</p>
        <p>''What they're voting on is a statement of philosophy,'' said Ed Leahy, president of New York United Special Education Parents, a nonprofit group with about 500 members. ''It's not a bad philosophy, but there are so many unanswered questions.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Goldstein said yesterday that the board would have a detailed plan for carrying out the new program by the end of the summer. The program would not actually take effect until the 2001-02 school year, she said, because it would take a full year to train special education teachers and regular classroom teachers for the changes.</p>
        <p>Encouraging schools to move as many students as possible into regular classrooms -- a process known as mainstreaming -- has long been Board of Education policy, but the new plan would speed movement in that direction.</p>
        <p>The plan is the board's latest response to pressure from the federal government, which has long criticized New York City for placing too many students -- especially black and Hispanic boys -- in special education classrooms.</p>
        <p>Roughly one in eight of the school system's 1.1 million students are currently classified as disabled. Of those, more than half spend most or all of their time in specially designated classrooms, while the remainder are pulled out of regular classrooms for part of the day for special instruction tailored to their disability.</p>
        <p>The board currently spends $2 billion of its $12 billion annual budget on special education. Ms. Goldstein said yesterday that spending on special education would probably increase under the plan, although she did not have an estimate. The costs would be higher in part because the school system would need more special education teachers, many of whom would be ''team teaching'' with regular teachers in regular classrooms.</p>
        <p>Board officials hope that the plan will improve the academic performance of disabled students, most of whom lag far behind their peers. The board is under pressure to improve the performance of disabled students, because new statewide graduation standards require that all students, including those in special education, pass the rigorous Regents exams.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leahy and several other advocates said yesterday that while mainstreaming was an admirable goal for many disabled children, they were worried that schools would feel pressure to keep some children in regular classrooms who would be much better off in special education classes.</p>
        <p>''If the goal is to put as many kids as possible into mainstream classes, I don't think the system is prepared to handle that,'' Mr. Leahy said. ''Teachers will have to really want to reach out to these children and go the extra mile with them. But you can't force every teacher in the system to go the extra mile.''</p>
        <p>Leaders of the union representing New York City teachers also expressed concerns about the plan yesterday. Carmen Alvarez, a vice president of the United Federation of Teachers, questioned whether the board would give teachers the resources necessary to accommodate so many disabled students in regular classrooms. She also questioned how teachers would deal with students who have behavioral problems.</p>
        <p>''When you don't have social promotion anymore and you have high-stakes testing and all this pressure,'' Ms. Alvarez said, ''how much time and energy can you put into kids who can't sit still?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
