<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Melding of Cultures the Next Step in Seagram Deal</title>
    <meta content="Y21DEA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209116"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seagram Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vivendi Sa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E3DD1031F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1096" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Melding of Cultures the Next Step in Seagram Deal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Vivendi SA's acquisition of Seagram Co focuses on enormous challenge facing new company as both sides try to merge their vastly different businesses and cultures into global force the combines European business sensibility with American popular culture; after acquisition is formally announced, investors worry about companies' ability to create seamless worldwide telecommunications and entertainment giant managed by a French company; shares of Vivendi decline 8.7 percent, while Seagram's shares fall about 9 percent; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sitting on a stool next to Jean-Marie Messier, the chairman of the newly minted Vivendi Universal, Edgar Bronfman Jr. looked a little uneasy.</p>
        <p>But it soon become clear that Mr. Bronfman was not anxious because he had announced the sale of the Seagram Company, his family's business, for about $34 billion in stock to Vivendi S.A., the French water utility turned telecommunications and entertainment conglomerate. It was a much more practical problem: he could not understand his new boss's presentation, because, as one journalist whispered quite loudly, ''He doesn't speak French.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sitting on a stool next to Jean-Marie Messier, the chairman of the newly minted Vivendi Universal, Edgar Bronfman Jr. looked a little uneasy.</p>
        <p>But it soon become clear that Mr. Bronfman was not anxious because he had announced the sale of the Seagram Company, his family's business, for about $34 billion in stock to Vivendi S.A., the French water utility turned telecommunications and entertainment conglomerate. It was a much more practical problem: he could not understand his new boss's presentation, because, as one journalist whispered quite loudly, ''He doesn't speak French.''</p>
        <p>The moment offered a glimpse into the  enormous challenge facing the new company as both sides try to merge their vastly different businesses and cultures -- and, of course, languages -- into a global force that combines European business sensibility with American popular culture. Vivendi Universal would become the second-largest media company after Time Warner-America Online.</p>
        <p>After the acquisition was formally announced today, investors worried about the companies' ability to create a seamless worldwide telecommunications and entertainment giant managed by a French company. Shares of Vivendi declined 8.35 euros, or 8.7 percent, to 88.10 euros, or $84.55, while Seagram fell about 9 percent, or $5.6875, to $58.625. Mr. Messier attributed the market's reaction to ''classical arbitrage'' and said it was a great time to buy Vivendi stock.</p>
        <p>Under the terms of the deal, Vivendi will issue stock valued at $77.35 for each share of Seagram. Seagram shareholders will get 0.8 share of Vivendi stock if Vivendi's share price is less than $96.69. If Vivendi's stock rises to more than $124.30 a share, the ratio is fixed at 0.622 shares. With about 440 million shares outstanding, that brings the value of the acquisition to about $34 billion.</p>
        <p>Vivendi also plans to buy the 51 percent of Canal Plus, the pay television group, that it does not already  own for about $10.6 billion. Canal Plus shareholders will receive two  Vivendi shares for each Canal Plus share held. Shares of Canal Plus fell 12 percent yesterday, to 178.6 euros.</p>
        <p>Vivendi has agreed to pay Seagram $800 million as a breakup fee, if the deal falls apart.</p>
        <p>Though Salomon Smith Barney analyst Jill Krutick described the deal as a ''home run'' yesterday, she nevertheless downgraded her recommendation on Seagram from buy to  neutral, contending that trading in the stock reflected a frenzy, but not the fundamentals. Scott Davis of First Union also came out with a neutral recommendation after being bullish.</p>
        <p>The union of Vivendi and Seagram puts Universal Studios and Polygram records under the same roof as Canal Plus as well as Vizzavi, an Internet portal that will allow access across Europe through wireless devices and personal computers.</p>
        <p>The companies are hoping to leverage Seagram's stable of entertainment content over Vivendi's many  distribution channels, especially in  the potential market for downloading digital media over the Internet and wireless devices.</p>
        <p>Mr. Messier was also enthusiastic about his new relationship with USA Networks, of which Seagram owns 42 percent, with the right to increase its investment. He acknowledged, however, that he had not yet met with the USA chairman, Barry Diller, though he had spoken to him by phone and planned a meeting in the next few days in New York.</p>
        <p>As to whether Mr. Diller will have one of the 5 seats that Seagram will control on the 18-member board, Mr. Bronfman said that had yet to be decided. Three of the seats go to Mr. Bronfman Jr.; his father, Edgar; and his uncle Charles.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Bronfman said yesterday that his family was completely behind the deal, he added that it did have the right to sell its stock beginning 90 days after the deal's completion, which is expected to happen next January or February, Vivendi officials said.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Bronfman was unhappy about giving up control of the company his family had run for decades, he handled it smoothly yesterday, saying that if his mission had been to keep control, he would not have sold. But, he said, his goal had been to enhance shareholder value.</p>
        <p>The combined companies will have revenue of $65 billion, of which $28 billion will represent entertainment and media operations. There will be about 1.2 billion shares outstanding.</p>
        <p>The French press had tempered praise for the deal today. ''They should be applauded, but with some reserve,'' an editorial in Le Monde, the French daily, said of the deal. ''This bet is founded on a certain number of risks.''</p>
        <p>The editorial went on to warn: ''All foreign companies burned their wings in Hollywood.'' The editorial was referring to Matsushita Electric Industrial Company's troubled ownership of MCA before it was sold to  Seagram, and Sony's somewhat difficult ownership of Columbia Pictures.</p>
        <p>Vivendi will be putting a Frenchman, Pierre Lescure, Canal Plus's  chairman, in charge of the combined company's film units, including Universal Studios. Mr. Lescure will try his hand at managing the unit from  here rather than from Hollywood. Mr. Messier went to great pains to explain that the daily operations of the United States business would still be managed by Americans.</p>
        <p>The cultural differences between Mr. Messier and Mr. Bronfman were also made apparent today, despite both executives' efforts to point out their similarities. Telling the audience about his first meeting with Mr. Bronfman at his house on Oct. 12, Mr. Messier ribbed him for showing up ''without a tie and in short sleeves.'' (Mr. Bronfman was on vacation.)</p>
        <p>For Mr. Messier, a former investment banker, the meeting was an opportunity to discuss his vision to create what is now called Vizzavi and was then code-named MAP, for multi-access portal, before its development by Vivendi and Vodafone AirTouch, the wireless telephone company. Both executives believed in the idea of delivering content over the Internet and believed that was the key to striking a deal.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, executives close to the talks said, Mr. Bronfman continued to shop the company around, particularly to Sony and the News Corporation. While both companies expressed initial interest, talks with neither company went anywhere. Over the next eight months, Mr. Bronfman met with Mr. Messier nine more times before reaching a handshake deal about 10 days ago.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
