<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Announcements Getting Worse, Subway Riders' Group Contends</title>
    <meta content="21SUBW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209092"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Guidebooks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Straphangers Campaign</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E3DF1031F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Announcements Getting Worse, Subway Riders' Group Contends</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Study by Straphanger's Campaign finds that despite improvements in guides and promise by New York City Transit Authority to make flow of information better from train crews to riders, announcements of reasons for delays have gotten worse (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a dozen years, many conductors on the city's subways have carried a palm-sized blue book that was put out as a kind of bible for a lapsed observance: announcements.</p>
        <p>The 26-page book includes rules on the kinds of announcements conductors should make in certain situations. (Unruly person on board? Refer to announcement 4: ''Ladies and gentleman, this is the conductor. We are delayed because of a disturbance on the train. We are investigating.'')</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For a dozen years, many conductors on the city's subways have carried a palm-sized blue book that was put out as a kind of bible for a lapsed observance: announcements.</p>
        <p>The 26-page book includes rules on the kinds of announcements conductors should make in certain situations. (Unruly person on board? Refer to announcement 4: ''Ladies and gentleman, this is the conductor. We are delayed because of a disturbance on the train. We are investigating.'')</p>
        <p>But an advocacy group for riders contended yesterday that despite the improvement in the guides in 1996 and a promise then by New York City Transit to make the flow of information better from train crews to riders, announcements of reasons for delays were growing worse.</p>
        <p>The three-month survey, by the Straphangers Campaign, found that in 78 percent of the delays experienced by a group of 58 volunteer surveyors, the conductor either made no announcement, or the announcement was inaudible, garbled or used transit terms that meant little to the average rider.</p>
        <p>In a similar survey from late 1998 to early 1999, there were bad or missing announcements 73 percent of the time, and in the first survey a year earlier, 67 percent of the time.</p>
        <p>Gene Russianoff, a staff attorney at the Straphangers Campaign, said, ''It's disappointing that it's gotten worse, and I think that part of it is that communication within the agency in general has gotten worse.''</p>
        <p>Al O'Leary, chief spokesman for New York City Transit, said he believed that the survey's findings were simply wrong. He said transit officials did public opinion polls in the first quarter of this year that found that 82 percent of riders who experienced delays reported being ''very well or somewhat'' informed.</p>
        <p>He said announcements would continue to be plagued by mechanical problems -- static, squealing, low volume, outrageously high volume -- until outdated cable and radio equipment was replaced with fiber-optic networks and computer-based communications systems, which will take many years. He added that new subway trains that would begin running on the 2, 5 and 6 lines over the next two years would have clear automated announcements.</p>
        <p>But the Straphangers said there were many nonmechanical things that conductors could do now to keep riders informed. For example, in early 1999, transit officials changed a rule for conductors so they now announce information on the station and transfer options after the train is stopped in the station and the doors open. In the past, those announcements came as the train pulled in.</p>
        <p>Mr. Russianoff said the change meant that people got information far too late and that many riders did not have time to get off trains before the doors closed again.</p>
        <p>Transit officials said yesterday that they made the change so that the announcements would not compete with the moving trains' noise.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
