<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton and Senators Maneuver to Expedite Vote on China Trade</title>
    <meta content="Y21TRA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209121"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">China-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Trade Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E0DD1031F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton and Senators Maneuver to Expedite Vote on China Trade</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton, month after House approved decisive bill on trade with China, summons bipartisan group of senators to White House to map strategy to press Republican leaders to begin debating issue; Senate backers have more than enough votes to secure passage but want to pass clean version of House bill free of amendments that would force measure back to House for potentially treacherous second vote; procedure is proving tricky (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four weeks after the House approved a decisive bill on trade with China, President Clinton summoned a bipartisan group of senators to the White House tonight to talk strategy on pressing Republican leaders to set a date for bringing up the bill in the Senate.</p>
        <p>Unlike supporters in the House, who had to hustle votes up to the last minute, Senate backers of granting China permanent normal trading status say they have more than 70 votes in favor. That is enough to defeat a filibuster and win handily.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four weeks after the House approved a decisive bill on trade with China, President Clinton summoned a bipartisan group of senators to the White House tonight to talk strategy on pressing Republican leaders to set a date for bringing up the bill in the Senate.</p>
        <p>Unlike supporters in the House, who had to hustle votes up to the last minute, Senate backers of granting China permanent normal trading status say they have more than 70 votes in favor. That is enough to defeat a filibuster and win handily.</p>
        <p>But supporters want to pass a clean version of the House bill, free of amendments that would force the measure back to the House for a potentially treacherous second vote. And that is proving to be tricky.</p>
        <p>Senator Trent Lott, the majority leader and a supporter of the bill, has said the Senate does not have time to defuse all possible amendments and to vote on the measure before the weeklong July 4 recess. That leaves a three-week window in July before the long August recess.</p>
        <p>But the Republican leadership has given priority to approving several must-pass spending bills this summer before considering the trade measure, which would end Congress's annual review of China's trade status. Some top Senate Republican aides suggested that the twists and turns of the spending bills could put off a vote on the China legislation until September, which supporters angrily said could imperil the bill, as it might get caught up in election-year politics.</p>
        <p>''If we go into September, our chances for passage drop precipitously,'' said Senator Tom Daschle of South Dakota, the Democratic leader.</p>
        <p>At the White House early this evening, Mr. Clinton met with 17 Republicans and Democrats who support the bill. They included the top Republican and Democrat on the Finance Committee, William V. Roth Jr. of Delaware and Daniel Patrick Moynihan of New York. It was Mr. Clinton's second strategy session with senators since the House passed the measure, 237 to 197, on May 24.</p>
        <p>''This is undoubtedly one of the most important votes any of these senators will ever take,'' the White House spokesman, Joe Lockhart, said today. ''And it's certainly our hope we can get this done quickly and without the long arm of partisan politics entering the fray.''</p>
        <p>House Republicans who support the bill say they were watching the Senate machinations and consulting with Senator Lott's staff. ''We're monitoring it and we're not worried -- yet,'' said one House aide.</p>
        <p>Senator Lott and Senator Daschle are talking with several senators who have expressed interest in offering amendments. Senator Jesse Helms, a North Carolina Republican who heads the Foreign Relations Committee, has promised a ''robust debate'' and ''uncomfortable votes'' on issues ranging from China's use of prison labor to its crackdown on political dissent. Senator Paul Wellstone, the Minnesota Democrat, said today that he would offer amendments on human rights and labor conditions in China.</p>
        <p>But the most immediate problem for Senator Lott and the administration is an amendment sponsored by Senators Fred Thompson, a Tennessee Republican, and Robert G. Torricelli, a New Jersey Democrat. The amendment would provide for an annual review of China's record in trafficking nuclear, chemical and biological warfare and missile technology. The measure would also require the administration to impose sanctions on individuals, groups or companies that the United States identifies as weapons proliferators.</p>
        <p>Today, the national security adviser, Samuel R. Berger, met with Senate Republicans to discuss Senator Thompson's proposal and other national security issues. On Friday, the White House chief of staff, John D. Podesta, also met with Senator Thompson about his proposal.</p>
        <p>Senator Lott is trying to negotiate with Democrats to allow Senator Thompson's measure to be voted on as a separate bill -- the price for his agreeing not to add the provision, which is likely to be popular, as an amendment to the trade bill.</p>
        <p>Senator Thompson said today he would insist on a vote on his measure before the Senate considers the trade bill. But the administration opposes it, saying it is unnecessary and overly broad and has thresholds for imposing sanctions that are too low.</p>
        <p>This week, Senators Roth and Moynihan sought to assuage some senators' concerns by asking the General Accounting Office, an investigative arm of Congress, to monitor China's compliance with World Trade Organization rules.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
