<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lakers Have a Ring and a Lot of Upside</title>
    <meta content="21HOOP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209159"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E3DA1031F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1087" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lakers Have a Ring and a Lot of Upside</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Pro Basketball column on Los Angeles Lakers winning NBA championship; team's future discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shaquille O'Neal stepped up to the dais Monday night just as Jerry Buss, the owner of the Los Angeles Lakers, finished telling the tale of how the supernova center, the new age coaching sage and the young, bright shooting guard came together to lead the franchise to its first championship in 12 years.</p>
        <p>Buss smiled at the sight of the 7-foot-1-inch, 330-pound behemoth pretending to clear his throat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shaquille O'Neal stepped up to the dais Monday night just as Jerry Buss, the owner of the Los Angeles Lakers, finished telling the tale of how the supernova center, the new age coaching sage and the young, bright shooting guard came together to lead the franchise to its first championship in 12 years.</p>
        <p>Buss smiled at the sight of the 7-foot-1-inch, 330-pound behemoth pretending to clear his throat.</p>
        <p>''Extension,'' O'Neal said through a mock cough. ''Extension.''</p>
        <p>Buss finally gave in. ''Whatever you want, baby,'' he told O'Neal.</p>
        <p>What do you give the center who has everything? Or maybe a better question: at what price a dynasty?</p>
        <p>After the cigar smoke had finished wafting through the Staples Center -- and the Indiana Pacers had been dispensed in six mostly pulsating games -- the Lakers toasted one another with Champagne, waited for the rowdy streets outside the building to clear, and then went their separate ways.</p>
        <p>The parade is scheduled for Wednesday, at which point O'Neal will reiterate what he said after the clinching 116-111 Game 6 victory over the Pacers on Monday night in the National Basketball Association finals.</p>
        <p>''We're going to get one next year, too,'' he said.</p>
        <p>O'Neal, Kobe Bryant and Phil Jackson. Some triangle, no? The triumph of the Lakers' trinity makes you wonder about the possibilities, whether the N.B.A. has another dynasty on its hands.</p>
        <p>Michael Jordan won six titles in the 1990's with the same coach who guided Kobe and Shaq to their first this season. The way Bryant broke down defenses and O'Neal unleashed indefensible weapons the past few months brought back shades of Magic Johnson and Kareem Abdul-Jabbar, that Hall of Fame guard-center combination that led the Lakers to five championships in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>O'Neal averaged 38 points and 16.7 rebounds in the finals. He became only the third player in league history to close out a season with the scoring title, the most valuable player award and a championship ring, and the third player to be named M.V.P. of the regular season, the All-Star Game and the N.B.A. finals.</p>
        <p>At 28, O'Neal will only get better. Asked if the potential is there for the Lakers to win multiple titles, Larry Bird, who won three with the Boston Celtics and came close to another during his three seasons as coach of the Pacers, replied:</p>
        <p>''Well, it is with Shaquille O'Neal. He's the most dominating player in our league. He's powerful, strong, able to get the ball in the hole. He's just so dominating that they have an opportunity to do something great for a number of years.''</p>
        <p>If O'Neal is the most dominant player in the league, Bryant has quickly become the most dangerous perimeter player in the N.B.A.</p>
        <p>Named to the league's all-defensive team, he elevated his stature in overtime of Game 4 by scoring 8 points after O'Neal fouled out in the 120-118 victory at Conseco Fieldhouse. Bryant is only 21.</p>
        <p>They both joined the Lakers in the summer of 1996, Bryant in a draft-day trade with Charlotte and O'Neal, who had played with Orlando, through free agency. They have never been the best of friends, coexisting despite a feud that has turned ugly at times. But on the court, they are undeniably the best inside-outside combination in pro basketball.</p>
        <p>O'Neal can extend his seven-year, $120 million contract this summer -- a given, Buss said. Bryant appears to be a Laker for life. If neither petty jealousy nor growing tired of seeing each other every day gets in the way, few things can undermine their potential.</p>
        <p>''They have definitely made their mark as one of the best combinations ever to play this game,'' the Lakers reserve guard Derek Fisher said Monday night. ''They carried us, and the rest of us stepped it up when we needed to.''</p>
        <p>Falling short for four seasons, they crossed the precipice in Game 7 of the Western Conference finals against Portland, rallying from 15 points down in the final 10 minutes to shock, and eliminate, the Trail Blazers. By barely escaping losing a three-games-to-one lead in the conference finals and by staving off Indiana, the Lakers avoided the indignity of becoming only the second 67-victory team not to win a title.</p>
        <p>It was one of several signs revealing their vulnerability, signs that should give 28 other teams a glimmer of hope -- including those free-spending Blazers.</p>
        <p>Beginning with a Game 3 debacle against Sacramento in the first round, the Lakers went 4-6 in elimination games. The game before they claimed their first title of the post-Magic era, the Lakers suffered their worst loss of the season, a 33-point rout in Indianapolis.</p>
        <p>They did not wield the hammer until Monday night, needing the final minutes to wear down the game-but-defensively challenged Pacers. Through it all, Jackson looked on like a ski instructor who expected his students to fall off the chair lift now and then.</p>
        <p>He molded the egos and talent together flawlessly, siphoning every ounce of energy from O'Neal to make sure the often-injured center kept himself in prime physical condition. He did not have qualms about singling Bryant out in front of his teammates, telling him often and bluntly, ''Trust the offense.''</p>
        <p>When they finally raised the Larry O'Brien trophy and the purple and gold confetti rained down from the rafters, it was plain to see: all three sides of the triangle fit perfectly.</p>
        <p>''The difference has been Phil Jackson,'' said Bill Walton, the NBC analyst and Hall of Fame center. ''What he did in terms of challenging Shaq and Kobe to refocus their priorities, to become defensive players, to become rebounders, to become passers, to get in good shape, to become so focused in on the team, well, that has made them champions.</p>
        <p>''I see nothing that's going to keep these guys from staying at the top -- unless they stop listening to the coach.''</p>
        <p>There are but a few questions. Glen Rice? He is not expected back. Ron Harper may retire. A. C. Green won't start at power forward much longer. But then, as long as Jerry West is in charge of personnel, there are no worries.</p>
        <p>Only two-fifths of the starting lineup is guaranteed to return. Those players just happen to be the only two the Lakers cannot lose. Supporting casts don't collect banners as much as stars do.</p>
        <p>Shaq and Kobe have one -- and counting.</p>
        <p>ON PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
