<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vivendi Vis-a-Vis the Internet</title>
    <meta content="Y21POR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seagram Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vivendi Sa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seagram Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E7DD1031F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vivendi Vis-a-Vis the Internet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis of Vivendi SA's acquisition of Seagram Co focuses on Vivendi's hopes of becoming portal for millions of mobile Internet surfers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Judging by the public pronouncements, one might think that the acquisition of Seagram by Vivendi will create a global telecommunications powerhouse.</p>
        <p>''World's Largest Wireless Footprint,'' read one of the highlighted  points at the top of the news release announcing the agreement. ''Vizzavi Will Be the Default Home Page for 80 Million Potential Mobile and Interactive TV Customers,'' read another, referring to one of Vivendi's Internet initiatives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Judging by the public pronouncements, one might think that the acquisition of Seagram by Vivendi will create a global telecommunications powerhouse.</p>
        <p>''World's Largest Wireless Footprint,'' read one of the highlighted  points at the top of the news release announcing the agreement. ''Vizzavi Will Be the Default Home Page for 80 Million Potential Mobile and Interactive TV Customers,'' read another, referring to one of Vivendi's Internet initiatives.</p>
        <p>Here are some facts. This is the main telecommunications asset to be owned by the new Vivendi Universal: 52 percent of Cegetel, which is the No. 2 long-distance provider in France and also the owner of 80 percent of France's No. 2 cellular phone carrier. Vivendi Universal would also own Canal Plus, a European pay television company with 14 million subscribers, 25 percent of a British satellite television operation and 50 percent of the Vizzavi European Internet portal, which began its first operations, in France, Monday night.</p>
        <p>Vizzavi took center stage yesterday. At their Paris news conference, Jean-Marie Messier, Vivendi's chairman, and Edgar Bronfman Jr., Seagram's chief executive, repeatedly held out Vizzavi as one of the cornerstones of their deal, as perhaps the main engine for Vivendi Universal's growth. They heralded Vizzavi as a tool for delivering music and potentially video to millions of people using hand-held wireless devices.</p>
        <p>''You'll be able to get connected to your own personal music library,'' Mr. Bronfman said at the news conference. ''I'm a great believer in the future of wireless opportunities.</p>
        <p>''We can supply Internet content way beyond Europe,'' Mr. Bronfman added. When someone suggested that it might take years for the technology to arrive to realistically deliver mobile wireless music, he said, ''Years? Months! We will be able to distribute wireless music within months.'' Met with skepticism, he said, ''I didn't say we'd be able to do it to 80 million people, did I?''</p>
        <p>Vizzavi is meant to be an Internet portal with three legs: wireless devices, personal computers and interactive televisions.</p>
        <p>Here are some more facts: Vizzavi barely exists. Vivendi, not to mention Seagram, has essentially zero business providing Internet access to computers in any country. Even Vivendi does not expect to be able to deliver Internet access to televisions in Europe until next year at the earliest. It will in fact be a year or two until any company, in Europe or the United States, is able to deliver digital music to wireless phones on any meaningful scale. It will take at least two years after that until anyone is able to deliver decent-quality video on the same scale.</p>
        <p>Vivendi Universal has no realistic chance of becoming a player in the United States wireless Internet market any time soon. And the upshot is that it is not at all clear just how acquiring Seagram helps Vivendi with all of the hard work it faces in building Vizzavi on its own.</p>
        <p>''I don't necessarily look at this deal as one where the whole is worth more than the sum of its parts,'' one United States media analyst said yesterday on the condition of anonymity. ''I happen to think the Bronfmans are cashing out.''</p>
        <p>That said, the general concept behind Vizzavi is solid. The catch phrase that was electronic commerce two years ago, the buzzword that was business-to-business last year, is definitely mobile Internet access this year. While many electronic-commerce companies have struggled recently, no one can deny that they are serious industries. Mobile Internet access will be serious as well, but Vivendi Universal does not appear to be a company tailor made to exploit it.</p>
        <p>For one thing, Vivendi Universal has to work through another company to gain access to mobile wireless users outside France. That company is Vodafone AirTouch P.L.C. of Britain, the world's No. 1 wireless telephone provider. (That is how Vivendi and Seagram came up with that first highlighted point.)</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, Vodafone and Vivendi agreed to create Vizzavi as a 50-50 joint venture. Vodafone has 58 million wireless subscribers in Europe but has only minority investments in some of the carriers that serve those customers. (The 80 million figure in the second highlighted point came from adding those 58 million users to Vivendi's pay television roster and the total number of Cegetel customers.) Vodafone wants Vizzavi to be the preferred Internet portal for all of its European networks but cannot necessarily deliver all of them (though it will probably deliver most).</p>
        <p>Vodafone is also talking to other companies about their wireless Internet portals. Though no deal appears imminent, Vodafone has at least met with America Online about carrying that service in Europe, according to people close to those talks.</p>
        <p>And then there is the United States. Or, in reality, then there is not the United States.</p>
        <p>There was some talk yesterday about Vizzavi expanding to the United States, but that is not going to happen in a meaningful way soon. First of all, most of the big United States wireless providers are building portals of their own, sometimes in partnership with United States Internet companies like Yahoo.</p>
        <p>Vodafone is a partner in the new Verizon wireless carrier, which also includes Bell Atlantic's wireless operation and will soon include GTE's.</p>
        <p>''We have an agreement with Vodafone, and as part of that we have an agreement to be considered as a premier provider of content in the U.S. as we have in Vizzavi,'' Philippe L. Germond, a senior executive vice president of Vivendi, said in a telephone interview yesterday.</p>
        <p>But it appears that that consideration is over, at least for now.</p>
        <p>''Verizon will launch its own wireless Internet portal in the next couple of weeks,'' Jim Gerace, a Verizon spokesman, said yesterday. ''It's separate and apart, though compatible with what Vodafone is doing overseas. Our customers will be able to go to it if they choose.''</p>
        <p>Under the Verizon model, however, customers will be able to go just about anywhere else on the Internet, as well, which means that that compatibility is fairly close to meaningless. That is not a word that applies to Vizzavi just now. But in Vizzavi's current state, it might come close.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
