<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Curiouser And Curiouser, Chapter 2</title>
    <meta content="21REST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nicholson (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimes, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EFDE1331F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1354" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Curiouser And Curiouser, Chapter 2</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Grimes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Grimes reviews Manhattan restaurant Nicholson; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH all its quirks and aberrations, Manhattan is often thought of as America's Oz. But there lurks, right in the heart of the city, a smaller, even weirder Oz -- a Mini-Me of strangeness. It is Nicholson, and nearly everything about it seems designed to neutralize all known standards of restaurant criticism.</p>
        <p>The place has a history. For nearly half a century, it was Cafe Nicholson, named after its creator, Johnny Nicholson, a window dresser, antiques dealer and bohemian with a taste for high society. In 1949, almost on a whim, he decided to open a cafe, enlisting Edna Lewis as his chef. Within a couple of years, the restaurant moved into its present location, a former artist's studio, and a legend was born. Cafe Nicholson became the haunt of society folk, writers, artists, actors and theater people. In a New York restaurant scene defined by cozy neighborhood joints and imposing temples of haute cuisine, Cafe Nicholson stood alone and apart, a theme restaurant whose only theme was its owner's idiosyncratic style.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH all its quirks and aberrations, Manhattan is often thought of as America's Oz. But there lurks, right in the heart of the city, a smaller, even weirder Oz -- a Mini-Me of strangeness. It is Nicholson, and nearly everything about it seems designed to neutralize all known standards of restaurant criticism.</p>
        <p>The place has a history. For nearly half a century, it was Cafe Nicholson, named after its creator, Johnny Nicholson, a window dresser, antiques dealer and bohemian with a taste for high society. In 1949, almost on a whim, he decided to open a cafe, enlisting Edna Lewis as his chef. Within a couple of years, the restaurant moved into its present location, a former artist's studio, and a legend was born. Cafe Nicholson became the haunt of society folk, writers, artists, actors and theater people. In a New York restaurant scene defined by cozy neighborhood joints and imposing temples of haute cuisine, Cafe Nicholson stood alone and apart, a theme restaurant whose only theme was its owner's idiosyncratic style.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nicholson sold the restaurant last year, and it would have seemed a safe bet that, with his disappearance from the scene, the air would rush out of the souffle. Not so. A meal at Nicholson (the restaurant has dropped ''Cafe'' from its name) may still be the oddest legal experience available in New York.</p>
        <p>To begin with, Nicholson occupies a peculiar spot, perched at the edge of the entrance to the upper roadway of the Queensboro Bridge. It looks like a guardhouse, and it's not much larger. You enter through a narrow, open-air passageway, walk down five steps, and enter what feels like a private home. Past a tiny bar and a lounge, the dining room awaits.</p>
        <p>It is a very distinctive room. Mr. Nicholson's decor was once described as Spanish-Portuguese belle epoque, and under the new owner and chef, Patrick Woodside, working with the architect Alexander Gorlin, things have become only more complex. The cane-work settees with their silk throw pillows remain. So do the brightly colored Spanish wall tiles with a satyr motif, the pastel panels filled with cupids, and the stenciled ceiling border depicting lily pads and lizards. The skylight, however, has been replaced with a recessed panel covered in gold leaf, and the room is now dominated by a large central table supporting multiple exotic floral arrangements. Up front, the intimate lounge with a small bar is also new.</p>
        <p>An erratic Modernist streak now runs through the design. Plates look like heavyweight 1950's ashtrays. Water is poured from a white ceramic cone, and bread is served in a cylindrical stone container carved to resemble a curled strip of birch bark. Diners who reach for the bread must then place it on a bread plate that looks like a surfboard designed by Russel Wright. The sugar container is a Pyrex custard cup.</p>
        <p>The streamlined dishes seem like antonyms, given the florid, flamboyant style of cooking at Nicholson, which finds its natural reflection in the dining room's Versailles-style gilt mirrors. One evening, I ordered one of the house drinks, a Champagne cocktail flavored with Cointreau, Chambord, gin, orange muscat and lavender. It arrived in a shallow coupe, wide enough for a mouse to swim laps in. A plump strawberry sat precariously on the rim. As a prelude to the meal, the drink was the perfect symbol.</p>
        <p>Mr. Woodside, who also owns CamaJe Bistro and Lounge in Greenwich Village, has an opulent sensibility and a jeweler's sense of design. Diners who might quail at the longer fixed-price menus need have no fear. The leisurely pace of the service, and the appetizer-size portions, make even the eight-course extravaganza an ultra-fancy snack.</p>
        <p>Like the decor, the food at Nicholson swings wildly between extremes. It can be romantic and elegant, or almost insanely misjudged. The eight-course tasting menu, on one visit, began with a wonderful amuse-bouche, a lump of sweetbread arranged in a mille-feuille with cream and truffle essence.</p>
        <p>The road ahead was bumpy. A miniature assemblage of seared scallops in a syrupy balsamic reduction was straightforward enough, but the scallops lacked flavor. Three grape tomatoes, huddled together in the center of a discus-size plate, made a bright second act, tartly sweet in a vibrant basil vinaigrette. Lamb carpaccio, glazed with mint and basil, had just enough thickness to support a well-judged spicing of cumin and chili. It is hard to find a New York menu without carpaccio. It has become a cliche. But Nicholson's ranks among the best that I've come across.</p>
        <p>Truffle cream, truffles, caviar and mushrooms loom large in Mr. Woodside's cooking vocabulary. They are the fins on his 1958 Cadillac. One evening, some combination of the four showed up on every dish except the chocolate souffle. So it was no surprise, in my eight-course excursion, to see truffle cream surrounding my croustillant of shrimp and langoustine. What was surprising was the espresso-chicory sabayon, looking unfortunately like beach foam, that came with a lovely shell-pink pave of salmon. If the combination sounds strange, I can testify that it tastes even stranger.</p>
        <p>Mr. Woodside regained firmer ground with a pan-roasted pork tenderloin in a red-wine reduction flavored with oxtail. It was one of two entree choices. The alternative was a lobster treated Souvaroff-style, a 19th-century overload preparation here involving morels, chanterelles, spring onions and, surprise! -- truffle cream.</p>
        <p>After the grand tour, it's a short, sweet trip at dessert time. Nicholson limits itself to a few classic souffles, led by a superb but breathtakingly alcoholic apple-Calvados souffle, and old-fashioned pleasers like a poached peach with Champagne sabayon.</p>
        <p>The atmosphere at Nicholson is almost indescribable. Stillness reigns, interrupted only by the gentle creak of the parquet floor, signaling the approach of a waiter, who, in truth, seems less like an employee than a faithful family retainer, just as the restaurant feels a bit like a room in the far west wing of Crotchet Castle. The clientele seems to break down into two groups: neighborhood residents of advanced years (it's been a long time since I've heard an animated conversation about Perle Mesta) and young couples seemingly on their way to a cotillion, if such things exist anymore.</p>
        <p>I have to say, I left Nicholson on each visit with a look of stupefied wonder on my face, and a feeling of regret. It is the one restaurant guaranteed to make the world outside its doors, the mad, mad circus of Manhattan, seem like an absolute bore.</p>
        <p>Nicholson  *  [Rating: one star]  323 East 58th Street; Upper East Side; (212) 355-6769.</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE: Flamboyant French food in an idiosyncratic rococo town-house dining room.</p>
        <p>SOUND LEVEL: Hushed.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES: Endive and Asian pear salad, braised squab with truffle cream, grape tomato salad, lamb carpaccio glazed with mint and basil, navarin of John Dory with fennel froth, poached peach with Champagne sabayon, apple-Calvados souffle.</p>
        <p>SERVICE: Butler-like.</p>
        <p>WINE LIST: A not very interesting list of 60 bottles, most of them French and American, but with some real bargains at the low end.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE: Dinner, four courses, $64; six courses, $78; eight courses, $98 ($135 with matching wines).</p>
        <p>HOURS: Monday through Saturday, 5:30 to 11 p.m.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS: All major cards.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: Entrance is five steps down; restrooms are on dining room level.</p>
        <p>WHAT THE STARS MEAN:</p>
        <p>(None)Poor to satisfactory  *Good  **Very good  ***Excellent  ****Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>Past restaurant reviews from The New York Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics, are available on New York Today:  www.nytoday.com</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
