<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sierra Leone Asks U.N. For Role In War Court</title>
    <meta content="Y21LEO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sierra Leone</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kabbah, Ahmad Tejan (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4D61331F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sierra Leone Asks U.N. For Role In War Court</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, June 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sierra Leone Pres Ahmad Tejan Kabbah asks UN to set up war crimes tribunal to try rebel leaders whose troops maimed and killed residents and abducted 500 international peacekeepers, plunging country into new round of violence in May (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sierra Leone has asked the United Nations to set up a war crimes tribunal to try rebel leaders whose troops maimed and killed Sierra Leoneans and abducted 500 international peacekeepers, plunging the country into a new round of violence in May.</p>
        <p>But the proposed court, as outlined in a letter to Secretary General Kofi Annan from Sierra Leone's president, Ahmad Tejan Kabbah, would be a far cry from an international tribunal of the sort established in the 1990's for the Balkans and Rwanda. Instead, it would be closer to the one now being created for Cambodia's Khmer Rouge, with considerable power in the hands of the national government. Prosecutors and judges would be a mix of Sierra Leoneans and foreigners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sierra Leone has asked the United Nations to set up a war crimes tribunal to try rebel leaders whose troops maimed and killed Sierra Leoneans and abducted 500 international peacekeepers, plunging the country into a new round of violence in May.</p>
        <p>But the proposed court, as outlined in a letter to Secretary General Kofi Annan from Sierra Leone's president, Ahmad Tejan Kabbah, would be a far cry from an international tribunal of the sort established in the 1990's for the Balkans and Rwanda. Instead, it would be closer to the one now being created for Cambodia's Khmer Rouge, with considerable power in the hands of the national government. Prosecutors and judges would be a mix of Sierra Leoneans and foreigners.</p>
        <p>The hybrid court envisioned by Sierra Leone would be based there and limited to hearing cases against only one faction, the Revolutionary United Front of Foday Sankoh. This spring, Mr. Sankoh broke a year-old peace agreement that had given him a role in government and turned his troops on both Mr. Kabbah's army and United Nations peacekeepers. He is now in custody.</p>
        <p>Britain, which sent troops to Sierra Leone last month, helped Sierra Leone draft its proposal for a tribunal, diplomats said today. The court would be established under one of possibly three Security Council resolutions on Sierra Leone to be debated in coming weeks. The other two would impose an embargo on arms sales and diamond exports and enlarge the United Nations peacekeeping force and strengthen its powers.</p>
        <p>Diplomats say the United States originally appeared to want a more international tribunal, but now seemed to be closer to supporting the British-assisted plan outlined by President Kabbah. An American official said that the United States was still far from a decision on the shape of the court.</p>
        <p>At a Security Council meeting today, the American Ambassador,  Richard C. Holbrooke, said that he was against creating a new tribunal for Sierra Leone but that ''some form of extension of the international war crime umbrella to cover these odious people must be undertaken.''</p>
        <p>A copy of President Kabbah's letter and its detailed annex, sent a week ago, was made available to The New York Times by experts outside the United Nations. Officials in the organization would not discuss the plan, saying it is still being studied.</p>
        <p>The limitations on the proposed court's reach and the large role reserved for the weak government and justice system of Sierra Leone raise fears among some international human rights experts, who say numerous factions have been involved in abuses in Sierra Leone, in a war marked by the hacking off of civilians' limbs and the destruction of countless communities.</p>
        <p>''There are two main concerns that we have,'' said Peter Bouckaert of Human Rights Watch, who recently returned from Sierra Leone. ''One is that it deals only with the R.U.F. We think for a tribunal to have any kind of international credibility, it would have to address the criminal responsibility of all sides in the conflict.''</p>
        <p>In addition to the Revolutionary United Front, he said, there are the Armed Forces Revolutionary Council; one of its most violent factions, known as the West Side Boys; and bands of former government soldiers who joined the rebels to attack Freetown, the country's capital, in January 1999 after Mr. Sankoh broke an earlier peace agreement.</p>
        <p>A second concern cited by Mr. Bouckaert was ''the dominant role that Sierra Leone would play in this proposed hybrid court, considering the politicization that would take place and also the limited capacity that the Sierra Leone judiciary has at this stage.''</p>
        <p>President Kabbah said in his letter and annex that a court created by the Security Council would have ''the advantage of strong enforcement powers that will call for cooperation from states in investigations, arrest, extradition and the enforcement of sentence.'' He also asked that it be paid for through an international trust fund.</p>
        <p>Turning to the working of the court, Mr. Kabbah called for a ''narrow'' list of those to be charged from the Revolutionary United Front, possibly in the dozens. He said this would allow the court to be ''quick and efficient.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kabbah asked for a blend of Sierra Leone and international law to be applied in order to include crimes against humanity and crimes against peacekeepers, which are not in the national code. He expected the court to sit in Sierra Leone unless security made it necessary to move elsewhere. It would have West African and possibly other judges. For appeals, the tribunal could make use of an appeals panel in The Hague, which hears cases from the Balkans and Rwanda.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
