<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investors Oppose Breakup of Russia's Electric Monopoly</title>
    <meta content="Y21RUS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Unified Energy Systems</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tavernise, Sabrina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E5D71331F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="694" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investors Oppose Breakup of Russia's Electric Monopoly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SABRINA TAVERNISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tavernise, Sabrina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Group of foreign investors in Russia's electricity monopoly, Unified Energy Systems, has asked Pres Vladimir V Putin to stop corporate restructuring investors say is moving too fast and would destroy value of their holdings; group of 18 investors, representing more than 15 percent of Unified Energy's stock, sends letter to Putin stating that restructuring proposal would reduce future investment levels in energy sector by robbing company of its principal assets at extremely low prices; identities of of all foreign investors that signed letter are not immediately clear (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A group of foreign investors in Russia's electricity monopoly, Unified Energy Systems, has asked President Vladimir V. Putin to stop a corporate restructuring the investors say is moving too fast and would destroy the value of their holdings.</p>
        <p>The group of 18 investors, representing more than 15 percent of Unified Energy's stock, sent a letter to Mr. Putin stating that the restructuring proposal would reduce future investment levels in the energy sector by robbing the company of its principal assets at extremely low prices. The identities of all the foreign investors that signed the letter were not immediately clear. But people who had seen a copy said it included some of the most prominent names in the asset management business -- Morgan Stanley, Merrill Lynch, Templeton and Baring Asset Management.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A group of foreign investors in Russia's electricity monopoly, Unified Energy Systems, has asked President Vladimir V. Putin to stop a corporate restructuring the investors say is moving too fast and would destroy the value of their holdings.</p>
        <p>The group of 18 investors, representing more than 15 percent of Unified Energy's stock, sent a letter to Mr. Putin stating that the restructuring proposal would reduce future investment levels in the energy sector by robbing the company of its principal assets at extremely low prices. The identities of all the foreign investors that signed the letter were not immediately clear. But people who had seen a copy said it included some of the most prominent names in the asset management business -- Morgan Stanley, Merrill Lynch, Templeton and Baring Asset Management.</p>
        <p>Their letter elevates what has been a simmering dispute between foreign investors and the management of Unified Energy, which runs the world's biggest power grid and is the most actively traded Russian stock.</p>
        <p>The restructuring proposal, designed by Anatoly B. Chubais, Unified Energy's chief executive, would break the monopoly into hundreds of smaller companies and sell stakes in them to raise $30 billion in badly needed investment over 10 years. The company said on Monday that it had reworked the proposal and planned to submit the new version to the government on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The restructuring proposal has attracted widespread attention in Russia and abroad as a test case for the country's investment-starved energy sector. Mr. Chubais was the architect of Russia's state asset sales program in which prize companies were sold at bargain prices, and he has championed free market changes and foreign investments in Russia. As recently as last year, Mr. Chubais was a favorite of foreign investors. The foreign investors of Unified Energy even voted to make it more difficult to oust him from the post of chief executive. But now, some Unified Energy investors have joined forces against him, saying they fear a repeat of his asset sales program within their own company.</p>
        <p>''It's a complete mess,'' said Alexander Branis, associate director at Prosperity Capital Management in Moscow, with $140 million under management, a quarter of which is in power companies. ''I doubt that the proposal has changed much. For us it's disturbing that Chubais has admitted that some of our concerns were legitimate but is still pressing ahead.''</p>
        <p>Unified Energy currently holds majority stakes in most of the country's more than 70 regional power companies and more than 30 federal power plants. Investors say breaking regional companies up into distributors, sellers and generators would create companies too small to attract buyers.</p>
        <p>Unified Energy should merge groups of regional companies and later sell stakes in the larger companies, they say. They also contend that Russia must allow electricity prices to rise before Unified Energy's assets will be attractive to serious buyers. Tariffs are still well below production costs, while unpaid electricity bills cripple the finances of the regional companies. Russians pay about 1.5 cents a kilowatt hour for their electricity, while Western Europeans pay about 7 cents.</p>
        <p>Company management and shareholders agree that a restructuring is needed. They argue that aging regional power stations need new equipment and that companies need the ability to charge market prices for electricity and terminate service to nonpayers.</p>
        <p>Unified Energy has said the country will suffer major gaps in power supplies without investments in the next five years.</p>
        <p>Some market watchers said investors must be willing to give up Unified Energy's dominant role. Charles Frank, acting president of the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development, which invests in post-Soviet Russian companies, said last week in St. Petersburg that some of the criticism of Unified Energy's plans was valid, but some was driven by a desire to preserve the company's dominance. The Unified Energy monopoly, he said, ''must be broken soon, without waiting for the perfect regulatory regime or 100 percent tariff collection.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
