<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>5 Men Are Indicted in Attacks On Women in Central Park</title>
    <meta content="21PARK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209166"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puerto Rican Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puerto Ricans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Central Park (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finkelstein, Katherine E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taylor, John (Suspect)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDA1031F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>5 Men Are Indicted in Attacks On Women in Central Park</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHERINE E. FINKELSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finkelstein, Katherine E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manhattan grand jury indicts five young men on charges of rioting and sexually assaulting women in June 11 melee in Central Park after National Puerto Rican Day Parade; John Taylor, sixth man who was arrested last week, is released pending further investigation; police continue to search for 22 more suspects (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Manhattan grand jury yesterday indicted five young men on charges of rioting and sexually assaulting women in the June 11 melee in Central Park after the National Puerto Rican Day Parade.</p>
        <p>But a sixth man who was arrested last week, John Taylor, 24, was not indicted, and the judge waived his $30,000 bail. Mr. Taylor was released, pending further investigation by the grand jury.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Manhattan grand jury yesterday indicted five young men on charges of rioting and sexually assaulting women in the June 11 melee in Central Park after the National Puerto Rican Day Parade.</p>
        <p>But a sixth man who was arrested last week, John Taylor, 24, was not indicted, and the judge waived his $30,000 bail. Mr. Taylor was released, pending further investigation by the grand jury.</p>
        <p>The men appeared in Manhattan Criminal Court in wrinkled T-shirts and baggy jeans, and all but one of them seemed largely subdued after a week spent in the eye of a public storm. They had been arrested after the police offered rewards and released their photographs, taken from amateur videotapes of the melee, in which 53 women say they were attacked.</p>
        <p>The exception was Manuel Vargas, 18, who the police have said was an  instigator. He was identified by at least five victims as having participated in the attacks, the police said. Mr. Vargas grinned as he entered the courtroom of Judge Cynthia Kern and thrust his fist into the air.</p>
        <p>The assistant district attorney, Maxine Rosenthal, said that the grand jury had indicted Mr. Vargas, Stephen Burt, 31, Emanuel Nunez, 18, Roberto Camacho, 16, and Jensen Soto, 16. Mr. Soto did not appear in court. None have posted bail.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rosenthal said another man arrested in the attack and still in custody, Isaias Lozano, 20, of Queens, was not indicted yesterday but would remain in jail pending further investigation by the grand jury.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Taylor, who runs a barber shop near Rockaway Beach in Queens, was let go. When he walked out of the courtroom through the front door, he was embraced by his mother, Patricia, tears coursing down her face, and more than a half-dozen family members.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor, who has said he was involved in a water fight after the parade but not in any of the attacks on women, told reporters that one of the worst moments for him was when his picture was released. ''I thought about all the kids who saw it on TV and all the kids in the community,'' he said. ''I want to clear my name, that's all. Glory be to God.''</p>
        <p>Also yesterday morning, another suspect, Dellon Evans, 17, was arraigned in Manhattan Criminal Court. The police, who said Mr. Evans corralled women into the hands of their attackers, charged him with rioting and sexual abuse. Judge Carol Edmead admonished him for ''encouraging an outrageous act against women,'' and set bail at $50,000. His case will go before the grand jury.  Outside the courtroom, his lawyer, Mitchell Schuman, denounced the amount of the bail, saying it was ''a human sacrifice at the altar of public opinion.''</p>
        <p>The police also announced 2 more arrests yesterday in the attacks, bringing the total to 20. Prosecutors said they expected the others in custody to be indicted within a week.</p>
        <p>The police said they had 22 other suspects -- based on witness accounts and the videotapes -- who had not yet been arrested.</p>
        <p>Late Monday night, Alexander Eraide, 23, of 123-48 135th Street in Queens, surrendered at the 13th Precinct station house in Manhattan and was charged with sexual abuse and rioting, the police said, after callers  identified him from a photograph. The police said that Mr. Eraide, along with four men who have not yet been identified, touched a woman on the buttocks.</p>
        <p>And a 15-year-old boy, whose name and address have been withheld, surrendered with his lawyer and was charged with sexual abuse and rioting. ''There was no picture or video of him,'' Detective George Nagy said.</p>
        <p>Later in the day, Police Commissioner Howard Safir said that the  police were searching for the other suspects. ''The 22 of you know who you are,'' he said. ''I suggest you surrender, because we are going to find you.''</p>
        <p>Marilyn Mode, a Police Department spokeswoman, said the police had obtained a new videotape of the assaults, were isolating photographs from it and expected to release four more pictures today.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
