<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Results at Goldman Sachs Beat Forecasts</title>
    <meta content="Y21GOLD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209110"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Goldman Sachs Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFDE1031F932A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Results at Goldman Sachs Beat Forecasts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Goldman Sachs Group reports 21 percent increase in net income in its fiscal second quarter ended May 26 from year earlier; company earned $755 million; investment banking revenue of $1.59 billion is 29 percent higher than in first quarter, which was Goldman's most profitable since it became public company a year ago, and 59 percent higher than in second quarter of 1999 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Overcoming big paper losses on some of its investments, the Goldman Sachs Group rode its best performance in investment banking to a 21 percent increase in net income in its fiscal second quarter from a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Goldman said yesterday that it had earned $755 million, or $1.48 a diluted share. The profits were as good as analysts had expected before cautious talk from Goldman caused analysts to lower their estimates last month. On May 25, a day before Goldman's quarter ended, the analysts surveyed by First Call/Thomson Financial estimated that the firm would earn $1.47 a diluted share, but by yesterday that projection had dropped to $1.37.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Overcoming big paper losses on some of its investments, the Goldman Sachs Group rode its best performance in investment banking to a 21 percent increase in net income in its fiscal second quarter from a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Goldman said yesterday that it had earned $755 million, or $1.48 a diluted share. The profits were as good as analysts had expected before cautious talk from Goldman caused analysts to lower their estimates last month. On May 25, a day before Goldman's quarter ended, the analysts surveyed by First Call/Thomson Financial estimated that the firm would earn $1.47 a diluted share, but by yesterday that projection had dropped to $1.37.</p>
        <p>The results compared favorably with the pro forma earnings of $1.30 a share Goldman reported last May -- adjusted for the costs of its initial public offering -- but they were 16 percent below the record earnings of $887 million, or $1.76 a diluted share, it recorded in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>Despite the unexpectedly strong earnings, Goldman's share price fell $2.625, to $89 on the New York Stock Exchange, while stocks of some of other securities firms, including Merrill Lynch &amp; Company and Lehman Brothers Holdings, rose 2.5 percent or more.</p>
        <p>''This is the second time that Goldman has reported strong numbers and other firms have rallied,'' said Henry McVey, a Morgan Stanley Dean Witter analyst. Mr. McVey said investors appeared to be hunting for less expensive stocks that would benefit from the same factors that drove Goldman's earnings.</p>
        <p>Investors are also worried that the firm's employees and former partners will flood the market with new shares that they can sell for the first time this week, analysts said. Only about 15 percent of the firm's outstanding shares have been available to trade, Mr. McVey said.</p>
        <p>''People are worried that what gave the stock a huge lift on the way up -- an imbalance of demand and supply -- will start to work against it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Goldman's balance sheet received its biggest boost from underwriting stocks and advising companies on mergers in the United States and, increasingly, in Europe. Its investment banking revenue of $1.59 billion was 29 percent higher than in the first quarter, which was Goldman's most profitable since it became a public company a year ago, and 59 percent higher than in the second quarter of 1999.</p>
        <p>Goldman reaped hefty fees for underwriting huge stock offerings for AT&amp;T Wireless and PetroChina and for advising on acquisitions like British Petroleum's purchase of ARCO and Royal Bank of Scotland's purchase of National Westminster Bank. Goldman ranked first during the quarter as an underwriter of stocks, both global and in the United States,  David Viniar, the firm's chief financial officer, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>''We really dominated that sector completely in the quarter,'' Mr. Viniar said.</p>
        <p>The gains from banking and trading more than offset a sharp drop in the value of Goldman's investments in private companies and companies that have recently gone public. With the sell-off in technology stocks that began in April, the value of those investments fell $321 million in the quarter. Mr. Viniar estimated those markdowns would result in a loss of about 19 cents a share after taxes.</p>
        <p>Much of that loss represents a markdown on paper of unrealized gains that had inflated Goldman's earnings in previous quarters, Mr. Viniar said. Goldman recorded increases in the value of its principal investments of more than $600 million in the previous two quarters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Viniar called that reversal a ''give-back of some of the froth that was in the market.'' Still, he said, Goldman is looking at ''excellent'' returns on all of the investments that it had to mark down last quarter.</p>
        <p>Goldman's trading desks were living in two different worlds: revenue in stock trading rose 76 percent, while revenue from trading bonds, currencies and commodities sank 30 percent from the year earlier.</p>
        <p>The bond markets ''were really just slow,'' Mr. Viniar said, but they have picked up in the last few weeks. ''When we look at the business environment, we think the long-term prospects for our business are as good as they have ever been.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
