<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Microsoft Urges Court to Start on Appeal</title>
    <meta content="Y16SOF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appeals Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brinkley, Joel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE3DA1E3EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Microsoft Urges Court to Start on Appeal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL BRINKLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brinkley, Joel</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Microsoft Corp tells Court of Appeals that judges should ignore government brief asking them not to begin work on company's antitrust appeal until Supreme Court decides whether to take it (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Continuing the battle of the briefs, Microsoft told the Court of Appeals today that the judges should ignore a government brief asking them not to begin work on the company's antitrust appeal until the Supreme Court decided whether to take it.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department, the 19 state attorneys general who are its partners, and the trial judge, Thomas Penfield Jackson, are all working to move Microsoft's appeal directly to the Supreme Court, under an obscure law known as the Expediting Act. But the company wants its case heard first by the Court of Appeals, which ruled in its favor in a previous case.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Continuing the battle of the briefs, Microsoft told the Court of Appeals today that the judges should ignore a government brief asking them not to begin work on the company's antitrust appeal until the Supreme Court decided whether to take it.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department, the 19 state attorneys general who are its partners, and the trial judge, Thomas Penfield Jackson, are all working to move Microsoft's appeal directly to the Supreme Court, under an obscure law known as the Expediting Act. But the company wants its case heard first by the Court of Appeals, which ruled in its favor in a previous case.</p>
        <p>In a 10-page brief filed this afternoon in response to a government filing on Wednesday, Microsoft raised a potentially important argument: it asserted that the states were not covered by the Expediting Act, which allows direct appeal of significant antitrust cases ''in which the United States is the complainant.''</p>
        <p>The Justice Department and the states dispute that interpretation, but all the parties acknowledge that they are debating an unsettled area of the law with no direct precedents.</p>
        <p>Still, if a court rules in Microsoft's favor on this point, it would damage the direct-appeal effort, probably ensuring that the appeal of both federal and state cases would be heard by the Court of Appeals.</p>
        <p>That court has shown it is eager to take the appeal, and most analysts say they believe Microsoft's chances would be better there.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department declined to respond to Microsoft's brief today, though it remains possible -- even likely, given the experience of the last week -- that the department will file its own brief on the subject later.</p>
        <p>But the department has already addressed the issue at length in a brief filed with Judge Jackson on Tuesday. In that brief, and in Microsoft's offering today, both sides extracted isolated moments or statements from the long antitrust trial to support the view that the two cases should or should not remain joined for appeal.</p>
        <p>The state and federal cases were researched and prepared separately but filed jointly and consolidated for trial. On Tuesday, the Justice Department brief noted that at the start of the antitrust trial, Microsoft ''called consolidation 'unquestionably appropriate' because of 'the same factual and legal theories' that 'go to the very heart' of both suits.''</p>
        <p>It added that Judge Jackson ''entered a single findings of fact, a single set of conclusions of law and a single final judgment in the case.''</p>
        <p>But Microsoft's brief notes that the states asked for the right to conduct separate cross-examinations at trial.</p>
        <p>It is not clear which court will settle the debate. But the Court of Appeals may already have its own opinion. When the judges decided on Tuesday that the full court would hear the case, not the usual three-judge panel, they issued two separate orders. One was for the Justice Department, the other for the states.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
