<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Albany Passes Bill on False Abuse Charges</title>
    <meta content="16REGI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Raymond</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE1D81E3EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Albany Passes Bill on False Abuse Charges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND HERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hernandez, Raymond</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, June 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Legislature passes measure to remove names of hundreds of people wrongly accused of child abuse from state registry of suspected abusers; registry, in existence since 1973, contains about one million names (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York State Legislature passed a measure today that would remove the names of hundreds of people who have been wrongly accused of child abuse from a state registry of suspected child abusers.</p>
        <p>The registry has been in existence since 1973, though the information it contains is only available to child abuse investigators, not to the public. It contains the names of about a million individuals accused of child abuse, as well as the names of their victims.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York State Legislature passed a measure today that would remove the names of hundreds of people who have been wrongly accused of child abuse from a state registry of suspected child abusers.</p>
        <p>The registry has been in existence since 1973, though the information it contains is only available to child abuse investigators, not to the public. It contains the names of about a million individuals accused of child abuse, as well as the names of their victims.</p>
        <p>For more than two decades, the names of suspected abusers were removed from the registry when the authorities concluded that the allegations against the suspect were unfounded or determined that there was not enough evidence to substantiate the claim.</p>
        <p>But that changed after the 1995 death of 6-year-old Elisa Izquierdo. The child was killed by her mother, who had repeatedly come to the attention of child welfare workers as a result of allegations of child abuse that were leveled against her.</p>
        <p>Although the mother's name was never on the state list, there was a public outcry resulting from the case, and Gov. George E. Pataki and the Legislature changed the registry rules to prevent unfounded allegations from being expunged until 10 years after the 18th birthday of the youngest child in the alleged abuser's family.</p>
        <p>The measure that was passed today will allow people who were wrongfully accused to get their names removed from the list when they provide ''clear and convincing evidence'' of their innocence.</p>
        <p>In the past, similar proposals have failed because of disagreements about how much proof would be required to remove a person's name from the registry. The new law was sponsored by State Senator Nick Spano, a Republican, and State Assemblyman Richard Brodsky, a Democrat, both of Westchester County.</p>
        <p>The measure was passed in the Assembly this morning; the Senate ratified it Wednesday night. It is expected to be signed into law by Mr. Pataki.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brodsky said the new law would balance the needs of investigators to know as much as they can about a suspect with the rights of the wrongfully accused who want to protect their names. ''We unintentionally created a new class of victims and we're now giving them a chance to get out from under a bureaucratic nightmare that is not of their own making,'' he said. ''I'm only sorry it took this long to do.''</p>
        <p>It is unclear precisely how many people currently on the registry have been wrongfully accused. Mr. Brodsky and other experts estimate that there are at least hundreds. They include Michael and Donna Divon, of Hastings, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, a woman approached Mr. Divon in a grocery store and asked him how his 6-year-old son got a bruise on his face. Mr. Divon explained that the boy, Jonathan, had fallen against a sandbox in the school playground.</p>
        <p>But the woman reported the Divons to the authorities, suspecting child abuse. The allegations were found to be untrue after two teachers said they witnessed Jonathan's accident at the playground. But the Divons were never able to get their names off the registry.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Divon praised the Legislature's action today, saying she and her husband never thought they would be able to clear their names. ''I'm thrilled,'' she said. ''I thought this cloud would never be lifted from our heads. This has been a tough three and a half years.''</p>
        <p>The two houses also passed a bill that would allow the state's Department of Correction to grant work-release to women convicted of killing their spouses or boyfriends, provided that the woman can show that they were being abused by the person they killed.</p>
        <p>State Assemblyman Scott Stringer, a Democrat from Manhattan who sponsored the bill, said there are about 100 such women in state prisons today. He said the legislation is especially important since the state's decision to eliminate parole has meant that these women have no choice but to serve their whole sentences just like other convicted killers.</p>
        <p>''After years of tough-on-crime legislation, this is one of the few times we've moved in the direction of mercy,'' Assemblyman Stringer said. ''These women deserve a second chance at life, at rejoining their families. There's basically no recidivism among women like this.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
