<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Costly Move In Paris, But Typical</title>
    <meta content="16ANTI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207685"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ANTIQUES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moonan, Wendy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rossi, Jean-Marie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE2D7113EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1228" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Costly Move In Paris, But Typical</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Wendy Moonan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moonan, Wendy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Antiques column on Jean-Marie Rossi, well-known Paris antiques dealer who has moved his Aveline gallery to renovated 18th-century house on Place Beauvau; drawing; interview (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Quirky. Eccentric. Self-assured. Amusing. All over the place. Modern. Spontaneous. Competitive. Expensive. Charming. Arrogant.</p>
        <p>These are some of the adjectives people use to describe Jean-Marie Rossi, considered the doyen of Paris antiques dealers. Mr. Rossi is a big man (6-foot-5) with a large personality. After 44 years in business, he recently moved his gallery, Aveline, to the Place Beauvau on Rue du Faubourg Saint-Honore, across the street from the Elysee Palace, the home of the presidents of France.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Quirky. Eccentric. Self-assured. Amusing. All over the place. Modern. Spontaneous. Competitive. Expensive. Charming. Arrogant.</p>
        <p>These are some of the adjectives people use to describe Jean-Marie Rossi, considered the doyen of Paris antiques dealers. Mr. Rossi is a big man (6-foot-5) with a large personality. After 44 years in business, he recently moved his gallery, Aveline, to the Place Beauvau on Rue du Faubourg Saint-Honore, across the street from the Elysee Palace, the home of the presidents of France.</p>
        <p>At great expense, he hired a renowned Paris decorator, Francois-Joseph Graf, to transform two floors of a private house built in 1771 into a large, spacious, light-filled gallery. He then installed the antiques himself, creating vignettes with clever combinations of furniture, paintings, porcelains and objets d'art.</p>
        <p>Moving was an expensive gamble for someone at this stage of his career, but he dismissed such talk. ''I paid for it with one Roy Lichtenstein painting,'' he said. ''I bought 'The Ring' in 1963 for 6,000 francs and sold it for 12 million.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rossi may or may not be the oldest of the great Paris dealers; nor is his taste the most classical. While he is known, as his first wife and current gallery director, Barbara Hottinguer, put it, as an ''extreme connoisseur'' in 18th-century furniture from France, Italy, Germany and Russia, he sells things from many periods, specifically from the time of Louis XIII through the 19th century.</p>
        <p>''I like what's unpredictable -- with life, women, interiors and objects of art,'' said the dealer, who is married to his fourth wife, Marie. ''I like Frank Lloyd Wright and Brancusi. I like whatever is modern for its period. I don't care what century it is as long as it's original.''</p>
        <p>His client list includes Rothschilds, Helene David-Weil, Henry Kravis, the Getty, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Louvre, the Musee d'Orsay and the Toledo Museum of Art. Among the big-name designers who shop at his gallery are David Mlinaric of London; Alberto Pinto, Jacques Garcia and Jacques Grange of Paris and David Easton, Duane Hampton, Juan-Pablo Molyneux and Peter Marino of New York.</p>
        <p>''I also have 40-year-olds buying in the gallery,'' he said. ''Both European and American.'' Mr. Rossi insists that his staff treat everyone with courtesy, so Americans in jeans feel welcome. He does not want the gallery to be intimidating, he said.</p>
        <p>''Rossi is not like other dealers,'' said Tony Victoria, a New York dealer specializing in French antiques. ''He's respected because he puts together modern and antique. He's a flamboyant figure in a staid world. He has flair. He is always putting wild modern stuff like Lucite with 18th-century antiques.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Victoria, who recently opened a second, more modestly priced French antiques shop on Main Street in Bridgehampton, N.Y., added: ''Rossi is no old-fashioned, true-blue, 18th-century-French-furniture dealer, like Jean-Paul Fabre, who is the touchstone of authenticity in Paris. Rossi has a wide intellect, but he's equally known for a sense of humor -- and tongue to match -- which is unknown in this business.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Victoria said his father used to buy from Mr. Rossi's partner, Maurice Aveline. ''When Jean-Marie took over, it got too stratospherically expensive,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rossi does have a reputation for very high prices. He would not disclose them but said he was willing to spend a lot -- perhaps more than anyone else -- for top merchandise. ''Everyone has taste, but good taste costs a fortune today,'' he said. ''It's like wine. If you order the most expensive wine in a restaurant, you normally get the best. In the 1940's and 1950's you could build great collections without a lot of money. Now, unfortunately, you need money. In a way, it's easier when it's expensive. You have less competition.''</p>
        <p>His prices are defended by Leon Dalva, a French furniture dealer in New York. ''There's a small group of us trying to uphold the standard,'' he said. ''We have competed with Rossi at auction, and sometimes we dealers fall in love with a thing and feel we have to have it at any price. People think we always buy cheap and sell dear. It's not true. French furniture from the 18th century is the most beautiful furniture anyone has ever made. It's expensive.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dalva said he admired Mr. Rossi because he also bought ''outlandish, amazing things from the 19th century.''</p>
        <p>''Rossi was the first to buy things of that period,'' he said. ''They were not copies of anything, but real 19th-century originals.''</p>
        <p>Didier Aaron, a Paris dealer who has known Mr. Rossi for over 40 years, said: ''Like me, he buys whatever he likes. It's not work for us; it's a passion. It is not a question of price. If you have good taste, you can buy things from any century or style.''</p>
        <p>Khalil Rizk, director of the Chinese Porcelain Company in New York, said that Mr. Rossi ''is all over the place, but with his eye even normal pieces seem to take on an aura.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rossi also works hard. He is training his 26-year-old daughter, Marella, in the gallery. After receiving a degree in art history at the Sorbonne, studying at the Louvre and at Versailles and taking the Christie's art education course, Ms. Rossi began to work at Aveline a year ago. She has created its Web site (www.Aveline.com).</p>
        <p>''Father goes to Drouot every day,'' she said, referring to the French auction house. ''Last Sunday, he flew to London for a Sotheby's furniture sale preview. Three months ago, he bought 10 percent of the Karl Lagerfeld sale in Monaco.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rossi, the son of a French mother and an Italian immigrant who ran a ball-bearings factory, studied law and was certified as a government notary. It was a gentlemen's profession, but he loved the world of art and antiques more.</p>
        <p>''When I was 25, I asked Maurice Aveline if I could help him,'' he said. ''He was a well-known dealer. I did administration and learned how to restore pieces. Eventually I took over.'' Today, his inventory is unpredictable. Most classic, perhaps, is a Louis XVI architect's table stamped by G. Jacob, one of the best names in 18th-century French furniture. The deceptively plain mahogany table has a top that tilts up to form a writing surface. The top is supported by several slim columns designed to hold oversize portfolios. Some columns have garlands of olive leaves carved on them. The table looks modern enough for a SoHo loft.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, there are a pair of German commodes from about 1770, highly ornamented, from a chateau in the Duchy of Limbourg. The demilune commodes are creamy white and decorated with gilded Corinthian capitals, medaillons, portraits and trellis work. They are as dazzling as anything from Pavlosk Palace outside St. Petersburg.</p>
        <p>He also has a very tall, revolving Japanese bookcase made for the World's Fair in 1867. The columns are faux bamboo wood decorated with bronze Japanese dragons. ''It would have been the most modern thing at the fair,'' Mr. Rossi said.</p>
        <p>ANTIQUES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
