<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Page Floats, Transformed</title>
    <meta content="16SCOT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207678"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A O</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E1D8113EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2177" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Page Floats, Transformed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A O</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A O Scott Critic's Notebook comment on film adaptations of works of fiction; notes that giants of postmodernism have erected prose pyramids so intricate as to defy replication while, at same time, American movies still seem to languish under tyranny of story; photos of movie scenes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Apart from the luster of borrowed seriousness, what literature most often provides the movies is access to a deep and self-replenishing reservoir of stories. Film and the novel are cousins not far removed, and the DNA they share is narrative. But their narrative codes -- owing partly to obvious differences of media, partly to their divergent histories -- have grown further and further apart. After several generations of fervid experimentation, the flouting of storytelling norms has become, among ambitious fiction writers, a convention in itself.</p>
        <p>While it would be a distortion to say that the rise of the movies as a parallel and competing art form has been the cause, the signature effects of postmodern fiction -- recursive language games; self-conscious, unreliable and multiple narrative voices; Mobius-strip skeins of allusion and parody, sincerity and irony -- seem almost flagrant in their defiance of cinematic appropriation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Apart from the luster of borrowed seriousness, what literature most often provides the movies is access to a deep and self-replenishing reservoir of stories. Film and the novel are cousins not far removed, and the DNA they share is narrative. But their narrative codes -- owing partly to obvious differences of media, partly to their divergent histories -- have grown further and further apart. After several generations of fervid experimentation, the flouting of storytelling norms has become, among ambitious fiction writers, a convention in itself.</p>
        <p>While it would be a distortion to say that the rise of the movies as a parallel and competing art form has been the cause, the signature effects of postmodern fiction -- recursive language games; self-conscious, unreliable and multiple narrative voices; Mobius-strip skeins of allusion and parody, sincerity and irony -- seem almost flagrant in their defiance of cinematic appropriation.</p>
        <p>The giants of postmodernism -- William Gaddis, Thomas Pynchon, Don DeLillo -- have erected pyramids of prose so intricate in their conceits and so saturated with references as to defy replication altogether. Their most recognizable progeny carry on this resistance. Can you picture the 1,100 pages of David Foster Wallace's ''Infinite Jest,'' with its 400 footnotes and uncountable subplots, on the screen?</p>
        <p>At the same time, American movies seem, perhaps more than ever, to languish under the tyranny of story, a regime with its own bureaucratic jargon. Aspiring screenwriters are schooled in the dogma of ''three-act structure,'' ''character arcs'' and ''through-lines.'' The average Hollywood product, confined within iron boundaries of genre and subjected to the killing discipline of test marketing, arrives in theaters overstuffed with incident, whipsawed by the need for suspense and predictable from start to finish.</p>
        <p>It is hardly surprising, then, that a handful of restless and independent-minded filmmakers have turned to contemporary fiction for relief, as though envious of the liberties writers have claimed for themselves -- the freedom to meander, to proliferate loose ends, to think out loud. Alison Maclean's ''Jesus' Son,'' opening in New York today, is the latest in a series of intriguing efforts to translate the words of particularly idiosyncratic writers into the visual and aural idioms of film.  Like Sofia Coppola's ''Virgin Suicides,'' Bette Gordon's ''Luminous Motion,'' Mary Harron's ''American Psycho'' and Stephen Frears's ''High Fidelity,'' ''Jesus' Son'' is at once a tribute to its source and a bold refashioning of it, an attempt to preserve the author's style and to advance the director's vision in a single gesture.</p>
        <p>In some ways, Ms. Maclean is doggedly faithful to her source, a slim volume of resonant, anecdotal stories by Denis Johnson. The book is held together by his shuffling, soulful, absent-minded hero, a young man adrift in a landscape of drugs, sad women and surreal jobs. Mr. Johnson's lean, wry prose infiltrates the film's soundtrack through dialogue and voice-over, and some of his descriptive passages are reproduced with meticulous obedience, as though they were architectural drawings.</p>
        <p>But reading ''Jesus' Son,'' you wonder how its spare, half-mumbled vignettes and loopy, hipster jokes could sustain the flesh-and-blood realism of a movie. The supporting characters, not all of whom are named, seem like interchangeable apparitions from a jumbled series of acid flashbacks, and the book as a whole is like a long conversation with a voluble, not entirely sane or sober companion on a cross-country bus trip.</p>
        <p>The book's resonance and humor seem to dwell between the lines, in the capacity of Mr. Johnson's artful prose -- and prose in general -- to be at once more abstract and more sensual than film, however ingenious, can ever hope to be. Language is able to track the stutterings of consciousness, the bleeding together of thought and sensation, the dislocated experience of time, by the simplest and most efficient of means. Poetry, Robert Frost said, is what gets lost in translation, and a corollary might be that prose is what disappears before your eyes.</p>
        <p>Consider a typical passage from ''Jesus' Son'': ''Or maybe that wasn't the time it snowed. Maybe it was the time we slept in the truck and I rolled over on the bunnies and flattened them. It doesn't matter. What's important for me to remember now is that early the next morning the snow was melted off the windshield and the daylight woke me up. A mist covered everything and, with the sunshine, was beginning to grow sharp and strange. The bunnies weren't a problem yet, or they'd already been a problem and were already forgotten, and there was nothing on my mind. I felt the beauty of the morning.''</p>
        <p>In a hundred words, Mr. Johnson evokes several distinct states of feeling, jumps backward, forward and sideways in time, and leaps with careless grace from the narrator's inner world to the world outside. The camera may be able to approximate some of these effects, or convey, through the alchemical interactions of light on the landscape and the human face, a faint equivalent of them. But never with this kind of effortless, off-the-cuff efficiency.</p>
        <p>Or consider another passage, a kiss from Jeffrey Eugenides's ''Virgin Suicides'' that is stranger, truer, and far more vividly icky than even the most splendidly backlighted classic-Hollywood smooch:</p>
        <p>''He could sense her whole being through the kiss, he said, as though her soul escaped through her lips, as the Renaissance believed. He tasted first the grease of her Chap Stick, then the sad Brussels-sprout flavor of her last meal, and past that the dust of lost afternoons and the salt of tear ducts. The peach schnapps faded away as he sampled the juices of her inner organs, all slightly acidic with woe.''</p>
        <p>If this seems overdone, it's purposely so, since Mr. Eugenides's theme is obsessive longing, to the point, precisely, of this kind of lunacy, which teenage boys are capable of when confronted with the unfathomable reality of teenage girls.</p>
        <p>''The Virgin Suicides,'' published in 1993, is a lyrical meditation on death, loss and the suburbs, filtered through the collective consciousness of an anonymous group of young men. Its central event is signaled by the title and spelled out in the first sentence, so that its story plays out to the melancholic rhythms of longing. The sense of mystery that pervades the book is sustained by its lush, obsessive style. As in ''Jesus' Son,'' its most striking feature is its voice.</p>
        <p>The same might be said of Scott Bradfield's ''History of Luminous Motion,'' Nick Hornby's ''High Fidelity,'' and even Bret Easton Ellis's aggressively styleless, brutally misunderstood ''American Psycho.'' This is not just a matter of style, which all good writers possess, but of the sometimes excessive application of style to the creation of a seamless subjective reality. The way the narrators address the reader -- intimate, formal, conversational, but above all palpably artificial -- is also, in each case, a way of making the world strange, of rendering the familiar, forgettable details of childhood, family life, popular culture and urban consumer capitalism outlandish and disturbing.</p>
        <p>In ''The History of Luminous Motion'' Phillip -- an 8-year-old boy who accompanies his mother from town to town and man to man in a beat-up car crammed with textbooks, stolen credit cards and strange mementos -- has the vocabulary and philosophical acuity of a graduate student, as well as an ability to interpret his own life with curious detachment.</p>
        <p>''In order to grow and learn,'' he observes, ''we must permit the world to betray itself.'' The voice we hear in the novel, of course, is not the voice of an actual child, any more than the ''we'' who relates the doom of the Lisbon sisters in ''The Virgin Suicides'' is a literal chorus of wishful Michigan schoolboys. These voices are rather representations of consciousness: what the characters might say if they could.</p>
        <p>But in movies, what we hear is what people do say, even if only to us, out of earshot of the other characters. The shortest, roughest route from the page to the screen is the voice-over, a device that has gone from rarity to near-ubiquity.</p>
        <p>''The Virgin Suicides'' distills the mournful voice of the novel's collective narrator into the unseen person of Giovanni Ribisi. Phillip's prickly, precocious thoughts in ''Luminous Motion'' are channeled through the squeaky voice of Eric Lloyd, the cute, pudgy-faced actor enlisted to play this murderous, possibly psychotic character. ''American Psycho'' rings the most daring change on this convention by turning the novel's long, turgid parodies of rock criticism into spoken preludes to murder, addressed by Patrick Bateman to his uncomprehending victims.</p>
        <p>The voices that echo in our heads are not like the ones that echo in the darkness of a movie theater. The reliance on voice-over as a convenient preservative erases this difference and reduces the literary to the literal. Who talks that way? Why would he say that? What's that supposed to mean?</p>
        <p>Or, most treacherously, Why doesn't he just shut up? That question is brazenly risked by ''High Fidelity,'' which transfers large tracts of Mr. Hornby's novel directly into the mouth of John Cusack, ironing out its Britishisms to suit Mr. Cusack's amiable Midwestern delivery. The movie beautifully captures the riffing, digressive energy of Mr. Hornby's prose, and of all the films discussed here it's perhaps the most shapely and satisfying.</p>
        <p>But also the least daring. Its story, after all, hews to one of the top five movie plots: a self-centered, basically decent guy confronts his self-centeredness, affirming his basic decency and thus meriting the love of the woman he had driven away. Like the novel, the movie restricts itself entirely to that guy's point of view, and most of the film's action consists of Mr. Cusack speaking into the camera directly to us, obstructing our view of what the other characters might be doing.</p>
        <p>''High Fidelity'' thus manages to be engaging without quite being a movie; it's more like a staged reading of the novel, with some interesting visual illustrations and a soundtrack to die for.</p>
        <p>''High Fidelity,'' like the other books mentioned, is narrated by a young -- or at least not quite mature -- man, and its subject, buried under the flash and noise of rock 'n' roll, is the way young men think about women. It's a curious coincidence (and a sign of welcome and overdue, if tenuous, change) that the directors of ''The Virgin Suicides,'' ''American Psycho,'' ''Luminous Motion,'' and ''Jesus' Son'' are women, who have staked the development of their own distinctive styles on bringing studies in male narcissism to the screen and then quietly, respectfully but pointedly subverting them.</p>
        <p>In all of these books, women -- the star-crossed Lisbon sisters in ''The Virgin Suicides,'' the alcoholic mother in ''The History of Luminous Motion,'' the barely differentiated wives and girlfriends in ''Jesus' Son,'' and the victims in ''American Psycho'' -- are visible only through the distorting lens of male self-regard. They are objects of longing, rage and need, but never selves in their own right with autonomous interior lives, fears and desires. But the transformative magic of movies is that characters who on the page may be ciphers, icons or fantasies are permitted to come alive as embodied persons.</p>
        <p>Readers of ''Jesus' Son'' may be stunned to find that Michelle, a character whose abortion figures in one of the stories and about whom we never learn much more, has become Samantha Morton, whose noble, fearless performance gives the movie an emotional depth and coherence not found in the book.</p>
        <p>And the remorseless self-obsession of Patrick Batemen in ''American Psycho'' is brilliantly undermined, in Ms. Harron's sharply satiric rendering of the book, by Cara  Seymour as the prostitute who grasps, perhaps better than the audience does, what Patrick is about. Deborah Kara Unger in ''Luminous Motion'' and Kirsten Dunst in ''The Virgin Suicides'' provide those movies with similar emotional gravity and intelligence.</p>
        <p>None of these films are perfect. All of them have the rough edges of worthwhile experiments pursued with discipline and imagination. Their imperfections make them interesting and suggest new permutations in the long relationship between literature and cinema. In the end it may not be possible to make such odd and challenging books into movies, but Ms. Harron, Ms. Coppola, Ms. Gordon and Ms. Maclean have nonetheless transformed them into novels.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
