<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Said to Sidestep a Sticking Point in Talk With Arafat</title>
    <meta content="Y16PREX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E3D91E3EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Said to Sidestep a Sticking Point in Talk With Arafat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton meets with Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat at White House to try to set stage for three-way summit meeting in Washington with Israeli Prime Min Ehud Barak; administration official says Clinton and Arafat are paying particular attention to proposed borders for a Palestinian state but have sidestepped issue of Israel's final withdrawal from West Bank; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton met with the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, for an unusually long session at the White House today to try to set the stage for a summit meeting here, but they did not resolve one of the immediate obstacles to convening the meeting, a senior administration official said.</p>
        <p>Even so, efforts by the administration to get the summit meeting off the ground are expected to accelerate in the coming days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton met with the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, for an unusually long session at the White House today to try to set the stage for a summit meeting here, but they did not resolve one of the immediate obstacles to convening the meeting, a senior administration official said.</p>
        <p>Even so, efforts by the administration to get the summit meeting off the ground are expected to accelerate in the coming days.</p>
        <p>The official said negotiations between Palestinian and Israeli officials now under way in Washington would continue for the next few days. The administration's senior envoy, Dennis Ross, will fly to the region next week and Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright will go in 10 days to assess whether a summit meeting is feasible, the official said.</p>
        <p>The Israeli prime minister, Ehud Barak, is reported to want the three-way summit meeting -- Mr. Barak, Mr. Arafat and Mr. Clinton as mediator -- soon after July 4, a timetable that also dovetails with Mr. Clinton's need to hold a meeting before the presidential election season gets under way in earnest.</p>
        <p>During their more than three hours together today, Mr. Clinton and Mr. Arafat dwelled on all the major issues of a final peace accord, paying particular attention to the proposed borders for a Palestinian state, the official said.</p>
        <p>There was little discussion, he said, of Mr. Arafat's insistence that the Israeli government proceed with the final withdrawal from land on the West Bank called for in the Oslo accords of seven years ago. Mr. Arafat has threatened that if the Israelis fail to make the final pullout, which would give the Palestinians more than 80 percent of the territory on the West Bank, he would refuse to go ahead with a summit meeting.</p>
        <p>It appeared from the account by the senior administration official that Mr. Clinton decided to defuse that immediate issue by putting it to one side.</p>
        <p>''We didn't try to move him off it,'' the official said, adding that the withdrawal remained ''very important'' to Mr. Arafat.</p>
        <p>The Palestinian leader publicly kept up the pressure, saying as he emerged from the White House that Mr. Barak was unwilling to do what he had promised.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Barak up to this moment lacks a desire to work with us in order to achieve a comprehensive lasting peace in the region,'' Mr. Arafat said. He singled out the slow rate of release of Palestinian prisoners from Israeli jails. The Palestinian leader said that Mr. Barak was offering to free only three prisoners. ''That's an insult,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Clinton administration officials have sounded notes of guarded optimism and then slight pessimism in the last two weeks as they have concentrated on pushing the Israelis and the Palestinians close enough on the issues to merit a summit meeting for a peace agreement.</p>
        <p>In Lisbon two weeks ago, Mr. Clinton said that a summit meeting was ''in view'' but made clear that substantial progress was needed to narrow the gaps on the vital issues of the shape of a Palestinian state, the future of refugees and the status of Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>One thing the White House does not want is a summit meeting that collapses. ''For a date for a summit we have to be in a position to have at least a reasonable chance to reach bridging solutions,'' the senior official said today.</p>
        <p>At the moment, the official said, the two leaders are not yet prepared to make the necessary decisions on the big issues, and the talks between the negotiating teams have not yet played out.</p>
        <p>The administration's choreography for bringing the summit meeting together includes a three-pronged approach: the Palestinian-Israeli talks now in progress in Washington, involving senior officials from both sides; visits by Dr. Albright to the region; and one-on-one sessions of Mr. Clinton with Mr. Barak and with Mr. Arafat.</p>
        <p>Essentially, the session at the White House today appeared to focus on Mr. Clinton's sounding out Mr. Arafat on what ground he was willing to give and what Mr. Arafat needed from Mr. Barak to make a summit meeting work.</p>
        <p>But a fundamental tension has infused the efforts since Mr. Clinton, while in Lisbon, announced his desire for a summit meeting, Israeli and Palestinian officials said.</p>
        <p>On the Israeli side, ''there is a feeling that Arafat wants more without giving,'' one official said.</p>
        <p>On the Palestinian side, there is an intense frustration, a Palestinian official said. Israel has threatened that if the Palestinians reject its request to postpone the final pullout, it will stick to a decision of the government of Benjamin Netanyahu and give up only one percent of the West Bank.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
