<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SEOUL CELEBRATES DAWN OF 'NEW DAY' AS TALKS CONCLUDE</title>
    <meta content="16KORE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207779"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE KOREAN BREAKTHROUGH -- THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">South Korea-International Relations-North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">French, Howard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kim Dae Jung (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kim Jong Il</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boucher, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3D61E3EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1225" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SEOUL CELEBRATES DAWN OF 'NEW DAY' AS TALKS CONCLUDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">French, Howard W</byline>
      <dateline>SEOUL, South Korea, June 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>In a triumphant return home from his summit meeting with North Korea, Pres Kim Dae Jung tells jubilant South Koreans that 'a new day is beginning' for their divided people; Kim also tries to calm concerns in United States and Japan that security issues were ignored during his talks with Kim Jong Il, saying they had frank discussions on sensitive security issues, including North's nuclear and missile programs as well as US military presence in South; accord, which produced a common agenda for reconciliation, is widely praised, notably by Japan, China and Russia; United States is considerably more guarded in its praise, with State Department spokesman Richard Boucher citing continued threat from North Korea's long-range ballistic missile program; photos of the two leaders embracing and of luncheon that concluded summit, where participants joined hands to sing 'Our Wish Is Unification' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a triumphant return home from his summit meeting with North Korea, President Kim Dae Jung told jubilant South Koreans today that ''a new day is beginning'' for their divided people.</p>
        <p>''When I was in Pyongyang, I realized Pyongyang is our land,'' Mr. Kim said in an address at the airport as he returned from three days of talks with his North Korean counterpart, Kim Jong Il. ''People in Pyongyang are our people. And they have deep-rooted love for their southern compatriots.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a triumphant return home from his summit meeting with North Korea, President Kim Dae Jung told jubilant South Koreans today that ''a new day is beginning'' for their divided people.</p>
        <p>''When I was in Pyongyang, I realized Pyongyang is our land,'' Mr. Kim said in an address at the airport as he returned from three days of talks with his North Korean counterpart, Kim Jong Il. ''People in Pyongyang are our people. And they have deep-rooted love for their southern compatriots.</p>
        <p>''We are at the juncture of opening a new chapter in our history, putting an end to 55 years of division and hostility,'' he told the thousands of children and officials who turned out to give him a hero's welcome, much of it orchestrated by the government.</p>
        <p>After the speech, the president's motorcade drove past cheering crowds, as tens of thousands of colorful balloons were released into the skies over downtown Seoul. As the limousines moved through the city, many South Koreans sang ''Our Wish Is Unification,'' a song popular on both sides of the heavily fortified border between the two countries.  Earlier in the day, the two leaders also sang the song at a lavish banquet while joining hands.</p>
        <p>Upon arriving home, the South Korean leader tried to calm concerns among his allies in Washington and Tokyo that security issues had been ignored during the talks. During his speech at the airport, Kim Dae Jung said that he and Kim Jong Il had indeed had frank discussions on sensitive security issues, including the North's nuclear and missile programs as well as the 37,000 American soldiers stationed in the South.</p>
        <p>Kim Dae Jung did not describe in detail what he and the North Korean leader had said about the security matters, which were not mentioned in their final agreement signed on Wednesday. He only said their talks had been frank and productive.</p>
        <p>The accord, which produced a common agenda for national reconciliation and -- theoretically -- eventual reunification, will of course face many obstacles before it is implemented. Still, the agreement was widely praised today.</p>
        <p>''As in the case of the collapse of the Berlin Wall, the agreement constitutes a major change toward peace,'' said Japan's prime minister, Yoshiro Mori.</p>
        <p>China, North Korea's one remaining true ally, also hailed the accord in unusually strong terms.</p>
        <p>But the United States, which has continued to station troops in South Korea to defend against an attack from the North, was considerably more guarded in its praise.</p>
        <p>''Certainly a reduction in tensions is important, but on the specific issue of possible missile threats, I haven't seen nor heard of anything in the summit that negates that,'' said Richard Boucher, the State Department spokesman. The Clinton administration, citing the potential threat from North Korea's long-range ballistic missile program, has proposed developing an antimissile shield to guard against what it considers ''rogue states'' like North Korea, Iran and Iraq.</p>
        <p>But the Russian Foreign Ministry strongly praised the outcome of the talks. The two Koreas ''will have to do a great deal of difficult work to overcome the mutual prejudice and mistrust that had been accumulating for decades,'' a ministry statement said. ''Russia intends to make an active contribution to this process.''  And, in fact, President Vladimir V. Putin is to make the first visit by a Russian president to North Korea this year, probably in July.</p>
        <p>The accord also included agreements on family reunions and the repatriation of Communist prisoners, and a pledge not to engage in offensive military operations against each other. And the accord covered other things as well, like rail connections, hot lines between leaders, offices in each other's capitals and joint economic projects.</p>
        <p>While the two countries have agreed to many things in the past, it has never been done at the level of a summit meeting -- and never with such apparent good will.</p>
        <p>Beginning with a surprise greeting of the South Korean president at the Pyongyang airport by the 58-year-old Kim Jong Il, the meetings between the two men seemed to evolve into a rolling, emotional getting-to-know- you party. So warm were the currents between them by the end that the two men embraced firmly on the tarmac just before Kim Dae Jung boarded his return flight home.</p>
        <p>Despite the goodwill, hard questions over the implementation of the agreement are expected to emerge in the coming days. But few here seem likely to forget the extraordinary distance traveled in the short time since secret talks began between the two sides in Beijing in March. So completely had their history of war and hostile ideologies separated them, in fact, that even the Korean language they both use had evolved in ways that made it difficult to draft talking papers.</p>
        <p>''It is so exciting that I am sort of floating right now,'' said Chang Ching Wee, a political scientist at Yonsei University in Seoul. ''It is difficult to think.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Chang quickly grew sober and spoke of the difficult work ahead that would be required to transform the diplomatic feats of Pyongyang into lasting political achievements. ''It will take time and continuous effort to implement what these two gentlemen have agreed upon,'' he said. ''Everyone is excited because this was so unexpected, but there will be surely be difficulties ahead.''</p>
        <p>South Korean officials speaking off the record, and others who watch relations between the two Koreas closely say that a rough sequence of events has been outlined, and that many of the ideas emerged in draft form in six or more secret talks held before the summit meeting.</p>
        <p>''It would be wrong to look at what just happened as ceremonial,'' said one senior South Korean official. ''But many points were worked on beforehand.''</p>
        <p>The official said that as a confidence-building measure, North Korea would allow dramatic reunions for a symbolic but significant number of the nearly two million South Korean families that have lost contact with their relatives in the North since the end of the Korean War.</p>
        <p>The South, meanwhile, will extend millions of dollars' worth of financial assistance to the North, whose collapsing barter economy has suffered repeated setbacks in the last decade.</p>
        <p>Only after these steps have been taken will serious talks begin on security issues, and a path be cleared for a visit to Seoul by Kim Jong Il, which is seen as an important gauge here of his commitment to progress.</p>
        <p>Many experts said there were reasons to hope that the self-assured performance of the previously little known Kim Jong Il during the summit would encourage further confidence building and moderation.</p>
        <p>Leon V. Sigal, a North Korea expert at the Social Science Research Council in New York, said, ''All this speaks of a lot of self-confidence which may mean they are ready to begin doing things a bit differently.''</p>
        <p>THE KOREAN BREAKTHROUGH -- THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
