<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foes Hone Strategy for Web Copyright Clash</title>
    <meta content="Y16MUSI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207742"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Napster (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Recording Industry Assn of America</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richtel, Matt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boles, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E5DA1E3EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="627" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foes Hone Strategy for Web Copyright Clash</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT RICHTEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richtel, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, June 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Napster, an Internet music start-up, and recording industry sharpen their legal strategies in battle with potentially broad implications for copyright law in Internet era; moves are punctuated by Napster's disclosure that it is hiring David Boles, Justice Department's special counsel in antitrust case against Microsoft Corp; legal maneuvering is precursor to July 26 hearing in federal court in San Francisco in case that many see as landmark for unresolved Internet and technology-era copyright issues; Recording Industry Association of America argues that court should stop Napster from operating pending outcome of trial; brief says Napster is contributing to growing and irreparable harm to commerical music industry (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Napster, an Internet music start-up, and the recording industry sharpened their legal strategies this week in a battle with potentially broad implications for copyright law in the Internet era. The moves were punctuated by Napster's disclosure today that it is hiring the lawyer who led the government's case against Microsoft.</p>
        <p>The legal maneuvering is a precursor to a July 26 hearing in federal court in San Francisco in a case that many see as a landmark for unresolved Internet and technology-era copyright issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Napster, an Internet music start-up, and the recording industry sharpened their legal strategies this week in a battle with potentially broad implications for copyright law in the Internet era. The moves were punctuated by Napster's disclosure today that it is hiring the lawyer who led the government's case against Microsoft.</p>
        <p>The legal maneuvering is a precursor to a July 26 hearing in federal court in San Francisco in a case that many see as a landmark for unresolved Internet and technology-era copyright issues.</p>
        <p>In a brief filed late Monday, the Recording Industry Association of America, which represents major record labels, argued that the court should stop Napster from operating pending the outcome of the trial. The brief said Napster is contributing to growing and irreparable harm to the commercial music industry.</p>
        <p>Napster, based in San Mateo, Calif., responded today, saying it had hired David Boies, the Justice Department's special counsel in the antirust case against Microsoft.</p>
        <p>''This is an obviously important case,'' Mr. Boies said in an interview today, explaining his decision to work with Napster. ''People are focusing on the music, but it's a case that raises broader policy issues and legal issues'' about copyright law on the Internet.</p>
        <p>Napster makes software that can be used to share music files over the Internet.</p>
        <p>Napster asked Chief Judge Marilyn Patel of the United States District Court for the Northern District of California to reject the industry association's suit, but on May 8 the judge denied the request, setting the stage for the case to be heard.</p>
        <p>The association brief filed Monday said ''over 10 million Napster users are sharing tens of millions of copyrighted files.'' The brief says Napster is guilty of contributing to copyright infringement because it knows of and profits from the practice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boies acknowledged today that the recording industry might have a point, though he said studies on the issue were inconclusive.</p>
        <p>In its brief this week, the association cited a survey it commissioned by the Field Research Corporation, a San Francisco-based research firm, that stated 22 percent of Napster users said that because of Napster, they did not buy CD's any more or they buy fewer CD's.</p>
        <p>A study by the Digital Media Association released this week stated, however, that 59 percent of people who download or play music over the Internet said the activity led them to purchase music later.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boies said that the case would turn in part on whether the individual Napster users were violating copyright law and he said Napster would argue they were not.</p>
        <p>Rather, he said that Napster users are participating on a grand scale in behavior that is widely accepted on a smaller scale today. For instance, he said that individuals would not be sued for copyright infringement for making a copy of a song or a television movie for a friend.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boies said he would argue that if the users of Napster were not guilty of copyright infringement, then Napster itself could not be held accountable for abetting copyright infringement.</p>
        <p>The recording association argues, however, that the behavior of Napster users is not legal.</p>
        <p>''Whether or not it is lawful for users to share music one on one, on a small scale, there can be no question it is unlawful when done on a large scale, as with Napster,'' said Cary Sherman, general counsel for the association.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
