<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Whole Lotta Shakin': Just What He Was Lookin' For</title>
    <meta content="16TVWK$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207701"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV WEEKEND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arts &amp; Entertainment Network</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dutton, Charles S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wertheimer, Ron</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Phillips, Sam</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Deadlocked (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sam Phillips: The Man Who Invented Rock 'n' Roll (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Biography (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E5DF1E3EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1164" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Whole Lotta Shakin': Just What He Was Lookin' For</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ron Wertheimer</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wertheimer, Ron</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ron Wertheimer TV Weekend reviews A&amp;E Biography program Sam Phillips: The Man Who Invented Rock 'n' Roll; photos; also reviews TNT movie Deadlocked starring Charles S Dutton (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The photograph, taken in 1956, is an icon of American pop music history. Four young men are gathered around a piano in a simple recording studio. Struggle, success and bitter disappointment lay ahead for all of them. At that moment, though, they shared raw talent, buckets of hope and Sam Phillips.</p>
        <p>Mr. Phillips -- just out of camera range that night in his Sun Records studio in Memphis -- had orchestrated the publicity shot just as he had organized the early careers of the four young men: Jerry Lee Lewis, Carl Perkins, Johnny Cash and Elvis Presley. By 1956 Elvis had already graduated from Mr. Phillips's limited orbit, as the others were soon to do.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The photograph, taken in 1956, is an icon of American pop music history. Four young men are gathered around a piano in a simple recording studio. Struggle, success and bitter disappointment lay ahead for all of them. At that moment, though, they shared raw talent, buckets of hope and Sam Phillips.</p>
        <p>Mr. Phillips -- just out of camera range that night in his Sun Records studio in Memphis -- had orchestrated the publicity shot just as he had organized the early careers of the four young men: Jerry Lee Lewis, Carl Perkins, Johnny Cash and Elvis Presley. By 1956 Elvis had already graduated from Mr. Phillips's limited orbit, as the others were soon to do.</p>
        <p>Perkins, the biggest Sun star of that moment, had been making a record that day, with Mr. Lewis playing backup piano. When Elvis dropped by, Mr. Phillips, ever the quick-thinking promoter, first summoned Mr. Cash, then called a newspaper, requesting a photographer and reporter, who dubbed the group the Million-Dollar Quartet.</p>
        <p>It was just a moment, four men noodling around with songs they all knew, hymns mostly. Then, like Mr. Phillips's time of great influence, it was over. But that time is worth remembering. And it's done so well in the documentary ''Sam Phillips: The Man Who Invented Rock 'n' Roll,'' which A&amp;E is offering on Sunday night under its ''Biography'' banner.</p>
        <p>The film -- written by the rock historian Peter Guralnick and directed by Morgan Neville -- is filled with the sounds of Mr. Phillips's America: generous samples of gospel, country music and early rock. And it's filled with the sound of Mr. Phillips, still going strong and looking amazingly youthful well into his 70's. ''Nobody knows more about sound than me,'' he proclaims.</p>
        <p>In 1950, at age 27, Mr. Phillips, an Alabama native who had become a Memphis radio personality, opened his studio as a sideline. He began recording black Southern musicians, including the bluesmen B. B. King and Howlin' Wolf, for established record companies. A group called Jackie Brentson and His Delta Cats, including a young Ike Turner on piano, brought Mr. Phillips a hard-driving rhythm tune called ''Rocket 88.''</p>
        <p>''Boy, was that what I was looking for,'' Mr. Phillips says, recalling how he marveled at ''the force that was in that thing.'' Today ''Rocket 88'' is widely regarded as the first rock 'n' roll record. Mr. Phillips may not have invented it, but he had the sense to package it, and soon he was selling it under his own label, too.</p>
        <p>Among the first Sun hits was ''Just Walking in the Rain'' (1953), recorded by Johnny Bragg and the Prisonaires, inmates at the Tennessee State Penitentiary. (The tune was later covered by white artists like Johnnie Ray.) The scene of the hulking Mr. Bragg, standing now in the rusting ruins of his old cellblock singing his song with an expression of ultimate bliss, is unforgettable.</p>
        <p>Everything changed -- everything -- in '53 when a 19-year-old Elvis Presley walked into the Sun studio asking to make a record as a birthday gift for his mother. Mr. Phillips's employees told the boss about this ''white boy with a Negro sound.'' You know the rest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Phillips began promoting other white artists, Roy Orbison and Charlie Rich among them. But there was only one Elvis, and after releasing his first five records, Mr. Phillips released Elvis, selling his contract to RCA for $35,000. His canny investments set him up for life. But his moment was over. Today he runs a string of radio stations and happily wallows in the role of rock patriarch.</p>
        <p>The film assembles a roster of performers and former staff members, all of whom say they're glad their lives were touched by the ebullient Mr. Phillips. ''I kind of think of Memphis as the Emerald City,'' says Jack Clement, a Sun producer, ''the Emerald City of rock 'n' roll at least. And that could make Sam the Wizard of Oz.''</p>
        <p>DEADLOCKED  TNT, Sunday night at 8</p>
        <p>''Deadlocked'' gives Charles S. Dutton a chance to build a head of steam, progressing from regret to anger to a rage of Vesuvian proportions. He takes the viewer with him on this journey, and if he is lustily chewing the scenery by the film's climax, you may be ready to offer him another helping. Although nothing else in the production is quite up to the level of Mr. Dutton's affecting performance, the drama succeeds, at least by the flexible standards of the made-for-television movie.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dutton plays Jacob Doyle, a retired corrections officer whose son, Demond (Jo D. Jonz), has just been convicted of a brutal rape and murder. Ned Stark (David Caruso) successfully prosecuted the case, but that took no particular effort. The white victim was found dead in her husband's office; DNA tests showed that she had had sex with Demond, a black former gang member and petty criminal, who refuses to say a word in his own defense.</p>
        <p>The final matter of business before the jury is consideration of the death penalty. Jacob has come to court to beg for his son's life, maintaining, despite the evidence, that Demond is the victim of a system that discriminates by race and class. Jacob starts meekly, but when he realizes the futility of his words, he pulls out two pistols and starts firing. His ear bleeding from a court officer's return fire, Jacob herds Demond, the jurors and the dead woman's husband into the jury room and demands to see Ned.</p>
        <p>When Jacob declares to Ned, ''I'm the father that made the boy you convicted,'' Mr. Dutton manages to make Jacob an overwhelmingly sympathetic character. When he gives Ned 24 hours to find evidence that will free Demond, and Ned agrees, you can't help rooting for them.</p>
        <p>When the film, directed by Michael Watkins from a script by David Rosenfelt and Erik Jendresen, moves beyond the unbearably tense jury room, it sometimes feels like an episode of some generic crime series. The latter part of the story depends on some turns that you will probably see coming, even as they test credibility to the breaking point. And the plot's overwrought conclusion is the kind of smokescreen that covers a hasty retreat. Still, Mr. Dutton leaves you satisfied, even after the smoke clears.</p>
        <p>BIOGRAPHY  Sam Phillips: The Man Who Invented Rock 'n' Roll  A&amp;E, Sunday night at 8</p>
        <p>Written by Peter Guralnick and directed by Morgan Neville. Mr. Neville and Mr. Guralnick producers; Andrew Tilles, supervising producer; Helen Hood Scheer, associate producer; Shaun Peterson, editor; Craig W. Spirko, director of photography. Produced for A&amp;E by Peter Jones Productions. Peter Jones and Jerry Schilling, executive producers; CarolAnne Dolan, A&amp;E executive producer; Billy Bob Thornton, narrator.</p>
        <p>TV WEEKEND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
