<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Only in a Water Fight, A Park Suspect Says</title>
    <meta content="16SUSP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puerto Rican Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Central Park (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taylor, John (Defendant)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershaw, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2DE1F3EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Only in a Water Fight, A Park Suspect Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH KERSHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershaw, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Taylor, 25, one of several men arrested in abuse of women in Central Park after New York's Puerto Rican Day parade, says he was involved only in water fight (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Taylor was watching the basketball finals at his barber shop at an apartment complex in the Rockaways on Wednesday when newscasters interrupted the game to report that the police were releasing the photographs of seven men sought in Sunday's melee in Central Park, his family said.</p>
        <p>The camera zoomed in on the photographs, gleaned from amateur videotape, and there were two of Mr. Taylor, 25. One was a close-up of his face, showing him in a red cap. The other showed his left arm, bearing a large tattoo of a crucifix with ''Work hard, pray hard,'' scrawled around the cross.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Taylor was watching the basketball finals at his barber shop at an apartment complex in the Rockaways on Wednesday when newscasters interrupted the game to report that the police were releasing the photographs of seven men sought in Sunday's melee in Central Park, his family said.</p>
        <p>The camera zoomed in on the photographs, gleaned from amateur videotape, and there were two of Mr. Taylor, 25. One was a close-up of his face, showing him in a red cap. The other showed his left arm, bearing a large tattoo of a crucifix with ''Work hard, pray hard,'' scrawled around the cross.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor was arrested and charged yesterday with first-degree sexual abuse and was being held last night pending his arraignment. He said in an interview from the 13th Precinct in Manhattan that he had played no role in the melee.</p>
        <p>''I saw my face on the news,'' he said, adding that he had been planning to go to the police yesterday, after seeing himself on the news, because he knew he should step forward.</p>
        <p>But the police got to him first, arresting him early yesterday morning. Their strategy of releasing the photographs and offering a reward for any information on the identity of the men had netted a tip from someone who recognized Mr. Taylor and gave detectives the address of his mother, Patricia Taylor, who lives in Ocean Village, the same apartment complex as he does, in the Arverne section of Queens.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor gave a brief account of what happened at the parade on Sunday. He said he saw some girls being groped but that he was involved only in what he described as ''an innocent water fight that got out of hand.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor said that as the scene around him grew wilder, he told his friends, ''Somebody's going to get arrested, let's get out of here.' And sure enough, that's what happened.''</p>
        <p>Terri Christopher, 15, who lives at Ocean Village and has known Mr. Taylor for several years, said that she and about 40 others from the complex, including Mr. Taylor, had attended the parade together. She said she was standing near Mr. Taylor when men started pouring water on women, and that she saw someone videotape Mr. Taylor as he raised his tattooed arm over his head. ''The only thing we saw him do was pour water on one girl,'' she said. ''He didn't touch her or anything, and she laughed.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor, who grew up in Ocean Village, a blocklong complex that stretches from Edgemere Avenue to Rockaway Beach, and graduated from Beach Channel High School, is well known in the community. He has run a small barber shop in the complex for several years, called GQ Cuts, and he often helps his mother, the president of the tenants association, organize barbecues for children, his friends and relatives said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor has also been a model, and his photograph has appeared in magazines and on billboards in an advertisement for Enyce, a record label and urban apparel line.</p>
        <p>In his mother's living room is an enlarged and framed photograph of the ad, which features Mr. Taylor and four clones of him, sharply dressed and wearing sunglasses. In the same room, on the coffee table yesterday, was The Daily News, which pictured Mr. Taylor, along with the other suspects, on the front page under the headline ''WANTED.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
