<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y16BRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207715"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE0DD1E3EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CANADA: GUN LAW UPHELD  The Supreme Court has unanimously upheld the nation's gun control law, which is stricter than United States gun laws. Rejecting a challenge by 2 of Canada's territories and 6 of its 10 provinces, the court upheld the 1995 Firearms Act, which requires the licensing of all of Canada's gun owners by the end of this year and the registration of all guns by the end of 2002. Firearms owners had largely boycotted the licensing process, awaiting the outcome of the court challenge.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CANADA: GUN LAW UPHELD  The Supreme Court has unanimously upheld the nation's gun control law, which is stricter than United States gun laws. Rejecting a challenge by 2 of Canada's territories and 6 of its 10 provinces, the court upheld the 1995 Firearms Act, which requires the licensing of all of Canada's gun owners by the end of this year and the registration of all guns by the end of 2002. Firearms owners had largely boycotted the licensing process, awaiting the outcome of the court challenge.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>CANADA: POVERTY-PROTEST CLASHES  Anti-poverty protesters fought with the police outside the Ontario legislature in Toronto. Several people were injured and at least three were arrested. Protesting the austerity policies of Ontario's Conservative government, demonstrators, some obscuring their faces with bandannas, gas masks or helmets, attacked the police with rocks, bricks and paint bombs. The police responded with pepper spray and horseback charges.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>MEXICO: EXITS RACE  Porfirio Munoz Ledo, one of Mexico's six presidential candidates, formally withdrew from the race to throw his support behind the leading opposition contender, Vicente Fox. Mr. Munoz Ledo, a onetime leader of the governing party, helped found Mexico's largest leftist party in 1989, but was running this year as the nominee of the tiny Authentic Party of the Mexican Revolution.</p>
        <p>Sam Dillon (NYT)</p>
        <p>SURINAME, GUYANA: OIL DISPUTE  The two South American neighbors faced an impasse over which country owns an offshore oil concession at the center of a renewed century-old territorial dispute. Surinamese patrol boats evicted a rig owned by a Canadian company from the concession awarded by Guyana in 1998 off South America's northeast shoulder. The two sides held talks in Guyana's capital, Georgetown, and will convene again tomorrow and Sunday in Suriname. But they appeared to have made little headway.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: HEROIN DEATHS  Officials investigating the deaths of 35 heroin addicts in England, Scotland and Ireland said the cause was a strain of clostridium, a bacterium usually found in soil or dirt. The clostridium strain, known as Clostridium novyi Type A, is well known as a cause of severe infection in farm animals and can lead to a bovine illness known as Black Disease, which kills off flesh, turning it black. It rarely infects humans.</p>
        <p>Sarah Lyall (NYT)</p>
        <p>KOSOVO: ARMS SEIZED  British and other troops made a major raid in an Albanian stronghold, seizing a large quantity of weapons and ammunition. The operation follows an upsurge in attacks by ethnic Albanians against Serbs. The house-to-house search began at dawn in a 58-square-mile area in the Drenica region, the heartland of the Kosovo Liberation Army, which fought the Serbs until NATO's bombardment of Yugoslavia last year.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>FRANCE: BARDOT CONVICTED  Brigitte Bardot was found guilty of inciting ''discrimination, hatred or racial violence'' for criticizing a Muslim festival in which sheep are slaughtered, and she was ordered to pay fines and damages of $7,150. The actress and animal rights activist lamented in her 1999 book, ''Pluto's Square,'' that ''my country, France, my homeland, my land is again invaded by an overpopulation of foreigners, especially Muslims.'' Miss Bardot was convicted for similar remarks in 1996.</p>
        <p>Suzanne Daley (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>PAKISTAN: TAX AMNESTY EXTENDED  The government has extended by two weeks a tax amnesty plan that, according to Finance Minister Shaukat Aziz, has already led errant taxpayers to declare $96 million in assets. Less than 1 percent of the country's people pay any income tax, and the military government has declared that such evasion must cease if Pakistan is ever to climb out of debt.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFGHANISTAN: DROUGHT RELIEF  Trying to reach drought victims in the remote northern province of Jowzjan, the United Nations World Food Program is using 700 donkeys to deliver 130 tons of wheat through rugged mountain terrain.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>IRAN: NEW VOTES SET  The second round of elections for two of Tehran's seats in Parliament will take place June 30, more than four months after the first round of voting, Iranian television said. All four candidates for the seats are reformers allied with President Mohammed Khatami. Reformists and their allies hold 210 of the 265 seats whose elections have been finalized.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>IRAQ: WEST ACCUSED  Baghdad said Western aircraft had attacked northern Iraq using ''flare bombs'' intended to burn crops and civilian installations. The official Iraqi News Agency, quoting a military spokesman, said planes flew over the provinces of Duhouk, Arbil and Nineveh and dropped four flare bombs on civilian areas in Nineveh Province. It reported no casualties. There was no immediate confirmation of the raids from the United States or Britain.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>SOUTH AFRICA: U.S. TALKS  Treasury Secretary Lawrence H. Summers, who is traveling through Africa, met with his counterparts from several southern African nations in Pretoria to talk about poverty, debt relief and the effects of health problems like AIDS on the region's economies. Mr. Summers, who stopped in Nigeria and Tanzania before arriving in South Africa, will also visit Mozambique and Egypt.</p>
        <p>Henri E. Cauvin (NYT)</p>
        <p>WESTERN SAHARA: POLISARIO TALKS  A United Nations mediator, James A. Baker III, will convene a second round of talks between Morocco and Polisario Front rebels on June 28 and 29 in London in a bid to end a deadlock over the disputed territory of Western Sahara. A long-delayed United Nations plan calls for a referendum to decide whether the former Spanish colony should be part of Morocco or become independent, as called for by the Algeria-based Polisario Front.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
