<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Facing Elimination, Pacers Face Long List of What-Ifs</title>
    <meta content="16PACE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207741"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E5DA1E3EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="957" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Facing Elimination, Pacers Face Long List of What-Ifs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, June 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Indiana Pacers, facing elimination for NBA title, vow to halt Los Angeles Lakers (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has been a place of advantage all season long, a place where hardly anyone wins besides the Indiana Pacers. So how odd it would be for the Los Angeles Lakers to hug and dance while wearing championship caps amid the throwback features of Conseco Fieldhouse.</p>
        <p>The Pacers, down by three games to one in the four-of-seven-game National Basketball Association finals, claim they will not let that happen, that there will be no Lakers' celebration at all, let alone on their beloved floor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has been a place of advantage all season long, a place where hardly anyone wins besides the Indiana Pacers. So how odd it would be for the Los Angeles Lakers to hug and dance while wearing championship caps amid the throwback features of Conseco Fieldhouse.</p>
        <p>The Pacers, down by three games to one in the four-of-seven-game National Basketball Association finals, claim they will not let that happen, that there will be no Lakers' celebration at all, let alone on their beloved floor.</p>
        <p>''We can't have that,'' Indiana forward Jalen Rose said. ''We've got to find a way to play with force and not let them celebrate on our home court.''</p>
        <p>While almost no one except for the Pacers' players, coaches and fans thought Indiana would win this series, the Lakers' coronation is now all but inevitable. No team has recovered from a 3-1 deficit to win a championship, and if the Lakers stumble Friday in Game 5, they will have two chances to make amends at home in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Even so, the Pacers, at least on the surface, remain optimistic, convinced that they will shock the basketball world.</p>
        <p>''It's not going to be easy, but at the same time I don't think it's going to be as hard as it's made out to be,'' said Mark Jackson, Indiana's point guard. ''It's going to be a difficult task, but one that we can accomplish.''</p>
        <p>But if the Pacers did not win Game 4, how will they manage to defeat the Lakers even twice in a row?</p>
        <p>Indiana played a terrific game Wednesday on its home floor, and still left disappointed. The Pacers foiled the best defense in the league, shooting 50 percent from the field and scoring 118 points. They hit 10 of 19 3-pointers and 24 of 28 free throws. Though beaten badly on the offensive backboards, the Pacers stayed nearly even off the glass over all, grabbing only three fewer rebounds than the Lakers. And Indiana got 24 points from center Rik Smits.</p>
        <p>''We shot the ball extremely well from the field, from the 3-point line, the free-throw line,'' Indiana Coach Larry Bird said. ''It's very disappointing to lose a game when you shoot that well. We felt we played very well. We just lost the ballgame.''</p>
        <p>Reggie Miller, who had done slight damage to his reputation for great clutch play by going 0 for 7 in the fourth quarters of the first three games, was phenomenal in Game 4, making 6 of 9 3-pointers in scoring 35 points, including 19 after the third quarter. But he missed a potentially game-winning 3-pointer in the final seconds of overtime, and admitted that he will wonder about the way things went.</p>
        <p>''There were a lot of what-ifs, personally for myself,'' Miller said.</p>
        <p>Three moves by the Pacers can be second-guessed.</p>
        <p>First, there was Miller's decision to shoot a 3-pointer instead of a 2-pointer with Indiana trailing by 120-118 with 5.9 seconds left in overtime. Shaquille O'Neal was on the bench after fouling out, so why didn't the Pacers try to take their chances in a second overtime?</p>
        <p>''I'm not so much worried about the shot because I had a great look at it,'' said Miller, who had to arc the ball higher than usual to get it over the outstretched arms of the 6-foot-10-inch Robert Horry. ''But I was talking to Mark in the back, wondering if we should have went for 2 or not. But with 5.9 seconds left and the play we ran, that's not enough time to get a 2 off. If we're going to lose, I want to lose with me shooting.''</p>
        <p>Before that, Travis Best shot a 15-foot airball with three seconds to play in regulation and the score tied.</p>
        <p>Why was Best shooting the ball instead of Miller or Rose? The Pacers inbounded the ball to Best with 17 seconds remaining and he pounded his dribble for 14 seconds. There was time to attempt to get the ball to Miller, but Bird liked Best's matchup against O'Neal, who had switched onto him off a pick.</p>
        <p>''I liked what I'd seen when Shaq was on him,'' Bird said. ''He was trying to make a move. Shaq was backing up. He had a look at the basket, just didn't make it.''</p>
        <p>Then there was the issue of Smits's absence in the fourth quarter. All series long the Pacers talked about needing to get more production out of Smits, who averaged just 7.3 points and 4.3 rebounds through the first three games. He hit 11 of 14 shots Wednesday night, only to be benched the entire fourth quarter. The strategy was to play Sam Perkins and let him hack Shaq. Perkins committed four fouls in the quarter, and O'Neal made 6 of 11 free throws. When Smits went back into the game during overtime, he scored 8 points. Would the outcome have been different if Smits, who finished with four fouls, had played in the fourth?</p>
        <p>All but over the cliff, the Pacers said it is futile to ponder what might have been.</p>
        <p>''There's no time to worry about that,'' Jackson said. ''If you dwell on that, then this thing could be over with.''</p>
        <p>Even in Conseco.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>TRAVIS BEST is questionable for Friday's game with a sprained left shoulder. He injured himself while falling after flagrantly fouling SHAQUILLE O'NEAL during Game 4.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
