<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dazzling Flash, Reflected at Last Upon History</title>
    <meta content="16SMIT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207675"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Souza Cardoso, Amedeo (d1918)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Roberta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E5D8113EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1605" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dazzling Flash, Reflected at Last Upon History</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Roberta</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roberta Smith reviews AXA Gallery's show of work of Amedeo de Souza Cardoso, Portuguese Modernist painter who died during 1918 influenza epidemic, month before his 31st birthday; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Modernism may or may not be over, but that hasn't kept historians from adding names to its roster. With more and more names from more parts of the world, it is at last being defined as a multinational, multicultural phenomenon, which it always was.</p>
        <p>One of the latest additions is the Portuguese painter Amedeo de Souza Cardoso, who arrived in Paris in 1906 on his 19th birthday, drank the elixir of the new and in a very short period produced a little newness of his own.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Modernism may or may not be over, but that hasn't kept historians from adding names to its roster. With more and more names from more parts of the world, it is at last being defined as a multinational, multicultural phenomenon, which it always was.</p>
        <p>One of the latest additions is the Portuguese painter Amedeo de Souza Cardoso, who arrived in Paris in 1906 on his 19th birthday, drank the elixir of the new and in a very short period produced a little newness of his own.</p>
        <p>Souza Cardoso loved Paris and probably would have spent most of his life there, but World War I began while he was on a visit home, and Portugal's neutrality barred him from re-entering France. And his work might have remained more visible if he had not died during the worldwide influenza epidemic of 1918, a month shy of his 31st birthday and just two weeks before the Armistice that would have allowed him to return to Paris.</p>
        <p>But over the last few decades Souza Cardoso's achievement has gradually resurfaced, first in Portugal, where he is by now something of a national treasure, and then in the rest of Europe. Now it is being seen in the United States in its first solo exhibition, a show of works borrowed primarily from the Gulbenkian Museum in Lisbon and organized by the Corcoran Gallery of Art in Washington and Portugal's Culture Ministry. By some serendipity of scheduling, a New York stop has been added, at the AXA Gallery in Manhattan, the space formerly known as the Equitable Gallery.</p>
        <p>Both the show and its catalog (the first of Souza Cardoso's work to be published in English) were overseen by Jack Cowart, formerly deputy director and chief curator of the Corcoran, now executive director of the Roy Lichtenstein Foundation. After opening there last fall, the show traveled to the Arts Club in Chicago, a natural choice, as that city is the only place in the United States where paintings by Souza Cardoso can be seen. The Art Institute owns three, all from the bequest of Arthur Jerome Eddy, one of the first American collectors of 20th-century art, who purchased them from the 1913 Armory Show. Two of the Chicago paintings are in this exhibition.</p>
        <p>It is an exciting show, exemplary of the dropped-from-the-sky genre of retrospective. It has only 49 paintings and drawings, but it reveals an artist who imbued nearly everything he touched with a distinct sense of emotional and formal concentration.</p>
        <p>The works reveal Souza Cardoso to be a master draftsman whose earlier drawings imitate the sharp black and white of modern woodcuts and elaborate the landscapes of his childhood into manic, revved-up patterns. His later drawings are so hyper-refined, they suggest Ingres high on Cubism.</p>
        <p>But the show also introduces an artist who was equally gripped by painting as a physical process, one whose last Cubist works, created in Portugal during the war, are unusual for their robust color, solid visual structure, compartmentalized space and extensive use of physical texture and collage. Resplendent in the show's final gallery, these works don't present a single object seen from multiple viewpoints in the manner of orthodox Cubism. Instead they present a kind of cultural continuum that mixes objects, abstract motifs, bits of Portuguese folk art and stenciled words and numbers.</p>
        <p>These works in particular earn Souza Cardoso a place among an array of talented outsiders who journeyed from the margins to the heart of modernism, took what they needed and combined it with elements that reflected their own personal and cultural roots. His American counterparts include Marsden Hartley, Gerald Murphy and Stuart Davis.</p>
        <p>Souza Cardoso's story suggests a confident self-starter of the first order. Photographs show that he had Picasso's dark Iberian looks, only more handsome, and a similarly solid, energetic physique and combative attitude. He almost invariably looks straight into the lens. In one photograph he stands with his legs apart, like a young boxer. In another he poses with friends, bare chested, a brocade bedspread across his lap, a crown of flowers on his head. The group is supposed to be imitating Velasquez's ''Borrachos,'' but he looks like something straight out of Carravaggio.</p>
        <p>In a third, his eyes smolder beneath the rim of a big, dark fedora while he caresses a guitar. Not only did he know how to play, but according to a label in the exhibition he also accompanied himself while singing fado songs for friends in cafes. Occasionally he wore a magnificent Alentejo cape, possibly the only one is Paris, which was worn in his country only by noblemen.</p>
        <p>The son of wealthy vintners, Souza Cardoso grew up on the family estate in Manhufe, near Armarante in northern Portugal. He showed an early talent for drawing. After studying architecture in Lisbon he persuaded his parents to send him to Paris. Within a year he had forsaken architecture for painting, by far the livelier art of the moment. (Cezanne's paintings were seen for the first time in the Salon d'Automne of 1907.) Over the next few years he studied painting at the Academie Viti, submitted to what he referred to as ''French artistic imperialism'' and ventured far beyond the circle of Portuguese artists who had been his first companions in Paris.</p>
        <p>He became friends with Brancusi, Archipenko, Diego Rivera, Apollinaire and especially Modigliani, with whom he staged a joint exhibition in 1911. By then Souza Cardoso had already shown his work in the Salon des Independants. He would show there again in 1912 and 1914, as well as in the Salon d'Automne.</p>
        <p>The current show begins with works made in 1911; they reflect attention to the stylization of Art Nouveau and the ''primitivism'' of Henri Rousseau. The most striking work in the first gallery is ''Leap of the Rabbit,'' which depicts the animal suspended over a cluster of tropical plants like a fish in an aquarium. Everything about this painting conveys effortlessness and ease: the lightly worked surface, the outlined flowers above, the odd little colored discs below (early hints of the influence of Delaunay's Orphism) and other touches of color, the rabbit's startled masklike face and the body-paint patterns of its body.</p>
        <p>Little else in Souza Cardoso's work is quite so relaxed. Nearly everything seems packed, almost tightly wound, as if he was determined to get the most out of every inch of available surface. His maniacally patterned landscapes seem to presage Art Deco as much as they reflect the influence of Art Nouveau. Sometimes they are the settings for exotic hunting scenes, as in ''The Tiger''; sometimes for cavorting nudes that suggest an awareness of Picasso's ''Demoiselles d'Avignon.''</p>
        <p>Best of all is a drawing of an aristocratic couple standing in a garden. The encroaching plant life elaborates the male of the species, who already wears wildly checked jodhpurs, into a kind of peacock.</p>
        <p>In the show's middle section, Souza Cardoso comes to grips with Cubism and Futurism, usually buoyed by Delaunay's strong colors. At times Souza Cardoso resurrects antiquated themes that evoke his Portuguese heritage, depicting a cavalier and a prince mounted for the hunt in pale paintings that look a little like tapestries.</p>
        <p>But in ''Abstract Composition'' (1913), probably one of the earliest completely nonrepresentational paintings of the 20th century, he reduces the world to transparent spheres of radiant color. He then applies this scheme to ''Don Quixote,'' a large 1914 painting in which the spheres tumble and spin, curving down toward the strange red and black eyes and masklike face of the patient steed Rocinante, who drinks water from a stream.</p>
        <p>In a small horizontal abstraction from 1913 Souza Cardoso flattens the Cubist grid and extends it almost to the edges of the canvas, creating a shadowy nocturnal space that he livens up with red and white.</p>
        <p>It's not clear how he got from these Cubist variations to the commanding works in the last gallery, with their carefully deployed planes of color, their textural variety and their surprising additions, like the Johnsian stenciled letters and little bits of mirror. Perhaps distance from his beloved Paris actually helped, or he benefited from continued contact with the Delaunays, who spent most of the war in Portugal.</p>
        <p>But especially in works like ''Entrada'' and ''Painting,'' styles, spaces and objects seem to break down into a kind of superbly controlled chaos held in suspension, like the wall-eyed rabbits of Souza Cardoso's early paintings and drawings. Call these last works post-Cubist. They show an artist working ahead of his time, moving toward a future that he would never reach.</p>
        <p>''At the Edge: A Portuguese Futurist -- Amadeo de Souza Cardoso'' is at the AXA Gallery, 787 Seventh Avenue, at 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 554-1704, through Sept. 16.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
