<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oh, It's Not What It Used to Be</title>
    <meta content="16BOWE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bowery (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brawarsky, Sandee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EEDA113EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2114" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oh, It's Not What It Used to Be</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANDEE BRAWARSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brawarsky, Sandee</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sandee Brawarsky article on Bowery past and present as it wends northward from Chinatown to Cooper Square above Houston Street; photos; map; Bouwerie country road to Peter Stuyvesant's farm in New Amsterdam became entertainment center in 19th century, flophouse district in 20th, and is being rejuvenated in 21st (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bowery is nobody's idea of paradise. But when the aging buildings and their fire escapes shimmer in the morning light, it's a place of urban beauty, alluring like an Edward Hopper painting. Its flat facades, with their mismatched colors and styles and uneven heights, create an eclectic backdrop for a glimpse of what the city might have been like the last time the century turned. The Bowery deserves better than its skid row connotations.</p>
        <p>Long shadowed by the Third Avenue El until it was torn down in 1955, the Bowery now has remarkable light. The width of the street and the low buildings on either side create an airiness unusual in Manhattan. Looking north, there's a clear vista of the skyscrapers in Midtown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bowery is nobody's idea of paradise. But when the aging buildings and their fire escapes shimmer in the morning light, it's a place of urban beauty, alluring like an Edward Hopper painting. Its flat facades, with their mismatched colors and styles and uneven heights, create an eclectic backdrop for a glimpse of what the city might have been like the last time the century turned. The Bowery deserves better than its skid row connotations.</p>
        <p>Long shadowed by the Third Avenue El until it was torn down in 1955, the Bowery now has remarkable light. The width of the street and the low buildings on either side create an airiness unusual in Manhattan. Looking north, there's a clear vista of the skyscrapers in Midtown.</p>
        <p>Once a grand boulevard, the mile-long stretch from Chatham Square to Cooper Square is a street of many incarnations. Ever-changing, it's still home to a shrinking population of men living in its remaining lodging houses where daily rent can begin at $5 or $10 for a cubicle. Increasingly, the Bowery's residents are people living in renovated lofts on sites that might once have been music halls or dime museums. Commercially, a new wave of immigrants makes its mark, alongside some longstanding family businesses.</p>
        <p>There are three distinct Boweries: Chinatown, at the southern boundary; the blocks from Grand to Houston Street, dominated by shops selling lighting fixtures and equipment for stores and restaurants, where sunlight bounces off stainless steel sinks and pizza ovens displayed on the sidewalk; and the northern end, above Houston Street, which is as close as the Bowery gets to being hip, with El Sur, the street's first new cafe, at the corner of Bleecker, and across the way, at 315 Bowery, CBGB's, a club where the punk rock and new wave movements flourished in the 70's. At one new restaurant, a glass of wine costs $7 -- not much value for the more typical Bowery consumer, whose drink of choice remains Wild Irish Rose, $2 a pint at one of two liquor stores left on the street.</p>
        <p>Early mornings, the Bowery wakes up energetically. At the 237 Grand Restaurant, most recently a Jewish-style cafeteria called Moishe's, diners huddle over breakfasts of noodles and other specialties. All along the Bowery, merchants are lifting the heavy gates over their storefronts, as truckers hurl supplies onto the sidewalk. At the corner of Delancey Street, people do tai chi on a rooftop. Across Delancey, someone is scrubbing down an oven, preparing it for resale, and a few men sweep the sidewalks. No one seems to notice when a man with silver lame pants and no shirt dashes by, his thick mane of black hair flying behind him.</p>
        <p>I remember the days when morning began all day long on the Bowery, when men would find sunny plots of sidewalks for napping, brown paper bags at their side. As a child, I'd often visit my father's business, and the only way to get to the entrance was to step over several sleeping men. My sisters and I would sit in the front window on bar stools, waving to passers-by and to the men as they woke up. My father knew most of them. One gent named Bill the Sailor, who had stars tattooed on his forehead, would always tip his hat.</p>
        <p>A few of the Old Guard are still around, but most are long gone. In the days before political correctness, we didn't think twice about calling them bums. From the late 1800's, the Bowery was their capital; it was home to people who had no place else to go. Some worked, some were decorated war veterans, some chose life amid the camaraderie of men and the bottle. But by the 1970's, we no longer had to climb over bodies on the pavement. Flop-houses were closing and many of the men left the area. Still, at No. 227 near Prince Street, the Bowery Mission continues, after more than a century, to offer aid as well as shelter to those in need of it. Along with a few nearby lodging houses it is a reminder of a down-and-out past that is quickly fading. A friend who has lived on the Bowery for almost 30 years misses the days of having 50 doormen -- when they weren't asleep in his doorway -- watching out for him and his children.</p>
        <p>Now, I enjoy wandering along the Bowery, and it's the buildings and their stories that most interest me. Little is marked, so connecting present and past is a combination of rumor and research. Passing by commercial sites once occupied by H &amp; S Raynor's Bowery Circulating Library at No. 76 (circa 1820), the Pig and Whistle Tavern at No. 131 (late 1700's) and Hammacher Schlemmer's hardware store, between Delancey and Rivington Streets at No. 209 (1859-1926), I have the impulses of an archaeologist, curious about how these sites reveal layers of history and, at the same time, hide secrets.</p>
        <p>Older than New York City, the Bowery dates back to the time when Lower Manhattan was a Dutch colony, and Gov. Peter Stuyvesant built a country estate, or farm -- bouwerie in Dutch, sometimes spelled bowerij -- in what was then the suburbs, at about what is now Sixth Street, in the 1650's. A road named De Bouwerie  linked New Amsterdam and his farm, following an old Indian trail. Along the road were other farms, Dutch cottages and an occasional tavern; engravings of the scene at the time show a country lane lined with tall poplars.</p>
        <p>That part of Bowery history is mostly invisible now, other than the names; the DeLanceys owned much of the farmland east of the Bowery, the Bayards to the west. The farms were parceled off to become shops and homes, some quite elegant, and the Bowery was a fashionable stretch in the first decades of the 19th century.</p>
        <p>The Bowery's history unfolds in the evolution of a plot of land. South of what is now Canal Street, on the site of a cattle market connected to the Bull's Head Tavern, the neo-classical Bowery Theater was built in the 1820's. Then the largest theater in the country, it was the first in New York to be gaslit. Its 1826 opening production was ''The Road to Ruin,'' which many later said was prescient of its future, for the theater burned down six times and was rebuilt five times. The final fire was in 1929, and by then it had been renamed the Thalia, showcasing Yiddish, German, Italian, and Chinese theater. Now in its place are Chinese restaurants.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1800's, the city's theatrical life centered on the Bowery. The first stage version of ''Uncle Tom's Cabin'' opened at the National Theater, No. 104, in 1852, between Hester and Grand Streets, although serious theater gave way to melodrama, vaudeville, circus acts, minstrel and variety shows. Theatrics reigned inside and outside the theaters: the Bowery was an ongoing carnival. Crowded with trolleys and pedestrians, pushcarts, organ grinders and chestnut sellers, the street was lively late into the night, illuminated by streetlights and, after 1878, with the lights of the elevated train.</p>
        <p>A working-class haven, the street was lined with pawnshops, pool halls, used book stores barber schools, tattoo parlors and black-eye fixers, hotels of all kinds and missions to save residents from its vices. A German section, Kleindeutschland, served the large immigrant population in its beer gardens and theaters. Beggars worked the street, and a couple of blind men were known to regain their sight nightly after some whisky.</p>
        <p>Much has been written about the Bowery boys -- or b'hoys, in their dialect -- picturesque 19th-century characters who walked with a swagger, dressed colorfully and welcomed a good fight. I wonder about the women of the Bowery. A 1904 play, ''Strenuous Mame: The Bowery Girl: A Vaudeville Cocktail,'' is about a tough-talking, gum-chewing aspiring actress whose speech is as colorful as a Bowery b'hoy's. No doubt she would have gotten the hook, which presumably first came into use at Miner's Bowery Theater, No. 167, on its ''Amateur Nights'' in the 1880's.</p>
        <p>Today on the Bowery the tallest building -- other than the 1970's Confucius Plaza in Chatham Square -- is the 10-story Salvation Army Chinatown Corps, No. 225, near Rivington Street; most are three or four stories. Three buildings have landmark status. At No. 18, around 1789, the merchant Edward Mooney built a three-story Georgian-influenced house, at what is now the corner of Pell Street, that's Manhattan's oldest surviving town house and the Bowery's oldest building. Later it was a tavern, then was rumored to be a brothel, and more recently it became an O.T.B. office and the headquarters of Summit Associates.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most ornate structure is No. 330, the Bouwerie Lane Theater, at the corner of Bond Street, housed in an 1873 Italianate cast iron former bank. At No. 130, a monumental temple of a bank near Grand Street that gives the Bowery a bit of grandeur, was built in 1894 as the Bowery Savings Bank by McKim Mead &amp; White. While it has since changed hands, it is still popularly known by its original name, which can be seen on the building's facade. Another bank giving the Bowery a certain stature -- in its palmy days, the avenue was a commercial strip as well as a raffish one -- is the majestic pile of the former Germania Bank, now a private residence, whose gray opulance graces the northwest corner of Spring Street.</p>
        <p>Another structure of architectural and historical note is now occupied by the Hong Kong Shanghai Banking Corporation, No. 58, at the corner of Canal Street. The domed, classical 1924 building is on the site of the Black Horse Inn, not far from where George Washington and his troops gathered on Nov. 25, 1783, for their triumphal march through a New York City liberated from British troops.</p>
        <p>A cultural landmark, the Amato Opera, at No. 319, is completing its 52nd season this weekend in its tiny Bowery jewel box theater, with cast members singing the ''The Marriage of Figaro'' as though they're at the Met. At the other end of the Bowery, shoppers can make deals on diamonds in the many booths at the jewelry exchanges at Canal Street, and walking north might find Chinese pastries, bridal dresses, track lighting, industrial shelving, a cinema-style popcorn maker, slicing machines, chairs for rent and, in a former parking lot, plants and flowers.</p>
        <p>For drivers, crossing the Bowery north of Delancey Street can sometimes resemble the Bowery Follies, the name of a now defunct establishment favored by sailors at No. 265, off Houston Street. The Bowery interrupts the city's straightforward grid. Streets like Prince, Spring and Bleecker on the west side, and Stanton, Rivington and First on the east, end -- or begin -- at the Bowery. In some cases, the names change: Delancey becomes Kenmare; Bond becomes East Second; Great Jones becomes East Third.</p>
        <p>It's a street that surprises. Old-timers gape at a two-story terraced gray penthouse, recently erected atop a dark orange brick building. A number of the facades -- some Federal style, some Georgian, most an architectural mix -- have been restored, and others seem battered, although traces of rich details are plentiful. Some buildings with unremarkable exteriors house astonishing interior renovations.</p>
        <p>Mention the Bowery to most New Yorkers and they're more likely to associate it with ''bums'' than ''beauty,'' but I do find the Bowery striking. Still seedy around the edges, the Bowery is not yet gentrified -- there's no Starbucks, no Gap -- and it's not clear whether it will soon look more like SoHo, to the west.</p>
        <p>In the shadow of the former Bowery Theater, the street's spirit lives on in the light-footed Roland Joseph, a traffic policeman on the corner of Canal Street, at the entrance to the Manhattan Bridge. His hands in white gloves, he theatrically salutes and talks to virtually every passing driver, wiggling his hips to avoid being sideswiped, getting the dance steps right without ever looking at his feet. Always smiling, he's another master performer where all the street's a stage.</p>
        <p>Map of Manhattan highlighting The Bowery. (pg. E37)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
