<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Travels With a Stoned Candide: Best of Worlds? Uh, Say What?</title>
    <meta content="16JESU$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Jesus' Son (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E5D6113EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Travels With a Stoned Candide: Best of Worlds? Uh, Say What?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from A O Scott's April 7 review of movie Jesus' Son, which was shown as part of New Directors/New Films Series and is now in commercial release; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Jesus' Son'' was shown as part of this year's New Directors/New Films Series. Here are excerpts from A. O. Scott's review, which appeared in The New York Times on April 7. The film opens today at United Artists Union Square, Broadway at 13th Street in the East Village.</p>
        <p>''Jesus' Son,'' Alison Maclean's scruffy, likable new film adapted from a book of linked short stories by Denis Johnson, follows the adventures of a young man known only by a nickname that can't be printed in this newspaper. He acquires this sobriquet -- the initials are F. H. -- because of his almost miraculous propensity to screw things up, to bring bad luck on himself and those around him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Jesus' Son'' was shown as part of this year's New Directors/New Films Series. Here are excerpts from A. O. Scott's review, which appeared in The New York Times on April 7. The film opens today at United Artists Union Square, Broadway at 13th Street in the East Village.</p>
        <p>''Jesus' Son,'' Alison Maclean's scruffy, likable new film adapted from a book of linked short stories by Denis Johnson, follows the adventures of a young man known only by a nickname that can't be printed in this newspaper. He acquires this sobriquet -- the initials are F. H. -- because of his almost miraculous propensity to screw things up, to bring bad luck on himself and those around him.</p>
        <p>But as incarnated first in Mr. Johnson's dreamy, neo-beatnik prose and now in Billy Crudup's transcendent goofing, F. H. retains a curious aura of innocence. He's like Candide strung out on every drug he can find, or an itinerant holy man hitchhiking across the Midwest in wet, filthy hipster hand-me-downs.</p>
        <p>One of the pleasures of ''Jesus' Son'' is watching a filmmaker take risks and discover new resources of style. True to her source, Ms. Maclean tells the young man's story in a looping, absent-minded manner, skittering ahead and then scrambling backward to fill in forgotten details.</p>
        <p>Her decision to string together a series of self-contained vignettes could have resulted in meandering tedium, but she manages to find a loose, improvisatory rhythm that matches Mr. Johnson's discursive riffing, and that gives her scenes a keen edge of surprise.</p>
        <p>Her use of Mr. Johnson's own words in the voice-over narration works less well. Some of his breathless beatnik invocations of the beauty of the universe lose their innocence on the journey from page to soundtrack and come across as more fussy than inspired.</p>
        <p>The film is fragmentary and episodic, but its first two sections, set mostly in the brown wintriness of Iowa in 1971, achieve a tattered narrative unity, thanks to the hero's on-again, off-again obsession with a doomy, passionate young woman named Michelle (Samantha Morton).</p>
        <p>As their relationship ambles along on its inevitable course from stoner comedy to junkie tragedy, our hero encounters a succession of memorably messed-up characters, including Wayne (Denis Leary), who sucks spilled booze out of a cocktail napkin and smashes the walls of his own house to find copper wire to sell for scrap, and Georgie (Jack Black), a hospital orderly who is either a gifted healer or a dangerous psychopath.</p>
        <p>Georgie figures in the film's most memorable sequence, a set piece shot in the hallucinatory fluorescence of a late-night hospital.</p>
        <p>A man wanders in off the street with a hunting knife sticking out of his eye. ''Patient complains of a knife in his eye,'' the intake nurse dutifully reports, and later she asks  the man, who was stabbed by his wife, if he wants the hospital staff to call the police. ''Only if I die,'' he says.</p>
        <p>This kind of surrealist deadpan humor, visual and verbal, pervades ''Jesus' Son.'' The movie may remind you, in style and subject, of Gus Van Sant's ''Drugstore Cowboy,'' which similarly imagined the early 1970's as the golden age of American junkiedom and was suffused with a rough, dreamy masculine lyricism.</p>
        <p>Mr. Van Sant's film featured William S. Burroughs as its household saint of pharmacological enlightenment. For her part Ms. Maclean trots out Dennis Hopper, once the Lord Byron of the drug culture and now its Ancient Mariner, for a cameo as a scary guy our young friend meets in rehab.</p>
        <p>As it follows F. H. into recovery, the film loses momentum. The last section is devoted to his new life, post-Michelle, in Arizona. He has a job at a treatment center for disturbed and disabled patients, a new love (Holly Hunter) and a voyeuristic devotion to a Mennonite housewife.</p>
        <p>But these details, bereft of the desperate energy of need that had propelled the movie, feel small and anecdotal. It's not that ''Jesus' Son'' romanticizes drug use; on the contrary, it rubs our faces in the tawdry emptiness of an addict's days. But if drugs wreck -- and sometimes take -- the lives of F. H. and his misfit tribe, they also make them interesting, vivid and oddly beautiful.</p>
        <p>These words also apply to Mr. Crudup and Ms. Morton, whose chemistry (so to speak) keeps the film from nodding off into feckless hustler attitude.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crudup plays a lost, irresponsible and stupid young man with discipline and intelligence, using every muscle in his face to suggest the unreachable emotion and the accidental goodness of his character. His F. H. is authentically creepy and unexpectedly charming. If you saw him on the street, you wouldn't know whether to cross to the other side, give him a quarter or take him home with you.</p>
        <p>Ms. Morton, nominated for an Oscar for her portrayal of the mute laundress in Woody Allen's ''Sweet and Lowdown,'' is just as fierce, sweet and angry here, and without much more to say. She inspires her errant knight to fantasies of rescue and saves this movie from its own self-destructive impulses.</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
