<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Resemblance? It's Only Natural</title>
    <meta content="16FLIC$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207680"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AT THE MOVIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corman, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harris, Rosemary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ehle, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Szabo, Istvan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Warburton, Patrick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Devor, Robinson</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Warrick, Ruth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kehr, Dave</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sunshine (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Seinfeld (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Woman Chaser, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Citizen Kane (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns/At the Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns/At the Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7D7113EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1277" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Resemblance? It's Only Natural</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dave Kehr</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kehr, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>At the Movies column; Rosemary Harris comments on co-starring with her daughter, Jennifer Ehle, in Istvan Szabo's movie Sunshine; Harris plays Ehle's character in old age; photo; Patrick Warburton, famous in Seinfeld lore as Elaine's boyfriend David Putty, stars in Robinson Devor's independent film The Woman Chaser; Ruth Warrick, last surviving star of Citizen Kane, will discuss movie classic at Film Forum; Julie Corman chairs New York University graduate film and television department (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In ''Sunshine,'' the family saga by the Hungarian filmmaker Istvan Szabo that opened in New York last Friday, the actresses Jennifer Ehle and Rosemary Harris play the same character at two different stages in her life. Ms. Ehle is the young, rebellious Valerie Sonnenschein, who marries her cousin Ignatz (Ralph Fiennes) in the twilight years of the Austro-Hungarian Empire; Ms. Harris is the mature Valerie, who survives both the death camps of World War II and the Stalinist repression of the 1950's.</p>
        <p>It's a smooth transition, made smoother by the fact that Ms. Ehle is Ms. Harris's daughter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In ''Sunshine,'' the family saga by the Hungarian filmmaker Istvan Szabo that opened in New York last Friday, the actresses Jennifer Ehle and Rosemary Harris play the same character at two different stages in her life. Ms. Ehle is the young, rebellious Valerie Sonnenschein, who marries her cousin Ignatz (Ralph Fiennes) in the twilight years of the Austro-Hungarian Empire; Ms. Harris is the mature Valerie, who survives both the death camps of World War II and the Stalinist repression of the 1950's.</p>
        <p>It's a smooth transition, made smoother by the fact that Ms. Ehle is Ms. Harris's daughter.</p>
        <p>''We've done it twice, actually,'' Ms. Harris said in the Upper East Side apartment that serves as the family pied-a-terre in Manhattan (home base is North Carolina, where Ms. Harris's husband, the novelist John Ehle, was raised). ''The first time was 'The Camomile Lawn,' a lovely British television series that Sir Peter Hall directed,'' Ms. Harris said. ''He chose Jennifer for the bulk of the story. I think there were seven episodes, and she was in six of them. But the last one jumped to 40 years later when the survivors from World War II met at a funeral, and Jennifer's was one of the surviving characters. And Peter Hall asked me if I would be Jennifer.''</p>
        <p>''I seem to be riding on her coattails a lot,'' said Ms. Harris of her daughter, who won a Tony Award this month for her performance in ''The Real Thing'' -- thus beating out her mother, who had been nominated for her role in ''Waiting in the Wings.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Harris added: ''When Ralph and Istvan were talking about casting, apparently, as Jennifer explained it to me the other day, Ralph said, 'Well, I know an actress who would be right for the older Valerie,' and Istvan said, 'Well, I've seen a girl who I think should play the younger Valerie.' And then by chance they put the two pieces together and said, 'Well, isn't that a funny thing -- they're mother and daughter.'</p>
        <p>''I said to Jennifer, 'Should we sit down and talk about it?' and she said, 'Oh, no -- do you think we should?' I said, 'No, if we don't know each other pretty well by now, nobody knows us better than we do.' I didn't watch any film clips of her performance. I knew with 'Sunshine' she would be playing from her own personality, so we didn't discuss it too deeply.''</p>
        <p>One of the great figures of the London and New York stage, whose lengthy resume includes Laurence Olivier's legendary 1963 ''Uncle Vanya'' and her own Tony for the original 1966 production of ''A Lion in Winter,'' Ms. Harris has been mysteriously neglected by the cinema.  ''I've never played a really big part in a movie,'' she said. ''I think it would be lovely to go in every day and, like threading beads on a string, to gradually let your part grow, like one does in the theater. But so far, I've not been offered a part that was more than a few scenes.''</p>
        <p>''I have to say I feel more at home on the stage, partly because of the text -- you get a bigger lump to grab hold of. I jokingly said once I was like an animal that had evolved: I've grown gills for the stage; I breathe in a different way. I am in my element, my own element, when I'm on the stage. I'm in a slightly different element when I'm in a film.''</p>
        <p>Ruthless but Deadpan</p>
        <p>Although he appeared in only nine episodes, Patrick Warburton will forever be associated with ''Seinfeld'': the 6-foot-3, broad-shouldered actor played David Puddy, the massively impassive boyfriend of Elaine (Julia Louis-Dreyfus). Mr. Warburton plays a very different character in ''The Woman Chaser,'' an independent feature adapted by the first-time filmmaker Robinson Devor from a neglected pulp novel by Charles Willeford.</p>
        <p>As Richard Hudson, a used-car dealer in 1960's Los Angeles, he's a ruthless manipulator who suddenly discovers his artistic calling. He has to make a movie to show the world what he's learned about it. ''I thought the whole story was intriguing -- you've got a guy who does some pretty reprehensible things, but there's not a total lack of empathy for this character,'' Mr. Warburton said.</p>
        <p>''His way of dealing with people is so wrong sometimes,'' the actor added. ''But I thought if we were able to approach this in the right way, it could be a very humorous story. I've read 'spoof' in some critiques, but I've never thought of this being a spoof. When I read this I thought it could work on all sorts of different levels. I think we accomplished some of that.''</p>
        <p>''I hear the word deadpan a lot,'' he said in regard to his sober style of comic acting. ''I'm not sure exactly what it means other than the fact that I know when I look at something and I find it funny, that I really think the approach has got to be one of an earnest, honest take on something.  You let the viewer find the humor. You don't spell it out. Otherwise it's just not funny. Puddy is not a joke to Puddy, and Richard Hudson is not a joke to Richard Hudson.''</p>
        <p>''I loved Jerry Lewis when I was growing up,'' Mr. Warburton said by way of explaining a gift for comedy not always evident in men of his size. ''I was a bit of a little freak. My parents sent me to an all-boys Catholic prep school in Anaheim, and I had to take a bus for a full half-hour each way. You were either an academic or a football player, and I was neither. Sophomore year, I weighed 105 pounds; I was the littlest kid in the whole school, and I had big old Coke-bottle glasses. I am absolutely blind. I'm farsighted, and I am cross-sighted, and I have a huge astigmatism. I had to rely on having something of a sense of humor just to survive life at the time.''</p>
        <p>'Really, Charles . . .'</p>
        <p>Ruth Warrick, the last surviving member of the principal cast of ''Citizen Kane,'' will turn 85 on June 29.  For the occasion, she's been persuaded to appear that evening at the Film Forum, 209 West Houston Street in the South Village, for an onstage interview with the film historian Foster Hirsch. The talk will follow a 6:45 screening of ''Kane,'' in which she plays the disapproving upper-crust wife of Orson Welles's grasping newspaper magnate: ''Really, Charles . . . What will people think?'' He replies, ''What I tell them to think!''</p>
        <p>Though Film Forum members will be given priority, a number of tickets for the public have been set aside. Information: (212) 727-8110.</p>
        <p>Indie Veteran</p>
        <p>The graduate film and television department at New York University has a new chairwoman. She's Julie Corman, a veteran producer of independent films who founded New World Pictures in 1970 with her husband, Roger Corman. Ms. Corman's first producing credit was for the 1971 ''Boxcar Bertha,'' which happened to be the first feature directed by one of N.Y.U.'s most famous graduates, Martin Scorsese. Ms. Corman's duties begin this fall.</p>
        <p>AT THE MOVIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
