<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>West Nile Test May Set Off City Spraying</title>
    <meta content="16NILE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207839"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides and Pests</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Corona (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Neal L (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lueck, Thomas J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E0DE1F3EF935A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>West Nile Test May Set Off City Spraying</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lueck, Thomas J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City health officials prepare to spray insecticide over broad swath of Corona, Queens, after blood tests show that chicken in area infected with West Nile encephalitis virus; photo; map; Comr Neal L Cohen says spraying will commence only if follow-up tests on chicken in monitored flock confirm diagnosis (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City health officials said yesterday that they were preparing to spray insecticide over a broad swath of Corona, Queens, next week after blood tests showed that a chicken in the area had been infected with the West Nile virus.</p>
        <p>At a City Hall news conference, Dr. Neal L. Cohen, the city's health commissioner, said the spraying in Corona would take place only if follow-up tests on the chicken confirmed the diagnosis of West Nile encephalitis, which is transmitted by mosquitoes. The tests should be completed over the weekend, he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City health officials said yesterday that they were preparing to spray insecticide over a broad swath of Corona, Queens, next week after blood tests showed that a chicken in the area had been infected with the West Nile virus.</p>
        <p>At a City Hall news conference, Dr. Neal L. Cohen, the city's health commissioner, said the spraying in Corona would take place only if follow-up tests on the chicken confirmed the diagnosis of West Nile encephalitis, which is transmitted by mosquitoes. The tests should be completed over the weekend, he said.</p>
        <p>If spraying is ordered, officials said, it could begin as early as Monday night, using trucks that would spray only at night. The officials said it would not involve either aerial spraying from helicopters or the insecticide malathion, both of which provoked protests when they were used to combat an extensive outbreak of the virus last fall.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cohen said the city would use resmethrin, marketed under the brand name Scourge, a substance he described as ''relatively nontoxic to humans, dogs, cats and other mammals.'' But he urged people in Corona with asthma or respiratory conditions to stay indoors when the spraying occurs and to keep their doors closed and air-conditioners turned off.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cohen said the Corona chicken provided the first example of the city's efforts this year ''to identify the possible return of West Nile virus as early as possible.'' The chicken was part of an early detection procedure in which 14 small flocks of sentinel chickens have been placed in coops -- providing a form of mosquito bait -- across the city. The chickens are given periodic blood tests to see if they have been bitten by a mosquito carrying the West Nile virus.</p>
        <p>The effort also includes intensive monitoring of dead birds in the region and the use of millions of tiny fish that eat mosquito larvae in the city's waste treatment plants.</p>
        <p>If the chicken from Corona is found to be carrying the West Nile virus, it will be the first confirmed case in New York City this year. Last week, the disease was found to have killed three crows not far from New York City's borders, in Rockland County and in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>In April, Dr. Cohen said that aerial spraying of insecticides would be a ''last resort,'' and that if neighborhoods became infected, the city would spray primarily from trucks. But some environmental experts asked yesterday whether the plan to spray from trucks in Corona was an overreaction, even if the city's test chicken has been infected. Health Department officials said the area to be sprayed would include Flushing Meadows-Corona Park and the surrounding area, and could probably be completed in one night.</p>
        <p>''Does one test bird indicate a real risk?'' asked Laura Haight, an environmental analyst for the New York Public Interest Research Group. Because the evidence of infection in Corona has emerged so early in the summer, she said, ''there are not a lot of adult mosquitoes flying around out there, and all the spraying will do is kill adult mosquitoes.''</p>
        <p>But others, including two medical experts and the Queens borough president, Claire Shulman, said the city plan to spray immediately after the first confirmed case of West Nile infection was prudent because of the severe dangers posed by the disease. The outbreak last fall killed 7 people and sickened 62 others in the metropolitan region. ''The risk of spraying seems to be minimal, and if they can prevent one person from getting this deadly encephalitis, it's worth it,'' Ms. Shulman said.</p>
        <p>The city's selection of resmethrin came after angry protests last year over the use of malathion, an insecticide that some experts had associated with severe health side affects. After its use by the city, malathion was subjected to a fresh safety review by federal environmental officials, who last month said they had concluded that it was safe for routine use in killing mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>Dr. Philip J. Landrigan, director of the Center for Children's Health and the Environment at Mount Sinai Medical Center, said yesterday that resmethrin was ''much safer than malathion.'' He said the city's plan to confine its spraying in Corona to trucks and avoid aerial spraying would ''greatly reduce the risk of insecticide drifting into areas beyond its control.''</p>
        <p>He added that he saw a particularly urgent need to spray in Corona if the city's test chicken was found to have West Nile virus because of the nature of the city's tests. Because the chicken had been confined to a coop in Corona, he said, ''we know there are mosquitoes flying around in exactly that location and we can't stand back and do nothing.''</p>
        <p>Ray Parsons, the director of the Harris County Mosquito Control Program in Houston, which has long experience battling St. Louis Encephalitis, a mosquito-borne virus similar to West Nile, said yesterday that New York officials were correct to spray quickly. He said the discovery of three dead crows close to the city and an infected chicken could suggest a serious threat of an outbreak later in the summer.</p>
        <p>City health officials said they did not expect to decide whether they would proceed with the spraying in Corona until tomorrow or Sunday, when final test results on the chicken are received from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Atlanta and the National Veterinary Laboratory of the Department of Agriculture in Ames, Iowa.</p>
        <p>They said information would be posted on New York City's Web site at NYCLink.org/health and would be available on the Health Department's information line at (877) WNV-4692.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
