<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Barber Gives Giants a Real Offense</title>
    <meta content="11NFLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/11/sports/11NFLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229791"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Eagles</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barber, Tiki</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Philadelphia Eagles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E0DB1F39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="884" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Barber Gives Giants a Real Offense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mike Freeman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Pro Football column discusses performance of New York Giants running back Tiki Barber in victory over Philadelphia Eagles; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the minutes before an offensive explosion by the Giants against Philadelphia that might have made even the St. Louis Rams wink with appreciation, running back Tiki Barber, while being tackled, had his head slammed into the turf. It was not your normal football tackle, but something much more vicious. The fans at Veterans Stadium were quiet because they could sniff the offensive storm that was coming, so when Barber's head hit, the vibrations reverberated high in the stands, a cracking sound that resembled a car wreck, and Barber lay motionless on the ground.</p>
        <p>For a moment, it was scary. The artificial turf here is ragged and unkempt. Most important, it is like playing on concrete. Giants players would say after the game that they knew -- just knew -- that Barber must have a serious concussion. But Barber bounced up after only a few seconds and showed later why he, and this offense, would be fine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the minutes before an offensive explosion by the Giants against Philadelphia that might have made even the St. Louis Rams wink with appreciation, running back Tiki Barber, while being tackled, had his head slammed into the turf. It was not your normal football tackle, but something much more vicious. The fans at Veterans Stadium were quiet because they could sniff the offensive storm that was coming, so when Barber's head hit, the vibrations reverberated high in the stands, a cracking sound that resembled a car wreck, and Barber lay motionless on the ground.</p>
        <p>For a moment, it was scary. The artificial turf here is ragged and unkempt. Most important, it is like playing on concrete. Giants players would say after the game that they knew -- just knew -- that Barber must have a serious concussion. But Barber bounced up after only a few seconds and showed later why he, and this offense, would be fine.</p>
        <p>After a 25-yard touchdown catch by Amani Toomer gave the Giants a 13-3 lead, Barber, hard noggin and all, gave Philadelphia its own headache. The Giants again advanced deep into Eagles territory in the first half, and Barber turned a routine running play on first down -- called 42 fold -- into a spectacular gallop by first breaking right, then cutting left and outrunning the entire Eagles defense for a 31-yard score. The Giants led by 20-3 at halftime and never looked back.</p>
        <p>The play was symbolic in many ways. Only a few years ago Barber had a bad case of the fumbles, which for a National Football League running back is like catching the bubonic plague. Coach Jim Fassel did not trust Barber, and Barber's confidence suffered.</p>
        <p>Now, Barber is not only trusted, he is also arguably the most valuable player on the offense and has developed into a top weapon, on a par with some of the best playmakers in the league. Barber is one of the biggest reasons the Giants are 2-0 for the first time since 1994 and leading the National Football Conference East.</p>
        <p>It is no coincidence that as Barber has grown this season, the offense has become, well, a real offense. Barber excels at everything -- running, pass catching, blocking -- preventing defenses from locking in on the backfield and stacking the line with defenders. That in turn leaves wide receivers Ike Hilliard and Toomer in one-on-one coverage.</p>
        <p>There is truth to what many Giants players were repeating to anyone who would listen after they blasted the Eagles by 33-18: no one should read too much into how dominating the offense was. It is just one game, Giants players were saying. Don't get carried away.</p>
        <p>But in the sports media, our job is to hyperventilate. And as someone who has not seen a decent Giants offense since the early 1990's, it is my civic duty to go a little gaga.</p>
        <p>That's because after two solid performances, last week against Arizona and this week against Philadelphia, it seems as if the Giants are close to putting all the offensive pieces together for the first time since the 1990 Super Bowl season. They have a quarterback in Kerry Collins. (Ernie Accorsi, the team's general manager, took heat for signing Collins to a large contract, but Accorsi now looks like a genius.) They have excellent receivers in Hilliard and Toomer, and a booming back in Ron Dayne. And, of course, Barber.</p>
        <p>He had 96 yards on 11 carries against Philadelphia, 3 receptions for 29 yards, and 3 punt returns for 35 yards. Barber also had two or three key pickups when the Eagles blitzed. This follows his game last week against Arizona in which he rushed for 144 yards.</p>
        <p>Barber (160 all-purpose yards), Collins (220 passing yards), and Hilliard and Toomer (15 catches, 164 yards, 2 touchdowns combined) moved the ball with ease, scoring on 7 of 10 possessions.</p>
        <p>Barber broke from the more conservative statements of his teammates by stating the truth: that the Giants' offense is becoming fluid and potent. ''We're trying to get that feeling of invincibility,'' he said, ''where you feel like you can score anytime you want, from anywhere on the field.''</p>
        <p>Barber lost 15 pounds in the off-season to regain his quickness, and from practically the first day of training camp he has been the team's best player. He is tough enough to break runs up the middle, has enough zip to break them outside, and his intelligence allows him to digest the complicated system.</p>
        <p>Barber was all smiles after the game, as he should have been. Few running backs are playing on the level he is. But what about that hit where his head slammed the ground? It was fresh in his thoughts. Barber joked that his mind was so full of plays and formations, there was no room for his brain to move inside his skull, so any danger of a concussion was minor.</p>
        <p>''But this turf is the worst ever,'' he added. ''We might as well play in the parking lot.''</p>
        <p>Wherever you play, Tiki, just watch the head. You're about to have a Pro Bowl year.</p>
        <p>ON PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
