<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Indiana's President Fires Coach Knight, Citing Bad Behavior</title>
    <meta content="11BOB.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/11/sports/11BOB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knight, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brand, Myles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, Neil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harvey, Kent</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E2DA1F39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Indiana's President Fires Coach Knight, Citing Bad Behavior</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Knight is fired as basketball coach at Indiana University by president, Myles Brand, for 'uncivil, defiant and unacceptable' behavior; dismissal follows allegation by Kent Harvey, a student, that Knight recently assaulted him physically and verbally outside school's basketball arena; Brand admits severity of Knight's confrontation is in dispute, but cites other transgressions that violated zero-tolerance policy laid down on May 15 after board of trustees found he demonstrated pattern of inappropriate behavior and had embarrassed university; sanctions stemmed from investigation into allegation from former player Neil Reed that night choked him at 1997 practice, event caught on videtoape; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bob Knight's storied career as basketball coach at Indiana University ended abruptly yesterday when the university president, Myles Brand, dismissed him for demonstrating a pattern of ''uncivil, defiant and unacceptable'' behavior since May that culminated with a student's allegation that Mr. Knight had physically and verbally assaulted him last week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brand acknowledged that the severity of Mr. Knight's confrontation last Thursday with the student, Kent Harvey, outside Assembly Hall, the basketball arena on the Bloomington campus, was in dispute. But Mr. Brand offered a list of transgressions by Mr. Knight that he said violated the zero-tolerance policy he laid down on May 15 for Mr. Knight after the board of trustees found that he had demonstrated a ''pattern of inappropriate behavior'' and had embarrassed the university.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bob Knight's storied career as basketball coach at Indiana University ended abruptly yesterday when the university president, Myles Brand, dismissed him for demonstrating a pattern of ''uncivil, defiant and unacceptable'' behavior since May that culminated with a student's allegation that Mr. Knight had physically and verbally assaulted him last week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brand acknowledged that the severity of Mr. Knight's confrontation last Thursday with the student, Kent Harvey, outside Assembly Hall, the basketball arena on the Bloomington campus, was in dispute. But Mr. Brand offered a list of transgressions by Mr. Knight that he said violated the zero-tolerance policy he laid down on May 15 for Mr. Knight after the board of trustees found that he had demonstrated a ''pattern of inappropriate behavior'' and had embarrassed the university.</p>
        <p>Those sanctions stemmed from an investigation into an allegation from a former player, Neil Reed, that Mr. Knight had choked him at a 1997 practice -- an event caught on videotape. Mr. Knight was suspended for three games and fined $30,000 then.</p>
        <p>Mr. Knight agreed to the sanctions to save his job. He offered a general apology for what the trustees and Mr. Brand called ''persistent and systematic'' abusive behavior by Mr. Knight, a Hall of Fame coach who has won three national titles in his 29 seasons at Indiana, becoming an icon in the state. Not since the Ohio State football coach Woody Hayes was dismissed in 1978 for punching an opposing player during a game has the fate of a collegiate athletic figure stirred such national debate.</p>
        <p>''I still believe we had to give him one last chance,'' Mr. Brand said at a news conference yesterday in Indianapolis. ''He failed to live up to that. That was his decision. His unacceptable behavior not only continued since then but increased.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brand said that he spoke with Mr. Knight by telephone on Friday night and that Mr. Knight wanted to keep his job. Mr. Brand said he gave Mr. Knight the choice yesterday morning of resigning, but he would not; Mr. Brand then told him he would be dismissed.</p>
        <p>Knight returned to Bloomington last night and met with his players at Assembly Hall, and some later criticized the university.</p>
        <p>''Coach Knight has been treated badly,'' the junior guard Dane Fife, tears in his eyes, told ESPN after the meeting. ''The administration was pressured and wimped up.''</p>
        <p>Tom Geyer told The Associated Press that he and other players would have to decide whether to stay at Indiana. He said the players told Mr. Brand they wanted the assistant coaches to stay and lead the team.</p>
        <p>The news of the firing brought students to the arena, where some cursed Mr. Brand. Then, thousands strong, they marched to the president's home on campus while police officers in riot gear watched. Within an hour of the announcement, car horns blared and chants of ''We love Bobby'' echoed on campus.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brand cited several incidents involving Mr. Knight in the past 17 weeks that he said violated the ''letter and spirit of the guidelines.''</p>
        <p>*Mr. Knight refused to work within the chain of command within the athletic department, ignoring Mr. Brand's personal request to speak with the athletic director, Clarence Doninger, with whom Mr. Knight had an altercation last winter.</p>
        <p>*He made angry and inflammatory remarks about university officials and trustees.</p>
        <p>*He showed disrespect for university alumni by refusing to participate in previously scheduled Varsity Club events in Bloomington, Indianapolis and Chicago.</p>
        <p>*He verbally abused a high-ranking female university official recently in the presence of others.</p>
        <p>*As recently as Friday, in the midst of the Harvey investigation, Mr. Knight refused Mr. Brand's repeated requests to cancel a fishing trip to Canada so he would be available to answer the charges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brand tried to minimize the impact of Mr. Knight's confrontation with Mr. Harvey, the 19-year-old stepson of a former Bloomington radio show host and frequent critic of the coach, Mark Shaw. Mr. Harvey told the campus police that he bumped into the coach outside the arena and said, ''Hey, what's up, Knight?'' The coach responded by grabbing Mr. Harvey by the arm and cursing him for his lack of respect, according to Mr. Shaw.</p>
        <p>In a news conference on Friday, Mr. Knight acknowledged holding Mr. Harvey momentarily and giving him a brief and measured lesson in ''manners and civility.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brand acknowledged only that Mr. Knight initiated physical contact and the two had an ''uncomfortable exchange.'' He told reporters, ''If that was the only instance that took place, you would not be here today.''</p>
        <p>He also lauded Mr. Knight as a ''legendary coach'' who built a program measured not only in terms of winning but also by graduation rates among the nation's highest for basketball programs and the loyalty and high personal quality of his players.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brand said the university would pay the remaining two years of Knight's salary, which he said was $170,000 a year. The search for an interim coach will begin right away.</p>
        <p>Besides amassing a 661-239 record at Indiana, Mr. Knight led the Hoosiers to 11 Big Ten Conference titles and coached the United States men's team to the gold medal at the 1984 Olympic Games. But he also displayed a fiery temper. He appeared to kick his own son in the shin while the son played for his Indiana team.</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Shaw, Mr. Harvey's stepfather, was stunned by yesterday's turn of events. He says the family, which had received threats, wanted only an apology -- something Mr. Shaw said was in the works yesterday morning through a friend of Knight's. Mr. Shaw, however, said that he was disturbed the university waited so long to dismiss Knight.</p>
        <p>COLLEGES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
