<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Fight for a Sound Education</title>
    <meta content="11MON1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/11/opinion/11MON1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E6DB1F39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Fight for a Sound Education</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial supports efforts to invoke state constitutions to force states to provide a fair level of financing to schools serving poor and minority students and to give these students broader educational opportunity; scores those state governments that argue that their constitutional responsibilities in education are minimal even as they urge higher standards</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nearly 50 years have passed since the Supreme Court ruled in Brown v. Board of Education that the practice of confining black students to inferior, racially segregated schools violated the Constitution and barred African-Americans from full participation in civic and professional life. But some of the same inequalities cited in Brown are still evident as 50 million children return to the public schools this month, many of them to failing schools that fall far short of new academic standards being adopted in just about every state.</p>
        <p>That situation may begin to change under the pressure of litigation in state courts. In the last decade alone, 17 states have been jolted by court decisions dictating that the state governments provide poor and minority students with fair levels of school financing -- and broader educational opportunity. Most of these decisions are based on the premise that the state constitutions require the state governments to provide schoolchildren with an adequate education. This is beginning to be defined in terms of the education reforms that have been put in place across the country in recent years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nearly 50 years have passed since the Supreme Court ruled in Brown v. Board of Education that the practice of confining black students to inferior, racially segregated schools violated the Constitution and barred African-Americans from full participation in civic and professional life. But some of the same inequalities cited in Brown are still evident as 50 million children return to the public schools this month, many of them to failing schools that fall far short of new academic standards being adopted in just about every state.</p>
        <p>That situation may begin to change under the pressure of litigation in state courts. In the last decade alone, 17 states have been jolted by court decisions dictating that the state governments provide poor and minority students with fair levels of school financing -- and broader educational opportunity. Most of these decisions are based on the premise that the state constitutions require the state governments to provide schoolchildren with an adequate education. This is beginning to be defined in terms of the education reforms that have been put in place across the country in recent years.</p>
        <p>The rulings have dramatically reshaped the public school debate. They have also revealed a disturbing hypocrisy among state officials, who trumpet the need for high standards but have tended to defend mediocrity and inequality in court when their systems are challenged.</p>
        <p>Lawsuits aimed at revising the property tax formulas by which many states finance their schools began to appear in the 1970's, most notably in California and New Jersey. Californians responded to a court order requiring that the state equalize spending levels between rich and poor schools by passing Proposition 13, which placed strict limits on property taxes, the effect of which was to push down spending so that all schools received less money.  California dropped from fifth in per-pupil spending to 42nd. A similar court ruling in New Jersey resulted in a 30-year battle between the courts and the Legislature, which is just beginning to act on decisions requiring that more money be shifted to poorer districts.</p>
        <p>Judges who ruled in those early cases were at a loss to find a clear set of remedies for educational inequality. But the inequalities -- and solutions for dealing with them -- were underscored during the 1980's, when the states began to articulate new education goals, along with specific ways for students to reach them. Faced with new curriculums, tests and teacher training requirements, legal advocates shifted their lawsuits from issues of funding equity to the question of whether or not the states were providing students with the means to meet the standards laid out by state education departments and, in some cases, codified in law.</p>
        <p>State courts are increasingly ruling that the  education clause in a state constitution places the onus on the state to furnish students with the opportunity to receive a sound education -- and that the responsibility cannot be passed on to localities. Courts have issued such rulings in several states, including Kentucky, Alabama, Massachusetts, New Jersey, North Carolina and Ohio. Suits based on these arguments are pending in Pennsylvania, New York and California.</p>
        <p>State responses to these legal challenges have occasionally ranged from the flip to the reprehensible. In Pennsylvania, for example, state lawyers argued that the state government could interpret the State Constitution's education clause anyway it wished, up to or including defining basic education as teaching students to tie their shoes. New York State was similarly appalling in arguing recently that it could fulfill its constitutional duty by teaching students to read at the eighth-grade level.</p>
        <p>Whatever their legality, these arguments are morally indefensible. Having raised the education bar higher and higher -- making it steadily tougher for students to move through school -- the states now face the burden of insuring that every child has modern textbooks, a competent teacher and a clean, safe place to sit.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
