<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="11FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E4DA1F39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1350" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Palestinians Postpone Independence Deadline  A Palestinian leadership assembly decided to postpone a declaration of statehood and recommit to the Middle East peace effort. The Palestinian Central Council backed down from its pledge to declare an independent Palestinian state no later than Sept. 13. It adjourned for up to two months, entrusting its statehood aspirations to Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, and his advisers.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Palestinians Postpone Independence Deadline  A Palestinian leadership assembly decided to postpone a declaration of statehood and recommit to the Middle East peace effort. The Palestinian Central Council backed down from its pledge to declare an independent Palestinian state no later than Sept. 13. It adjourned for up to two months, entrusting its statehood aspirations to Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, and his advisers.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>OPEC to Increase Production  The Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries, faced with growing international pressure to drive down high oil prices, decided at a meeting in Vienna to increase its crude production by 800,000 barrels a day, spokesmen for the group and delegates said. Oil industry experts said that the increase was probably not enough to significantly decrease the cost of crude oil.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>British Raid Frees Hostages  British troops surprised renegade guerrillas in Sierra Leone and in a 90-minute gun battle freed seven soldiers who had been taken hostage. British officials said the raid was undertaken because the lives of the hostages, six of them British soldiers helping the country to rebuild its armed forces, were in danger.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>2 Koreas Addressed U.S. Role  President Kim Dae Jung of South Korea, in an interview in Manhattan, said that the most important outcome of his summit conference with North Korea in June was an understanding that American troops must stay in South Korea to prevent a defense vacuum on the Korean peninsula.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Hong Kong Voters Stay Home  Hong Kong residents turned out in far smaller numbers than expected to vote in the second legislative election since the former British colony reverted to Chinese rule in 1997. Experts attributed the low turnout, 43 percent of registered voters, to a variety of factors, but most agreed that widespread unhappiness with the territory's Beijing-appointed government had alienated voters.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Rights Case Challenges Mexico  Ricardo Miguel Cavallo, accused of running a torture operation during the era of Argentina's dictatorship, is being held in Mexico City on a Spanish warrant. If Mexico extradites him, rights experts say, it could establish the principle that justice knows no borders.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-23</p>
        <p>Government Drops Case Against Nuclear Scientist  The government agreed to drop virtually its entire case against Wen Ho Lee, the former Los Alamos scientist accused of stealing nuclear weapons secrets, in return for Dr. Lee's agreement to plead guilty to a single charge that he improperly downloaded classified data on an unsecure computer. Dr. Lee could be freed after nine months in prison.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>So many important decisions broke for Dr. Lee before the plea deal, on issues like bail and racial profiling, that it is easy to forget what formidable odds his legal team first confronted. But his team recovered from a series of defeats and withstood the might of the government.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Mysteries of Tire Debacle  The story of the Firestone tire debacle, blamed for as many as 150 deaths around the world, is one of missed hints, lost opportunities and unsolved mysteries, a review of more than 100 company and government documents showed. With another hearing in Congress scheduled tomorrow, the pressure remains intense to find answers to questions such as why Ford or Firestone did not recognize sooner that the combination of tire failures and rollovers would prove lethal.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Gore vs. Entertainment Ads  Vice President Al Gore and his Democratic running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, said that if the entertainment industry does not stop marketing violent films, recordings and video games to children, they would propose legislation or new regulatory authority allowing the federal government to sanction the industry. Mr. Gore said he would give industry officials six months to ''clean up their act.''</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Uproar Over Civic Rules  The Coral Gables City Commission has warned it will ban citizens in the Florida city who are ''boisterous'' or ''impertinent.'' The warning is a reaction to a series of meetings in which some residents have spoken loudly and at times rudely to the commission. Violators could be ejected or barred from meetings.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Texas Cities Push Dead Aside  As population growth explodes across Texas and other states in the South and Southwest, yet another issue has emerged for planners and preservationists: some cities have so many new residents that they are encroaching upon cemeteries.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Prices and Shortages Raise Worries Over Energy  Energy experts and meteorologists say that the Northeast, for reasons as varied as the patterns of Canadian arctic air flows, decisions made by Midwest oil refiners and oil buyers in Germany, and a shortage of natural gas, is now facing what could be an expensive heating season.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Debate Over Lazio Handshake  The White House this weekend released an official photograph showing Rick A. Lazio, the Republican opponent to Hillary Rodham Clinton in the New York Senate race, shaking hands with Yasir Arafat nearly two years ago. The Lazio campaign, concerned about the reaction of Jewish voters, criticized what it called the White House's use of official resources to help Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Big Effort for Mob Indictments  New York's most significant construction racketeering indictments focusing on the mob in years involved investigators marshaling technology, hours of labor and resourcefulness.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Police Raid Gang Faction  Seven people were being held on drug and weapons charges after police raids in Bushwick, Brooklyn, that resulted from an undercover investigation into one of the few surviving factions of the Latin Kings gang, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY</p>
        <p>D1-12</p>
        <p>Knight Out at Indiana  Indiana University fired basketball coach Bob Knight for a pattern of ''unacceptable'' behavior.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Another Open Ending for Woods  Tiger Woods won the Canadian Open by one stroke over Grant Waite. He became the only other golfer besides Lee Trevino in 1971 to win the U.S. Open, British Open and Canadian Open in the same year.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Safin Upsets Sampras  Marat Safin of Russia beat Pete Sampras, 6-4 6-3 6-3, to win the U.S. Open men's tennis championship for his first Grand Slam title.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-22</p>
        <p>Hewlett-Packard in Talks  Hewlett-Packard is in negotiations to acquire the consulting unit of PricewaterhouseCoopers for as much as $20 billion, executives close to the talks said. The talks could still break down, but a deal would turn Hewlett-Packard into a full-service computer hardware manufacturer and consulting services company.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Details of London Exchange Bid  OM Gruppen offers details of its hostile bid for the London Stock Exchange and says why its plan makes more sense than a friendly merger with the Frankfurt exchange.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Drug Technology Deal  Human Genome Sciences, a company that is developing drugs based on the discovery of genes, said it had acquired Principia Pharmaceutical for about $120 million in stock. Principia is developing a technology that could enhance the effectiveness of human proteins used as drugs.</p>
        <p>C18</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>Some Surprises at the Emmys  ''The West Wing'' won the Emmy for the best television drama as well as several other awards, and ''Will &amp; Grace'' was chosen as the best comedy. ''The Sopranos'' had many nominations but only one award, James Gandolfini for best actor.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A24-25</p>
        <p>Editorials: The fight for a sound education; clash time in the Senate race; siphoning money from Medicaid.</p>
        <p>Columns: William Safire, Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E4  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A14  Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E7  Metro Diary</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>B8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
