<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Father's Footsteps Echo Throughout a Son's Career</title>
    <meta content="11DAD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/11/politics/11DAD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="GOVERNOR BUSH'S JOURNEY -- The Legacy" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229779"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE LEGACY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kristof, Nicholas D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George Prescott (Former Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DB1F39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3589" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Father's Footsteps Echo Throughout a Son's Career</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS D. KRISTOF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kristof, Nicholas D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Governor Bush's Journey, 14th article in series on lives of presidential candidates, focuses on influence of father's legacy on his political career; Bush is loath to discuss manifold ways in which his life has been molded and prodded by father's and family's legacy; is extremely sensitive to questions relating to his political inheritance, notably over whether he is his own man; examination of his entire life suggests that almost everything he has achieved was in part because of his name and family connections, which opened doors that would otherwise have been closed; common theme runs through each stage of his life, namely, of hero worship of father leading to instinct to follow father's trail; many friends believe that, at some level, driving force of his career has been effort to honor father's legacy, or at least to please and emulate him, and that presidential bid is culmination of quest; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the thrill of his father's election to the presidency in 1988 began to fade a bit, George W. Bush began to wonder what it would mean for him.</p>
        <p>So he commissioned a secret report, asking one of his father's aides to write about what happens to the children of presidents. The 44-page report, ''All the Presidents' Children,'' was sobering: since the founding of the republic, some children had flourished because of bountiful new opportunities, while many others had been crushed by heightened expectations and scrutiny.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the thrill of his father's election to the presidency in 1988 began to fade a bit, George W. Bush began to wonder what it would mean for him.</p>
        <p>So he commissioned a secret report, asking one of his father's aides to write about what happens to the children of presidents. The 44-page report, ''All the Presidents' Children,'' was sobering: since the founding of the republic, some children had flourished because of bountiful new opportunities, while many others had been crushed by heightened expectations and scrutiny.</p>
        <p>For example, one of John Adams's sons, John Quincy Adams, also became president, but two other sons disintegrated into alcoholism. And of John Quincy Adams's sons, one thrived and another committed suicide.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, chilled by the implications of the report, ordered all extra copies destroyed, a longtime friend said. Yet simply by commissioning the report, he demonstrated an awareness of something he is usually loath to discuss: the manifold ways in which his life has been molded and prodded by his father's career and his family's legacy.</p>
        <p>One of the questions Mr. Bush is most sensitive about has to do with this inheritance: To what degree is he his own man? A look across his life suggests a fairly straightforward answer: almost everything he achieved, he did in part because of his name and family connections. Typically, his name opened doors that would otherwise have been closed, but once inside he impressed people with his energy and enthusiasm.</p>
        <p>If it were not for his background, Mr. Bush very likely would not have gotten into Yale, would not have become a baseball team owner, would not have become governor of Texas -- and would not be a presidential candidate. Yet much the same was said of John F. Kennedy, and even Vice President Al Gore benefited enormously when he first ran for Congress by carrying the name of his father, a former senator.</p>
        <p>When one steps back from any stage of Mr. Bush's life and examines his biography as a whole, one theme runs through each stage of his life: hero worship of his father, leading to an instinct to follow his father's trail. Many friends think that at some level, a driving force of George W.'s career has been an effort to honor his legacy and please his father, or at least to emulate him. Some acquaintances, though not all, even believe that this year's presidential bid is a culmination of that quest.</p>
        <p>''What makes him tick?'' asked an old friend of both Bushes. ''It's Daddy.''</p>
        <p>''Daddy allows him to do things and achieve ambitions that he would not do on his own,'' the friend added. ''Daddy is the motivation -- to please his dad.''</p>
        <p>Yet his father's experience also taught Mr. Bush lessons about what to avoid, and in some respects he is campaigning this year as the anti-Dad. His campaign organization has a beyond-the-Beltway, down-home-Texan feel to it that his father's did not. It is led by old Texas buddies who, at least until recently, have run a disciplined and virtually leak-proof organization that is the opposite of President Bush's 1992 campaign, dominated by Washington politicos.</p>
        <p>Moreover, for all his father's efforts to enjoy pork rinds and boycott broccoli, Mr. Bush has a far more natural Bubba quality. More than his father, he genuinely seems delighted by the chance to work crowds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush comes across as by nature remarkably cheerful, relaxed and free of neurosis or inner conflict. But one exception creates a fascinating knot in the grain: his complex relationship with his father and his family legacy.</p>
        <p>As his brother Jeb once observed, growing up in the shade of a prominent father can create ''all sorts of pathologies.''</p>
        <p>Powerful Role Models</p>
        <p>Diane Paul was a serious girlfriend of Mr. Bush when he was in his mid-20's. She speaks very fondly of him, which is no surprise: Mr. Bush seems to be regarded more warmly by his ex-girlfriends than many men are by their wives.</p>
        <p>Ms. Paul says that that even during the period Mr. Bush has called his ''nomadic years,'' when he was partying aggressively and avoiding anything that hinted of a responsible career, he was casting about for a way to live up to his family. She remembers his speaking of his father and grandfather with such awe that she knew they were powerful role models.</p>
        <p>''The whole way he talked about his father and grandfather, it's no accident that he tried to repeat just what his dad did, in the same order,'' Ms. Paul said. ''It's what I thought his goal was. His goal was to see how he could step into those shoes, how he could live up to that family legacy. It was in his bones.''</p>
        <p>''I think George at that time had more of an intensity than people realized about living up to his legacy,'' Ms. Paul added. ''That was the psychological tension in him: how am I going to live up to this?''</p>
        <p>One result of this tension is that he has spent most of his life traipsing along the same trail his father had already blazed -- yet leaving much smaller footprints.</p>
        <p>Young George followed his father to Phillips Academy in Andover, Mass., and then to college at Yale, with worse grades and less memorable achievements at both. Based on his mediocre high school grades (he never made the honor roll even one term, unlike 110 boys in his class) and college boards (which totaled 1206, compared with an average of 1386 for his classmates in the Yale class of 1968), it is difficult to see how he could have gotten into Yale if his father and grandfather had not attended before him.</p>
        <p>Like his father, he entered and became president of Delta Kappa Epsilon fraternity, was tapped into the Skull and Bones secret society and became a fighter pilot. But while his father had been a much decorated combat pilot in World War II, George W. avoided service in Vietnam by piloting obsolete fighter planes in Texas.</p>
        <p>After leaving the Air National Guard, George W. began a business career just as his father had: by driving to Midland, Tex., and starting an oil business with a name that would not get lost in the phone book. (His father chose Zapata, around the end of the listings, and he chose Arbusto, near the beginning.) His father made millions of dollars, while George W. lost millions. And the son had the opportunity to lose millions only because of his name: for investors, he tapped relatives and family friends.</p>
        <p>Finally, both began political careers with a run for Congress while in their 30's. Both lost, but the elder George ran such a strong race that he retained his political credibility, while young George emerged simply as, well, a loser.</p>
        <p>In short, George W.'s career was not a precise copy of his father's but rather -- until a sudden flowering in the last decade -- a poor-quality carbon.</p>
        <p>It was only when Mr. Bush was in his early 40's that his life took on a new direction, and this seemed to empower him.</p>
        <p>''The conventional wisdom on George is that the turning point of his life was giving up drinking,'' noted Roland W. Betts, a friend since Yale days and a partner in the purchase of the Texas Rangers baseball team in 1989. ''I don't believe that. The turning point of his life was buying the Texas Rangers, succeeding with the Texas Rangers.</p>
        <p>''The reason is that it was the first real deviation from the script, which was his father's life. He had tried to emulate everything his father had done.''</p>
        <p>With baseball, Mr. Betts said, Mr. Bush not only tackled something his father had not done but did it very well. The son helped turn the Rangers around and presided over the construction of a grand new stadium, one of the best in major league baseball.</p>
        <p>A Path Made for Frustration</p>
        <p>This pattern of following Dad's footsteps strikes almost everyone who knows the family.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure there was something subconscious,'' mused Donald B. Ensenat, a fraternity brother, sometime roommate and longtime friend. ''It was never sitting down and saying, 'I'm going to follow my dad's career path.' But whoever your dad is, he's your first and most powerful role model.''</p>
        <p>George W. Bush is unconvinced by this analysis. Asked if this pattern of similar behavior was a coincidence, he shifted uncomfortably in his chair.</p>
        <p>''I don't know,'' he answered. ''You could write anything you want. I haven't spent a lot of time psychoanalyzing myself.''</p>
        <p>This attitude mimics his father's famous discomfort with any probing of his psyche. Friends and family members say the entire Bush family is exceptionally averse to introspection, in part because of an ingrained notion that excessive reflection is wimpish and also because of a fear that journalists will pounce on any self-searching and exaggerate any vulnerabilities it reveals.</p>
        <p>One natural tactic for a young adult caught in the shadow of a powerful parent would be to flee it. The elder George Bush had escaped from his own powerful family by moving to Texas after graduating from college. And Jeb had set out in a new direction by majoring in Latin American studies in college, marrying a Mexican woman and working for a time as a banker in Venezuela, although in the end he, too, followed his father into politics, eventually being elected governor of Florida.</p>
        <p>George W., instead of fleeing that shade as Jeb did, embraced it -- and after college followed his father's route almost precisely. Yet this was a path tailor-made for frustration and disappointment: the elder George Bush enjoyed a career in the spotlight -- member of Congress, ambassador to the United Nations, chairman of the Republican National Committee, envoy to China, head of the Central Intelligence Agency -- while young George floundered, going nowhere.</p>
        <p>But what shines through in speaking to Mr. Bush's oldest acquaintances is the deep respect he has always felt for his father.</p>
        <p>Even in 1969, the year of Woodstock, when young George was 23 and the generation gap was as great as it has ever been in America, he wrote his parents a warm thank-you note and added about his siblings: ''Someday Jeb, and Neil, Marvin, and Doro will know how lucky they are -- someday they'll know what it is to be surrounded by love.''</p>
        <p>His father wrote one of his staff members about how warm that made him and Barbara feel: ''We wiped back our tears and we said, 'We are very lucky to have a boy today who understands.' ''</p>
        <p>Some acquaintances believe that Mr. Bush's political career arose from a desire to avenge his father's defeat, although Mr. Bush dismisses the idea. In any case, the interplay between father and son is a constant backdrop to the presidential contest.</p>
        <p>The younger Mr. Bush is very sensitive to suggestions that he is a princeling, and as a result keeps his father largely out of sight. But they speak often and remain very close, and the father remains a vast if barely seen presence hovering over the son's campaign.</p>
        <p>Yet although they have a very trusting and mutually respectful relationship, father and son always remained separated by a generational divide. They were loving but not exactly best buddies.</p>
        <p>''Dad was shy,'' young George told an interviewer in 1992, before he entered politics and became careful of everything he said. ''We never had 'the talk,' '' he said, and with regard to the use of a condom he added, ''He never told me to wear a 'raincoat' or anything.''</p>
        <p>In some respects, friends say, Mr. Bush was closer to his mother, Barbara, and she was an equally powerful but very different force in molding the family. The father and grandfather were grand figures but also a bit remote, while Barbara, the disciplinarian, inspired less reverence and more fear.</p>
        <p>''It was really Barbara who raised them all,'' noted Elsie Walker, a cousin. ''Big George was really busy in that time. So she was the one who lived with the day-to-day anguish -- 'Where are your socks?'  'Clean the bathroom,' that kind of thing.''</p>
        <p>George W.'s looks come from his father, but his personality resembles his mother's. He shares her impetuousness, her dismissiveness of critics, and above all her rapier wit. Nothing is so central to Mr. Bush's style as his needling humor, his tendency to see just about everybody as a jousting partner, and all that borrows from his mother.</p>
        <p>Friends remember that George was much more likely to quarrel with his mother than with his father, and he was less likely to speak worshipfully of his mother as a role model. But he did often speak of her with deep affection, and perhaps it is telling that he ended up marrying somebody a good deal like his mother: a strong and intelligent woman who nonetheless chose not to pursue a career after marriage.</p>
        <p>A decade before he married Laura Welch in 1977, he had almost married another woman. And while human motivations are always complex, some friends believe that earlier engagement was telling.</p>
        <p>His father had become engaged to Barbara Pierce at the age of 20, and they had lived off campus while the elder George studied at Yale. A generation later, when young George was a 20-year-old junior at Yale, he, too, fell in love: achingly, passionately, irrationally, buy-a-diamond-right-away in love.</p>
        <p>So, one rainy winter night in Houston over Christmas vacation from Yale, a childhood friend named Doug Hannah drove George W. to Neiman-Marcus. Mr. Bush darted into the store and emerged soon afterward bearing a large diamond ring to give his beloved.</p>
        <p>''I was impressed,'' Mr. Hannah recalled. ''But the whole thing seemed ill conceived to me.'' And to just about everybody else. Mr. Bush had been dating the woman, Cathy Wolfman, for only a short period, and his roommates at Yale were stunned when he returned from Christmas vacation with the news.</p>
        <p>''He came back,'' recalled Clay Johnson, then a roommate, ''and said, 'Guess what, guys? I got engaged.' ''</p>
        <p>In explaining how it came to pass, some friends turn not just to the obvious motivations -- Ms. Wolfman was a catch, a former high school cheerleader and now an excellent student at Rice University -- but also to some inner drive to follow the example set by his father, in love as in almost everything else. Another explanation is simply that Mr. Bush was famously impetuous, even rash, in making decisions.</p>
        <p>Whatever the logic, the couple kept delaying the wedding date and finally called off the engagement.</p>
        <p>''It was postponed, and then it gradually died,'' Ms. Wolfman recalled. ''We weren't in the same city, and we just drifted apart.''</p>
        <p>Friends had the impression that Mr. Bush was more in love with Ms. Wolfman than she with him, and he seemed hurt when they decisively split up after graduation and she moved to Washington. Within a year, she had married a young man who had just graduated from Harvard Business School.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush took it very hard. Once more, he had come close to emulating his father's storybook life, but again he had fallen short. Initially reticent when the topic of the engagement came up in an interview, Mr. Bush later acknowledged that it had been a very difficult time.</p>
        <p>''I asked Cathy Wolfman to marry me,'' he said. ''I struggled with the decision. There was a conflict there. I think both of us realized that it wasn't the right thing. And she went off and married another man, which was fine. But there was a conflict there. You can imagine what it was like to think you wanted to get married and then both of us decided not to.''</p>
        <p>'You Have Disappointed Me'</p>
        <p>The Bush clan gets together each year at the family compound in Kennebunkport, Me., and in each generation there is a star around whom others revolve.</p>
        <p>''At Kennebunkport with his family, you could see that George Senior was the one they would cluster around,'' recalled Ms. Paul, George W.'s former girlfriend. ''His brothers were all successful, but George's father was the one they would gather around and look up to. I think George wanted to be like that in his generation. I think he felt competitive with his brothers.''</p>
        <p>Others echo the comment, emphasizing that while the Bushes are held together by tremendous affection and mutual support, there is also a good deal of rivalry in the mix. When George W. was playing tennis with his brother Marvin at Kennebunkport more than a dozen years ago, Marvin began to goad his brother about being behind -- until George W. charged across the court at his brother and chased him up the fence.</p>
        <p>One of the few major parental reproaches that anyone can remember occurred during George W.'s college years, when he quit a summer job on an oil rig a week early so he could party with his friends in Houston. His father immediately summoned him to his office in Houston and lectured him.</p>
        <p>''Son, you agreed to work a certain amount of time, and you didn't,'' young George later remembered his father saying. ''I just want you to know that you have disappointed me.''</p>
        <p>Young George was left to stew in his own guilt. Two hours later, his father called him again to signal forgiveness and invite him to an Astros baseball game, but the reproach left a mark.</p>
        <p>''Those were the sternest words to me, even though he said them in a very calm way,'' George W. later recalled. ''He wasn't screaming and he wasn't angry, but he was disappointed. When you love a person and he loves you, those are the harshest words someone can utter. I left that office realizing I had made a mistake.''</p>
        <p>Another family clash came in the spring of 1973, George W. recalled, when he was visiting his parents in Washington, where big George was chairman of the Republican National Committee and defending the Nixon presidency in the midst of revelations about the Watergate scandal. Young George drove after drinking too much and, with his brother Marvin in the car, he slammed into a neighbor's garbage can and drove down the street with the can still caught under the car, creating a ruckus.</p>
        <p>His father, angry, asked to see George immediately in the den. And George marched in and challenged his father, asking if he wanted to go ''mano a mano.''</p>
        <p>The confrontation was quickly defused, and while it underscored young George's combustibility and fondness for alcohol, it was not typical of the family dynamic.</p>
        <p>Politics or Baseball?</p>
        <p>The ''All the Presidents' Children'' report, written by a White House aide named Doug Wead, warned that being the first son was ''not going to be easy,'' but it suggested that history pointed to one career path in particular.</p>
        <p>''Curiously,'' the report declared, ''politics is one of the least criticized professions for a President's children. Get a job as a journalist, and people will say it was the contact. Get elected to Congress and you are 'on your own.' ''</p>
        <p>The report added: ''Historically, there are three dynamics present when a President's offspring launches a successful political career.</p>
        <p>''1.) The Presidency must be viewed as successful, or, at least, as not unsuccessful.</p>
        <p>''2.) The family must appear united behind the decision.</p>
        <p>''3.) The career should be launched quickly, even while the President is in office.''</p>
        <p>That logic suggested Mr. Bush should move quickly into politics, and he thought about running for office in Texas in 1990.</p>
        <p>''At the time we were going to do this,'' Mr. Betts said, referring to the purchase of the Rangers in early 1989, ''he said he was looking at the governorship and Senate seat for 1990. But I told him: 'I'm totally dependent on you. I'm going to stay in New York and I don't know anybody in Texas. So if that's what you're going to do, you owe it to me to tell me, because then I'm not going to do this.''</p>
        <p>Somewhat later, Mr. Betts recalled, Mr. Bush promised that he would not run for office in 1990. Instead, he turned his focus on the Rangers, and on blazing his own trail to elective office. He quickly realized that by deviating from his father's route and going into baseball, he had gained credibility.</p>
        <p>''It solved my biggest political problem in Texas,'' Mr. Bush told a reporter in his first baseball season as an owner. ''My problem was, 'What's the boy ever done?' ''</p>
        <p>Governor Bush's Journey  This is the 14th article of a series about the lives of the presidential candidates. The next installment will focus on George W. Bush and the Texas Rangers baseball team.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE LEGACY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
