<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clash Time in the Senate Race</title>
    <meta content="11MON2$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/11/opinion/11MON2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4DA1F39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clash Time in the Senate Race</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says Hillary Rodham Clinton and Rep Rick Lazio are sure to use Sept 13 debate to seek Jewish vote and defend the tactics they have been using to get it; says debate will give Lazio greater exposure but also a more intense kind of testing; says Mrs Clinton, lacking a legislative record, must convince voters by the force of personality and conviction (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York's Senate race had settled recently into a tediously safe campaign between two cautious candidates. All that changed over the weekend with the politically motivated White House decision to release a 1998 photograph of Representative Rick Lazio shaking hands with Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader. As a result, Mr. Lazio and Hillary Rodham Clinton will likely use their debate in Buffalo on Wednesday to continue their highly charged battle for the Jewish vote and to defend the tactics being used in that competition.</p>
        <p>Indeed, New York voters will have to judge  substance as well as tactics. On substance, they should be clear that both sides are trying to sell pejorative explanations of acceptable diplomatic behavior. President Clinton was right to shake the hand of President Fidel Castro of Cuba when they met at the United Nations last week. Mrs. Clinton made the correct protocol judgment not to have a public confrontation with Suha Arafat during a trip to Israel last year. Finally, Mr. Lazio and the other Congressmen who joined Mr. Clinton in a meeting with Mr. Arafat made the appropriate judgment in shaking Mr. Arafat's hand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York's Senate race had settled recently into a tediously safe campaign between two cautious candidates. All that changed over the weekend with the politically motivated White House decision to release a 1998 photograph of Representative Rick Lazio shaking hands with Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader. As a result, Mr. Lazio and Hillary Rodham Clinton will likely use their debate in Buffalo on Wednesday to continue their highly charged battle for the Jewish vote and to defend the tactics being used in that competition.</p>
        <p>Indeed, New York voters will have to judge  substance as well as tactics. On substance, they should be clear that both sides are trying to sell pejorative explanations of acceptable diplomatic behavior. President Clinton was right to shake the hand of President Fidel Castro of Cuba when they met at the United Nations last week. Mrs. Clinton made the correct protocol judgment not to have a public confrontation with Suha Arafat during a trip to Israel last year. Finally, Mr. Lazio and the other Congressmen who joined Mr. Clinton in a meeting with Mr. Arafat made the appropriate judgment in shaking Mr. Arafat's hand.</p>
        <p>What New York voters should look for Wednesday is the level of maturity with which Mr. Lazio and Mrs. Clinton discuss the whole range of issues and the level of skill with which they address this skirmish. After weeks of long-range exchanges, the public will at last get a chance to see them really tested. Mr. Lazio will now have to show that he can explain the seeming hypocrisy of his position that some handshakes are worse than others. For her part, Mrs. Clinton needs to show that she does not need meddling from a White House well known for trickery to prop up her candidacy.</p>
        <p>With polls showing a very tight race, the debate offers the advantage of broader exposure for Mr. Lazio. But with the exposure will come a more intense kind of testing. So far, Mr. Lazio's ability to respond under pressure has been an unknown factor. His supporters have counted on the deep animosities that many people feel toward Mrs. Clinton to keep his campaign moving. Those feelings among conservatives have helped boost state and national fund-raising for Mr. Lazio. But many people still want to vote for somebody they feel can do the job, not merely against someone who irritates them.</p>
        <p>Like the two other debates scheduled before the election, this one presents difficulties for the first lady. Since she lacks a legislative record, she must convince voters by the force of personality and conviction. Her advisers want her to focus on issues like education, health care and the economy. Polls show that Mrs. Clinton has recently gained support among Jewish voters after months of tension. She won some applause for using her White House influence in the effort to keep Jonathan Pollard, an American convicted of spying for Israel, from being transferred to a rougher prison environment. Further attempts to meddle in this case would almost surely backfire, however, because of its serious national security implications.</p>
        <p>Against this landscape, we can see key tasks for each candidate. Mr. Lazio has to show that he can function outside the cozy world of Long Island G.O.P. politics. Mrs. Clinton must prove that she can fight her corner without help from her husband or the White House press office. And the reality for both candidates as they face the cameras is that the winning votes are still in play.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
