<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Town That Prosperity Forgot; Blighted, Broke and Crime-Ridden, Irvington Seems Helpless to Help Itself</title>
    <meta content="11IRVI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/11/nyregion/11IRVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Irvington (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6D91F39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Town That Prosperity Forgot; Blighted, Broke and Crime-Ridden, Irvington Seems Helpless to Help Itself</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>IRVINGTON, N.J., Sept. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Irvington, NJ, Newark suburb, has become blight filled and crime ridden; high taxes and increased crime have caused township of 59,000 people to lose a tenth of its population since 1980 and 15 percent of its housing stock; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like many of those who live in this fraying suburb of Newark, Margaret Jackson moved her family here two decades ago to escape the lawlessness, decay and despair then spreading through the city that nearly surrounds it. With its no-nonsense police force and racially mixed neighborhoods, Irvington beckoned middle-class Newark residents with the promise of safe, suburban-style living.</p>
        <p>''What a beautiful, beautiful neighborhood this was,'' Mrs. Jackson, a secretary, recalled as she stood in front of her house on 21st Street, just over the border from Newark. ''We had all kinds of people living here: whites, blacks, Puerto Ricans. I thought it was a solid investment.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like many of those who live in this fraying suburb of Newark, Margaret Jackson moved her family here two decades ago to escape the lawlessness, decay and despair then spreading through the city that nearly surrounds it. With its no-nonsense police force and racially mixed neighborhoods, Irvington beckoned middle-class Newark residents with the promise of safe, suburban-style living.</p>
        <p>''What a beautiful, beautiful neighborhood this was,'' Mrs. Jackson, a secretary, recalled as she stood in front of her house on 21st Street, just over the border from Newark. ''We had all kinds of people living here: whites, blacks, Puerto Ricans. I thought it was a solid investment.''</p>
        <p>As she spoke one recent evening, Mrs. Jackson took in a Dresdenesque landscape of fire-blackened homes, collapsing front porches and trash-filled lots. Mrs. Jackson's house, sandwiched between two crumbling ruins, is the only occupied building on her side of the block.</p>
        <p>''If I could sell this place, I'd be gone in a heartbeat,'' she said. ''But who's going to want to live here?''</p>
        <p>These days, not many. Irvington, a township of 59,000 people, has lost a tenth of its population since 1980 and 15 percent of its housing stock. In an era of long-running prosperity, when even Newark can crow about revival, Irvington remains a stubborn pocket of dread and instability.</p>
        <p>A shrinking tax base and years of fiscal mismanagement have left the township insolvent, and it has been declared a ''distressed city'' by the state, a status qualifying it for emergency aid. Property taxes are so high -- among the highest in the state -- that scores of homeowners are walking away from their investments. While crime continues to decline elsewhere, Irvington now has the state's second-highest violent crime rate per capita, behind the shore resort of Seaside Heights. Last year there were 15 homicides within Irvington's 2.8 square miles, up from 9 in 1998.</p>
        <p>With a mixture of envy and disgust, Mrs. Jackson pointed out the new crop of town houses rising down the street in Newark while the stately homes on her block rotted or fell prey to fires inadvertently started by squatting drug addicts. ''I can't even get the city to clean up this trash,'' she said, gesturing to a mound of clothing and bricks and a broken toilet bowl on the sidewalk. ''It's deplorable and it's breaking my heart.''</p>
        <p>Many residents blame the mayor and Township Council members for Irvington's problems, saying that these officials are more interested in internecine warfare than in governing. Others point to the overwhelmed police force, which has been accused of ignoring the drug dealing and prostitution that flourishes in many neighborhoods. And some say that Irvington is simply suffering from the aging infrastructure, crime and public indifference that have ravaged so much of urban America.</p>
        <p>With its mix of prewar apartment buildings and rows of tightly packed two-family houses, Irvington long ago lost its appeal to home buyers who craved spacious lawns and more privacy. ''Irvington is typical of a class of old bedroom communities tied to the state's vanished manufacturing economy,'' said James W. Hughes, dean of the Edward J. Bloustein School of Planning and Public Policy at Rutgers University. ''Its housing stock has become outmoded and obsolete. It's not going to be an easy future.''</p>
        <p>Irvington may have been dealt a bad hand, but state officials partly blame the local government for making Irvington's problems worse. In the last year, federal authorities have begun two investigations: one examining the Police Department's exclusive contract with a local towing company and another into the Irvington Board of Education, which has been mired in a case involving bribery charges against Kenneth A. Gibson, an engineering consultant who is a former mayor of Newark.</p>
        <p>''I wish I could say things are looking up, but things are getting worse,'' said David Lyons, a member of the Township Council who is frequently at odds with his colleagues.</p>
        <p>In what the state calls a typically bungled opportunity, the township removed its parking meters and did not replace them until more than three years later, depriving municipal coffers of nearly $1 million. Last year, $22 million of the township's $73 million budget came from Trenton, which is monitoring its finances. The mayor of Irvington, Sara B. Bost, who was first elected in 1994, did not respond to numerous telephone messages left at her office.</p>
        <p>Irvington began its most precipitous decline after 1996, when the state forced it to reassess its property values, leading to a 30 percent tax increase. The higher taxes have been driving many working-class homeowners into foreclosure. These days the tax collection rate is less than 86 percent, a situation that makes taxes even higher for those who do pay.</p>
        <p>The township, which is a month late with its state-mandated financial statement, has been without a business administrator and a financial officer since last spring.</p>
        <p>''We have some very deep and ongoing concerns for Irvington,'' said Ulrich H. Steinberg Jr., director of the State Division of Local Government Services. ''They need to step up their management and provide direction for recovery. Until now, they haven't been able to do that.''</p>
        <p>Real estate brokers complain of taxes so high -- an average of $4,000 a year for a single-family house -- that many prospective buyers will not even look at Irvington, despite its affordable housing and proximity to New York City and major highways.</p>
        <p>''The drug situation gets worse day by day, the taxes are ridiculous and the services are nonexistent,'' said Arthur Rosa, president of Rosa Realty, which has several offices in and around Newark. ''I've never seen a town deteriorate so quickly.''</p>
        <p>Still, officials say there are reasons for optimism. On a recent tour of Springfield Avenue, the township's main commercial strip, Janet Nunez, coordinator of an urban enterprise program, pointed out new trash cans, hanging flower baskets and a string of refurbished facades.</p>
        <p>''As soon as there's a vacancy here, the space gets snapped up,'' she said, adding that the township's industrial zone is drawing new businesses. In the last four years, she said, 360 full-time jobs have been created in Irvington. ''Things are really looking up,'' she said. ''Right now we need to overcome the negative press.''</p>
        <p>But well-swept sidewalks and hanging geraniums cannot offset the sight of the empty police booth that sits at the center of town. Although the enterprise program spent $16,000 building the booth last year, the Police Department cannot afford to station an officer in it.</p>
        <p>The police chief, Steven Palamara, said response time by the police lagged because his force of 163 officers had a dozen fewer officers than it had three decades ago, when there were 8,000 annual service calls. Last year there were 80,000. The increasing workload, he said, leaves little time for old-fashioned patrolling. Low-priority calls, including those that involve drug dealing and prostitution, receive scant attention, Chief Palamara added. ''It gets wild here at night,'' he said apologetically, explaining that the police are often kept busy responding to emergency calls.</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, the improving fortunes of Newark, he said, have been bad for Irvington. With a much larger force, the Newark police have unintentionally pushed crime across the border, he said. ''We're like a small town, except we have big-city problems and a small town's resources,'' Chief Palamara said. But help will arrive in December, he said, with the addition of 26 officers, their salaries paid with state money.</p>
        <p>Record crime seems to be on everyone's mind. Last year, Mayor Bost's home in the East Ward was sprayed by gunfire. Although at first she said the attack was in retaliation for her get-tough stance on crime, investigators say it is now believed to be the result of random gunplay between rival drug dealers.</p>
        <p>It is in the East Ward that Irvington's desperation is on full display. Uriel Burwell, 27, who grew up just across the border in Newark, said the changes in Irvington have been numbing. ''Irvington was one of those towns you didn't want to get caught in after dark,'' he said. ''The police would lock you up just for crossing the line.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Burwell, who runs Standing Together Against Neighborhood Decay, a group serving a neighborhood that straddles the Irvington-Newark border, said there were 500 abandoned buildings on the Irvington side, at least 150 of them in immediate need of demolition. ''Every day,'' he said, ''someone else walks away from their home.''</p>
        <p>His group is using government grants and low-interest loans to build 35 houses in Newark. Until things get better on the Irvington side, he said, he does not hold any hope for a revival there.</p>
        <p>Across town, on a tree-lined, well-manicured block, Elouise McDaniel was driving down Nesbit Terrace in her West Ward neighborhood and pointing out what she called early signs of encroaching blight: a half-painted house, an overgrown front lawn, a ''for sale'' sign that had been up far too long.</p>
        <p>''These people refuse to maintain their property,'' Mrs. McDaniel, a retired Newark schoolteacher, said with indignation. The landscape a few blocks east seemed to bear out her fears: Colonial-style houses sealed with plywood, uncollected trash, knots of young men loitering about and a collection of go-go bars. (Irvington, she said, has 13 of them.)</p>
        <p>As she drove, Mrs. McDaniel shook her head and recalled a time not long ago when these streets resembled tidy Nesbit Terrace. She spends most days writing letters to elected officials, organizing community meetings and pestering neighbors to clean up their yards. Selling her brick-faced split-level home is out of the question: she knows it would fetch less than what she paid for it 25 years ago.</p>
        <p>''I wish I could just pick up my house and move it someplace else,'' she said. ''But I'm stuck. The only thing left to do is fight.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
