<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Day of Terror, Not Brotherhood, at the Olympics</title>
    <meta content="11WERT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/11/arts/11WERT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229732"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wertheimer, Ron</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">One Day in September (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6D71E39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Day of Terror, Not Brotherhood, at the Olympics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RON WERTHEIMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wertheimer, Ron</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ron Wertheimer reviews documentary, One Day in September, on HBO; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The world became both smaller and bleaker on Sept. 5, 1972. That day an international television audience watched a real-life drama unfold in real time, as a group of Palestinian terrorists murdered two Israeli Olympians at the Summer Games in Munich, holding nine more as hostages. Those old enough will surely remember that the episode ended more horribly than it began. After a chaotic gunfight at a German air base, all the Israelis, five of their eight captors and a German police officer were dead.</p>
        <p>Reliving those events with chilling immediacy is the grim accomplishment of ''One Day in September,'' winner of this year's Oscar for best documentary feature, which HBO is showing tonight. The film, produced by Arthur Cohn and John Battsek and directed by Kevin Macdonald, is clearly the product of determination, effort and no small quantity of anger. It deals sympathetically with the Israelis, while it treats the Palestinians with a cool journalistic objectivity. It saves its simmering rage for the West German authorities, who emerge, if not as the documentary's villains, then certainly as its tragically inept fools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The world became both smaller and bleaker on Sept. 5, 1972. That day an international television audience watched a real-life drama unfold in real time, as a group of Palestinian terrorists murdered two Israeli Olympians at the Summer Games in Munich, holding nine more as hostages. Those old enough will surely remember that the episode ended more horribly than it began. After a chaotic gunfight at a German air base, all the Israelis, five of their eight captors and a German police officer were dead.</p>
        <p>Reliving those events with chilling immediacy is the grim accomplishment of ''One Day in September,'' winner of this year's Oscar for best documentary feature, which HBO is showing tonight. The film, produced by Arthur Cohn and John Battsek and directed by Kevin Macdonald, is clearly the product of determination, effort and no small quantity of anger. It deals sympathetically with the Israelis, while it treats the Palestinians with a cool journalistic objectivity. It saves its simmering rage for the West German authorities, who emerge, if not as the documentary's villains, then certainly as its tragically inept fools.</p>
        <p>The film begins with two survivors whose memories form the narrative backbone. One is Ankie Spitzer, the widow of Andre Spitzer, the Israeli fencing coach, who was killed at the air base. She remembers her husband as a man who ''tried to channel aggression into respect for your opponent.'' The other is Jamal al-Gashey, the only surviving member of the group of hostage takers, who says that once he joined the militant Black September group, ''I wasn't just a wretched refugee but a revolutionary.''</p>
        <p>Using a conventional blend of new interviews and archival film and videotape, ''One Day in September'' recalls the optimism of the 1972 Summer Games, which the Germans hoped would eclipse the memory of the Nazis' 1936 Olympics in Berlin.</p>
        <p>That optimism was a casualty, too, once eight armed Palestinians managed to evade the lax Olympic Village security and gain access to the apartment complex where the Israelis were staying. The stated goal of the raid was to trade the hostages for more than 200 prisoners held by Israel and other countries, a demand that was immediately rejected.</p>
        <p>''We had no orders to kill,'' Mr. Gashey says. ''We were forced to only when things went wrong.'' Which they did from the start.</p>
        <p>After two Israelis were killed at the Olympic site, Hans-Dietrich Genscher, the German interior minister, offered himself in exchange for the hostages. The offer was refused, as was its follow-up, an unlimited sum of cash.</p>
        <p>Rebuffing the Israelis' plan to send in their own rescue team, the Germans deployed a group of armed police officers, thinly disguised with sweat suits, forgetting that the world literally was watching.</p>
        <p>''This building is now swarming with Germans trying to rescue the Israelis,'' Jim McKay of ABC told American viewers. Inside the Israelis' apartment captors and captives, like everyone else, followed those officers' movements on television.</p>
        <p>The Germans' next plan was to offer a plane to take the Palestinians and their hostages to any country. ''To move the team from the Olympic compound in order to let the Olympic Games carry on, this was the main objective,'' says Zvi Zamir, who at the time was the chief of Mossad, the Israeli intelligence agency. ''The Israeli team and its rescue was secondary.''</p>
        <p>The Germans didn't know how many terrorists they were dealing with, so they deployed only five sharpshooters at the Furstenfeldbruck air base. As the Israelis, Palestinians and some Olympic officials were on their way to the base by helicopter, a team of policemen who were disguised as the crew of the proffered plane decided to abandon the dangerous mission. Once the copters landed, shooting erupted. The deaths quickly followed.</p>
        <p>Compounding the tragedy, the Germans announced that the hostages had been rescued, a report that was relayed around the world before it was superseded by the truth. The three surviving Palestinians were captured but were freed seven weeks later, exchanged for the passengers on a hijacked German airliner.</p>
        <p>Spitting out his lines like a righteous prosecutor, the film's narrator, Michael Douglas, says, ''Acting with indecent haste and without consulting the Israeli government, the Germans handed over the three prisoners.'' Quoting unnamed Palestinian sources, he says the hijacking was a setup concocted by the German authorities hoping to protect their country from further terrorism. No one could protect Mr. Gashey's two comrades, who were tracked down and killed by Israeli assassins. He is now hiding in an undisclosed African country.</p>
        <p>Given the power of its story, ''One Day in September'' seems at times to be pushing too hard. Having worked so diligently to lay out the facts, the filmmakers should have trusted them to make their impression. The production team might also have lightened up on the annoying pop tunes and other background music as well as those slow-motion shots of Olympic runners and hurdlers. Still, this is an important and properly disturbing film. Showing it now, as athletes gather again for the Olympics, is a potent reminder that despite all the talk about international brotherhood, the world remains not only small but dangerous.</p>
        <p>ONE DAY IN SEPTEMBER  HBO, tonight at 8</p>
        <p>Lillian Birnbaum, executive producer; directed by Kevin Macdonald; produced by Arthur Cohn and John Battsek; cinematography by Alwin Kuchler and Neve Cunningham; edited by Justine Wright; special stills photography by Raymond E. Depardon; Michael Douglas, narrator. An HBO Presentation of an Arthur Cohn Production. A Passion Picture Production.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
