<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Essay; Giving Putin a Veto</title>
    <meta content="11SAFI$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/11/opinion/11SAFI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229786"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E3DB1F39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="737" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Essay; Giving Putin a Veto</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire column scores Clinton administration for not pursuing deployment of missile defense system out of deference to Pres Vladimir Putin of Russia</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vladimir Putin, playing the weakest of hands, stopped the U.S. from beginning to build a defense against missiles from rogue nations and terrorists.</p>
        <p>President Clinton and Al Gore, holding all the high cards, folded and let the Russian obstruct a vital element of American defense of our major cities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vladimir Putin, playing the weakest of hands, stopped the U.S. from beginning to build a defense against missiles from rogue nations and terrorists.</p>
        <p>President Clinton and Al Gore, holding all the high cards, folded and let the Russian obstruct a vital element of American defense of our major cities.</p>
        <p>That's the plain meaning of the Clinton-Gore decision to overrule Defense Secretary Bill Cohen, who leaned toward making it possible to deploy a limited defense as soon as it is ready. The urgency is to have a shield in place before North Korea and Iraq build the means to blackmail us with too-credible threats of mass destruction.</p>
        <p>Clinton could have decided to press ahead. But that would have upset dovish Democrats and angered Putin, who claims the old ABM treaty gives him a veto over U.S. missile defenses. Contrariwise, Clinton could have decided to abort the anti-missile program entirely, risking not only the lives of millions but incurring the future ire of his successor caught in the agony of vulnerability.</p>
        <p>So, with Al Gore's full approval, he decided not to decide -- to kick that can into the future, couching his indecision as ''an opportunity for President Putin and the next American president to reach a common position.''</p>
        <p>Frankly, that was the best that missile defenders could expect from this administration. Jesse Helms made it clear that Senate Foreign Relations would ratify no appeasement of Moscow's desire to let outdated cold war restrictions slop over into the new millennium. Better no decision from Clinton at all -- which lets current testing continue, but without stating the truth about our intent to deploy -- than a decision to scuttle limited national missile defense.</p>
        <p>But then Bill Clinton went a concession too far. To accommodate Russia and placate China, Clinton is putting off construction of a radar facility that will be needed by the time our anti-missile system is ready. That's not ''not deciding''; on the contrary, it is a decision to delay that could well put American lives in danger for a year.</p>
        <p>Putin came to New York to accept this surrender, further sweetened by a half-billion-dollar U.S. Export-Import oil loan guarantee. As American diplomacy beat its retreat, he triumphantly invited the U.N. to Moscow next spring for a propaganda extravaganza to counter America's ''alarming . . . plans for the militarization of outer space.''</p>
        <p>We have here what should be a major issue in our presidential campaign. George W. Bush has spelled out his position: build and deploy the anti-missile system, which does not threaten Russia's deterrent, and not make it subject to a Putin veto.</p>
        <p>Al Gore takes the Clinton position: keep negotiating in hopes that Putin will change his mind and agree to amend the ABM treaty so as to allow the U.S. to deploy a shield against terrorist missiles -- perhaps too late.  Apparently Gore believes his powers of persuasion will be greater than Clinton's have been.</p>
        <p>But what if Putin strings Gore along the way he has diddled Clinton? If so, does Gore propose (a) to cave in, (b) to withdraw from the obsolete treaty, or (c) to continue the Clinton-Gore policy of kicking the can along while terrorists get the bomb and American cities lie defenseless? Will Gore propose more billions in loan guarantees to buy Putin's permission?</p>
        <p>Bush and his running mate should be hammering away at this survival issue. If Dick Cheney were the Republican serving in Clinton's cabinet, and if the President overruled him on the most important policy decision at the Pentagon, would he continue to serve and shut up? Cheney should call on the rebuffed defense secretary to put the public interest first, to step down and speak out.</p>
        <p>Only Putin is drawing the anti-missile issue, on his own terms, and to the U.S. detriment. He went on TV with Larry King to disinform Americans without rebuttal. At a 21 Club repast with media biggies, his missile comments were off the record and not followed up (though Maureen Orth of Vanity Fair reportedly dared to question him sharply on press repression).</p>
        <p>Would Gore continue this administration's feckless pursuit of Russian approval? Unless he becomes his own man and refuses to be vetoed, we have to assume Gore would continue Clinton's appeasement of Vladimir Putin.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
