<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MERTO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="11MBRF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229829"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3D91F39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MERTO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE STRUNSKY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: PARK SHOOTING REPORT INVESTIGATED -- Detectives are investigating a report by a man who said he was shot in the back while sitting on a bench in Central Park late Saturday night, the police said. The man, Troy Cupano, 33, of Somerset, N.J., arrived by cab at Mount Sinai Medical Center shortly before midnight Saturday. He had been shot once in the lower back with a small-caliber pistol, the police said. The authorities said he told detectives that he had been waiting for a friend near West Drive and West 100th Street when two men approached and fired one bullet. Mr. Cupano was in stable condition yesterday.</p>
        <p>C. J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: PARK SHOOTING REPORT INVESTIGATED -- Detectives are investigating a report by a man who said he was shot in the back while sitting on a bench in Central Park late Saturday night, the police said. The man, Troy Cupano, 33, of Somerset, N.J., arrived by cab at Mount Sinai Medical Center shortly before midnight Saturday. He had been shot once in the lower back with a small-caliber pistol, the police said. The authorities said he told detectives that he had been waiting for a friend near West Drive and West 100th Street when two men approached and fired one bullet. Mr. Cupano was in stable condition yesterday.</p>
        <p>C. J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>LAKE GEORGE: GASLIGHT VILLAGE GOES OUT -- One buyer paid $150 and ran away with the dish that ran away with the spoon. A Vermont couple paid $125,000 for a double-decker carousel made in Spain. In all, 430 pieces of nostalgia from the old Gaslight Village family amusement park here, including the dish lawn ornament and the carousel, sold for more than $1 million at an auction Saturday. Gaslight Village was opened in 1960 by Charles R. Wood in this lakeside resort 53 miles north of Albany. He closed it this year as part of a plan to build a civic center.  (AP)</p>
        <p>ALBANY: $750,000 FOR CONTAINER PORT -- Seeking to improve the local economy, Gov. George E. Pataki yesterday said the state would spend $750,000 to modify 2,000 feet of track this fall so barges from New York City can load shipping containers directly onto rail cars. Making Albany a barge-to-rail container port along the Hudson River would preserve 120 jobs and add 80 more by 2005, when the city could handle up to 24,000 containers annually, Mr. Pataki said.  (AP)</p>
        <p>ALBANY: FAMILY GROUP FAULTS AGENCY -- An advocacy group for poor families says the state is too quick to open and close investigations of child abuse. Two-thirds of the 145,500 abuse claims in 1998 were found to be unsubstantiated, while 40 percent of substantiated cases were closed the same day they were investigated, said the group, the State Communities Aid Association. The group called on the Child Protection Services division to develop a two-tiered response system, dispatching investigators to homes with potential for the most dangerous situations, and sending workers from social service agencies in other cases. Bill Van Slyke, a spokesman for the Office of Children and Family Services, which oversees Child Protection Services, said the agency was examining the group's findings.  (AP)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>FAIRFIELD: KENNEDY PLANE AUCTIONED -- Maybe mourning has not yet turned to nostalgia. Or maybe it was what some call the Kennedy curse. The high bid of $120,000 for John F. Kennedy Jr.'s first plane was well short of the $300,000 figure that auctioneers at Essex County Airport had used as an opening bid on Saturday. Mr. Kennedy sold the 1977 Cessna Skylane in May 1999, two months before crashing a more advanced Piper Saratoga off Martha's Vineyard. A used-car dealer from Tulsa, Okla., Jonathan Knoerdel, will fly the Cessna home for $138,000, including an $18,000 auction fee, unless the seller, who is anonymous, rejects the bid, said Louis B. Fisher III, the auctioneer. Mr. Fisher said the infamous curse discouraged at least one bidder. ''His wife didn't want him to buy it for that reason,'' he said.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>BRIGANTINE: GUARD JET ENGINE RECOVERED -- Work has begun to salvage the wreckage of a New Jersey Air National Guard jet that plunged into the Atlantic Ocean on Aug. 31 as people watched from the Atlantic City Boardwalk. The rear of the fuselage, the engine and the engine data recorder are among the parts recovered since the operation began on Saturday. The wreckage was discovered two days earlier in 35 feet of water about two miles east of here, said Maj. Roger Pharo, wing executive for the National Guard's 177th Fighter Wing. He said an accident investigation board convened by the Air Force could issue a report on the crash within six weeks. The pilot, who was praised by superiors for safely ditching the F-16C Falcon after the engine faltered, bailed out and sustained minor injuries.  (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEWARK: TWO MOTORCYCLISTS KILLED -- Two men riding motorcycles were killed on the New Jersey Turnpike after they drove off an elevated ramp and fell 33 feet, the state police said. The two men were traveling at ''excessive speed'' in Newark on Saturday night when they crashed through a guardrail on a ramp leading from the Newark Bay Extension to the turnpike at Exit 14, the police said. William Bouyea, 25, of Valley Stream, N.Y., died at the scene. Dwight Anthony Crooks, 27, of Brooklyn died at University Hospital in Newark, the police said. A third rider, Marshall Brown, 27, of Rochester, N.Y., who crashed but did not fall, was listed in stable condition at the hospital last night.  (AP)</p>
        <p>SOUTH BRUNSWICK: SOCCER PARENTS BRAWL -- A soccer game between teams of 8- and 9-year-old boys led to a brawl among a dozen parents and coaches over a tie-breaking shootout, the police said. The incident began when a coach from a Staten Island team argued that a coach of a regional team from northern Hunterdon County could not stand behind the goal during the shootout. The argument turned into a fistfight when parents and coaches joined in, said the police, who intervened before anyone was seriously hurt. No children were involved in the fight, and neither team was awarded a victory.  (AP)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT: $270 MILLION UNCLAIMED -- Residents can use the Internet to see if any of $270 million in unclaimed assets held by the state is theirs. This morning, State Treasurer Denise Nappier will unveil a Web site -- www.nameitandclaimit.org -- listing 500,000 people who failed to claim cash, uncashed paychecks and other assets. These assets, found in bank accounts, with employers or in other places, are typically turned over to the Treasury after three years. For Spanish speakers, a phone line, (800) 618-3404, has been added for the same purpose. And on Wednesday, Connecticut's daily newspapers will carry ads showing 29,000 names added to the list this year, said Bernard Kavaler, a treasury spokesman.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
