<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pesky Themes Will Emerge When You're Not Looking</title>
    <meta content="11JOHN$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/11/arts/11JOHN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Writers on Writing" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WRITERS ON WRITING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Diane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Writers on Writing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFD71E39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1732" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pesky Themes Will Emerge When You're Not Looking</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANE JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Diane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Diane Johnson, in Writers on Writing series, discusses matter of themes in novels, and who should determine what they are, author or reader; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I've been going around doing readings from a new novel (''Le Mariage''), and often, on these occasions, I've been asked surprising questions about its themes. At first I was somewhat confounded by this. The novelist may be the last to know the theme of her work, may even have avoided thinking about it too particularly, lest, like happiness, it disappear on too close examination or seem too thin and flimsy to live.</p>
        <p>In Seattle a man asked me what the theme of rescued cats and dogs in my books meant. I had to think about that, because I hadn't really noticed they there there. Freud would say those cats and dogs are children, but that doesn't seem quite right to me.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I've been going around doing readings from a new novel (''Le Mariage''), and often, on these occasions, I've been asked surprising questions about its themes. At first I was somewhat confounded by this. The novelist may be the last to know the theme of her work, may even have avoided thinking about it too particularly, lest, like happiness, it disappear on too close examination or seem too thin and flimsy to live.</p>
        <p>In Seattle a man asked me what the theme of rescued cats and dogs in my books meant. I had to think about that, because I hadn't really noticed they there there. Freud would say those cats and dogs are children, but that doesn't seem quite right to me.</p>
        <p>Must a novel have a theme? If so, who is in charge of it?</p>
        <p>You can't help but wonder if each writer has themes typical to him, if the themes are as particular to the writer as to the work. To read, as I have, of my own books, that they are full of desperate women fleeing their circumstances, greatly surprised this contented and settled housewife. Certainly I have never thought of them that way. To me, my heroines are interpretive consciousnesses through whom to observe external events, in Iran, California or France.</p>
        <p>I have written elsewhere about the plight of the reliable female narrator, a modern innovation perhaps, for whom we are unprepared by a literary tradition of heroines who were only acted upon. My friend Max Byrd says that all fiction can be reduced to one of two plots: a stranger comes to town, or someone goes on a trip. And mine are the latter, that's all, about travelers to whom things happen, as things will.</p>
        <p>But that's not all about them. Any novel has lots of themes, if I understand the word correctly. It seems like a holdover term from high school English class, useful for discussing novels, but not very relevant to the process of writing them. There's something too close to ''thesis'' about it; the idea of imposing a preconception is anathema to a novelist who likes to imagine she is observing life and manners without any didactic intention and without forcing her characters to follow a plan.</p>
        <p>Of course a writer, like anybody, has a set of general ideas: the inhumanity of man to man, or that life is a struggle, or that nature is beautiful. Some of the ideas will be received ideas; some may be original or idiosyncratic or even suspect, as was said of Ayn Rand's, for instance, or some of T. S. Eliot's, or Pound's. Taken together, a writer's themes are thought to typify the writer despite him- or herself, except for protean geniuses like Shakespeare, invisible in the dense thicket of their contradictions.</p>
        <p>I suppose the major theme of a given work is the sum of all its ideas. That's implicit in those joke contests on the Internet about Merged Novels, in which people compress the essence of two books into one, like ''The Maltese Faulkner.'' (''Is the black bird a tortured symbol of Sam's struggles with race and family? Or is it merely a crow, mocking his attempts to understand? Or is it worth a cool mil?'') Or ''Catch-22 in the Rye.'' (''Holden learns that if you're insane, you'll probably flunk out of prep school, but if you're flunking out of prep school, you're probably not insane.'')</p>
        <p>But every novel is a ''spongy tract,'' as E. M. Forster put it, a tissue of ideas so dense and various it would be impossible to tease them all out.</p>
        <p>Too many themes and the novelist risks committing a ''novel of ideas,'' a term that can conceal a note of reservation. As a phrase, ''novel of ideas'' is gathered from what seems now a somewhat dated typology used to categorize all novels as ''of ideas,'' or as comedy of manners, or action, romance and so on, depending on the general effect. These were also shorthand ways of saying serious, boring, comic, moving account of personal anguish, love story, etc.</p>
        <p>Even while there is a liking for the glib identification of themes, there is a resistance to the idea of ideas in novels. Two examples from my own experience:</p>
        <p>The British publisher of ''Le Divorce,'' a novel about a young woman's coming to worldliness in Paris, omitted an entire chapter wherein Americans in Paris in about 1995 fall into a bitter dispute about the Vietnam War, a subject still dividing us after 30 years. The publisher thought this would not be interesting to an British audience. Now people ask how I could have been so docile about allowing this omission, and the answer is, I don't know. Maybe I was still insecure about that theme.</p>
        <p>Another time, a French translator, under the impression that ''Persian Nights,'' a novel about the political situation in prerevolutionary Iran, was a bodice-ripper, a genre the French are fond of, omitted all the heroine's observations of the political scene and stressed all her moments of personal danger, preferably the risk of rape (which in fact never came up). Here I did protest, and the problem was partly fixed.</p>
        <p>Several reviewers of Susan Sontag's new novel ''In America'' have used the expression ''novel of ideas,'' perhaps because the characters have ideas about Fourier's utopianism, or methods of acting, and discuss them. But you have to wonder what a novel without ideas would be like? One idea or theme in, say, Forster's ''Passage to India'' is that people from different cultures rarely understand one another. Reduced to this simple statement, ''Passage to India'' has the same theme as many novels that many other writers, including me in ''Le Mariage,'' have tried to write.</p>
        <p>In its particulars of course ''Passage to India'' is utterly unlike any other novel. Is it a novel of ideas or a comedy of manners? The characters discuss philosophy. ''When evil occurs, it expresses the whole of the universe,'' says the Indian Professor Godpole. Asked if he means that good and evil are the same, he says: ''Oh, no. . . . good and evil are different, as their names imply. But, in my humble opinion, they are both of them aspects of my Lord.'' He is talking to  Fielding, for whom good and evil seem expressions of the indifference of the universe. Where does Forster stand in this difference of opinion? Does he take a stand?</p>
        <p>Can the novelist entirely control the ideas in her text, or conceal herself among them? There's the phenomenon well known to writers whose characters, given their head, take off and do or say things the writer did not foresee. The writing has a Ouija board will of its own.</p>
        <p>On the other hand there are the covert operations of your own character -- your personal obsessions, perhaps -- that ordain that, however you start out, you end up with the sort of novel only you would write. (Obviously these two are functions of each other: the unexpected crops up out of some less conscious realm of your self.) There's age, birth order, geography. Nationality is certainly part of the imperatives of our natures, something that we can't help and that has programmed us.</p>
        <p>Of course you yourself can change with the years, with the events life deals you. I feel myself constantly struggling against some imperative of my own nature that dictates that no matter how much I want to write a serious, moving psychological novel, I end up with the sort of comic or tragicomic novel I have seen referred to as ''of manners,'' reflecting my interest -- and it is true that I'm interested in manners -- in the way people behave and especially the way people behave when out of their own culture, or how people in other cultures behave.</p>
        <p>But novels are never about what they are about; that is, there is always deeper, or more general, significance. The author may not be aware of this till she is pretty far along with it. A novel's whole pattern is rarely apparent at the outset of writing, or even at the end; that is when the writer finds out what a novel is about, and the job becomes one of understanding and deepening or sharpening what is already written. That is finding the theme.</p>
        <p>If the writer is the last to identify the theme, probably we as readers don't consciously articulate the theme as we read either. When we are asked what a book is about, we tend to focus on some element of the plot, to say, ''It's about a woman who was or wasn't molested in a cave in India,'' or ''an orphan who has to work as a governess in a wild, remote house.''</p>
        <p>We fasten on the principal feature of the action. But what we get out of a book is the lesson or the theme: courage, the indomitability of the human spirit in the case of ''Jane Eyre'' (and all the works of Charlotte Bronte) and in ''A Passage to India'' things about integrity and pride, especially on the part of the misfit. These deep messages are the satisfying qualities that make us admire a book.</p>
        <p>If a book had a wicked or meretricious message, we might reject or mistrust it, or in some way feel it to be subversive. Or we might be taken in by it, briefly. History is full of ''dangerous'' books, though they never prevail. But attempts to suppress them always eventually backfire, too. The moral careers of books are always fascinating.</p>
        <p>Writers on Writing</p>
        <p>This article is part of a series in which writers explore literary themes. Previous contributions, including essays by John Updike, E. L. Doctorow, Ed McBain, Annie Proulx, Jamaica Kincaid, Saul Bellow and others, can be found with this article at The New York Times on the Web: www.nytimes.com/arts</p>
        <p>WRITERS ON WRITING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
