<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Track and Field</title>
    <meta content="11XTRA$32" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/11/olympics/11XTRAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229712"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="2000 SYDNEY GAMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E7D81E39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Track and Field</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jere Longman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Preview of Sydney Olympics track and field events; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>POPULAR IN Europe but largely off the American radar screen between Olympic years, track and field continues to be the flagship sport of the Games. This year there is added spice as Marion Jones attempts to become the first woman in track and field to win five gold medals in one Olympics. Cold, windy weather may prevent any world records.</p>
        <p>THE WOMEN -- Jones will attempt to win golds at 100 meters, 200 meters, the long jump, the 4 x 100-meter relay and the 4 x 400-meter relay. The record for women is four golds won by Fanny Blankers-Koen of the Netherlands in 1948. Jones's weakest event is the long jump.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>POPULAR IN Europe but largely off the American radar screen between Olympic years, track and field continues to be the flagship sport of the Games. This year there is added spice as Marion Jones attempts to become the first woman in track and field to win five gold medals in one Olympics. Cold, windy weather may prevent any world records.</p>
        <p>THE WOMEN -- Jones will attempt to win golds at 100 meters, 200 meters, the long jump, the 4 x 100-meter relay and the 4 x 400-meter relay. The record for women is four golds won by Fanny Blankers-Koen of the Netherlands in 1948. Jones's weakest event is the long jump.</p>
        <p>Her top competition in the sprints is her fellow American Inger Miller, whose father, Lennox, won two sprinting medals for Jamaica. Miller came within a hundredth of a second of defeating Jones in a 100-meter sprint in Stockholm this summer. Otherwise, she has not seriously threatened her. Last year, after Jones was injured, Miller won the world championship at 200 meters in 21.77 seconds, faster than Jones ran all season.</p>
        <p>Others who could spoil Jones's sprinting hopes are Merlene Ottey of Jamaica, Christine Arron of France and Zhanna Pintusevich-Block of Ukraine. But Jones hasn't lost a sprint final in three years, and it seems unlikely she will lose the 100 or 200 in Sydney. But she is hardly the favorite in the long jump. Fiona May of Italy and Tatyana Kotova of Russia have jumped farther than a struggling Jones has this season.</p>
        <p>The women's pole vault will be contested for the first time in the Olympics, and Stacy Dragila of the United States is the world record-holder at 15 feet 2 1/4 inches.</p>
        <p>In the distance events, Suzy Favor Hamilton will attempt to become the first American woman to win the 1,500 meters. Her chances improved with the withdrawal of Regina Jacobs, the Olympic trials winner, who has a viral infection. But Svetlana Masterkova of Russia, the reigning Olympic champion, is back to defend her title after surgery on both Achilles' tendons. This is the only distance longer than 400 meters in which an American man or woman is considered a medal candidate. Maria Mutola of Mozambique, who lives in Springfield, Ore., will try to win the 800 meters against the Clark family -- the sisters Hazel Clark and Joetta Clark-Diggs and their sister-in-law Jearl Miles-Clark.</p>
        <p>The women's marathon should be one of the most engaging events, featuring the world record-holder Tegla Loroupe of Kenya and the defending champion, Fatuma Roba of Ethiopia.</p>
        <p>THE MEN -- The luster of the sprints has been dulled by cramping injuries to Michael Johnson and Maurice Greene that caused both of them to withdraw during the 200 meters at the Olympic trials in July. But both sprinters have recovered and are still favored to win two gold medals apiece. Greene, the world record-holder in the 100 at 9.79 seconds, has regained his dominance on the European circuit and will anchor the 4 x 100 relay, which should bring a gold medal. Barring another injury, Johnson appears unbeatable at 400 meters. He holds the world record of 43.18 seconds and has lost the event only three times in 11 years. If the early spring weather cooperates, Johnson believes he could run 42 seconds at the Games.</p>
        <p>One of the most redemptive moments of the Sydney Games should occur in the men's 1,500 meters, where the world record-holder Hicham el-Guerrouj of Morocco is heavily favored. Entering the final lap of the metric mile at the 1996 Atlanta Olympics, el-Guerrouj prepared to make his move into first place, only to tangle with another runner and fall. He has lost only one race since.</p>
        <p>The 800 meters will finally have Wilson Kipketer of Denmark in the field after a long saga. A native of Kenya, Kipketer moved to Denmark a decade ago. He would have been favored to win in Atlanta, but he was not yet a Danish citizen, and he declined to run for Kenya. He has since set the world record but may not be fully recovered from a bout of malaria that ruined his 1998 season.</p>
        <p>In the shot put, C. J. Hunter, Jones's husband, may not compete after recent knee surgery. The Dartmouth graduate Adam Nelson is the favorite.</p>
        <p>Jere Longman</p>
        <p>2000 SYDNEY GAMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
