<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Experts Fear a Brutal Season For Heating in the Northeast</title>
    <meta content="11HEAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/11/nyregion/11HEAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229776"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northeastern States (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E3DC1F39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1402" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Experts Fear a Brutal Season For Heating in the Northeast</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Northeast faces what could be particulatly brutal heating season; shortage of natural gas is sending wholesale prices soaring; regional forces, especially steep drop in Northeast heating oil inventories and predictions of colder autumn and winter, are likely to compound effect of high prices (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was perhaps only natural, as chilly, fall-like air flowed into the New York region last week -- capping a much cooler than normal summer -- to let out a sigh of relief. Electricity experts had predicted power failures and brownouts, but neither happened. Bills went up, but not as much as they could have, because air-conditioners were not running round the clock.</p>
        <p>But don't gloat just yet. Energy experts and meteorologists say that the Northeast, for reasons as varied as the patterns of Canadian arctic air flow and decisions made by oil refiners in the Midwest and oil buyers in Germany, is now facing what could be a particularly brutal heating season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was perhaps only natural, as chilly, fall-like air flowed into the New York region last week -- capping a much cooler than normal summer -- to let out a sigh of relief. Electricity experts had predicted power failures and brownouts, but neither happened. Bills went up, but not as much as they could have, because air-conditioners were not running round the clock.</p>
        <p>But don't gloat just yet. Energy experts and meteorologists say that the Northeast, for reasons as varied as the patterns of Canadian arctic air flow and decisions made by oil refiners in the Midwest and oil buyers in Germany, is now facing what could be a particularly brutal heating season.</p>
        <p>Much of the problem, they say, is broad and national: a shortage of natural gas, the most common heating fuel nationwide, sent wholesale prices last week to a level that market researchers say has never been reached in early September, nearly double what it was a year ago.</p>
        <p>Regional forces, however, especially a steep drop in Northeast heating-oil inventories and what some forecasters predict will be a sharply colder autumn in the Northeast, are likely to compound the effect of those high prices.</p>
        <p>Although no utility or regulatory body is predicting an actual shortage of fuel oil or natural gas for the region, the public anxiety over the price and availability of a commodity that most people consider a necessity is almost certain to keep the energy issue on the front burner. The economic tumult of a deregulated electricity market in New York State, the key energy issue of this summer, will be heightened in winter by the strategies of petrochemical traders around the world.</p>
        <p>''It's a bit of Murphy's Law -- a lot of little things have gone wrong,'' said Sarah Emerson, the managing director of Energy Security Analysis Inc., a research and consulting firm in Wakefield, Mass.</p>
        <p>Last month, for example, the price of No. 2 heating oil -- used primarily in homes -- arriving in New York Harbor reached its highest level in nearly 10 years: more than $36 a barrel, up 59 percent from August 1999. At the same time, the regional oil inventory, called days of supply, reached its lowest level since 1996, and inventories in August were 47 percent below the level of a year ago. The monthly average wholesale price of natural gas on the New York market was also up about 59 percent from August 1999.</p>
        <p>KeySpan Energy, the region's largest provider of natural gas, warned its customers in July, even before the latest price surge, that this winter's bills would be 12 percent to 15 percent higher than last winter's. And one of the first long-range weather forecasts for the region, issued late last month, said that temperatures in the New York region this fall would be much cooler than last year.</p>
        <p>The emerging winter's tale of energy in New York City is also vastly more complicated than this summer's. In June, July and August, the key questions were how hot the weather would get and whether the electricity supply would be able to handle the demand. The new terrain is as unpredictable as the next northeaster. Energy experts said the heating-oil inventory problem, for instance, could resolve itself suddenly with a vast increase in supplies in midwinter, as sellers from around the world rush to capitalize on high prices. Or the problem could be compounded as sellers try to play the market, holding back oil and choking off supply even more as they wait for higher prices to come.</p>
        <p>The reach of the global economy also explains why reserves have fallen so low already. Because the price of gasoline was high in the Midwest this summer, refinery owners found that making plain old heating oil just did not pay. At the same time, Germany went on a buying binge to bolster its oil reserves, taking much of the European supply. A fire at a Kuwaiti oil field cut back the trans-Atlantic oil flow even more. A commodities-trading phenomenon that sounds like a new dance craze, contango, in which traders bet that prices will drop in the future, gave oil distributors little incentive to stockpile oil. With the heating season only weeks away, inventories in the mid-Atlantic states were nearly 40 percent below the 1990's average for this time of year.</p>
        <p>But however it happened, low inventories in the Northeast have become a factor in the price of energy.</p>
        <p>''When you have very low inventories, there are ripple effects,'' said Kevin Lindemer, a senior director at Cambridge Energy Research Associates, a research and consulting firm in Cambridge, Mass. ''Unexpected things can cause price fluctuations.''</p>
        <p>During one winter in the early 1990's, for example, high winds kept oil barges from docking in New York for weeks. But that was not a problem then because reserves were twice as high as they are now. In other winters, iced-over rivers or snow-clogged streets hampered oil deliveries, but the problem did not make the front page because supplies were ample. This year, Mr. Lindemer said, bad weather that affects deliveries could be as much of a factor as bad weather that makes people use more fuel.</p>
        <p>Another important factor in the energy price picture is that the mix of fuels in the region has changed. Demand for natural gas in the Northeast has soared in recent years and is expected to climb further, altering the chemistry of a region that long had a national distinction for its dependence on heating oil. All the new electricity-generating plants in the region, for example, burn natural gas, and the ones being proposed will also burn natural gas. And customers of KeySpan have been requesting conversions from oil to gas in record numbers this year, the company says. All those extra buyers of natural gas could push prices up if national supplies remain tight.</p>
        <p>New York State and the federal government have both taken steps to smooth out potential bumps. The Clinton administration said late last month that it had reached agreements to bring two million barrels, or 84 million gallons, of heating oil into New Jersey and Connecticut to bolster reserves. And although most energy analysts said the added oil would dampen price increases, others said the new supply could make some suppliers complacent about building up their own inventories.</p>
        <p>The New York State Public Service Commission, which regulates energy delivery companies, issued rules last month requiring some big energy customers, especially industrial users that can switch from one fuel to another, to increase their oil reserves now so that sudden surges in demand caused by switching will not unbalance the markets. A spokesman for KeySpan said the company was training two dozen inspectors to make sure that customers comply with the rules.</p>
        <p>The weather, of course, is the biggest variable of all. Energycast, an online energy and weather-forecasting service, said late last month that the daily average temperature for November in New York would be 39.6 degrees, 4.4 degrees colder than last year's daily average for November. On the other hand, the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, which also issues long-range forecasts, has said the fall and early winter forecast in the Northeast is too uncertain to call.</p>
        <p>Behind all these variables is a certain mystery. The oil inventories that are reported to government agencies and energy consultants are based on huge wholesale stockpiles, not on the more precise numbers from local companies, which do not have to tell anyone what they have. If a supplier admitted to sitting on a lot of oil, market analysts say, his customers could reasonably ask why their bills were so high. So the suppliers speak in a kind of code.</p>
        <p>''They say, 'I'm wet,' which means, 'I have product,' or, 'I'm dry,' which means they don't have any,'' said Tom Collins, a spokesman for the New York State Energy Research and Development Authority. ''That's all you have to work with.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
