<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South Korean Says North Agrees U.S. Troops Should Stay</title>
    <meta content="Y11KOR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/11/world/11KORE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North Korea-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">South Korea-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North Korea-International Relations-South Korea</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kim Jong Il</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kim Dae Jung (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEFDA1F39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1312" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South Korean Says North Agrees U.S. Troops Should Stay</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with South Korean Pres Kim Dae Jung, who says most important outcome of his summit with North Korean Pres Kim Jong Il in June was common understanding American troops must stay in South Korea to prevent power vacuum on Korean peninsula that would be inviting to its neighbors; Kim says Communist government wants normal relations with US; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most important outcome of his summit conference with North Korea in June, President Kim Dae Jung of South Korea says, was a common understanding that American troops must stay in South Korea to prevent a vacuum on the Korean peninsula that would be inviting to its neighbors.</p>
        <p>''We are surrounded by big powers -- Russia, Japan and China -- so the United States must continue to stay for stability and peace in East Asia,'' he said. Mr. Kim said he was recounting almost the exact words of his counterpart, Kim Jong Il, in North Korea during their meetings in Pyongyang.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The most important outcome of his summit conference with North Korea in June, President Kim Dae Jung of South Korea says, was a common understanding that American troops must stay in South Korea to prevent a vacuum on the Korean peninsula that would be inviting to its neighbors.</p>
        <p>''We are surrounded by big powers -- Russia, Japan and China -- so the United States must continue to stay for stability and peace in East Asia,'' he said. Mr. Kim said he was recounting almost the exact words of his counterpart, Kim Jong Il, in North Korea during their meetings in Pyongyang.</p>
        <p>The Communist government in North Korea, whose hostility has been cited by the Clinton administration as a major reason for pursuing a missile defense system, wants normal relations with United States, Kim Dae Jung said.</p>
        <p>''I believe that North Korea wants improved relations with the United States,'' Mr. Kim said on Saturday in an interview at his Manhattan hotel at the end of the gathering of world leaders at the United Nations. ''That is their basic goal. If it is not their basic goal, there is no reason why they should change their position on American forces.''</p>
        <p>The mantra of Communist propaganda since the end of Korean War has been that American troops must leave South Korea. So the North Korean leader's support of their staying is a reversal of position -- albeit one that Pyongyang has not yet acknowledged in public.</p>
        <p>After a peace treaty replaces the armistice now in place between the two Koreas, the presence of American troops in South Korea and on the Japanese island of Okinawa would operate ''under the same logic'' that governed the continuing presence of American troops in Europe as part of NATO after the collapse of the Soviet Union, the South Korean president suggested.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim, a human rights dissident who was put on death row by the South Korean military junta and then survived to become the democratically elected president, spoke eloquently of what he saw as the steady but long journey to bring the two Koreas together.</p>
        <p>During his visit here, Mr. Kim, 75, was a sought-after figure: he met privately with President Clinton, he answered questions from Democratic and Republican experts who are advising the two presidential candidates on Asia and he delivered a speech at a Korea Society event.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim, dapper in a blue suit and pink tie, said he was encouraged that Republican and Democratic experts supported the continued presence of American troops on the peninsula.</p>
        <p>Overall, he said it was impossible to predict the speed and substance of what would happen. ''No one predicted unification in Germany so suddenly,'' he said in the interview. But for the moment, he said, the goal in Korea is not unification between the totalitarian regime in the North and the democratic government of the South. Even it that were to occur, he said, ''it would create a lot of negative consequences.''</p>
        <p>By the end of his term in a little more than two years, he wants to see ''peace, cooperation and exchanges'' with North Korea, cemented by a peace treaty, he said. But to get even that far, he added, South Korea needs help from its allies.</p>
        <p>''For things to progress smoothly, there must be improved relations between the United States and North Korea, between North Korea and the European Union and between North Korea and Japan,'' he said. ''We cannot carry on this process on our own.''</p>
        <p>One important step toward better United States-North Korean relations, he said, would be looking seriously at the suggestion by Kim Jong Il that North Korea is willing to curb its missile program in exchange for financing that would allow it to launch satellites.</p>
        <p>The North Koreans first broached the idea this summer to the Russian president, Vladimir V. Putin, who discussed it with President Clinton in July. Since then, American officials have held talks with Moscow on exactly what North Korea had in mind. Senior administration officials said last week that the idea appeared to be worth pursuing but that the United States needed to ensure that it did not involve the transfer of technological advances to the North Koreans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim said he had spoken to President Clinton in their meeting this week about the possibility of a satellites-for-missiles deal. Mr. Kim said he believed that the North Korean suggestion would ''serve as the basis'' for the ongoing negotiations between North Korea and the United States on Pyongyang's missile program.</p>
        <p>On the financing of the satellite launchings, Mr. Kim said it was not clear to him whether the North Koreans were seeking assistance from the United States or from multilateral sources.</p>
        <p>But one aspect is clear, he said. Although the North's leader suggested three satellite launchings a year at the cost of $300 million each, ''the experts on our side say that the rocket launches do not cost as much as the chairman says.''</p>
        <p>Once relations between the United States and North Korea improve, Mr. Kim said, there will be enough confidence for wealthy nations, multilateral institutions -- the International Monetary Fund, the Asia Development Bank -- and private investors to help develop the moribund North Korean economy.</p>
        <p>The South Korean government does not have the resources to carry the burden of investment in the north, but will encourage the country's businesses to plunge ahead, he said.</p>
        <p>Since the summit conference in June, officials from South and North Korea have started working on a basic economic framework to encourage investment in the North, he said. The steps include investment guarantees, avoidance of double taxation and dispute arbitration, he said.</p>
        <p>Officials from the defense ministries on both sides are scheduled to meet to discuss measures to reduce tension. Those would include observations by each side of the other's military exercises and exchanges of information on each other's troop movements.</p>
        <p>Talking of the peace treaty that he said he hoped he would sign with North Korea before leaving office in 2003, Mr. Kim said the United States and China, who were also combatants in the Korean War, would play ''supporting roles'' without being signers.</p>
        <p>By the time he leaves office, he said, he wants to see North Korea as a ''responsible member of the international community.''</p>
        <p>In economics, he hopes there will be ''significant'' cooperation between the United States and North Korea. The North, he suggested, could follow the model of China and North Vietnam, where ''the economy is very successfully opened'' but the political system remains intact.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim said the North Korean leader might visit Seoul as early as this fall, but more likely next spring. A close aide to Kim Jong Il arrived in Seoul today to discuss the visit, Agence France-Presse reported.</p>
        <p>As the moves towards normal relations unfold, there are seemingly small bumps that require considerable effort to overcome.</p>
        <p>One occurred at the start of the United Nations gathering, when the second most powerful leader in North Korea, Kim Yong Nam, angrily turned back home after being put through a body search at Frankfurt Airport by employees of an American airline.</p>
        <p>The South Korean president was supposed to meet with the North Korean in New York as part of the reconciliation process. So he asked President Clinton for his help in calming the insulted North Koreans.</p>
        <p>On Friday, Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright announced that the North Koreans had accepted the apologies and that the North Korean foreign minister, Paek Nam Sun, would be coming to the United Nations this week. But he will arrive after President Kim leaves New York.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
