<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Basketball</title>
    <meta content="11XBAS$42" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/11/olympics/11XBASK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229730"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="2000 SYDNEY GAMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E7D71E39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Basketball</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mike Wise</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article in special section on Sydney Olympics discusses outlook for men's and women's basketball at Games; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FORTY AND 0. Since the United States was first represented by National Basketball Association players in 1992, Olympic men's basketball has been a coronation rather than a competition.</p>
        <p>The Dream Team moniker should have been done away with after Magic, Jordan and Bird teamed for gold eight years ago. Still, you can't bet against a crew featuring Vince Carter, Kevin Garnett and Jason Kidd. Even with only one natural center, Alonzo Mourning, the American men are not in serious trouble.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FORTY AND 0. Since the United States was first represented by National Basketball Association players in 1992, Olympic men's basketball has been a coronation rather than a competition.</p>
        <p>The Dream Team moniker should have been done away with after Magic, Jordan and Bird teamed for gold eight years ago. Still, you can't bet against a crew featuring Vince Carter, Kevin Garnett and Jason Kidd. Even with only one natural center, Alonzo Mourning, the American men are not in serious trouble.</p>
        <p>As for the United States women, that's another story. The Australian men and women could both win a medal, with the women possibly pushing the United States for gold. A team featuring Lisa Leslie, Sheryl Swoopes and the five-time Olympian Teresa Edwards should be a lock. But lack of practice time because of commitments for the Women's National Basketball Association and stiff competition from the host country, Russia, Brazil and Cuba may prove too much of a task. Unlike the men, they can be beaten.</p>
        <p>THE SETUP -- The United States men have a virtual cakewalk in the first three games of the preliminary round, opening with China, Italy and a watered-down Lithuania. Russia, Yugoslavia and Australia will mix it up in Group B, with the highest-seeded survivor eventually advancing to face the United States for the gold medal.</p>
        <p>Here is one personal setup: Mourning is actually leaving the Games on Sept. 22 for his home in Miami and is not scheduled to return to Sydney until Sept. 26. He is flying 9,330 miles round trip so that his wife, Tracy Wilson-Mourning, can give birth by induced labor to the couple's child. Apparently, Coach Rudy Tomjanovich is not too concerned with the inside game of either New Zealand or France, the two opponents Mourning will miss.</p>
        <p>THE WOMEN -- The Australians, who won the bronze in 1996, feature not only the former Olympians Michele Timms, Carla Boyd and Michelle Griffiths but also Lauren Jackson, a 19-year-old wunderkind who figures to be the first pick in the 2001 W.N.B.A. draft. She gives the host country a good shot at competing for a medal.</p>
        <p>She stands 6 feet 5 inches, can post up or play on the perimeter and her ponytail belies her ferocity. Jackson elbowed Lisa Leslie during an exhibition last fall. The two jawed at one another. Jackson said afterward: ''I'm not going to sit back and let some Lisa Leslie go at me. I really don't care what she says to me because one day I'll be as good as her.''</p>
        <p>At some point, Sheryl Swoopes may have to match up against Brazil's Janeth Arcain, her Comets teammate.</p>
        <p>If they don't falter in the preliminary round and find a way to claw past Brazil, the Aussies could find themselves in a spirited game for the gold against a United States team still trying to find the perfect chemistry over a short period of time.</p>
        <p>THE MEN -- The lack of marquee players stands out. Beyond the absences of Shaquille O'Neal, Kobe Bryant, Tim Duncan and Grant Hill from the United States, neither Rick Fox nor Jamaal Magloire, a 2000 N.B.A. draft pick, will play for Canada. Vlade Divac is not playing for Yugoslavia. And injuries to Arvydas Sabonis, Zydrunas Ilgauskas and Arturas Karnisovas cripple Lithuania's chances. Croatia, which could have featured Toni Kukoc,  did not even qualify.</p>
        <p>France's 7-1 Frederic Weis, whom the Knicks chose with the 15th pick in the 1999 draft but who has yet to play an N.B.A. game, and China's 7-foot Wang Zhizhi, taken in the second round of the '99 draft by Dallas, will play and make for some good conversation. Zhizhi, his 7-4 teammate Yao Ming and the 6-11 Menk Bater have been christened by the Asian news media as the ''Walking Great Wall.''</p>
        <p>Still after the Vinsanity dunk-a-thon has ended, the quest is for silver again on the men's side.</p>
        <p>A weakened European field could enable the Australian men to finally win a basketball medal. Like Teresa Edwards, Andrew Gaze is a five-time Olympian. Chris Anstey, Luc Longley and Shane Heal give the Aussie men three more players with N.B.A. experience. If either team advances to the gold-medal game, expect the Sydney Superdome to shake. The United States could be susceptible to a perimeter team that starts knocking down 3-pointers and builds a quick lead.</p>
        <p>And if either Mourning or Gary Payton blows a fuse at a key juncture, who knows? The American men do not have to worry about overconfidence, but keeping their composure could be a chore.</p>
        <p>Mike Wise</p>
        <p>2000 SYDNEY GAMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
