<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Degrees of Separation For Coach and Indiana</title>
    <meta content="Y11BER$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/11/sports/11BERK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229790"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berkow, Ira</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knight, Bob</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Ira Berkow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E0DB1F39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1022" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Degrees of Separation For Coach and Indiana</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berkow, Ira</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ira Berkow Sports of The Times column discusses dismissal of Indiana University basketball coach Bob Knight; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ZERO tolerance, after nearly 29 years of maximum tolerance at Indiana University, may not have much wiggle room. And after an incident last May -- one of scores involving Bob Knight over the years -- the president of the university, Myles Brand, said that Knight deserved a ''last chance.'' If he does anything that is deemed embarrassing to the school, Brand said, he will be dismissed.</p>
        <p>And Bob Knight seemingly, and perhaps finally, understood the possible ramifications of zero tolerance when he conducted a news conference on Friday to explain his grabbing an Indiana student by the arm and, possibly, spewing profanity at him. The student had said, ''Hey, what's up, Knight?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ZERO tolerance, after nearly 29 years of maximum tolerance at Indiana University, may not have much wiggle room. And after an incident last May -- one of scores involving Bob Knight over the years -- the president of the university, Myles Brand, said that Knight deserved a ''last chance.'' If he does anything that is deemed embarrassing to the school, Brand said, he will be dismissed.</p>
        <p>And Bob Knight seemingly, and perhaps finally, understood the possible ramifications of zero tolerance when he conducted a news conference on Friday to explain his grabbing an Indiana student by the arm and, possibly, spewing profanity at him. The student had said, ''Hey, what's up, Knight?''</p>
        <p>Knight apparently stopped the freshman, who was buying football tickets with friends, and admittedly held his arm and said: ''Son, my name is not Knight to you. It's Coach Knight or it's Mr. Knight.'' The student, Kent Harvey, said that the grip was so tight that Knight's nails broke the skin on his arm.</p>
        <p>Mike Davis, an assistant coach for Knight, witnessed this and said, ''The grip was more like shaking hands.'' Some handshake, apparently.</p>
        <p>Knight, who turns 60 soon, his gray hair cut short, a palpable paunch under his red sweater, on Friday drew a diagram on the chalkboard to demonstrate the closeness of having to pass the student in a corridor. He even desperately invoked a scene in church when he was a youngster -- ''some people may not believe that I was ever in church'' -- and talked about a high school coach of his who taught him the lesson of respecting elders. A lesson, it is apparent, that Knight has frequently forgotten.</p>
        <p>But there he was, with a look in his eyes that reminded me of Richard Nixon trying to explain misdeeds -- Pat's Republican cloth coat and that poor dog Checkers -- a look, that is, of being trapped when guilty.</p>
        <p>The fact is, Knight is a full professor at a highly regarded university. The fact that he is a coach of a basketball team that has won three National Collegiate Athletic Association titles, and that he has won more Division I games than any other active coach, is beside the point. If an English professor or a dean of students acted as Knight has over the years, he would surely have been out long ago. If Knight wants to make a point to a student about correct behavior, all he has to do is tell him, e-mail him or call his parents. But keep your hands off him. And if civility or professional behavior isn't incentive enough, then how about being under probation of zero tolerance?</p>
        <p>But not Knight. Knight is out of control. If he doesn't have an emotional problem, then he surely has an ego problem. You don't have to be a psychologist to comprehend that. He said last spring that he didn't really have a problem with anger, but something else. ''I've always been too confrontational,'' he said, ''especially when I know I'm right.''</p>
        <p>So his problem, folks, is that he's always right. He has also believed that he could get away with anything -- because he has, to the utter shame of Indiana University and other institutions where he has worked, and worked over people. But the buck has finally stopped. Brand, who announced Knight's dismissal yesterday, called Knight ''defiant and hostile'' and said the coach had shown a continued unwillingness to work within the guidelines of the athletic department.</p>
        <p>In May, when Neil Reed, one of Knight's former players, charged that Knight had once choked him in a practice, Knight protested that it was a lie -- that he had just held the young man's shoulder -- and Knight's sycophantic assistant coaches and players also denied it had occurred. But a film of the incident exposed the lies of Knight and his supporters. Around the same time, it was learned that Knight had also intimidated a 64-year-old secretary in the athletic department with foul language and had thrown a vase, and had gotten into abusive arguments and physical altercations with colleagues and subordinates.</p>
        <p>Brand fined Knight $30,000, suspended him for three games and issued the zero tolerance warning.</p>
        <p>Knight's numerous other incidents of physically and verbally abusing people have been a public scandal for years.</p>
        <p>It goes back a long, long way. When Knight was starting out as a high school basketball coach in Ohio, a student in the school, Susan Wilkinson, recalled in a letter to me some time ago, that he used to ''rant and rave'' in the hallways.</p>
        <p>''One particular time, I had the misfortune of being in the hall when he was throwing a student up against a locker,'' she wrote. ''I couldn't equate this behavior with being in sports or being human. It scared me to death.''</p>
        <p>When Knight was a coach at West Point, his team played Boston College in Madison Square Garden. Bob Cousy, then coaching B.C., recalled being shocked at halftime when he noticed that Knight had one of his players up against the wall and his hand at the boy's throat. Cousy continued to observe Knight through the years. ''It's time to grow up,'' Cousy said of Knight a few years ago, ''and he hasn't grown up.''</p>
        <p>In 1993, Knight pulled his son Patrick from a game and appeared to kick him in the shin.</p>
        <p>Supporters of Knight say that at least he doesn't cheat and abides by N.C.A.A. rules. Cousy counters correctly: ''That the only alternative to wholesale prostitution is to do it the way Bob Knight does? I certainly hope not.''</p>
        <p>Brand has, at length, answered in the affirmative.</p>
        <p>Knight deserves a good rest, and a long-deserved retribution for acts that were neither scholarly nor cultured. At long last, someone in authority has had the courage to render to him what is fitting and proper.</p>
        <p>No one, however, should take joy in Brand's decision. In the end, it is a sad and tragic -- if not concluding --  chapter in what should have been fully one of the most glorious careers in American sports.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
