<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Takes Tough Stand on Violent Entertainment</title>
    <meta content="11GORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/11/politics/11GORE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229782"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Misleading and Deceptive Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Trade Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Joseph I Lieberman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DB1F39F932A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1603" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Takes Tough Stand on Violent Entertainment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore and Sen Joseph I Lieberman say they will propose legislation or new regulatory authority allowing federal government to sanction entertainment industry if it continues marketing violent products to children; Gore says he will give industry six months to make changes, after which he and Lieberman will encourage Federal Trade Commission to move against industry by using power to prohibit false and deceptive advertising; position, while not new for Lieberman, is departure for Gore, who has always stopped short of suggesting government-imposed restrictions on media marketing; says care would have to be taken to ensure that any enforcement does not violate First Amendment protections; acknowledges there has been no constitutional tests of use of deceptive advertising laws to challenge marketing strategies, as opposed to advertising content; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore and his running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, said today that if the entertainment industry did not stop marketing violent films, recordings and video games to children they would propose legislation or new regulatory authority allowing the federal government to sanction the industry.</p>
        <p>In an extended interview on the veranda of the vice president's residence, Mr. Gore said he would give industry officials six months to ''clean up their act.'' If they do not, and if he and Mr. Lieberman win the November election, the vice president said he would encourage the Federal Trade Commission to move against the industry by using its power to prohibit false and deceptive advertising.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore and his running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, said today that if the entertainment industry did not stop marketing violent films, recordings and video games to children they would propose legislation or new regulatory authority allowing the federal government to sanction the industry.</p>
        <p>In an extended interview on the veranda of the vice president's residence, Mr. Gore said he would give industry officials six months to ''clean up their act.'' If they do not, and if he and Mr. Lieberman win the November election, the vice president said he would encourage the Federal Trade Commission to move against the industry by using its power to prohibit false and deceptive advertising.</p>
        <p>The position taken today by the Democratic candidates is not particularly new for Mr. Lieberman, who warned last year that entertainment industry leaders would ''invite legal restrictions on their freedom'' if they did not address public concerns about children's access to media violence. But it is quite new for Mr. Gore, who has always stopped short of suggesting government-imposed restrictions on media marketing, even during his wife's crusade against explicit rock lyrics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said he understood that care would have to be taken to ensure that any enforcement did not violate First Amendment protections of speech. And he acknowledged that there had been no constitutional tests of the use of deceptive advertising laws to challenge marketing strategies, as opposed to advertising content.</p>
        <p>But in a clear appeal to voters concerned about moral issues, and particularly to women with children, Mr. Gore said he was determined to use the presidency to give parents more control over the cultural influences that bombard their children.</p>
        <p>''If I'm entrusted with the presidency,'' he said, his voice rising, ''I am going to do something about this.''</p>
        <p>As in past elections, the Democrats have collected millions of dollars in campaign contributions this year from the entertainment industry. But Mr. Gore, who has chastised the industry even as he solicited its wealthy leaders, suggested that he was not concerned about alienating his backers in Hollywood and New York City.</p>
        <p>''Those who don't like it, well, they don't like it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Today's interview, which was requested by The New York Times, came on the eve of the release of an trade commission report that is expected to harshly criticize the entertainment industry for marketing violent, adult-rated entertainment to young people.</p>
        <p>Several people familiar with the report said it concludes that, despite voluntary rating and labeling systems adopted over the years, the makers of films, recordings and video games routinely use marketing strategies to entice young consumers into buying products that the manufacturers themselves deem inappropriate. The commission study, which relies on internal marketing documents provided by the industry, found that the companies did this largely by placing advertising in publications and television broadcasts that appeal to young people.</p>
        <p>The report will be released by the commission's chairman, Robert Pitofsky, on Monday, and will be discussed at a Senate hearing on Wednesday at which Mr. Lieberman plans to testify.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Lieberman has been known in the Senate as a crusader against media violence, the Gore campaign has been eager to demonstrate that there is little distance between the two running mates on the issue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, whose wife, Tipper, was among the first to call for warning labels on recordings with explicit lyrics, has also taken active stands on the topic. But several published reports over the years have suggested that Mr. Gore has taken strong anti-industry positions in public while backing away from them in private meetings with entertainment executives and contributors.</p>
        <p>While the F.T.C. report recommends that the entertainment industry better regulate the behavior of its companies, it pointedly does not propose the kind of legislation or new regulatory authority threatened by Mr. Gore and Mr. Lieberman.</p>
        <p>''The commission's position is that self-regulation should be the primary approach in this area,'' said Eric London, a commission spokesman. ''However, if it doesn't work, there would be a need to take further action, possibly in the form of legislation.'' Mr. London said the commission had no legal opinion on whether deceptive advertising laws could be used to sanction the industry.</p>
        <p>Jack Valenti, the president of the Motion Picture Association of America, said today that Mr. Gore and Mr. Lieberman were ''very wise people'' who understood that ''the reason the F.T.C. did not recommend government intervention -- in a nonexistent problem, I might add -- is that they know such legislation would be dead on arrival in the first federal court that reviews it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Valenti dismissed the Democrats' proposal as carefully calibrated political posturing. ''Frankly,'' he said, ''if I were running for office I'd be trashing the movie industry myself.''</p>
        <p>Hilary Rosen, the president of the Recording Industry Association of America, said that Mr. Gore's threat of government action could be counterproductive. Several weeks ago, Ms. Rosen said, her industry voluntarily adopted guidelines against marketing recordings with explicit lyrics in publications that were read primarily by children under 16.</p>
        <p>''This just proves that no good deed goes unpunished,'' she said, ''because these voluntary guidelines, if suddenly subjected to criminal sanctions, would be withdrawn immediately and you would create a disincentive in the marketplace for people to try and do the right thing.''</p>
        <p>First Amendment experts said that regulating the marketing of violence through deceptive advertising laws was a plausible legal theory, but would not necessarily pass constitutional scrutiny.</p>
        <p>''Congress could readily enlarge its jurisdiction to embrace this territory of what might constitute false and misleading advertising,'' said William Van Alstyne, a law professor at Duke University. ''But that would just set up the constitutional question.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said he was convinced it could be done in cases where companies seem to be undermining their own rating and labeling standards by marketing inappropriate material to children. ''If the industry violates its own rules and actively misleads parents with advertising, then the industry should be held accountable,'' he said. ''If the industry promises parents that it will not market violent material to children and then proceeds to do so, then the industry's practices could constitute false and deceptive advertising.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman joined Mr. Gore in calling the F.T.C.'s findings troubling. ''It obviously makes a mockery of their own rating system,'' he said of the entertainment industry. ''They've rated their own content and then not lived by their own rating.''</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Gore and Mr. Lieberman have made a campaign tactic of attacking cultural influences. Mr. Gore, in his nomination speech, spoke of challenging ''a culture with too much meanness, and not enough meaning.'' Mr. Lieberman speaks of helping families ''win the competition against the popular culture.''</p>
        <p>Those are lines that play particularly well with female voters, who are shown by polls to be more concerned than men about moral issues. And they are designed to help change the impression found in some polling that Republicans in general and the party's presidential nominee, Gov. George W. Bush, in particular, would be better at upholding moral values than the Democrats and Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Ray Sullivan, a spokesman for Mr. Bush, said the Republican nominee ''believes there clearly needs to be greater responsibility'' shown by the entertainment industry. He said that Mr. Bush prefers that the industry impose its own restrictions rather than be regulated by the federal government.</p>
        <p>But the notion of regulating the entertainment industry is politically perilous for the Democratic ticket because of the party's longtime reliance on the industry as a source of campaign funds. As it is, some Hollywood figures have said they are uneasy with Mr. Gore's choice of Mr. Lieberman and have encouraged Democratic contributors to pocket  their wallets.</p>
        <p>During the 2000 election cycle, Democratic committees have received $13.6 million from individuals, companies and political action committees associated with the television, film and music industries, according to the Center for Responsive Politics, a Washington group that monitors campaign financing. Republican committees have received $8.6 million, the center found.</p>
        <p>In addition, the Gore-Lieberman campaign has received $928,000 from the industry, compared to $725,000 for the Bush campaign. On Thursday, Mr. Gore is to appear at a $5 million fund-raiser for the Democratic National Committee at Radio City Music Hall in New York City featuring a long list of entertainers, ranging from Bette Midler to Paul Simon to Ben Affleck. The following week, he is scheduled to attend another party fund-raiser, in Los Angeles, that is expected to generate contributions from Hollywood.</p>
        <p>Republicans have long maintained that the industry's financial clout with Democrats has compromised the Clinton administration's ability to use its bully pulpit to persuade entertainment executives to change their practices. A Gore administration, they say, would be no different.</p>
        <p>''What I fear with the Gore-Lieberman ticket,'' said Senator Sam Brownback, a Kansas Republican, ''is that you'll hear words but see no action or real push to deal with the products produced by these billion-dollar companies because of the money they put into their campaigns.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
