<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Acquisitions by the technology companies of start-up small-fry offer a sampler on how deals can go wrong.</title>
    <meta content="05NECO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEW ECONOMY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/New Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E3D71F3CF936A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1187" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Acquisitions by the technology companies of start-up small-fry offer a sampler on how deals can go wrong.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Seth Schiesel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Communications equipment industry, sector in which obscure start-ups with little or no revenue are routinely acquired for large sums in stock by industry giants, provides examples of risks of get-bigger-by-buying strategy; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN no sector of the technology business have more companies with less revenue been acquired for richer sums than in communications equipment. It is almost routine for obscure start-ups with little or no revenue to be acquired for hundreds of millions or even billions of dollars in stock by industry giants unable to keep up with all the changes in communications technology.</p>
        <p>Just last week, for instance, Lucent Technologies agreed to pay $4.5 billion in stock for Chromatis Networks, which is developing technology to enhance the capacity and capabilities of fiber optic networks within cities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN no sector of the technology business have more companies with less revenue been acquired for richer sums than in communications equipment. It is almost routine for obscure start-ups with little or no revenue to be acquired for hundreds of millions or even billions of dollars in stock by industry giants unable to keep up with all the changes in communications technology.</p>
        <p>Just last week, for instance, Lucent Technologies agreed to pay $4.5 billion in stock for Chromatis Networks, which is developing technology to enhance the capacity and capabilities of fiber optic networks within cities.</p>
        <p>On the surface, many of these deals look good for everyone, and they often are. The buyers can move into new areas. The entrepreneurs become rich, as do the venture capitalists who buy into the target company. But not every deal can be a success, and as the pace of acquisitions grows, so may the number of bad deals -- like the examples below, all of which offer lessons on the risks of the get-bigger-by-buying strategy.</p>
        <p>CIENA-OMNIA, $429 MILLION, MARCH '99  Ciena is a leader in optical communications equipment. But when Ciena agreed to buy Omnia Communications last spring, it was trying to move into a new market: data networking. Omnia was developing products using a technology called asynchronous transfer mode, which uses optical networks but is not itself an optical system.</p>
        <p>So far, Omnia has generated essentially zero revenue for Ciena, and few analysts foresee any such revenue any time soon.</p>
        <p>Ciena says that customers simply do not want to buy Omnia's sort of product. That means either that Ciena badly misgauged the market or that its sales force, tailored to optical gear, has not figured out how to sell Omnia's technology. (Ciena's acquisition last spring of Lightera, an optical systems company, has gone much better.)</p>
        <p>''We don't expect significant revenue this year from that product, so that's a disappointment to us,'' said Denny Bilter, a Ciena spokesman.</p>
        <p>Lesson: Be careful when expanding beyond your core market and make sure your sales force can distribute the new product.</p>
        <p>SIEMENS-ARGON, $240 MILLION, MARCH '99  When Siemens of Germany decided to become serious about data networking last year, it bought three United States start-ups -- Redstone Communications, Castle Networks and Argon Networks -- and put them into a new division called Unisphere. Redstone, which makes gear that pools data traffic at the edge of big networks, has been a big success. Castle, which wants to develop the next-generation of voice telephone switches, seems to be making headway. And then there is Argon.</p>
        <p>When Siemens agreed to acquire it, Argon wanted to make an ultrahigh-capacity switch for the core of big networks using both asynchronous transfer mode and Internet protocol formats. That was pretty much the last anyone heard about Argon.</p>
        <p>One problem was that Argon's technology did not mesh smoothly with Redstone's. Unisphere is trying to work out the kinks.</p>
        <p>Siemens might be faulted for not recognizing this problem before spending hundreds of millions of its shareholders' dollars on Argon. But at the time, other European communications giants like Alcatel and Ericsson were rushing into the data communications market, and Siemens apparently did not want to be left behind. Unisphere executives declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Lesson: Even if the competition is making noise, take the time to do technical due-diligence research. Moving recklessly can cost a lot of time and money later.</p>
        <p>TELLABS-NETCORE, $575 MILLION, JUNE '99  In a move somewhat similar to the Ciena-Omnia deal, Tellabs, a leader in optical transmission, tried to move into a new market by acquiring NetCore Systems -- a company that wanted to build high-capacity routers using asynchronous transfer mode and Internet protocol formats for the core of big networks.</p>
        <p>But NetCore's technology did not work as well as Tellabs had anticipated, and it is not clear when the deal may start paying off.</p>
        <p>''In NetCore's case you have a combination of a less-than-elegant integration of the company into Tellabs, probably a product that was not as mature as Tellabs' management thought it was, and a marketplace that got pretty competitive,'' said Steven D. Levy, chief communications equipment analyst for Lehman Brothers.</p>
        <p>Investors judge older companies like Tellabs mainly on the growth of their per-share earnings. With a market value of only $27 billion, Tellabs cannot throw its stock around as aggressively as bigger companies can, without risking dilution of its earnings. That has led some experts to believe that Tellabs is simply afraid to pony up the money necessary to acquire private companies with the best technology. Tellabs declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Lesson: Be careful expanding into new markets but also remember that spending too little may yield little in results.</p>
        <p>CISCO-MONTEREY, $500 MILLION, AUGUST '99  Cisco Systems' acquisition of Monterey Networks, which makes gear that links optical communications networks at high speeds, appears set to become much more successful than the Omnia, Argon and NetCore deals. But it is not a home run just yet.</p>
        <p>And home runs, or at least doubles, are what the market has come to expect from Cisco, almost surely the most successful corporate acquirer the last decade. On the day the Monterey deal was announced, Cisco also said it was buying Cerent, a different sort of optical networking company, for about $6.9 billion. That deal has definitely been a home run; Cerent may well generate $1 billion in revenue for Cisco this year.</p>
        <p>But the Monterey deal has just about fallen off the radar screen. People close to Cisco have said the company's original internal target of moving Monterey's products into the market this spring was a result of unwarranted optimism within the Monterey team.</p>
        <p>Cisco still has not announced any sales of Monterey's systems, though people close to the company said last week that they expected announcements of some tests with major communications carriers shortly.</p>
        <p>Lesson: Even acquisition champs like Cisco can have an off day. That is one reason Cisco, using a portfolio approach, does so many deals.</p>
        <p>LUCENT-NEXABIT, $900 MILLION, JUNE '99  In this deal, Lucent did not seem to get what it thought it was buying. But at least it got something of value, and even the original vision may finally be coming into focus.</p>
        <p>Nexabit was supposed to catapult Lucent to immediate leadership in the market for ultrahigh-capacity Internet routers -- devices that help direct data traffic. According to many communications experts, it turns out that Nexabit's technology is actually better-suited for transmitting information in a format known as frame relay rather than the conventional Internet's protocol format.</p>
        <p>The Nexabit deal could still work. This week, Lucent plans to announce that VCities, a small communications carrier based in Dallas, has agreed to buy the Internet protocol version of the Nexabit product.</p>
        <p>Lesson: The lesson from Lucent and all these companies is that nothing can replace thorough research before a deal and nose-to-the-grindstone execution afterward. With the pace of acquisitions accelerating, it is only getting easier to make bad deals.</p>
        <p>NEW ECONOMY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
