<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inventors dream of a world in which no pair of socks is ever mismatched again.</title>
    <meta content="05PATE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PATENTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Socks (Apparel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chartrand, Sabra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E5D61F3CF936A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1175" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inventors dream of a world in which no pair of socks is ever mismatched again.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sabra Chartrand</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chartrand, Sabra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patent database shows inventors continue to tinker with sock and to devise sock accessories; patents for athletic socks and support socks are so numerous that many are barely distinguishable from one another; act of donning socks and challenge of keeping pairs of socks together in laundry also seem to captivate footwear inventors (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE common sock hardly seems in need of taming. Its basic design has remained unchanged for generations, serving to protect and warm the foot, and provide a liner between skin and shoe.</p>
        <p>As with all clothing, socks are subject to the whims of fashion and the improvements possible with modern materials. But in the end, most people own socks that are essentially similar to the socks their ancestors wore, and just like the socks their friends and neighbors own.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE common sock hardly seems in need of taming. Its basic design has remained unchanged for generations, serving to protect and warm the foot, and provide a liner between skin and shoe.</p>
        <p>As with all clothing, socks are subject to the whims of fashion and the improvements possible with modern materials. But in the end, most people own socks that are essentially similar to the socks their ancestors wore, and just like the socks their friends and neighbors own.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the nation's patent database proves that there is always someone who believes the sock can be improved. Inventors continue to tinker with the sock and to come up with sock accessories.</p>
        <p>Occasionally, historical trends are apparent. In the 1970's, for example, there were several attempts to create the dress tube sock, a dark-colored sock with no defined heel.</p>
        <p>More mechanically-minded inventors tend to devote their time to making the sock perform double duty. In the last 20 years, patents have been awarded for socks with pockets, heated socks, cushioned socks, inflatable socks, open-toe socks, half-socks, sock dickies, socks with hidden shoe horns, tap dance socks, moisturizing socks, exercise socks, medicated socks and socks with simulated jewelry.</p>
        <p>Patents for athletic socks and support socks are so numerous that many are barely distinguishable from one another, except for their varying promises to improve performance and strengthen and support feet, ankles and legs.</p>
        <p>After sock enhancements, two fields appear to captivate footwear inventors: the act of donning socks, and the challenge of keeping pairs of socks together in the laundry.</p>
        <p>Embarrassment seems to motivate the inventors of sock sorters. In their patents, they cite the challenges of owning multiple, one-size-fits-all socks knitted in similar yarns and colors, or of living in a household where several people own lots of socks. These inventors are alarmed by how easy it is to wind up with mismatched pairs of socks.</p>
        <p>''Usually, the mismatch is discovered when the wearer is in situations that can cause great embarrassment,'' Wayne Reichle wrote in his patent for what he called a ''device for sorting socks.'' Mr. Reichle recently won patent 6,067,659 for an invention that clamps sock mates together. The clamp is color-coordinated to the sock, with each side bearing an identifying symbol. The clamps can be attached anywhere on the sock, but Mr. Reichle recommends attaching them to the top edge of the sock so they will be covered by pant legs.</p>
        <p>Grandma might have just tied socks together before tossing them into the wash, but even in her day, inventors were hoping to add technology to the process. In 1957, a patent was awarded for a washable strip of fabric to which pairs of socks could be fastened.</p>
        <p>Other inventors have tried to solve the matching problem by knitting a word or icon into the sock during weaving. One invention added identifying labels to socks. In 1988, Bruce Anderson won patent 4,734,938 for simply writing the color name on the sock. Rodney Mazzoli won patent 4,965,902 for a method of joining two socks by wrapping or tying them together with a strip of material that is impregnated with fabric softener or anti-cling compound.</p>
        <p>In a more recent attempt to solve multiple-sock challenges, Jonathan Hartzell won patent 5,467,510 for a method of tagging socks with a four-part, color-coded disc. The color of the disc indicates the ''fundamental color category to which its sock belongs,'' he writes in his patent. Another part of the disc identifies the person who owns the sock. And ''by noticing whether a sock features a protruding dome-shaped cap or a flat tack disc, an observer is immediately aware of the inside-out, right side-out status of that sock.''</p>
        <p>Then there are the sock sorters that use clamps, snaps, tags, pins, or clasps to hold pairs together in the wash. Joel Hicks won patent 5,926,925 for magnets that pair socks. Other patents require holes in the socks to accommodate the pins and tags; others fit tags over the sock's top edge. The tags often come in pairs bearing matching colors, letters or numbers.</p>
        <p>Americans are not the only ones interested in tracking their socks. Louise Christy and Frank Saffioti live in New South Wales, Australia, and won patent 5,579,541 for sock tabs fastened with hook-and-loop patches like Velcro.</p>
        <p>Other inventors have focused on making it easier to put socks on, since elderly people, handicapped individuals, arthritis sufferers and pregnant women may all find it difficult to bend over and pull on socks. Eugene Santamaria, who lives in Crescent City, Fla., won patent 6,056,171 last month for a long, curved handle with flexible side wings that expand to stretch the ''opening of a sock for aiding the insertion of a user's foot into the sock.'' Mr. Santamaria writes in his patent that his design is intended for ''users having limited mobility or flexibility to don their socks on their own and without the aid of others.''</p>
        <p>Other devices include frames, handles, shoe horns and telescoping arms designed to help people put on socks. Ignace Willemin won patent 5,924,610 for a pair of tongs with jaws. ''The first gripping jaw keeps the sock open wide enough so that the tip of the foot can be slipped in and then the heel,'' Mr. Willemin writes in his patent. ''It is then possible to put on the sock and to pull it up along the calf of the leg without the user having to bend over. One of the gripping jaws also has a catch element enabling socks to be removed.''</p>
        <p>Other devices are made of horseshoe-shaped plastic over which a sock is draped or stretched. Often they come with string or rope to assist in pulling up the sock. Some can be inserted into an empty shoe, so a person could slip his or her foot into a sock and shoe at the same time. John and Frank Pettit use a pair of hinged posts with two attached arms in their patent 4,756,453. An inverted sock is placed over both arms. ''The user then spreads the posts apart to stretch the sock open and pushes a foot into the open sock,'' the Pettits' patent says, ''the sock unfolding as it is mounted on the foot.''</p>
        <p>Then there is Frank Krack's design for a sock that is inherently easy to pull on. Mr. Krack, who won patent 5,575,013, designed a sock with a pleat down the length of its front. When the pleat is open, the sock is  easy to pull on ''without the pulling, squeezing and rubbing associated with conventional socks,'' he says. Once the sock is on, the pleat is closed with a hook-and-loop fastener.</p>
        <p>And pleated socks are probably very easy to identify in the wash.</p>
        <p>PATENTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
