<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Magazine Giant Weighs In on Internet Business</title>
    <meta content="05HUEY$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Time Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">E-Company Now (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuczynski, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Huey, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E0D61F3CF936A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Magazine Giant Weighs In on Internet Business</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX KUCZYNSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kuczynski, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with John Huey, who headed Time Inc's effort to create E-Company Now, monthly magazine about Internet business; graph compares magazines in field; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Huey is a magazine editor known for his Southern charm and pit-bull mentality: when he has an idea between his teeth, he might be pleasant about it, but he will never let go.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Mr. Huey, managing editor of Fortune magazine, decided that Time Inc. ought to start or purchase a magazine about Internet business. He flew  to San Francisco and met with editors and publishers at The Industry Standard, Red Herring and Business 2.0, deciding who or what or whether to buy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Huey is a magazine editor known for his Southern charm and pit-bull mentality: when he has an idea between his teeth, he might be pleasant about it, but he will never let go.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Mr. Huey, managing editor of Fortune magazine, decided that Time Inc. ought to start or purchase a magazine about Internet business. He flew  to San Francisco and met with editors and publishers at The Industry Standard, Red Herring and Business 2.0, deciding who or what or whether to buy.</p>
        <p>No luck.</p>
        <p>''We tried to see if there was a way that we each could satisfy the other's goals, and we basically decided we could not,'' Mr. Huey said.</p>
        <p>Since he could not buy 'em, he joined 'em. The result is E-Company Now, a new monthly magazine from Time Inc. that Mr. Huey said cost less to start ''than it would have ever cost to pay the Internet multiples everyone was asking for.''</p>
        <p>With the first issue, released three weeks ago, Mr. Huey and his editors jumped, some would say belatedly, into a fray of magazines that besides The Standard and Red Herring includes titles like Upside, Fast Company and -- take a deep breath -- the newly rechristened Ziff-Davis Smart Business for the New Economy.</p>
        <p>And no one expects the dot-com advertising boom to last forever. What's more, Mr. Huey must keep E-Company Now from leeching content from Fortune, its inspirational parent.</p>
        <p>But none of this daunts Mr. Huey. ''I'm relatively confident this is going to work,'' he said in an interview last week from his home in Atlanta. (Mr. Huey prefers to commute to work from Georgia most weeks than to live in New York City.) ''We figured out about two years ago that the whole Internet story was moving out of the realm of being a tech story alone. But we never wanted Fortune to drill down so deep into the subject that it became a magazine just about the Internet.''</p>
        <p>E-Company Now may soon have something else going for it that the other magazines do not, words that would make any Internet-magazine mogul's heart go pitter-pat: America Online and Time Warner.</p>
        <p>Most of the other magazines in the field do not have the benefit of Time Inc.'s expertise in consumer magazines or the marketing clout of AOL, which has given the magazine special placement on choice CompuServe, AOL and Netscape sites. So far, those sites have generated more than 30,000 subscriptions, said Ned Desmond, editor in chief of E-Company Now.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huey said the advantages of Time Inc.'s backing were obvious. ''We are not running around trying to raise a new round of financing or preparing an I.P.O.,'' he said. ''We're running around trying to get the best editors and writers we can.''</p>
        <p>Then again, most of the magazines about Internet business -- even those that are still raising financing and preparing initial public offerings -- are thriving and expanding.</p>
        <p>Business 2.0, which is published by Imagine Media in San Francisco, shifted from a monthly to a twice-a-month publication three issues ago. Red Herring, published by Red Herring Communications, will do the same in November; its June issue is 628 pages. Ad pages for The Industry Standard, the weekly from IDG, are up almost 500 percent against last year and have almost surpassed those of People magazine. Its issues often reach 360 pages, including both advertising and editorial material.</p>
        <p>Of course, the magazines have been buoyed by the fact that the market for advertising pages promoting dot-com companies has grown exponentially the last three years. Online, Internet and e-commerce companies spent $113.2 million on advertising in American magazines in 1997, according to Competitive Media Reporting. That climbed to $153.6 million in 1998 and then surged to $687.3 million last year.</p>
        <p>But the tide has shifted in recent months, as some of the speculative excess in technology and Internet stocks has subsided; many of those advertisers can no longer afford to spend so freely and no longer need to reach the venture capitalists who thumb through the Internet magazines. Rich LeFurgy, chairman of the Internet Advertising Bureau, said the flow of dot-com advertising would soon abate and probably fall steeply.</p>
        <p>''The shift is toward more moderated spending and more effective spending,'' Mr. LeFurgy said. ''You were getting to absurd lengths with some of these magazines as it was. They were getting out of control in terms of the number of ad pages relative to editorial. That will change.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Huey said he had already thought of that.</p>
        <p>''We're not naive about advertising,'' he said. ''We have, along with the dot-com advertising, consumer advertising and business advertising, liquor, cars, fashion. Yes, we will take every dot-com ad that can pay for it, but our business plan is not built on soaking up an ever-growing pool of dot-com advertising.''</p>
        <p>The real battle among the Internet magazines may play out not in terms of advertising pages, but in the more mundane sphere of old-fashioned circulation. While some of the Internet business magazines have significant circulations, most remain fairly small. Ziff-Davis Smart Business for the New Economy has a circulation of 1,048,941, according to the Audit Bureau of Circulations, but that was all gained when the magazine was still known as PC Computing. (Ziff-Davis repositioned the magazine to a business-strategy magazine with the May issue.) And Fast Company's circulation is 402,603, according to the circulation bureau.</p>
        <p>But the rest of the magazines have circulations closer to that of Model Railroader, and many give away the bulk of their subscriptions free.</p>
        <p>Upside, which is not audited by the Audit Bureau of Circulations, reports circulation of 257,000, of which 15,000 are paid. Gini Talmadge, president of Upside Media, said that the subscriptions were given away to qualified readers, meaning readers who have filled out a survey.</p>
        <p>''So our subscriber list reads like a Who's Who of the Internet,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Industry Standard, which also is not audited by the Audit Bureau of Circulations, gives away half of its weekly 150,000 circulation to qualified subscribers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huey said that competition like The Industry Standard, Business 2.0 or Red Herring was not a threat to his new magazine, which has guaranteed advertisers a circulation of 200,000 readers.</p>
        <p>''The Industry Standard says they are a must-read for anybody doing business on the Internet,'' Mr. Huey said. ''If that's true, why does it have a circulation of 150,000 and half of it they give away? They are the hot trade book. And that's a very good position to have. But look at us. We want to be a national business magazine that is informed by the Valley.''</p>
        <p>Jonathan Weber, editor in chief of The Industry Standard, does not dispute the circulation figures. But he said paid circulation was growing ''at a healthy pace'' and that ''substantial increases'' would be announced soon. He dismissed Mr. Huey's other criticisms.</p>
        <p>There are potential pitfalls for Mr. Huey's and Mr. Desmond's magazine. Editors of competing magazines are quick to criticize Time Inc. for coming late to the game.</p>
        <p>''They are two years late to the party,'' said James Daly, editor in chief of Business 2.0. ''They have to do something that other magazines are not doing, and there's not a lot of space left.''</p>
        <p>Another potential problem is that E-Company Now is a monthly in a field now almost exclusively on weekly or twice-a-month schedules. But Mr. Huey said the magazine's Web site, with its daily columnists and a business-to-business component, would help keep readers plugged in. He suggested the shift to twice-a-month publication by Business 2.0 and Red Herring was part of a ploy to get more advertising.</p>
        <p>''It seems pretty obvious to me what that's about,'' he said. ''Our argument is that they are not doing the frequency thing for the reader.''</p>
        <p>About Mr. Huey's theory, Ted Gramkow, publisher of Red Herring, said, ''I don't think so.'' He countered, ''This is John Huey's way, and Fortune and Time Warner's way, of attracting dollars that have been beyond their high price in Fortune. This is a pure advertising play.''</p>
        <p>Of course, it would be hard for any publisher to argue that readers want even more Internet magazines. But the titles continue to proliferate. Business 2.0 will start an as-yet-unnamed offshoot in October, a business lifestyle magazine whose editor in chief is a former editor of Harper's Bazaar and In Style.</p>
        <p>The former publisher of Office Products International is introducing line56, an Internet-business magazine whose title was inspired by the  Shakespearian soliloquy that begins with the words ''To be or not to be,'' which appear in line 56 of Act III of ''Hamlet.''</p>
        <p>IDG, The Industry Standard's parent company, has just introduced Darwin: Business Evolving in the Information Age.</p>
        <p>''It's getting to be way too much for me,'' Mr. LeFurgy of the Internet Advertising Bureau said. ''I have total information anxiety. The magazines just stack up and stack up in my office now.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
