<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Painter Happily Emerges From a Determined Battle</title>
    <meta content="05GIMP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204981"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salamon, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whiteford, William A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Keplinger, Daniel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">King Gimp (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E6D61F3CF936A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Painter Happily Emerges From a Determined Battle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE SALAMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salamon, Julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Julie Salamon reviews King Gimp, television documentary directed by William A Whiteford and written by Daniel Keplinger, disabled painter who is subject of film; photo</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was one of those embarrassing, exhilarating spectacles people hope for when they watch the Oscars. In March, when ''King Gimp'' won the award for best documentary short, the film's writer and subject sprang out of his wheelchair in a burst of excitement.</p>
        <p>Tonight HBO is showing the documentary, which is exhilarating in its way but far from embarrassing in any way. It tells the story leading up to that Oscar moment, and how Daniel Keplinger, the flailing man in the wheelchair, tries to force the world to see only the man.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was one of those embarrassing, exhilarating spectacles people hope for when they watch the Oscars. In March, when ''King Gimp'' won the award for best documentary short, the film's writer and subject sprang out of his wheelchair in a burst of excitement.</p>
        <p>Tonight HBO is showing the documentary, which is exhilarating in its way but far from embarrassing in any way. It tells the story leading up to that Oscar moment, and how Daniel Keplinger, the flailing man in the wheelchair, tries to force the world to see only the man.</p>
        <p>His job is not easy because cerebral palsy has set his various body parts moving to separate rhythms. It is painful to watch him change shirts. He rolls like a toddler on the floor, struggling to coerce his uncooperative self into elusive arm and neck holes. So when he first appears on screen, it is hard to grasp what is going on with him because this young man with dark shaggy hair does not stop moving and sputtering. Then subtitles appear to translate those bursts of noise.</p>
        <p>''Most people think 'gimp' means someone with a lame walk,'' says Mr. Keplinger. ''But gimp also means a fighting spirit.'' Suddenly he comes into focus. Mr. Keplinger the documentary subject was discovered at age 12 when Susan Hannah Hadary and William Whiteford began investigating the lives of children with physical disabilities. For the next 13 years they periodically checked in with him.</p>
        <p>His progress surprised everyone except perhaps his mother. She appears to be a calm woman who refused to put her son in an institution as her husband wanted. He left the family when Dan was 6 and she continued her child-rearing plan. ''I treated him the way I would have treated any normal baby,'' she says.</p>
        <p>In family photographs he looks normal. The freeze frame of the still camera stops his perpetual motion, at least for the photo albums.</p>
        <p>After spending a few years at a school for disabled children, Mr. Keplinger was ''mainstreamed.'' His social life was negligible, but he found solace. Like the cerebral-palsy-stricken Irish writer and painter Christy Brown (memorialized by Daniel Day-Lewis's bravura performance in ''My Left Foot''), Mr. Keplinger turned to art. Using a specially designed headpiece to hold a brush, he began to paint and draw under the guidance of an understanding teacher. Somehow the contact of the brush and canvas seems to steady him.</p>
        <p>''At Parkville High, an artist was born and the artist was me,'' says Mr. Keplinger.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile he did what teenage boys do: he grew a mustache and a ponytail and asserted his independence. Before he graduated, he moved into his own apartment.</p>
        <p>At 20 he enrolled in Towson State University in Maryland, where two teachers would not speak to him and another told him he would never be an artist. Mr. Keplinger thought he might never paint again, until another teacher took him seriously. So he could make reasonable suggestions to his student, this teacher tried on Mr. Keplinger's head contraption and tried painting with it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Keplinger's paintings are fierce, almost defiant, but also strangely beautiful: or maybe it's impossible not to read them like this after watching his struggle.</p>
        <p>His work can be seen at the Phyllis Kind Gallery in SoHo through June 30. HBO is simultaneously mounting a virtual exhibit on the Internet, at hbo.com.</p>
        <p>KING GIMP  HBO, tonight at 7</p>
        <p>Directed and photographed by William A. Whiteford; Susan Hannah Hadary and William A. Whiteford, producers; written by Daniel Keplinger; music by Michael Bacon; Loye Miller, contributing editor. For Tapestry International: Nancy Walzog, executive producer. For HBO: Sheila Nevins, executive producer; Carole Rosen, senior producer; Lisa Heller, supervising producer; edited by Geof Bartz.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
