<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cornered, Camby Opens Up A Bit</title>
    <meta content="05BASK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Camby, Marcus</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905EEDA163FF936A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cornered, Camby Opens Up A Bit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE, N.Y., June 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knickerbockers forward Marcus Camby discusses his injuries, disappointing postseason play and future of team (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A year ago this time, Marcus Camby was the high-flying component in the Knicks' run to the finals, a player whose future with the team seemed as far-reaching as his wing span. But today, a reluctant Camby spoke about a miserable postseason performance that contributed to the Knicks' loss in the Eastern Conference finals and clouded his future with the team.</p>
        <p>For the record, he wants to stay in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A year ago this time, Marcus Camby was the high-flying component in the Knicks' run to the finals, a player whose future with the team seemed as far-reaching as his wing span. But today, a reluctant Camby spoke about a miserable postseason performance that contributed to the Knicks' loss in the Eastern Conference finals and clouded his future with the team.</p>
        <p>For the record, he wants to stay in New York.</p>
        <p>''This team has been known to make changes; they've made changes before,'' Camby said after the Knicks cleaned out their lockers two days after the Indiana Pacers eliminated them in Game 6. ''That's how I got here. Nothing really surprises me in this business. But this is where I want to be now. I just want to be wanted. It's not what I feel. I love playing in New York. I like being here.''</p>
        <p>The words did not come easily for Camby, who had been open and accessible since arriving in New York almost two years ago. He probably preferred to say nothing publicly, a stance he had taken since Game 5.</p>
        <p>Even today, while the rest of the Knicks trickled out of the locker room and into one parking lot, stopping to discuss the end of their season and the team's uncertain future, Knicks officials had to coax Camby into speaking. In order to avoid the news media again, he had parked his Range Rover in another lot.</p>
        <p>Finally, Camby walked into the parking lot, with reporters waiting for him and his teammate Rick Brunson driving Camby's car up to greet him.</p>
        <p>And when he finally spoke, he carefully considered each word, dodging some questions and refusing to speculate on where his season went wrong and what might be next.</p>
        <p>''I just wasn't on top of my game,'' said Camby, who was also bothered by a knee injury. ''I won't use the knee as an excuse. I never have. I just didn't make shots and didn't make plays.''</p>
        <p>For the entire postseason, Camby averaged 4.8 points on 33.7 percent shooting and pulled down 7 rebounds a game. His scoring numbers dropped every series, from 6.7 a game on 40.9 percent shooting in the opening round against Toronto, to 5.3 on 33.3 percent shooting against Miami, to only 3.3 points on 28 percent shooting against Indiana. The rebounds dipped, too, from 7.7, to 7.1, and finally to 6.5 against Indiana.</p>
        <p>In the last two games of the playoffs, he missed all five of his field-goal attempts.</p>
        <p>This debacle of a postseason came one year after he averaged 14.3 points and 10.7 rebounds against the Pacers, seeming to signal that he had reached a new level in his career. Camby signed a six-year, $39 million contract extension during the 1998-99 season, shortly after being acquired from Toronto for Charles Oakley and the Knicks' second-round pick in the 1998 draft, Sean Marks.</p>
        <p>Camby, a Connecticut native, spoke of his fondness of playing and living in the New York area, and why the team should ignore his postseason play.</p>
        <p>''I like being involved in the community,'' he said. ''I definitely feel wanted. There's a lot of respect from the fans, when they see me out, and we have a great bunch of guys around here that are committed to winning. I mean, the things I've done in the community, the things I've done on the court, coming to training camp in shape and starting, gladly giving up my spot to Patrick and just playing my role off the bench, everybody sacrificed a lot.''</p>
        <p>The injuries affected Camby's season. He missed 17 games after he sustained a mild strain of the anterior cruciate ligament in his right knee on Feb. 6 and the team physician, Norman Scott, performed diagnostic arthroscopic surgery. He never fully recovered, returning for 18 games and then going back on the injured list for the final week of the season because of a sprained medial capsule in the same knee.</p>
        <p>For all of his problems, Camby said: ''I don't look at it like a miserable season, like a lot of you guys wrote and I read. I wish everybody was healthy, not just myself, and we could have had a better season. We had a decent year, not a good year. We just came up short. Next year, if things stay intact, we'll make another run.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>One of the players who competed with MARCUS CAMBY for minutes in the frontcourt was KURT THOMAS, who is also aware that he may have played his last game as a Knick. The lone free agent among the regular eight-man rotation, Thomas is in the final year of a three-year, $3,675,000 contract and is unsure whether he will be back. ''I don't want to speak on that right now,'' he said Sunday.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
