<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Puente's Wake, a Flood of Memories</title>
    <meta content="05PUEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205038"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Puente, Tito</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5DA163FF936A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Puente's Wake, a Flood of Memories</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUAN FORERO</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wake held at Riverside Memorial Chapel on Upper West Side of Manhattan for legendary band leader Tito Puente; scene described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hundreds of people, from world-famous musicians to retired taxi drivers, came together at a Manhattan funeral chapel yesterday to say goodbye to the Mambo King.</p>
        <p>Tito Puente, the legendary band leader and percussionist, died Wednesday after half a century of delighting crowds the world over with his Latin jazz and frenetic salsa. And yesterday, faithful fans and loyal friends waited for hours for the brief chance to spend a quiet moment beside the white coffin that held his body.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hundreds of people, from world-famous musicians to retired taxi drivers, came together at a Manhattan funeral chapel yesterday to say goodbye to the Mambo King.</p>
        <p>Tito Puente, the legendary band leader and percussionist, died Wednesday after half a century of delighting crowds the world over with his Latin jazz and frenetic salsa. And yesterday, faithful fans and loyal friends waited for hours for the brief chance to spend a quiet moment beside the white coffin that held his body.</p>
        <p>Mourners started arriving at the Riverside Memorial Chapel on the Upper West Side as early as 10 a.m., and hours later hundreds of people remained, waiting in a line that stretched nearly a block along West 76th Street from the corner of Amsterdam Avenue.</p>
        <p>For many, it was an emotional farewell.</p>
        <p>''I just tearfully saw him, left him a kiss and said goodbye,'' said Michael Terrace, 74, a former professional dancer who often performed at the old Palladium in Midtown where the Tito Puente Orchestra solidified its reputation in the 1950's. ''It hurts. It really hurts. You have to say: 'Tito, I enjoyed working with you. I loved you.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Puente, who died at age 77 after suffering complications from open-heart surgery, will be buried tomorrow after a private funeral in Nanuet, N.Y.</p>
        <p>So it was yesterday's seven-hour wake -- along with another wake to be held today between 11 a.m. and 7 p.m. at the chapel -- that gave fans a chance to bid farewell to El Rey.</p>
        <p>Public officials like Peter F. Vallone, the City Council speaker, and Representative Jose E. Serrano of the Bronx attended. Latin music fans penned in behind police sawhorses, meanwhile, reveled in the collection of young and old Latin musicians who came together to pay their respects to a man who shaped their music, including Ruben Blades, the Panamanian singer and actor; Cheo Feliciano, the baritone; and Tito Nieves, the salsa star.</p>
        <p>''I've seen musicians that I hadn't seen since I was a little girl,'' said Cindy Rodriguez, the daughter of the late band leader Tito Rodriguez, who, with Mr. Puente and Machito, are credited with driving the mambo craze. ''You know, you're not going to see these people in one place again.''</p>
        <p>Those who spent hours in line waiting to get into the chapel were rewarded with a walk up a short flight of stairs to a chapel where Mr. Puente's body, clad in a white suit and white tie, lay in a coffin surrounded by white orchids.</p>
        <p>Eight pictures of Mr. Puente, one of him in a Navy uniform during World War II and the others showing him banging on his timbales with delight, were placed around the coffin.</p>
        <p>One by one, the mourners passed the coffin, many saying a brief prayer or kissing the plexiglass that covered the open coffin.</p>
        <p>Esperanza Rengifo of Queens carried four of Mr. Puente's 118 albums, clutching them to her chest as she recalled how important his music had been to her. ''I've been here since 8 a.m.,'' said Ms. Rengifo, 73, as she neared the entrance to the chapel at 1 p.m. ''I missed Mass to be here, so I asked God for forgiveness. I said 'I'll have to miss Mass because I need to see Tito Puente.' ''</p>
        <p>Many of those who came, it seemed, had a personal memory of the band leader: salseros who danced to his music in the Palladium half a century ago, friends who laughed and joked with a man famous for his sense of humor, musicians who performed with him in smoky neighborhood joints and world-class music halls.</p>
        <p>Luz Pagan said being so close to Mr. Puente reminded her of the days when she paid $1.50 to get into the Palladium to dance for hours to his music. ''Imagine, how great it was,'' she said. ''To hear those timbales. You would feel it in your blood.''</p>
        <p>Others carried Puerto Rican flags in honor of one of the island's most famous sons, who was born in 1923 in East Harlem to Puerto Rican migrants and is credited with spreading the island's music to far corners of the world.</p>
        <p>''I knew I had to come here,'' said Pedro Aguilar, a dancer known as Cuban Pete, who first met Mr. Puente in 1949. ''I just couldn't miss this. I wanted to say my goodbyes properly.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
