<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Calling Her a Threat, State Bars an Advocate From Prisons</title>
    <meta content="05PRIS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Alice</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siegal, Nina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E4D9163FF936A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="757" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Calling Her a Threat, State Bars an Advocate From Prisons</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NINA SIEGAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siegal, Nina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alice Green, one of New York State's leading inmate advocates, has been barred from state prisons because correctional officials think she helped organize systemwide inmate strike, which was supposed to begin last Jan 1 but was averted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the state's leading inmate advocates has been barred from state prisons because correctional officials think she helped organize a systemwide inmate strike, which was supposed to begin last Jan. 1 but was averted.</p>
        <p>The advocate, Alice Green, executive director of the Center for Law and Justice, has visited state prisons for 20 years as an unofficial liaison between inmates, their families and the state. As an employee of the New York Civil Liberties Union in the 1970's, she helped prisoners prepare for their release, with jobs training and advice on the difficult transition to life outside.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the state's leading inmate advocates has been barred from state prisons because correctional officials think she helped organize a systemwide inmate strike, which was supposed to begin last Jan. 1 but was averted.</p>
        <p>The advocate, Alice Green, executive director of the Center for Law and Justice, has visited state prisons for 20 years as an unofficial liaison between inmates, their families and the state. As an employee of the New York Civil Liberties Union in the 1970's, she helped prisoners prepare for their release, with jobs training and advice on the difficult transition to life outside.</p>
        <p>For the past 10 years, her Albany-based group, the Center for Law and Justice, has organized an annual meeting between prisoner advocates and state lawmakers, called the Prison Legislative Conference. Ms. Green said she typically visits state prisons about once a month to plan for the conference and meet with inmates for other reasons.</p>
        <p>But for more than a year, Ms. Green said, she has been denied entry to every prison she has sought to visit. About a month ago, she began calling the State Department of Correctional Services each day to find out if she was, in fact, being banned.</p>
        <p>Last week, she received a letter from Glenn S. Goord, the commissioner of the department, dated May 9, which stated: ''You are correct. Pursuant to the authority vested in me by law, I have directed each superintendent to deny all visitation access by you and any member of your organization.''</p>
        <p>The reason, wrote Mr. Goord, was that Ms. Green posed ''a clear threat to the safety and security'' of inmates and prison employees. The letter accused Ms. Green's organization of ''encouraging an illegal systemwide inmate action on Jan.1.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Green said she had not been permitted to enter the prisons since last spring, months before the inmate action was scheduled. She said she thought she had been barred because of an incident in January 1999 in which she unfurled a banner that read ''No More Prisons'' behind Gov. George E. Pataki while he was giving a speech. She was arrested but acquitted.</p>
        <p>''After that, I got an invitation from prisoners at Attica and I was approved to go in, but then, at the last minute, I was told I couldn't come in,'' she said. ''I was told I was a radical, opposed to prisons, and that was the reason for not letting me in.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Green said she did not help foment a prison strike. ''I certainly brought it to the attention of people outside but I in no way encouraged that strike,'' she said. ''I had not even been in the prisons for at least a year, and I've worked in the prisons for 20 years without incident.''</p>
        <p>James B. Flateau, a spokesman for the Department of Correctional Services, said there was no connection between the Pataki rally and the denial of prison access. He said members of Ms. Green's group were allowed into the prisons until late last fall, but he declined to comment further on any role she might have had in a strike.</p>
        <p>To avert a strike, many inmates were transferred, two prisons were placed under lockdown and guards were added.</p>
        <p>Under state law, no member of the public is allowed into state prisons without permission from Mr. Goord's office; he can deny access as he sees fit.</p>
        <p>Ms. Green said it will be almost impossible to plan the prison legislative conference this year without visiting inmates, and her advocacy on behalf of inmates will be hurt by the ban.</p>
        <p>Barbara J. Olshansky, assistant legal director for the Center for Constitutional Rights in New York, has been following Ms. Green's case. She said she was worried that the ban against Ms. Green would squelch advocacy by other prisoner support organizations.</p>
        <p>''They are going to be very concerned about saying anything they believe in, whether inside or outside the prison, because they're going to be afraid that they will be exiled as well,'' she said. ''Then everyone's First Amendment rights get squashed.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Flateau disagreed.</p>
        <p>''The work her group ostensibly is doing is carried on by a number of groups, and we don't expect there to be any noticeable impact on the inmate population because she's not there,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
