<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Killing Raises Doubts on Mexico's War on Drugs</title>
    <meta content="Y05BAJ$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205013"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mexico-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Golden, Tim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pastino Moreno, Jose</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Madrazo, Jorge (Atty Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4DD163FF936A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1642" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Killing Raises Doubts on Mexico's War on Drugs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM GOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Golden, Tim</byline>
      <dateline>TIJUANA, Mexico</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Murder of Mexican anti-drug official Jose Patino Moreno and two colleagues, presumably by drug traffickers, raises questions among US drug officials and others over how nation's drug offensive led by Atty Gen Jorge Madrazo has been carried out and whether it will be sustained; American officials say they have seen no clear sign of change in loyalties of Mexican officials or institutions linked to protection of traffickers; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jose Patino Moreno was unusually well versed in the risks of his work as a narcotics investigator. He had seen colleagues killed by drug traffickers, and he had seen traffickers bribe their way free.</p>
        <p>He had watched raid after raid compromised by corrupt officials. He even lost his job for a time after a senior official in league with smugglers grew displeased with his efforts against the drug trade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jose Patino Moreno was unusually well versed in the risks of his work as a narcotics investigator. He had seen colleagues killed by drug traffickers, and he had seen traffickers bribe their way free.</p>
        <p>He had watched raid after raid compromised by corrupt officials. He even lost his job for a time after a senior official in league with smugglers grew displeased with his efforts against the drug trade.</p>
        <p>Mr. Patino pressed on, friends said, partly because he believed that someone at some point would finally make headway in the fight against organized crime.</p>
        <p>But late on the morning of April 10, months after taking charge of a new team set up to pursue Mexico's most-wanted drug suspects, he and two other officials were abducted as they drove here from San Diego. Their badly tortured bodies were found the next day in a desert ravine.</p>
        <p>In the weeks surrounding Mr. Patino's death, the Mexican authorities have made their most significant progress in years against the the Tijuana-based gang he had come to fight, run by the Arellano Felix brothers. And Mexican officials have suggested that the deaths of Mr. Patino and his two colleagues might foster the success that they could not achieve themselves.</p>
        <p>''The blood of our friends was not spilled in vain,'' Attorney General Jorge Madrazo promised his subordinates at a service for the three. ''The hour has come to act and to come together.''</p>
        <p>Yet almost as quickly, questions have emerged among United States officials and others about how the offensive has been carried out and whether it will be sustained.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Madrazo and his federal police have taken much of the credit for the most important blows landed in the new offensive -- the arrests of two of the drug organization's presumed leaders -- officials say the attorney general's office had almost no role in either action. Nor do those arrests appear to have involved much work by American law enforcement officials.</p>
        <p>Rather, officials said privately, the man accused of running the day-to-day operations of the gang, Ismael Higuera, was tracked down by Mexican civilian and military intelligence officers who received unusually good information from the Central Intelligence Agency. The capture a few weeks earlier of a powerful uncle of the Arellano brothers was the work of a military intelligence unit that the C.I.A. trained and supported, the officials said.</p>
        <p>American officials say they have seen no clear sign of a change in the loyalties of Mexican officials or institutions linked to the protection of the drug traffickers.</p>
        <p>Some terrified Mexican anti-drug agents here even asked to be reassigned after Mr. Patino's death, officials said, and the government has denied reports that other agents quit rather than be sent here.</p>
        <p>The push in the state of Baja California comes after a long stretch of frustration. Last year, the number of drug seizures was mostly down, the government's promises to extradite drug suspects to the United States were unfulfilled and official corruption was widespread. Only last fall, American officials were despairing that the Mexican authorities had effectively given up in Tijuana.</p>
        <p>Then the prosecutor who heads the long-running federal inquiry in San Diego, Gustavo P. Curiel, and his new boss, United States Attorney Gregory A. Vega, decided to fly to Mexico City to meet with Mr. Madrazo. ''We figured that unless we re-engaged with the Mexicans -- unless we did something -- nothing was going to happen,'' Mr. Vega said in an interview.</p>
        <p>At that time, Mr. Madrazo and his drug enforcement chief said they would begin a new campaign against the Arellanos. Mexican prosecutors and military officials agreed to focus on different leaders of the gang, and Mr. Madrazo put Mr. Patino, 49, in charge of his side of the investigation.</p>
        <p>Pepe Patino, as his friends called him, was in some ways an obvious choice. He had worked intermittently on the Arellano case since 1993, when the gang was blamed for killing a Roman Catholic cardinal.</p>
        <p>Although American law enforcement officials are generally loath to vouch for their Mexican counterparts, Mr, Patino had earned a reputation for honesty on both sides of the border.</p>
        <p>''If you needed any kind of help, he was there,'' said Reid C. Pixler, a federal prosecutor in Phoenix who worked closely with Mr. Patino. ''He was absolutely courageous. He was extremely bright. He did everything he ever promised and more.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Patino rushed to the scene on March 3, 1994, after Mexican federal agents working under a young police commander, Alejandro Castaneda, caught up with a man they believed to be Ismael Higuera and one later identified as the youngest of the Arellano brothers, Francisco Javier, in Tijuana. When Mr. Castaneda ordered the men to surrender, they and their bodyguards opened fire, killing him.</p>
        <p>In an interview years later, Mr. Patino said he argued bitterly with state justice officials over the custody of the suspects. After a tense standoff, the state officials took the men away, only to allow them to sneak out the back entrance of a state police office hours later.</p>
        <p>''That was the way things were,'' Mr. Patino recalled.</p>
        <p>For the federal police team with whom Mr. Patino worked, it was the latest in a long series of mishaps and frustrations. ''They got their clocks cleaned in Tijuana,'' recalled Alex M. Romero, an American drug enforcement agent who worked with Mr. Patino's group on several cases in the early 1990's. ''That was definitely their Waterloo.''</p>
        <p>Three weeks after Mr. Castaneda was killed, the shock of his death was swept aside by the assassination here of the governing party's presidential candidate, Luis Donaldo Colosio. Mr. Patino's team was pulled back to Mexico City. Then, after a shake-up in the attorney general's office, the team was disbanded by a senior official who was later found to have worked for the traffickers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Patino returned to the federal anti-drug force in 1997. United States officials were strongly encouraged when he was selected to lead the new push in Baja California.</p>
        <p>The Americans also took it as an indication of Mexico's seriousness that Mr. Patino and a few colleagues had decided to work from San Diego rather than Tijuana -- farther from the prying eyes of other Mexican officials.</p>
        <p>Still, despite the supposed priority and evident danger of their mission, it took Mr. Patino months to obtain financing from Mexico City to rent a house, and his pleas for an armored car were answered only by promises.</p>
        <p>Working closely with agents of the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the Drug Enforcement Administration, Mr. Patino and his colleagues began compiling addresses and seeking search warrants for safe houses, law offices and other businesses that the traffickers used.</p>
        <p>The team had not gotten far, officials said, when word came on March 11 that members of the army's drug intelligence unit had captured the Arellanos' uncle and reputed confederate, Jesus Labra Aviles, a wealthy Tijuana executive.</p>
        <p>Some American officials later speculated that Mr. Patino had been made a target by the Arellanos for his role in helping to transport Mr. Labra to a high-security prison outside Mexico City.</p>
        <p>But a Mexican official who worked closely with him said Mr. Patino appeared to have drawn the traffickers' attention in long battles over search warrants in the notoriously corrupt courts here.</p>
        <p>Colleagues of Mr. Patino said he had been acutely aware of the dangers he had faced. But because of a longstanding dispute between Mexico and the United States over whether agents of one country working in the other could carry guns, Mr. Patino and the two other officials were unarmed when they drove to Tijuana from San Diego on April 10.</p>
        <p>It was only a short distance from the border crossing to a federal police office where they kept their weapons. Along the way, officials said, the three men were intercepted by perhaps 10 others who were heavily armed and clearly knew their routine.</p>
        <p>The three were tortured with a brutality that immediately led officials to suspect Mr. Higuera, 38, who has a considerable reputation for savagery. The men were cut with knives, beaten with bats or pipes and run over with a large truck. The heads of two are thought to have been crushed in a pneumatic press.</p>
        <p>Mr. Higuera, indicted in federal court in San Diego on charges of conspiring to ship tons of cocaine into the United States, was captured on May 3. Mexican police officials said they had helped arrest him at a house near the port city of Ensenada after neighbors had reported a wild party.</p>
        <p>But officials said he had been caught in a complex operation in which Mexican intelligence agents, set in motion by the C.I.A., had tracked his Colombian girlfriend and a friend of hers.</p>
        <p>American officials said they had growing evidence that Mr. Higuera had been captured by the Mexican military a month before in Mazatlan, the western resort city, only to be freed by the police.</p>
        <p>Mr. Madrazo's office denied that. But its account was publicly challenged by a spokesman for the Defense Ministry and an army general in Baja California.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
