<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commencement; Speaker Implores Science Graduates To Be Ethical</title>
    <meta content="05COMM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">Polytechnic University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Massey, Walter E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E3D7163FF936A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="337" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commencement; Speaker Implores Science Graduates To Be Ethical</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>More than 840 students receive degrees from Polytechnic University during its 145th commencement in Avery Fisher Hall; Walter E Massey, president of Morehouse College, speaks (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than 840 students received degrees from Polytechnic University during its 145th commencement in Avery Fisher Hall yesterday.</p>
        <p>The students, from Polytechnic's campuses in Brooklyn, Long Island and Westchester County, were awarded degrees in science, engineering and technology.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than 840 students received degrees from Polytechnic University during its 145th commencement in Avery Fisher Hall yesterday.</p>
        <p>The students, from Polytechnic's campuses in Brooklyn, Long Island and Westchester County, were awarded degrees in science, engineering and technology.</p>
        <p>The university also bestowed honorary degrees on Nathan Marcuvitz, an emeritus professor at Polytechnic and a former Pentagon official who worked in military research and engineering; Morton L. Topfer, a member of the board of directors at the Dell Computer Corporation; and Walter E. Massey, president of Morehouse College in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>Dr. Massey, who delivered the commencement address, cited individuals like Rosa Parks and Vaclav Havel in emphasizing the importance of ethical leadership. Dr. Massey defined ethical leadership as ''service inspired by the highest moral standards and tradition'' and said such leadership is especially important in the scientific and technological fields in which Polytechnic graduates will be working.</p>
        <p>''You have a responsibility and a civic obligation,'' he told the students, ''to see that the fruits of science and technology accrue to the benefit of humankind.''</p>
        <p>Dr. David C. Chang, the university's president, said he envisioned a future that included creating kidneys for transplant out of a petri dish, an AIDS vaccine, and other scientific developments that Polytechnic graduates could help create. He urged the students to continue to gain knowledge, create new knowledge and transform the world.</p>
        <p>David Hernandez, the valedictorian, received degrees in computer and electrical engineering and offered a different kind of advice to his classmates. ''Be crazy,'' he implored them. ''Challenge assumptions. Think different. Don't be afraid to rock the boat.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
