<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Instant Excitement and Mystery. Just Add Ice.</title>
    <meta content="05HOCK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205040"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Stars</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Dallas Stars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E3DA163FF936A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="980" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Instant Excitement and Mystery. Just Add Ice.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joe Lapointe</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Hockey column discusses bad ice conditions inside Reunion Arena where Dallas Stars are playing host to New Jersey Devils in Stanley Cup championship series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Stanley Cup finals continue in a state that borders Mexico, the players fret about bad ice inside Reunion Arena and everyone else notices the warm and humid conditions outside in June.</p>
        <p>''The ice is so bad,'' Martin Brodeur, the Devils' goalie, said yesterday. He tried to leave his net a few times to play the puck Saturday night against the Stars but thought better of it. ''I couldn't get to the puck because I missed the first two, three steps because of the ice,'' Brodeur said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Stanley Cup finals continue in a state that borders Mexico, the players fret about bad ice inside Reunion Arena and everyone else notices the warm and humid conditions outside in June.</p>
        <p>''The ice is so bad,'' Martin Brodeur, the Devils' goalie, said yesterday. He tried to leave his net a few times to play the puck Saturday night against the Stars but thought better of it. ''I couldn't get to the puck because I missed the first two, three steps because of the ice,'' Brodeur said.</p>
        <p>Most players seem to agree that the best ice, any time of year, any place in the National Hockey League, is in Edmonton, where the best teams used to be found when Glen Sather's Oilers won the cup five times from 1984 through 1990.</p>
        <p>Would it make everyone happy for the N.H.L. to do it the way the National Football League does? The N.F.L. plays the Super Bowl at a warm-weather or domed site every January. Why not play the hockey finals every June in Edmonton, a neutral site? They love hockey there. And the late-spring weather is still cold enough to play hockey on outdoor ice.</p>
        <p>(Just kidding on that last one, Canadian friends. Been there in June. Know about the pleasant temperatures and the late-evening sun so far north. Also remember the late-May snowstorm during one finals there back when playoffs used to end before training camp began.)</p>
        <p>It's easy to think about Edmonton these days because so many former Oilers are front and center. Wayne Gretzky, the former Edmonton star, bought into the Phoenix team last week. Sather, the former Edmonton general manager, took over as boss of the Rangers. And Jason Arnott of the Devils, a former Edmonton prospect, scored a dynamic goal Saturday night to help his team gain a 2-1 victory over the Dallas Stars and a two-games-to-one lead in the four-of-seven-game championship round, which resumes here tonight.</p>
        <p>Arnott leads the Devils in playoff points with 19. According to Ken Daneyko, New Jersey's veteran defenseman, Arnott has really started to take on a leadership role. ''He wants to be the go-to guy,'' Daneyko said. ''To be an elite hockey player in this league, you have to have that cocky attitude in a good way.''</p>
        <p>Arnott was a rarity in the last decade of Sather's Edmonton regime: A good pick on the first round of the entry draft. Sather, also a cocky guy, is an angle-player who last week scored a good deal for himself in New York. Critics who cite Sather's poor draft record in Edmonton in the 1990's might also consider his trading record.</p>
        <p>He sent Arnott and Bryan Muir to the Devils in 1998 in a deal for Bill Guerin and Valery Zelepukin. Lou Lamoriello, the Devils' boss, got the best of that one. Like Sather of recent weeks, Lamoriello will soon be a free agent. Unlike Sather, Lamoriello will not take over the Rangers.</p>
        <p>While Lamoriello gets credit for building this Devils team, much applause is directed toward Larry Robinson, the coach who replaced Robbie Ftorek with eight games left in the regular season. For now, Robinson is on a motivational roll. When he threatened to bench Scott Gomez in the Toronto series, Gomez perked up. When Robinson screamed at the team in the Philadelphia series, the team responded well.</p>
        <p>When Robinson publicly chastised the careless play of Petr Sykora and Patrik Elias after Game 2 of the finals, Arnott's Czech wings helped him dominate Game 3. Sykora scored the winning goal Saturday and that line had 13 shots. Here's to you, Mr. Robinson. And today, Elias was not afraid to respond to his coach, in an oblique sort of way.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it is the right approach to just blame individuals for a loss because this is a team,'' Elias said. But he was smiling through the news conference, he and Sykora, up there like two wild and crazy guys, joshing with teammates in the back of the room and off to the sides.</p>
        <p>Such was the mood with these chatty Devils, so many smiles as they mingled with the news media. On the Dallas side, things are glum. Stars supporters fear that the defending champions are too old, too tired, too injured, too slow. But a Dallas victory tonight would change everyone's tune. And tunes are so much a part of the atmosphere in funky Reunion, a barn only two decades old that feels antiquated.</p>
        <p>It seems to hold heat and humidity. Flying insects were cruising the press box Saturday night -- without credentials. The players may hate to skate here and the cramped quarters give the league logistical problems. But the fans are enthusiastic and friendly and the music adds to the ambience. Unlike most N.H.L. arenas, they employ a disc jockey who refuses to assault the senses and sensibilities of the customers by continuously blaring strip-joint rock.</p>
        <p>When the gates opened Saturday, and the fans climbed to their dark, green seats, he softly played ''Sympathy for the Devil,'' in deference to the visiting team. The lights were still dim and the effect was wonderfully creepy. After an icing whistle on the bad ice, the speakers softly emitted ''Ice, Ice, Baby.'' It almost makes a neutral observer pull for a Stars victory tonight to guarantee Game 6 here next Saturday. All things considered, hockey in Dallas is pretty cool.</p>
        <p>ON HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
