<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brownsville Journal; Colorful Flock Seeks Better Life in a Border City</title>
    <meta content="Y05PAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">1008 Words</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFDC163FF936A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1008" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brownsville Journal; Colorful Flock Seeks Better Life in a Border City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROSS E. MILLOY</byline>
      <dateline>BROWNSVILLE, Tex., June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Just as the blazing afternoon sun softens and begins to set, the parrots start to arrive, squawking and keening as they wheel high overhead in the blue sky and drop into the upper fronds of palm trees growing along the Rio Grande. ''They do</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just as the blazing afternoon sun softens and begins to set, the parrots start to arrive, squawking and keening as they wheel high overhead in the blue sky and drop into the upper fronds of palm trees growing along the Rio Grande.</p>
        <p>''They do that every night,'' says  Jessie Moreno, a cashier at the Fort Brown Hotel, who likes to watch the birds roosting on the hotel grounds. ''They come swooping back here when it starts to get dark and spend the night up in those palm trees. In the morning they'll take off again and fly out over the city looking for food.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just as the blazing afternoon sun softens and begins to set, the parrots start to arrive, squawking and keening as they wheel high overhead in the blue sky and drop into the upper fronds of palm trees growing along the Rio Grande.</p>
        <p>''They do that every night,'' says  Jessie Moreno, a cashier at the Fort Brown Hotel, who likes to watch the birds roosting on the hotel grounds. ''They come swooping back here when it starts to get dark and spend the night up in those palm trees. In the morning they'll take off again and fly out over the city looking for food.''</p>
        <p>The birds call to each other as they dart from tree to tree, brightly colored slashes of green, yellow and blue, and when a truck backfires nearby they howl and take to the air as one, screaming wildly as they swirl overhead.</p>
        <p>''Don't worry,'' Ms. Moreno says, ''they'll be back.''</p>
        <p>But the parrots, more than 300 of a species known scientifically as Amazona viridigenalis, are not really supposed to be here in the first place.</p>
        <p>Wild parrots in an urban environment like this dusty, bustling border city seem unusual enough, but this flock is also odd for other reasons, local experts say.</p>
        <p>They are at least a hundred miles from their typical roosting grounds deep in Mexico, and a third of the parrots are birds released by or escaped from smugglers trying to slip them illegally into the country, said Steve Walker, a staff member at the University of Texas at Brownsville who leads birding tours as part of the university's adult education programs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walker said a devastating freeze in 1982, coinciding with an agrarian overhaul that deforested large sections of northern Mexico, combined to draw a majority of the birds into the Brownsville area.</p>
        <p>''After that freeze we started seeing large numbers of free-range parrots here,'' Mr. Walker said. ''Our conjecture is that a flock of old veterans, who had made the trip before, decided to come up out of Mexico into this area to forage. These birds can live to be 60 to 70 years old, and sometimes longer than that.''</p>
        <p>There is anecdotal evidence from old military diaries, Mr. Walker said, of sightings of parrots even farther north, along the Nueces River area, at a time when Gen. Zachary Taylor's troops were quartered there in the Mexican War in 1847.</p>
        <p>''That was in November, in the pecan season, and these parrots just love pecans,'' he said. ''So they must have flown at least 200 miles even further north to look for them.''</p>
        <p>The Brownsville flock now contains more than 160 nesting pairs of three types of parrots: yellow-cheek parrots, also known as red-lored, red-crowned parrots, and, the most colorful of the local flock, yellow-head parrots, Mr. Walker said.</p>
        <p>''We think most, if not all, of the yellow-heads are escaped or released birds,'' he said. ''But the red-crowns have just wandered into the area to feed and ended up staying.''</p>
        <p>Most of the escaped or released birds would have been trapped along the Rio Corona or Rio Soto La Marina in southern Tamaulipas, Mexico, Mr. Walker said, and the red-crowned parrots would have come from still farther south. It is illegal to bring any of the parrots into the country, he said.</p>
        <p>''You can see that some members of the flock still have their wings clipped as a bird smuggler would do; those are released or escaped birds,'' Mr. Walker said, adding that they were easy to spot: ''They have to beat their wings twice as fast to go half as far.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Walker, who became interested in the birds when he was the host of a local wildlife show on television, says the birds eat palm dates, citrus from the vast commercial groves that surround Brownsville, and mosquitoes that swarm over the city's many ''resacas,'' a kind of catchment pond for rain.</p>
        <p>Until two years ago, there was a Catch-22 in protecting parrots from hunters or trappers, Mr. Walker said.</p>
        <p>''They weren't supposed to be here, so they weren't really covered by state laws,'' he said. But Mr. Walker and other local wildlife enthusiasts worked with the Texas Birding Association to have the local parrots designated as a native population in 1998, making them a protected species.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walker also led a successful effort to have the parrot designated as the official bird of Brownsville.</p>
        <p>The birds are monogamous for life, keep their families together for a long time, and have what Mr. Walker calls shared intelligence. ''That means they like to talk to each other,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The parrots are also amazingly adaptive creatures, he said. The same freeze that drew the birds here in the early 1980's killed many local palm trees, and the rotted trunks make perfect homes for the parrots.</p>
        <p>To build their nests, the parrots find holes made by woodpeckers seeking insects in bark. The parrots then patiently peck and claw at the woodpecker holes to create a cavity large enough for nesting.</p>
        <p>Back on the hotel grounds, Ms. Moreno slapped the base of one of those palm trees with her bare hand and two small yellow parrot heads popped inquisitively from a hole halfway up the tree.</p>
        <p>''Those two have a nest in there, so we'll be seeing some more babies soon,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
