<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks Want Ewing for Another Run</title>
    <meta content="05KNIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE2DA163FF936A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1119" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks Want Ewing for Another Run</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE, N.Y., June 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article speculates on possible changes for New York Knickerbocker next season following loss to Indiana Pacers in NBA Eastern Conference championship series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Patrick Ewing backed his cobalt blue Porsche into a parking space, untangled his long legs from behind the wheel and stepped out to greet a young boy holding a basketball and pen in front of him.</p>
        <p>''I ain't signing that,'' he grumbled as he hustled inside the Knicks' practice facility to pack his things two days after the team was eliminated in the Eastern Conference finals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Patrick Ewing backed his cobalt blue Porsche into a parking space, untangled his long legs from behind the wheel and stepped out to greet a young boy holding a basketball and pen in front of him.</p>
        <p>''I ain't signing that,'' he grumbled as he hustled inside the Knicks' practice facility to pack his things two days after the team was eliminated in the Eastern Conference finals.</p>
        <p>Irascible? Yes. But underneath the crankiness, he is also a valiant figure in Knicks lore and a beleaguered but still valuable center whom General Manager Scott Layden wants to keep for another run at the National Basketball Association finals.</p>
        <p>Usually spare in personnel comments, Layden broke out of character today and sent a message to any teammates who have privately grumbled about Ewing and the critics who have dismissed his worth to the Knicks.</p>
        <p>''Once again, we need to find a way to get back to the finals,'' Layden said just after the players ended a half-hour team meeting with Coach Jeff Van Gundy at SUNY-Purchase. ''I believe in order to get back to the finals, he has to be part of the team. That's very important. I think Patrick is a critical part of the team. I appreciate what he does and what he brings night in and night out.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to get into anyone else. I mention that because I feel like, over the last while, he's been taking unfair criticism. That's why him.''</p>
        <p>Layden did not issue the same support for Latrell Sprewell, Allan Houston, Marcus Camby or any other Knick. Any or all could be gone by next season. And Ewing could be among them. Increasingly weary from years of scrutiny in New York, Ewing was less than emphatic about his plan to return, though he has one year left on his $68 million deal.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to answer any questions about that stuff,'' he said. ''I don't want to answer that. Last year I said something and y'all blew it out of proportion.''</p>
        <p>A year ago, after sitting out the Knicks' appearance in the finals with a partly torn Achilles' tendon, Ewing was asked if he could have made a difference against San Antonio.</p>
        <p>''I need to play,'' he said. ''That's it.'' Then he stubbornly added, ''My role doesn't change.''</p>
        <p>Today, Ewing was more subdued and more measured in his responses.</p>
        <p>''I'm not doing the same thing this year,'' Ewing said before rattling off answers to questions that were not asked. ''So, I'm very happy with my teammates. We had a good year. I'm disappointed we didn't beat Indiana and get to the finals, but hopefully next year we can accomplish that.''</p>
        <p>Once again, the Knicks will try to find the right complementary starters if Ewing returns. The Knicks are certain to pursue sign-and-trade options for Detroit's Grant Hill and player-for-player trade scenarios for Seattle's Gary Payton. To make either deal a reality, the Knicks would have to break up the duo of Houston and Sprewell. One would have to go.</p>
        <p>''I don't know what to expect,'' Sprewell said. ''I hope I'll be here. You never know what will happen. I don't expect to be traded, but you don't know. I would love to stay. If I don't, I'd be very disappointed.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell, as a small forward, is part of a structural flaw in the Knicks: their small lineup has been vulnerable to rebounding discrepancies. Not only is Sprewell matched up against bigger bodies, so is Larry Johnson, who is a battered small forward playing power forward.</p>
        <p>''Rebounding in itself, and I don't want to talk about specific changes, but it's critical to being able to win in the playoffs,'' Van Gundy said. ''Possessions are so important. In 12 of our 16 playoff games, we were outrebounded. I don't know what the change is, but a critical change has to be rebounding.''</p>
        <p>Durability has become a weakness. Camby missed 23 regular-season games; Chris Childs (7), Ewing (20, plus 2 playoff games) and Johnson (11) also had injury absences.</p>
        <p>Camby was especially haunted by a midseason knee injury. He never seemed to regain the explosive form of last season's playoffs, and now he may be used in a trade to find a sturdier power forward.</p>
        <p>''I think my statement during the year was that this was our best chance to win a title, but not necessarily our last chance,'' Van Gundy said. ''When I said that, we were the healthiest we'd been in a long time. We were playing well. Things changed from the time. I don't think by any means it was a last chance. But the durability of our team, some of that can be corrected, but not all of it can be.''</p>
        <p>Ewing, 38, and Johnson, 31, have chronic pains. One day, the pain may prompt Johnson to exit the league before the last four years of his 12-year $84 million deal are up. He is expected to have minor surgery next week on a disk in his lower back to alleviate chronic pain.</p>
        <p>One day, Ewing will retire. Just not soon. ''I have a lot of good years in me,'' he said.</p>
        <p>There is only one year left on his deal, though. Layden would like to see him retire as a Knick -- ''Patrick is a Knick, and he exemplifies what this team is all about,'' Layden said -- but he did not comment about whether Ewing expressed a desire to return next season, or if the organization would offer him a contract extension this summer.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to discuss anything more about Patrick,'' Layden said.</p>
        <p>For the typically reserved Layden, a public show of affection for Ewing meant a lot. Ewing, if he desires, will be back. Some of his teammates -- a few of whom quietly blamed Ewing for their troubles -- could be on their way out. These are the decisions Layden will make in his first off-season as the architect of the Knicks.</p>
        <p>''Is the ball in my court?'' Layden said. ''These decisions are not made right after you lose. You always have to have a period to let things settle down, let the emotions settle down. We had a tough loss in the Garden, and you don't make decisions that night.''</p>
        <p>Soon, though, very soon.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
