<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sales? The Internet Will Handle That. Let's Talk Solutions.</title>
    <meta content="07SLAD$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TO BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Salesmen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slade, Margot</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EEDC1E3DF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1273" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sales? The Internet Will Handle That. Let's Talk Solutions.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGOT SLADE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slade, Margot</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Internet is changing role of sales representatives; managers in many industries are pressing their sales forces to use time freed up by customers' ability to track product availability, price and deliveries via Internet to harness Internet to redefine and expand their roles and turn customers into long-term business partners; extranets, secure sites or links with limited access to business customer, are at heart of current sales force transformation; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CALL them ''vendors'' at your peril. Even references to working in ''product sales'' are met with tight-lipped grins.</p>
        <p>Try relationship managers, account specialists, value-added consultants, solution providers, orchestra leaders or quarterbacks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CALL them ''vendors'' at your peril. Even references to working in ''product sales'' are met with tight-lipped grins.</p>
        <p>Try relationship managers, account specialists, value-added consultants, solution providers, orchestra leaders or quarterbacks.</p>
        <p>And what exactly do these born-again sales representatives do? Opportunity identification, client development and service delivery, or as one executive put it, in a phrase echoed by others, ''They leverage our intellectual capital so that we and our customers win.''</p>
        <p>Take that, Willy Loman.</p>
        <p>No longer are business-to-business sales simply a matter of closing the deal. Over the last two years, customers have been learning to do it themselves -- track product availability, price and deliveries -- using well-crafted Web sites and a few quick clicks. Such self-sufficiency frees up the 40 percent of a sales representative's day that was consumed with these mundane tasks, according to several executives who did time and management studies.</p>
        <p>Managers in many industries expect their sales forces to use those hours creatively by harnessing the Internet to redefine and expand their roles and turn stop-and-shop customers into long-term business partners.</p>
        <p>''I don't simply sell chemicals anymore; I sell the full range of Eastman's services,'' said Kathy M. Wachala, a principal account supervisor at the Eastman Chemical Company in Kingsport, Tenn., an international manufacturer of plastics, chemicals and fibers with $4.6 billion in sales last year. ''I identify Eastman's capabilities and those of our customers. Then I look for partnering opportunities -- a manufacturing process we could help simplify, a new product we could help improve.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Wachala has worked for the company, an international manufacturer of plastics, chemicals and fibers with $4.6 billion in sales last year, for 10 years. Her job these days, she said, is to lead a ''consultative team'' culled from each department; her goal is to nurture relationships by making customers ''more loyal, more profitable, more reliant on us.''</p>
        <p>Sound like the death of a salesman? How about the resurrection and rebirth? But not without labor pains.</p>
        <p>Listen, for example, to the description of the perfect sales representative, according to Christian Nivoix, the global general manager, distribution sector, for I.B.M.: ''The best sales people must be curious enough to learn all they can about each customer; smart enough to embrace the Web as a valuable tool in that regard; flexible enough to engage in 'co-opetition,' '' or joining forces in one area today with a customer you'll compete against tomorrow. They also must be intimate enough with I.B.M. to ''weave together integrated solutions'' to new business needs.</p>
        <p>''Some people are willing and capable of this fluidity,'' Mr. Nivoix said. ''Others are not.''</p>
        <p>Roger K. Mowen Jr., vice president for Eastman's CustomerFirst initiative and chief information officer, agrees. ''We've given our sales people every opportunity to 'skill up,' '' he said. ''But we hold them responsible for keeping up as we change our company's culture from product-based to customer-centric, from transactional to problem solving.''</p>
        <p>And if they don't? ''We try to find other options for them within the organization. But for some, this may not be the place.''</p>
        <p>The sales ranks, he noted, have already thinned. ''Mostly new hires form the core now,'' he said. ''The rest were worked out of the system.''</p>
        <p>At the heart of the current sales force transformation are extranets -- secure sites or connections with limited access to, in this case, a business customer. Databased transactions, like ordering from catalogs, checking prices and product availability, and tracking deliveries, are ripe for this Web-style automation.</p>
        <p>''As the low-hanging fruit -- the common transactions -- migrate to the Web, what's left requires more intellectual input from sales reps, who we call associates,'' said Joe McCrone, area sales director in e-solutions at Ingram Micro Inc., the world's largest wholesale distributor of technology products. Customers, for example, may not have the equipment to perform certain tasks, or with only $100,000 of equity, they want to know whether they can complete a $4 million deal. ''Associates are now in the business of providing solutions, which makes them -- and this company -- value added,'' Mr. McCrone said.</p>
        <p>Many members of Ingram Micro's sales force welcomed the Web as a tool to improve customer satisfaction, thus strengthening loyalty to the company and the sales staff, whose members are now free to trouble-shoot. But as at other transaction-rich enterprises, some members of the telephone sales staff at Ingram Micro, which had $28 billion in revenue last year, feared that the Net would lead to lost sales.</p>
        <p>''They argued that if we made Web use too easy, customers were less likely to call, which gave them fewer opportunities to fine-tune orders or interest customers in other purchases,'' said Guy Abramo, a senior vice president and chief information officer. It was a concern among management, too.</p>
        <p>One response has been to provide incentives to customers who close deals on the phone: the possibility of negotiating lower prices. Other companies are ensuring that sales representatives receive a financial piece of any of their customers' transactions, whether they are conducted in person, by phone, fax or on the Web.</p>
        <p>''It encourages account managers to nurture personal relationships with customers,'' said Harry J. Harczak Jr., the chief financial officer of CDW Computer Centers Inc., a direct marketer of brand-name computer products. ''And it's those relationships that make it difficult -- and costly -- for customers to switch suppliers.''</p>
        <p>Web-literate sales representatives have learned to use extranets to assemble customer sales histories. By analyzing the data, they can augment their own sales potential.</p>
        <p>Lynn Brubaker, the vice president and general manager of the commercial market, aerospace, at Honeywell, said that by compiling and sharing data, her sales force was spotting trends and identifying opportunities for growth -- opportunities that customers sometimes knew nothing about.</p>
        <p>''You wouldn't necessarily think that this would require our sales people to become strategic marketing people,'' she said. But it has.</p>
        <p>I.B.M. sales representatives have used extranets to identify clients they might otherwise have missed. The process can start, said David J. White, I.B.M.'s director of solution sales and business partners for the public sector, when sales representatives go to large state meetings and get the word out to small municipalities that I.B.M. can serve their needs. When customers log on to the appropriate Web site, Mr. White and his colleagues take the initiative.</p>
        <p>''I can see which products and services they're interested in,'' he said, ''and begin to anticipate their needs.''</p>
        <p>In suburban Chicago, CDW Computer Centers uses the extranet to help its telephone sales force project that ''personal touch'' once reserved for face-to-face encounters. The 17-year-old company, which had just more than $2.5 billion in revenue last year, has 820 account managers. None of them venture into the field.</p>
        <p>They do post their photographs online, however, as well as those of their backups, so that their customers can see the people behind the voices. Thanks to a special hookup, customers can even see whether their account manager is in the office.</p>
        <p>''It saves time when you're trying to track someone down,'' Mr. Harczak said, which makes it a natural enhancement to customer satisfaction. ''Besides, it's a great way to bond.''</p>
        <p>And, who knows, it could be the beginning of a beautiful friendship.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS TO BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
