<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Down at the Pub: Good Food, for One Thing</title>
    <meta content="07PUBS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="EN ROUTE: ENGLAND" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205395"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Apple, R W Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EEDB143FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2111" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Down at the Pub: Good Food, for One Thing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Apple, R W Jr</byline>
      <dateline>ROWDE, England</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>R W Apple article, one in series on Britain, reports on the vast improvement in food served at country pubs; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANGLOPHILE though I am, there are several English institutions whose charm has always eluded me, like hot-water bottles and milky tea. Country pubs used to have an honored place on that short list as well.</p>
        <p>You know the type: smoky, grubby joints where a bunch of rheumy old men commune with their beers and a bunch of noisy young louts drink away their disappointments. Food, obviously an afterthought, consists of delicacies like stodgy industrial sausages, more soybean than pork; canned baked beans; frozen fish; meat pies with cardboard crusts; and faded greens drenched in salad cream, a kind of sweet, runny mayonnaise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANGLOPHILE though I am, there are several English institutions whose charm has always eluded me, like hot-water bottles and milky tea. Country pubs used to have an honored place on that short list as well.</p>
        <p>You know the type: smoky, grubby joints where a bunch of rheumy old men commune with their beers and a bunch of noisy young louts drink away their disappointments. Food, obviously an afterthought, consists of delicacies like stodgy industrial sausages, more soybean than pork; canned baked beans; frozen fish; meat pies with cardboard crusts; and faded greens drenched in salad cream, a kind of sweet, runny mayonnaise.</p>
        <p>Generations of Britons ate this wretched stuff, and politely pronounced it ''lovely'' if asked by the publican whether they had enjoyed it, largely because nothing else was available at an affordable price.</p>
        <p>Happily, the last decade has seen the birth of an altogether different breed. The old boozers, thousands of them, are still in business, but their parking lots are not as crowded as those of the new places that concentrate on food as much as drink, and on wine as much as beer. These are called gastro-pubs. I know, I know, the word is horrible. It sounds like a patent remedy for indigestion, but the pubs themselves are a godsend for hungry travelers -- imaginative and informal, inexpensive and democratic.</p>
        <p>There are not nearly enough of them. But the visitor to Bath can take a detour to Rowde to lunch on Tim Withers's twice-baked cheese souffle at the George and Dragon. The foot-weary pilgrim to Canterbury can dine at the Dove, in nearby Dargate, whose address (Plum Pudding Lane) is as irresistible as Nigel Morris's saddle of lamb and the lilacs that perfume its garden in spring. Those headed north will find fine pub grub in the Lake District, at the Punch Bowl Inn, Crosthwaite, and in Yorkshire, the land of hearty eaters, at the Angel Inn in Hetton and the Star Inn at Harome.</p>
        <p>A few brave souls have been cooking expertly in publike settings for a very long time. But the modern gastro-pub movement started in 1991 on Farringdon Road in London, not far from the offices of The Guardian newspaper, when David Eyre and Michael Belben set up shop. Their pub, the Eagle, attracted hordes of customers with pastas, simply grilled meats and fish, California-style salads and meridional exotica like squid and paella Valenciana.</p>
        <p>It soon attracted competition -- at first in the capital and more recently in the countryside. The food critic Matthew Fort wrote, ''We were ready for anywhere that divvied up good-grade grub at non-rip-off prices, and didn't demand that we wear a jacket and tie and speak in whispers.''</p>
        <p>In 1998, the Michelin guide to Britain began listing pubs; this year, it singles out a dozen for special recognition for good food.</p>
        <p>THE George and Dragon may be the prototypical country gastro-pub. Housed in a nondescript building in a nondescript village, it does nothing to call attention to itself. You could drive past it 100 times and never imagine it was anything special.</p>
        <p>Inside, there's a bar with pumps for British beer, a few stools, a fireplace. No rugs on the floor, just a few bright pictures and a collection of old plates on the walls. Old, mismatched wooden chairs and tables, with no cloths. Paper napkins and no-nonsense stainless steel cutlery. As in many pubs, you order your food and drink at the bar before finding an empty table somewhere.</p>
        <p>But the menu instantly puts you on notice that this is something different. One day this spring, it offered not-so-plain English dishes like a wild mushroom and quail's egg tart, a warm salad of scallops and bacon -- and that aforementioned souffle, a rich little number, as much savory custard as souffle, which my wife, Betsey, has ordered every single time we have eaten in Rowde. Oh yes, and a half-dozen deeply cupped Exe River oysters, opened with great care so not a drop of the sweet juices was wasted.</p>
        <p>Regulars never fail to cast an eye toward the blackboards above the bar, where the daily fish specials are listed -- perhaps Thai fish curry with shrimp, red mullet, tuna and scallops would appeal, or a hefty slab of perfectly grilled turbot on a lake of chervil-flecked hollandaise. All of this comes straight from day boats operating from small ports in Cornwall, the bit of England that juts the farthest out into the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>Another day, there might be a whole cracked crab or grilled lobster with herb butter. Mr. Withers cooks only what is freshest and best, and while he is open to methods and combinations from everywhere, he knows enough not to stretch for effect. Underlying every dish is his unpretentious brand of classicism. Good ingredients do their own thing, with minimal mucking about. That is the gastro-pub style.</p>
        <p>Mr. Withers's pedigree is impeccable: he worked with Joyce Molyneux, whose Carved Angel at Dartmouth was one of the country's best restaurants in the 1970's and 1980's; she worked with George Perry-Smith, who ran the Hole in the Wall in Bath in the 1950's and 1960's. He, along with the food writer Elizabeth David, led the postwar English culinary renaissance.</p>
        <p>Most gastro-pubs have short, serviceable wine lists. The George and Dragon's is longer and more imaginative than the norm, reflecting the catholic tastes of Bill Baker, the wine merchant who helped to assemble it. The reds include Chivite from Navarre, Rioja's underrated next-door neighbor; Qupe syrah from California; and Bandol from Tempier in the South of France. Whites range from Aubert de Villaine's deliciously crisp, modestly priced Bouzeron from Burgundy to Avignonesi's well-balanced Tuscan chardonnay, Il Marzocco.</p>
        <p>ANOTHER pub with a taste for fish is the Drewe Arms at Broadhembury, a blissfully unspoiled village of thatched houses, lost in a maze of hedgerow-bordered lanes at the eastern edge of Devon. In this idyllic countryside, almost too peaceful to be true, sheep graze on ever-green hillsides. Yet, the motorway is only minutes away.</p>
        <p>Like most gastro-pubs, the Drewe Arms is owned by its chefs. Nigel Berge and his wife, Kerstin, take turns cooking. Her Swedish roots show in dishes like exceptionally silky gravlax, pickled herrings served with a healthy shot of aquavit, and Jansson's Temptation, an inspired Nordic version of scalloped potatoes that incorporates lightly cured anchovies.</p>
        <p>But this is England, and the Drewe Arms also serves an excellent grilled Dover sole. Service is full of good cheer; when someone at our table thought his sole slightly undercooked, it was whisked away and returned moments later, done to a golden turn.</p>
        <p>Across the county line in Dorset, deep in Thomas Hardy country, the Fox Inn at Corscombe serves an astonishing variety of food in an old thatched building garlanded in roses. A sign warns, ''No dogs or badly behaved children.'' We saw no evidence of either. This is a cottagey pub, welcoming in winter with its low ceilings, flagstone floors and broad inglenook fireplaces. When we stopped for lunch in January, primroses were blooming out front; the climate-tempering English Channel is nearby.</p>
        <p>''It's like going to visit Snow White,'' Betsey said as we watched locals cluster around the bar. Not everyone eats, but everyone drinks and everyone chats. The Fox has retained its role as the neighborhood meeting place while establishing a reputation as a restaurant. As he emptied his pint, a regular called out to the barman: ''Cheerio, Peter. See you tonight.''</p>
        <p>Game, fish and meat come from local sources. We liked the tagine of beef; the sparklingly fresh squid in a spicy sauce of ginger, garlic and chili peppers; and the chicken breasts in a light, peppery cream sauce, a dish that spoke more of the 1950's than the 2000's. The roast leg of lamb, grossly overcooked from our viewpoint, was an unwelcome reminder of the bad old days.</p>
        <p>Defining a gastro-pub can be tricky. Some pubs that serve good food are no longer real pubs; they have crossed the line into restaurant territory. You can't imagine people popping in for a whiskey or a shandy, and they are no longer quite basic enough. Tablecloths or carpets or even wallpaper makes an appearance at places like the Three Lions at Stockton in Hampshire and the Sir Charles Napier at Chinnor, in the Chiltern Hills of Oxfordshire.</p>
        <p>The Goose at Britwell Salome, also near Oxford, has carpets on the floor, and its barroom is painted a most unpublike shade of pink (the back dining room is a more subdued bottle green). But everything else rings true, especially the daily three-course set lunch for a mere $16 -- a bargain in a country that offers few of them. Not surprisingly, it was jammed when I stopped by on a rainy Thursday recently.</p>
        <p>For the price of an appetizer in some of the grander London salons, I had a frittata of vegetables and herbs (red, green and yellow peppers, zucchini, thyme and rosemary), topped with Parmesan, followed by a slice of grilled salmon draped across a mound of delectable baby spinach and topped with a light chive cream sauce, followed by a cream-filled meringue with orange segments and a zesty orange sauce.</p>
        <p>Everything was light, bright-tasting and carefully thought out. Food fit for a king, you might say, or at least a prince: Chris Barber, the chef and owner of the Goose, cooked for a decade for the Prince of Wales, a notable exception to the gastronomic philistinism of the royal family.</p>
        <p>In the lovely Cotswolds, on the other (western) side of Oxford, whose picturebook villages of golden stone lure visitors by the thousands, one of the better restaurants is the Marsh Goose at Moreton-in-Marsh. Now, its owners, Sonya Kidney and Leo Brooke-Little, have put two nearby pubs at the service of local trenchermen. One is the Churchill Arms at Paxford, not far from the famous gardens at Hidcote; the other is the Hare and Hounds at Foss Cross, on an old Roman road near Cirencester.</p>
        <p>Here again the goal is to provide food that satisfies rather than stupefies. At the Hare and Hounds, I remember a superb chicken-liver parfait and a very slim but tasty peppered ribeye steak, with a sauce so good that my dinner companion literally licked his plate. A good rhubarb and plum crumble came with a glob of Cornish cream.</p>
        <p>The cooking at the Churchill Arms seeks after robust flavors -- Caribbean-style fish cakes with a spicy tomato sauce, for example; deep-fried blue-cheese fritters, nicely paired with beets; lemon sole with a sharp, lemony sauce. Plus world-class French fries and notable desserts, including a cherry frangipani tart and properly sticky toffee pudding. It all tasted fabulous the last time we were there, partly (but surely not exclusively) because we ate under an umbrella in the garden on a rare 73-degree summer day.</p>
        <p>The Dove Inn, near Canterbury, is a final example of what happens when a chef, rather than a cook, takes over in the kitchen of a pub. Mr. Morris learned his craft in well-regarded country-house kitchens, and his wife, Bridget, knows instinctively how to make people feel welcome. Add a bosky landscape dotted with oast houses, apple trees and trellises of hops, and graceful chestnut colts idling nearby, and you have a magic day in Kent.</p>
        <p>Inside, the pub is all unpainted wood -- bar, paneling, floor, chairs, tables. Old sepia-toned photographs of pub and village hang on the walls. On the plate, the influence of France, an hour or so away through the Channel Tunnel, is clear in dishes like a terrine of goose foie gras and a confit of duck served on a heap of mashed potatoes lightly flavored with Meaux mustard. But there are also simply cooked fish from local harbors, and Anglo-Italian items like sweetbreads with a sorrel risotto.</p>
        <p>It's all a long, long way from fish fingers and baked beans on toast.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
