<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mount Holyoke Drops SAT Requirement</title>
    <meta content="Y07HOL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205474"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Scholastic Assessment Test</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mount Holyoke College</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilgoren, Jodi</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E4DC153FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="451" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mount Holyoke Drops SAT Requirement</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JODI WILGOREN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilgoren, Jodi</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mount Holyoke College drops requirement that applicants submit College Board scores after year-long study by faculty committee; similar policy adopted by other institutions noted; college dean Jane Brown says students spend exaggerated amount of time preparing for test which could be spent in more valuable ways to better support their success in college (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a time of increased reliance on standardized tests -- and mounting concern over their fairness -- Mount Holyoke College, the nation's oldest institution of higher learning for women, has decided to stop requiring applicants to submit College Board scores.</p>
        <p>Mount Holyoke, an elite liberal arts campus of about 2,200 students in South Hadley, Mass., joins a handful of highly selective colleges, including Bates and Bowdoin, both in Maine; Connecticut College in New London and Bard in Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., which have made standardized tests optional. Over all, about 390 of the country's nearly 1,800 four-year colleges and universities do not require such tests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At a time of increased reliance on standardized tests -- and mounting concern over their fairness -- Mount Holyoke College, the nation's oldest institution of higher learning for women, has decided to stop requiring applicants to submit College Board scores.</p>
        <p>Mount Holyoke, an elite liberal arts campus of about 2,200 students in South Hadley, Mass., joins a handful of highly selective colleges, including Bates and Bowdoin, both in Maine; Connecticut College in New London and Bard in Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., which have made standardized tests optional. Over all, about 390 of the country's nearly 1,800 four-year colleges and universities do not require such tests.</p>
        <p>Holyoke plans a five-year study, supported by the Mellon Foundation, to look at how making SAT scores optional affects its applicant pool and student success.</p>
        <p>''There has been a kind of reductionism in higher education, reducing students to numbers, reducing institutions to numbers,'' said Joanne V. Creighton, the college's president.</p>
        <p>Several other institutions -- including public universities in Texas, California, Florida and Massachusetts -- have also recently moved to de-emphasize College Board scores to ward off criticism from opponents of affirmative action, since whites tend to perform better on such tests than black and Hispanic students.</p>
        <p>Jane Brown, dean of enrollment at Mount Holyoke, said the college decided to abandon SAT's after a year of study by a faculty committee. At Holyoke, test scores account for only about 10 percent of admission decisions; the college also requires students to submit several essays, and it interviews applicants and studies their resumes in search of leadership ability and other special talents.</p>
        <p>''One of our concerns is that students are spending an inordinate amount of time, an exaggerated amount of time, preparing for the test,'' Ms. Brown said. ''It could be spent in more valuable ways that would better support their success in college.''</p>
        <p>Chiara Coletti, a spokeswoman for the College Board, said Holyoke's move ''means very little for us,'' observing that students took 2.4 million SAT tests in 1999, an increase of 27 percent over the past six years. She said colleges should never make an admission decision based solely on test scores, adding, ''It's not the test that is the culprit, it's the misuse of tests that is at fault and creates a kind of hysteria.''</p>
        <p>''The kinds of signals that Bates or Mount Holyoke or Bowdoin send by not requiring testing say we're going to look at you as an individual, and we're going to look very hard and very carefully,'' said William C. Hiss, a Bates vice president who was its dean of admissions from 1978 to 1994. ''This is not a relaxing of standards.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
