<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Change Jobs Like Clothes? Click Here</title>
    <meta content="07ADEL$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205371"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Adelson, Andrea</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEEDE1E3DF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1423" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Change Jobs Like Clothes? Click Here</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREA ADELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Adelson, Andrea</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Job applicants and employers are increasingly turning to Internet, which has mushroomed with e-cruiting sites; electronic recruiting sites pushed Web hiring into mainstream by spending millions of dollars on high-profile commercials encouraging job seekers to post their resumes without cost; these companies let job seekers search sites by category and location and forward their data to listed employers electronically; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST fall, Gage J. Fellows gamely tried to expand 1159.com, a ''best'' Web site about Denver nightclubs, into a national online travel and entertainment guide. To hire advertising sales representatives, he turned to a local recruiting agency and bought newspaper and radio advertisements. Applicants applied, all right; trouble was, most lacked basic computer skills.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fellows's luck improved with a trial posting on Hotjobs.com, one of the Internet's largest job boards, with 197,000 listings. In three days, 1159.com received 100 resumes from better-qualified applicants. ''People who use Hotjobs have computer skills,'' Mr. Fellows said. ''These are candidates who understand the product.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST fall, Gage J. Fellows gamely tried to expand 1159.com, a ''best'' Web site about Denver nightclubs, into a national online travel and entertainment guide. To hire advertising sales representatives, he turned to a local recruiting agency and bought newspaper and radio advertisements. Applicants applied, all right; trouble was, most lacked basic computer skills.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fellows's luck improved with a trial posting on Hotjobs.com, one of the Internet's largest job boards, with 197,000 listings. In three days, 1159.com received 100 resumes from better-qualified applicants. ''People who use Hotjobs have computer skills,'' Mr. Fellows said. ''These are candidates who understand the product.''</p>
        <p>With renewed confidence, he agreed to a two-month, $1,800 contract with Hotjobs and posted 30 job openings in six cities. Now, Mr. Fellows has a different problem. ''We need a breather,'' he said, buried by an avalanche of 5,000 resumes. He has already hired 10 sales representatives and has 30 more sales positions open. ''It helped us organize a national sales force in a cost-effective way,'' Mr. Fellows said.</p>
        <p>Workers with wanderlust and labor-short employers are increasingly turning to the Internet, which has mushroomed with e-cruiting sites like Monster.com, Hotjobs.com and Headhunter.net. These companies pushed Web hiring into the mainstream by spending millions of dollars on high-profile 1999 Super Bowl commercials aimed at people who might be restless in their jobs.</p>
        <p>Millions responded, posting their resumes without cost. By allowing job seekers to freely search the sites by category and location, these sites allow them to forward their information to listed employers with a mouse click, accelerating the traditional job-hunting process. Some sites update their postings hourly and offer candidates e-mail notices about openings that match their criteria. To forge long-term relationships with consumers, Hotjobs lets job seekers block some viewers (like a current employer) from reviewing their resumes; Monster sends registered members newsletters with career-management tips. In a telling sign of the virtual world mimicking the real one, e-cruiting traffic peaks on Mondays.</p>
        <p>''The balance of power has shifted,'' said Richard Johnson, the chief executive of Hotjobs.com in Boston, whose quirky marketing taps into worker discontent and belittles corporate loyalty.</p>
        <p>''Ultimately, it's not about the job but the job seeker,'' said Jeffrey C. Taylor, the founder and chief executive of Boston-based Monster.com, the Internet's largest job site, which is owned by a leading recruitment-advertising agency, TMP Worldwide Inc. Monster's advertisements prod the psyche, suggesting the dream career need not be a dream deferred.</p>
        <p>Currently, the fastest-growing group of job hunters are those with less technical acumen, who are now posting their resumes in far greater number. Their influence is starting to broaden the sorts of career-management tools available online, like salary surveys and certification tests, which still cater to the Net's early adopters, technology professionals.</p>
        <p>''It can be tricky finding a site that has a lot of positions for the noncomputer geeks,'' said Christine Tetrault, the human resources director for a software company in Virginia, who found her job at Careerpathcom. The site is built on newspaper classified advertisements and is owned by eight newspaper companies, including The New York Times Company.</p>
        <p>''It was easy and quick and I saved a fortune in stationery and stamps,'' she said in an e-mail message. ''I also liked the ease involved in setting search parameters and checking out what comes up instead of getting all cramped and grimy leaning over the classifieds.''</p>
        <p>Nagib Tharani, 25, a Canadian electrical engineer, is still stunned at the speed at which Hotjobs transformed his life when he graduated from college a year ago. ''I applied to four or five companies on March 4th, got calls on the 8th, flew for an interview on the 16th and was hired the 25th,'' he said, referring to the job he took with a branch of Ericsson Inc., the Swedish wireless company, in Santa Barbara, Calif.</p>
        <p>The sites earn their meal tickets from employers, who pay for a range of services, and advertising sponsors. Job lists come from corporate offices, media buyers and temporary agencies like Manpower and Kelly Services. (An exception is Hotjobs, which refuses to list recruitment-agency openings.) The sites allow managers and commission-based recruiters to tally how often their listings are searched. Some include matchmaking software that pairs resumes with appropriate job descriptions. Most charge employers for access to peruse a site's database of resumes. Top executives, still mostly loyal to headhunters to fill high-level slots, often use job sites to monitor their in-house recruiters.</p>
        <p>For some employers, the Web sites' resume databases are all they need to fill job openings. That is the approach of Julian H. Fisher, the president of Paperpath Inc., a small software publisher in Chestnut Hill, Mass. ''I've changed tactics completely,'' he said, expressing dissatisfaction with recruiters who expected 33 percent commissions and brought him ill-suited prospects. ''They didn't get the jobs we had.''</p>
        <p>Most Internet recruiting sites are voluminous versions of the newspaper classified pages they mirror. Some are addressing the industry's shortcomings: in-baskets that overflow with the resumes of the wrong prospects, and job seekers demoralized when their phones do not ring. Some sites are specialized, while others, mainly those for technology workers, offer screening mechanisms to narrow the applicant field.</p>
        <p>In addition to sites that offer job listings for the technologically savvy like Techies.com and Dice.com, a crop of job sites specialized by industry, region and even subjects is emerging. Sites for bankers, pharmacists and truck drivers are cited at Interbiznet.com, the publisher of a Mill Valley, Calif., online recruiting newsletter that lists job sites. Jobs at summer camps and casinos as well as a site called the Feminist Career Center are listed in Career Crossroads, a directory published by MMC Group of Kendall Park, N.J. Craigslist.org, a San Francisco bulletin board where residents post employment and housing ads, was ranked the ''most efficient'' job recruiting site nationwide in a recent survey of 50 recruiters by Forrester Research in Cambridge, Mass.</p>
        <p>Another twist comes from Flipdog.com, which searches and extracts job postings each week on corporate Web sites and posts them without charge. The site has 505,735 openings, 25 percent more than Monster, some as obscure as a $7-an-hour Zamboni driver needed to groom a Michigan ice rink. ''We're building a site and service that lets people fit in wherever they come from,'' said Brett C. Walker, the vice president for marketing at the company, based in Provo, Utah.</p>
        <p>Late to the party are old-line executive search companies like Korn Ferry International and Heidrick &amp; Struggles, which have set up Futurestep.com and Leadersonline.com, respectively. Analysts predict that, as with other Net latecomers, established recruiters will ultimately eclipse Internet-only start-ups. ''It's the revenge of the bricks and clicks,'' said Adam Waldo, a Credit Suisse First Boston analyst. Most industry executives think that local commission-based recruiters will be the ones most pinched by the Web's lower costs.</p>
        <p>SOME of the first specialty job sites that failed to draw enough visitors are already disappearing and being absorbed in general sites like Monster, which has 3.3 million resumes and most of the Fortune 500 companies as clients. ''It's a community,'' said Mr. Taylor, of Monster. ''You need to have strengths on both sides.''</p>
        <p>It is clear that the real world has its own strengths. Even though e-cruiting revenue is expected to increase fourfold by 2003, to $2.3 billion from $600 million last year, it still is expected to make up just 1 percent of recruiting revenue globally, according to Forrester Research.</p>
        <p>Where electronic job sites still fall short is in assessing a candidate's skills, except in the technical realm. ''Very few job sites have testing screens,'' said Mark J. Anderson, the recruiting director for DoubleClick Inc., an online advertising company in New York that was trying to fill 220 jobs. A third of the company's recent hires came from about 75 online job sites, he said.</p>
        <p>''Attempting to quantify softer skills is a much touchier subject,'' said Mr. Anderson, adding that employers would value behavioral tests to assess applicants before interviewing them. ''The business of talent acquisition is tough.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
