<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="07DIGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E6D8153FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1038" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT&amp;T Plans to Raise Fees On Long-Distance Service  With great fanfare last week, AT&amp;T and the Federal Communications Commission announced that millions of telephone customers would see lower bills as the company passed on savings from a government-ordered reduction in the fees that long-distance companies pay to local phone companies.</p>
        <p>But AT&amp;T also filed documents with the commission that said the company would actually be raising most of the per-minute charges on the basic accounts of millions of customers who make few calls. Moreover, AT&amp;T said this week that it would be raising the monthly fee for some of its popular One Rate plans, which charge single per-minute long-distance rates, by 66 percent, to $5 from $3. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT&amp;T Plans to Raise Fees On Long-Distance Service  With great fanfare last week, AT&amp;T and the Federal Communications Commission announced that millions of telephone customers would see lower bills as the company passed on savings from a government-ordered reduction in the fees that long-distance companies pay to local phone companies.</p>
        <p>But AT&amp;T also filed documents with the commission that said the company would actually be raising most of the per-minute charges on the basic accounts of millions of customers who make few calls. Moreover, AT&amp;T said this week that it would be raising the monthly fee for some of its popular One Rate plans, which charge single per-minute long-distance rates, by 66 percent, to $5 from $3. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>J. P. Morgan to Pay $200,000 Fine  J. P. Morgan agreed to pay a $200,000 fine after regulators found that the firm had repeatedly violated rules requiring that customer limit orders be displayed to the market. N.A.S.D. Regulation, the regulatory arm of the National Association of Securities Dealers, said that the fine was by far the largest ever levied for violation of those rules. Shares of J. P. Morgan fell $3.75, to $133.375. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Profit-Taking Sends Stocks Down  Stocks closed lower as investors took some profits after three consecutive strong sessions. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 79.73 points, or 0.7 percent, to 10,735.57. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index dropped 9.79 points, or 0.7 percent, to 1,457.84, and the Nasdaq composite index decreased 65.39 points, or 1.71 percent, to 3,756.37. [C11.]</p>
        <p>G.M. Chief Plans No Big Changes  G. Richard Wagoner Jr., 47, who became the youngest chief executive of General Motors ever last Thursday, said at G.M.'s annual meeting that he planned to maintain the company's current strategies and expected that new truck models and an emphasis on Internet marketing would lift market share. [C2.]</p>
        <p>A New Studio Receives Financing  Joe Roth, the former head of Walt Disney Studios, has obtained financial backing for his new movie company, Revolution Studios, from Sony Pictures, the Starz Encore Group and Fox Entertainment. [C22.]</p>
        <p>A Chief Who Is Her Own Best Ally  Marguerite McLeod's mother once advised her that minority women always have to be better at everything. So she worked her way through college and graduate school and up the ladder at I.B.M. in Canada. Now, she is the chief executive of an Internet start-up she founded with her husband. The Boss. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Productivity Growth Accelerates  Worker productivity grew 3.7 percent in the first quarter compared with figures in the period a year earlier, the fastest pace in seven years, helping businesses contain labor costs and keeping inflation in check, a government report showed. [C11.]</p>
        <p>An Insurance Inquiry in New York  The New York State Department of Insurance is investigating reports that some insurance companies discriminate against blacks and other minority members. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Pay Attention to These Executives  Now that women make up 40 percent to 45 percent of the business-travel market, the hotel industry is becoming more aware that if it wants to market to them, it has to listen to demands for better service and more home-like rooms. Also, the industry should be aware that women, far more then men, network with one another and are far more likely to compare notes on their travel experiences. Joe Sharkey: Business Travel. [C10.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
