<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="07FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E1D9153FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1232" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-19</p>
        <p>Mideast Talks Are Set To Resume in the U.S.  Israeli and Palestinian negotiators will resume talks on a permanent peace accord next week in the Washington area, Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright said, and Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, will meet with President Clinton there next Wednesday.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-19</p>
        <p>Mideast Talks Are Set To Resume in the U.S.  Israeli and Palestinian negotiators will resume talks on a permanent peace accord next week in the Washington area, Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright said, and Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, will meet with President Clinton there next Wednesday.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Crisis Hurting Fiji's Image  Fiji's appeal to tourists is being severely tested by a hostage drama at the highest levels of government that is exposing ethnic tensions and prompting denunciation abroad.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Peacekeeper Money Released  Senator Judd Gregg, a Republican, who had blocked hundreds of millions approved by Congress for United Nations peacekeeping missions, agreed to release $50 million for a mission in Sierra Leone.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Suharto Loses Libel Case  A Jakarta court ruled that Time magazine did not libel the former Indonesian leader in an article that said Mr. Suharto and his family had amassed a $15 billion fortune in his three decades in power.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Peru Leader Addresses Critics  President Alberto K. Fujimori is promising new efforts to strengthen democratic safeguards in response to international criticism over his re-election in a vote that was widely viewed as flawed.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Hopeful Hint on Church Rift  President Vladimir V. Putin explained to Italians that he had not explicitly invited Pope John Paul II to Russia because he did not want to interfere with discussions on a longstanding rift between the Orthodox and Roman Catholic Churches.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Dispute Over Altered Foods  Prince Charles found his passionately stated views against growing genetically modified crops under assault from his sister, Princess Anne, and his father, Prince Philip.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Women's Foreign Policy Views  American women are more likely than men to frame foreign policy concerns around global social issues like health, poverty and human rights, a poll indicated.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A20-28</p>
        <p>Medicare to Pay for Trials Of Drugs and Treatments  President Clinton will order Medicare to start covering most of the costs of clinical trials testing the value of new drugs and medical treatments for millions of elderly and disabled people, officials said.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Democrat Ad Effort for Gore  The Democratic Party said it was undertaking a $25 million television campaign to ''redefine'' Vice President Al Gore. Breaking with Mr. Gore's own proposal to ban the use of unrestricted contributions to pay for advertising, officials said soft money would cover part of the costs.</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore proposed $38 billion in incentives and tax breaks to improve child care nationwide.</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>G.O.P. Abortion Plank Stands  The chairman of the Republican platform committee has told party members who support abortion rights that Republican leaders plan no change in the platform's strong anti-abortion language.</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>Feuding in the Senate  There were signs that Republicans and Democrats were trying to patch things up after weeks of vitriol and partisanship that threatened the Senate's reputation, or self-image, for deliberation and effectiveness.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>Deciding Fund-Raising Inquiry  A House committee disclosed internal government documents central to a debate over whether Attorney Janet Reno should have sought an independent counsel to investigate Democratic fund-raising in 1996.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>Pizza Chain Settles Bias Case  Domino's said it had reached an agreement with the Justice Department to guarantee deliveries to all neighborhoods unless there was proven evidence that a particular area posed a threat to drivers.</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Mapping Cosmic 'Continents'  A robotic telescope in Australia has produced detailed, large-scale maps of the region of the universe inhabited by Earth and the Milky Way.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Limits on Abortion Pill Foreseen  The government is considering rules for use of the abortion pill RU-486 that could restrict access to the early abortion option, Planned Parenthood's director said.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-12</p>
        <p>Corzine Wins in New Jersey; Republicans in Tight Race  Jon S. Corzine, the Wall Street multimillionaire whose $35 million campaign set a record for a Senate race, defeated former Gov. Jim Florio in the Democratic primary for the seat being vacated by Senator Frank R. Lautenberg. Mr. Florio conceded defeat and said he would support Mr. Corzine in the general election. In the Republican race, State Senator William L. Gormley, a veteran lawmaker from the Atlantic City area, was neck and neck with United States Representative Robert D. Franks, with two other contenders trailing. Rain held down turnout.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Moving Toward Hate-Crime Law  The State Senate is expected to pass its first hate-crimes bill today, and members of the Assembly predicted that some form of hate-crime legislation would become law this year.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Hunt for Mystery Tenant  A woman in an Upper West Side apartment found a skin shed by what experts said was a 54-inch boa constrictor, but no one -- the police, building workers -- has been able to find the snake.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Lazio Pledge on Housing Aid  Representative Rick A. Lazio, the Republican Senate candidate in New York, told a conference of mayors that he would continue to favor federally supported housing and community development programs.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>SAT Requirement Dropped  Mount Holyoke College, the nation's oldest institution of higher learning for women, will stop requiring College Board scores.</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>New Los Angeles Schools Chief  Former Gov. Roy Romer of Colorado was named superintendent of the Los Angeles Unified School District, succeeding Ramon C. Cortines.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C23</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Linebacker Testifies in Atlanta  Ray Lewis testified under a plea agreement that a co-defendant showed him how he repeatedly stabbed a man during a fatal street brawl after the Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>D5</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-22</p>
        <p>Fees May Fall, but Not Rates  AT&amp;T, which said last week that millions of customers would have lower phone bills because of government-ordered cuts in fees, filed documents with the F.C.C. the same day saying it would raise per-minute charges for millions of customers, in some cases by as much as 163 percent.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Deal Made for Bestfoods  Unilever said it would pay $20.3 billion in cash for the maker of Knorr soups, Skippy peanut butter and Hellmann's mayonnaise.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>U.S. Inquiry Into EBay Bidding  The F.B.I. opened an inquiry into whether several eBay users committed fraud by bidding up prices on one another's online auction offerings.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>N.A.S.D. Fines Firm  J. P. Morgan agreed to pay a $200,000 fine after regulators found that the firm had repeatedly violated rules requiring that customer limit orders be displayed to the market.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>$10 Million Gift to Arts Center  James V. Kimsey, an Internet billionaire, gave $10 million to the Kennedy Center in Washington.</p>
        <p>E5</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-10</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A30-31</p>
        <p>Editorials: The new death penalty politics; bringing in Europe on missile defense; how D-Day was won; cleaner power in New York.  Columns: Paul Krugman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E7  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
