<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>10 Months, 10 Minutes, $10 Million</title>
    <meta content="07BARR$32" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WebTaggers.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">barry, courtney</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EFDE1E3DF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>10 Months, 10 Minutes, $10 Million</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COURTNEY BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">barry, courtney</byline>
      <dateline>AUSTIN, Tex.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>WebTaggers.com is one of 21 Internet startups that sought funding at recent Texas Venture Capitalists Conference, Austin; company's long preparation for 10-minute opportunity to pitch business plan described; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EIGHT a.m. Thursday, May 4. Nervous, bleary-eyed, already highly caffeinated, 21 finalists in the Texas Venture Capitalist Conference wait for the lineup at the Four Seasons Hotel. Today they will pitch their business plans, each in a span of 10 minutes, each hoping to secure the start-up money to become an overnight Internet success, complete with initial public offering and a listing on Nasdaq.</p>
        <p>The partners in WebTaggers.com -- Rudy Rouhana, 24, Sean McCullough, 25, and his twin brother, Craig -- have been working nonstop toward this moment since last July, when Mr. Rouhana and Sean McCullough, graduates of New Mexico Tech University, ran into each other in Austin, had a beer and tossed around ideas for a new company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EIGHT a.m. Thursday, May 4. Nervous, bleary-eyed, already highly caffeinated, 21 finalists in the Texas Venture Capitalist Conference wait for the lineup at the Four Seasons Hotel. Today they will pitch their business plans, each in a span of 10 minutes, each hoping to secure the start-up money to become an overnight Internet success, complete with initial public offering and a listing on Nasdaq.</p>
        <p>The partners in WebTaggers.com -- Rudy Rouhana, 24, Sean McCullough, 25, and his twin brother, Craig -- have been working nonstop toward this moment since last July, when Mr. Rouhana and Sean McCullough, graduates of New Mexico Tech University, ran into each other in Austin, had a beer and tossed around ideas for a new company.</p>
        <p>The original idea had to do with posting messages on Web pages, but that has evolved. Now the company's business plan describes WebTaggers as ''an application service provider that delivers highly targeted content for e-merchants,'' enabling retailers from Barnes &amp; Noble way down to Bob's Books to learn the preferences of potential customers who surf their Web sites.</p>
        <p>WebTaggers had to clear high hurdles to get here. Two-hundred twenty companies across the nation applied for a place at this morning's conference, according to David Gerhardt, the president of Capital Network, the  nonprofit economic development firm in Austin that organized it. Capital Network's team of early-stage investors winnowed that number to 21.</p>
        <p>On this warm and humid May morning, WebTaggers' three principals, along with David Chevalier,  their 45-year-old chief executive, are putting the finishing touches on Mr. Chevalier's 10-minute pitch. For the last 18 hours they have allowed me to observe their last-minute preparations, and between cups of lukewarm coffee and frantic phone calls, they have been filling me in on their short, eventful history.</p>
        <p>The three young partners made their first official move last August, hiring a law firm -- Gray Cary Ware &amp; Freidenrich of San Diego -- and working on patent issues. By fall, they had raised their first million dollars in venture capital, from an Austin company called AVLabs. From that experience, Mr. Rouhana said, he and his partners learned an interesting business principle: ''Once you have a venture capitalist, everyone wants to start dating you.''</p>
        <p>AVLabs took the partners through a ''think and drink'' conference, at which potential investors and chief executives meet entrepreneurs over a cocktail to see whether they are a good match. (As Sean McCullough later noted, ''We were asked if we were old enough to drink.'')</p>
        <p>At that meeting, they met Mr. Chevalier. They needed a leader, said Rob Adams, the founder of AVLabs, adding, ''They were optimistically naive -- they didn't know what they didn't know.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chevalier, a tall, dapper former vice president at Dell Computers who has led six other start-ups to success, stepped on board Dec. 1. His job was to develop the company's structure, hire people and, most important, get financing. ''At certain stages,'' he said, ''C.E.O.'s of dot-coms spend 90 percent of their time raising money.'' And that is his job today, at what he calls the ''beauty pageant.''</p>
        <p>''In that 10-minute pitch I've got to give the whole story,'' Mr. Chevalier said. ''And ask for $10 million.''</p>
        <p>4 P.M. WEDNESDAY, MAY 3 -- Seventeen hours to go. Craig McCullough, tired, head in hands, sits in WebTaggers' office in north Austin in front of a computer, barely keeping his eyes open. Computers are everywhere; desks are strewn with papers.</p>
        <p>Sean McCullough, slim, quiet, with a goatee and a nose stud, is reviewing resumes for the six positions they must fill. Mr. Rouhana, tall, confident, eager and sharp-witted, is on the phone talking to potential investors who are not part of the venture capital conference.</p>
        <p>8 P.M. -- Craig McCullough takes the business plan to a printing shop downtown to make copies. Mr. Chevalier is rehearsing his pitch on his trip back to Austin from San Francisco, where he has just met with another start-up company. Sean McCullough and Joe Gorman, the company's marketing director, are writing final code and planning screen shots for the company demos.</p>
        <p>9:30 P.M. -- Tomorrow's audience, the venture capitalists, are in the lounge of the Four Seasons. They are well groomed and prosperous looking: casually dressed but exuding confidence. They are here to have a good time, drinking in the lounge, but are restless, as though ready and eager for the hunt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rouhana is here, working the venture capitalists. He talks shop with Bryan Steffen, of the Berthel Fisher Company. A round of drinks arrives. Nobody seems daunted by Mr. Rouhana's clothing, which is pure grunge: T-shirt and baggy, faded olive-drab military pants. (At the pitch the next morning, he will be wearing the same outfit.)</p>
        <p>11 P.M. -- Throughout the night, phone calls have been flying back and forth. At 11, Mr. Rouhana learns there is a problem with the printing job for the business plan: the shop, backlogged, does not have the right binders. Craig McCullough and WebTaggers' network administrator, Vance  Shtraikh, roll up their sleeves and head over to help with the print job.  Back at the hotel suite, Sean McCullough is trying to open a port on WebTaggers' server: they must be able to connect from the hotel to show the demos. Sometime after midnight, Sean succeeds.</p>
        <p>2 A.M. THURSDAY -- The partners have connected with Mr. Chevalier, whose flight from Dallas was delayed and who has just made the four-hour drive to Austin in a rental car. He had been told by the event's sponsors that on the night before the pitch, there would be a dress rehearsal of sorts.</p>
        <p>''They said, 'No problem, you guys come in any time -- we'll be there,' '' Mr. Chevalier said. ''Well, with all my flight delays and having to drive from Dallas, I ended up at the Four Seasons at midnight or 1 in the morning, and nobody was there in the hotel ballroom. Basically it was just me and all the hotel employees, setting up the chairs and tables. And so I said the hell with it. I just got up and rehearsed my pitch on my own to the hotel employees.''</p>
        <p>At 3, after debating whether to try to get some sleep, the partners and Mr. Chevalier decide to get breakfast at an all-night diner.</p>
        <p>7 A.M. -- The conference kicks off with a buffet breakfast. A Nasdaq representative, Chris Santiago, tells the audience how the exchange has added 228 companies just since January. Impressive, but is anyone paying attention? People look up, acknowledge that he is talking, turn back to their tablemates and sip their coffee. Eyes skirt the room; the venture capitalists seem to be wondering, ''Who should I be talking to here?''</p>
        <p>The room is awash in business cards floating from hand to hand. In the lobby during the presentations, there is a friendly competition among the service providers, and perhaps a biting envy lurking beneath. Lawyers and accountants have booths with slick slogans (''Winning Matters''). They smell money and are dying to land these new companies as clients. At one law firm booth, representatives, friendly at first, offer me a book on Silicon Valley; when they realize I am not a presenter, they dismiss me with a curt ''Enjoy your book.''</p>
        <p>8:01 A.M. -- One hour until showtime. Craig McCullough calls Mr. Rouhana from the print shop. The business- plan copies are done at last. Mr. Chevalier is suited up and ready for the pitch, so ready that he sits in on the four other company pitches before his.</p>
        <p>9:18 A.M. -- Mr. Chevalier speaks before an audience of more than 600 investors, developers, service providers, lawyers, accountants and others. He opens with a joke about an incident involving his family, but it is  his delivery that is crucial. Unlike some of the presenters, who cling to the lectern, he uses the front of the room as a stage, walking confidently  around as he speaks. He seems to know intuitively what the venture capitalists want to hear. ''Very smooth,'' one says.</p>
        <p>Was it a success? The WebTaggers guys say they will not know until the wire transfer date, Aug. 15,  when WebTaggers anticipates that funds from investors will have traded hands. After that? Jan. 1, 2001, the ''fume date,'' which no one really wants to think about -- the point at which, if no venture capital is coming in, the partners must admit defeat.</p>
        <p>''But that's not going to happen,'' Mr. Chevalier said, and there was reason to hope that he was right. Though the recent skid in technology stocks has made venture capitalists want to ''look for deals only with bulletproof economic models,'' as he put it in an interview in late May, the company is showing a profit. And any day now, it is expecting to receive its first formal proposals from a short list of potential investors.</p>
        <p>Courtney Barry, a writer in Austin, Tex., has just finished her first novel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Courtney Barry, a writer in Austin, Tex., has just finished her first novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
