<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All Her Stage Is a World; Its Women Call for Justice</title>
    <meta content="07WOME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205412"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Equality Now (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Sarah (Performance Artist)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Women Can't Win (One-Woman Show)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905EFD9143FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1049" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All Her Stage Is a World; Its Women Call for Justice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Sarah Jones, performance artist whose latest work, Women Can't Win, was commissioned by Equality Now, an international women's organization, to be performed in New York before delegates to UN conference on women; she plays eight characters from eight different countries, each suffering discrimination in different ways; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even for a high-voltage performance artist like Sarah Jones, this was some assignment: draw life and soul, hurt and anguish from the paper and ink of laws that discriminate against women worldwide. That is what Ms. Jones was asked to do by a international women's organization looking for a way to make a United Nations conference sit up and take notice.</p>
        <p>''I've always got some sort of ax to grind in my work,'' said Ms. Jones, 26. So she took the challenge. ''We get to kind of play with reality a little,'' she added.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even for a high-voltage performance artist like Sarah Jones, this was some assignment: draw life and soul, hurt and anguish from the paper and ink of laws that discriminate against women worldwide. That is what Ms. Jones was asked to do by a international women's organization looking for a way to make a United Nations conference sit up and take notice.</p>
        <p>''I've always got some sort of ax to grind in my work,'' said Ms. Jones, 26. So she took the challenge. ''We get to kind of play with reality a little,'' she added.</p>
        <p>The result is ''Women Can't Wait,'' a show written and acted by Ms. Jones, who honed her accents and pithy character portrayals at downtown poetry slams, then graduated to small clubs. Her first solo show, ''Surface Transit,'' a collection of eight New York characters created around the themes of tolerance and intolerance, had its premiere in 1998 at the Nuyorican Poets Cafe and later played at the American Place Theater. It was praised in publications like The Village Voice and Time Out New York and is headed for a summer run at P.S. 122, starting on June 14.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jones -- born into a multiethnic family in Baltimore, raised in Washington and New York and educated at Bryn Mawr -- writes her own material. Her ideas and characters have always come from her own experience, she said. Until now.</p>
        <p>Like ''Surface Transit,'' ''Women Can't Wait'' has eight characters. But these are not the people she sees around her in New York, where she lives. Ms. Jones uses only one prop, a diaphanous shawl, to create her international population. She covers her head and becomes Praveen, a timid woman from India working up the courage to talk about beatings by her husband and the family that denied her sympathy. In an instant, with the shawl transformed into a scarf tied jauntily around her neck, she is Emeraude, a vivacious Frenchwoman defying laws against women working at night.</p>
        <p>And so it goes: shawl up, shawl down, shawl around the waist or over her shoulder. Ms. Jones is Tomoko from Japan, Hala from Jordan, Alma from Uruguay, Bonita from the United States, Shira from Israel. By the time she becomes little Anna from Kenya, the shawl has been balled up and transformed into a child's doll.</p>
        <p>Through it all runs the thread of women who do not theorize but speak from personal, often horrific experience and who sometimes awaken to the injustice done them.</p>
        <p>Today ''Women Can't Wait'' will have a different audience from the one Ms. Jones normally draws in clubs. It is to be performed at the United Nations for official delegates and nongovernmental representatives at an international conference being held five years after the world's largest gathering of women took place in Beijing in 1995.</p>
        <p>Meryl Streep will introduce Ms. Jones. Two additional shows, also limited to conference participants, will be held at the United States Customs House, where the United States government and New York City are to act as hosts to unofficial delegations to the weeklong United Nations meeting. The conference will bring thousands of women from more than 150 nations to the city.</p>
        <p>She will also perform ''Women Can't Wait'' on Friday night at 8 at the Judson Memorial Church, 55 Washington Square South, Greenwich Village. Gloria Steinem will introduce Ms. Jones at that performance, which is open to the public.</p>
        <p>The organization that commissioned the one-woman show, Equality Now, an advocate for women's rights based in New York, works with immigrants in the United States and women in poor countries to fight  laws that it identifies as limiting women's rights and freedoms. For inspiration, it provided Ms. Jones with videos of women in various countries. She said she was deep into research for the piece on the Internet, which she calls ''an interesting kind of portal'' to the world.</p>
        <p>As she does in her other work, she drew ideas from real people but invented her own characters, writing their speeches herself. In this way her pieces differ from those of Anna Deavere Smith, who interviews people and uses their words onstage.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jones, who volunteers in a homeless shelter on Saturdays, said she also drew on those experiences to create her portraits of oppression.</p>
        <p>''These women in the shelter, many of them are facing some of the same problems,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jones's parents are both doctors who met at Johns Hopkins University, an African-American father and a mother of European and Caribbean descent. She said she picked up her fascination with accents and mannerisms while a high school student at the United Nations International School in New York. ''So this show is a homecoming for me,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''I've never been trained; I laugh when people call me an actor,'' she said. ''In my family background I had access to different accents. And then in school, it was amazing. There were all these kids, something like 150 nationalities, and everybody had these gorgeous accents, and I would listen all day. The U.N. school opened up so much for me. It really broadened my horizons. As a kid I was suddenly aware of the plights of people not only in my own backyard but all over the place.''</p>
        <p>From there she went to Bryn Mawr College. ''I drifted into performance art in the middle of college, and it yanked me right the heck out of the Main Line area and back home,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''Surface Transit'' brought Ms. Jones to the attention of Equality Now after Ms. Steinem, an adviser to the group, saw her show. Then, in December, the group's executive director, Jessica Neuwirth, was taken by her staff, as a birthday gift, to a club where Ms. Jones was performing, and she was invited to prepare her piece for the United Nations conference.</p>
        <p>Writing ''Women Can't Wait'' has been a consuming journey, Ms. Jones said. ''It's life and death,'' she said. ''This is about actual peoples' lives'  being on the line every day.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
