<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State Senate To Pass Bill On Hate Crime</title>
    <meta content="07HATE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hate Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hate Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E1DA153FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1077" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State Senate To Pass Bill On Hate Crime</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Senate will pass hate crimes bill making it all but certain that some version of bill will become law this year; Senate bill provides for longer prison sentences for various crimes when victims are singled out because they are gay or lesbian, in addition to those victimized on basis of race, religion, sex or age (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After blocking it for more than a decade, the State Senate will pass a hate crimes bill on Wednesday, leaders said today, making it all but certain that some version of the bill will become law this year.</p>
        <p>The Senate bill provides for longer prison sentences for various crimes when victims  are singled out because they are gay or lesbian, in addition to those victimized on the basis of race, religion, sex or age. That settles the longstanding dispute over the inclusion of gays that had prevented the bill's passage. If enacted, lawmakers said, it would be the first time that the words ''gay'' and ''lesbian'' or the phrase ''sexual orientation'' appear anywhere in the dozens of volumes of New York State laws.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After blocking it for more than a decade, the State Senate will pass a hate crimes bill on Wednesday, leaders said today, making it all but certain that some version of the bill will become law this year.</p>
        <p>The Senate bill provides for longer prison sentences for various crimes when victims  are singled out because they are gay or lesbian, in addition to those victimized on the basis of race, religion, sex or age. That settles the longstanding dispute over the inclusion of gays that had prevented the bill's passage. If enacted, lawmakers said, it would be the first time that the words ''gay'' and ''lesbian'' or the phrase ''sexual orientation'' appear anywhere in the dozens of volumes of New York State laws.</p>
        <p>New York is well behind the national curve on this issue. Forty-one states have hate laws that provide for added penalties if a person who commits a crime singles out the victim because of bias based on race, religion, sex or a number of other criteria; 23 states include sexual orientation in that list. New York is the only state in the Northeast without such a law, and the only one on the Eastern Seaboard except for South Carolina.</p>
        <p>The Assembly, controlled by Democrats, has passed a hate crimes bill 11 years in a row, always including gays in the list of protected groups. The leaders of the Senate's Republican majority have said for years that they would consider a bill that did not include sexual orientation, but the Assembly leaders always responded that their house would not vote on a bill that left that category out.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, when Senate Democrats tried unsuccessfully to force a vote on their own bill, the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, promised a vote this year on some version of a hate crimes bill, though it was not clear what form it would take. Today, he said that vote would occur on Wednesday, as first reported today in The New York Post.</p>
        <p>''I don't believe that a bias or hate bill by itself is going to do anything to reduce crime,'' he said. ''I think this whole issue is one of symbolism.''</p>
        <p>But, he added, ''I think the public generally feels like a hate, so-called bias bill, perception-wise, does some good, that it delivers the right message.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bruno said the Senate will vote on a bill introduced by Gov. George E. Pataki, a Republican, rather than the version approved by the Assembly. Mr. Bruno would not say whether he planned to vote for it, but several Republican senators made it clear privately that they plan to oppose it. They argued that such a bill places greater value on one victim than another, that it makes a crime of a defendant's thoughts, and that current laws suffice.</p>
        <p>Legislators in both houses, and groups that have lobbied for passage, said that the differences between the bills were small, and that they thought a compromise would be reached. ''We're very, very hopeful,'' said Patricia Lynch, spokeswoman for the Assembly speaker, Sheldon Silver.</p>
        <p>Several of the groups that have lobbied actively for the bill said they would be happy with either bill. ''It's really a great victory over hate and prejudice,'' said Matthew Forman, executive director of one of those groups, the Empire State Pride Agenda, a gay rights organization.</p>
        <p>Senator Roy M. Goodman, a Manhattan Republican who is the prime sponsor of the bill, called Mr. Bruno's decision ''a landmark development.'' He said, ''It's been a long time in coming.''</p>
        <p>Senator David A. Paterson, a Democrat from Manhattan, introduced the first hate crimes bill in the Senate in the 1980's. ''Now I can die in peace,'' the 46-year-old senator said today. ''If nothing else ever happens here, I feel that I can point to a contribution that I made.''</p>
        <p>Senators in both parties said the bill is certain to pass, with all or nearly all the Democratic votes and several Republican ones, as well. But it will be an unusual break with the tradition here that the majority party in either house will not allow a vote on a bill if it needs minority party votes for passage. To do so is considered a sign of weakness.</p>
        <p>The Senate's turnabout on a measure that polls show is very popular comes in a year when the Republicans are nervous about maintaining their 36-to-25 majority in the chamber in the November election.</p>
        <p>Advocates of the hate crimes bill have been handing out leaflets in the districts of Republican senators who are considered vulnerable, particularly those in Nassau County, where a voter backlash against the party last November gave Democrats control of the county Legislature for the first time. And they had made plans to broadcast radio and television advertisements, criticizing those vulnerable lawmakers for the Senate's failure to act.</p>
        <p>In the last several months, the Senate has moved sharply to the left, placating various interest groups by voting to increase cigarette taxes, to create health insurance subsidies for the working poor, to require that cigarettes meet fire safety standards, to make it a crime to block access to abortion clinics, to impose new restrictions on lobbying, and to decriminalize the sale and possession of hypodermic needles.</p>
        <p>Under the governor's bill, a judge or jury weighing whether a defendant committed a crime would also be asked to say whether the defendant, beyond a reasonable doubt, chose the victim because of prejudice. If a guilty verdict is returned, the defendant would face a longer prison term if there were a finding of bias than if there were not.</p>
        <p>For low-level felonies, the maximum penalty would increase by three years. For more serious crimes, the additional term for a bias crime would be greater -- adding a decade or more to the possible sentence in some cases. The Assembly bill takes a different approach procedurally, and would add a maximum of four years to sentences.</p>
        <p>The governor's bill would also require all of the state's law enforcement agencies to keep statistics on bias crimes and the groups singled out, something that only a few police agencies now do.</p>
        <p>A jury or judge could find that a crime was motivated by prejudice even when the defendant was mistaken about the victim's identity. For instance, a defendant who believed his victim was Hispanic could be convicted of a hate crime even if the victim was not.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
