<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Matchmakers for Services That Really Mean Business</title>
    <meta content="07STAM$15" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205385"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stamler, Bernard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DA1E3DF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1079" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Matchmakers for Services That Really Mean Business</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD STAMLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stamler, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Selling of business-to-business services online is in its infancy; field of e-marketplaces for services is wide open, with no industry leader or dominant model; marketplaces are taking variety of approaches; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY have been designing and building Web sites since 1994, the proverbial dawn of the Internet age. But even though they have more potential business than ever before, work has become more complicated in recent years for the people at Choice One OnLine, Inc. a Buffalo, N.Y., Web host and Web design services company.</p>
        <p>''Sure, there are lots of potential customers out there now,'' said Kyle Kraus, director of sales for Choice One, which was known as Edgenet until it was acquired in February by Choice One Communications of Rochester, N.Y., a local and long-distance phone company. ''But in our industry, it's still hard to find a qualified lead -- someone who is willing to attach a budget to the project and who believes that there's going to be a return on his investment.''</p>
        <p>Enter IT-Radar (www.it-radar .com, a Minneapolis company that links companies like Choice One with those that want to buy a range of information technology services. A so-called e-marketplace, IT-Radar's New York pages made their Web debut in late January. As Edgenet, Choice One was among the first to sign on; by mid-May, the company had received at least a dozen leads.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY have been designing and building Web sites since 1994, the proverbial dawn of the Internet age. But even though they have more potential business than ever before, work has become more complicated in recent years for the people at Choice One OnLine, Inc. a Buffalo, N.Y., Web host and Web design services company.</p>
        <p>''Sure, there are lots of potential customers out there now,'' said Kyle Kraus, director of sales for Choice One, which was known as Edgenet until it was acquired in February by Choice One Communications of Rochester, N.Y., a local and long-distance phone company. ''But in our industry, it's still hard to find a qualified lead -- someone who is willing to attach a budget to the project and who believes that there's going to be a return on his investment.''</p>
        <p>Enter IT-Radar (www.it-radar .com, a Minneapolis company that links companies like Choice One with those that want to buy a range of information technology services. A so-called e-marketplace, IT-Radar's New York pages made their Web debut in late January. As Edgenet, Choice One was among the first to sign on; by mid-May, the company had received at least a dozen leads.</p>
        <p>''What IT-Radar has done is to hook us up to people who are serious about what they're looking for,'' Mr. Kraus said.</p>
        <p>Although business-to-business sales of goods on the Internet are exploding, the selling of business services online is in its infancy and amounted to a relatively meager $22 billion last year, according to Forrester Research in Cambridge, Mass. That number is expected to rise to $44 billion this year, compared with $406 billion in total business-to-business transactions. Most of those services were sold one-to-one by companies with an established relationship; very few transactions were, in fact, made at e-marketplaces, where service offerings have just begun.</p>
        <p>The reasons are obvious. Buying a service often requires a chemistry between buyer and seller, which is especially true of complex and subjective services, like legal advice or creative design. Such services are less than ideal to sell at arm's length, notably between people who share only an Internet connection.</p>
        <p>Still, those who use e-marketplaces to buy tangible goods say they like what they find, which is a system that encourages shopping around and finding substantial savings over traditional catalog prices. Given that, are e-marketplaces for services catching up?</p>
        <p>Bruce D. Temkin, a Forrester analyst, thinks so. ''Over the next three to four years we expect services to take hold,'' he said. ''Even the most complex, human-intensive services will have an Internet component.''  As a result, Forrester predicts that business-to-business sales of services should rise tenfold over the next few years.</p>
        <p>The field is wide open, Mr. Temkin said, ''with no industry leader or model having yet emerged.'' E-marketplaces that are taking a crack at services are doing so in several different ways.</p>
        <p>FreeMarkets, which arranges auctions of industrial materials and is one of the oldest business-to-business marketplaces, began offering services in 1997. But they make up less than 5 percent of the company's business -- $123.8 million of the $2.7 billion in sales made through the site, Mr. Meakem said. Services bought and sold included temporary help, corporate car-rental contracts and a $3.1 million contract for telecommunications services recently fulfilled for the state of Pennsylvania. Mr. Meakem thinks that these impersonal services will continue to dominate e-marketplaces.</p>
        <p>''To make an auction market, a buyer has to be able to specify exactly what he or she needs and be willing to take it from any supplier,'' Mr. Meakem said. ''You can't do that with corporate legal advice, but you can do it with services that are conducive to the bidding process.''</p>
        <p>Must an e-marketplace relegate customers to formal auction bidding in their service transactions? No, said Alexander Straub, the United States chief executive of Mondus (www.mondus.com), an e-marketplace that operates in the United States, Britain, Germany and France. Instead, the site offers goods and services to small and midsize companies through a system in which bids are presented to prospective buyers who can make their decisions at leisure. The process lets buyers make purchases using considerations other than price, and buyers often negotiate directly with sellers after receiving their bids. Sellers pay Mondus.com a commission if a sale is made.</p>
        <p>That means that a buyer can get to know a seller before making a purchase. ''With services, you often want to talk to the vendor, and with our system you can do that,'' Mr. Straub said.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Straub, customers who originally came to Mondus for products are beginning to use it to shop for services as well, mostly standardized ones like courier services and translation. More personalized things like human resources, legal services and public relations remain a harder sell.</p>
        <p>And that is precisely the kind of resistance that IT-Radar is determined to overcome. Unlike most e-marketplaces, where the sale of services has a secondary role, IT-Radar deals in nothing else.</p>
        <p>''In this market -- information technology services -- there is a lot of subjectivity on both sides,'' said Don Peterson, the chairman. Providers and buyers are selective, he said, adding, ''Like a law firm, they decide whether to take a client.'' Moreover, although buyers and sellers of goods and raw materials often benefit from the national or international scope of an e-marketplace, the market for services is far more fragmented, with a ''unique mix in each town,'' Mr. Peterson said.</p>
        <p>So IT-Radar operates locally, with businesses in 11 markets thus far, including Denver, Atlanta, New York, Chicago and Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Although the places differ, the process is the same. Service providers prepare profiles of themselves that the company keeps on file. Then, as  prospective purchasers require services, they prepare lists of their needs, which are sent to providers, who file their responses. The process continues, often with negotiations and direct contact, until the client makes a selection. Meanwhile, service providers pay IT-Radar a fee depending on how many leads they accept.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kraus, of Choice One OnLine, is pleased with the service so far. ''We've closed a couple of deals already,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
