<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ethnic Crisis in Fiji Threatens a South Seas Eden</title>
    <meta content="07FIJI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205488"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sugar</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Fiji</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verhovek, Sam Howe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chaudhry, Mahendra (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Speight, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Fiji</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Fiji</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E0DB153FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2305" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ethnic Crisis in Fiji Threatens a South Seas Eden</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Verhovek, Sam Howe</byline>
      <dateline>SUVA, Fiji, June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fiji's idyllic reputation is being tested severely by bizarre hostage-taking drama at highest levels of government, exposing simmering ethnic tensions and prompting denunciation abroad, most viscerally from India; political crisis is veering alarmingly toward economic calamity, as foreign tourists are staying away and European Union begins boycotting sugar, dominant cash crop, in bid to force resolution; article examines background to tensions between native Fijians and ethnic Indians that culminated in May 19 insurrection, in which Fijian businessman George Speight and band of armed followers took three dozen people hostage, including first ethnic Indian Prime Min Mahendra Chaudry; maps; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Surrounded by a turquoise sea, lush emerald hills and the tropical trade winds that blow across their island nation, Fijians like to say their serenity matches the scenery.</p>
        <p>''Fiji -- the way the world should be,'' was the official tourist slogan for years, and Pope John Paul II, on a visit in 1986, said the racial harmony he found here made Fiji ''a symbol of hope for the world.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Surrounded by a turquoise sea, lush emerald hills and the tropical trade winds that blow across their island nation, Fijians like to say their serenity matches the scenery.</p>
        <p>''Fiji -- the way the world should be,'' was the official tourist slogan for years, and Pope John Paul II, on a visit in 1986, said the racial harmony he found here made Fiji ''a symbol of hope for the world.''</p>
        <p>But Fiji's idyllic reputation is being severely tested by a bizarre crisis, a hostage-taking drama at the highest levels of government that is exposing simmering ethnic tensions and prompting denunciation abroad, most viscerally from India. And even more alarmingly for people here, the political crisis is rapidly veering toward an economic calamity, as foreign tourists stay away and the European Union takes steps to boycott sugar, Fiji's dominant cash crop, in a bid to force a resolution.</p>
        <p>It was all set off May 19, when a bankrupt, part-Fijian businessman, proclaiming that he was acting in the name of all indigenous Fijians, stormed the parliamentary compound here with a small group of armed followers. He took three dozen people captive, including Prime Minister Mahendra Chaudhry, the first ethnic Indian to hold that post in Fiji's history.</p>
        <p>As attempted coups go, the one here in Suva, the capital, has not proven particularly frightening -- so far, at least. Hundreds of mainly rural ethnic Fijians who support the insurrection mill around the hostage scene, roasting pigs and chickens and singing Christian hymns. With tents, lean-tos and lines of laundry flapping everywhere, they have completely taken over the government complex, a group of low teak-and-stucco buildings set amid hibiscus and coconut palms and overlooking the Pacific.</p>
        <p>And while leaders of some rebellions cultivate an air of menacing mystery, the leader of this insurrection, George Speight, a brawny man with a shaved head who recently moved from Australia and had been under investigation here for his role in an insurance swindle, takes the opposite tack. He holds frequent long news conferences, often barefoot and dressed in a sulu skirt, traditional garb for Fijian men. He uses a jocular, first-name manner to address television reporters from Australia and New Zealand, nations with an intense interest in the crisis, both because they regard themselves as guardians of peace in the South Pacific and because Fiji is a major vacation destination for their citizens.</p>
        <p>But even if the immediate hostage crisis is resolved without bloodshed, as negotiators insist it eventually will be, the standoff is taking a huge psychic and economic toll on a nation that most of the rest of the world, when it thinks about Fiji at all, tends to view as Eden on the South Seas.</p>
        <p>And though Fiji is one of the most remote spots on earth, about 1,100 miles north of New Zealand and 2,800 miles southwest of Hawaii, the events here have rippled far beyond  e South Pacific.</p>
        <p>For one thing, the British Commonwealth, under heavy pressure from India, today suspended Fiji from the organization's councils -- a step short of full expulsion from the commonwealth -- and agreed to send a mission to Fiji to press for ''the restoration of democracy.'' On Saturday, India's prime minister said recent events here had exposed a ''condemnable'' strain of discrimination in Fiji against the ethnic Indians, whose ancestors were brought here as indentured servants in the sugar-cane fields when Fiji was a British colony.</p>
        <p>The Commonwealth, a loose confederation consisting mainly of former British colonies, kicked Fiji out of their union once before, after Fiji underwent two coups 13 years ago and wound up with a new Constitution. That document specifically barred ethnic Indians, who make up about 44 percent of the population, from holding top posts like president, prime minister or commissioner of police, or from holding a majority of seats in Parliament.</p>
        <p>Fiji was later readmitted, with India's assent, after it drew up yet another Constitution, in 1997. That one guaranteed rights to all races and ultimately paved the way for Mr. Chaudhry's ascension to the prime minister's office in 1999.</p>
        <p>But that is the same Constitution that Mr. Speight and his followers now insist must be abrogated, one of several conditions the failed businessman has set for releasing the hostages unharmed. Another is amnesty for himself and all involved in the insurrection.</p>
        <p>The commander of the Fijian armed forces, Commodore Voreqe Bainimarama, who has declared the nation to be under martial law and imposed a nighttime curfew here, said he was willing to meet both of those demands; on Monday he described the Constitution as a ''blank page,'' waiting to be rewritten yet again. But he said Mr. Speight had made other, unspecified demands that were ''impossible to meet.''</p>
        <p>At its most basic level, the hostage drama here has certainly opened a window on strains between ethnic Indian Fijians and the indigenous Fijians, who make up 51 percent of the population of 812,000.</p>
        <p>Though they have led a largely peaceful coexistence ever since the Indians were brought here late in the 19th century, the two groups have never come close to embracing a melting-pot theory of race relations.</p>
        <p>Intermarriage remains very rare, and while Indian men sometimes date Fijian women, the opposite almost never happens, at least in public. Many members of each group seem to hold remarkably hardened stereotypes about the other.</p>
        <p>Indo-Fijians, who are largely urban and dominate the merchant and professional classes, often describe the Fijians as lazy and disinclined to think about self-advancement.</p>
        <p>''We work hard, 9, 10 hours a day, but they don't know what their future is,'' said Pritam Sharma, an Indian shopkeeper in the main tourist town of Nadi. ''And they don't care. They are just, 'Oh, one day at a time.' ''</p>
        <p>Indigenous Fijians, meanwhile, many of whom work in low-paying tourism jobs or as subsistence farmers, typically cast their fellow citizens of Indian descent as manipulative, grasping and humorless.</p>
        <p>''An Indian man, he will only buy from his own kind,'' explained Ameo Liaci, a 30-year-old political aide to a Fijian nationalist party, who was one of 200 or so of Mr. Speight's followers encamped outside the Parliament building today. ''The Fijian man is not like that. We are the most tolerable and accommodating people on earth, brother. The Indian man has been here all these years and still, he cannot accept the Fijian way.''</p>
        <p>Native Fijians take it as a matter of course that the country is theirs, and most say that while Indians may live here, the government should be run by Fijians.</p>
        <p>Such a view has led Sir Vijay Singh, a former attorney general and a leader of the ethnic Indians here, to accuse native Fijians of trying to impose a form of ''reverse apartheid.'' Fijians, of course, take extreme umbrage at being compared to white South African oppressors, and instead liken themselves to the aborigines of Australia or Maoris of New Zealand, economically marginalized and pushed off their native lands.</p>
        <p>Some Fijian ultra-nationalists have even suggested that all Indians be ''repatriated'' out of Fiji, an idea that is met with anger and disbelief among Indians, many of whom were born here and have never left Fiji.</p>
        <p>''Where would we go?'' said Himmat Lodhi, a jeweler and president of the downtown retailers association. ''We wouldn't know where to go and what to do. My ancestors came here 120 years ago.''</p>
        <p>Negotiators insist that the crisis will be resolved peacefully, and Commodore Bainimarama said Monday that he had ''not even considered the military option as a means of freeing the hostages'' -- perhaps in part because some senior military leaders count close relatives among the captives.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the Fiji Red Cross delivers food, mail and fresh clothes and bedding each day to the prime minister and his fellow captives. The group includes many of his cabinet members and the daughter of Fiji's 80-year-old president, Ratu Sir Kamisese Mara, a venerated figure who led Fiji to independence from Britain in 1970.</p>
        <p>And the scene at the compound has an incongruous carnival air, even with the hostages held in a room upstairs. Though some young men run around with machine guns, nearly all are polite and exceedingly friendly to foreign reporters.</p>
        <p>''America? America?'' one young man, dressed in a Baltimore Orioles T-shirt, said to a reporter today. ''Have a Bud, man!'' he proclaimed, then thrust out his hand with a thumbs-up gesture.</p>
        <p>The captors gather in knots, the women often to sing and the men to laugh, tell stories and sip kava, a mildly narcotic drink that is the ubiquitous beverage of Fiji. And those amiable sounds are often all but drowned out by the pleasant melodies of hundreds of brightly colored tropical birds that zip through the compound.</p>
        <p>Many indigenous Fijians, whose ancestors were part of a wave of migration centuries ago by Melanesians and Polynesians, do not support Mr. Speight. That is especially true in bigger cities, including Suva and Nadi, where the international airport is situated.</p>
        <p>''George -- you are a con man,'' and ''Give it up, George, don't ruin the country,'' read two of the banners hoisted by native Fijians at a rally the other night in Nadi.</p>
        <p>The standoff is an undeniable economic blow that could compound over time.</p>
        <p>The European Union normally buys about 75 percent of all Fiji's exported sugar, paying roughly three times the world market price under agreements it has with former colonies in Africa, the Caribbean and the South Pacific. That amounts to roughly $150 million a year. The United States, Australia and New Zealand are all threatening sanctions too, and Australian trade unions are refusing to handle cargo and mail between the two countries.</p>
        <p>Tourism, which posted a record 409,955 visitors last year and earned more than $250 million, has plunged amid publicity about Fiji's turmoil. Fiji's tourism bureau said today that more than 80 percent of workers in the hotel industry, nearly all of them indigenous Fijians, were earning less pay because they have been put on sharply reduced working hours.</p>
        <p>The breadth and depth of support for Mr. Speight is difficult to gauge.</p>
        <p>Vijay Naidu, director of the Center for Development Studies at the University of the South Pacific here in Suva, said Mr. Speight had clearly tapped a well of deep resentment in some rural areas, where half or more of the people earn less than the annual poverty level of roughly $2,500.</p>
        <p>''This is a time-tested thing, to seize on frustrations with the indigenous-rights issue,'' Professor Naidu said. ''There are right-wing, racist, lunatic fringes in all countries, but in Fiji we have the misfortune of these guys trying to get power, real power, and they're able to get away with it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Speight, at a news conference tonight, said the prime minister's government had been secretly carrying out ''its grand plan'' to make Fiji an Indian colony.</p>
        <p>Many experts doubt that Mr. Speight will ever succeed in taking over the government, as he has suggested he would like to do. But Brij Lal, another professor at the University of the South Pacific and an author of the 1997 multiracial Constitution, describes Mr. Speight as ''a convenient front man for an assortment of interests,'' including military leaders and ambitious Fijian politicians who would like to run for office under a revised constitution.</p>
        <p>How or when it will all end, and with or without violence, no one seems know.</p>
        <p>There have been several incidents of looting and arson against Indian-owned stores, especially in rural areas. And one death occurred last week, when a native Fijian policeman was shot -- accidentally, Mr. Speight said -- during a scuffle near a government building.</p>
        <p>Mr. Speight has met frequently with Commodore Bainimarama. Once the two men even exchanged whale's teeth, a ritual Fijian sign of respect that led many here to speculate that an agreement to end the crisis was at hand. Another critical component in the complicated negotiations over a solution is the Great Council of Chiefs, a 100-member group of hereditary and appointed chiefs, who have great influence over native Fijians in rural areas.</p>
        <p>But so far, any draft accords have fallen apart, and while Mr. Speight says he wants peace, he also said the other day that he was prepared to shoot hostages if his ''demands'' were not eventually met.</p>
        <p>Leaders of the armed forces said that even after a resolution, there would almost surely be a period of military rule, aimed at paving the way for a smooth return to a functioning democracy.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Speight and his lot have come up with an oversimplistic solution to the social problems faced in our country,'' proclaimed a military statement on radio over the weekend. ''This is the time for us to stand up and defend the democracy that we believe in, where each man is created equal in the eyes of God.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
