<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Promising Farm Tool, for Some</title>
    <meta content="07DIRK$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TO BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Farm Bureau Federation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Dirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01EEDD103DF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Promising Farm Tool, for Some</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Dirk</byline>
      <dateline>EARLVILLE, Ill.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American Farm Bureau Federation sees agricultural business poised for transformation through computers; so far, farmers are using Internet mainly to shop for best deals on machinery and supplies; some are exploring Internet to find best prices for crops; some Web sites let them sell crops directly to consumers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN it was finally time to trade his old John Deere tractor for a newer model, Steve Lake, a 55-year-old farmer, went shopping on the Internet.</p>
        <p>To find just the used model he wanted -- a front-wheel-drive machine with 130 horsepower -- he would have needed to flip through farm magazines and newspapers from all over the Midwest. But trolling on his computer, Mr. Lake took only 30 minutes to discover a dealership in Lowden, Iowa, offering just what he wanted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN it was finally time to trade his old John Deere tractor for a newer model, Steve Lake, a 55-year-old farmer, went shopping on the Internet.</p>
        <p>To find just the used model he wanted -- a front-wheel-drive machine with 130 horsepower -- he would have needed to flip through farm magazines and newspapers from all over the Midwest. But trolling on his computer, Mr. Lake took only 30 minutes to discover a dealership in Lowden, Iowa, offering just what he wanted.</p>
        <p>''There it was on the screen,'' said Mr. Lake, who stands 6-foot-2 in work boots. ''It was just what I was after.''</p>
        <p>With a digital camera, Mr. Lake photographed the 1976 tractor he wanted to trade and sent it by e-mail to the dealership. The dealer wanted $63,000 for the newer tractor, which had 1,500 hours of use. The farmer expected $16,000 for his machine, which had racked up 6,000 hours.</p>
        <p>Confident that a bargain could be struck, Mr. Lake drove to Iowa, haggled a bit, then returned to the farm. After a few e-mail messages back and forth, the farmer and the dealer reached a deal.</p>
        <p>''Farmers are stuck out here in the middle of nowhere,'' Mr. Lake said. ''But the computer gives us knowledge from the rest of the world, and knowledge is power.''</p>
        <p>Mace Thornton, a spokesman for the American Farm Bureau Federation, says the agricultural business appears to be poised for a transformation through computers. ''So many ag Web sites have been introduced in the last six months it's hard to keep up with them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>So far, farmers are using computers mainly to shop for the best deals on machinery and supplies, especially chemicals to kill bugs and weeds. To a lesser extent, some farmers are exploring the Internet to find the best prices for their crops. Web sites in California and Wisconsin, among other places, allow farmers to sell produce and meat directly to consumers, yielding a better price at both ends because the middleman has been eliminated.</p>
        <p>But in the view of David Furry, the manager at Strackbein's Inc., the Iowa dealership where Mr. Lake found his tractor, the pace of e-commerce in agriculture lags behind computer use in other industries because most farmers are over 50.</p>
        <p>''People of a certain age are less comfortable doing business on the computer -- they still want to kick the tires,'' Mr. Furry said. ''It's a different story for younger men, the ones who are taking over for their dads.''</p>
        <p>One big problem for computer-savvy farmers is the low quality of telephone service in many rural areas, which slows transmission on the Web.</p>
        <p>''I'm out here on six miles of copper lines, so there's a lot of noise in there,'' said Mr. Lake, referring to the frequent losses of computer connections. ''And when you hit the keys for a search, you might as well go get a cup of coffee while it searches, because it's going to take a while.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lake, a fifth-generation farmer whose 1,400 acres are planted with corn and soybeans -- ''a cow-chow factory,'' he calls it -- has had a computer since 1988. (He also uses it to stay tethered to the world outside, reading major newspapers online and scanning restaurant reviews and museum exhibitions in Chicago, 75 miles away.)</p>
        <p>Before the computer, Mr. Lake said, finding and buying used machinery was a tedious chore that often ended unsatisfactorily. ''If I'd just gone to my local dealer, I wouldn't have found what I was looking for,'' he said. ''So the dealer would have tried to push me to buy something that he had but that I didn't really want.''</p>
        <p>Even some of the Web sites could use some improving, Mr. Lake said, noting that some lack important details.</p>
        <p>''If it doesn't have a picture, it just doesn't reach out and grab you,'' he said. ''And you'd like to know about the history of the machine.''</p>
        <p>In Mr. Lake's case, he wanted to be certain that the tractor had not been used on a big hog operation, which could make the inside of the cab stink, and that the previous owner was not a cigarette smoker, which could do the same.</p>
        <p>But he found precisely what he had envisioned. The newer John Deere tractor, painted green just like the older model, has run like a champ over the last few months during planting season.</p>
        <p>''You just flip a button on the dash,'' Mr. Lake marveled, ''and it goes into front-wheel drive.''</p>
        <p>It also does not hurt that the cab is equipped with a stereo.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS TO BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
