<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dissent Fails to Halt Revamping of Russian Energy Concern</title>
    <meta content="Y07ELEC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205433"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chubais, Anatoly B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">tavernise, sabrina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D6143FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dissent Fails to Halt Revamping of Russian Energy Concern</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SABRINA TAVERNISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">tavernise, sabrina</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anatoly Chubais, head of Russia's national electric company, Unified Energy Systems, says he will go ahead with plan to reorganize the company despite opposition from foreign investors who say the plan will destroy the value of their holdings and deprive them of control over assets; plan, presented in April, calls for splitting off regional power plants and power generators from the company to raise $30 billion in badly needed investment over 10 years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anatoly Chubais, the head of Russia's national electric company, said today that he would go ahead with a plan to reorganize the company despite opposition from foreign investors who say the plan will destroy the value of their holdings and deprive them of control over assets.</p>
        <p>The plan, presented in early April, proposes splitting off regional power plants and power generators from the company, Unified Energy Systems, to raise $30 billion in badly needed investment over 10 years. Some investors say the proposal may lead to sales of power plant assets at bargain prices, and that the plan should be halted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anatoly Chubais, the head of Russia's national electric company, said today that he would go ahead with a plan to reorganize the company despite opposition from foreign investors who say the plan will destroy the value of their holdings and deprive them of control over assets.</p>
        <p>The plan, presented in early April, proposes splitting off regional power plants and power generators from the company, Unified Energy Systems, to raise $30 billion in badly needed investment over 10 years. Some investors say the proposal may lead to sales of power plant assets at bargain prices, and that the plan should be halted.</p>
        <p>''It simply doesn't make sense,'' said Mark Cooke, fund manager at Brunswick Capital Asset Management, with $350 million under management. ''U.E.S. must be the only company in the world that is sitting on a quasi-monopoly that's effectively trying to destroy itself.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chubais, once well regarded by foreign investors, began running Unified Energy in 1998. Earlier, in a series of cabinet posts under former President Boris N. Yeltsin, he designed Russia's controversial program to sell state assets that left a handful of men with the best of them.</p>
        <p>Investors say they are concerned that the plan for the breakup of Unified Energy will end similarly, with a few local businesses acquiring stakes in power companies for bargain prices.</p>
        <p>Speaking today at a briefing, Mr. Chubais said he was prepared to alter the plan to take investors' opinions into account, but that he would not slow the pace. He will set the plan into action next spring if the company's board approves it this month.</p>
        <p>''We're ready to alter the concept, but under no circumstances are we ready to do nothing,'' he said. ''If we don't start restructuring soon, in five years, there'll be no energy system -- it would be a catastrophe for the country.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chubais has already made some changes. Instead of spinning regional companies off into subsidiaries controlled by management, the new plan entails splitting regional companies into new companies -- distributors, sellers and producers. Current ownership will be redistributed evenly throughout each company, and Unified Energy will gradually reduce its stakes by issuing additional shares. Unified Energy will wait for better market conditions before acting on the plan, he said.</p>
        <p>Some investors like the plan, saying a restructuring in the industry is long overdue. Charles Hirsch, manager of the Russian Opportunities Fund, with $10 million in Russian equities, and more than 50 percent in Unified Energy and its subsidiaries, said: ''The system was badly thought out years ago and must be completely replaced. It worked under potato- payment conditions for 10 years, but now the game is over. You have to invest.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chubais has met with more than 40 investors from London to New York trying to drum up support for his plan. An anticipated autumn increase in tariffs will add to the allure of regional power companies and help sway investors, he said.</p>
        <p>Still, many are not convinced. A group of foreign investors will meet Wednesday to discuss a plan of action. They say they will ask Mr. Chubais to scrap the plan and include them in drawing up a new one.</p>
        <p>''Investors don't think the changes are material enough,'' said Boris Fyodorov, a Unified Energy board member who is planning to attend Wednesday's meeting. ''The language of the concept has changed, but the principle remains the same. It's clear that the plan is not in the interests of shareholders.''</p>
        <p>Shareholders also object to pilot projects with regional energy companies that they say are under way in several cities including Samara and Omsk. Those cities are centers of heavy industry and shareholders fear assets will be sold cheaply to big energy consumers like Sibneft, the oil company, and AvtoVaz, the car producer. Chubais said no reorganization had begun for either of the companies.</p>
        <p>Foreign investors control 33 percent of Unified Energy. They voted last year to amend the company's charter, which now requires a 75 percent vote by shareholders to oust Mr. Chubais. Investors say they may call an emergency shareholders' meeting to try to get the votes for an ouster. The Federal Securities Commission of Russia also criticized the plan, saying it violates the rights of shareholders.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
