<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Math Muddles Schools' Regents Scores</title>
    <meta content="07REG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205459"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zernike, Kate</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DD153FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1024" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Math Muddles Schools' Regents Scores</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE ZERNIKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zernike, Kate</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses how new scoring method of New York State Regents exams will affect school pass/fail numbers because it is based on average grade enrollment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a season of tests, a test question: when is a perfect score not a perfect score?</p>
        <p>Answer: In the school-by-school scores on the New York State Regents, which will be given to thousands of high school students over the next two weeks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a season of tests, a test question: when is a perfect score not a perfect score?</p>
        <p>Answer: In the school-by-school scores on the New York State Regents, which will be given to thousands of high school students over the next two weeks.</p>
        <p>According to the way the state measures performance on the Regents, it is possible that every single student who takes the math test will pass, and the state will report that only 75 percent of that school's students passed. Likewise, if 75 percent passes, the state may report that 100 percent did.</p>
        <p>This little mathematical oddity is produced by a factor known as the average grade enrollment, which is, as the name suggests, the total number of students in a school divided by the number of grades in that school. The state reports what fraction of that average class size passed the test, which is where the problem comes in.</p>
        <p>If there are 400 students in a high school with four grades, the average grade enrollment is 100. If 75 students take the Regents and all pass, the state reports that the school had a 75 percent passing rate. And a not-so-perfect score can become perfect; if 110 students take the test, and only 100 pass, the school gets a 100 percent passing rate -- or a perfect score.</p>
        <p>''You have phantom children,'' said Dr. Stanley Toll, superintendent in Ardsley. ''To your community, it looks like you have gone down ten points, when you haven't.''</p>
        <p>The State Department of Education began using average grade enrollment 10 years ago, when only about 30 percent of the high school students in the state took the Regents tests. Many schools would try to inflate the percentage of students who passed by holding back students teachers thought would fail. A district's scores might look great if only six students took the test.</p>
        <p>''We were encouraging schools to have students take the test, and pass,'' Alan Ray, a spokesman for the Department of Education, said. Measuring by the average number of students in a school, he said, would give schools a reason to allow more students to take the test.</p>
        <p>Officials at the State Department of Education now say that they will replace these kind of ratings when they come up with a new system, within three years. But some say it is misleading to continue to use the ratings, which every year are reported to the media and appear on the school report cards posted on the department's Web site.</p>
        <p>The superintendents have had many gripes about the new, tougher state exams.They are, depending on whom you ask, too long, too hard, too easy, too narrow. But they say rating of schools by average class size is especially frustrating for smaller, and usually suburban or rural, high schools, because there it takes fewer students to affect the percentages.</p>
        <p>''A district like mine gets creamed,'' said Dr. Vincent T. Beni, the superintendent of Irvington schools, with about 350 high school students. There, the average grade enrollment in 1998 was 83, but there were only 66 students in the 12th grade.</p>
        <p>All 54 of the students who took the foreign-language test in 1998 passed, but the state report cards said only 65 percent passed. The math III exam scores suggested an even worse performance. While 41 of the 42 students who took that test passed, the state reported a 49 percent passing rate.</p>
        <p>The apparently low score jolts the public.  ''This is just one example of what we feel are twists and turns in the statistics,'' said John A. Chambers, the superintendent in Bronxville.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ray said the state will begin using a more sophisticated data reporting system -- one that accounts for the nuances superintendents say the average grade enrollment misses -- in three years. That system, Mr. Ray said, will identify each student so that the state can track when students move schools, how many times they take the tests, and in general, will give a more complete, longerterm picture of how well students and schools are performing.</p>
        <p>Even now, the state also reports how many students took the test, and how many passed, which gives parents a simpler way to evaluate how their schools are doing. But the superintendents say the number that gets reported is the percentage of the average grade enrollment that passes, because it is one number, and simpler to report.</p>
        <p>''That tends to be what gets the attention of parents,'' Dr. Beni said. ''What happens when you're a superintendent is, when you get up in front of the public and the state report card says 75 percent passed, they think the state number is the right number. When you try to explain it to them, they say 'Why would the state do that?' You're put in a defensive position.''</p>
        <p>In fact, superintendents acknowledge that the average-grade-enrollment system has encouraged schools to push more students to take the tests. ''Under the old rule, why would you put your kids at risk?'' Dr. Toll said. ''Now, you're saying to yourself, 'Let's make sure every kid is prepared.' I'd like to think I always thought every kid ought to be encouraged. But in some school districts, you're going to look at the data and say, 'How can we make ourselves look good?' ''</p>
        <p>By 2003, when the state will require all students to pass the Regents, grading by average grade enrollment may become a moot point. But until then, superintendents say, why not stop using numbers that can mislead?</p>
        <p>''They're moving in the right direction,'' Dr. Beni said. ''All I'm saying is, for those three years, let's call a truce.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
