<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Whodunit? A Professor Turned Novelist, That's Who</title>
    <meta content="07ARTS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS ABROAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rio De Janeiro (Brazil)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garcia-Roza, Luiz Alfredo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil/Rio de Janeiro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E1DA143FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1311" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Whodunit? A Professor Turned Novelist, That's Who</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Larry Rohter</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO, June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Luiz Alfredo Garcia-Roza discusses his success as writer of detective fiction after a distinguished 33-year career at Federal University in Rio de Janeiro, where his field was psychology and philosophy; his three best-selling novels are all set in Rio, a city that has never had a writer to chronicle its local underworld; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four years ago, as he was about to turn 60, Luiz Alfredo Garcia-Roza was contemplating retirement and the end of a long and distinguished academic career. During 33 years at the Federal University here he had organized a postgraduate program in psychoanalytical theory and written eight philosophy and psychology textbooks, and the time had come, he decided, to try something new.</p>
        <p>Today Mr. Garcia-Roza is enjoying literary success in a genre far removed from the scholarly world. The three detective novels he has written since his decision to ''try to subvert the pattern of my life'' have become best sellers. The movie rights to two of them have been sold, he has won a pair of Brazil's most prestigious book prizes, and critics continue to praise him for giving a distinctly Brazilian twist to the familiar formula of the police procedural and private eye novel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four years ago, as he was about to turn 60, Luiz Alfredo Garcia-Roza was contemplating retirement and the end of a long and distinguished academic career. During 33 years at the Federal University here he had organized a postgraduate program in psychoanalytical theory and written eight philosophy and psychology textbooks, and the time had come, he decided, to try something new.</p>
        <p>Today Mr. Garcia-Roza is enjoying literary success in a genre far removed from the scholarly world. The three detective novels he has written since his decision to ''try to subvert the pattern of my life'' have become best sellers. The movie rights to two of them have been sold, he has won a pair of Brazil's most prestigious book prizes, and critics continue to praise him for giving a distinctly Brazilian twist to the familiar formula of the police procedural and private eye novel.</p>
        <p>Though one of the world's most celebrated cities, Rio has never really had a writer to chronicle the local underworld as Raymond Chandler did in Los Angeles or as Jean-Claude Izzo, to select just one of a new generation of European writers, has done more recently in Marseille. But as Mr. Garcia-Roza cheerfully admits, his own name would not necessarily have sprung to mind as the leading candidate to rise to such a challenge.</p>
        <p>''I'd always been fascinated by the detective novel and had read all the American masters, from Dashiell Hammett and Raymond Chandler to Ross Macdonald and Lawrence Block,'' he said in an interview. ''But I'd never set foot in a police station before I started on this and had no idea what went on in there or at a coroner's office.''</p>
        <p>There was another problem, too. ''Like most Brazilians, I lived through a long period of repression here,'' he said, speaking of the military dictatorship that ruled the country from 1964 to 1985. ''Anyone who has ever experienced a dictatorship is going to have a hard time hearing the word policeman or soldier without a defense mechanism being activated.'' Once Mr. Garcia-Roza made the acquaintance of detectives and began listening to their stories, that suspicion abated somewhat, though his novels do not shy away from portraying police corruption and brutality.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, he also discovered that his academic training was good preparation for describing a universe of murderers, prostitutes, grifters and police officers.</p>
        <p>''Policemen are like psychiatrists in that they live at the frontiers of two different universes, the normal and its opposite,'' he said. ''The territory in which they operate is the dividing line between sanity and madness, order and disorder, and I find that borderline and the confrontations it produces to be fascinating.''</p>
        <p>''Nevertheless, writing fiction was difficult at the start, harder to write than any of my academic books. If I am writing about Kant or Plato, the path is well trod, with a lot of reference points and commentators to aid me. But with literary creation, your raw material is fantasy, and you have to learn to give yourself over to your imagination.''</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Garcia-Roza said, when he finished the draft of his first novel, ''I did not know if I had written something good or not.'' So he went to the editor of his academic works, which include ''Chance and Repetition in Psychoanalysis'' and ''Freud and the Unconscious,'' and was told that it was very good indeed. The book was published by a house specializing in fiction, Companhia das Letras, in 1997 as ''O Silencio da Chuva,'' or ''The Silence of the Rain.''</p>
        <p>Encouraged by his immediate success, Mr. Garcia-Roza wrote two more novels set in the demimonde of the city's Copacabana district: ''Achados e Perdidos,'' (''Lost and Found'') and ''Vento Sudoeste'' (''Southwesterly Wind''). The protagonist in all three novels is Detective Espinosa, named in homage to the author's favorite philosopher, Spinoza. When ''Southwesterly Wind'' was published late last year, Paulo Roberto Pires, the critic for the newspaper O Globo, described Espinosa as ''an irresistible character.'' More than a conventional hero, he argued, Espinosa is ''the center of a specific universe, full of nuances and subtleties and, for that reason, not likely to become a cliche of himself.''</p>
        <p>Like his hard-boiled American counterparts, Espinosa is world-weary. He set out to be a lawyer but dropped out and became a cop to support a wife who eventually abandoned him and headed off with their son for a job at the Brazilian Embassy in Washington, leaving Espinosa to live alone in Copacabana in a bachelor apartment whose refrigerator is crammed with packages of frozen lasagna.</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Garcia-Roza makes clear, Espinosa works in a third world environment fundamentally different from that familiar to readers of police books in the United States and Europe.</p>
        <p>The detective is constantly made aware of how that wide that gap is, for instance, when he tries to identify a badly burned corpse. ''If this were an American movie, the identification could only be made by the dental plate,'' Mr. Garcia-Roza said. ''But it so happens that almost nobody has their dental records, much less if they are poor people who don't have a dentist or, in most cases, even their teeth.''</p>
        <p>Asked for his opinion on the books, Edson de Mesquita, the recently arrived real-life chief of the Copacabana precinct, at first seemed skeptical of Mr. Garcia-Roza's credentials. ''I've never heard of him or his books,'' he said. But after it was suggested that he take a look at some selected passages, his attitude quickly changed. ''This guy really knows what he is talking about,'' Mr. de Mesquita said after reading one segment aloud. ''Yeah, this is our reality,'' he observed, a wry smile on his face, after reading another. His parting remark: 'So you say I can find all three of these novels at any bookstore?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia-Roza is also admired for the way he uses the landscape and weather of Rio de Janeiro as another character, subtly evoking the spirit and peculiar qualities of the city, much as Chandler did for Los Angeles. ''What attracted me most of all is the soulfulness that Luiz Alfredo manages to inject into the book and its characters,'' said Murilo Salles, the movie director, who bought the rights to ''The Silence of the Rain.'' ''He works within a genre that is international and has its conventions, but his characters are very Brazilian and the book has a real Rio flavor. He looks at the city with a refined affection, and you feel that he really loves not just the postcard sights but the bar on the corner, with all its smells and odd characters.''</p>
        <p>Like Espinosa, Mr. Garcia-Roza was born in Copacabana and has lived in Rio all his life. At the moment he is immersed in a fourth novel, working daily from 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. When faced with writer's block, he said, his solution is often to get out on the streets and wander around the world that his characters inhabit, absorbing its sights and sounds for future use.</p>
        <p>''When I was 18 years old, I had a job downtown that entailed a lot of walking about, and even now I sometimes like to stop work just to walk around for a couple of hours,'' he said. ''To me, any open door is an invitation to enter and discover an urban world different from mine.''</p>
        <p>ARTS ABROAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
