<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Domino's Reaches Deal on Accusations of Bias</title>
    <meta content="Y07PIZ$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205476"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delivery Services</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Domino's Pizza Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Christian, Nichole M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E0DC153FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Domino's Reaches Deal on Accusations of Bias</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLE M. CHRISTIAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Christian, Nichole M</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Domino's Pizza, in move to settle string of racial bias complaints, reaches agreement with Justice Department to guarantee deliveries to all neighborhoods unless there is proven evidence that area poses threat to drivers; has come under fire from African-Americans, who say drivers refuse to deliver to neighborhoods or in some cases force customers to wait in street; says practice stems not from racism but from rash of robberies and driver attacks in poor neighborhoods (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moving to settle a string of racial bias complaints, Domino's Pizza said today that it had reached an agreement with the Justice Department to guarantee deliveries to all neighborhoods unless there was proven evidence that the area posed a threat to drivers.</p>
        <p>Domino's, the nation's No. 2 pizza chain and a unit of Bain Capital, has come under fire recently from African-Americans across the country who say drivers refuse to deliver to their neighborhoods or in some cases force customers to wait in the street for their pizza. The company says its practice stems not from racism but from a rash of robberies and driver attacks in poor neighborhoods.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Moving to settle a string of racial bias complaints, Domino's Pizza said today that it had reached an agreement with the Justice Department to guarantee deliveries to all neighborhoods unless there was proven evidence that the area posed a threat to drivers.</p>
        <p>Domino's, the nation's No. 2 pizza chain and a unit of Bain Capital, has come under fire recently from African-Americans across the country who say drivers refuse to deliver to their neighborhoods or in some cases force customers to wait in the street for their pizza. The company says its practice stems not from racism but from a rash of robberies and driver attacks in poor neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>''We've never discriminated,'' said Tim McIntyre, a Domino's vice president. ''It's a reality in the U.S. that some neighborhoods are dangerous. We've taken steps to keep our people from being victims of crime in those places, and in doing so we've found ourselves being accused of discrimination.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McIntyre said the company did not track reports of violence against drivers because 90 percent of its stores were operated by independent franchisees. Domino's employs nearly 80,000 drivers.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement, which did not require an admission of guilt from the company, based in Ann Arbor, Mich., owners and managers of Domino's 4,600 stores in the United States must follow a new national policy requiring that they evaluate crime statistics with local law enforcement agencies and meet with community groups before deciding to restrict delivery to a neighborhood. A decision to limit delivery will also require approval from Domino's corporate director of safety and security. Local store managers must agree to review the areas annually.</p>
        <p>''The new delivery policy ensures that decisions on delivery limitations will be based on the legitimate concern for the safety of Domino's employees and not on the racial composition of a neighborhood,'' Bill Lann Lee, the department's acting assistant attorney for civil rights, said.</p>
        <p>The agreement settles complaints before the Justice Department, although the department brought no suit. The company's franchises have faced a barrage of complaints in cities and states. Two years ago, a federal judge in Jacksonville, Fla., ordered a Domino's franchise there to stop forcing residents of American Beach, a small, predominantly black neighborhood, to wait at a convenience store for their pizza deliveries.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the department said it would monitor Domino's efforts to enforce its new policy.</p>
        <p>Some lawyers say the agreement essentially strips drivers of their only means of protection.</p>
        <p>''The only thing these drivers have to protect themselves is discretion,'' said Ted Williams, a lawyer in Washington who represents a Domino's driver accused of pizza redlining in the city. ''Why should they be made to deliver in an area that police say is safe, yet they fear for their lives? They know better than anyone how quickly a safe neighborhood can turn violent.''</p>
        <p>Lawyers representing customers who accuse Domino's of biased delivery practices called today's agreement a victory.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
