<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Devils Focusing on Some Unfinished Business</title>
    <meta content="07DEVI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205511"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY: STANLEY CUP FINALS -- DEVILS VS. STARS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">832 Words</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Stars</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Dallas Stars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E5D9153FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Devils Focusing on Some Unfinished Business</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New Jersey Devils preparing for Game 5 of NHL Stanley Cup championship series against Dallas Stars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a span of 10 weeks, the Devils have gone from a team with uncertain prospects for capturing the Stanley Cup to being a game away from winning hockey's ultimate prize.</p>
        <p>Although they are just a step from their second championship in five years, the Devils were very cautious here today, the day after putting the defending champion Stars on the brink of losing their title.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a span of 10 weeks, the Devils have gone from a team with uncertain prospects for capturing the Stanley Cup to being a game away from winning hockey's ultimate prize.</p>
        <p>Although they are just a step from their second championship in five years, the Devils were very cautious here today, the day after putting the defending champion Stars on the brink of losing their title.</p>
        <p>Coach Larry Robinson and a number of his players said this morning at the team hotel before they departed for New Jersey and a day of rest that there was no room for premature celebrations.</p>
        <p>''Satisfaction will come when it's all over,'' Robinson said. ''We've gone through a lot of obstacles and made sacrifices, but it's not over yet.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Devils said that Jason Arnott, who left Game 4 with about eight minutes remaining when he was hit in the mouth by Derian Hatcher, should be available for Game 5 at the Meadowlands on Thursday. ''There is no concussion and he's fine,'' said Lou Lamoriello, the president and general manager. ''I see no reason why he should not play.''</p>
        <p>Going into their prospective cup clinching in Game 5, the Devils cited their Philadelphia series as a warning. Like the Dallas Stars now, the Devils faced elimination against the Flyers, then won the Eastern Conference finals with three consecutive victories.</p>
        <p>''After the Philly series, we know nothing is guaranteed,'' said Scott Gomez, one of the team's four rookies, who, like the other three -- John Madden, Brian Rafalski and Colin White -- conducts himself like a veteran. ''We have to stay focused.''</p>
        <p>Focused is the word that has been used by every member of the team before every game since the start of the playoffs. Randy McKay credited Robinson for keeping the team's eye on the ultimate goal.</p>
        <p>''Three months ago we were in kind of disarray,'' McKay said. ''We knew we had a good team. We were waiting to be led and Larry did it. We had players as leaders individually, but we needed someone to lead the group collectively. He's made a lot of difference.''</p>
        <p>Robinson, who took over the coaching from Robbie Ftorek late in the regular season, admitted that even at his age -- he is now a grandfather -- he felt nervous before every game.  Robinson, who has seven Stanley Cup rings, has apparently instilled that edge in his players.</p>
        <p>''If you don't get nervous, you don't care,'' Robinson said. ''Guys use their nervousness to get through fatigue. We've gone through a lot to get  here and I look at the next game as a great opportunity.''</p>
        <p>Of all the players on the Devils, the man who seems to want the Stanley Cup more than anyone is Scott Stevens, the defenseman and captain. His wife, Donna, certainly made that clear today.</p>
        <p>''He wants that cup so bad,'' she said after the Devils checked out of their hotel. ''That's all he talks about.''</p>
        <p>''Everyone knows what we've sacrificed and what it took us to get here,'' Stevens said. ''We're focused because we know the biggest game is yet to be played.''</p>
        <p>The players, however, were confident. They have been playing better with each game in the playoffs and seem to have peaked against the Stars.</p>
        <p>''The team grew so much in this series,'' McKay said. ''We're getting contributions from everyone, but we can't get excited because we know there is another game.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>DERIAN HATCHER apparently escaped suspension for the unpenalized hit he leveled on JASON ARNOTT in Game 4. COLIN CAMPBELL, the National Hockey League vice president in charge of discipline, said after the game that the shot had deserved a penalty. But Hatcher, who led with his elbows, was still unrepentant after viewing the videotape. ''I just watched the hit for the first time and I still don't even think I hit him that hard,'' Hatcher said after the Stars met Tuesday morning at their practice site. ''I must have hit him perfect. He was there and leaning forward. I went to hit him and he was a little off balance and I came up with my hands a little bit. Maybe some of it was frustration, but I still don't think I hit him that hard.'' Coach KEN HITCHCOCK said he was not worried that Hatcher would be suspended. ''It's part of the game,'' Hitchcock said. . . . The Stars were fined $10,000 for not making enough players available to the news media on Sunday.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY: STANLEY CUP FINALS -- DEVILS VS. STARS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
