<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Net Is Calling Them Home, but Many More Are Needed</title>
    <meta content="07FAN.$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ONLINE OVERSEAS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fan, Grace</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E0DC1E3DF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1161" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Net Is Calling Them Home, but Many More Are Needed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRACE FAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fan, Grace</byline>
      <dateline>SHANGHAI</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Grace Fan article on overseas Chinese who are giving up advantages of life abroad to work as bilingual senior managers in China's infant Internet industry; China's many Internet startups are competing for small number of skilled top executives; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Xin Ye returned to Beijing after a 14-year absence to take a senior position at one of China's most popular Internet portals, Sohu, he left behind his wife, two daughters, a California lifestyle and a job prospect at a Silicon Valley start-up.</p>
        <p>''My heart at this point is still in Silicon Valley,'' said Mr. Ye, 36, a former senior technical manager at Marimba, as he emerged from a meeting on his first day of work early last month. ''The ocean was five minutes away. The mountains were half an hour's drive away. But how many times does an opportunity come up to build a leading portal in China? Just once, right?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Xin Ye returned to Beijing after a 14-year absence to take a senior position at one of China's most popular Internet portals, Sohu, he left behind his wife, two daughters, a California lifestyle and a job prospect at a Silicon Valley start-up.</p>
        <p>''My heart at this point is still in Silicon Valley,'' said Mr. Ye, 36, a former senior technical manager at Marimba, as he emerged from a meeting on his first day of work early last month. ''The ocean was five minutes away. The mountains were half an hour's drive away. But how many times does an opportunity come up to build a leading portal in China? Just once, right?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ye is not alone among overseas Chinese who have given up the advantages of life abroad, for the time being, to chase Internet gold in a nation he no longer calls home. In growing numbers, first- and second-generation Chinese from Hong Kong, Taiwan, Singapore and the United States are returning to China, many recruited to feed a hunger for bilingual senior managers in the country's infant Internet industry.</p>
        <p>''It's like a reverse brain drain,'' said Jay Kuo, a lawyer who left his job as a marketing manager at BSEM, an agricultural equipment manufacturer, in January to co-found Fudao.net, a finance site for families that is going online next month. ''A lot of my friends have come back for the singular opportunity to write the next Internet chapter. Many mainland friends who have the opportunity to go overseas now haven't gone for this reason.''</p>
        <p>Beijing has tried for years, without much success, to lure natives with technical and managerial skills back to China. But the explosion of the Internet in China is finally ''bringing them back in droves,'' said Charles Zhang, chairman of Sohu.</p>
        <p>Still, while Web entrepreneurs like Tang Haisong of Etang, an online portal, and Joseph Chen of Chinaren, a community Web site, are coming back waving their Harvard and Stanford M.B.A.'s -- and flush with millions of dollars in venture capital -- what start-ups really need are senior executives with hands-on management experience and technical talent, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Norman Liu, co-founder of 51job.com, a job site, said, ''Once companies pass their first three- to six-month periods, human resources inevitably becomes the most important and most difficult problem for them.''</p>
        <p>They will particularly have to to fill certain upper-echelon spots. ''They need key senior people with the vision and capability to lead them to an I.P.O.,'' Mr. Liu said. ''The Chinese are good at execution, but weak on problem-solving, and lack a keen knowledge of the business as well.''</p>
        <p>Though established multinational companies have lamented that there is a scarcity of executive talent in China, the rash of new dot-com companies is fast turning this shortage into a cross-industry regional drought.</p>
        <p>''The Internet industry is a big, sore open wound right now,'' said Steve Chiu, chief sales officer of Zhaopin, another job site. ''We have over 500 companies advertising on our site now, many of them looking for the same people. It's a really really crazy scene.''</p>
        <p>A chief technical officer, with five to eight years of management experience, tops the wish lists of more than 100 start-up companies. A talented vice president for marketing is another highly coveted yet hard-to-find executive. Longer-established dot-coms, including the popular portal Netease, are beginning to recruit older executives, who can offer a depth of experience that their brash young founders lack.</p>
        <p>Though well-known sites like Sohu and Sina have the money and name recognition to lure talent from Silicon Valley, many start-ups without these advantages are settling for employees with less experience, including managers from state-owned enterprises and graduates with master's degree in engineering. Salaries for even less-qualified chief technical officers can be as much as as $100,000, plus stock options.</p>
        <p>''It's not the most rational hiring decision,'' Mr. Liu said, ''because they'll hit a wall in six months. But companies nowadays are getting more and more desperate.''</p>
        <p>With demand up and supply down, it is no surprise that recruiting firms like Wang &amp; Li Asia Resources, which culls talent from greater China and San Francisco, has seen its Net business explode 80 percent over the last six months. About 300 competing job- search dot-coms have also crowded into the recruiting field, Mr. Chiu said, all trying to capitalize on the expanding market.</p>
        <p>For example, Sinobit, a site for technology entrepreneurs, prominently features a ''Western returnee'' center, hoping to lure overseas talent. The site was co-founded in January by Zhang Lei, who hastily packed his bags three months before finishing his M.B.A. from Yale University to return to China and join the Internet rush ''before it was too late.''</p>
        <p>Others scoff at the perception that returnees are a sure-fire bet, saying that some people come back with a superior attitude that offends their staff members, or have been away too long to immediately grasp the complexities of a business environment literally changing by the month.</p>
        <p>Still, for now, many smaller start-ups -- from Web development design firms to city guides -- are not worrying about an industry-wide scarcity of senior managers. Competent junior-level and midlevel managers are plentiful, thanks in part to multinational firms that started promoting local employees five years ago.</p>
        <p>Though more than a few executives are disappointed by the lack of creative graphic designers or talented and self-motivated editors, which they attribute largely to an education system that does not foster creativity, many have devised innovative ways to deal with the problem.</p>
        <p>An American executive at Menkou, a lifestyle and entertainment site, routinely does pull-ups in his hallway or plays his stereo loudly to encourage his employees to do wacky things. Fudao.net has built a jungle gym in its office to give its 27 employees a way to ''keep their creative juices flowing,'' as Mr. Kuo puts it. Other Internet start-ups, unhappy with local programmers and graphic designers, have contracted the work out to people in other countries.</p>
        <p>Employees have also realized that they are in demand. With bidding wars and raiding on the rise, salaries have increased in some companies as much as 50 percent for writers and 80 percent for junior-level programmers since a year ago. Across the industry, wages have generally risen a more modest 20 percent to 30 percent, but sudden promotions are also in vogue. One Internet company lured a sales clerk from another start-up by offering her a salary 12 times higher than her previous one, and the position of chief executive.</p>
        <p>''We couldn't even find good-quality secretaries at average salaries,'' Mr. Kuo said. ''Some even asked us for stock options. And we gave it to them.''</p>
        <p>ONLINE OVERSEAS Grace Fan writes about business and the Internet in Shanghai.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Grace Fan writes about business and the Internet in Shanghai.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
