<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BULLETIN BOARD</title>
    <meta content="07BULL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000608T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205491"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartocollis, Anemona</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education/Columns/Bulletin Board</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DB153FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BULLETIN BOARD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT and ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona; Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bulletin Board column offers college and school news; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rudy Crew's New Assignment</p>
        <p>RUDY CREW, the former schools chancellor, has joined the board of National Computer Systems, which has an exclusive contract to service scanning equipment that grades tests in nearly all of the city's schools.</p>
        <p>Conflict of interest rules prohibit a former employee from doing business with the board for one year after leaving. But an official said Dr. Crew was not covered by that rule because, as a director, he is not personally involved in board contracts. The five-year contract for $7.3 million  was renewed last month without competitive bids.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rudy Crew's New Assignment</p>
        <p>RUDY CREW, the former schools chancellor, has joined the board of National Computer Systems, which has an exclusive contract to service scanning equipment that grades tests in nearly all of the city's schools.</p>
        <p>Conflict of interest rules prohibit a former employee from doing business with the board for one year after leaving. But an official said Dr. Crew was not covered by that rule because, as a director, he is not personally involved in board contracts. The five-year contract for $7.3 million  was renewed last month without competitive bids.</p>
        <p>National Computer's directors get options for 3,500 shares of stock, and last year, each was paid $18,250. Dr. Crew did not return a phone call. Maggie Knack, a company spokeswoman, said Dr. Crew was appointed not because of the city contract but because he ''is a renowned leader in K-12 education, and we believe he will offer us great assistance with new product development.''</p>
        <p>New Director for New Visions</p>
        <p>New Visions for Public Schools, a nonprofit group that has helped to start many of the city's small schools, has selected ROBERT HUGHES as its new director. Mr. Hughes is co-counsel to the Campaign for Fiscal Equity, which is suing New York State over school aid allocation. JUDITH A. RIZZO, deputy chancellor of instruction, was a contender for the job.</p>
        <p>Principal Is Rehabilitated</p>
        <p>SERGE RENE was ousted from the principalship of Public School 72 in Brooklyn after a 1997 report accused him of  mismanagement and corruption. He then processed medical papers for the board. But last week Mr. Rene was made principal of Intermediate School 166 in East New York, Brooklyn, replacing MILTON STRONG, who retired under pressure. ''I know it's no easy task to find someone to put in charge of a school,'' said ROBERT RICCOBONO, the former superintendent in East New York, who is suing the board for removing him. ''But this seems inappropriate.''</p>
        <p>EDWARD F. STANCIK, the schools investigator, had found that Mr. Rene had illegally pressured employees at P.S. 72 to buy fund-raising tickets for Heriberto Mateo, a candidate for the local school board. Mr. Rene denied the charge. Yesterday, he could not be reached. Margie Feinberg, a board spokeswoman, said Mr. Rene had got the job because the charges had been resolved and he had made restitution. Mr. Stancik said he was discouraged, because Mr. Rene had engaged in ''the epitome of the patronage game.''</p>
        <p>Lisa Kudrow's Epiphany</p>
        <p>LISA KUDROW, the flaky massage therapist Phoebe Buf-fet on NBC's hit comedy ''Friends,'' may be more of an actress than anyone realizes. Ms. Kudrow is no ditz at all. She majored in biology at Vassar College, and she worked with her father, a research physician, studying headaches. Last weekend, she went to Vassar for her 15th reunion and saw gardens and buildings she had overlooked.</p>
        <p>''There's this beautiful Shakespeare garden that everybody talked about, and I'd never even noticed it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kudrow spent the year after Vassar trying a life of science before telling her parents she wanted to act. ''Good for you!'' her father said. ''Finally! What are you doing with all this biology stuff? What kind of life is that?''</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 8, 2000, Thursday  Because of an editing error, a report in the Bulletin Board column of the Education page yesterday about a new appointment for Serge Rene, who was removed as a Brooklyn principal in 1997, misstated his title. While he is temporarily in charge of Intermediate School 166 in East New York, he is assistant principal, not principal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 8, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a report in the Bulletin Board column of the Education page yesterday about a new appointment for Serge Rene, who was removed as a Brooklyn principal in 1997, misstated his title. While he is temporarily in charge of Intermediate School 166 in East New York, he is assistant principal, not principal.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
