<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Undignified and Screaming, Senate Seeks to Right Itself</title>
    <meta content="Y07SEN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205487"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alvarez, Lizette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DB153FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1086" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Undignified and Screaming, Senate Seeks to Right Itself</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZETTE ALVAREZ and ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alvarez, Lizette; Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Senate, long viewed as more dignified and cautious body in Congress, is mired in partisan, sand-lot warfare more typical of House of Representatives; past few weeks have been marked by arm-waving screaming match between Republican and Democratic leaders and series of threats and counter-threats over spending bills that must be passed before November elections; members of both parties agree vitriol and partisanship has reached new heights, casting shadow on Senate's reputation for careful deliberation and effectiveness; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Long viewed as the more dignified and cautious body of Congress, the Senate now finds itself mired in partisan, sand-lot warfare more typical of the House of Representatives.</p>
        <p>The past few weeks in the Senate have been marked by an arm-waving screaming match between the Republican and Democratic leaders  and a series of threats and counter-threats over spending bills that must be passed before the November election. The Senate has passed only a handful of significant bills this year, leaving things like increasing the minimum wage and cracking down on juvenile crime still in limbo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Long viewed as the more dignified and cautious body of Congress, the Senate now finds itself mired in partisan, sand-lot warfare more typical of the House of Representatives.</p>
        <p>The past few weeks in the Senate have been marked by an arm-waving screaming match between the Republican and Democratic leaders  and a series of threats and counter-threats over spending bills that must be passed before the November election. The Senate has passed only a handful of significant bills this year, leaving things like increasing the minimum wage and cracking down on juvenile crime still in limbo.</p>
        <p>Today, after a 10-day cooling-off period, there were signs that both sides were trying to patch up their differences. But some Senate Republicans and Democrats agreed that the vitriol and partisanship between the two parties has reached new heights, casting a shadow on the Senate's reputation, or at least its self-image, for careful deliberation and effectiveness.</p>
        <p>And while this kind of infighting routinely fuels election-year politics, this year's sparring is about more than just issues; it is also about the manner in which the Senate is conducting its business.</p>
        <p>Republicans say that the Democrats, rather than pushing for consensus, are behaving more like their rowdy counterparts in the House. All too often, Republicans argue, Democrats cavalierly slow things on the floor by attaching irrelevant amendments to important bills and by threatening filibusters so they can portray the Republicans as ''do-nothing'' senators in an election year.</p>
        <p>''The last couple of weeks before we went out has been the most obstructionist I've ever seen them,'' said Senator Trent Lott of Mississippi, the majority leader, referring to Democratic senators. ''I don't think it's in anybody's best interest for the Senate to be balled up with obstructionism on either side.''</p>
        <p>''Everything has been difficult this year,'' Mr. Lott said.</p>
        <p>For their part, Democrats say the Republicans have effectively gagged them and stifled thorough, deliberative discussion. They want Mr. Lott to loosen his hold and permit the Democrats to debate such issues as managed health care, gun control and the minimum wage. Until that happens, they say, they will continue to engage in parliamentary tactics.</p>
        <p>Senator Tom Daschle of South Dakota, the Democratic leader, lamented Mr. Lott's style of running the Senate, arguing that denying the minority the chance to vote on its agenda has hurt the overall institution.</p>
        <p>''This has been probably the most damaging to the Senate institutionally that I can recall,'' Mr. Daschle said today, referring to Mr. Lott's method of limiting debate and refusing amendments. ''If this practice continues, there really won't be any difference in how the Senate and House function.''</p>
        <p>Even President Clinton jumped in the fray today. He held a Rose Garden ceremony to lambaste Congress, and specifically the Senate, for sitting on emergency spending bills that are needed to fight drugs in Colombia, pay for the military operation in Kosovo and provide relief for hurricane victims.</p>
        <p>''I think what is required is for everybody in the Senate to recognize that this is something we ought to just put beyond whatever the other squabbles are and get it done and put it behind us,'' Mr. Clinton said, refraining, at least for now, from stepping in the partisan muck.</p>
        <p>It seems the Senate is trying to do some compromising. Senator Lott, who faces pressure not just from Democrats but also from conservatives in his own party, called up a defense authorization bill and permitted Democrats to bring up any amendment they might choose. In addition, a Republican senator, John McCain of Arizona, was told by Mr. Lott that he might offer his amendment on overhauling the campaign finance system.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Lott and Mr. Daschle were trying to reach an agreement that would settle their differences and allow orderly votes on spending bills.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lott's frustration was still evident. He all but dared Democrats to bring up what are regarded as  ''nongermane'' amendments on a bill that deals with national security.</p>
        <p>Less than three weeks ago, Mr. Lott and Mr. Daschle stood on the Senate floor and traded bitter words over parliamentary procedures on a largely symbolic gun control resolution. The exchange resulted in a logjam that was broken briefly, a week later, when the Senate voted on federal judgeship nominations.</p>
        <p>''If senators want to play games and cause mischief with the defense of our country, then the people will see once and for all that they are just up to playing games and are not serious, even about national defense,'' Mr. Lott said this afternoon. ''Maybe they will get some of this out of their system, and we can move on.''</p>
        <p>Many Republicans wondered how many times the Senate must vote on gun control, managed care and the minimum wage. The issues have come up in the past, but Democrats say Republicans have tied them up in committee, preventing a final vote.</p>
        <p>''We've already debated them and voted on them,'' Senator Connie Mack, Republican of Florida, said.</p>
        <p>Pleased by Mr. Lott's decision, Democrats said they would seize the opportunity and probably soon bring up amendments on managed care reform and raising the minimum wage.</p>
        <p>But they added that they would not be satisfied with a cursory airing of their views and a few procedural votes. Their issues, they say, deserve full debate and a vote.</p>
        <p>''We'll do what we have to do,'' said Senator Harry Reid of Nevada, the second-ranking Democrat, referring to attaching amendments to the military authorization bill. ''That doesn't mean when that bill is pulled or done with that we are through.''</p>
        <p>The battle for their ''rights,'' as Democrats call them, will go forward.</p>
        <p>''We have always been free to talk, always free to offer amendments,'' said Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan, Democrat of New York.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Moynihan said he worried that those freedoms might vanish, with the imposition of time limits and other restrictions like those in the House.</p>
        <p>''The Senate,'' he said, ''was never meant to be that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
