<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's a Whole New Lexicon</title>
    <meta content="07WCOL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Workplace" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205392"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LIFE'S WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Careercreations.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gitlin, Todd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belkin, Lisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2DB143FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="841" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's a Whole New Lexicon</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA BELKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belkin, Lisa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lisa Belkin (Life's Work) column on how today's young job seekers apply for positions: asking for what they want; says some of today's job seekers are doing their asking on Interet at job-search sites like Careercreations.com, founded by Todd Gitlin, age 22; describes her experience in applying for job using Gitlin's site (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A FORMER professor of mine called the other day and asked if I'd speak to a group of graduating students about juggling life and work. It's been nearly 20 years since I was a graduating senior myself, and I certainly don't remember anyone talking to me then about life in the same sentence as work.</p>
        <p>Back when I was their age (back when I swore I would never say things like ''back when I was their age''), a job search was all about whom we could persuade to hire us, not whom we would deign to work for. I have vague memories of my mother suggesting that ''international law requires a lot of time away from home, dear,'' but I wasn't really listening, and I did not for a moment consider choosing a career because it would provide something as complex as flextime-in-preparation-for-the-day-when-I-had-children. Back then the vocabulary with which to articulate that idea didn't even exist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A FORMER professor of mine called the other day and asked if I'd speak to a group of graduating students about juggling life and work. It's been nearly 20 years since I was a graduating senior myself, and I certainly don't remember anyone talking to me then about life in the same sentence as work.</p>
        <p>Back when I was their age (back when I swore I would never say things like ''back when I was their age''), a job search was all about whom we could persuade to hire us, not whom we would deign to work for. I have vague memories of my mother suggesting that ''international law requires a lot of time away from home, dear,'' but I wasn't really listening, and I did not for a moment consider choosing a career because it would provide something as complex as flextime-in-preparation-for-the-day-when-I-had-children. Back then the vocabulary with which to articulate that idea didn't even exist.</p>
        <p>Today's students, I'm learning, are fluent in this new language. They have watched their parents (gulp, my peers) try to give 100 percent of themselves twice over, and, because this is a mathematical impossibility, they have watched them fail. ''They have mothers and fathers who were never around,'' says Dan Golden, a dean at Wheaton College in Norton, Mass., where students are counseled, beginning as freshmen, about the ''triangle'' of life-work, significant relationships and community service. ''They saw their parents get sliced apart trying to balance everything,'' he says, ''and they are determined to do things differently.''</p>
        <p>Schools, in turn, are determined to help them. Just look at the name of Mr. Golden's department. No longer ''career services,'' his office of ''Work and Service Learning'' holds seminars throughout the year, with recent graduates returning to tell students about the real world. ''We don't want them to come back in 20 years,'' he explains, ''and say, 'Why didn't you tell us how hard it was going to be?' ''</p>
        <p>Instead, armed with knowledge and bouyed by a microscopic unemployment rate, they march into today's job interviews and ask for what they want. ''Dress code is a big one,'' says Dr. Larry Salters, director of the University of South Carolina's Career Center. ''They want to know, 'What are the dress expectations? How flexible is my schedule? Can I set my own hours? Can I do some of my work from home or in my car? How involved will I be in making the important decisions?' ''</p>
        <p>Some of them do their asking on the Web, at job-search sites like Careercreations .com. Founded by 22-year-old Todd Gitlin, who is barely one year out of California State University at Chico, the site proclaims: ''Forget about searching for job openings. Search for employers by the things that matter to you -- signing bonus, car allowance, stock options, on-site massages, flexible schedules and more.''</p>
        <p>One afternoon a few weeks ago I did just that. I logged on as the me I was my senior year, a confused Ivy League political science major who thought she might want to go to law school but figured journalism might be fun, too. Under ''fields of interest'' I entered advertising, publishing, consulting and the Internet. That last one didn't exist when I graduated, but if it had I don't imagine I could have resisted that which lures this whole generation.</p>
        <p>Then I scrolled through Mr. Gitlin's ingredients for a balanced life. I clicked ''yes'' to all the insurance benefits, to the stock-option plan, to paid personal days, paid sick days, paid vacation days, paid holidays. I clicked 'not essential'' to the commuting allowance and auto allowance because my 22-year-old self expected to live in the middle of a city. My only ''no'' was to paternity leave, for obvious biological reasons.</p>
        <p>I said I needed a flexible schedule and a smoke-free environment, but I could live without a casual dress code and the right to bring my (nonexistent) dog. On-site food facilities were on my list of requirements and, as a result, so was an on-site gym. Wanting to appear reasonable, I said that an on-site hairdresser, dry cleaner, car wash and massage therapist were ''nonessential.'' I was, I admit, sorely tempted to check ''yes'' to the massage.</p>
        <p>After agreeing to move anywhere in the country, I hit the send button. A list of more than a dozen companies appeared, and most were technology-related. Not one had all the features I had checked, but a few had most.</p>
        <p>Would I have been happy with a life spent writing banner ads for Internet sites? Perhaps. Would all this advance warning really have prepared my 22-year-old self for the cataclysmic changes brought to that life by adding children? Probably not. No class nor Web site can prepare you for that. But I would have been well served to have paid some attention. The biggest change since I was ''their age'' is not that they have all the answers, but that they know enough to ask the questions.</p>
        <p>LIFE'S WORK This column about the intersection of jobs and personal lives appears every other week. Lisa Belkin's e-mail address is Belkin@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">This column about the intersection of jobs and personal lives appears every other week. Lisa Belkin's e-mail address is Belkin@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
