<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="07PUBL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205464"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kassirer, Suri</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Teitelbaum, Bruce J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fitzpatrick, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nemy, Enid</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E2DD153FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON with Elisabeth Bumiller and Enid Nemy</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth; Nemy, Enid; Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column; Suri Kassirer, wife of Bruce J Teitelbaum, who managed Mayor Rudolph Giuliani's campaign for US Senate, discusses why she is now supporting Hillary Rodham Clinton's campaign; lawyer Charles Fitzpatrick discusses his attempts to sell his website www.hillaryforpresident.com; Mayor Giuliani unveils Fashion Walk Hall of Fame in Garment District (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All's Fair in Love And Politics</p>
        <p>HILLARY RODHAM CLINTON'S latest defender on the talk shows? SURI KASIRER, whose husband, BRUCE J. TEITELBAUM, managed RUDOLPH W. GIULIANI'S campaign.</p>
        <p>''I've always been a Democrat,'' Ms. Kasirer said, but she kept a low profile on the Senate race while her husband was involved. She worked mostly, she said, for VICE PRESIDENT AL GORE's campaign.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All's Fair in Love And Politics</p>
        <p>HILLARY RODHAM CLINTON'S latest defender on the talk shows? SURI KASIRER, whose husband, BRUCE J. TEITELBAUM, managed RUDOLPH W. GIULIANI'S campaign.</p>
        <p>''I've always been a Democrat,'' Ms. Kasirer said, but she kept a low profile on the Senate race while her husband was involved. She worked mostly, she said, for VICE PRESIDENT AL GORE's campaign.</p>
        <p>Now, with her husband's boss out of the race, Ms. Kasirer is being more public about her support for Mrs. Clinton. She turned up on New York 1 News on Tuesday, on a panel about Jewish voters and the Senate race. She argued that undecided voters who might have cast their ballots for Mr. Giuliani, are more likely now to support the First Lady than her new opponent, REPRESENTATIVE RICK A. LAZIO.</p>
        <p>''As they get to know her,'' Ms. Kasirer said yesterday, ''they're going to come back home to the Democratic Party. They're going to be supporters of Hillary Clinton.''</p>
        <p>Is Mr. Teitelbaum surprised that she is saying this?</p>
        <p>''He knew all this when he married me,'' she said. ''It didn't come as a shock. One of the things I liked about Bruce -- I dated many men who were apathetic. They may have been Democrats, but they were apathetic. Bruce and I may at the end of the day support different candidates, but we feel strongly about the importance of being involved, taking an active role.''</p>
        <p>Thinking Ahead Of Possibilities</p>
        <p>CHARLIE FITZPATRICK, a lawyer in San Antonio, Tex., thinks Mrs. Clinton should think beyond November.</p>
        <p>Of course he would think that: He is the owner of the Internet domain name www.hillaryforpresident .com, which he is offering for sale at $100,000 ''or best offer.'' (None so far, he said.)</p>
        <p>''I bought the Web site believing that my cat, Hillary, would be a better president than either of my current candidates,'' Mr. Fitzpatrick said. ''Alternatively, if anyone else named Hillary chose to run for president in the future, they might find it a useful site for campaign-donation gathering.''</p>
        <p>He figured that that someone would be Mrs. Clinton. ''I felt like when Giuliani's campaign evaporated, the likelihood of her making the Senate increased,'' he said, ''so the likelihood of her running for president increased.''</p>
        <p>Not so, said HOWARD WOLFSON, a spokesman for Mrs. Clinton's Senate campaign. ''Absolutely no interest in running for president,'' he said. As for the domain name, he added, ''I wouldn't even buy it for a dollar.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Giuliani As a Fashion Plate</p>
        <p>MAYOR RUDOLPH W. GIULIANI, who has displayed a certain onstage flair for cross-dressing, was so impressed with the theatrical new Hilton Times Square hotel yesterday that he sounded as if he wanted to put on a dress and kick up his heels again.</p>
        <p>''It's much more beautiful than I thought it would be,'' Mr. Giuliani said at the opening of the hotel, on 42nd Street between Seventh and Eighth Avenues. ''And it looks to me like a Broadway set, or an opera set. So I may actually put on a dress and perform. I'm feeling the urge to do that here.''</p>
        <p>In a still talked-about performance, the mayor appeared as ''Rudia'' at the Inner Circle show, an annual black-tie gathering that features reporters doing humorous skits about the mayor. In 1997 he appeared in a sequined gown, full makeup and a blond wig. He appeared in a video with JOAN RIVERS at this year's show, reprising ''Rudia,'' and has appeared as an Italian grandmother on ''Saturday Night Live.''</p>
        <p>But maybe the mayor just wants a medallion on the sidewalk alongside four men who design dresses.</p>
        <p>His appearance at the hotel came after he had unveiled the Fashion Walk of Fame, created by the Fashion Center Business Improvement District. ''Everyone would agree that New York City is the capital of the world for fashion,'' he declared as he unveiled medallions honoring GEOFFREY BEENE, BILL BLASS, CALVIN KLEIN and RALPH LAUREN. The mayor compared them to baseball's Babe Ruth and Ty Cobb.</p>
        <p>The medallions have been set in the sidewalk on the east side of Seventh Avenue between 39th and 40th Streets. Four other, commemorating the designers RUDI GERNREICH, HALSTON, CLAIRE MCCARDELL and NORMAN NORELL, have been placed between 38th and 39th Streets.</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON with Elisabeth Bumiller and Enid Nemy</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
