<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Is the House That Shaq Built</title>
    <meta content="07SHAQ$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205493"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL: N.B.A. FINALS -- LAKERS VS. PACERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Neal, Shaquille</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EFDB153FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Is the House That Shaq Built</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Los Angeles Lakers center Shaquille O'Neal, in interview at his home, discusses his preparations to play Indiana Pacers in NBA championship series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are Superman logos on each side of the walkway. Violets form the ''S.'' Golden marigolds form the background of the emblem, which also appears on the stained-glass front doors, the computer room and the bedspread.</p>
        <p>Shaquille O'Neal's infatuation with the superhero can be seen all over his contemporary, three-story, 15,000-square foot home in the Santa Monica Mountains, where the National Basketball Association's largest pillar of strength lives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are Superman logos on each side of the walkway. Violets form the ''S.'' Golden marigolds form the background of the emblem, which also appears on the stained-glass front doors, the computer room and the bedspread.</p>
        <p>Shaquille O'Neal's infatuation with the superhero can be seen all over his contemporary, three-story, 15,000-square foot home in the Santa Monica Mountains, where the National Basketball Association's largest pillar of strength lives.</p>
        <p>Sunlight cascades through nearly every window, a stuffed, 7-foot polar bear shows its fangs in the wildlife room adjacent to the expansive, white-marble foyer and 8-foot doorways accommodate a 7-foot-1-inch, 330-pound man. There is a live-in, personal chef to bake O'Neal a cake every day and monitor his diet. Three video-game machines, a pool table and an antique slot machine in the entertainment center.</p>
        <p>From his backyard -- where his affectionate Rottweiler, Thor, and pit-bull mutt, Rocki Lou, stand sentry over an oblong-shaped swimming pool and tennis court below -- a breathtaking panorama of the San Fernando Valley unfolds.</p>
        <p>''Yo, Leonard, how much you think it would cost to turn the tennis court into an indoor basketball court?'' O'Neal said to his agent, Leonard Armato.</p>
        <p>''Well, you'd probably have to get permission first,'' Armato said. ''There might be building codes and zoning laws involved.''</p>
        <p>''About 300?'' O'Neal said, meaning $300,000.</p>
        <p>''Not even.''</p>
        <p>''I wonder if I can sell it without a tennis court.''</p>
        <p>''Hey, you can have a combination basketball-indoor tennis court.''</p>
        <p>O'Neal thought and smiled. He asked Thor to raise each paw to shake his hand before retreating to his spacious oak-stained kitchen and grabbing a bottle of iced tea.</p>
        <p>''This is nice, all this,'' O'Neal said Monday as he sat back in a plush, leather chair inside his office, a row of size 22 basketball sneakers on the shelf behind him. ''But it's not everything. I need to win it all. On a personal level, that would make it complete. Because when it's all said and done, I don't want any 'buts' behind my name. I don't want to hear he was a great and dominant player, but. . . .''</p>
        <p>O'Neal, this year's most valuable player, pursues his first N.B.A. championship tonight in Game 1 of the finals against the Indiana Pacers. With Los Angeles still agog over his Game 7 dunk in the last minute of the Western Conference finals on Sunday, even Indiana Coach Larry Bird is unsure how to stop him.</p>
        <p>''I don't know,'' Bird said today when asked how he plans to contain O'Neal. ''You got any ideas for me?''</p>
        <p>O'Neal led the league in scoring and finished in the top five of four other statistical categories. Agile and spry for his size, O'Neal affirmed his position as the most dominant player in the game, mowing over the rest of the league like a beer truck with a broken parking brake.</p>
        <p>Winning a title would mark the culmination of an interesting year, one that began last summer during a meeting with new Coach Phil Jackson at his Montana home.</p>
        <p>''When I rode up to his big log cabin, he had a window there and in the window were his six championship balls,'' O'Neal said of Jackson's replica championship trophies he won as the coach of the Chicago Bulls. ''I jumped on the trampoline and hung out with his kids and he told me what he expected of me. He expected me to play good defense, dominate, play hard.</p>
        <p>''He didn't want me to get injured. He wanted me to come in good shape and he wanted me to be in shape the whole year, and he told me I was going to be in the game the whole time. He wanted me to average 40-something minutes. And I just did what I was asked to do.''</p>
        <p>At age 28, O'Neal has become the model for fusing entertainment with sport. Between his pro basketball career, movies, hip-hop recording and countless commercials, his face has become one of America's most recognized -- Shaq, that lovable bear of a man whose smile stretches from baseline to baseline.</p>
        <p>At one point during a tour of his 11-room home on Monday afternoon, he posed for pictures by inserting buck teeth onto his top molars, an altogether silly scene that had Armato begging a photographer to stop shooting.</p>
        <p>''No, Shaq, please, don't do it,'' Armato pleaded as O'Neal burst out laughing.</p>
        <p>''I got them at drbukk.com while I was on the Internet,'' he said. ''You can't believe the things they sell there. I might order some more.''</p>
        <p>When O'Neal left Orlando for Los Angeles in 1996 -- signing a free-agent contract with the Lakers worth $121 million over seven years -- the symmetry almost seemed scripted. From Disney World to Disneyland, he could essentially be a big kid the rest of his career.</p>
        <p>In the movie ''Arthur,'' in which a millionaire refuses to grow up, the character played by Dudley Moore is asked how it feels to have all that money. ''It feels great,'' he says.</p>
        <p>O'Neal is essentially Arthur in high-tops, enjoying every moment of fortune and fame. He wrestles with his half-brother, Jamal Harrison, who recently finished junior college and is now living with O'Neal.</p>
        <p>O'Neal's home, which he bought in 1996 for approximately $4 million, is nestled in the Santa Monica Mountains, in Mulholland Estates -- a posh, gated community above  of downtown Los Angeles. Aside from the Superman logos and wildlife room, O'Neal's home, in a cul-de-sac, is understated. The decor is punctuated by soft-beige rugs and white-marble floors.</p>
        <p>In the front room, O'Neal watches a 70-inch television screen on his American Indian-patterned couch. Off to the right is a wet bar with a framed collage of programs from Billie Holliday concerts. His wine cabinet is filled with only 30 bottles of sparkling cider.</p>
        <p>The wildlife room is a sight to behold, stuffed animals that look as if they should be enclosed behind plate glass at the American Museum of Natural History. There is a polar bear on its hind legs, standing nearly 8-feet tall, forever growling. A zebra and a lion, locked in mortal combat. An orangutang in front of a fireplace. A hyena and a bobcat. Wood-carved African facemasks and giraffes give it a safari-like appeal.</p>
        <p>He is asked if he purchased the animals or killed them himself.</p>
        <p>''I hunt,'' O'Neal said. (Armato said O'Neal was kidding and worried that his client's animal-loving reputation would suffer.) ''The first time I wore a fur in New York, the animal activists were all over me,'' O'Neal said.</p>
        <p>O'Neal heads upstairs to his bedroom. Covering his 9-foot long mattress and box spring is a black comforter with a white Superman logo.</p>
        <p>''Watch this,'' he says as he hits an electronic clicker to dim the lamp. Suddenly, blinking strobe lights appear over his bed. He hits another button to lower a movie screen from the ceiling and yet another to activate his VCR.</p>
        <p>A compilation of O'Neal's most spectacular dunks appear on the screen, edited and compiled by him in a computer room adjacent to his bedroom.</p>
        <p>''This is same tape I watch before every game,'' he says as the image of the Utah Jazz frontline running for cover plays out in the background.</p>
        <p>On a night stool rests, ''Message to the Blackman in America,'' by Elijah Muhammad. On one wall hangs a wooden plaque in memory of his grandmother, Odessa Chambliss, who died in 1996. Pictures of his two children, Tahira, who will turn 4 in July and recently implored him to bend his knees while shooting foul shots, and Shareef, his four-month-old son, can be found throughout the home.</p>
        <p>Aromatherapy candles line his bathtub, which is the size of small Jacuzzi.</p>
        <p>''When I come home, I come to rest,'' he said. ''I really don't spend time that much time here. I come home after practice, take a nap, go back and work on my free throws and eat. Pretty simple.''</p>
        <p>O'Neal said one of his favorite things to do is watch TV in the dining room. ''That's where I just chill out and enjoy life,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He is asked if he would do anything special if the Lakers win their first championship in 12 seasons. ''I'll probably get like 10 rings made and pass them out to my crew,'' he said. ''I'll give my father one, my Uncle Mike one and my grandfather one and other people close to me.</p>
        <p>''Then I might ride from here to Vegas on my bike. Just ride. I think I'm also going to visit my old high school coach on the outskirts of Dallas. Dave Madura, I haven't seen him in a while.''</p>
        <p>O'Neal rises and thanks his visitors for stopping by. In the kitchen, Thomas Gosney, the personal chef, has just pulled a roasted chicken from the oven and is preparing a salad for his employer, the man who has everything but an N.B.A. title.</p>
        <p>''I know after I get one there will be a couple of 'buts,' he said. ''Magic got five, Mike got six, Bird got three. I'm sure after I'll get one, they'll want me to get two and three and four. But that's O.K. You have first to live up to your own expectations before you can live up to anybody else's.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL: N.B.A. FINALS -- LAKERS VS. PACERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
