<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Most Online Investors, Information Beats Speed</title>
    <meta content="07ROSE$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205367"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL FINANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Schwab, Charles, &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosen, Jan M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EEDE1E3DF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Most Online Investors, Information Beats Speed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN M. ROSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosen, Jan M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Internet is making first-class stock information available to individual investors, both those trading online and those using traditional brokers; many investors are also moving from research to trading online, with assets in online brokerage accounts growing 23.5 percent, Jan-Mar, to over $1 trillion and online trading volume rising 69 percent in period; Charles Schwab leads in online trading, with 21.4 percent of market share; graphs profile online traders (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DESPITE those banner advertisements on Web sites for, say, $7 stock trades, the Internet's greatest gift to investors is not online trading but the wealth of information it offers people who are researching a company or a mutual fund before investing.</p>
        <p>''The Internet has empowered people,'' said Robert N. Gordon, the president of the Twenty-First Securities Corporation, an investment management firm in Manhattan that specializes in risk-reduction strategies. ''Investors used to be hostage to their brokers; if they wanted stock quotes, they had to call their brokers, and only the brokers had access to research reports. The Internet has broken down the information wall. Now investors can eliminate the middleman.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DESPITE those banner advertisements on Web sites for, say, $7 stock trades, the Internet's greatest gift to investors is not online trading but the wealth of information it offers people who are researching a company or a mutual fund before investing.</p>
        <p>''The Internet has empowered people,'' said Robert N. Gordon, the president of the Twenty-First Securities Corporation, an investment management firm in Manhattan that specializes in risk-reduction strategies. ''Investors used to be hostage to their brokers; if they wanted stock quotes, they had to call their brokers, and only the brokers had access to research reports. The Internet has broken down the information wall. Now investors can eliminate the middleman.''</p>
        <p>Tim Kochis, the president of Kochis Fitz, a San Francisco money-management firm, called online investing ''fast, reliable and convenient, a great thing.'' But referring to  the popular image of the get-rich-quick day trader, he warned that online investing ''can be abused by the user.''</p>
        <p>Financial professionals have long warned against trading impulsively on supposedly hot tips, saying many people cannot resist buying shares of what will surely be the next Microsoft the minute they hear about it from the guy in the office down the hall. And with Internet chat rooms creating even more hype, people with poor impulse control can lose money even faster. After all, it's just a few mouse clicks from chat room to trade, with no one to toss out a caveat or suggest an alternative.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, first-class information is also available; it can be used profitably  whether one is trading online or through a traditional broker, is an active investor or just rethinks strategies at tax or tuition time. All the leading brokerage firms, both full-service and discount, have secure, accessible Web sites, as do service organizations like Morningstar and Bloomberg.</p>
        <p>Tracey E. Curvey, the executive vice president of Online Brokerage for Fidelity Personal Investments, compares this more thoughtful approach to the Internet to patients' use of the Web to research health problems before visiting a doctor.</p>
        <p>Many investors are also moving from research to trading. Assets in online brokerage accounts grew 23.5 percent in the first quarter of this year, to more than $1 trillion, US Bancorp Piper Jaffray reported last  month. And online trading volume rose 69 percent over the previous quarter. The leader was Charles Schwab, which had 3.7 million accounts for a 21.4 percent market share, averaging 290,000 trades a day.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Kochis cautioned, ''stock picking is not for the casual, lay investor,'' although a handful of his clients who have spent  substantial time and effort on research have been successful in fairly aggressive online trading. Many more prefer to have the firm manage their investments.</p>
        <p>Neither approach is right or wrong, Mr. Kochis added, but is a matter of personality and individual choice. Some people are entrepreneurial, while others like to delegate. Online investing can be ideal for middle-income people with long-term goals, Mr. Kochis said. Say a couple with a 3-year-old  wants to save for the child's education. They might go online to buy no-load mutual funds through companies like Fidelity, Vanguard or T. Rowe Price.</p>
        <p>WITH the information available on the Internet, people who feel insecure about making investments  can learn the basics of investing and personal finance before they trade. Online trading is the easy part -- with a few mouse clicks,  you can buy or sell. ''You can do it on your own time,'' Ms. Curvey pointed out.</p>
        <p>But prudent investors do not trade until they have researched a security's fundamentals and considered how it fits into their  financial plan and their tolerance of risk. One approach is to put the money you're investing into a money-market account. You can use the resources on your brokerage firm's Web site to learn about the market, then set up a dummy portfolio, research stocks or mutual funds and simulate trades. ''When you feel comfortable, go ahead and make a transaction,'' Ms. Curvey said.</p>
        <p>Many consumers are smarter about their future than their predecessors 20 years ago, having gained experience with their 401(k) plans. Many young people, too, have grown up using computers, so online research and trading seems natural. The leap to online trading is undoubtedly easier for self-directed customers of a discount broker, like Fidelity, than for those working with traditional brokers. In return for the higher commissions, the full-service firms offer  clients guidance as well as execute transactions, but even these brokers are pressured to offer online trading and resources.</p>
        <p>Merrill Lynch, for example, offers a lot of  information at www.mlol.ml.com. There are financial calculators, asset allocation models, courses on financial planning and understanding risk, mutual fund and stock scanners and detailed reports from the firm's analysts, as well as access to news and one's own account performance. There are also  services like online bill paying and shopping that can earn frequent-flier points.</p>
        <p>When it comes to trading, Merrill Lynch  clients can deal with a financial consultant, as they have traditionally; choose a managed account; trade online through Merrill Lynch Direct at $29.95 a transaction; or use some of each by linking accounts.</p>
        <p>Joel S. Isaacson, a certified public accountant and certified financial planner who is the president of his own firm in Manhattan, said that online trading could be ''good for do-it-yourselfers, provided they do the research, buy good stuff and hold it'' rather than trading in and out. Even so, he added, ''most people are better off using some advice or buying index funds.''</p>
        <p>People who open an account where cheap trades are advertised may lose more through poor executions than they gain on  low commissions, Mr. Isaacson said. ''If you're just executing a trade, you can sometimes negotiate low commissions with a full-service broker,'' he said, especially when a  block of stock is involved.</p>
        <p>For people who do want to invest online, the quality of information on a broker's site can be more important than the charge for each transaction. But it is good in any case to remember that the Internet does not offer investors a superhighway around the market's ups and downs. People who speed ahead may well crash.</p>
        <p>Danger Signs For Traders</p>
        <p>INVESTING online does not condemn an investor to becoming a crazed day trader any more than enjoying a glass of wine at dinner leads inexorably to alcoholism. Still, for certain people, online investing, like taking a drink, can lead to trouble.</p>
        <p>''If you had a bad day at work or with your family, go to the gym, not the computer,'' said Linda Barbanel, a Manhattan psychotherapist and the author of ''Sex, Money &amp; Power.'' Some people who think that they have stumbled or have not been appreciated in one area try to prove themselves in another, she explained. In the last couple of years, that other area has often been the stock market, where people take unwarranted risks in the quest to make a killing and impress their spouse, boss or friends.</p>
        <p>''Many alcoholics who give up alcohol take up other compulsions -- shopping, spending and now online trading,'' Ms. Barbanel said. ''Gamblers and day traders tend to be compulsive. They can't tear themselves away when trading, because when they are doing it, they do not have to think about their frustration, anger and depression.''</p>
        <p>For people who follow prudent financial practices and research their investments carefully, online trading can be remunerative, Ms. Barbanel added, but compulsive traders often skip that part of the process. ''They think of it as a game, but it is a treacherous one,'' she said, citing these warning signs:</p>
        <p>*If you feel it is important to make trades every day.</p>
        <p>*If you see online trading as a way to get rich quick, even quitting a job to devote more time it.</p>
        <p>*And if you are borrowing money, running up credit card debt or taking a second mortgage on your house to trade, you are in serious trouble.</p>
        <p>People who do well at online trading tend to be entrepreneurial, Ms. Barbanel said, adding: ''They want to be captain of their own ship. They like to make their own decisions. They are risk-takers to begin with.</p>
        <p>''They wish to be powerful, respected and in control,'' she noted, even when it would be smarter to get help.</p>
        <p>JAN M. ROSEN</p>
        <p>PERSONAL FINANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
