<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Women's Global Views Examined by Survey</title>
    <meta content="Y07WOME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205440"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aspen Institute</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE5DF153FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1037" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Women's Global Views Examined by Survey</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Survey commissioned by Aspen Institute finds American women are more likely than men to frame their foreign policy concerns around global issues like health, poverty and human rights; interests make women marginally stronger supporters of diplomacy and cooperation in international organizations, while men are more likely to favor military solutions; survey is released to coincide with special General Assembly session on progress of world's women; its findings detailed; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American women are more likely than men to frame their foreign policy concerns around global social issues like health, poverty and human rights, a new poll has found. The independent survey was released this week to coincide with a special General Assembly session on the progress of the world's women.</p>
        <p>These interests, the survey found, make women marginally stronger supporters of diplomacy and cooperation in international organizations, while men are more likely to favor military solutions or put a higher priority on trade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American women are more likely than men to frame their foreign policy concerns around global social issues like health, poverty and human rights, a new poll has found. The independent survey was released this week to coincide with a special General Assembly session on the progress of the world's women.</p>
        <p>These interests, the survey found, make women marginally stronger supporters of diplomacy and cooperation in international organizations, while men are more likely to favor military solutions or put a higher priority on trade.</p>
        <p>''What this poll tells us is that American women understand that the well-being of themselves, their families and communities are increasingly intimately connected with the well-being and stability of other countries,'' said Joan Dunlop, a fellow at the Rockefeller Brothers Fund and director of the Women's Lens on Global Issues project at the Aspen Institute, the policy research group that commissioned the survey.</p>
        <p>The poll, conducted by Belden Russonello &amp; Stewart, surveyed 1,500 women and 701 men and has an overall margin of error of 2.2 percentage points.</p>
        <p>The world has come closer to home, Ms. Dunlop said in an interview today, and that is reflected in women's attitudes.</p>
        <p>''You sit down and eat food from other countries,'' she said. ''Your kid at school gets inoculated for TB because a refugee from Kosovo is infected. Your husband comes home and worries about his job being moved to Mexico.''</p>
        <p>A debate over whether women have different attitudes toward issues of war, peace and economic development has been going on for years in women's organizations, whose leaders have often been reluctant to characterize any set of ideas as a woman's view.</p>
        <p>Women in government and foreign-policy making have very mixed records that fit no pattern, they say.</p>
        <p>Prime Ministers Indira Gandhi of India and Margaret Thatcher of Britain have waged successful wars, for example. Meanwhile, Ms. Dunlop says she is often asked why the many women who have served as political leaders in South Asia have not alleviated the region's poverty or raised the status of its women.</p>
        <p>''I don't believe feminism is gender-specific,'' said Ms. Dunlop, the founder and past president of the International Women's Health Coalition, which supports medical services for women in developing countries. ''We're talking about a set of values.''</p>
        <p>As new threats to American life have replaced cold war fears about nuclear war, many issues once considered ''women's issues'' have moved to the center of national security, and men often line up with women in giving them emphasis.</p>
        <p>Epidemic disease ranks high on this list, said Donna Shalala, the secretary of health and human services, who has been leading the United States delegation here at the special Assembly session, called to measure progress on women's rights since the Fourth International Conference on Women, held in Beijing in 1995.</p>
        <p>''Foreign policy requires a new conceptualization,'' Ms. Shalala said in an interview today. ''It is no longer as narrow as defined by the literature as well as by the foreign policy professionals -- and they're resisting. When we said that AIDS was an international security issue, they went crazy. And it's not just AIDS. It's malaria, it's tuberculosis.</p>
        <p>''Infectious diseases destabilize economies. They shift resources. They take the public health infrastructure apart. The world has changed out there. If we look at markets, there's not going to be a market if you knock down a generation between 25 and 35.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Shalala said that she now had a senior public health official attached to the National Security Council, and that another is a high-ranking aide in the State Department.</p>
        <p>In the Aspen poll, 69 percent of the women sampled said global problems made it necessary for the United States to work closely with international organizations like the United Nations. Thirty-nine percent of the women said they wanted greater attention to foreign affairs by the government.</p>
        <p>Women consistently put a higher priority than the men questioned in the survey on international programs to prevent childhood diseases, promote equal education for girls, make birth control available and promote fair labor practices.</p>
        <p>When asked what kind of countries should get the most United States support, 35 percent of the women said poor countries, followed by nations important to American security next, at 34 percent, and trading partners third, at 26 percent. The men gave first ranking to nations important to security (37 percent) and those that are trading partners (34 percent), with poor poor countries trailing at 25 percent.</p>
        <p>Sixty-seven percent of the women, compared with 56 percent of the men, said the most important reason for international involvement was responsibility to future generations. Protecting the world's environment was considered important to women.</p>
        <p>But men and women shared some very similar views on America's role in the world: just over half of each group polled said the United States should be a ''good neighbor'' to other nations. Only 4 percent of women and 5 percent of men want to see Americans be global policemen.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dunlop said results like these would indicate that foreign policy views held by men may not be as fundamentally at variance with those of women as other questions or other polls generally indicate.</p>
        <p>''Women and men share the same vision of what they want the U.S. to be as a global citizen,'' she said. ''The differences between women and men are not significant. What is different is the level of intensity.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
