<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unilever Deal For Bestfoods Signals More Acquisitions</title>
    <meta content="Y07FOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205494"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bestfoods</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Unilever</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nestle Sa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nabisco Holdings Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Quaker Oats Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hays, Constance L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EEDB153FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unilever Deal For Bestfoods Signals More Acquisitions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE L. HAYS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hays, Constance L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bestfoods accepts Unilever's offer of $20.3 billion, or $73 a share, creating world's second-largest packaged foods company; Unilever will be rivaled only by Nestle, world's largest food maker; hopes that in acquiring Bestfoods that it can regain power with supermarkets that has eroded over the last two years; acquisition is likely to accelerate mergers in food business, with Nabisco Holdings and Quaker Oats among the likely takeover targets; analysts note that Bestfoods recent statement indicating possible merger with Campbell Soup Co appears to have been part of strategy to coax better offer from Unilever; photo of Bestfoods products; chart profiling both Bestfoods and Unilever; graphs on food company rankings within industry (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a deal that sets the stage for further consolidation in the food industry, Unilever said yesterday that it would pay $20.3 billion in cash, or $73 a share, to acquire Bestfoods, the maker of Knorr soups, Skippy peanut butter and Hellmann's mayonnaise.</p>
        <p>Unilever will be rivaled only by Nestle. as the world's largest food maker once the combination is completed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a deal that sets the stage for further consolidation in the food industry, Unilever said yesterday that it would pay $20.3 billion in cash, or $73 a share, to acquire Bestfoods, the maker of Knorr soups, Skippy peanut butter and Hellmann's mayonnaise.</p>
        <p>Unilever will be rivaled only by Nestle. as the world's largest food maker once the combination is completed.</p>
        <p>Unilever hopes that by acquiring Bestfoods' well-known brands and increasing their sales it can regain power with supermarkets that has eroded over the last two years. In that period, food manufacturers lost much of their ability to demand shelf space for their products as the supermarket business became concentrated in a few hands.</p>
        <p>''The global retailers are clearly looking for brands that can draw consumers into their stores,'' Antony Burgmans, the co-chairman of Unilever, said in a telephone interview yesterday after the deal was announced in New York. ''Knorr will now become the largest Unilever brand, and it will play a terrific role in the eye of the retailer in drawing crowds into their stores.''</p>
        <p>Unilever, an British-Dutch company, had originally offered about 10 percent to 20 percent less for Bestfoods, but the Bestfoods chairman and chief executive, Charles R. Shoemate, resolutely held out for a higher price. Unilever was willing to pay more, in part because it identified additional savings that could be achieved, said Niall FitzGerald, the other Unilever co-chairman. The estimate of annual cost savings, originally $500 million, was increased to $750 million, he said.</p>
        <p>Not all the savings ''will be about eliminating things,'' Mr. FitzGerald said. ''Some will be about efficiencies'' in purchasing, for example, and other manufacturing areas. Still, stock analysts said they expected most of the savings to come through job reductions, although Mr. FitzGerald did not provide details.</p>
        <p>At Bestfoods headquarters in Englewood Cliffs, N.J., ''people are absorbing the news,'' said Gale L. Griffin, a company spokeswoman. Bestfoods, with 16,000 employees around the United States and 32,000 more abroad, is far smaller than Unilever, which has 255,000 workers.</p>
        <p>''It's just a matter of deciding whose factory makes it and whose factory gets shut,'' said Daniel Peris, a stock analyst at Argus Research. ''They will go over the assets one by one, deciding whose is stronger in India, in Latin America and in North America.''</p>
        <p>Unilever intends to fold its food-service business into that of Bestfoods, which has a stronger operation, Mr. Burgmans said last month. Bestfoods also has a big European operation, and the combined company will have considerable strength in Latin America and Asia. ''At a single stroke, we could have them in a million shops,'' Mr. Burgmans said of Bestfoods products. Bestfoods had about $9 billion in sales last year, while Unilever had about $43 billion from Ragu sauce, Lipton tea, Breyers ice cream and nonfood products like Suave shampoo.</p>
        <p>The combined company will be known as Unilever and will retain its headquarters in London and Rotterdam, the Netherlands. It was unclear yesterday what would become of the Bestfoods headquarters, which is next to the headquarters of Unilever's United States food business, known as Thomas A. Lipton, or what role there would be for Bestfoods management.</p>
        <p>The deal requires the approval of shareholders as well as regulators in the dozens of countries where Bestfoods and Unilever do business. In a conference call with analysts, Unilever's chairmen expressed confidence that the merger would be approved, said John M. McMillin, a food stocks analyst at Prudential Securities. One sticking point could be Brazil, he said, where the combined company would dominate the market with about $1 billion in sales.</p>
        <p>The acquisition is likely to accelerate mergers in the long-sleepy food business. Nabisco Holdings, the maker of Ritz crackers and Oreo cookies, is already for sale, with Philip Morris, Cadbury Schweppes and Groupe Danone among those showing interest. Another likely takeover target is Quaker Oats, the maker of Gatorade, which would be worth about $85 a share if it attracted a price near the 14 times 1999 earnings that Unilever is paying for Bestfoods, Mr. McMillin said. Quaker Oats shares closed yesterday at $69.3125, up 81.25 cents. Shares of Campbell Soup, with which Bestfoods had recently flirted, fell $1.5625, to $29.5625.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shoemate won praise yesterday from stock analysts and shareholders who said he had played a skillful game of poker to draw a higher price out of Unilever. In his 10-year reign as chief executive, the company changed its name from CPC International Inc. and focused on packaged foods. Its products include Entenmann's baked goods, Mazola corn oil, Arnold bread, Thomas' English muffins, Mueller's pasta and Karo corn syrup.</p>
        <p>In their extended courtship, Unilever tried various tactics to lure the Bestfoods executives to the negotiating table before the deal was clinched yesterday morning at $73 a share. The Bestfoods board flatly rejected a previous bid of $66 a share, which had been raised from an initial range of $61 to $64 a share. When they were rebuffed, the Unilever chairmen engaged in a carefully plotted crusade, taking their arguments in favor of the merger directly to analysts and money managers at a Goldman, Sachs conference on May 15.</p>
        <p>As recently as Monday, Bestfoods was said to be pursuing a possible merger with Campbell Soup, a match that stock analysts said would do nothing for Bestfoods shareholders. Earlier reports said that Bestfoods had approached Diageo, another global food maker.</p>
        <p>Those efforts appear to have been part of a strategy to coax a better offer out of Unilever, which was, in the end, the only company that bid on Bestfoods. ''The management team did an excellent job getting the price that I think is right for the value of the company, especially at a time when food stocks have been out of favor,'' said Alexi Makkas, a principal equity analyst for State Street Global Advisors in Boston, which owns 5.7 million shares of Bestfoods.</p>
        <p>State Street also holds 8.2 million shares of Unilever, and Mr. Makkas said he was pleased with the deal from that point of view, too. ''This adds a potent lineup to what Unilever has had to offer and at a decent price,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The two companies held their first talks on Friday, Mr. FitzGerald said. Unilever was represented by Goldman, Sachs and UBS Warburg, and by the law firm of Cravath, Swaine &amp; Moore. Bestfoods' advisers were Merrill Lynch and Salomon Smith Barney, as well as the law firm of Fried, Frank, Harris, Shriver &amp; Jacobson.</p>
        <p>After Unilever raised its offer, the  Bestfoods board met Monday night for several hours and then resumed meeting early yesterday morning. It approved the deal about 10 a.m., Ms. Griffin said. ''The deal really did come together this morning,'' said one person close to the talks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shoemate addressed the issue of increasing shareholder pressure yesterday. ''We all live in this world of shareholder relationships and shareholder interests,'' he said. ''We have a dedication to doing the very best for our shareholders.''</p>
        <p>When asked about Mr. Shoemate's future role at the company, Mr. Burgmans said: ''For now he will have the role we all have, to make sure we bring these two terrific businesses together and get the management going in the right direction to fulfill the plans we have for the businesses. He will in due course come to his own conclusions.''</p>
        <p>The companies expect the deal to close in the fourth quarter of this year. Though Bestfoods shareholders will receive $73 in cash for each share, the stock of Bestfoods rose yesterday by only $6.1875, to $69.1875,  a slight discount that Mr. McMillin said reflected the uncertainty and the time needed to gain approvals. Before Unilever expressed interest in the company, Bestfoods' stock was languishing at $46.</p>
        <p>Unilever will also assume $4 billion in Bestfoods' debt, including about $262 million that was assumed by Bestfoods in February when it acquired Arisco, a Brazilian food maker.</p>
        <p>The acquisition is part of a bigger plan at Unilever to bolster a sagging stock price and deliver sales growth. In February, the company said it would cut 10 percent of its work force and shed more than 1,000 poorly performing brands to concentrate on its best products.</p>
        <p>Then in April, Unilever agreed to acquire Ben &amp; Jerry's Homemade for $326 million and Slim-Fast, the diet food company, for $2.6 billion. At the time, Mr. Burgmans said the additions were intended to fill gaps in Unilever's food lineup. Neither of those product lines has been marketed heavily abroad.</p>
        <p>Unilever's executives said the deal for Bestfoods came together in the end because the two companies were so similar. ''The strategic case was absolutely compelling,'' Mr. Burgmans said. ''It had to happen.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
