<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.O.P. Platform Chief Says Abortion Language Will Stand</title>
    <meta content="Y07ABO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205482"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toner, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Tommy G (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cullman, Susan R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E5DB153FF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.O.P. Platform Chief Says Abortion Language Will Stand</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Toner, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican Party platform committee chairman Gov Tommy G Thompson of Wisconsin tells party activists who support abortion rights that Republican leaders plan no change in platform's strong anti-abortion language and no public hearings on issue before July convention in Philadelphia; Republican Pro-Choice Coalition co-chairman Susan Cullman, who met with Thompson, remains optimistic but says organization must make sure public gets involved in process and in touch with delegates; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The chairman of the Republican Party's platform committee has told party activists who support abortion rights that Republican leaders plan no change in the platform's strong anti-abortion language and no public hearings on the issue before the July convention in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Still, Susan Cullman, co-chairwoman of the Republican Pro-Choice Coalition, said she was encouraged by the friendly tone of a meeting on Monday in Madison, Wis., with Gov. Tommy G. Thompson of Wisconsin, the platform chairman, who promised them ample private opportunities to air their views.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The chairman of the Republican Party's platform committee has told party activists who support abortion rights that Republican leaders plan no change in the platform's strong anti-abortion language and no public hearings on the issue before the July convention in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Still, Susan Cullman, co-chairwoman of the Republican Pro-Choice Coalition, said she was encouraged by the friendly tone of a meeting on Monday in Madison, Wis., with Gov. Tommy G. Thompson of Wisconsin, the platform chairman, who promised them ample private opportunities to air their views.</p>
        <p>''This is the beginning of the process,'' Ms. Cullman added.</p>
        <p>In fact, the meeting suggested that the quadrennial wrangling over the party's abortion platform is starting anew, but will be decidedly muted, if Republican leaders have their way.</p>
        <p>Rather than formal public hearings, Republicans plan two ''policy forums'' later this month for platform committee leaders to hear expert testimony on several issues, including Social Security, education and health care. Abortion will not be covered, the Republican advocates of abortion rights were told, but Mr. Thompson said their views would be welcomed in private discussions with members of the platform committee, which some advocates said they considered an encouraging sign.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cullman said: ''We certainly feel better than we did in '92 or '96, in that we're at least talking to people involved in the process. Then, we were totally stonewalled out of the process. It's true, these are small victories, but they're not unimportant.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Cullman added of Mr. Thompson, ''He's made it very clear there's no indication that the platform is going to change, which says to us we'll have to make sure the public gets involved in the process, gets in touch with the delegates.''</p>
        <p>Kevin Keane, a Thompson spokesman, said, ''He did express that we've gotten clear direction from the R.N.C. that the plank is going to stay the same.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Keane characterized the meeting as ''very good'' and ''very open,'' part of a series of meetings Mr. Thompson is holding to solicit views.  He met last month with Phyllis Schlafly, a staunch advocate of maintaining the abortion language.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson's message this week was not unexpected, in part because Gov. George W. Bush, the presumptive Republican presidential nominee, has repeatedly said that he wants no changes in the platform language on abortion. That plank calls for the outlawing of abortion, without exceptions, and the appointment of judges ''who respect traditional family values and the sanctity of innocent human life.''</p>
        <p>Ari Fleischer, a campaign spokesman, said Mr. Bush ''views the platform as a grass-roots document reflecting the views of the party as a whole, and he does not seek to make any changes to the abortion language.'' Still, Mr. Bush has himself declined to embrace a litmus test for appointments to the court and has indicated he is considering supporters of abortion rights as potential running mates. And the governor's view on abortion, Mr. Fleischer said,  ''is pro-life, with the exception of rape, incest or if the life of the mother is at stake.''</p>
        <p>The effort by supporters of abortion rights to soften their party's platform has become a regular feature of Republican pre-convention politics. Party leaders routinely admonish those activists to think of the good of the party and its nominee, and avoid a bruising battle with the anti-abortion forces. Some abortion rights supporters said they expected that pressure to be particularly strong this year, with the party intent on ending an eight-year Democratic reign and with a nominee who has positioned himself so carefully in the center.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
