<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Assessing the Online Exchanges: From One Expert, a Mixed Grade</title>
    <meta content="07HANS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205349"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TO BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hansell, Saul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clemons, Eric K (Prof)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFD6133DF934A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1421" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Assessing the Online Exchanges: From One Expert, a Mixed Grade</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAUL HANSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hansell, Saul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Prof Eric K Clemons on boom in Internet business-to-business exchanges; he compares new industrial exchanges with earlier online financial exchanges and holds they are doomed to repeat many of same mistakes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE bull market has not just been on the stock exchange but in exchanges themselves. The frenzy to find business-to-business uses of the Internet is prompting people to create online exchanges where companies will be able to trade everything from sheet steel to hotel sheets.</p>
        <p>To Eric K. Clemons, a professor in the Information Strategy, Systems and Economics group at the Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania, this boom is reminiscent of the late 1980's, when a whole crop of online exchanges started to compete with the existing face-to-face stock exchanges and futures markets. Mr. Clemons has studied why as many of these markets failed as succeeded, and he has consulted for many of them, too.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE bull market has not just been on the stock exchange but in exchanges themselves. The frenzy to find business-to-business uses of the Internet is prompting people to create online exchanges where companies will be able to trade everything from sheet steel to hotel sheets.</p>
        <p>To Eric K. Clemons, a professor in the Information Strategy, Systems and Economics group at the Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania, this boom is reminiscent of the late 1980's, when a whole crop of online exchanges started to compete with the existing face-to-face stock exchanges and futures markets. Mr. Clemons has studied why as many of these markets failed as succeeded, and he has consulted for many of them, too.</p>
        <p>Now he's turning his attention to the new industrial markets and says that many of them are doomed to repeat the mistakes of their financial predecessors.</p>
        <p>He discussed the lessons from the financial markets in a series of e-mail messages last month.</p>
        <p>Q. Electronic trading exchanges first began opening in financial markets 15 years ago, amid great skepticism by traditional traders that they would work. Remind us, what happened?</p>
        <p>A. Many markets moved partially to electronic form faster than people had expected. Back in September of 1986, just before London's Big Bang [the deregulation of its financial markets], you will remember, many of the large houses expected the floor to continue to hold a dominant share of equities trading. Five minutes into the first day's trading, the floor was empty.</p>
        <p>London still uses intermediaries -- market makers who buy from every seller and sell to every buyer. Like most markets, London has been unwilling to take the next step, in which computers match buyers and sellers directly.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, stock and futures markets in France and Germany have moved more completely to fully electronic systems without intermediaries and have been enormously successful.</p>
        <p>In the United States, the New York Stock Exchange has continued to rely on an active face-to-face trading floor. And Globex and other electronic futures exchanges have had very little impact.</p>
        <p>Q. So why did some electronic exchanges work and others not?</p>
        <p>A. I guess the biggest difference between success and failure continues to be liquidity. When there are enough buyers and sellers to determine an effective price, then online trading can occur. If buyers and sellers are widely separated in time, and if there is little information on ''comparables'' to help buyers or sellers determine fair prices, then intermediaries will continue to serve an essential function. Thus, I would not expect to see real estate agents disappear anytime soon.</p>
        <p>Similarly, exchanges didn't help instruments that no one understands, or no one wants to trade, such as contracts tied to hurricanes in Florida or the cost of cellular air time in August in Midtown Manhattan or other forms of catastrophic risk.</p>
        <p>Q. But online exchanges also failed in the United States in some very liquid markets like futures.</p>
        <p>A. It's hard to get market participants to leave a structure that's liquid and working well, even if it is not working perfectly. Thus, online trading has captured markets abroad where there had been no previous exchange or where the existing stock market had been less efficient and more expensive than its U.S. equivalents. Online trading in the U.S. continues principally to provide lower-cost access to existing exchanges, rather than replacing these existing exchanges, in general because they have been doing such a good job.</p>
        <p>Q. So what sort of industrial markets will be most suited to online exchanges?</p>
        <p>A. The invisible hand of the marketplace does the best job when buyers and sellers are fragmented and thousands of small orders interact simultaneously. This is true whether I want to buy 1,000 shares of I.B.M. at the current price on a stock exchange or if I want to buy 1,000 standard memory chips in one of the emerging industrial exchanges. The guiding principle here is that the random flow of small orders is sufficient to assure that the market finds the right price.</p>
        <p>Q. What's an example of an industry that meets the test to find the right price?</p>
        <p>A. Game fish, like sashimi-grade toro or hamachi. They are not farmed, and production cannot be fully predicted or matched to current demand. Likewise it cannot be stored for long. An exchange that found regional market clearing prices, let buyers throughout Asia bid on fish available in Tokyo or allowed buyers throughout the East Coast to bid on the regional catch would allow supply and demand to determine a market clearing price. Sellers would get a better price, through aggregation of demand. Buyers would have access to greater supply, again through aggregation. There would be less waste.</p>
        <p>Q. So what about the proposed exchanges in industries like auto parts, where there are a handful of buyers and not all that many sellers of each type of item?</p>
        <p>A. If the order flow is heavily concentrated in a small number of buyers or a small number of sellers, or if delivery must be carefully coordinated and scheduled between buyer and seller, then an exchange is likely to be less effective.</p>
        <p>If I need several million fuel injectors or pistons, an exchange-based market will not be my best alternative. If my pistons arrive too late, my production line will shut down. In business environments such as these, I will want to carefully negotiate order quantities and delivery schedules, quality levels and purchase prices.</p>
        <p>Q. Even in those industries, proponents say, online exchanges are a great way to unload excess inventory.</p>
        <p>A. I'm not so sure excess inventory is still such a great idea. I recently studied exchanges in the glass industry. Excess production is indeed sold through exchanges, but at prices only slightly better than the pre-exchange mechanism for liquidating overproduction, which was to grind glass down and remelt and reuse it.</p>
        <p>But the new exchange causes a secondary problem: it floods the market with cheap glass, and thus depresses the prices of primary production runs.</p>
        <p>Selling overproduction through an exchange is seldom as cost-effective as properly planning production.</p>
        <p>Q. A lot of people say the real value of the exchanges in the long run won't be the lower transaction costs or even the lower prices, but the efficiencies throughout the production stream that would flow from the instant -- universal, transparent demand information being shared. I take it you don't completely agree.</p>
        <p>A. That's right. For some industries full transparency will indeed produce allocative efficiency -- by setting the right prices, based on aggregating supply and demand, the product will end up in the hands of the customers who value it most highly. In industries with rapidly evolving products -- personal computers -- this might indeed be a new and optimal design.</p>
        <p>In these cases the key issue is not determining the right price, but scheduling delivery of the right quantity at the right time.  Ford or G.M. might be more concerned with assuring that spark plugs and fuel injectors arrive in the right-sized batches at precisely the right times to avoid disrupting their assembly lines; getting the right quantity of products at the right time is closer to traditional supply-chain optimization than it is to the design of trading mechanisms.</p>
        <p>Q. Some people argue that one benefit of these new exchanges is that they open up world markets, allowing a small steel maker in Thailand to find a buyer in Peru. Does that make sense?</p>
        <p>A. Globalization of markets and exchanges, likewise, will be important only if buyers and sellers have a real need for global access. But when they do, geographical separation appears to be no longer relevant as a barrier to trading, as long as the item's description is clear enough to be described online without too much ambiguity, and its value is sufficient to justify shipping costs. I will admit that the online trading of Beanie Babies through eBay caught me pretty much by surprise.</p>
        <p>Q. Will we see these industrial exchanges come to resemble the futures pits in Chicago where investors could hedge piston prices or speculate in spark plugs?</p>
        <p>A. Actually, I am quite convinced that they will. You will see forwards, for physical delivery, tradeable commodity-style physical-settlement futures contracts to lock in supply, and cash-settlement contracts to lock in a price. You will see speculators, regulators and all the infrastructure you currently see in futures markets.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS TO BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
