<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E*Trade and Wit Capital Join to Face Off-Line Rivals</title>
    <meta content="Y16WAL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Etrade Group Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wit Capital Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">E-Offering</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Epoch Capital Partners</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Schwab, Charles, Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Td Waterhouse Group Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ameritrade Holding Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EFDA113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E*Trade and Wit Capital Join to Face Off-Line Rivals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>ETrade Group and Wit Capital Group say they will team up to compete against their off-line rivals; ETrade will form alliance with Wit Capital after online investment bank acquires E-Offering, competitor that ETrade helped to finance a year ago; deal coincides with arrival of potentially formdiable competitor: online investment bank in San Francisco that is being developed by Epoch Capital Partners with backing of Charles Schwab Corp and electronic brokerage firms, TD Waterhouse and Ameritrade Holding Corp (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Acknowledging how hard it has been to break the stranglehold Wall Street has on the underwriting of new stocks, two online financial services companies, the E*Trade Group and the Wit Capital Group, said yesterday that they would team up to compete against their off-line rivals.</p>
        <p>E*Trade, a leading electronic brokerage firm, said it would form an alliance with Wit Capital after that online investment bank acquires E-*Offering, a competitor that E*Trade helped to finance a year ago. Wit Capital, which started out as a boutique brewery in Manhattan's SoHo district, said it would issue stock worth $328 million to the shareholders of E*Offering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Acknowledging how hard it has been to break the stranglehold Wall Street has on the underwriting of new stocks, two online financial services companies, the E*Trade Group and the Wit Capital Group, said yesterday that they would team up to compete against their off-line rivals.</p>
        <p>E*Trade, a leading electronic brokerage firm, said it would form an alliance with Wit Capital after that online investment bank acquires E-*Offering, a competitor that E*Trade helped to finance a year ago. Wit Capital, which started out as a boutique brewery in Manhattan's SoHo district, said it would issue stock worth $328 million to the shareholders of E*Offering.</p>
        <p>The deal coincides with the arrival of a potentially formidable competitor: an online investment bank in San Francisco that is being developed by Epoch Capital Partners with backing from the Charles Schwab  Corporation and two other electronic brokerage firms, TD Waterhouse and the Ameritrade Holding Corporation.</p>
        <p>Under terms of the alliance, E*Trade and Wit will form a mutually exclusive relationship, with Wit as the sole provider of stock research, initial public offerings and other new issues of stock to E*Trade's 2.6 million customers. E*Trade expects to record a gain of about $50 million on its investment in E*Offering, a money-losing venture that has had trouble building a stable management team.</p>
        <p>Christos Cotsakos, the cheerleading chairman and chief executive of E*Trade, said that the alliance would create ''a category killer in the online financial services space.'' But some analysts were less excited, characterizing the deal as a trade-off that will allow each firm to concentrate on its core business.</p>
        <p>Analysts and competitors said that the deal demonstrated the difficulty of building an investment banking operation from scratch. Some saw it as a signal of more consolidation among online financial companies that are too small to compete effectively.</p>
        <p>''It's an admission that it is very, very difficult to move up'' the ranks of underwriters, said Richard Repetto, an analyst at Lehman Brothers Holdings. ''Wit and E*Offering were in a number of deals, but they weren't the lead managers.''</p>
        <p>The role of lead manager of an initial public offering is the most coveted on Wall Street. Those deals carry the biggest fees for investment bankers, as much as 7 percent of the amount of money raised from investors. But the firms chosen by corporations as lead underwriters keep most of that money for themselves.</p>
        <p>Online investment banks have tried to persuade technology companies to hire them for their expertise in distributing shares over the Internet and for the technological savvy of their customers. But most of the recent crop of Internet companies to go public have followed the beaten path to Wall Street and chosen the likes of the Goldman Sachs Group and Morgan Stanley Dean Witter &amp; Company to manage their offerings.</p>
        <p>E*Offering, whose other owners include the venture capital firms General Atlantic Partners, Softbank Venture Capital and Battery Ventures, had revenue of just $20 million last quarter and expects to lose about $10 million in its current fiscal year. Faced with the prospect of continuing losses if the market for new stocks remains depressed, some of those investors approached Wit Capital management about a deal a few weeks ago, people close to Wit said.</p>
        <p>The deal gives E*Trade significant say in the operation of Wit, which has about 100,000 customers. E*Trade will have a stake of about 7 percent in Wit and Mr. Cotsakos and a partner in General Atlantic will have seats on Wit's board. E*Trade will also gain access to a set of products that none of its competitors can offer.</p>
        <p>The deal has benefits for Wit, too, analysts said. ''They basically were able to eliminate a competitor from the marketplace,'' said Amy Butte, an analyst with the Bear Stearns Companies.</p>
        <p>It will also weaken a competitive advantage Epoch Capital Partners had been citing to potential clients. ''Epoch's pitch to issuers against Wit Capital was that Wit had only 100,000 accounts versus Epoch's millions'' through Schwab, Waterhouse and Ameritrade, Ms. Butte said.</p>
        <p>All of those firms and their online competitors have been scrapping for bigger pieces of stock offerings, especially initial offerings. That has not changed, despite the wilting market for new stocks, said Suzanne Richardson, president of Fbr.com, the online arm of the investment banking firm Friedman, Billings, Ramsey Group.</p>
        <p>''Online investors are primarily interested in I.P.O.'s,'' she said. ''But that's going to change. We will start to see online investors as opposed to online traders.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Richardson said the deal would most likely lead more established investment banks to make acquisitions or form alliances that will give them access to an online distribution channel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
