<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AOL Pays a Fine to Settle a Charge That It Inflated Profits</title>
    <meta content="Y16SEC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">America Online Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1DE113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="640" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AOL Pays a Fine to Settle a Charge That It Inflated Profits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>America Online Inc agrees to pay fine of $3.5 million and to restate its books from 1995 and 1996 after Securities and Exchange Commission charged that company improperly inflated profits by hundreds of millions of dollars; America Online neither admits nor denies wrongdoing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>America Online Inc. agreed to pay a fine of $3.5 million and to restate its books from 1995 and 1996 yesterday after the Securities and Exchange Commission charged that the company had improperly inflated profits by hundreds of millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>The settlement, in which America Online neither admitted nor denied wrongdoing, recalls a time -- less than four years ago -- when the company's very survival seemed to be in question. That is a far cry from now, when it is viewed as an Internet powerhouse and is in the process of acquiring Time Warner, a far larger company in terms of revenue but one that is viewed by investors as being worth less than AOL.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>America Online Inc. agreed to pay a fine of $3.5 million and to restate its books from 1995 and 1996 yesterday after the Securities and Exchange Commission charged that the company had improperly inflated profits by hundreds of millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>The settlement, in which America Online neither admitted nor denied wrongdoing, recalls a time -- less than four years ago -- when the company's very survival seemed to be in question. That is a far cry from now, when it is viewed as an Internet powerhouse and is in the process of acquiring Time Warner, a far larger company in terms of revenue but one that is viewed by investors as being worth less than AOL.</p>
        <p>For America Online, which stopped using the disputed accounting method in 1996, the settlement is probably of minimal import now. But the settlement nonetheless could have an impact on other companies in young and rapidly changing industries because the commission's position will force them to deduct all promotional expenses from earnings immediately.</p>
        <p>Thomas Newkirk, the associate director of the commission's enforcement division, said the action was an indication ''of how important we view accounting games, particularly in the dot-com area.'' He noted that many Internet companies were spending large sums for promotion and added, ''there is a suspicion that some of those expenses may not be properly accounted for.''</p>
        <p>Richard Walker, the commission's director of enforcement, said it was trying to ensure that financial reports of technology companies ''reflect present reality, not hopes about the future.''</p>
        <p>The specific issue in the AOL case concerned an accounting rule adopted in 1995 that carved out a small exception from the rule that advertising and promotional costs must be expensed -- that is, deducted from profits -- when they are incurred. The exception, the S.E.C. said, allowed the capitalization of direct-response advertising costs ''only when persuasive historical evidence exists that allows the entity to reliably predict future net revenues that will be obtained as a result of the advertising.''</p>
        <p>America Online had a model to make such forecasts, but the S.E.C. concluded it was unreliable because AOL's business was growing and changing so rapidly. ''To meet the requirements,'' the commission said, ''an entity must operate in a sufficiently stable business environment that the historical evidence upon which it bases its recoverability analysis is relevant and reliable.''</p>
        <p>AOL had grown rapidly during the period covered by the S.E.C. action, with the share price rising as the company was able to report profits. But in October 1996, the company abruptly changed accounting policies and wrote off $385 million in deferred marketing costs. That write-off wiped out all the profits the company had previously reported. It came after AOL's stock price had fallen 65 percent in five months, on concerns about increased competition.</p>
        <p>The reality, however, turned out to be that America Online's spending to get new customers had been wise, and enough of those customers have proved loyal to the company to make it easily the largest supplier of Internet access in the country.</p>
        <p>The company's stock is now trading at 38 times what it was when the new accounting policy was announced, having split four times since then. Yesterday the stock rose $3.25, to $58.50.</p>
        <p>America Online said it would restate its books to remove the $385 million write-off and instead apportion those costs during the earlier periods when they were incurred.</p>
        <p>There was no explanation from the S.E.C. or the company as to why the settlement came so long after the facts were known. But it appeared that the company had resisted a settlement and gave in only after it became clear that the S.E.C. would bring a case anyway.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
