<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Four A's gather in Bermuda, are visited by the striking actors, and weigh dot-com clients.</title>
    <meta content="Y16ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Assn of Advertising Agencies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EEDF113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Four A's gather in Bermuda, are visited by the striking actors, and weigh dot-com clients.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on some of highlights, lowlights and sidelights of 2000 management conference of American Association of Advertising Agencies, held last week in Southampton, Bermuda (Advertising column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HERE is a look at some of the highlights, lowlights and sidelights of the 2000 management conference of the American Association of Advertising Agencies, held last week in Southampton, Bermuda:</p>
        <p>SOLIDARITY FOREVER? -- A last-minute addition to the agenda of the conference was a presentation on the two-week-old strike against the association, known as the Four A's, and its counterpart, the Association of National Advertisers, by two unions that represent commercial actors, the Screen Actors Guild and the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HERE is a look at some of the highlights, lowlights and sidelights of the 2000 management conference of the American Association of Advertising Agencies, held last week in Southampton, Bermuda:</p>
        <p>SOLIDARITY FOREVER? -- A last-minute addition to the agenda of the conference was a presentation on the two-week-old strike against the association, known as the Four A's, and its counterpart, the Association of National Advertisers, by two unions that represent commercial actors, the Screen Actors Guild and the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists.</p>
        <p>Ira Shepard, counsel to the committee of the two associations negotiating with the unions, began his upbeat assessment of the strike from the management perspective with this quotation from an editorial in The Wall Street Journal on May 2, the day after the strike began: ''When the Screen Actors Guild is striking, the joke goes, you can't find a waiter.'' The audience laughed.</p>
        <p>But the unions struck back, so to speak, by finding a way to make their presence felt directly by the conference attendees, who are top executives at the agencies that produce the commercials in which the actors appear. On Friday night, a tugboat loudly blowing its horn followed the ships taking the attendees to a dinner at the Royal Navy Dockyard. Attached to the side of the tugboat was a large sign with a message urging a ''fair contract for S.A.G./A.F.T.R.A.''</p>
        <p>And later, when the attendees returned to their rooms at the Fairmont Southampton Princess hotel, they found under their doors a leaflet listing dozens of striking members of the unions. The list appeared under this headline: ''Just a short list of talent that advertising agencies will not be delivering to their clients'' until the strike is settled.</p>
        <p>NAME THAT PRODUCT -- The members of the Four A's are always paying attention to brand names because most advertisers hire them to promote those products. For instance, at a reception sponsored by executives of TBWA Worldwide, part of the Omnicom Group, the liquors served were Absolut vodka and other brands marketed by a big TBWA client, the Seagram Company.</p>
        <p>The conference, however, was the first to be held in Bermuda and exposed attendees to some brands they rarely see. The Esso brand, which long ago became Exxon in the United States, is still in use at gasoline stations around the island. Among the other unfamiliar names were: Cadbury Crunchie candy bars, the Daihatsu Applause, Humpty Dumpty potato chips, Lantic sugar, Outerbridge's Original Sherry Rum Peppers Sauce and the Toyota Lite Ace.</p>
        <p>Attendees already seemed to have some familiarity with one brand from Bermuda: Gosling's Black Seal rum. There was also an automobile that ought to become a favorite among agency creative executives hoping to win more awards: the Renault Clio.</p>
        <p>IS 'ICON' SHORT FOR 'ICONOCLASTIC'? -- There was some lively discussion during a panel that was part of the general session on Friday, devoted to the ''new, young icons'' among creative executives at smaller agencies.</p>
        <p>At one point, the moderator, Andrew Jaffe, executive director at the Clio Awards, part of VNU USA, asked the panelists to discuss agencies that form stand-alone interactive advertising operations. He gave as an example iDeutsch, the interactive unit of Deutsch Inc. in New York.</p>
        <p>''Is iDeutsch a site about Donny?'' asked Alex Bogusky, vice chairman and creative director at Crispin Porter &amp; Bogusky in Miami, referring to Donny Deutsch, the larger-than-life chief executive at Deutsch. ''Is it all about Donny?''</p>
        <p>SPILL THE WINE -- At another panel on Friday about creativity, Ken Mandelbaum, chief creative officer at BBDO West in Los Angeles and San Francisco, part of the BBDO Worldwide unit of Omnicom, was asked to discuss trends on the West Coast, where many clients are dot-coms.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mandelbaum said he had been compiling a reel of the best commercials of the 1980's created by West Coast agencies, which were ''all for wine coolers.''</p>
        <p>''The parallels are terrifying,'' he added as the audience laughed. ''We all know what happened to the wine cooler industry.''</p>
        <p>BY THE NUMBERS -- For decades, the Four A's conference held in the spring was known as the annual meeting. In recent years, as the format was changed to focus on topics of interest to agency managers -- and conferences were added to appeal to media and creative executives -- that description was modified. First the event was called the management conference and annual meeting, then the words ''annual meeting'' were dropped.</p>
        <p>With that change, the venerable association also eliminated almost all references to the conference's place in Four A's history. So for those of you at home who keep track of such things, it was the 82nd annual meeting.</p>
        <p>COINING A PHRASE -- All during the conference, attendees were closely following the developments in London and New York as Sir Martin Sorrell, chief executive at the WPP Group, finally reached an agreement to acquire Young &amp; Rubicam Inc. after weeks of off-again-on-again negotiations centered on honing the financial terms of the deal. That provided fodder for several speakers, including Philip B. Dusenberry, chairman of BBDO New York, part of the BBDO Worldwide unit of Omnicom.</p>
        <p>Attendees enjoyed watching Bermudians ''diving for coins,'' Mr. Dusenberry said in a speech on Saturday after he formally became the 2000-2001 chairman of the Four A's, ''and watching Martin Sorrell trying to take the coins away from them.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
