<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Affairs; Complete And Utter Nonsense</title>
    <meta content="16FRIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199938"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">China-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Trade Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Thomas L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E1D8113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Affairs; Complete And Utter Nonsense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Thomas L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas L Friedman's Op-Ed column derides opposition of labor movement, notably AFL-CIO, to China's entry into World Trade Organization (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During a visit to Shanghai last year my Times colleague Seth Faison and I interviewed the top managers of one of China's largest food companies, which had been partially privatized. While Seth interviewed the Chinese executives in Chinese, I leafed through the company's annual report. On the first page there were four pictures: the chairman, the vice chairman, the general manager and ''the Communist Party representative'' to the company. At one point I interrupted Seth's interview, pointed to the picture of the Communist Party rep and asked our Chinese hosts: ''Say, what does this guy do?'' They waved at the picture with disdain, as if to say: ''He doesn't do anything. Just ignore him.''</p>
        <p>That encounter always stuck in my mind because it illustrated one of the political implications of the rise of the private, free-market economy in China. When managers and workers, students and intellectuals are no longer totally dependent on the state or the Communist Party for jobs, they are much more likely to speak their own mind and act on their own interests. That is a fact worth remembering as the U.S. Congress now debates whether to grant China permanent normal trade relations with America.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During a visit to Shanghai last year my Times colleague Seth Faison and I interviewed the top managers of one of China's largest food companies, which had been partially privatized. While Seth interviewed the Chinese executives in Chinese, I leafed through the company's annual report. On the first page there were four pictures: the chairman, the vice chairman, the general manager and ''the Communist Party representative'' to the company. At one point I interrupted Seth's interview, pointed to the picture of the Communist Party rep and asked our Chinese hosts: ''Say, what does this guy do?'' They waved at the picture with disdain, as if to say: ''He doesn't do anything. Just ignore him.''</p>
        <p>That encounter always stuck in my mind because it illustrated one of the political implications of the rise of the private, free-market economy in China. When managers and workers, students and intellectuals are no longer totally dependent on the state or the Communist Party for jobs, they are much more likely to speak their own mind and act on their own interests. That is a fact worth remembering as the U.S. Congress now debates whether to grant China permanent normal trade relations with America.</p>
        <p>To be sure, the claims by some Clintonites or business types that trade will lead inexorably to democracy in China are exaggerated and too deterministic. But even more ridiculous is the claim by John Sweeney, head of the A.F.L.-C.I.O., that ''there is no information showing that China is improving its human rights situation or workers rights situation,'' and thus no reason to support permanent normalized trade ties with China.</p>
        <p>As any regular visitor to China can see (unfortunately the U.S. unions have been discouraging members of Congress from visiting China and seeing for themselves), there is ample evidence that the strengthening of private enterprises and free markets in China, and the surge in Internet usage there, is creating the space and private incomes for more Chinese to live independent of the government and thereby expand their personal freedoms. And the more Chinese can live without the state, the more the democrats among them can afford to speak their minds and the more other Chinese can afford to listen.</p>
        <p>Read Elisabeth Rosenthal's May 8 front-page piece from Beijing in this newspaper. It details the messy reality of today's China, where the leadership, terrified about the political fallout from China's joining the World Trade Organization, is cracking down -- and will continue to do so -- at the same time that Chinese liberals are becoming more self-confident and willing to challenge the state.</p>
        <p>''In the China of today,'' writes Ms. Rosenthal, a Times Beijing reporter, ''threats from the central authorities have diminished influence. Bookstores are still filled with provocative books. And people fired from government institutes can now often find a way to make a living in the expanding private sector. . . . Even as Chinese intellectuals bemoan the current climate, they feel more inconvenienced than terrified by the government's wrath. 'The methods are pretty much the same as in Deng Xiaoping's and even Mao's time,' [a] professor said. 'What's different is that nobody pays attention anymore. . . . Intellectuals don't feel that much pressure.' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Rosenthal also notes that several recent devastating critiques of China's rulers, and disclosures about corruption in the Communist Party, have been circulated first on the Internet in China, and the Chinese leadership has been powerless to stop it. The China trade pact Congress is currently debating greatly enhances the ability of U.S. companies to invest in Internet development in China.</p>
        <p>The truth is the A.F.L.-C.I.O. couldn't care less about political change in China. That is just a cover for their head-in-the-sand protectionism. China could become a democratic paradise tomorrow and Mr. Sweeney and his union would still oppose this trade bill, because they see it (wrongly) as just a vehicle to move U.S. manufacturing jobs to China.</p>
        <p>The A.F.L.-C.I.O. is free to argue that this bill will hurt U.S. workers. Republican hard-liners are free to argue that China's entry into the W.T.O. will make it a more formidable geopolitical rival to the U.S. But for either of them to say that this bill will hurt the cause of democratization in China, or that it won't help create more islands from which Chinese democrats can operate and more tools by which they can communicate, is to speak utter nonsense, and, one hopes, a majority of Congress will see it as such.</p>
        <p>Gail Collins is on vacation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gail Collins is on vacation.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
