<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hardaway Will Start Despite Foot Sprain</title>
    <meta content="16HEAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199907"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hardaway, Tim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riley, Pat</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nobles, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DA113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hardaway Will Start Despite Foot Sprain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nobles, Charlie</byline>
      <dateline>COCONUT GROVE, Fla., May 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Point guard Tim Hardaway says he will start for Miami Heat in playoff game against Knicks despite injury; Heat coach Pat Riley lauds him; rejects concerns that he might be hindering team (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Slowed by a sprain in his left foot, point guard Tim Hardaway fielded suggestions after the Miami Heat's loss to the Knicks on Sunday that he might be hindering his team. Today, after meeting with Coach Pat Riley, Hardaway announced that he would start Wednesday night in Game 5 of the four-of-seven-game series at American Airlines Arena.</p>
        <p>The 11th-year pro, who has made just 8 of 30 field-goal attempts and has been a defensive liability in the series, would not discuss what happened in his meeting with Riley. But that was not necessary; earlier, Riley had given the news media an earful about Hardaway's worth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Slowed by a sprain in his left foot, point guard Tim Hardaway fielded suggestions after the Miami Heat's loss to the Knicks on Sunday that he might be hindering his team. Today, after meeting with Coach Pat Riley, Hardaway announced that he would start Wednesday night in Game 5 of the four-of-seven-game series at American Airlines Arena.</p>
        <p>The 11th-year pro, who has made just 8 of 30 field-goal attempts and has been a defensive liability in the series, would not discuss what happened in his meeting with Riley. But that was not necessary; earlier, Riley had given the news media an earful about Hardaway's worth.</p>
        <p>''Tim is absolutely playing as courageously as he can and despite what people say, he has been a positive for us,'' Riley said. ''He struggled in the third quarter a little bit yesterday, but we need him. We need his heart, we need his savvy.''</p>
        <p>The more Riley talked, the more upset he became about the pointed questions directed at Hardaway after the Knicks tied the series at two games each.</p>
        <p>''I can't believe anyone's going to go after him and start putting him on the burner,'' Riley said. ''Tim has given everything he can give. I don't think his presence out on that court ever hurts our team. I know guys who would have packed up and left for the summer and people would accuse them of being cowards, right? Tim is just the opposite.''</p>
        <p>Even so, Riley kept Hardaway on the bench in the fourth quarter Sunday, the second consecutive game in which Riley has opted for the quick rookie Anthony Carter down the stretch. But that absolved Hardaway of blame in the Heat's collapse, in the coach's view.</p>
        <p>''He wasn't on the court and he didn't make nine turnovers and he didn't miss four free throws and he did what he had to do to give us an opportunity to win the game,'' Riley said. ''So I wouldn't be pointing a finger at Tim Hardaway. That's totally unfair.''</p>
        <p>Riley did acknowledge, though, that Miami was ''working our way around'' Hardaway's limitations.</p>
        <p>Power forward P. J. Brown said it had become apparent early in the game Sunday that the Knicks' game plan involved attacking Hardaway with Charlie Ward and Chris Childs. Ward finished with 20 points; Childs had 3.</p>
        <p>''They're going after him, and trying to take advantage,'' Brown said. ''All of us have to be held accountable in helping out.''</p>
        <p>The Heat is sticking with Hardaway in large part because of his leadership and his long-range shooting.</p>
        <p>''He can't break defenses down or do the things he's used to doing or wants to do, but he's still directing the team,'' Brown said. ''The Knicks still rotate to him because his 3-pointer is still deadly.''</p>
        <p>Hardaway cut off questions today about his injury, incurred late in the regular season. ''Yes, I'm going to play on Wednesday,'' he said. ''Everybody knows I'm hurt. It's not going to get better until after I'm through playing. That's it.''</p>
        <p>He acknowledged that he was upset by reporters' questions on Sunday and noted that Riley's defense of him made it easier for him to turn the page. ''It's always good for him to blow up instead of me,'' Hardaway said, ''because I say some outlandish things.''</p>
        <p>The light atmosphere produced by that remark was fleeting. Hardaway's face tightened when someone asked about Ward's elusiveness on Sunday.</p>
        <p>''I've got to deal with all these questions now,'' he said, walking off. ''If I was 100 percent, we wouldn't be talking about that.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>After watching the videotape of Game 4 on Monday, center ALONZO MOURNING and backup point guard ANTHONY CARTER were allowed to leave early because of flu-like symptoms.  Coach PAT RILEY of Miami said he felt ''disgusted'' by the Heat's showing Sunday, which he said reminded him too much of the team's 6-point loss in Game 2. ''Everything was exactly the same,'' Riley said, ''and that's disconcerting to me. I'm not even going to try to explain it anymore. I'm not even going to try to teach it anymore. But I'll start coaching again tomorrow and then I'll coach on Wednesday.'' . . . Riley expressed no surprise at CHARLIE WARD's performance Sunday for the Knicks, calling him a ''consummate, above and beyond'' example of professionalism. ''They should make a mold of him and send it to every kid who comes into the league as a rookie as to how to become a pro basketball player,'' Riley said. ''How to live your life. How to believe in your team, do your job. How to hustle. How to play a role.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
