<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pollution Victims Start to Fight Back in China</title>
    <meta content="16CHIN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenthal, Elisabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EEDA113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pollution Victims Start to Fight Back in China</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenthal, Elisabeth</byline>
      <dateline>HUAIROU, China</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Increasing number of Chinese farmers whose livelihoods have been destroyed by water pollution are fighting back with lawsuits seeking compensation; although China has enacted strict antipollution laws in past decade, enforcement is still lax in many places in country's whose rivers are among dirtiest in world; aggressive central government campaign to identify and punish polluters has made big difference in some cities and other places where it has focused, but has failed to penetrate fully vast rural areas, where laws are often ignored by local enterprises and officials; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The nadir of Zhang Jinhu's career occurred in the fall, when thousands of his ducks unsteadily waddled out of the nearby river with singed feathers and burned feet, became paralyzed and died.</p>
        <p>A prosperous farmer with a flock of 4,000 birds here on the northern outskirts of Beijing, Mr. Zhang had weathered the sporadic deaths of some ducks from caustic river water over the last few years. But he was not used to this sort of prolonged carnage, which culminated one day in September, when several hundred of his ducks died.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The nadir of Zhang Jinhu's career occurred in the fall, when thousands of his ducks unsteadily waddled out of the nearby river with singed feathers and burned feet, became paralyzed and died.</p>
        <p>A prosperous farmer with a flock of 4,000 birds here on the northern outskirts of Beijing, Mr. Zhang had weathered the sporadic deaths of some ducks from caustic river water over the last few years. But he was not used to this sort of prolonged carnage, which culminated one day in September, when several hundred of his ducks died.</p>
        <p>Frustrated, Mr. Zhang did what very few Chinese have done. He sued a business upstream for compensation, adding to a small but growing number of environmental suits by pollution victims that may become test cases.</p>
        <p>No one doubts that pollution in the sudsy green river killed the ducks. But in this relatively poor and extremely polluted country, there is often no simple remedy for the millions of people such as Mr. Zhang whose livelihoods have been destroyed by pollution. Though China has enacted strict antipollution laws in the last decade, enforcement is still lax in many places. Flagrant violations occur without so any serious investigation.</p>
        <p>After local government agencies gave him little satisfaction in the duck deaths, which he calculates cost him $12,000, Mr. Zhang turned to a new legal-aid center in Beijing.</p>
        <p>''The deputy chief of the local environmental protection bureau came and said they were powerless to correct it unless we could isolate the source of the pollution,'' Mr. Zhang said as he chain-smoked in the tin-roof shack that he built on the riverbank. He said he believed that he knew the culprit, chemicals from an upstream pig farm. ''But I'm just a farmer. How can I do that? There are lots of things that dump waste water into this river, mostly in the middle of the night.''</p>
        <p>Wang Canfa, who opened the legal-aid office, the Center for Legal Assistance to Pollution Victims, in the fall, said, ''China has many laws and regulations regarding the environment, but the situation just gets worse, because they are often not implemented.'' The legal-aid center, the first in China to focus on pollution, is affiliated with the Law and Politics University in Beijing.</p>
        <p>China's rivers are some of the dirtiest in the world. An aggressive central government campaign to identify and punish polluters has made a big difference in some cities and in other places where it has focused. But it has failed to penetrate fully the vast rural areas, where antipollution laws are often blithely ignored by local enterprises.</p>
        <p>The police are often reluctant to prosecute such businesses because they are cornerstones of local economies and, in many cases, are owned by local governments. Also, inquiries are often prohibitively expensive for local agencies and politically complicated, because the pollution sources may be in other jurisdictions.</p>
        <p>Those who suffer the most are often individuals who are frequently unaware of the hazards and their rights. ''They don't understand the law or how to go about getting the problem solved,'' Mr. Wang said. ''So polluters are not afraid, and they keep skirting the law.''</p>
        <p>For three months, the news media have reported many cases of serious unchecked water pollution. In central Anhui Province, a spill devastated fish along a 15-mile stretch of the Haozhouguo River, destroying the livelihoods of 179 families. In Leshan, Sichuan Province, extensive fish deaths along 135 miles of the Minjiang River followed a chemical spill. No suits have been filed and no compensation has been paid.</p>
        <p>Against that backdrop, the Center for Legal Assistance to Pollution Victims is receiving more than 100 calls a month, mostly from workers and farmers who have read the newspaper advertisements of the center. Mr. Zhang, the duck farmer who was among the first to call, said many farmers had been economically devastated by the river pollution that  peaked in fall. They complained but felt that they had little recourse.</p>
        <p>Contributing to the pollution has been a severe drought, which has lowered water levels, concentrating contaminants.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Zhang built his ramshackle complex of huts and pens, it was on a bank of a river 200 feet wide. Today, the river snakes a narrow winding path down the middle of a vast sandy bed. As a child, Mr. Zhang used to swim and bathe in the  river, a tributary of the Chaobai. Five years ago, he said, a fisherman could catch 300 pounds of fish a day. But in the last year, the fish and river grass have died. So do cows and pigs if they drink river water. ''If people go in, they get covered with scabs,'' Mr. Zhang said.</p>
        <p>In recent years, the Chinese government has acknowledged problems with law enforcement and has buttressed its inspection system, particularly along the seven major rivers. Nationwide, the enforcement division has grown rapidly, to its current 30,000 inspectors, with plans to expand to 40,000 or 50,000 by 2002. In 1998, 39,754 polluters were penalized, mostly through fines. In addition, the Environmental Protection Administration took 621 cases to court and obtained 579 convictions.</p>
        <p>''We've strengthened our enforcement to make sure they meet standards,'' the deputy director of the environmental inspection and supervision division in the administration, Chen Shanrong, said. ''We still have a long way to go.''</p>
        <p>Although such efforts have helped control industrial pollution in some places, they have often had little effect on situations like Mr. Zhang's, a disaster in a small river with local effects, where the suspected polluters are small companies that enjoy good relations with local officials.</p>
        <p>Under Chinese law, environmental protection is primarily the responsibility of local authorities, with the national administration providing just backup support. Mr. Chen acknowledged that there were ''local officials who, in order to follow their own interests, don't cooperate.''</p>
        <p>The fledgling pollution-control efforts have largely focused on industrial polluters, and government agencies are only starting to look at agricultural wastes like the chemicals that Mr. Zhang believes killed his ducks. Such chemicals can be harder to monitor, because they enter the water through seepage, not by obvious effluent pipes.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Zhang's ducks started dying, he unsuccessfully appealed to every local agency he thought might be inclined to help, the local government, the county environmental protection bureau and even the township women's organization. He carried duck carcasses to the local fish and wildlife office for autopsies.</p>
        <p>He and other farmers in the area have focused their attention on the pig farm, because ducks upstream had no problem in the fall, while ducks downstream died en masse.</p>
        <p>In response to Mr. Zhang's pleas, workers from the local environmental protection bureau arrived and tested the river water and found it highly alkaline. But they went no further in determining the nature of the pollution or its source.</p>
        <p>''We haven't even been able to figure out who owns the pig farm,'' Mr. Zhang said. ''I don't think anyone investigated really.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wang, the lawyer, said that the farm was partly owned by the government of an upstream village and that the Huairou environmental protection bureau had ''taken up some, but not all'' the issues.</p>
        <p>It is highly unlikely to do more without further pressure, he said, adding: ''Local businesses pay taxes and are big employers. So local governments need them and are reluctant to close them down.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wang has great hope that suits like Mr. Zhang's will change that, creating incentives to fight pollution. ''If they knew that victims might claim compensation, that would bring huge pressure on polluters, who would have to start paying a price for their actions,'' Mr. Wang said.</p>
        <p>Still, he added, it would be a hard battle, because such suits are relatively new in China. Mr. Zhang's case will be first heard in a local court here. But it can be appealed to a higher court in Beijing. For now, Mr. Zhang's neighbors who lost ducks are watching and say they will file their own suits if he succeeds. Mr. Zhang is not holding his breath.</p>
        <p>''I've sold the 200 ducks that remained,'' he said, wandering through empty pens to a smelly shack fitted with floor-to-ceiling cages, home to his new bird business. ''I've switched to quails,'' he said. ''It's safer. They never go near water.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
