<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Study Offers Grim Prognosis for Lasting Peace in Balkans</title>
    <meta content="Y16POL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bosnia and Herzegovina</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kosovo (Serbia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Accounting Office</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myers, Steven Lee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DC113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="570" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Study Offers Grim Prognosis for Lasting Peace in Balkans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myers, Steven Lee</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report by General Accounting Office says prospects for lasting peace in Kosovo, Bosnia and other parts of Balkans remain bleak, and warns of prospect of instability and even renewed violence; credits NATO-led peacekeeping missions for ending open conflict, but says little progress has been made toward creating peaceful, democratic governments committed to political and ethnic reconciliation (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the eve of a Senate vote to set a deadline for withdrawing American troops from Kosovo, a General Accounting Office report released today said that prospects for lasting peace in Kosovo, Bosnia and other parts of the Balkans remained bleak and warned of the prospect of instability and even renewed violence.</p>
        <p>The report, released by the House Armed Services Committee, credited NATO-led peacekeeping missions in Bosnia and Kosovo for ending open conflict. But it said that little progress had been made toward creating peaceful, democratic governments committed to political and ethnic reconciliation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the eve of a Senate vote to set a deadline for withdrawing American troops from Kosovo, a General Accounting Office report released today said that prospects for lasting peace in Kosovo, Bosnia and other parts of the Balkans remained bleak and warned of the prospect of instability and even renewed violence.</p>
        <p>The report, released by the House Armed Services Committee, credited NATO-led peacekeeping missions in Bosnia and Kosovo for ending open conflict. But it said that little progress had been made toward creating peaceful, democratic governments committed to political and ethnic reconciliation.</p>
        <p>The 90-page report is sure to provide support for critics of the prolonged American military operations in the Balkans.</p>
        <p>American troops have served in Bosnia since that country's ethnic warfare ended in 1995, and now total 4,200. About 5,900 Americans have been in Kosovo since a NATO-led peacekeeping force occupied the Serbian province last June following NATO's air war against Yugoslavia, of which Serbia is the larger of two republics.</p>
        <p>Last week, in a lopsided, bipartisan vote, the Senate Appropriations Committee approved an amendment setting a deadline of July 1, 2001, for withdrawing American ground troops unless Congress votes to give specific approval for an extension. The full Senate is expected to vote on the legislation on Tuesday as part of a larger military construction spending bill.</p>
        <p>The report by the General Accounting Office, the investigative arm of Congress, said that forces opposed to peace continued to wield influence in the Balkans, inhibiting progress toward political stability.</p>
        <p>The report's authors cited evidence of Serbian paramilitary units and former Kosovo Albanian fighters operating in Kosovo, as well as ''small groups of armed thugs organized and controlled by extremist political leaders'' in Bosnia, where Muslim, Croat and Serbian groups fought for control of the country for more than three and a half years.</p>
        <p>In both Kosovo and Bosnia, which were once part of the former Yugoslavia, ''the former warring parties largely retain their wartime goals,'' the report concluded.</p>
        <p>While the report criticized political leaders in Kosovo and Bosnia for failing to embrace ''political and social reconciliation considered necessary to build multiethnic, democratic societies and institutions,'' it also criticized the United Nations for failing to provide needed resources, particularly in Kosovo, where an international police force has been slow to get off the ground.</p>
        <p>The report did not advocate an American or NATO withdrawal, as some members of Congress have called for. On the contrary, the report said that factions in Bosnia and Kosovo ''would resume war if the NATO-led troops were withdrawn.''</p>
        <p>The report warned that the region could face ''an escalation of violent incidents or armed conflict'' over the next five years, not just in Bosnia and Kosovo, but also in Macedonia and in the two remaining republics of the former Yugoslavia, Montenegro as well as Serbia.</p>
        <p>Sen. John W. Warner of Virginia, a Republican who sponsored the Senate legislation with Sen. Robert C. Byrd of West Virginia, a Democrat, said today that the report underscored the concerns that led him to propose the amendment on the American presence in Kosovo.</p>
        <p>But Secretary of Defense William S. Cohen and senior Pentagon commanders have mounted an intense campaign against the legislation, warning that it would undermine NATO's operations and embolden the Yugoslav president, Slobodan Milosevic.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
