<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Los Alamos Becomes a Laptop Lab</title>
    <meta content="16ALAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199859"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Alamos (Nm)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Alamos National Laboratory</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Santa Fe Institute</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEED6103BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Los Alamos Becomes a Laptop Lab</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, George</byline>
      <dateline>SANTA FE, N.M., May 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many scientists at Los Alamos National Laboratory who were forced by wildfire to flee Los Alamos face being refugees from their homes and their second homes: laboratories and offices where they study particle physics and other areas of research unrelated to weapons design; for many theorists, their laboratories are as portable as their laptops; others, because of security reasons, cannot access all their files; Santa Fe Institute, nonprofit, multidisciplinary research and education center, has opened its computers, providing laboratory in exile for Los Alamos scientists, and many Santa Fe scientists have opened their homes to Los Alamos's burned-out scientists; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Throughout the 11-day-old fire that has swept through the pine forests around Los Alamos National Laboratory in northern New Mexico, the lab's computer system has remained up and running -- providing an eerie but comforting virtual presence for scientists exiled from their research. Everyday they have been able to sign on to the system to exchange e-mail messages, download unclassified files for work and reassure themselves that the lab is still there.</p>
        <p>''That's the sign that things are O.K.,'' said Dr. Luis Bettencourt, a physicist who, displaced from his office, has been working from his home in Santa Fe. ''I just hope the fire doesn't get worse over there in the next few days -- the winds are picking up,'' he said. Dr. Bettencourt said he worried about losing some files because he could not download everything. ''But that is really nothing compared to the people who have lost their homes.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Throughout the 11-day-old fire that has swept through the pine forests around Los Alamos National Laboratory in northern New Mexico, the lab's computer system has remained up and running -- providing an eerie but comforting virtual presence for scientists exiled from their research. Everyday they have been able to sign on to the system to exchange e-mail messages, download unclassified files for work and reassure themselves that the lab is still there.</p>
        <p>''That's the sign that things are O.K.,'' said Dr. Luis Bettencourt, a physicist who, displaced from his office, has been working from his home in Santa Fe. ''I just hope the fire doesn't get worse over there in the next few days -- the winds are picking up,'' he said. Dr. Bettencourt said he worried about losing some files because he could not download everything. ''But that is really nothing compared to the people who have lost their homes.''</p>
        <p>Little can be more wrenching than evacuating one's neighborhood not knowing if it will remain. Many of the scientists who have been forced by the Cerro Grande fire to flee Los Alamos face being refugees from their second homes: the laboratories and offices where they study cosmology, particle physics, immunology and other areas of research unrelated to weapons design.</p>
        <p>When Dr. Wojciech H. Zurek, an expert on quantum mechanics, evacuated his home, one of the first things he grabbed was his Powerbook. ''Over the last couple of years, I've ended up relying more and more on it and less on the laboratory computer system, which has become so secure that it is harder and harder to access files remotely,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One graduate student, afraid for his data, rushed to his office shortly after the fire began and, ignoring rules requiring a property removal form, grabbed his computer and took it home. ''He just took the law into his own hands,'' said his supervisor, Dr. Catherine Macken, a theoretical biologist. ''He said, 'I need my computer; my life's work is on it.' '' She said that under the circumstances she was sure there would be no disciplinary action.</p>
        <p>Others were less successful as they tried to rescue data. ''I was and still am anxious about data, books, papers, etc. -- essentially my scientific heritage for the last 25 years,'' said Dr. Alan Perelson, a Los Alamos scientist who uses computer simulations of the immune system to study the AIDS virus. Dr. Perelson, who also has an office at the Santa Fe Institute, a nonprofit, multidisciplinary research and education center, said he spent an afternoon downloading information off the Los Alamos computers. Because of security reasons, however, he could not access all the files.</p>
        <p>But that was the least of his worries. ''What is most difficult is trying to find out where people are,'' Dr. Perelson said. ''Work has almost ground to a standstill, not only because of lack of access to labs and computers, but because we are all concerned with the news and our friends and neighbors.''</p>
        <p>Like many Santa Fe scientists, Dr. Perelson has been housing displaced colleagues. ''I am currently housing two full families plus one lab visitor (10 people in all) as well as pets (3 cats, 1 dog); so things are chaotic and communal at my house,'' he wrote in an e-mail message.</p>
        <p>Just as people have opened their homes to friends, so has the Santa Fe Institute opened its computers, providing a kind of laboratory in exile for scientists who feel they must work even in such distressing times.</p>
        <p>''We had said early on that anybody who wants to show up should feel free to do so,'' said Dr. Erica Jen, a research professor at the institute. A conference room has been turned into a computer lab. Other Los Alamos scientists -- 10 to 15 were expected today -- are using some of the empty desks.</p>
        <p>Dr. Stirling Colgate came in over the weekend, talking himself past a security guard ''by saying, 'I'm a physicist from Los Alamos,' and making it sound convincing.'' Today he was transferring some files from Los Alamos and preparing to meet with a postdoctoral student from Pakistan about an astrophysics project. ''This is my lifeline to continue my work,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For many theorists, their laboratories are as portable as their laptops. Dr. Christian Forst, a biologist at the lab who uses computer models to study microbial genomes, said: ''I have an advantage compared to all the experimenters I collaborate with.  They can just sit and read some papers but I can at least do something.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Hans Frauenfelder, director of Los Alamos's Center for Nonlinear Studies, was worried that he would have to cancel his division's 20th annual conference early next month.  Gathering at his home in Santa Fe today, he and some colleagues decided that, one way or the other, the conference would go on.</p>
        <p>But there was another reason for the meeting, Dr. Frauenfelder said: ''People should feel that life is continuing and that we really care.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
