<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Without a Body, Murder Case of Widow Relies on Circumstantial Evidence</title>
    <meta content="16KIME$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199961"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohde, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barnes, Julian E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kimes, Sante</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kimes, Kenneth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Silverman, Irene</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E4D6113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1430" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Without a Body, Murder Case of Widow Relies on Circumstantial Evidence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID ROHDE and JULIAN E. BARNES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barnes, Julian E; Rohde, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jurors are deliberating in New York City trial of Sante and Kenneth Kimes, charged with murder of Irene Silverman in scheme to seize control of her $8 million town house; prosecutors faced daunting task of proving murder without body or physical evidence linking defendants to crime; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Valentine's Day, four of the Manhattan district attorney's senior prosecutors stood before 12 jurors and began an exhaustive, carefully choreographed presentation aimed at achieving the seemingly impossible. They vowed to prove beyond a reasonable doubt that a pair of con artists had murdered a wealthy elderly widow, even though investigators had failed to turn up a corpse or any other physical evidence linking the defendants to the crime.</p>
        <p>Three months and 129 prosecution witnesses later, the jurors in the murder trial of Sante and Kenneth Kimes, the accused mother and son, have either been impressed, or numbed, by the sheer bulk of evidence presented to them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Valentine's Day, four of the Manhattan district attorney's senior prosecutors stood before 12 jurors and began an exhaustive, carefully choreographed presentation aimed at achieving the seemingly impossible. They vowed to prove beyond a reasonable doubt that a pair of con artists had murdered a wealthy elderly widow, even though investigators had failed to turn up a corpse or any other physical evidence linking the defendants to the crime.</p>
        <p>Three months and 129 prosecution witnesses later, the jurors in the murder trial of Sante and Kenneth Kimes, the accused mother and son, have either been impressed, or numbed, by the sheer bulk of evidence presented to them.</p>
        <p>Witnesses have been flown to New York from across the nation. Experts have testified at length about forgeries, knockout drugs and offshore bank accounts. And detectives have testified about searching trash disposal sites in the city, Long Island, elsewhere in New York, New Jersey, Ohio and Pennsylvania for the body of Irene Silverman, an 82-year-old woman who prosecutors say was the victim of an elaborate scheme by the Kimeses to seize control of her $8 million Upper East Side town house.</p>
        <p>After a two-year investigation and hundreds of thousands of dollars in costs, the jurors began deliberating yesterday after enduring a drawn-out trial that was often like watching a jigsaw puzzle being assembled, with some occasionally bizarre courtroom theater thrown in. Behind it all was the unusual and daunting challenge of proving a murder case entirely on circumstantial evidence.</p>
        <p>Defense lawyers for the Kimeses, who have long been accused in a variety of grifter schemes but have an extensive track record of evading conviction, insist that their clients are innocent and the scapegoats of a vast conspiracy. Without a witness to any attack, a victim's body or conclusive proof that Mrs. Silverman is dead, the Kimeses cannot be convicted of murder, say the defense lawyers, one of whom called the prosecution's case ''a landfill '' of evidence, not a mountain.</p>
        <p>''There is no body, no witnesses,'' Michael Hardy, the defense lawyer, said yesterday after the jury began deliberating at 2:20 p.m. ''There is no proof of any murder at all.''</p>
        <p>The jury failed to reach a verdict yesterday after deliberating for more than four hours, and will continue deliberating today.</p>
        <p>If they choose to convict, the jurors will have to conclude that disparate pieces of evidence -- a stun gun, a forged deed and, most of all, lists written by Mrs. Kimes that appear to outline the scheme -- prove that the Kimeses murdered Mrs. Silverman.</p>
        <p>After initially insisting that she should be allowed to testify in her own defense, Mrs. Kimes changed her mind because prosecutors would have been allowed to question her about a 1986 conviction on federal slavery charges for enticing young women from Mexico to work for her, then refusing to pay them and preventing them from leaving. Mrs. Kimes served three years of a five-year prison sentence.</p>
        <p>In several outbursts to the judge in the current trial, she declared her innocence and demanded to be allowed to talk to reporters. Yesterday, she passed a note to a reporter for The New York Times in which she contended that she had bought the Silverman mansion for $7 million. The note said Mrs. Silverman's employees and the nonprofit group she founded, the Coby Foundation, were trying to stop the sale.</p>
        <p>''The deed is real,'' Mrs. Kimes wrote. ''The notary is liable and lying. The staff and Coby are trying to stop the sale and get the apartment free. They know where she is!''</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said the notarized deed transferring the house was forged and listed a sale price of $395,000. And in their closing remarks, prosecutors ridiculed suggestions that Mrs. Silverman's employees were involved in her murder.</p>
        <p>Over the last three months, the prosecutors have weaved a complex account for the jury that retraced the Kimeses' movements from Utah to California to Las Vegas to Florida and ultimately New York in June 1998.</p>
        <p>The Kimeses, prosecutors said, learned of Mrs. Silverman in 1996 from Ralph Pellecchia, a New Jersey insurance salesman who testified that he met Mrs. Kimes at an anti-aging symposium in the Kimeses' hometown, Las Vegas. It was not until March 1998 that she contacted him again, Mr. Pellecchia said.</p>
        <p>She arranged a meeting, began asking about Mrs. Silverman in more detail and learned the name of Rudy Vaccari, Mrs. Silverman's butcher and friend. The next month, Mrs. Kimes, using the name Eva, used Mr. Vaccari's name as a reference to reserve a room in Mrs. Silverman's mansion for a Manny Guerrin, an alias Mr. Kimes used.</p>
        <p>The next month, in May 1998, the Kimeses, according to prosecutors, moved to Florida, where they had a deed search conducted on Mrs. Silverman's mansion and stole the Social Security card of Athanassios Tsoukas, a Massachusetts doctor vacationing in Florida, who testified by videotape. They used Mr. Tsoukas's name to set up the Atlantis Group, the dummy corporation prosecutors said the Kimeses intended to use to take possession of the mansion.</p>
        <p>Posing as Eva and Manny, the Kimeses moved to New York in June 1998 and rented Apartment 1B on the first floor of Mrs. Silverman's house for $6,000 a month. Prosecutors said that as soon as they arrived they began hunting for Mrs. Silverman's Social Security card and examples of her signature.</p>
        <p>In the notebooks prosecutors said the Kimeses kept in Florida and New York, they wrote ''get social'' and ''get her signature in some way,'' references, they contend, to Mrs. Silverman's Social Security number and signature.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said the Kimeses got Mrs. Silverman's signature from the rental agreement she gave them, then traced it onto the fraudulent deed they had drafted. The first person they brought in to notarize the deed, Don Aoki, testified that he refused. But the second notary, Noelle Sweeney, testified that she gave her seal after Mr. Kimes took her into the apartment and introduced Mrs. Kimes, who, dressed in a bright red wig and Victorian nightgown, claimed to be Mrs. Silverman.</p>
        <p>The Social Security number proved harder to get. Prosecutors said Mrs. Kimes impersonated a casino employee offering Mrs. Silverman a trip to Las Vegas if she would divulge her Social Security number. They also tried to trick her employees into giving it to them. But prosecutors said the Kimeses were able to get the number only after they killed Mrs. Silverman.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors waited until their 12-hour closing argument to present a theory explaining the most seemingly difficult aspect of the crime -- a theory of how the Kimeses could have murdered Mrs. Silverman without leaving a trace. Prosecutors said the Kimeses grabbed the 4-foot-9-inch widow in a hallway, shocked her in the neck with a 300,000-volt stun gun, dragged her into an apartment and strangled her.</p>
        <p>''Sante Kimes was the brains of the operation,'' Ann Donnelly, a prosecutor, said in her closing arguments. ''Kenny was more of the muscle. Sante gives the instructions and Kenny carries them out.''</p>
        <p>The Kimeses then laid Mrs. Silverman's body on a shower curtain, wrapped her in duct tape, placed her inside garbage bags and stuffed her inside a six-foot duffel bag, prosecutors said. Her body was loaded into the trunk of their Lincoln Town Car and taken to an unknown location, Assistant District Attorney Connie Fernandez said.</p>
        <p>But defense lawyers insisted that such an episode was impossible, noting that the Kimeses were arrested only seven hours after Mrs. Silverman was last seen.</p>
        <p>''How would you do that?'' Mr. Hardy asked the jury in his summation. ''Get rid of someone without a trace, and appear at a hotel in full dress without a trace of Irene Silverman and no dirt or anything? I don't think it's possible.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
