<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As the Space Station Falls, NASA Moves to Prop It Up</title>
    <meta content="16STAT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000519T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atlantis (Space Shuttle)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, Kenneth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5DF113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As the Space Station Falls, NASA Moves to Prop It Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH CHANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chang, Kenneth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>International Space Station is brushing against wisps of atmosphere and dropping 1.5 to 2 miles a week as it orbits Earth at height of 210 miles; one of space shuttle Atlantis's missions will be to nudge space station upward by 20 to 25 miles to be ready for next piece of station, Zvezda service module, which Russia has scheduled for launching in July; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The space station is falling. As it orbits Earth, even at a height of 210 miles, the nascent International Space Station brushes against wisps of atmosphere, causing it gradually to lose speed and altitude.</p>
        <p>The Sun, as it approaches the height of its 11-year sunspot cycle, churns in a more unruly roil, throwing out more high-energy radiation that puffs out Earth's outer atmosphere. And the station falls faster.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The space station is falling. As it orbits Earth, even at a height of 210 miles, the nascent International Space Station brushes against wisps of atmosphere, causing it gradually to lose speed and altitude.</p>
        <p>The Sun, as it approaches the height of its 11-year sunspot cycle, churns in a more unruly roil, throwing out more high-energy radiation that puffs out Earth's outer atmosphere. And the station falls faster.</p>
        <p>Since February, the space station has been dropping 1.5 to 2 miles a week. At that rate, its orbit would dip below 200 miles by the time the next piece of the station, the Zvezda service module, is launched in July.</p>
        <p>That is still a safe altitude, but any further delay of Zvezda, already two and a half years late, could pose a problem.</p>
        <p>''Things won't really get precarious until the end of August,'' said Paul S. Hill, the space station's flight director. ''It'd be September before you'd hear loud noises and see a big splash.''</p>
        <p>If necessary, Mr. Hill said, flight controllers could fire the station's rockets to raise the orbit. But the station's limited propellant is needed to dock the station to Zvezda, and until Zvezda arrives, there is no way to refuel.</p>
        <p>This problem is one reason the space shuttle Atlantis is on the launching pad. In an 11-day mission, to begin Thursday, Atlantis is to nudge the space station upward by 20 to 25 miles.</p>
        <p>Originally, Atlantis was to fly a few weeks after Zvezda joined the two components already in orbit. But after the Russians put off Zvezda's launching until July, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration decided in February to split the original shuttle mission in two.</p>
        <p>Under the revised schedule, Atlantis will bring up more than a ton of supplies now -- including fans, air filters and replacements for failing batteries -- and then revisit the station with more supplies about five weeks after the launching of Zvezda.</p>
        <p>If all of these flights succeed, they will break the logjam that has stalled work on the $60 billion project. ''I think we're in a position to make very good, rapid progress, as soon as we get the service module in July,'' said W. Michael Hawes, NASA's chief engineer for the space station.</p>
        <p>The station's first full-time occupants are to arrive at the end of October. For now, NASA wants to make sure that what is already up stays up in working condition.</p>
        <p>''The primary reason is to do maintenance work on the station,'' James Hartsfield, a spokesman at NASA's Johnson Space Center in Houston, said of this month's trip. ''The re-boost is a close second.''</p>
        <p>When it split the mission in two, NASA also split the crew, reassigning three members to the later flight. The crew for the first mission includes James D. Halsell Jr., the commander; Dr. Scott J. Horowitz, the pilot, and Dr. Mary Ellen Weber and Jeffrey N. Williams, the mission specialists, who have been training together more than a year. Joining them will be two American astronauts, James S. Voss and Susan J. Helms, and a Russian astronaut, Yuri V. Usachev, who had been training in Moscow to be the station's second crew.</p>
        <p>Usually, a shuttle crew trains six months to a year for a mission. The short-notice shuffling is unusual, but NASA says the newcomers should have no trouble.</p>
        <p>''They were extremely familiar with all of the systems of the space station,'' said Rob Navias, a space center spokesman. Adding the three to the current mission ''made perfect sense from our standpoint,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The mission, postponed last month by bad weather, includes a 6.5 hour spacewalk to install a crane and other equipment outside the station.</p>
        <p>On the mission's eighth day, after all of the cargo has been unloaded to the station, the shuttle will use its leftover propellant to raise the station to a higher orbit.</p>
        <p>Then the falling begins again.</p>
        <p>At the altitude of the space station, the thin upper atmosphere is a better vacuum than what can be produced in the best vacuum chambers on the ground -- but it is not empty.</p>
        <p>''In space there are still some particles that impact the spacecraft and cause drag,'' Mr. Hill said.</p>
        <p>The number of particles rises and falls with the Sun's sunspot cycle.</p>
        <p>When the Sun is at its quietest, each cubic inch of space 200 miles above the ground still contains about two billion molecules, mostly atoms of oxygen.</p>
        <p>When the Sun is near the height of its solar activity, intense magnetic fields erupt out of its surface that heat gases in the Sun's atmosphere to millions of degrees.</p>
        <p>''When you have things at two million degrees, they give off X-rays,'' said Dr. Raymond G. Roble, a senior scientist at the National Center for Atmospheric Research's High Altitude Observatory.</p>
        <p>Only a small fraction of the Sun's light is emitted as X-rays, but the intensity of X-rays at solar maximum can be up to 10 times as great as at solar minimum. (At visible wavelengths, the Sun is only an imperceptible fraction of 1 percent brighter.)</p>
        <p>Ninety-three million miles away, some of those X-rays, as well as photons of short-wavelength ultraviolet light, slam into molecules in Earth's upper atmosphere, heating them up. At solar minimum, the temperature of the atmosphere 200 miles up is, on average, about 850 degrees Fahrenheit. At solar maximum, temperatures rise to more than 2,000.</p>
        <p>In the same way a hot air balloon rises upward, ''that extra heating causes the atmosphere to expand outward,'' Dr. Roble said.</p>
        <p>As a result, the density of the atmosphere is now nearly 10 times as great as when the Sun is at solar minimum. The denser atmosphere increases the drag on the station, and the station falls faster.</p>
        <p>The rate of falling peaked in the first half of last month at more than two miles a week, but it has since slowed down again as solar activity entered a temporary lull.</p>
        <p>The falling would never have been a concern at all, except for the slipping launching date of the Zvezda service module.</p>
        <p>The 42,000-pound Zvezda, which is to provide living quarters, propulsion and flight control and some laboratory space, was to have been launched five months after the first two segments, the Russian-built Zarya and the American-built Unity modules, were launched in late 1998.</p>
        <p>Zvezda, which means ''star'' in Russian, was first delayed by a lack of Russian financing. Then two Russian Proton rockets, the type that is to lift Zvezda into orbit, exploded and crashed, causing further delays.</p>
        <p>But according to some analysts, the rocket failures were a blessing, giving both the United States and Russia more time to test space station components on the ground instead of rushing them into orbit.</p>
        <p>''Last year's launch schedule was a game of space chicken, with both sides roaring down the road, hoping the other would blink first,'' said James E. Oberg of Houston, a former NASA engineer who is an expert on the space program. ''There was divine intervention. Both sides were saved by a Russian rocket failure, which gave the Russians the excuse everyone was hoping for.''</p>
        <p>Since the two crashes, the Russians have successfully launched three Protons with a fourth scheduled in June before the Zvezda launching, which is now scheduled for sometime between July 8 and 14.</p>
        <p>''I think the July launch date is much more realistic than anything we've had before,'' said Representative Dave Weldon, a Florida Republican who has been critical of Russian involvement with the space station.  ''But there's also the track record of delay upon delay upon delay.''</p>
        <p>A successful launching of Zvezda would be followed in September by the first piece of the truss that would be the backbone of the space station. The first three-member crew is scheduled to arrive in late October via a Russian Soyuz rocket. The first solar panels are to go up in November, and the American-built Destiny laboratory module is scheduled for launching in mid-January 2001.</p>
        <p>''At this time, the U.S. elements are looking in pretty good shape, and I think we'll be able to meet our launch schedule after the service module,'' Mr. Hawes said.</p>
        <p>But other schedule snags may still arise. Because Russia is keeping its aging Mir space station, there may not be enough rockets to ferry supplies and crews to both.</p>
        <p>The United States has also been building a substitute module for Zvezda in case the Russians run into further delays. In February, NASA's administrator, Daniel S. Goldin, announced that if Russia did not launch Zvezda by early August, NASA would instead send up its interim control module at the end of the year.</p>
        <p>But that $200 million module will not be ready by Mr. Goldin's December date. Part of the module's ground-to-station communication system has failed and needs to be replaced. ''We're probably a good seven weeks off the December schedule,'' Mr. Hawes said.</p>
        <p>Because the interim control module also uses a docking mechanism different from Zvezda, astronauts would have to reconfigure the dock in the Zarya module now in orbit. That would require a $4 million Russian-built pressure dome to provide the astronauts an air-filled work space.</p>
        <p>Representative Weldon said the space agency should set a launching date for the interim module in order to keep the pressure on the Russians. ''They don't understand talking,'' he said. ''We should be prepared to work with them, and if they don't deliver, we should be ready and able to work without them.</p>
        <p>If Zvezda is successfully launched on time, the interim control module will still become part of the station, but in a slightly different role.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the space station has already circled Earth more than 8,400 times, empty and falling.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 19, 2000, Friday  An article in Science Times on Tuesday about efforts to keep the International Space Station in its orbit misstated the effects of the atmosphere on its descent. As the space station loses altitude it speeds up, it does not slow down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 19, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times on Tuesday about efforts to keep the International Space Station in its orbit misstated the effects of the atmosphere on its descent. As the space station loses altitude it speeds up, it does not slow down.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
