<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A.P. Releases Files in Debate Over Massacre in Korean War</title>
    <meta content="Y16KOR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199935"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Korean War</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Associated Press</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barringer, Felicity</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Korean War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E3D8113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="813" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A.P. Releases Files in Debate Over Massacre in Korean War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICITY BARRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barringer, Felicity</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Associated Press releases detailed evidence to rebut critics of its Pulitzer Prize-winning news report that American soldiers, acting under orders, killed hundreds of South Korean civilians in July 1950 in early days of Korean War (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Associated Press released detailed evidence yesterday to rebut critics of its Pulitzer Prize-winning news report that said American soldiers, acting under orders, killed hundreds of South Korean civilians in July 1950, in the early days of the Korean War.</p>
        <p>Among the evidence released yesterday was a document that cast doubt on part of a critical article by U.S. News &amp; World Report that said records showed that one witness had been evacuated a full day before the shootings began. An editor for the magazine said the document was not included in its report through ''an oversight.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Associated Press released detailed evidence yesterday to rebut critics of its Pulitzer Prize-winning news report that said American soldiers, acting under orders, killed hundreds of South Korean civilians in July 1950, in the early days of the Korean War.</p>
        <p>Among the evidence released yesterday was a document that cast doubt on part of a critical article by U.S. News &amp; World Report that said records showed that one witness had been evacuated a full day before the shootings began. An editor for the magazine said the document was not included in its report through ''an oversight.''</p>
        <p>In addition, The Associated Press released full-length quotations from two former servicemen who said in the pages of U.S. News that The Associated Press had misquoted them. In both cases, the full quotations tended to refute that claim.</p>
        <p>The dueling documents and interviews are part of a controversy that is being closely watched by journalists, military observers and diplomats, because the outcome of the debate over the report could affect United States-South Korean relations. If a Pentagon-authorized commission that is investigating the case determines that the soldiers had been given orders to fire, that could mean that a war crime had been committed.</p>
        <p>Defense Department officials told The New York Times last week that they had confirmed the central element of the report, that United States troops had fired on unarmed civilians, killing hundreds. But on the crucial question of whether the troops were acting under orders, the evidence provided in the dueling journalistic accounts is both ambiguous and contradictory.</p>
        <p>Under the headline ''Doubts about a Korean 'Massacre,' '' a U.S. News reporter, Joseph L. Galloway, wrote, ''There is little doubt that something terrible happened there.'' But the article offered evidence from military documents that indicated that three witnesses quoted by The Associated Press -- Edward Daily, Delos Flint and Eugene Hesselman -- were not at the scene at No Gun Ri at the time.</p>
        <p>The Associated Press rebuttal reported that the magazine, in its suggestion about Mr. Flint, relied on a ''war diary'' written days later at the regimental level and ignored a ''morning report'' filed daily from the front. The morning report, indicating the location and status of G.I.'s, indicates that Mr. Flint was wounded on July 26th, the day of the reported shooting, and could have been there to witness it.</p>
        <p>The executive editor of the magazine, Brian Duffy, said last night, ''We should have cited the morning report that said he was wounded on the 26th, and on our part it was an oversight.''</p>
        <p>Another veteran who served in one of the units said to be involved in the killings gave conflicting accounts to the reporters for The Associated Press and Mr. Galloway, The A.P. released the full text of his remarks to them yesterday.</p>
        <p>The text indicates that when the veteran, Herman Patterson, said, ''It was just wholesale slaughter,'' he was speaking of the events at No Gun Ri, not another battle. Mr. Patterson told U.S. News that those remarks were taken out of context.</p>
        <p>A second witness who is being challenged, Edward Daily, told The Associated Press and other news organizations, including NBC News, The Washington Post, The New York Times and U.S. News, that he was a machine gunner at No Gun Ri and that he fired, under orders, into the refugees huddled under the stone bridge there.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Daily's service records, obtained by U.S. News, ''show that Daily was not at No Gun Ri on July 26, 1950; nor was he a machine gunner,'' the magazine reported.</p>
        <p>The wire service account acknowledges the discrepancy in the records. Both the wire service and U.S. News have reported that the original personnel records were lost in a fire in 1973 at the Army personnel records center in St. Louis. The current personnel records have been reconstructed.</p>
        <p>The Associated Press reported yesterday that other veterans said they had seen Mr. Daily at No Gun Ri. The wire service also said Mr. Daily had showed them a variety of documents attesting to his service in H Company, one of the units involved, in the months before the attack. Those papers included a driver's license and a menu from a dinner held by H Company at Christmas in 1949 that lists him with the company.</p>
        <p>The executive editor of The Associated Press, Jon Wolman, said in a statement yesterday: ''The Associated Press stands behind its carefully researched report of events in the early days of the Korean War near the village of No Gun Ri.</p>
        <p>''Even as we review discrepancies between several records and eyewitness accounts, we are confident of the accuracy and fairness of the central finding that Korean civilians were killed by U.S. forces.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
