<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Museum Says Strikers Cross Picket Line</title>
    <meta content="16MOMA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199948"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Museum of Modern Art (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Automobile Workers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenstein, Maida</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E1D7113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Museum Says Strikers Cross Picket Line</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Museum of Modern Art says 40 percent of 250 workers in United Auto Workers bargaining unit that represents museum workers have crossed picket line during 18-day strike; says strike may be losing steam and that union is highly divided; holds attendance has remained steady; Maida Rosenstein, union president, insists strike is going strong and has forced museum to cancel some events (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The union representing striking workers at the Museum of Modern Art has been put on the defensive  because 40 percent of the 250 workers in the bargaining unit, according to management's count, have crossed the picket line during the 18-day strike.</p>
        <p>Museum officials said the number of workers who had crossed the picket line showed that the strike might be losing steam and that the union was highly divided and having a hard time selling its message to many workers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The union representing striking workers at the Museum of Modern Art has been put on the defensive  because 40 percent of the 250 workers in the bargaining unit, according to management's count, have crossed the picket line during the 18-day strike.</p>
        <p>Museum officials said the number of workers who had crossed the picket line showed that the strike might be losing steam and that the union was highly divided and having a hard time selling its message to many workers.</p>
        <p>But Maida Rosenstein, president of the union, insisted that the strike was going strong, noting that the walkout had forced the museum to postpone a handful of events.</p>
        <p>''We think the museum is feeling the impact of the strike, and our members are becoming more resolute,'' said Ms. Rosenstein, who heads Local 2110 of the United Auto Workers, which represents several thousand white-collar employees in New York City.</p>
        <p>As evidence of the strike's success, union members pointed to a large and raucous demonstration on Friday night, saying that it persuaded many people not to visit the museum. That demonstration, in which more than 100 union members screamed at museumgoers, was quite different from the scene yesterday, when about 20 strikers stood outside the museum, rather quietly, penned in by police barricades on 53rd Street.</p>
        <p>Museum officials said attendance  had essentially remained steady during the strike.</p>
        <p>While disputing that 100 workers have crossed the picket line, Ms. Rosenstein said it was not surprising that many employees had returned to work because a third of the museum workers eligible for membership in the unit -- assistant curators, librarians, bookshop workers and others -- had chosen not to join.</p>
        <p>Summoned by federal mediators, negotiators for the two sides yesterday held their first bargaining session since the walkout began. The two sides are feuding over wage increases, the health care plan and job security, which has become more urgent because the museum plans temporary layoffs for scores of workers during a four-year, $650 million expansion project.</p>
        <p>Several workers said they had  crossed the picket line because they thought union leaders were emphasizing an issue that was more important to the leadership than to rank and file workers: the union's demand that all new employees join the union or, if they choose not to join, be required to pay union dues.</p>
        <p>Charles Silver, an assistant curator who is one of the founders of the museum's union, said he crossed the picket line because he believed the leaders were not representing the members' best interests. ''I believe this strike is based on manipulation,'' said Mr. Silver, who quit the union after repeatedly clashing with the leadership and calling them undemocratic. ''These people have engineered a strike for their own purposes. It has nothing to do with the benefits of the workers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver's criticism of the union are consistent with statements by the museum's management, which insists that the union's leadership is misinforming and manipulating  union members. The museum's workers belong to the Professional and Administrative Staff Association, a 30-year-old unit that is part of Local 2110.</p>
        <p>Robert Batterman, the museum's chief negotiator, said Ms. Rosenstein had been less than candid when she said her top priorities were protection against layoffs and preservation of the workers' health plan.</p>
        <p>Rather, he said, her first priority was a requirement that new workers join the union or pay union dues. That move, which would create what is called an agency shop, would go far to strengthen the union's hand in future negotiations.</p>
        <p>''Publicly and to the people on strike, they are saying agency shop is not a big deal,'' Mr. Batterman said. ''That is not what they're saying to us. I think the people on strike do not want to be on strike to support an agency shop.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Rosenstein said the museum's negotiators were putting that argument forward to undercut the union's leadership and divide its members.</p>
        <p>Mr. Batterman said the museum has never proposed cutting its health plan. And he said the museum was offering to grant a right of recall to workers laid off during the construction, which would amount to strong job security, he said.</p>
        <p>Taking a break yesterday afternoon from shouting at visitors not to enter the museum, John Gray, a cataloguer in the museum library, took sharp issue with Mr. Batterman. He asked why, if the museum's negotiators were sincere about not planning to cut the workers' health coverage, they were rejecting a provision promising not to make such cuts. He also said management's promise of a right of recall was unsatisfactory because it did not guarantee that all workers furloughed during construction would be called back.</p>
        <p>''I resent the statement by management that we are dupes of our union leaders,'' Mr. Gray said. ''If management doesn't like the idea that we rejected what they view as a fair contract, that's their problem. But don't call us stupid. I'm a great researcher. I've published seven books. Don't tell me I don't know how to analyze their proposals.''</p>
        <p>Neither management nor the union appeared to be putting much emphasis on wages. Wages run from $17,000 for bookshop workers to more than $50,000 for associate curators, and median earnings are around $28,500. Management has offered a 3 percent wage increase each year for three years, while the union wants a five-year contract with a 5 percent raise in the first year and 4 percent in subsequent years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
