<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Federal Tax Fraud Trial of 2 Brothers Opens</title>
    <meta content="16PIRR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199949"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">baker, al</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pirro, Albert J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pirro, Jeanine (Dist Atty)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pirro, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parker, Barrington D Jr (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1D7113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Federal Tax Fraud Trial of 2 Brothers Opens</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">baker, al</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS, May 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jury selection begins in tax fraud trial of Albert J Pirro Jr, husband of Westchester County, NY, Dist Atty Jeanine F Pirro, and his brother, Anthony G Pirro; Albert Pirro's lawyer seeks to bar potential jurors from hearing anything about old paternity suit against him; Judge Barrington D Parker Jr agrees to question potential jurors about their attitudes on paternity issues; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the first day of the federal government's tax fraud trial of two well-known Westchester brothers, most of the opening events hinged today on a matter outside the scope of the case: Albert J. Pirro Jr.'s fathering of an Indiana teenager.</p>
        <p>The issue came up as jury selection began and Gustave H. Newman, Mr. Pirro's defense lawyer, sought to bar potential jurors from hearing anything about an old paternity suit against him. Last June, DNA tests indicated that Mr. Pirro was the father of a teenage girl whose mother had sued him for child support.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the first day of the federal government's tax fraud trial of two well-known Westchester brothers, most of the opening events hinged today on a matter outside the scope of the case: Albert J. Pirro Jr.'s fathering of an Indiana teenager.</p>
        <p>The issue came up as jury selection began and Gustave H. Newman, Mr. Pirro's defense lawyer, sought to bar potential jurors from hearing anything about an old paternity suit against him. Last June, DNA tests indicated that Mr. Pirro was the father of a teenage girl whose mother had sued him for child support.</p>
        <p>Mr. Newman told the federal court today that any mention of the matter could impugn his client's character.</p>
        <p>But prosecutors contended that although their case was about taxes and not parenting, the money Mr. Pirro spent to defend himself against the paternity charge was part of the $1 million that they asserted he illegally deducted on his tax returns as personal expenses rather than business expenditures. The judge, Barrington D. Parker Jr., agreed to question potential jurors on their attitudes about paternity issues.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pirro, 52, the husband of the Westchester district attorney, Jeanine F. Pirro, 48, is being tried along with his brother, Anthony G. Pirro, 45, who was his accountant. Prosecutors say the $1 million was used between 1988 and 1997 for lavish personal expenses like Mercedes-Benz cars, cruise tickets, baby-sitting services and ornaments for Mr. and Mrs. Pirro's house in Harrison, N.Y.</p>
        <p>The brothers were indicted in February 1999 and have since become fierce adversaries. While Mrs. Pirro, who was not in court today, has not been charged with any wrongdoing, the indictment suggested that she benefited from some of the deductions, and the case has apparently already hurt her immediate political aspirations.</p>
        <p>Today's proceedings signaled how some of the intense interest swirling around the case has to do with matters other than the charges against the Pirro brothers.</p>
        <p>Jury selection, which normally takes one day in criminal trials, became a laborious process as Judge Parker explained that one of the defendants had resolved a paternity case. He asked potential jurors, one by one, whether they had any feelings about paternity -- as well as any involving lobbyists, lawyers, police officers, real estate developers, politicians or accountants -- that would not let them rule fairly in the case.</p>
        <p>By day's end, 12 potential jurors had survived; about 30 others had been rejected by the prosecution or the defense or had been excused for various reasons, including statements that they could not put aside personal feelings about paternity issues.</p>
        <p>When Judge Parker asked one potential juror, Martin Doris, how he felt about paternity, Mr. Doris said, ''Probably the same as lobbyists and lawyers: negative thoughts, but I think I can be fair.'' He was dismissed moments later.</p>
        <p>Jury selection is scheduled to continue Tuesday. The judge and lawyers said opening arguments could begin as early as Tuesday afternoon.</p>
        <p>Albert Pirro is a successful real estate development lawyer, as well as a formidable lobbyist and Republican fund-raiser. Tanned and trim, with a neat gray suit, he cut a confident path through the courthouse today, chatting with security guards and looking relaxed at a table with his legal team. By contrast, Anthony Pirro appeared tense, sitting hunched over a table behind his older brother, taking notes.</p>
        <p>The only time that the brothers appeared to acknowledge each other was when one man explained to Judge Parker that his reason for trying to avoid jury duty was a directive from his girlfriend: ''I was told to come home with good news.''</p>
        <p>The elder Pirro laughed, clapped loudly and briefly turned to his brother.</p>
        <p>When court adjourned, Anthony Pirro walked quickly away with his wife, Donna, refusing to comment.</p>
        <p>Albert Pirro, meanwhile, spoke with reporters, saying he would not rule out an appearance by his wife in court. Asked how he was holding up, he responded, ''Fantastic.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
