<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AstraZeneca to Sell a Genetically Engineered Strain of Rice</title>
    <meta content="Y16RIC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199897"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vitamin A</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beta Carotene</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Astrazeneca Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barboza, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vitamins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DB113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AstraZeneca to Sell a Genetically Engineered Strain of Rice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barboza, David</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, May 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>AstraZeneca PLC says it will sell genetically altered strain of 'golden rice' in developed world and also help make technology freely available to world's poorest countries; company says rice will be made available in three years; rice is fortified with beta carotene that converts to vitamin A (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AstraZeneca P.L.C., a giant pharmaceutical company, said today that it would sell a genetically altered strain of ''golden rice'' in the developed world and also  help make the technology freely available to the world's poorest countries.</p>
        <p>The London-based company, which announced the agreement here in a news conference with one of the scientists who invented the rice, said it would be made available in three years. The rice, which is fortified with beta carotene that converts to vitamin A, would be given away in the developing world in the hopes of improving the health of undernourished people and curing some forms of blindness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AstraZeneca P.L.C., a giant pharmaceutical company, said today that it would sell a genetically altered strain of ''golden rice'' in the developed world and also  help make the technology freely available to the world's poorest countries.</p>
        <p>The London-based company, which announced the agreement here in a news conference with one of the scientists who invented the rice, said it would be made available in three years. The rice, which is fortified with beta carotene that converts to vitamin A, would be given away in the developing world in the hopes of improving the health of undernourished people and curing some forms of blindness.</p>
        <p>The rice, which has been under development for seven years, has been hailed by the biotechnology industry as a symbol of the promise of agricultural biotechnology, which up until now has largely created an array of crops that benefit farmers by increasing yields.</p>
        <p>These crops have led to controversy in Europe and the United States, with many critics saying the crops have not been properly tested, an accusation the industry denies.</p>
        <p>The industry hopes that crops like golden rice will be more acceptable to the public, particularly if they serve humanitarian purposes. Scientists said they believed more than 124 million people worldwide suffer from a vitamin A deficiency, and that up to 2 million children die each year in early childhood and another 500,000 become afflicted with an irreversible form of blindness each year because they rely on a rice diet that is deficient in vitamin A.</p>
        <p>The scientists, Peter Beyer, a professor at the University of Freiburg in Germany, and Prof. Ingo Potrykus of the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Zurich first announced their discovery in January in the journal Science. Today, Mr. Beyer said they had reached a licensing agreement with Zeneca Ag Products, a division of AstraZeneca.</p>
        <p>Robert Woods, the president of Zeneca, said the crop had great nutritional benefits. ''And if we do the right things in verifying the safety, it will take out the political and emotional issues that have surrounded biotechnology,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Critics say that however noble the effort, they remain concerned about the safety of genetically altered crops, and see the announcement as an effort by the biotechnology industry to put a more favorable spin on those crops. ''It's a very laudable goal,'' said Joseph Mendelson III, a spokesman at the Center for Food Safety in Washington, an environmental advocacy group. ''But from our standpoint, genetic engineering has a host of unknown health risks; you can create new toxins and allergens.'' He said that while the new strain of rice might help cure blindness, it could also create unforeseen health or environmental risks.</p>
        <p>The research that led to the golden rice technology was initially financed by the Rockefeller Foundation in New York, which was searching for ways to improve the health of children in developing countries.</p>
        <p>Dr. Beyer and Professor Potrykus say they used a biotechnology process to integrate two genes from a daffodil and one from a bacterium in the rice genome to create a new strain of yellowish or golden rice that has high levels of beta carotene, which is the precursor of vitamin A. The scientists assigned their patent and the rights to Greenovation, a company in Freiburg, Germany, which in turn licensed the technology exclusively to Zeneca.</p>
        <p>Gary Toenniessen, director of food security at the Rockefeller Foundation, said the organization was pleased by the public-private collaboration. But he said biotechnology was just one tool. ''We're not believers that biotechnology is a silver bullet,'' he said. ''But when traditional breeding is not available, genetic engineering can be applied.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
