<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cybersex Gives Birth to a Psychological Disorder</title>
    <meta content="16CYBE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brody, Jane E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D8103BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cybersex Gives Birth to a Psychological Disorder</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brody, Jane E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Experts in field say affordability, accessibility and anonymity of Internet are fueling brand new psychological disorder--cybersex addiction--that appears to be spreading with astonishing rapidity and bringing turmoil to lives of those affected; say many men and women spend hours each week seeking sexual stimulation from their computers, masturbating to pornographic images or having 'mutual' online sex with someone contacted through chat room; say even when cybersex addicts and their partners seek treatment they often conceal real problem, and as result, diagnosis of cybersex addiction is often missed; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sex is the hottest topic among adult users of the Internet, with studies showing that fully a third of all visits directed to sexually oriented Web sites, chat rooms and news groups.</p>
        <p>For most people these forays into cybersex are relatively harmless pursuits, but experts in the field say that the affordability, accessibility and anonymity of the Internet are fueling a brand new psychological disorder -- cybersex addiction -- that appears to be spreading with astonishing rapidity and bringing turmoil to  the lives of those affected.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sex is the hottest topic among adult users of the Internet, with studies showing that fully a third of all visits directed to sexually oriented Web sites, chat rooms and news groups.</p>
        <p>For most people these forays into cybersex are relatively harmless pursuits, but experts in the field say that the affordability, accessibility and anonymity of the Internet are fueling a brand new psychological disorder -- cybersex addiction -- that appears to be spreading with astonishing rapidity and bringing turmoil to  the lives of those affected.</p>
        <p>Researchers writing in the current issue of the journal Sexual Addiction and Compulsivity report that many of the men and women who now spend dozens of hours each week seeking sexual stimulation from their computers deny that they have a problem and refuse to seek help until their marriages, their jobs, or both, are in jeopardy.</p>
        <p>For some people, the route to compulsive use of the Internet for sexual satisfaction is fast and short, said Dr. Mark Schwartz of the Masters and Johnson Institute in St. Louis. ''Sex on the Net is like heroin,'' he said. ''It grabs them and takes over their lives. And it's very difficult to treat because the people affected don't want to give it up.''</p>
        <p>Those most strongly hooked on Internet sex are likely to spend hours each day masturbating to pornographic images or having ''mutual'' online sex with someone contacted through a chat room. Occasionally, they progress to off-line affairs with sex partners they meet online.</p>
        <p>Dr. Al Cooper, a staff psychologist at Stanford who has conducted the largest and most detailed survey of online sex, calls the Net ''the crack cocaine of sexual compulsivity.'' The survey, conducted online among 9,265 men and women who admitted surfing the Net for sexually oriented sites, indicated that at least 1 percent were already seriously hooked on online sex. The survey found that as many as a third of Internet users visited some type of sexual site.</p>
        <p>Projected to the country as a whole, this would mean that a minimum of 200,000 men and women have become cybersex addicts in the last few years, Dr. Cooper said. And, he added, because the respondents were self-selected and because denial of the symptoms of sexual compulsivity is commonplace, there are likely to be many more cybersex addicts than the survey indicated.</p>
        <p>''This is a hidden public health hazard exploding, in part, because very few are recognizing it as such or taking it seriously,'' Dr. Cooper wrote in his Sexual Addiction and Compulsivity report.</p>
        <p>Another author, Dr. Jennifer Schneider, a  physician in Tucson, Ariz., who is associate editor of the journal, said in an interview that even when cybersex addicts and their partners sought treatment, they often concealed their real problem, and therapists often failed to ask questions that would disclose it. As a result, the diagnosis of cybersex addiction is often missed, Dr. Schneider said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kimberly S. Young of the Center for Online Addiction in Bradford, Pa., wrote that ''partially as a result of the general population and health care professionals not being attuned to the risks, seemingly harmless cyberromps can result in serious difficulties way beyond what was expected or intended.''</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Cooper, who works at the San Jose Marital and Sexuality Center in Santa Clara, Calif., cybersex compulsives are just like drug addicts; they ''use the Internet as an important part of their sexual acting out, much like a drug addict who has a 'drug of choice,' '' and often with serious harm to their home lives and livelihood. Especially vulnerable to becoming hooked on Internet sex, he wrote, are ''those users whose sexuality may have been suppressed and limited all their lives [who] suddenly find an infinite supply of sexual opportunities'' on the Internet.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dana Putnam, a psychologist in San Luis Obispo, Calif., said other factors that could increase a person's vulnerability to cybersex compulsion were depression and other forms of emotional distress, relationship problems and a failure to get one's sexual needs met.</p>
        <p>However, a second survey conducted by Dr. Schneider among 94 family members affected by cybersex addiction revealed that the problem could arise even among those in loving marriages with ample sexual opportunities. ''Sex on the Net is just so seductive and it's so easy to stumble upon it,'' she said. ''People who are vulnerable can get hooked before they know it.''</p>
        <p>To those who say a behavioral compulsion is not a true addiction, Dr. Schneider responded with a definition of addiction that would clearly apply to cybersex abusers: ''Loss of control, continuation of the behavior despite significant adverse consequences and preoccupation or obsession with obtaining the drug or pursuing the behavior.'' Although behavioral addictions involve no external drugs, preliminary research has suggested that they cause changes in brain chemicals, like the release of endorphins, that help to perpetuate the behavior.</p>
        <p>The sexual stimulation and release obtained through cybersex also contribute importantly to the continued pursuit of the activity, Dr. Schwartz said. He wrote: ''Intense orgasms from the minimal investment of a few keystrokes are powerfully reinforcing.''  He added, ''Cybersex affords easy, inexpensive access to a myriad of ritualized encounters with idealized partners. Many cybersex abusers are re-enacting aspects of past losses, conflicts or traumas in order to foster illusions of power and love.''</p>
        <p>Some cybersex addicts develop a conditioned response to the computer and become sexually aroused even before turning it on, Dr. Putnam said. This can exacerbate the problem for people whose jobs involve work on a computer. ''Simply sitting down to work at the computer can start a sexual response that may facilitate online sexual activities,'' he wrote in the journal.</p>
        <p>As with other addictions, tolerance to cybersex stimulation can develop, prompting the addict to take more and more risks to recapture the initial high, Dr. Schneider said. Online viewing that began as a harmless recreation can become an all-consuming activity and even lead to real sexual encounters with people met online.</p>
        <p>Cybersex compulsives can become so involved with their online activities that they ignore their partners and children and risk their jobs. In Dr. Cooper's survey, 20 percent of the men and 12 percent of the women reported they had used computers at work for some sexual pursuits. Many companies now monitor employees' online activities, and repeated visits to sexually oriented sites have cost people their jobs.</p>
        <p>And some people, including two physicians, have landed in federal prison for two years because they downloaded child pornography when authorities were watching, Dr. Schwartz said.</p>
        <p>Still, most who pursue cybersex consider it harmless and safe to do so. While social and safety concerns and fear of discovery may prevent someone from visiting an adult bookstore or prostitute, there are no such constraints when pornography and sexual partners can be called up at any time of the day or night on a computer screen in one's home or office, Dr. Putnam said.</p>
        <p>To those who say ''What's the harm? They're not risking disease or death,'' Dr. Schneider, who has written extensively on sexual addiction, responds that the damage  can be as devastating as that caused by compulsive gambling or addiction to alcohol or drugs. In her survey, 91 women and 3 men in committed relationships said they had experienced serious adverse consequences, including broken relationships, from their partners' cybersex addictions. Partners commonly reported feeling betrayed, devalued, deceived, ignored and abandoned and unable to compete with a fantasy.</p>
        <p>Among them was a 34-year-old woman married 14 years to a minister who she discovered was compulsively seeking sexual satisfaction by visiting pornographic sites on the Internet. ''How can I compete with hundreds of anonymous others who are now in our bed, in his head?'' the woman wrote. ''Our bed is crowded with countless faceless strangers, where once we were intimate.''</p>
        <p>A 38-year-old woman married 18 years to a man who compulsively masturbates to images on the computer wrote that her husband had once had an extramarital affair and that ''the online 'safe' cheating has just as dirty, filthy a feel to it as does the 'real-life' cheating.''</p>
        <p>Although Dr. Cooper's survey indicates that most female cybersex addicts are single, married women also become cybersex addicts and their husbands suffer the consequences. A 44-year-old man married 26 years to a woman who became hooked on cybersex wrote: ''At first we had sex more than ever as I desperately tried to prove myself. Then sex with her made me sick. I get strong pictures of what she did and lusted after, and I get repelled and feel bad.''</p>
        <p>Women who become cybersex addicts may face even greater risks than their male counterparts. Women, who tend to pursue relationships, are inclined to visit sexually oriented chat rooms rather than the pornographic Web sites that men prefer, Dr. Cooper said. As women become increasingly hooked on online sex, they are more likely to progress to off-line meetings, which can prove dangerous.</p>
        <p>Children, too, often become victimized by cybersex addiction in a parent. As Dr. Schneider noted, children can stumble upon the pornographic material left on or near the computer or walk in on a parent masturbating at the computer. Several mothers in her survey were worried because their husbands surfed the Net while supposedly watching their children, who got to view the pornography and sometimes the masturbation.</p>
        <p>Children may also suffer as a result of increasing conflict between the parents or breakup of the marriage. And even if the marriage survives, children may lack adequate parental attention when one parent is preoccupied with sex on the computer and the other is preoccupied with the cybersex addict.</p>
        <p>Once unleashed, the power of a cyberaffair, cybersex, or both, can cause a formerly loving man to become evasive and to demand his privacy online, according to Dr. Young and her co-authors. ''This 'new frontier' in relationship dynamics can lead a once warm and compassionate wife and mother to turn to the computer and its cyberworld lovers and/or sex partners and away from caring for her children.''</p>
        <p>As Dr. Putnam put it, ''Once people get hooked on cybersex, they tend to put themselves at risk and do things they wouldn't ordinarily do.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
