<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Good Propaganda, Bad Economics</title>
    <meta content="16SNEI$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199953"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sweatshops</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nike Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sneider, Jaime</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE0D7113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="553" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Good Propaganda, Bad Economics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jaime Sneider</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sneider, Jaime</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jaime Sneider Op-Ed article accuses student activists of propagating myth that Nike and other apparel companies contract out to 'sweatshops' where overworked and underpaid workers toil in unhealthful conditions; says they have ignored fact that company has championed well-being of workers internationally; says by punishing Nike students threaten to impoverish workers they claim to protect (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>College students continue to propagate the myth that Nike and other apparel companies contract out to foreign ''sweatshops'' where overworked and underpaid workers toil in unhealthful conditions. They are especially outraged by the recent decision by Phil Knight of Nike to withdraw a promised $30 million donation to the University of Oregon in  protest of the school's decision to join the Worker Rights Consortium, a labor rights group.</p>
        <p>Rather than condemn Mr. Knight, students should commend him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>College students continue to propagate the myth that Nike and other apparel companies contract out to foreign ''sweatshops'' where overworked and underpaid workers toil in unhealthful conditions. They are especially outraged by the recent decision by Phil Knight of Nike to withdraw a promised $30 million donation to the University of Oregon in  protest of the school's decision to join the Worker Rights Consortium, a labor rights group.</p>
        <p>Rather than condemn Mr. Knight, students should commend him.</p>
        <p>The Worker Rights Consortium, which was established last fall by students, unions and human rights groups, accuses Nike of failing to pay its workers a ''living wage,'' ignoring safety concerns, and forcing employees to work overtime. But, comparatively speaking, conditions at third world factories where Nike goods are made are remarkably benevolent. For example, a number of the plants have air conditioning in countries where it is a rarity. Some factories also have clinics that can be used by employees' families, who otherwise would have little if any medical care. Several others even have schools where workers' children can learn everything from reading and writing to biology and physics.</p>
        <p>A typical worker in a Nike factory in Vietnam makes about $564 a year, which may not seem like much, but is more than twice the country's average annual income. The employee turnover rate in Nike's factories in Indonesia is consistently below 2 percent, low even by American standards. Such loyalty suggests that workers do not have better prospects.</p>
        <p>Many statistics cited by student activists are misleading and originate with the A.F.L.-C.I.O., which has endorsed the Worker Rights Consortium. The A.F.L.-C.I.O. has a direct economic interest: the regulations advocated by the consortium would increase American companies' foreign manufacturing costs, thus encouraging them to abandon their operations abroad and manufacture products domestically instead -- employing union labor.</p>
        <p>Phil Knight has agreed to an open monitoring of Nike factories through the Fair Labor Association, a group composed of consumer groups, corporations and universities that has been endorsed by the White House. Nike has said that many students have genuine concerns about working conditions abroad, and that the company recognizes that there is always room for improvement.</p>
        <p>But, according to a Nike spokeswoman, ''the way to get true reform is to have all the players at the table.'' The Worker Rights Consortium, on the other hand, has not prescribed clear goals or monitoring procedures, and does not yet have legal status as a nonprofit organization. It has been reluctant to include companies like Nike in the dialogue, claiming that corporate participation of any kind threatens workers' rights.</p>
        <p>While many students uncritically believe the Worker Rights Consortium, they ignore the fact that Phil Knight and Nike have championed the well-being of workers internationally. By trying to punish Nike, these students threaten to impoverish the workers they claim to protect.</p>
        <p>Jaime Sneider is editorial page editor of The Columbia Daily Spectator.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jaime Sneider is editorial page editor of The Columbia Daily Spectator.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
