<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Battle Over Iroquois Land Claims Escalates</title>
    <meta content="16CLAI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199979"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iroquois Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Property</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E2DF1E3BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Battle Over Iroquois Land Claims Escalates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>ONONDAGA NATION</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Focus on escalating battle over Indian land claims in New York State, where tribes in Iroquois nation are demanding return of vast swaths of land based on treaties dating back to George Washington; stakes will increase in coming months as two cases head toward trial, one involving claim to heavily populated tract of 64,000 acres that includes city of Syracuse; New York occupies dubious position since, unlike other states which typically have Indian land claims in thinly populated areas resulting from federal seizure of land, it has more claims than any other and has been slowest in resolving them; Iroquois claims, backed by federal government, will likely lead to settlements or litigation costing taxpayers hundreds of millions of dollars and intensify anger over one of biggest and and touchiest topics upstate; Indian claims total roughly 620 square miles, or double size of New York City; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Oneidas want 250,000 acres of rural New York between Syracuse and Utica. The Cayugas are staking claim to a 64,000-acre wishbone at the northern tip of Cayuga Lake. The Senecas are eyeing the Buffalo bedroom community of Grand Island. And the Mohawks, though distracted by a possible Catskills casino, are asking for various islands and parcels straddling the Canadian border.</p>
        <p>For years, these Indian nations, all members of the Iroquois confederation, have demanded the return of vast swaths of land based on treaties dating back to George Washington's administration. But within the next few months, the stakes will increase as two cases head toward a trial and the Onondagas file the last, and most valuable, Iroquois land claim: a heavily populated tract of 64,000 acres that includes Syracuse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Oneidas want 250,000 acres of rural New York between Syracuse and Utica. The Cayugas are staking claim to a 64,000-acre wishbone at the northern tip of Cayuga Lake. The Senecas are eyeing the Buffalo bedroom community of Grand Island. And the Mohawks, though distracted by a possible Catskills casino, are asking for various islands and parcels straddling the Canadian border.</p>
        <p>For years, these Indian nations, all members of the Iroquois confederation, have demanded the return of vast swaths of land based on treaties dating back to George Washington's administration. But within the next few months, the stakes will increase as two cases head toward a trial and the Onondagas file the last, and most valuable, Iroquois land claim: a heavily populated tract of 64,000 acres that includes Syracuse.</p>
        <p>No one is saying that Syracuse will suddenly change hands, or that anyone will be forcibly uprooted. But with the Iroquois backed by the federal government, the claims will probably lead to settlements or litigation costing taxpayers hundreds of millions of dollars, and could intensify the anger over one of the biggest and touchiest topics in upstate New York.</p>
        <p>And unlike other states, particularly in the West, which typically have Indian land claims in thinly populated areas resulting from the federal seizure of land, New York occupies a dubious position: it has more claims than any other state, but has been the slowest to resolve those claims, which total roughly 620 square miles, about double the size of New York City.</p>
        <p>''There's a problem here that's over 25 years old,'' said Steven M.  Tullberg, director of the Washington office of the Indian Law Resource Center, which has advised numerous Indian groups, ''that's been passed from administration to administration, that's involved lots of people, lots of money, lots of lawyers, and after all that period of time, nothing is resolved.''</p>
        <p>To some residents, the real issues are: Why us? Why now? The subject has triggered such an antagonistic reaction that it could be a major issue in the fall elections and a potential problem for the Democratic Senate candidate, Hillary Rodham Clinton, whose husband's administration has been accused by Gov. George E. Pataki of giving unconditional support to unfair Indian land claims and a lawsuit naming 20,000 landowners as defendants.</p>
        <p>''They're buying plazas, stores, entire tracts, farmland, and the reservations are like checkerboards,'' said Leon R. Koziol, a Utica lawyer who has represented several landowner groups. ''Then eventually, what do you have? A virtual country within a country, and it's scary.''</p>
        <p>The Iroquois, though, say the issue has never been about greed or power. In fact, they have pledged not to evict any landowners. What they say is at stake is redressing ancient wrongs and securing a better future for their descendants.</p>
        <p>So it was all the more symbolic when about 50 chiefs from the Iroquois nations convened a rare meeting in March just south of Syracuse at the sacred longhouse that is the spiritual and political heart of the Iroquois -- or, as they prefer to be called, Haudenosaunee.</p>
        <p>While the formal agenda, conducted solemnly in Iroquois languages, focused on selecting new Mohawk leaders, the informal discussion swirled around the nation-by-nation status of their claims.</p>
        <p>''Our people have been waiting a long time for this,'' said Chief Oren Lyons of the Onondaga Nation. ''This is not something we just made up.''</p>
        <p>During the late 1700's and early 1800's, New York State bought or seized most Iroquois properties without Congressional ratification, thereby violating the Federal Trade and Intercourse Act of 1790. Yet for years, the Iroquois failed to reverse these deals, stymied by discrimination and legal obstacles, said Robert W. Venables, a senior lecturer in the American Indian program at Cornell University.</p>
        <p>In 1970, the Oneidas became the first Iroquois nation to file a land claim in federal court. And in 1985, the Supreme Court sided with the Oneidas, in a 5-to-4 decision concerning a test case that named Oneida and Madison Counties as defendants and claimed only 900 acres.</p>
        <p>At that point, the state and the Oneidas began settlement talks, which yielded mostly accusations of foot-dragging. Then, in December 1998, the Oneidas and the Justice Department, hoping to pressure the state and the two counties, moved to name 20,000 landowners as defendants.</p>
        <p>People noticed.</p>
        <p>''There has been much more activity in the last few months than in all the years previous,'' said Richard Rifkin, a deputy state attorney general, referring to all the claims.</p>
        <p>The landowners' predicament has prompted officials like Governor Pataki, Senator Charles E. Schumer and Representative Sherwood L. Boehlert to ask the Justice Department to drop the 20,000 landowners from the Oneida suit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki, for instance, sent a pointed letter to President Clinton in early April, accusing the administration of offering ''unconditional support'' to a tribe that held residents ''hostage under clouded real estate titles and the constant threat of eviction, while systematically executing a plan to amass large quantities of land upon which it pays no real estate taxes, evades all state and federal environmental and land use regulations, and wages a war of unfair business competition against the law- abiding, taxpaying business owners in central New York.''</p>
        <p>And in the Senate campaign, both Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani of New York and Mrs. Clinton have sympathized with the landowners, though neither has discussed the issue at length.</p>
        <p>In recent months, an Oneida settlement seemed close, thanks to the diligence of a court-appointed mediator, Ronald J. Riccio: a proposal of $500 million for the three branches of the Oneidas (the others are in Wisconsin and Ontario), as well as a cap on how much land the New York Oneidas could eventually acquire to buttress their current territory of 12,000 acres.</p>
        <p>But several weeks ago, the talks collapsed, as the Oneidas rebuffed the state's demand for 25 percent of the revenue from the Oneidas' hugely profitable Turning Stone casino east of Syracuse. So a trial may begin this summer before Judge Neal McCurn of Federal District Court in Syracuse.</p>
        <p>To date, the only land claim to go to trial in New York has been the Cayuga case.</p>
        <p>In 1980, the Cayugas, who have no land in New York, filed a claim for 64,000 acres in Seneca and Cayuga Counties. In February, a jury awarded them $37 million in a decision that stunned the Cayugas, who had appraised the land at $660 million. But a second phase of the trial is set to begin in July, and the Cayugas may challenge the award.</p>
        <p>In northeastern New York, the struggling Mohawks claimed 15,000 acres in 1985, mostly in St. Lawrence and Franklin Counties, as well as Barnhart Island -- the site of the New York Power Authority's Robert Moses-Robert H. Saunders hydroelectric dam.</p>
        <p>For years, the claim stalled, in part because of New York's desire to collect taxes from non-Indians who buy goods on all reservations. In recent months, though, the claim has become linked to the tribe's attempts to build a casino complex at the Monticello Raceway in the Catskills. That project is now in doubt, with the Mohawks mired in internal politics and juggling separate deals with competing developers.</p>
        <p>''It just adds some significant elements of confusion to what was already a confusing situation,'' Mr. Rifkin said.</p>
        <p>No less confusing are the Senecas, who live on three reservations and have two separate governments in western New York. They are claiming land in different areas, too, with the big prize being Grand Island, a middle-class Buffalo suburb, population 18,500, in the Niagara River.</p>
        <p>The Senecas filed their claim for roughly 18,000 acres in 1993. Not much happened, though, until late March, Mr. Rifkin said, when the state filed a motion to dismiss the case, based on old maps disputing the Senecas' historic claim.</p>
        <p>And now, it is the Onondagas' turn.</p>
        <p>The Onondagas plan to file a claim of about 64,000 acres, which would include Syracuse and Onondaga Lake, one of the most polluted lakes in the country. At the same time, the Onondagas -- traditionalists who oppose gambling -- want to help clean up the lake and champion projects to benefit their resource-poor nation of nine square miles, Chief Irving Powless Jr. said.</p>
        <p>''We know the land claim is going to cause some disruption, but we want to work with the community to minimize that,'' said Joseph J. Heath, a Syracuse lawyer who represents the Onondagas. ''We want to be different from the Cayuga and Oneida areas, where all of the politicians are acting as if they have hoods on their heads.''</p>
        <p>The Iroquois are not the only ones with land claims in the state: in 1986, the Stockbridge-Munsee band of Mohicans, who are now based in Wisconsin, filed a claim for six square miles,  within the Oneida claim.</p>
        <p>The Oneidas have challenged that claim, and nothing has happened for years, ''not even a phone call,'' said Sharon Greene-Gretzinger, tribal lawyer for the Stockbridge-Munsee band.</p>
        <p>Someday, land claims may also be filed by several groups without federal recognition, including the Shinnecocks and the Poospatucks on Long Island.</p>
        <p>But for now, the Iroquois claims have particularly unhinged residents in predominantly rural, working-class areas who sometimes talk about land as a family heirloom, not as a real estate commodity.</p>
        <p>It is not just a matter of the Iroquois asking for land that would quadruple the area of all current Indian holdings in the state. It is the specter of the Iroquois accruing land, removing it from the tax rolls and surrounding landowners and businesses in checkerboard fashion to where non-Indians feel compelled to sell out.</p>
        <p>There have been protest convoys decrying the ''special treatment'' of Indians, pickets of Indian-owned businesses, newsletters from landowner groups with articles titled ''Who were the first Americans? Who cares?''</p>
        <p>And the issue has become a big part of state politics. At a recent meeting of a new Syracuse group, the American Land Rights Coalition, Mr. Koziol and others discussed broader strategies, like lobbying trips to Washington, national alliances and get-out-the-vote endeavors.</p>
        <p>''It was a political issue in our local elections this last time, and, oh yeah, I see it having a great part in the elections this year,'' said Connie Tallcot, a bookstore owner in Union Springs, on Cayuga Lake. ''We're courting either party, and we don't care who helps us.''</p>
        <p>It has been enough of a cauldron that a Quaker group in Syracuse recently sponsored public forums to try to defuse tensions in anticipation of the Onondaga claim.</p>
        <p>''I definitely don't feel upbeat, because knowing what I know about the other land claims, it's not going to be an easy route,'' said Mary Teelin, a Syracuse nurse who has been active in landowner groups. ''No matter who wins the lawsuit, they'll appeal, and appeal, and appeal, and nothing is going to be resolved any time soon.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
