<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel Fears Security at Labs Hurts Foreign Hiring</title>
    <meta content="Y16LAB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Science Board</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glanz, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Bill (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDD113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel Fears Security at Labs Hurts Foreign Hiring</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES GLANZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glanz, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Science Board, panel of scientists and engineers that advises president and Congress, expresses concern that heightened security measures at federal laboratories may be damaging ability to hire and retain foreign-born minority scientists; Energy Seb Bill Richardson disputes contention that security measures are behind laboratories hiring difficulties; blames 'atmosphere of fear' generated by Congress (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A panel of scientists and engineers who advise the president and Congress issued a statement yesterday expressing concern that heightened security measures at federal laboratories appeared to be damaging their ability to hire and retain foreign-born and minority scientists.</p>
        <p>If the laboratories could not attract those scientists, who make up a large portion of the technical talent in the United States, the labs' abilities to perform tasks as diverse as ensuring the safety of the nuclear stockpile and cleaning up toxic wastes could be threatened, said the panel, the National Science Board.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A panel of scientists and engineers who advise the president and Congress issued a statement yesterday expressing concern that heightened security measures at federal laboratories appeared to be damaging their ability to hire and retain foreign-born and minority scientists.</p>
        <p>If the laboratories could not attract those scientists, who make up a large portion of the technical talent in the United States, the labs' abilities to perform tasks as diverse as ensuring the safety of the nuclear stockpile and cleaning up toxic wastes could be threatened, said the panel, the National Science Board.</p>
        <p>Energy Secretary Bill Richardson immediately disputed the board's contention that the security measures are behind the laboratories' hiring difficulties, pointing instead to ''an atmosphere of fear'' generated by Congress.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department, which runs the labs, ''is doing its best to strike the proper balance between protecting that which legitimately requires protection while encouraging the openness that science requires,'' Mr. Richardson said.</p>
        <p>Security requirements have been tightened at federal labs since Wen Ho Lee, a former nuclear scientist at Los Alamos National Laboratory, was arrested and charged with mishandling nuclear secrets more than a year ago. Rules involving close scrutiny of scientists' contact with foreign nationals, polygraph tests and limitations on scientific collaborations have been imposed.</p>
        <p>Some of the measures have been criticized as needlessly intrusive and unfairly burdensome to Asian and Asian-American scientists at the laboratories and are said to create a hostile and discriminatory workplace.</p>
        <p>The issue is a serious one, since, for example, more than a quarter of  doctorates in technical fields awarded in the United States each year are given to Asians or Asian-Americans.</p>
        <p>The statement from the National Science Board, which also governs the National Science Foundation, said the security concerns at the labs have led to a ''growing difficulty'' in attracting foreign-born and minority scientists ''because of perceptions based on nationality, ethnicity, or other characteristics.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Eamon Kelly, president emeritus of Tulane University and chairman of the science board, said: ''There's an accumulation of evidence that the current environment is becoming a detriment to the hiring of foreign-born and minority American scientists. This can have an impact on the integrity of the scientific process, which would be detrimental both to our national security and our economic growth.''</p>
        <p>He said that while the board was mindful of suspicion surrounding Asian scientists at federal laboratories, its concerns went further, covering all foreign-born scientists.</p>
        <p>Congress has also placed a moratorium on visits to the labs by scientists from numerous countries, except when special waivers are granted by Mr. Richardson. An Energy Department official said the routine paperwork generated by the security rules was ''overlaid with this sense of suspicion'' only because of the intrusion of needless restrictions imposed by Congress.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richardson said the security requirements by themselves did not discourage international collaborations or intimidate lab scientists. Rather, he said, ''It is Congress, by creating an atmosphere of fear, that has caused concerns among the foreign-born scientists.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
