<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Front Row</title>
    <meta content="16FRON$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199880"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Barney's Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellafante, Ginia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parkinson, Gregory</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1DD113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="767" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Front Row</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ginia Bellafante</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roundup of fashion industry news; New York designer Gregory Parkinson offers small collections of fanciful clothes; Barneys New York opens its Co-op shop at West 18th St, New York City; store offers weekend-oriented date clothes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Designer on the Move</p>
        <p>Gregory Parkinson is surely the only designer in New York, probably the only one in Milan, Paris or Antwerp, too, whose self-imposed bedtime is 8:30 p.m. Since he closed his Los Angeles shop three years ago and gave up putting celebrities in big gowns, Mr. Parkinson has led a hushed fashion life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Designer on the Move</p>
        <p>Gregory Parkinson is surely the only designer in New York, probably the only one in Milan, Paris or Antwerp, too, whose self-imposed bedtime is 8:30 p.m. Since he closed his Los Angeles shop three years ago and gave up putting celebrities in big gowns, Mr. Parkinson has led a hushed fashion life.</p>
        <p>After leaving Los Angeles, he returned to his native England before relocating to New York nearly two years ago, where he started designing whimsically patterned jackets, skirts and sweaters using old couture and upholstery fabrics and hand-dying them in his apartment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Parkinson's collections are tiny, with about 10 looks in each, but his clothes were immediately picked up by Barneys New York and Linda Dresner. Last year, Moet &amp; Chandon selected him to be in its  Bryant Park showcase of young talent. With his Fall 2000 collection, he tripled his orders over past seasons, he said.</p>
        <p>Susan Stone, the owner of Savannah, the stylish Santa Monica shop where Mr. Parkinson has developed a following, attributed his growing success to the fact that his clothes are, ''if not one of a kind, then close to it.''</p>
        <p>Barneys, Downtown Again</p>
        <p>With fashionably glossed concrete floors, rolling racks and enough Kiehl's products to keep an entire ZIP code's complexions glowing, Barneys New York opened its Co-op shop at 236 West 18th Street on Saturday. The store has the kind of weekend-oriented date clothes featured on the two Co-op floors of Barneys's Madison Avenue flagship. They are priced below Barneys's usual fare and are among the store's best sellers.</p>
        <p>The downtown version of the Co-op sits on a relatively untrafficked patch of Chelsea around the corner from the store's original Seventh Avenue site. It occupies the space where Barneys's semiannual warehouse sales are held. That tradition, oddly enough, will continue, with the Co-op closing for the six weeks of the year the warehouse sales take place.</p>
        <p>For the remaining 46 weeks, Co-op shoppers will have T-shirts, jeans and items like $300-plus suede skirts and beaded tank tops to try on in dressing rooms that, like the office bathrooms on ''Ally McBeal,'' are anomalously unisex. ''We wanted to make it more of a social thing,'' said David New, executive vice president for creative services at Barneys.</p>
        <p>The fact that there are men's clothes at all in the Co-op, as well as the store's industrial design, distinguish it from girlish shopping havens like Scoop and Calypso, which have fanned out all over the city and attract the kind of shopper who, in another era, would have looked toward the Co-op for things that weren't everywhere else.</p>
        <p>The main purpose of the new Co-op is to attract ''the downtown neighborhood customer who didn't come uptown,'' Judy Collinson, general merchandise manager of Barneys, said.</p>
        <p>Julie Brown, founder of a nonprofit children's services agency, Room to Grow, lives two blocks from the Co-op and visited it twice over the weekend. ''I liked having all the cosmetics,'' she said, but added that clothingwise, ''there wasn't much I could find that was useful. They should have reached out more to the person who doesn't want the slinky, beaded bias-cut dress or skirt.''</p>
        <p>Fashion Returns to Film</p>
        <p>An aging Italian designer whose name is a megabrand is having business problems. A brash young hip-hop star is aiming for fashion moguldom. Hip-hop star sets his sights on taking over the Italian house.</p>
        <p>Giorgio Armani's empire is not about to be bought by Puffy Combs, but they are the inspiration for two characters in a fashion film, ''Perfume,'' which finished shooting in New York last week. Paul Sorvino is the Italian designer; the Gap model and actor Omar Epps is the rapper.</p>
        <p>Nadia Leonelli, the producer, said the film, set for release next year, features intersecting stories a la ''Short Cuts,'' and all the acting is improvisational. Michael Rymer, an Australian director whose family is in the fashion business, decided to make ''Perfume'' after taking acting lessons in the improvisational technique.</p>
        <p>The movie, with Rita Wilson as an East Village designer, Michelle Williams as a runaway daughter of a fashion editor and Jeff Goldblum as a headhunter in search of new design talent, will take shape in the editing room, Ms. Leonelli said, adding, ''Right now, it's 10 movies.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
