<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Flyers Are Caught In a Game of Numbers</title>
    <meta content="16PHIL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199921"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Flyers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Philadelphia Flyers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EFD9113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="653" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Flyers Are Caught In a Game of Numbers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>VOORHEES, N.J., May 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Philadelphia Flyers players cite need to win second game of playoff series after losing first game to New Jersey Devils (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the second consecutive day, the Philadelphia Flyers' rookie goaltender, Brian Boucher, labeled the statistics documenting the Devils' dominance of the Flyers as junk.</p>
        <p>But after the Devils' 4-1 victory in Game 1 on Sunday in Philadelphia, Flyers wing Rick Tocchet indicated that the Devils had invaded the Flyers' psyche.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the second consecutive day, the Philadelphia Flyers' rookie goaltender, Brian Boucher, labeled the statistics documenting the Devils' dominance of the Flyers as junk.</p>
        <p>But after the Devils' 4-1 victory in Game 1 on Sunday in Philadelphia, Flyers wing Rick Tocchet indicated that the Devils had invaded the Flyers' psyche.</p>
        <p>To a man, the Flyers agreed today they could not afford to head up the New Jersey Turnpike down by 2-0 in the four-of-seven-game Eastern Conference finals.</p>
        <p>''We were down, 0-2, to Pittsburgh and came back,'' Boucher said, referring to the Flyers' second-round series with the Penguins. ''But I don't think you can expect that from a lot of series. That's why tomorrow night is a desperation situation for us. It's must-win.''</p>
        <p>Since the Devils upset the Flyers in six games in the 1995 Eastern Conference finals on their way to a Stanley Cup championship, the Devils have dominated the Flyers, especially at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>The 1995 series was the last time the teams met in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Since that time, according to the Elias Sports Bureau, the Devils and Flyers have played 26 regular-season games, with the Devils holding a 17-7-2 advantage.</p>
        <p>At Continental Arena, the Devils are 10-2-1 over the last five seasons. They are unbeaten in their last eight home games -- 7-0-1.</p>
        <p>Although the Flyers won four straight games, with three coming in Pittsburgh, to take the series against the Penguins, it would be difficult to win three from the Devils in Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>The Flyers have not won at New Jersey since March 25, 1997.</p>
        <p>''That's all you hear about here, how great they are,'' Tocchet said of the Devils after Sunday's loss.</p>
        <p>''That can get into your psyche. If we win Tuesday, maybe we get to change the psyche a little bit. You hear about our past record against them and how bad it is. It'd be nice to get a win, just to get that idea out of the way.''</p>
        <p>When asked today if he thought one victory against the Devils would be sufficient to end this discussion, Flyers Coach Craig Ramsay said, ''I doubt that very much.''</p>
        <p>A series victory would end the talk, however, and the Flyers are not short on confidence.</p>
        <p>At least, not yet.</p>
        <p>''We believe we can play against any team in any building,'' Ramsay said. ''It doesn't matter who.''</p>
        <p>John LeClair played down the statistical trend, too.</p>
        <p>''Because the only game that matters is tomorrow night,'' LeClair said. ''It's not a must-win. It never is until you're down three games. But it is an important game. We don't want to get down, 2-0, to these guys.''</p>
        <p>At least, they don't want to do that and then head back up the turnpike.</p>
        <p>''Personally, I don't know what the record is, nor do I care,'' Ramsay said. ''We can beat anybody, anywhere, when we play our game. Period.''</p>
        <p>As for all those statistics since 1995?</p>
        <p>''Junk,'' Ramsay said.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>ERIC LINDROS, who has not played since March 13 because of recurring concussions, was expected to fly from Toronto to Philadelphia on Monday night. Lindros was then expected to begin on- and off-ice workouts on his own on Tuesday. . . . KEITH PRIMEAU said he felt fine Monday after making a surprise return from a concussion for Sunday's Game 1. Primeau was injured in the opening minute of the final game of the Eastern Conference semifinal series against the Pittsburgh Penguins. . . . The Flyers issued a statement regarding heightened security at First Union Center, a day after a number of fights broke out in the stands during Game 1.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
