<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rumors That Suitors Are Ogling Nabisco Send Shares Higher</title>
    <meta content="Y16NAB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199900"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nabisco Holdings Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philip Morris Cos</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Danone Sa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cadbury Schweppes Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Icahn, Carl C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EFDB113BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rumors That Suitors Are Ogling Nabisco Send Shares Higher</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shares of Nabisco Holdings increase in response to article in The Wall Street Journal that number of companies including Philip Morris, Danone and Cadbury Schweppes have submitted preliminary bids to buy all or part of food business; so far, only Carl C Icahn has come out openly for Nabisco; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Investor interest perked up noticeably yesterday for Nabisco Holdings, the maker of Ritz crackers and Oreo cookies, and its parent, the Nabisco Group.</p>
        <p>On Wall Street, the price of Nabisco Holdings shares jumped $2.0625, to $46. And the Nabisco Group, which owns 80.6 percent of Nabisco Holdings but is saddled with potentially large liabilities from its days as a tobacco company, rose $3.375, to $23.0625. Fear of enormous damage awards resulting from class-action lawsuits has created a wide gap between the price of the food company and its parent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Investor interest perked up noticeably yesterday for Nabisco Holdings, the maker of Ritz crackers and Oreo cookies, and its parent, the Nabisco Group.</p>
        <p>On Wall Street, the price of Nabisco Holdings shares jumped $2.0625, to $46. And the Nabisco Group, which owns 80.6 percent of Nabisco Holdings but is saddled with potentially large liabilities from its days as a tobacco company, rose $3.375, to $23.0625. Fear of enormous damage awards resulting from class-action lawsuits has created a wide gap between the price of the food company and its parent.</p>
        <p>Shares of Nabisco Holdings increased in response to an article in The Wall Street Journal that a number of companies including Philip Morris, Danone and Cadbury Schweppes had submitted preliminary bids to buy all or part of the food business. Nabisco Holdings has directed its management to pursue strategies that would maximize shareholder return, including a sale of the company. Many expect the company to be sold by summer.</p>
        <p>Nabisco Holdings has said that no formal deadline exists for the submission of bids. But it has been widely assumed that interested parties had until yesterday to make a proposal. The process is not expected to be completed until sometime next month.</p>
        <p>None of the companies admitted having submitted an offer. But analysts said Nabisco's brands would be attractive to a wide range of potential buyers.</p>
        <p>''This is the best food asset that has been auctioned in over a decade, since Kraft was sold'' to Philip Morris, said John McMillin, an analyst at Prudential Securities. ''Whenever you get premium assets, you are going to get some interest.''</p>
        <p>Christopher Kircher, a Philip Morris spokesman, refused to comment on a possible bid. A spokesman for Cadbury Schweppes also declined to comment.</p>
        <p>In Paris, where Danone is based, Diane D'Oleon, a spokeswoman, said the company was in ''preliminary discussions'' with Nabisco about acquiring assets that fit in with Danone's core mineral water, dairy products and biscuits businesses.</p>
        <p>Analysts said that of the three, Philip Morris was most likely to be interested in acquiring all of Nabisco, and was best positioned financially to swallow the entire company.</p>
        <p>''They have the deepest pockets,'' said John O'Neil, an analyst at PaineWebber.</p>
        <p>Kraft is the world's second-biggest packaged food company behind Nestle. It had sales last year of $26.6 billion, more than three times the 1999 revenue of Nabisco Holdings.</p>
        <p>Nabisco's cookie and cracker business, which accounts for about half of an estimated operating profit of $605 million for this year, is probably attractive to Danone, analysts said.</p>
        <p>''They are the largest biscuit company in the world without a presence in the United States,'' said Jaine I. Mehring, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney. ''Having just divested their beer business, they are flush with cash and are down to the three core businesses that last week they said they are committed to growing.''</p>
        <p>Danone's biscuit portfolio includes the Lu and Britannia brands.</p>
        <p>Nabisco may also feel comfortable dealing with Danone: in the early 1990's the French company purchased some international businesses from what was then RJR Nabisco.</p>
        <p>Cadbury Schweppes is widely assumed to be interested in Nabisco's confectionary business, especially its LifeSavers and Breath Savers brands.</p>
        <p>''Cadbury is not a likely buyer of the whole thing,'' Mr. O'Neil said. ''A more likely scenario is that Danone and Cadbury combine for a bid to split the business, or Danone buying the whole thing and then selling the confectionary business to Cadbury.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Mehring said a joint bid was quite possible, and could involve a company that has not yet expressed an interest. ''I would not be at all surprised to see a Danone/Nestle bid,'' she said, ''because Nestle would love LifeSavers.''</p>
        <p>Thus far, Carl C. Icahn is the only party interested in Nabisco that has chosen to openly state his position.</p>
        <p>Mr. Icahn started the process earlier this year when he offered to pay $16 a share for the Nabisco Group. It was his fifth bid for the company in the last four years.</p>
        <p>In a regulatory filing last week, Mr. Icahn said he was willing to pay $22 a share, or about $6.5 billion, for the holding company. Currently, he owns just under 10 percent of the outstanding shares.</p>
        <p>There has apparently been some interest expressed in Nabisco Holdings by some financial investors. Recently Hicks, Muse, Tate &amp; Furst, the Dallas-based leveraged buyout firm, was rumored to be looking for a strategic partner to buy Nabisco Holdings.</p>
        <p>Analysts said that Mr. Icahn did not seem to have any interest in owning a food business.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Icahn is only interested in buying the holding company,'' Mr. O'Neil said.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Icahn is the only visible bidder for the Nabisco Group, the current wisdom on Wall Street is that he will not end up owning the company.</p>
        <p>The likely winner of an auction for the Nabisco Group is R. J. Reynolds Tobacco.</p>
        <p>RJR already assumes all of the tobacco-related liability that is attached to the Nabisco Group. As a consequence, it could buy the company that it had earlier spun off without assuming any additional cost or risk. That would likely happen after the food company was sold.</p>
        <p>''After a sale of the food company, which should be in excess of $50 a share, RJR could buy the estimated $11 billion in cash held by the holding company for about $8 billion, a nice benefit to its current $2.4 billion market cap,'' Mr. O'Neil said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mehring from Salomon Smith Barney noted that ''the idea RJR would be able to profit from its own liability is sort of laughable.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
