<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Serena Williams Marches On, Then Ducks</title>
    <meta content="30TENN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226423"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS: U.S. OPEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Serena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuerten, Gustavo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arthurs, Wayne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6D91630F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1202" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Serena Williams Marches On, Then Ducks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Serena Williams advances at United States Open tennis tournament; Gustavo Kuerten is upset by Wayne Arthurs; table of top results; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>White lines marked off the court inside Arthur Ashe Stadium, but Serena Williams arrived to defend her United States Open title as if stepping onto a dance floor, wearing a party dress from a Woodstock reunion.</p>
        <p>In a black mesh outfit cut low and high, with a fuchsia-colored tie-dyed print curving along provocative lines, Williams scrambled to put away points in hot-pink Pumas. But as impossible as she was to miss during her 6-3, 6-2 bludgeoning of Tina Pisnik yesterday, Williams managed to camouflage herself less than an hour later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>White lines marked off the court inside Arthur Ashe Stadium, but Serena Williams arrived to defend her United States Open title as if stepping onto a dance floor, wearing a party dress from a Woodstock reunion.</p>
        <p>In a black mesh outfit cut low and high, with a fuchsia-colored tie-dyed print curving along provocative lines, Williams scrambled to put away points in hot-pink Pumas. But as impossible as she was to miss during her 6-3, 6-2 bludgeoning of Tina Pisnik yesterday, Williams managed to camouflage herself less than an hour later.</p>
        <p>In a hallway outside of an interview room, Williams slipped inside of a vestibule, where she went unnoticed as Lisa Raymond exited an adjacent door and walked past her. ''I don't want to run into her,'' Williams admitted a few minutes later. ''Obviously, she's probably still not feeling great. It was a tough one to lose.''</p>
        <p>But Williams wasn't talking about a match. Just a week earlier, Raymond's lawyer argued in front of an arbitrator in Manhattan that she -- and not Williams -- had earned the right as the No. 1 doubles player to represent America on the four-woman Olympic team.</p>
        <p>In the past, the United States Tennis Association had picked the top doubles player to be the fourth person on the team. But this time, Coach Billie Jean King went against precedent and chose on singles rankings alone. And although the arbitrator Richard Jeydel called the  U.S.T.A.'s selection process unclear and misleading, he ruled last Wednesday that Williams would stay on the team with Lindsay Davenport, her sister Venus and Monica Seles.</p>
        <p>The outcome was devastating to Raymond. And perhaps most upsetting to her is that King, famous for fighting injustices against women, didn't come to her defense.</p>
        <p>''There's definitely an irony to that,'' Raymond said after dismissing Magdalena Grzybowska, 6-1, 6-0, on the Grandstand Court yesterday. ''Billie got her Dream Team.''</p>
        <p>America has a group capable of sweeping the medals, right down to the powerful doubles combo of Venus and Serena Williams. This is the intimidating team King wanted to assemble, the popular players the U.S.T.A. needs to promote the sport and the group NBC must be thrilled to have to boost the Olympic television ratings.</p>
        <p>It's win-win for everyone but the unassuming Raymond, a career wallflower on the Tour. Although Raymond is a top-25 singles player and dominant in doubles, she is more solid than sizzle on the tennis scene.</p>
        <p>''I think it's great we have the Williams sisters,'' Raymond said. ''I think it's great we have the Anna Kournikovas, the rivalries with the Williamses and Lindsay and Martina Hingis. You would just hope when you're making a decision like this, that would be put aside.''</p>
        <p>Of all the attention getters on the women's Tour, Serena Williams may be the hottest product. She is the one who rang the opening bell on the New York Stock Exchange Monday morning, the one with a doll created in her stylish image and the defending champion who turned everyone's head in her first-round match yesterday.</p>
        <p>With overhead smashes that made the crowd flinch at her might, with blistering forehands that clipped the lines, her powerful game was on display. As was her taste in a tennis dress she helped design.</p>
        <p>''It shows how well . . . how good I look, how well in shape I am,'' Williams said with a sly smile. ''It's just really flattering, I think.''</p>
        <p>Maybe the men will wear dresses next. As a sign of how anonymous the men's Tour has become, there was barely a buzz in Arthur Ashe Stadium when second-seeded Gustavo Kuerten was upset in four sets by  Wayne Arthurs of Australia.</p>
        <p>Here was the Tour's best hope to fill the void that will soon be created when Pete Sampras and Andre Agassi leave the stage. Here was the charismatic Brazilian with the colorful style and telegenic game. Here was the one player the Tour had heavily featured when officials kicked off a marketing campaign with the slogan ''New Balls, Please'' in an effort to promote the young stars. But the instant Arthurs slashed an ace by Kuerten on match point, the moment the curly haired French Open winner dropped his head in defeat, the marketing campaign aimed at the American audience during the Open suffered a humiliating hit.</p>
        <p>''No, I said to them, I don't want to be promoted,'' said Kuerten, who is an icon in Brazil. ''I'm already too much promoted. I want to be unknown. I don't want to go and people recognize me everywhere.''</p>
        <p>Some players are more comfortable with attention than others. Serena Williams seems to revel in it. At times during her match against Pisnik, she turned ordinary points into theater. Instead of a simple overhead, she cracked her racket like a whip as she crushed the ball for winners. Instead of giving up on a well-placed passing shot by the Slovene, she raced against the odds to reach it, if only to extend the point one stroke longer.</p>
        <p>Through it all, Williams put on a show for those assembled in Arthur Ashe Stadium, the site of her first -- and, so far, only -- Grand Slam title one year ago. If Williams feels any pressure from the hype around her, she isn't letting on. When told that John McEnroe was quoted as saying a good male college player or senior player could beat her, she just grinned.</p>
        <p>''You want a piece of me?'' Williams said, playfully challenging McEnroe. ''Obviously, men are stronger than women. He can throw down if he wants. I don't know. Who knows? It's interesting. It would be interesting to see where we stand on that.''</p>
        <p>Any match with Williams is usually quite a sight. Yesterday, everyone was riveted to one of the Tour's top entertainers.</p>
        <p>''It seems, wherever I go, there's a lot of attention on me, anyway,'' Williams said. ''It's like I'm used to it. It really doesn't change with the new outfit, the dolls, Stock Exchange bell. I'm kind of used to a lot of attention.''</p>
        <p>She can disappear when she wants, too. Raymond never saw Williams as she walked down the hall.</p>
        <p>''She's a really nice girl,'' said Williams, who was an unwitting participant thrown into the selection fray. ''She made it clear that she wasn't bringing the case against me; she just thought she should be able to go. It's completely understandable.''</p>
        <p>MATCH POINTS</p>
        <p>On Monday, the television ratings for USA Network received a 30 percent bump over last year's opening day at the United States Open, up from a 1.0 rating to a 1.3. . . . The second-seeded GUSTAVO KUERTEN's first-round exit marked only the second time since 1956 that the second-seeded man had lost in the first round. The only previous time came in 1994, when second-seeded GORAN IVANISEVIC was beaten by MARKUS ZOECKE of Germany.</p>
        <p>TENNIS: U.S. OPEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
