<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bloody Martini, Anyone?</title>
    <meta content="30DRIN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SIPS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wallse (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hesser, Amanda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4DB1F31F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bloody Martini, Anyone?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMANDA HESSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hesser, Amanda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peppar tomato served at Wallse in West Village is part martini and part Bloody Mary; recipe; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PERHAPS no other drink has been humiliated by interpretation the way the martini and the Bloody Mary have. For the serious drinker these days, even a straight one invites suspicion.</p>
        <p>The Peppar Tomato at Wallse in the West Village, however, could be the first (and only) exception, for it manages to be an interpretation that plays it straight. It is part martini and part Bloody Mary, with the best qualities of both.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PERHAPS no other drink has been humiliated by interpretation the way the martini and the Bloody Mary have. For the serious drinker these days, even a straight one invites suspicion.</p>
        <p>The Peppar Tomato at Wallse in the West Village, however, could be the first (and only) exception, for it manages to be an interpretation that plays it straight. It is part martini and part Bloody Mary, with the best qualities of both.</p>
        <p>There is the crispness and chill of the vodka -- quickly converted to a flash of alcoholic warmth on the tongue. It is joined by the familiar tomato and salt, and finally a pinch of heat at the back of your throat. It is as startling as it is delightful. It is clean yet meaty. Savory yet sweet. A martini yet a Bloody Mary.</p>
        <p>After a few sips -- which you will surely take in quick succession -- a sweetness sinks in. Not a cloying sweetness but a round, fresh sweetness like that of a ripe plum.</p>
        <p>The drink uses two kinds of vodka, but its foundation is tomato water, made with ripe beefsteak tomatoes, from the Greenmarket. Kurt Gutenbrunner, the chef at Wallse, purees them with salt and strains the mixture overnight in cheesecloth. What is left is a pale yellow juice, as thin as water, as concentrated and saline as oyster liquor.</p>
        <p>The bartender mixes the tomato water with Absolut vodka and Absolut Peppar vodka and lets in a drop of Tabasco and a dash of celery salt. Then he shakes it and shakes it, straining it into a chilled martini glass.</p>
        <p>The first sip, if you get it quickly enough, will be frothy, as a well-made drink should be.</p>
        <p>Then the salt will come. Then the sweetness.</p>
        <p>Soon it will be gone, and all that will be left is a question: Why on earth did he call something so lovely such a peculiar name?</p>
        <p>The Peppar Tomato is $10 at Wallse, 344 West 11th Street (Washington Street); (212)352-2300.</p>
        <p>PEPPAR TOMATO  Adapted from Wallse  Time: 15 minutes, plus 2 hours for straining the tomatoes</p>
        <p>2 pounds very ripe, fragrant tomatoes, cored and cut into chunks</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon sea salt  1 tablespoon chopped lemon thyme or lemon grass  4 ounces pepper vodka  4 ounces vodka</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon celery salt  4 drops Tabasco  Yellow, red and green cherry tomatoes, for garnish.</p>
        <p>1. In bowl of a food processor, combine  tomatoes, sea salt and lemon thyme. Puree  tomatoes for about 1 minute. Line a colander with cheesecloth, allowing cloth to overhang by several inches. Set colander over a bowl, and pour in tomato mixture. Tie ends of cheesecloth together, and set aside to drip for 2 hours.</p>
        <p>2. If necessary, twist cheesecloth to extract any remaining juice. Set bowl of tomato water aside.</p>
        <p>3. In a shaker filled with ice, combine pepper vodka, vodka, celery salt, Tabasco and 2 cups tomato water. Shake well, and strain into four martini glasses with cherry tomatoes.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>SIPS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
