<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="30FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226393"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E0DB1630F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1269" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>U.S. Agencies Divided Over Missile Defense  Senior officials at the Pentagon and the State Department said the two agencies were sharply divided over whether and how to move ahead with construction of a limited national missile defense. The dispute is rooted in legal interpretations of when the United States would have to give formal notice to Russia that it was violating the Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty of 1972, most likely involving construction of radar sites.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>U.S. Agencies Divided Over Missile Defense  Senior officials at the Pentagon and the State Department said the two agencies were sharply divided over whether and how to move ahead with construction of a limited national missile defense. The dispute is rooted in legal interpretations of when the United States would have to give formal notice to Russia that it was violating the Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty of 1972, most likely involving construction of radar sites.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Colombia Faults Drug Demand  President Andres Pastrana said his country could not stem international drug trafficking until the United States and other countries did more to control their peoples' appetite for drugs. He spoke on the eve of President Clinton's arrival to open a $7.5 billion plan to fight trafficking.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>American Held in Philippines  Muslim rebels seized Jeffrey Craig Schilling, 24, on a remote island and threatened to kill him if the United States did not meet unspecified demands. Washington condemned the kidnapping and demanded Mr. Schilling's release. Officials denied a rebel claim that he is a spy.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Plea for Jailed American  The wife of Edmond Pope, left, who has been jailed in Russia for five months on espionage charges, went to Moscow with her congressman to press Russia to let Western doctors examine her husband, who has bone cancer. After a prison visit, she said he ''is not doing very well.''</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Clinton Meets Mubarak in Cairo  President Clinton tried to build Arab support for a Middle East peace in an hourlong meeting with the Egyptian President, Hosni Mubarak.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Myanmar Dissident Stays Put  The pro-democracy leader Daw Aung San Suu Kyi spent her sixth day camped in her car near a country town in a symbolic attempt to travel to meet supporters. The Burmese military is blocking her way.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Minister Resigns in France  Jean-Pierre Chevenement, a pivotal figure in the socialist-led coalition of Prime Minister Lionel Jospin, stepped down as interior minister, citing a plan to end decades of separatist violence in Corsica. Mr. Chevenement has argued for several weeks that Mr. Jospin's plan threatens the unity of France.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-21</p>
        <p>U.S. Told to Yield Files In Nuclear Secrets Case  A federal judge ordered the government to turn over what could amount to thousands of pages of classified internal documents to help him determine whether there is evidence that the former Los Alamos nuclear scientist Wen Ho Lee was unfairly singled out for prosecution because he is Chinese-American.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Racketeer Law Applies to Police  A federal judge has ruled that the government's anti-racketeering statute, created to deal with drug bosses and organized-crime figures, can be used in lawsuits against the Los Angeles Police Department, which is struggling with scandal.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Judge Faults Texas Medicaid  A federal judge has ruled that Texas' system for administering preventive medicine and other health care for children in Medicaid programs is badly flawed, and he has ordered the state to make improvements.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Medical Marijuana Ban Remains  The Supreme Court continued a ban on the distribution of marijuana for medical purposes in California.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Ready for Prime Time  Gov. George W. Bush, disputing suggestions that he was hesitant to commit to prime-time presidential debates, said he wanted all the debates with Vice President Al Gore to be during evening hours, when television audiences are largest.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Gore Focuses on Health Care  Vice President Al Gore, campaigning in New Mexico, emphasized his plan for providing health care coverage for the country's 11 million uninsured children.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Lieberman Elaborates on Faith  Senator Joseph I. Lieberman sought to explain his call for a greater role for religion in public life by saying he meant it as a matter of public discourse, not policy, adding he does not consider those who are not religious to be amoral or unfit for office.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Clinton Challenges Penalty  President Clinton's lawyers said in Arkansas court papers that even if he did lie under oath to a federal judge about his relationship with a White House intern, disbarment would be too strong a penalty.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Expanding the Population  An influx of Asians and Hispanics eager to fill new construction and service-industry jobs in Las Vegas helped make Nevada the fastest-growing state in the 1990's, new government figures show.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>Study Questions Benefits Of Welfare Fingerprinting  A study conducted for New York State government three years ago found no evidence that electronic fingerprinting of welfare applicants had had any significant effect in preventing fraud. Officials said the study was flawed and is now outdated, and they dispute its findings.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>CBS Headquarters May Be Sold  Viacom, which acquired CBS this year, is said to be planning to sell Black Rock, the elegant granite-clad Midtown Manhattan skyscraper.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Doctor's Mental State Weighed  Dr. I. Kathleen Hagen, the New Jersey urologist charged with smothering her elderly parents, was being treated for manic-depression this time last year, records show. Her lawyers are developing a defense based on her mental condition.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>Rise in Minority Enrollment  The first freshman class selected for Florida's state college system since Gov. Jeb Bush ended race-based admissions last year has shown an increase of 12 percent in minority enrollment. Mr. Bush said the figures proved diversity could be achieved without affirmative action. Critics said one year's enrollment was insufficient for such a declaration.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Freeing Up Class Space  Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy ordered the city's 32 superintendents to evict any nonprofit groups, community organizations or police offices from schools if they were not needed for student instruction.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>Tracking German 'Communazis'  The F.B.I. spied on hundreds of German writers -- Jews and non-Jews -- who had fled Hitler, intercepting mail and sometimes keeping tabs on their sex lives, a coming book by an Ohio State professor says.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Williams Opens Title Defense  Serena Williams, the defending United States Open champion, beat Tina Pisnik, 6-3, 6-2.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-19</p>
        <p>A Swiss Move on Wall Street  Credit Suisse, a big Swiss bank, is expected to announce today that it plans to buy the investment firm Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette for about $12.8 billion, or $90 a share.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Ruling Against Ford  A California judge largely agreed with complaints that Ford knowingly installed defective ignition mechanisms in nearly two million vehicles produced from 1983 to 1995. The judge said he would issue orders ''compelling recall and repair.''</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Inquiry Into Tire Failures  Ford said its chief executive and president, Jacques Nasser, had declined invitations to testify before Congressional committees investigating tire failures, mainly on Ford Explorers. But Bridgestone/Firestone said its chief executive, Masatoshi Ono, would testify, although he speaks limited English.</p>
        <p>C19</p>
        <p>Executive Shake-Up at CNN  Richard N. Kaplan, president of United States news-gathering operation since 1997, is expected to announce today that he is leaving the network. CNN executives are planning a major reorganization of management, reflecting dissatisfaction with the channel's weak ratings in the absence of breaking news.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-10</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: Mr. Ray's ill-timed report, Congressional endorsements, a risky American course in Colombia, caveat investors.  Columns: Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>C20</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
