<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rafter, A 2-Time Champion, Is Ousted</title>
    <meta content="30OPEN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS: U.S. OPEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rafter, Patrick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blanco, Galo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3D81630F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rafter, A 2-Time Champion, Is Ousted</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patrick Rafter loses to Galo Blanco at United States Open tennis tournament; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Patrick Rafter lives on the tortured edge when his matches turn into a test of wills. In the murky hours of midnight at the United States Open, Rafter has crafted such a legacy. He will have to pack it home with him, back to Australia, a sour parting gift from early this morning.</p>
        <p>For the third consecutive year, Rafter opened the United States Open with a five-set match. But unlike last year, when he defaulted after the first game of the fifth set to Cedric Pioline with a torn rotator cuff and was forced into a five-month recuperation, Rafter did not take himself out of the tournament last night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Patrick Rafter lives on the tortured edge when his matches turn into a test of wills. In the murky hours of midnight at the United States Open, Rafter has crafted such a legacy. He will have to pack it home with him, back to Australia, a sour parting gift from early this morning.</p>
        <p>For the third consecutive year, Rafter opened the United States Open with a five-set match. But unlike last year, when he defaulted after the first game of the fifth set to Cedric Pioline with a torn rotator cuff and was forced into a five-month recuperation, Rafter did not take himself out of the tournament last night.</p>
        <p>Galo Blanco, 23, of Spain did.</p>
        <p>Rafter, the United States Open champion in 1997 and 1998 and a Wimbledon finalist this year, is ranked 20th in the world. He entered last night's match unseeded for the first time since 1996. Despite his shoulder pain, Rafter came in confident. He owned a 13-3 record in five-set matches, having won 12 of his last 13.</p>
        <p>Blanco had not won a five-set match in his career and has just one title to his name. But at 12:07 this morning he won his first on his biggest stage, outdueling Rafter to the final point, 7-6 (3), 2-6, 6-3, 1-6, 7-6 (5) on Arthur Ashe Stadium Court. ''This was my best match, my most important match in my life,'' Blanco said. ''I'm so happy for that.''</p>
        <p>Blanco is ranked 114th but did not play like the same man who had never advanced further than the second round in five years at the United States Open.</p>
        <p>He was not intimidated as the players traded momentum, sets and points all night. Therefore, it seemed only fitting that the match would end the way it began, on a tie breaker. Rafter served 24 aces, and played his typical attacking serve and volley style. Blanco, who served 17 aces, stayed back and was calm.</p>
        <p>''I made a lot of unforced errors;  when the match gets tight, I'm generally solid in making good shots,'' Rafter said. ''Tonight it was just far too many errors. I just wasn't hitting the ball well. I found it hard to pick the ball up on volleys, returns and ground strokes. I just missed a lot of the fundamentals. My game was off.''</p>
        <p>Rafter and Blanco's late-night theater proved the most dramatic of the day, following two young upset hopefuls who fizzled in the early evening.</p>
        <p>Harel Levy and Andy Roddick unleashed their cross-court forehands with the adrenaline of first-timers, smoking winners and celebrating grandly. At times, no more so than in their euphoric second-set victories, these Open rookies were brilliant against their former top-20 ranked opponents, offering an enticing glimpse to the future.</p>
        <p>Levy, a 22-year-old lanky Israeli qualifier making a stir on the ATP Tour, matched ground strokes with Michael Chang, not intimidated by the player he watched win the French Open 11 years ago.</p>
        <p>Roddick, the freckle-faced top junior in the world given a wild-card berth into the main draw, served and volleyed against Albert Costa last night, displaying power that belied his slight frame.</p>
        <p>But the two peaked too soon last night, showing they had barely approached the summit in their careers. Chang, showing that his career is not yet finished, downed Levy, a qualifier who has jumped to 68th in the world, 6-2, 3-6, 6-4, 6-4. Costa, the Spanish clay-court specialist, outlasted Roddick, from Boca Raton, Fla., 6-3, 6-7 (5), 6-1, 6-4.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, 12th-seeded Anna Kournikova, who has yet to win a pro tournament, won an uneven first-round match over Holly Parkinson, 6-2, 6-3, in the early night match.</p>
        <p>Chang, 28, who plummeted out of the top 10 in the last two years, exhibited his resurgence, as he has climbed to No. 25 in the world after winning the Los Angeles tournament this past July.</p>
        <p>TENNIS: U.S. OPEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
