<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="30MBRF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226468"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5D81630F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1813" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>PRINCETON: SMOKING BAN OVERTURNED  A Superior Court judge in Mercer County struck down Princeton's new antismoking regulations yesterday. The ban, approved in June by the Princeton Regional Health Commission, would have been the strictest antismoking ordinance in the state, prohibiting smoking in Princeton and Princeton Township bars, restaurants and workplaces. The National Smokers Alliance and three Princeton bars and restaurants challenged the ban. Judge Linda R. Feinberg ruled that the health commission did not have the authority to enact the ban.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>PRINCETON: SMOKING BAN OVERTURNED  A Superior Court judge in Mercer County struck down Princeton's new antismoking regulations yesterday. The ban, approved in June by the Princeton Regional Health Commission, would have been the strictest antismoking ordinance in the state, prohibiting smoking in Princeton and Princeton Township bars, restaurants and workplaces. The National Smokers Alliance and three Princeton bars and restaurants challenged the ban. Judge Linda R. Feinberg ruled that the health commission did not have the authority to enact the ban.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>TRENTON: H.M.O. LAWSUITS  Patients should be able to sue their H.M.O. insurance providers for claims of medical malpractice, a ranking Republican lawmaker said yesterday. Senate President Donald T. DiFrancesco, a Republican of Union County, said that the right to sue was a key point in a package of health care bills he planned to make public today. Another provision would require binding arbitration in disputes with patients. Mr. DiFrancesco has said he is considering a run for governor when Gov. Christine Todd Whitman leaves office at the end of her second term.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: HOUSING AGENCIES SUE H.U.D.  Three public housing agencies in New York are suing the federal Department of Housing and Urban Development and its head, Secretary Andrew M. Cuomo, for not complying with a federal law to provide financial assistance to maintain thousands of low-income apartments throughout the state. The lawsuit was filed yesterday in United States District Court in Manhattan by the housing authorities of New York City, Auburn and Plattsburgh. H.U.D. said in a written statement that it would be illegal ''to try and make up that shortfall by federalizing those units.''</p>
        <p>Edward Wong (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: HELP SOUGHT IN SEARCH FOR MOTHER  The police are asking for help in finding the mother of a newborn boy abandoned on a subway platform at 14th Street on Monday night. The baby was wrapped in an extra-large adult-size black fleece pullover with a Compaq logo on the left breast. The passenger who discovered him called 911 and the baby was taken to St. Vincents Hospital and Medical Center, where he is listed in good condition.</p>
        <p>Elissa Gootman (NYT)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: BODY FOUND  The badly decomposed body of a man was found in a park in Canarsie yesterday by two golfers who went to collect their stray balls from the tall weeds, the police said. The park, the Monroe Cohen ball field, is at Seaview Avenue and East 105th Street near the Belt Parkway. Sgt. Elias Nikas, a police spokesman, said it was impossible to immediately discern the dead man's age or race.</p>
        <p>Andy Newman (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE BRONX: INMATE CHARGED IN PLOT  A Rikers Island inmate awaiting trial in the 1999 kidnapping of a woman has been charged with trying to hire someone to murder her, prosecutors said yesterday. The inmate, Dany Castillo, 25, is at Rikers on charges that he kidnapped the woman in October and demanded a ransom of 100 kilograms of cocaine from her husband, prosecutors said. (She was rescued by the police.) Last month, according to charges on which Mr. Castillo was arraigned yesterday, he called a detective whom he believed to be a hit man and offered him half a kilogram of cocaine, worth about $10,000 wholesale, to kill the woman.</p>
        <p>Andy Newman (NYT)</p>
        <p>ROCHESTER: HOSPITAL LIABLE IN WOMAN'S DEATH  Genesee Hospital must pay $1 million to the husband of a woman who died after an emergency room physician diagnosed her damaged aorta as muscular-skeletal pain. A Supreme Court jury in Rochester gave the award to Steven Stewart, who sued the hospital for the wrongful death of his wife, Donna, 30, in 1996. After complaining of severe back pain, she was taken to the hospital, where a doctor gave her a sedative, which relieved some of her pain, and discharged her. She died 10 minutes later when her aorta ruptured.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: CHARITIES LOSE ON PHONE SOLICITATIONS  Connecticut charities that used paid telemarketers last year ended up with only 34 cents of every dollar raised by them, according to records. Attorney General Richard Blumenthal said on Monday that about $3.8 million of the $11.2 million raised by phone solicitors actually went to the charitable organizations, which he said was unacceptable. ''Most organizations should organize their volunteers so that they won't need a solicitor,'' Mr. Blumenthal said. The average of 34.18 percent of the money going to charities is the highest return recorded in the 13 years this survey has been conducted.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>BRANFORD: FIRE DEPARTMENT FINED  The state has again fined the Branford Fire Department for alleged safety and training violations similar to the problems cited after a volunteer firefighter, Edward Ramos, died in a warehouse fire in 1996. The department was cited for failure to keep track of personnel, especially after firefighters have entered a burning building. The fire chief, Peter Buonome, said on Monday that the department planned to contest the fine.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NORTH STONINGTON: TRIBAL RECOGNITION  The federal government will not investigate claims that the director of the Bureau of Indian Affairs has a conflict of interest in the federal recognition case of the Paucatuck Eastern Pequot and Eastern Pequot tribes. Officials in North Stonington, Ledyard and Preston have asked that Kevin Gover, the director, be barred from the case because he once served as a lawyer for another Connecticut tribe. But the Office of the Inspector General ruled Monday that the towns had failed to show how a conflict resulted from Mr. Gover's former position.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CALENDAR</p>
        <p>Today  BUS FARE MEETING  The New Jersey Department of Transportation holds a meeting on a proposed 2001 fare increase for private bus companies. Fourth floor east conference room, 225 East State Street, Trenton, 10 a.m. Information: (609) 292-5203.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
