<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CNN's Chief of Domestic News Expected to Announce Resignation</title>
    <meta content="Y30CNN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226418"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cable News Network</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaplan, Richard N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EFDA1630F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CNN's Chief of Domestic News Expected to Announce Resignation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard N Kaplan is expected to resign as president of US news-gathering operation of CNN, which is planning a major reorganization of its management in view of declining ratings; there are conflicting reports on whether Kaplan is leaving on his own accord or if he has been asked to leave (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Richard N. Kaplan, who has been the president of CNN's United States news-gathering operation since 1997, is expected to announce today that he is leaving the network, executives close to the situation said yesterday.</p>
        <p>CNN executives are also planning to announce a major reorganization of its management, reflecting dissatisfaction with the channel's inability to turn around its weak ratings in the absence of breaking news.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Richard N. Kaplan, who has been the president of CNN's United States news-gathering operation since 1997, is expected to announce today that he is leaving the network, executives close to the situation said yesterday.</p>
        <p>CNN executives are also planning to announce a major reorganization of its management, reflecting dissatisfaction with the channel's inability to turn around its weak ratings in the absence of breaking news.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaplan's resignation comes at a particularly difficult time for CNN, a unit of Time Warner Inc., leaving its leadership unclear during a presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>CNN's ratings have been sliding precipitously recently, and its parent company is about to complete its merger with America Online.</p>
        <p>News of Mr. Kaplan's departure began circulating through CNN late yesterday afternoon and took many on his staff by surprise. There were conflicting reports as to whether he was leaving on his own accord or if he had been asked to leave.</p>
        <p>But CNN executives made it clear last night that although they regarded Mr. Kaplan as a talented producer, they had been unhappy with his management of budgets and his occasionally explosive temper.</p>
        <p>His duties will be divided among a number of executives. Tom Johnson, the chairman of CNN, will continue in his position, with Eason Jordan formerly of CNN International taking over as the chief news executive. Phil Kent of Turner Broadcasting International will become the chief operating officer. Jim Walton, the president of the sports division, will head the network group for the United States. Chris Cramer, a former BBC news executive, will take over the international group.</p>
        <p>The changes are being instituted by Terence F. McGuirk, the chief executive of the Turner Broadcasting System and a longtime and trusted lieutenant to Ted Turner, the founder of CNN. Amid lagging CNN ratings, Mr. McGuirk, aided by Steven Heyer, the president of TBS and former head of Booz Allen's media group, had instituted a sweeping evaluation of the network. They are devising a plan to start a major marketing and advertising campaign to try to counter its lagging ratings, which have fallen during slow news days, and because of additional competition from networks like the Fox News Channel and MSNBC.</p>
        <p>Executives last night did not offer details of their findings. Mr. Kaplan did not return phone calls. Mr. McGuirk, who is also close to Mr. Johnson, was said to be unhappy with what one executive called ''Mr. Kaplan's my-way-or-the highway approach.''</p>
        <p>Certainly, his tenure at the network has been rocky.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaplan joined CNN after a 17-year career as a producer at ABC News, where he won 34 Emmy Awards serving as executive producer of that network's leading news programs ''Nightline'' and ''World News Tonight.'' He also became the first executive producer of the ABC news magazine program ''Prime Time Live.''</p>
        <p>At the time of his hiring, CNN executives had said they expected Mr. Kaplan to help them combat their traditional lull in ratings during slow news cycles.</p>
        <p>Audiences tune to CNN when important news breaks but do not commit to a regular schedule of programs. When Mr. Kaplan took over CNN, he promised an antidote to that problem, instituting what executives called ''appointment viewing'' -- network-news-style programming that people would watch regularly.</p>
        <p>But his time at CNN had been marked by a series of confrontations over news and personnel decisions. The main program that Mr. Kaplan created, ''CNN NewsStand,'' was embroiled in a fiasco in 1998 when its very first program, called ''Tailwind,'' a report contending that United States forces had used nerve gas in Vietnam, was found to be full of errors and had to be retracted, complete with an on-the-air apology. Two producers were fired, and one executive resigned.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaplan's job was considered in jeopardy at the time, but he was absolved of the final responsibility for the broadcast by Mr. Johnson.</p>
        <p>A year later, the highly popular Lou Dobbs, the anchor of the network's most profitable program, ''Moneyline,'' quit after fighting with Mr. Kaplan over news coverage that interrupted Mr. Dobbs's program. ''Moneyline'' has since dropped in both ratings and profits, and Mr. Dobbs has been publicly wooed by NBC.</p>
        <p>At one point last year, CNN's founder, Mr. Turner, expressed interest in bringing Mr. Dobbs back to CNN, a move that Mr. Kaplan strongly opposed. Mr. Dobbs did not return.</p>
        <p>Many at CNN had expected that Mr. Kaplan would leave the network after the election campaign.</p>
        <p>The executives said that he was offered various other opportunities with Turner Broadcasting, but that he declined them. His departure will be effective today.</p>
        <p>They believe they are in good hands with the new team of Mr. Jordan and Mr. Kent.</p>
        <p>''Eason Jordan may be the strongest young television executive in the world,'' one senior Turner executive said.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
