<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turning Baking Into Cooking</title>
    <meta content="30SSID$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Salt</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Petrossian (Manhattan Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Conticini, Philippe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hesser, Amanda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Salt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E5DA1F31F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turning Baking Into Cooking</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMANDA HESSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hesser, Amanda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Use of salt on desserts is only one the ways in which Philippe Conticini, executive chef at Petrossian in Paris and New York, has blurred distinctions between baking and cooking (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR Philippe Conticini, the executive chef at Petrossian in Paris and New York, lavishing salt on desserts was a hurdle passed long ago. He has since moved on to putting tuna, coconut and lime zest into batter and serving it as cake.</p>
        <p>For him, it is a matter not of innovation, but of transcendence. He has blurred the distinctions between baking and cooking. And now, he is reversing the traditional logic, working from baking to arrive at cooking. Which is exactly how that tuna ended up in a cake and how a fabulously unusual menu is forming at the Petrossian Boutique and Cafe here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR Philippe Conticini, the executive chef at Petrossian in Paris and New York, lavishing salt on desserts was a hurdle passed long ago. He has since moved on to putting tuna, coconut and lime zest into batter and serving it as cake.</p>
        <p>For him, it is a matter not of innovation, but of transcendence. He has blurred the distinctions between baking and cooking. And now, he is reversing the traditional logic, working from baking to arrive at cooking. Which is exactly how that tuna ended up in a cake and how a fabulously unusual menu is forming at the Petrossian Boutique and Cafe here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Conticini, 37, has been interested in pastry nearly all his life. When he was a boy in Paris, he made cakes every Sunday. Eventually, his parents, restaurant owners, sent him to do apprenticeships. When he worked for Jacques Chibois, the pastry chef at Gray d'Albion in Cannes, he saw plated desserts for the first time. ''It was an extraordinary discovery for me,'' he said. ''It was like painting. It was a way to express myself.''</p>
        <p>Now, he expresses himself in terms unfamiliar to most pastry chefs. (When explaining how he often uses coconut juice as a hidden flavor in desserts, for instance, he said: ''You can use some yellow with green and you'll get blue. You can use some yellow with red and you get some orange. You use yellow every time, but you never see the yellow.'')</p>
        <p>In 1986, he and his father and his brother, a chef, had a restaurant in Paris. Working with his brother, he was finally able to understand the disjunction of their crafts. ''When I tasted his food,'' he said, ''I had many flavors in my mouth. And when I tasted my cakes, I did not have all that flavor. I wanted emotion in my mouth.''</p>
        <p>So he began experimenting with flavors outside the limited sphere of desserts. Now, at Petrossian's boutique, he is in the stratosphere. Strange desserts are fitted with strange names. The halva, a kind of sundae, is a wacky mixture of preserved apple, orange-blossom water, crepes, riesling jelly and whipped cream; there is no ice cream. The baicale combines lemon-flavored honey syrup, grapefruit, vanilla cream and pine nuts. There is a white chocolate cake with herbs, spices and bitter-almond jelly. Chocolate ice cream comes smothered with jam, herbs, spices and coconut juice, or with pistachio cream, cherries, popcorn and coconut.</p>
        <p>In these, Mr. Conticini said he wants people to have both intellectual pleasure and what he calls ''affective pleasure,'' those familiar childhood references like ice cream sundaes. To most people, the first reaction might just be confusion.</p>
        <p>''Why can you open your eyes and your spirit with your cooking and not with your pastry?'' he asked, passion and defense in his voice.</p>
        <p>What is most interesting about what Mr. Conticini is doing is not on his dessert list, but on his savory menu. There is a savory cake with chorizo, onions, olives and curry. A sandwich of white smoked salmon on rye is spread with eggplant caviar, Parmigiano-Reggiano and riesling jelly. It is tangy, buttery, sweet and fantastically odd.</p>
        <p>''I like to mix, and I like to discover new things,'' he said. ''I think I do that with everything in my life. Well, I don't do it with my wife.''</p>
        <p>Ultimately, Mr. Conticini may find that his innovations not only affect the world of baking, but that of cooking, too.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
