<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Slam in Seattle Jolts Nelson and Erases Pettitte's Gem</title>
    <meta content="30YANK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226476"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Devil Rays</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E2D81630F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1169" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Slam in Seattle Jolts Nelson and Erases Pettitte's Gem</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, Aug. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Boston Red Sox defeat Tampa Bay, 8-0; other American League games noted; tables; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like Boston's Pedro Martinez, Andy Pettitte flirted with a no-hitter tonight. But unlike Martinez, Pettitte did not engage in any brawls, there were no ejections -- and after Pettitte's no-hitter was broken up in the sixth, he suffered the loss when the Seattle Mariners came back for five runs in the eighth inning.</p>
        <p>Edgar Martinez hammered a grand slam off reliever Jeff Nelson with two outs in the eighth, giving Seattle a shocking 5-3 lead over the Yankees. The Mariners had lost 13 of their last 15 games, and the Yankees had won three in a row. Pettitte (16-7) had won seven straight games.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like Boston's Pedro Martinez, Andy Pettitte flirted with a no-hitter tonight. But unlike Martinez, Pettitte did not engage in any brawls, there were no ejections -- and after Pettitte's no-hitter was broken up in the sixth, he suffered the loss when the Seattle Mariners came back for five runs in the eighth inning.</p>
        <p>Edgar Martinez hammered a grand slam off reliever Jeff Nelson with two outs in the eighth, giving Seattle a shocking 5-3 lead over the Yankees. The Mariners had lost 13 of their last 15 games, and the Yankees had won three in a row. Pettitte (16-7) had won seven straight games.</p>
        <p>The 5-3 loss markedthe third time in their last 11 games that the Yankees blew a three-run lead and lost.</p>
        <p>Carlos Guillen broke up Pettitte's no-hitter with a bloop single with two outs in the sixth, but Pettitte was in command, leading by 3-0. He retired the first batter in the eighth, but allowed three consecutive singles to load the bases. Stan Javier then hit a sinking line drive in the direction of Luis Polonia, the left fielder broke late and just missed a sliding catch; one run scored.</p>
        <p>Yankees Manager Joe Torre summoned Nelson to relieve Pettitte, and Nelson struck out shortstop Alex Rodriguez for the second out. Nelson fell behind Martinez, two balls and no strikes, fired a fastball and Martinez drove it to the opposite field, about three rows into the right-field stands, thrilling the Safeco Field fans. It was the second home run surrendered by Nelson this season.</p>
        <p>Pedro Martinez was three outs from completing a no-hitter against Tampa Bay when the Yankees began their game here tonight. It may be that as Pettitte changed T-shirts in the clubhouse or got a cup of water or had a last look at the Seattle scouting reports, he might have seen the last few outs of that game, the hit by Devil Rays catcher John Flaherty that broke up Martinez's no-hitter.</p>
        <p>Pettitte might have had no-hitter on the brain when he took the mound, but there was no way he would expect to throw one himself, for he is not well suited to do so. Unlike Martinez or Randy Johnson, Pettitte does not overpower hitters and compiles few strikeouts. To the contrary, Pettitte is reliant on his sinkerball, his objective to get batters to beat this pitch into the dirt and get lots of ground-ball outs. Going into tonight's game, Pettitte had allowed more than a hit an inning, 172 hits in 161 innings, with just 96 strikeouts.</p>
        <p>But Pettitte was particularly sharp tonight, throwing harder than usual; on an average day, his fastball will be clocked at 88 to 89 miles per hour, and tonight, the radar gun readings were 91 to 92 m.p.h. All three types of his fastball were moving well: the sinker down and away, the cutter darting inside, the fastball boring down on batters.</p>
        <p>The Mariners could not merely wait for a fastball, either, for Pettitte mixed in a curveball at about 73 to 75 m.p.h. and a changeup of 82 to 83 m.p.h., the change of speeds confounding. Pettitte retired the first nine hitters he faced on four ground balls, two strikeouts and three fly balls -- and he seemed appeared annoyed, nonetheless, griping to catcher Chris Turner as he walked off the mound at the end of third.</p>
        <p>Pettitte walked Rickey Henderson on four pitches leading off the fourth, but Javier grounded to short to start a double play, and Scott Brosius gloved Rodriguez's hot smash to close the inning. Pettitte retired the Mariners in order in the fifth, the last out coming when Chris Widger flailed at a breaking ball. Pettitte had a 3-0 lead, he had great stuff and he was facing a team in the midst of a deep, depressing, debilitating slump; the possibility of a no-hitter appeared real.</p>
        <p>Joe Oliver popped a foul ball near the stands, and Jorge Posada -- playing first base -- reached over the hands of some fans to make a leaning catch. Eleven outs to go. David Bell popped to second; 10 outs.</p>
        <p>But Pettitte's preponderance for creating contact finally manifested itself, in the form of a fluke hit. The right-handed-hitting Guillen swung hard and looped a pop fly into short right field, far out of the reach of the three fielders who pursued it, and the Seattle fans -- suffering through the team's drought -- stood and cheered, their enthusiasm tinged with sarcasm. Pettitte's expression never changed; it was impossible to tell, from his body language, whether he realized he was throwing a no-hitter, if he was vested in the idea of creating history.</p>
        <p>No, he just got the ball back and concentrated on facing the next hitter. Henderson slapped a double into the right-field corner, but with Javier representing the potential tying run at the plate, Pettitte rebounded, enticing Javier to chase a cut fastball in the dirt.</p>
        <p>The Yankees scored all their runs early, rewarded for their patience against the Seattle left-hander Jamie Moyer. Bernie Williams singled with two outs in the first, and designated hitter Jose Canseco waited through a walk.</p>
        <p>Before the game, Roger Clemens remarked how difficult it is for opposing pitchers to get through this part of the Yankees' lineup now, knowing that a mistake could kill them. It wears on a pitcher, Clemens explained, and eventually, the increased tension causes a mistake.</p>
        <p>Canseco has 444 career home runs, David Justice has 34 homers, Glenallen Hill is averaging a home run for every seven at-bats since he joined the Yankees, Posada is on a pace to hit 30 homers. With their revamped lineup, the Yankees have 45 homers this month, most in the league.</p>
        <p>So Moyer got himself into trouble with the Canseco walk, and suffered the consequences. Justice ripped a single to drive home Williams, and after Hill got ahead in the count, three balls and one strike, before lining a single to left. Yankees 2, Seattle 0.</p>
        <p>The Yankees added a run in the second, collecting three more walks; Moyer would allow seven in all, a career high, and last six innings.</p>
        <p>Over the last 46 games, the Yankees have knocked out opposing starters 12 times before the end of the fifth inning; only 13 pitchers have survived the seventh.</p>
        <p>Brett Tomko (7-4) gave up two hits in two innings to earn the triumph after replacing Moyer.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
