<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Popular Burmese Leader Tests Wills With Junta</title>
    <meta content="Y30BUR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/30/world/30BURM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Myanmar</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aung San Suu Kyi, Daw</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mydans, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Myanmar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Myanmar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4D61F31F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1122" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Popular Burmese Leader Tests Wills With Junta</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mydans, Seth</byline>
      <dateline>BANGKOK, Aug. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Burmese democracy leader Daw Aung San Suu Kyi remains camped out in her car at side of country road, in sixth day of standoff with authorities trying to prevent her from meeting with supporters outside capital; photo; map (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Her car has been shunted to the side of the road. The air has been let out of its tires. The military authorities say they are offering her food and medical care, but they are also making sure she is going nowhere.</p>
        <p>The pro-democracy leader of Myanmar, Daw Aung San Suu Kyi, has been camped in her car for six days now near a small country town in a symbolic attempt to travel to meet with her supporters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Her car has been shunted to the side of the road. The air has been let out of its tires. The military authorities say they are offering her food and medical care, but they are also making sure she is going nowhere.</p>
        <p>The pro-democracy leader of Myanmar, Daw Aung San Suu Kyi, has been camped in her car for six days now near a small country town in a symbolic attempt to travel to meet with her supporters.</p>
        <p>She has done this four times before, in 1998, sitting stubbornly in her small white Toyota for as long as 13 days at a time, unharmed but firmly prevented from carrying out her political activities.</p>
        <p>An official of her party, the National League for Democracy, described the standoff as a ''war of endurance.'' It is a phrase that applies equally well to her 12-year battle of wills with the military rulers of her country, the former Burma.</p>
        <p>''The story hasn't changed very much over the years,'' a Western diplomat said. ''It's a standoff between the government and Aung San Suu Kyi and her movement. It's perhaps worse to the extent that the government now seems engaged in an attempt to destroy her party definitively, once and for all.''</p>
        <p>As the years have passed and her party members have been jailed or forced to halt their political activities, Mrs. Aung San Suu Kyi's options have narrowed. She has been struggling just to keep her movement alive and to hold the attention of foreign governments that is perhaps her political lifeline.</p>
        <p>The Burmese military junta is equally stubborn.</p>
        <p>In 1988, when the people rose up against three decades of military repression, the army crushed huge demonstrations by force, taking hundreds of lives.</p>
        <p>In 1990, with Mrs. Aung San Suu Kyi under house arrest, her party won an overwhelming victory in a surprisingly free parliamentary election. The military reacted by annulling the results and tightening its grip on power.</p>
        <p>In 1995 she was freed from formal house arrest but found herself surrounded by security officers and restricted in her movements and political activities.</p>
        <p>When her husband, a British scholar, was dying of cancer two years ago, the government denied him permission to visit her, suggesting that it would be more appropriate for her to visit him abroad. She refused, convinced that the government would prevent her from returning, and he died without seeing her.</p>
        <p>Her current foray out of the capital, Yangon -- the former Rangoon -- demonstrates the weakness of her position as well as its strength. It shows how few options she has to challenge Myanmar's leaders but also how little she needs to do to draw international attention.</p>
        <p>''She needs to keep people, not only in Burma but the rest of the world, aware of the continuing repression and deprivation of rights in Burma,'' said Sunai Phasuk, a political scientist at Chulalongkorn University in Bangkok. Her gesture drew immediate support from the United States and Britain, as well as the London-based rights organization Amnesty International.</p>
        <p>''The United States condemns this abridgment of Aung San Suu Kyi's right to freedom of movement and her right to visit whomever she chooses,'' said Philip Reeker, a State Department spokesman. But beyond statements of support, there is little that foreign governments can do to affect the political situation in Myanmar. The United States has banned new investment there and barred visits from its leaders. The European Union has shunned Myanmar at international meetings.</p>
        <p>But Myanmar's leaders have only hunkered down, apparently comfortable with an international isolation that they first imposed on themselves in the early 1960's.</p>
        <p>In its public statements about the current confrontation, in the town of Dalla just across the river to the south of Yangon, the government has taken a lighthearted tone verging on ridicule.</p>
        <p>Asserting that ''security conditions'' do not permit her to travel farther, it portrays her -- and 14 supporters traveling with her in two vehicles -- as enjoying a pleasant rural interlude.</p>
        <p>''Daw Suu Kyi and her travel companions are still continuing taking a rest at Sarpachaun Ward of Dalla Town, a small but charming and scenic town which is a 10-minute boat ride from Yangon,'' read a statement issued on Monday. ''While Daw Suu Kyi visits some homes in Sarpachaun Ward, her travel companions and attendants enjoy visiting downtown Dalla as well as taking daily dips in Sarpachaun stream.''</p>
        <p>It said that a doctor and six medical assistants were standing by. And it suggested that she ''return home and continue her political activities in a more secure environment.''</p>
        <p>The government-controlled press joined the fray today, though it did not mention Mrs. Aung San Suu Kyi's attempted car trip, deriding her as a ''democracy princess'' and asserting, ''She'll go down the drain eventually.''</p>
        <p>The government also took the opportunity to argue against economic sanctions, which she and her party support, saying the sanctions had cost jobs in manufacturing and tourism.</p>
        <p>''Although the party claims to be promoting human rights,'' an official statement said, ''in reality the very rights of the people of Myanmar to enjoy a better and fuller life have been undeniably violated and abused by the very same people calling for democracy and human rights.''</p>
        <p>Photographs released by the government show two vehicles parked amid shrubbery, joined by a makeshift tent and surrounded by pink-shirted supporters, most of them members of the youth wing of her party.</p>
        <p>Witnesses said the cars were parked on a dirt trail about 180 yards off the main road, blocked from going further by two trucks. They told Agence France-Presse that the air had been let out of her tires and that party members were taking turns standing by her car with a large umbrella to shield Mrs. Aung San Suu Kyi from the hot sun.</p>
        <p>Calling the travelers ''a determined group,'' party members reached by telephone in Yangon said they were sending extra food, medicine and mosquito repellent in preparation for a long stay.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
