<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CBS's 'Black Rock' Building Is Said to Be for Sale</title>
    <meta content="30CBS.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Other Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Viacom Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Jayson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE5D91630F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1053" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CBS's 'Black Rock' Building Is Said to Be for Sale</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blair, Jayson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Viacom reportedly plans to sell Black Rock, landmark New York City office building built for its CBS unit; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Viacom, which acquired CBS this year, plans to sell Black Rock, the elegant granite-clad skyscraper built to symbolize the broadcasting company's view of itself as ''the Tiffany network,'' according to officials involved in the discussions.</p>
        <p>The building could be placed on the market as early as next month, the officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Viacom, which acquired CBS this year, plans to sell Black Rock, the elegant granite-clad skyscraper built to symbolize the broadcasting company's view of itself as ''the Tiffany network,'' according to officials involved in the discussions.</p>
        <p>The building could be placed on the market as early as next month, the officials said.</p>
        <p>The 38-story tower, at 51 West 52nd Street in Midtown, could fetch up to $370 million, according to real estate industry estimates. Viacom executives said that they were in the early stages of discussions with a real estate brokerage firm and that any potential sale would not involve moving many -- if any -- CBS employees. But they said those plans could change. If the building was sold with CBS continuing to occupy about half of it, the sale price would very likely be significantly reduced.</p>
        <p>The officials from Viacom and CBS, who spoke on the condition of anonymity, said that given the hot real estate market in that area of Midtown, near Rockefeller Center, selling Black Rock would be more profitable than continuing to lease it to other tenants.</p>
        <p>The 36-year-old building was placed on the market last year, but was taken off because the bids, which were about $300 million, were too low. But real estate industry officials say the company could get  significantly more for the building now, especially if it moves many CBS employees into other Viacom buildings.</p>
        <p>''This is a market with no vacancies, and they are one of the only significant blocks of space in Midtown Manhattan,'' said Darcy Stacom, the executive director for financial services at Cushman &amp; Wakefield, a commercial real estate brokerage firm in Manhattan. ''Clearly, the first time CBS went to market they were offering a fully leased building. If they are now going to offer an entire block of space, it will be an attractive investment opportunity.''</p>
        <p>If the building is sold without CBS as a tenant, Ms. Stacom estimates, it could garner as much as $425 per square foot, or about $369 million.</p>
        <p>Though Black Rock is a relatively young building, it was made a New York City landmark in 1997. Noted for its minimalist design and its somber, dark granite skin, Black Rock stands in stark contrast to the steel-and-glass towers nearby on the Avenue of the Americas. It has the distinction of being the only skyscraper designed by the famous Modernist Eero Saarinen.</p>
        <p>The potential sale was first reported yesterday by Bloomberg News. Insignia/ESG, a commercial real estate company that has done business with Viacom, is the leading contender for the project, officials familiar with the discussions said.</p>
        <p>The move comes after decisions by the other two major networks, NBC and ABC, to move parts of their operations out of that section of Midtown. Each of the networks has been acquired in recent years.</p>
        <p>The building was built by William S. Paley, the late founder of CBS, in the 1960's, when the network was moving beyond its status as a premier broadcast network and expanding into films, magazines and theater production. It began serving as the CBS headquarters in 1968, a time when Walter Cronkite and other distinguished journalists kept the network's pre-eminence in news broadcasting unchallenged.</p>
        <p>To Paley, Black Rock was not just a building; it was a monument to the company's success.</p>
        <p>But management problems, competition from cable, and other factors all contributed to troubles at Black Rock. In 1987, CBS began retrenching and focusing the company more solidly on broadcasting. In 1981, CBS had 9,900 employees working in New York; by 1992 there were only 4,700.</p>
        <p>That year, CBS, which has studios on West 57th Street, began moving workers out of Black Rock and began leasing the building to law firms and other tenants. The company now occupies only 350,000 square feet in the 870,000-square-foot building.</p>
        <p>Black Rock, named for the Canadian granite used for its exterior and lobby walls, is the only skyscraper built by Saarinen, the architect of the Vivian Beaumont Theater and the butterfly-shaped T.W.A. terminal at Kennedy International Airport. It was one of the last projects designed by Saarinen, who died in 1961, three years before CBS moved in.</p>
        <p>A building must be 30 years old to become a New York landmark; that designation was given to Black Rock at age 33, in 1997. ''We did it with a group of buildings to get the best of the Modernist buildings,'' said Katy McNabb, a spokeswoman for the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission. ''We wanted to show people what they had to offer.''</p>
        <p>In its designation report, the commission called the building ''one of New York's premier post-World-War-II-era skyscrapers and one of the country's great works of modern architecture.'' The report said it was New York's first postwar reinforced-concrete skyscraper. Saarinen said his goal was to build a structure that was both elegant and ''the simplest skyscraper in New York.''</p>
        <p>Despite CBS's diminished presence at Black Rock in recent years, it has gone to great lengths to protect both the symbolism and architecture of the building, a notion that has comforted historic preservationists.</p>
        <p>Carol Willis, an adjunct professor of urban studies at the Graduate School of Architecture, Planning and Preservation at Columbia University, said that the dark color and the absence of interpretations in its facades made the building unique.</p>
        <p>''It was designed to be the simplest Modernist building in New York City,'' Ms. Willis said.</p>
        <p>Its entrances are on West 52nd and West 53rd Streets, creating the effect of an absolutely pure granite slab on the Avenue of the Americas. ''Certainly, it is one of the most elegant of the Modernist buildings,'' Ms. Willis added. ''It is self-consciously unlike the other Modernist buildings, with its somber quality and its minimalist style. It is not like the glass box.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
