<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wife Visits American Held by Moscow</title>
    <meta content="30MOSC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/30/world/30MOSC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226372"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pope, Edmond</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pope, Cheri</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peterson, John (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tyler, Patrick E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6DD1630F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="737" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wife Visits American Held by Moscow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tyler, Patrick E</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Aug. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cheri Pope and Repr John E Peterson visit Pope's husband, Edmond, who has been in jail in Russia for five months on espionage charges; asks Russia to allow Western doctors to examine Pope, who has bone cancer; Pres Clinton and other US officials continue to pressure Russia to free Pope, who was arrested for supposedly trying to buy classified plans for Russian torpedo system (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The wife of an American who has been in jail here for five months on espionage charges came here today with her congressman to call on the Russian government to let Western doctors examine her husband, who has bone cancer.</p>
        <p>The woman, Cheri Pope, looked shaken and fatigued after visiting Lefortovo Prison, where her husband, Edmond, a former naval intelligence officer, has been incarcerated since early April. He was arrested for supposedly trying to buy classified plans for a high-technology Russian torpedo system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The wife of an American who has been in jail here for five months on espionage charges came here today with her congressman to call on the Russian government to let Western doctors examine her husband, who has bone cancer.</p>
        <p>The woman, Cheri Pope, looked shaken and fatigued after visiting Lefortovo Prison, where her husband, Edmond, a former naval intelligence officer, has been incarcerated since early April. He was arrested for supposedly trying to buy classified plans for a high-technology Russian torpedo system.</p>
        <p>Some Russian press reports have identified the torpedo-propulsion system, the Squall, as the same one carried aboard the nuclear submarine Kursk, which sank on Aug. 12 in the Barents Sea, killing all 118 crewmen aboard.</p>
        <p>''Seeing my husband and having to leave him there was extremely difficult,'' Mrs. Pope said at a news conference, dressed in a gray suit and speaking in subdued and emotional tones. ''And now I have to go back to my room and call his mother and father and our sons and tell them that Ed is not doing very well.''</p>
        <p>Representative John E. Peterson, the Pennsylvania Republican who accompanied her, was more blunt. ''If his cancer has returned and we do not catch it soon,'' Mr. Peterson said, ''Edmond Pope will die.''</p>
        <p>Russian officials have said Mr. Pope, 54, has been examined 10 times and is not facing any imminent health threat.</p>
        <p>Last week, a Russian court denied Mr. Pope's request to be released to receive medical treatment while awaiting trial.</p>
        <p>United States Embassy officials have been allowed to visit Mr. Pope 11 times. The visit today was Mrs. Pope's second.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peterson castigated Russian authorities for arresting Mr. Pope over the attempted purchase of ''10 year old'' torpedo technology that the Russian government openly sells to foreign governments, most recently to Canada. Mr. Peterson asked that all details of the charges be made public.</p>
        <p>''Everyone in America knows that Ed Pope is not a spy,'' Mr. Peterson said. ''He is an independent businessman who has been working with the Russians for five to six years'' to develop and sell high-technology products. He warned that Mr. Pope's incarceration spelled ''a very bad day for the future of American-Russian business relations.''</p>
        <p>State Department officials in Washington have said President Clinton raised the plight of Mr. Pope in a call to President Vladimir V. Putin during the frantic rescue operation for the Kursk. Today, Mr. Peterson said that Mr. Clinton and Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright had been raising the issue of Mr.  Pope's ''unfair imprisonment''  ''each time they meet with a Russian official.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Russia's intelligence service, reached by telephone, said the agency would not comment on the charges nor on when a trial might start.</p>
        <p>Russian press accounts quoting intelligence officials here say that Mr. Pope was arrested as he was giving $30,000 to a professor from Bauman State Technical University, Anatoly Babkin, 70, to purchase the plans for the torpedo system. Professor Babkin is a specialist in torpedo development and design.</p>
        <p>Some reports said Professor Babkin was subsequently released because of his advanced age and a heart condition, raising the question of how seriously the security services are taking his offense, which is usually treated as an act of treason.</p>
        <p>The Squall torpedo, according to a report from the Russian institute that designed it, was developed over two decades as a design that could be fitted with various warheads and rocket motors, depending on its mission. Its versatility included configurations for underwater attacks or for firing over the horizon at surface ships or distant submarine targets.</p>
        <p>Its most remarkable feature is its speed, more than 220 miles an hour in its own gas bubble, making it the fastest torpedo in the world, according to an article by Valery Kulbitsky, chief designer of the Russian Research Institute of Marine Technology.</p>
        <p>American Navy officials have reportedly shown a great deal of interest in the system, and two American submarines, one of them the Memphis, were monitoring the exercises in which the Kursk had been scheduled to fire a variety of weapons. Two senior Russian officials connected with the investigation into the Kursk's sinking have said that it was carrying an experimental torpedo and that an accident involving the weapon or its engine could have contributed to the disaster.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
