<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lieberman Explains Call For Bigger Role for Religion</title>
    <meta content="Y30LIE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/30/national/30LIEB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226412"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEMOCRATIC RUNNING MATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Anti-Defamation League</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Joseph I Lieberman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DA1630F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lieberman Explains Call For Bigger Role for Religion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ANAHEIM, Calif., Aug. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen Joseph Lieberman, explaining his call for greater role for religion in public life, says he meant it as a matter of public discourse, not public policy; adds that he does not consider those who are not religious to be amoral or unfit for public office; reacts to Anti-Defamation League's statement criticizing emphasis on religion by Democratic vice presidential nominee (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Explaining his call for a greater role for religion in public life, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman says he meant it as a matter of public discourse, not public policy, adding that he does not consider those who are not religious to be amoral or unfit for public office.</p>
        <p>''This is really less a matter of programs or legislation than it is of giving respect to the constructive role that faith can play in the lives of individuals, and in the lives of the community,'' Mr. Lieberman, the Democratic vice-presidential nominee, said in an interview aboard his campaign plane late Monday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Explaining his call for a greater role for religion in public life, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman says he meant it as a matter of public discourse, not public policy, adding that he does not consider those who are not religious to be amoral or unfit for public office.</p>
        <p>''This is really less a matter of programs or legislation than it is of giving respect to the constructive role that faith can play in the lives of individuals, and in the lives of the community,'' Mr. Lieberman, the Democratic vice-presidential nominee, said in an interview aboard his campaign plane late Monday night.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman spoke a few hours after the Anti-Defamation League issued a statement criticizing his emphasis on his faith and saying religion should have no place in the political arena. With that criticism, one of the nation's most prominent Jewish groups was publicly chastising the first Jew to be nominated by a major party for national office.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Lieberman knew of the Anti-Defamation League's statement when he gave the interview on Monday night, his aides said today that he did not then know its details. The senator declined to discuss the statement today, ignoring reporters' shouted questions as he hurried from a convention of the Communications Workers of America that he had addressed here.</p>
        <p>But his campaign spokeswoman, Kiki McLean, said, ''He is someone who always expresses his support of tolerance and separation of church and state, and believes the A.D.L. does a lot of good work, and in this instance respectfully disagrees.''</p>
        <p>Giving a homily at a church in Detroit on Sunday, Mr. Lieberman said that ''there must be a place for faith in America's public life,'' and quoted Adams and Washington as linking both the founding of the nation and morality to religion. He offered much the same sentiment on Monday at a breakfast with religious leaders in Chicago.</p>
        <p>But in the interview on Monday night, he said he had not meant to suggest that irreligious people cannot be moral. ''Religion in my opinion can be, and in my opinion usually is, a source of good behavior,'' he said. ''But two things: I know religious people who I consider not to be moral, and I also know people who are not religious who I consider to be extremely moral. So, you know, I'm talking here about probabilities.''</p>
        <p>Asked if he would object to an atheist's being president, he said, ''Personally, no, if I thought it was a good person'' -- a more liberal stance, polls show, than a great majority of Americans take.</p>
        <p>He said he respected former Senator Bill Bradley's refusal to talk about his religious views during the presidential primary campaign.</p>
        <p>Talk of religion is nothing new for Senator Lieberman, who made it part of his previous campaigns and wrote about it in a book published this year, ''In Praise of Public Life.'' At virtually every stop in this campaign, he mentions his own devout faith and the faith of Vice President Al Gore, frequently telling his listeners that people of all religions are ''children of the same God.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Gore and Gov. George W. Bush have both talked about religion in interviews and debates, Mr. Lieberman has gone further, making his faith a central part of his stump speech.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman's comments have inspired a debate on the role of religion in politics, raising concerns in some quarters about maintaining the separation of church and state.</p>
        <p>Today, on the New York Times/ ABC News Webcast ''Political Points,'' the Rev. Barry W. Lynn, executive director of Americans United for the Separation of Church and State, accused both parties of using religion to pander for votes.</p>
        <p>On the same Webcast, Forest Montgomery of the National Association of Evangelicals said the media applied a double standard, treating Mr. Lieberman more gently than they would a conservative Christian saying the same things. But Mr. Montgomery added, ''Evangelicals are very comfortable with everything the senator's been saying.''</p>
        <p>In Albuquerque today, Mr. Gore defended Mr. Lieberman in a series of interviews with local television stations around the country. ''He also believes, as I do, in separation of church and state,'' Mr. Gore told KSDK in St. Louis. ''I believe in what he's saying.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman and his aides have been quick to draw distinctions between his comments and efforts by some Christian conservatives to mingle religion and politics, noting, for instance, that he supports abortion rights and opposes organized prayer in public schools.</p>
        <p>''I think there's a difference here between respecting faith and feeling free to talk about the way in which it informs and benefits American life, and talking about it in a way that may make some people feel excluded,'' Mr. Lieberman said in the interview.</p>
        <p>''I understand that some people who are particularly sensitive to religious discrimination may get uncomfortable when people talk about their faith, but I find it both informative and encouraging,'' he added. When religious Christians discuss their faith, as Mr. Gore has done repeatedly, ''I don't feel excluded by it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''I think somehow, for various reasons, we either started to talk about religion in ways that were divisive, or we stopped talking about it altogether,'' he said. ''I think we lost something there.''</p>
        <p>Once again, he put his views in the context of the nation's founders, who he said valued both faith and religious freedom. They saw that in a society in which government does not tightly control people, ''it's helpful to have other sources of good behavior,'' he said, ''and so religion is one of those. So in that sense, it is an ally of government in trying to create a good society.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEMOCRATIC RUNNING MATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
