<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Pitches His Health Care Plan for Uninsured Children</title>
    <meta content="Y30GOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/30/national/30GORE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Mexico</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Albuquerque (Nm)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico/Albuquerque</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E2DA1630F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="947" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Pitches His Health Care Plan for Uninsured Children</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>ALBUQUERQUE, Aug. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore keeps campaign focused on health care, emphasizing his plan for providing access to coverage for nation's 11 million uninsured children; speaks to parents and health care workers in Albuquerque; photo; New Mexico is swing state where access to health insurance is serious problem (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore kept his campaign focused on health care today by emphasizing his plan for providing access to coverage for the country's 11 million uninsured children.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's plan, for insuring all children by 2005, relies primarily on an expansion of the Children's Health Insurance Program, or CHIP, an initiative that has provided coverage, with modest premiums, for about two million children since its enactment in 1997.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore kept his campaign focused on health care today by emphasizing his plan for providing access to coverage for the country's 11 million uninsured children.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's plan, for insuring all children by 2005, relies primarily on an expansion of the Children's Health Insurance Program, or CHIP, an initiative that has provided coverage, with modest premiums, for about two million children since its enactment in 1997.</p>
        <p>The program now covers children in families with incomes up to 200 percent of the poverty level, and Mr. Gore would raise that ceiling to 250 percent, or about $41,000 at present for a family of four.</p>
        <p>''We need to cover every single child within this next presidential term,'' Mr. Gore said, addressing a group of parents and health care workers gathered by his campaign in a park here.</p>
        <p>New Mexico is a swing state that was carried by President Clinton in both 1992 and 1996 but before then had voted for the Republican nominee in six consecutive presidential elections. Access to health insurance is a serious problem in the state, where 14 percent of poor children are uninsured, the sixth-highest proportion of any state, according to the Census Bureau. The problem is particularly severe among Latinos and American Indians, and Mr. Gore laced his comments today with Spanish phrases.</p>
        <p>The Democratic nominee had little to say about his Republican rival, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas. But, in what has become a regular feature of his policy discussions, he closed his remarks by challenging Mr. Bush to issue a detailed plan.</p>
        <p>''Presently he has not presented any plan to address this problem,'' Mr. Gore said of children's health coverage, ''but there is still time, even before Labor Day, to offer these specifics.''</p>
        <p>Dan Bartlett, a spokesman for Mr. Bush, called Mr. Gore's claim ''inaccurate,'' and said Mr. Gore should explain why the number of uninsured children had increased by more than two million during the Clinton-Gore years. Mr. Bush, Mr. Bartlett said, has put forth a plan to provide a tax credit of up to $2,000 for premiums of health insurance policies bought by families with incomes of $30,000 or less. Families earning $30,000 to $60,000 would qualify for a smaller credit.</p>
        <p>Sarah Bianchi, a Gore policy adviser, said the Bush credit would not be large enough to help many families buy insurance in the private market.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's proposals, which would increase access for both poor children and their parents, would cost the federal government an estimated $95 billion over 10 years. The CHIP program relies on states to sign up eligible children. The state and federal governments share the cost, with the federal government paying most of it.</p>
        <p>The proposal to raise the income ceiling for CHIP coverage is the centerpiece of Mr. Gore's plans to move incrementally toward a system of universal health coverage. That incremental approach, he has said, reflects the lessons learned from Mr. Clinton's failed efforts to insure all Americans in one vast restructuring of the American health care system.</p>
        <p>''I want to make it clear that the proposals that I'm announcing here do not represent a complete solution to every problem in health care,'' Mr. Gore said. ''The approach that I'm recommending is the step-by-step approach, paso a paso, so that we move toward universal health insurance for all.''</p>
        <p>In the Democratic primaries, Mr. Gore's opponent, former Senator Bill Bradley, criticized his reliance on the CHIP program, because it has had difficulty enrolling all eligible children. Currently an estimated seven million children eligible for CHIP are not enrolled.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore acknowledged that shortcoming today, but placed blamed for it on states that, he said, ''put up barriers to participation'' because they ''don't really want to put their own money into the program, and so they make it difficult for families to participate.''</p>
        <p>Some governors, noted Mr. Bartlett, the Bush spokesman, have attributed the problem to a lack of flexibility in federal regulations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has outlined a series of measures intended to lower what he called the ''cultural barriers'' to enrolling in CHIP. Those measures include simplifying applications for coverage, eliminating asset tests that sometimes intimidate eligible families, requiring states to change their minimum eligibility periods to a year from six months, and allowing families to apply by mail instead of in person.</p>
        <p>The vice president would also allow families with incomes above the higher CHIP ceiling that he proposes  to buy insurance for their children, through either CHIP or Medicaid. Those families would have to pay a full premium, but the financial burden would be reduced somewhat if they applied for Mr. Gore's proposed 25 percent tax credit on health insurance premiums.</p>
        <p>Another Gore proposal would extend CHIP coverage to the seven  million uninsured parents of children who are eligible for either CHIP or Medicaid. Some 85 percent of the parents of eligible children are not insured, according to Gore aides.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Gore's plan, states could set their own eligibility levels but would receive federal matching funds for those parents they enroll. If health coverage for parents is provided, Mr. Gore reasons, families  will be more likely to seek coverage for their children as well.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
