<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Funny Coincidence: Woody Allen, Meet S. J. Perelman</title>
    <meta content="30NOTE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226322"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hirschfeld, Al</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perelman, S J (1904-79)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Allen, Woody</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Small Time Crooks (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Night Before Christmas, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Critic's Notebooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Al Hirschfeld</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1DA1F31F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1141" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Funny Coincidence: Woody Allen, Meet S. J. Perelman</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mel Gussow</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mel Gussow's Critic's Notebook column on similarities in plot lines of Woody Allen film Small Time Crooks and S J Perelman's 60-year-old Broadway comedy, The Night Before Christmas; similarities were discovered by artist Al Hirschfeld, close friend and collaborator of Perelman and friend of Allen; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the recently published ''Most of the Most of S. J. Perelman,'' a portmanteau of Perelmania in the Modern Library Humor and Wit Series, Woody Allen is quoted as saying: ''What happens to you when you read Perelman and you're a young writer is fatal because his style seeps into you. He's got such a pronounced, overwhelming comic style that it's very hard not to be influenced by him.''</p>
        <p>Is the following a matter of influence? Or a homage? Or is it simply a coincidence?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the recently published ''Most of the Most of S. J. Perelman,'' a portmanteau of Perelmania in the Modern Library Humor and Wit Series, Woody Allen is quoted as saying: ''What happens to you when you read Perelman and you're a young writer is fatal because his style seeps into you. He's got such a pronounced, overwhelming comic style that it's very hard not to be influenced by him.''</p>
        <p>Is the following a matter of influence? Or a homage? Or is it simply a coincidence?</p>
        <p>Inept crooks take over a failing store with the idea of digging a tunnel from the basement to the vault of a nearby bank. Almost immediately everything goes awry. The thieves know less about tunneling than they do about safecracking, and customers keep coming into the store, an unwelcome intrusion. But before the caper is complete, a legitimate business deal brings in a windfall.</p>
        <p>This is the basic plot of Mr. Allen's movie, ''Small Time Crooks,'' and also of ''The Night Before Christmas,'' a play by Perelman and his wife, Laura (the sister of Nathanael West and Perelman's frequent screenwriting partner). The Perelman family comedy had a brief Broadway run in 1941.</p>
        <p>The similarity of the shenanigans in the two comedies over a period of almost 60 years was pointed out by the artist Al Hirschfeld, who saw both. He was a close friend and collaborator of Perelman and is also a friend of Mr. Allen.</p>
        <p>Each work has its own twists and turns. In the movie Tracey Ullman, playing the wife of the gang leader (Mr. Allen), opens a cookie shop that becomes phenomenally successful. After about a half-hour Mr. Allen, as director and screenwriter, abandons the caper and switches to a travesty of social climbing and of the idle rich.</p>
        <p>The play, which takes place in a lackluster luggage shop on Sixth Avenue in Manhattan, is less concerned with the bank robbery than with the eccentric characters in the neighborhood, busybodies and fussbudgets who keep wandering into the store and interrupting the action. Accidentally the thieves dynamite their way into a delicatessen, which leads to jokes about cole slaw and pastrami. Eventually the store is sold for a high price to the bank, and everyone -- or almost everyone -- ends happily.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Allen speaks about his great regard for Perelman, he is referring to him as an essayist and not as a screenwriter for the Marx Brothers, or in his lesser role as a playwright. Only two of his shows could be marked as successes, the Kurt Weill musical ''One Touch of Venus'' and ''The Beauty Part.''</p>
        <p>The essays omitted from ''Most of the Most of S. J. Perelman'' (for copyright reasons) are those from the book ''Westward Ha!'' That collection began with the story of ''Sweet Bye and Bye,'' a musical that Perelman wrote with Ogden Nash and Mr. Hirschfeld. In Perelman's words the show ''closed in Philadelphia like a 10-cent mousetrap,'' sending him and Mr. Hirschfeld on a round-the-world journey. He continued to be discouraged about his theatrical career. As he wrote in a self-portrait: ''Retired today to peaceful Erwinna, Pa., Perelman raises turkeys, which he occasionally displays on Broadway.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Allen was 5 when ''The Night Before Christmas'' opened, and closed after 22 performances. So far as is known the play has had no major revival. It is long out of print, although Samuel French, the theatrical publisher, found an archival copy from which a duplicate was made.</p>
        <p>There is an antic and occasionally a frantic quality to the humor. The thieves could have been sketches for characters to be played by the Marx Brothers. The pretentious leader of the gang, Otis J. Faunce, could have been made to measure for Groucho. The gangster dialogue, which Perelman drew from a con man of his acquaintance, is quaintly colorful. ''Yeah, I was sneezed in Saint Joe,'' says one ex-con. ''I was the wire for a cannon mob and I run into a wrong shamus.'' There is also, unfortunately, a sentimental love story between a drugstore clerk and a gun moll. Still there are slyly amusing moments in this screwball farce, and because of the authorship it is worth a second look.</p>
        <p>According to Perelman's biographer, Dorothy Herrmann, before the play opened on Broadway, it had been turned down by George S. Kaufman, and after its failure, Perelman's agent hawked it in Hollywood, where it was rejected by Abbott and Costello, W. C. Fields and the Marx Brothers themselves. Then Edward G. Robinson, looking to diversify his tough-guy career, decided to make the comedy and play for laughs.</p>
        <p>Retitled ''Larceny Inc.,'' with Robinson's character now named Pressure Maxwell, the movie opened in 1942. The cast included Broderick Crawford, Jackie Gleason, Jack Carson, Anthony Quinn and Jane Wyman (as the moll).</p>
        <p>Naturally, there is no patent on the idea of bumbling bank robbers. Think of ''Big Deal on Madonna Street'' or Mr. Allen's ''Take the Money and Run,'' in which, as Virgil Starkwell, he passes a holdup note to a bank teller saying that he has a gun, and the teller corrects his penmanship, insisting that the word as written is gub and is therefore invalid. Gub or not, the subject is open for recycling.</p>
        <p>Asked if he had ever heard of Perelman's play, ''The Night Before Christmas,'' Mr. Allen said, ''Now I have heard of it.'' He added that in reference to Perelman's Broadway career, he had only been aware of ''One Touch of Venus'' and ''The Beauty Part.''</p>
        <p>He said that in preparation for ''Small Time Crooks,'' he thought about Ernst Lubitsch's classic, ''Trouble in Paradise,'' ''and all those other heist movies I had seen, 'Rififi,' 'Topkapi' '' -- and of course ''Take the Money and Run.''</p>
        <p>Most likely two wits, mutual admirers, simply thought along related lines. There is, however, another possibility. The Modern Library series is edited by Steve Martin, who as a humorist owes his own debt to Perelman and perhaps to Mr. Allen. In the introduction to the series he says that before he started writing he had ''heard of S. J. Perelman, James Thurber and their like, but I was also aware that they were heavily influenced by me, even lifting some of my ideas, backdating them, and carefully inserting them in magazines from the 30's with the clever use of a razor blade and glue.''</p>
        <p>By this line of reasoning, it could be said that it was S. J. Perelman who borrowed from Woody Allen.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
