<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stevenson Also Seeking Maturity</title>
    <meta content="MB010438" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS: U.S. OPEN -- NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hollander, Sophia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Alexandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pierce, Mary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ivanisevic, Goran</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2D81630F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="485" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stevenson Also Seeking Maturity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOPHIA HOLLANDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hollander, Sophia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alexandra Stevenson, who lost first-round match at United States Open tennis tournament to Mary Pierce, comments on difficult year she has had after early success; Goran Ivanisevic comments on his first-round loss at Open (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alexandra Stevenson fidgeted on Louis Armstrong Stadium after each unforced error in her first-round match against fourth-seeded Mary Pierce. She wrinkled her nose, smoothed back her curly black hair, which was pulled into a tight ponytail, tugged her cap down over her eyes, and finally, after her worst mistakes of the day, clutched the top of her head with her hands in frustration.</p>
        <p>Although her sizzling returns elicited oohs from the sympathetic crowd, the 19-year-old could not string together a consistent streak of games, winning at love twice in the second set, but losing two games -- including match point -- on double faults. She fell to Pierce, 6-3, 6-4, in a loss riddled with blown opportunities. ''I think I made a couple'' -- she grinned ruefully -- ''well, a lot of unforced errors that I could have kept down.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alexandra Stevenson fidgeted on Louis Armstrong Stadium after each unforced error in her first-round match against fourth-seeded Mary Pierce. She wrinkled her nose, smoothed back her curly black hair, which was pulled into a tight ponytail, tugged her cap down over her eyes, and finally, after her worst mistakes of the day, clutched the top of her head with her hands in frustration.</p>
        <p>Although her sizzling returns elicited oohs from the sympathetic crowd, the 19-year-old could not string together a consistent streak of games, winning at love twice in the second set, but losing two games -- including match point -- on double faults. She fell to Pierce, 6-3, 6-4, in a loss riddled with blown opportunities. ''I think I made a couple'' -- she grinned ruefully -- ''well, a lot of unforced errors that I could have kept down.''</p>
        <p>It has been a trying year for the teenager, who stunned the world last year when she became the first qualifier to reach the women's semifinals at Wimbledon and soared to No. 36 in the world. But her joy at Wimbledon was stained. The world learned that her father, previously unnoted, was the basketball great Julius Erving, a revelation that spurred a news media frenzy.</p>
        <p>So far in 2000, her record is 9-22, including first-round losses in three of four Grand Slams. At Wimbledon, she was dismissed by Patricia Wartusch in straight sets. Before Wimbledon, she accused one player of a racial slur and another of pushing her mother. She has fallen to 76th in the world. It is has been a wrenching series of adjustments.</p>
        <p>''I just came out like a person that just graduated high school, like all happy, no stress, everything's really nice, everyone's really nice, there's no negativity,'' said Stevenson regarding her giddy introduction to professional tennis. ''Afterward, looking back on the year, I'm like, 'Wow, I was pretty dumb.' But now I'm not so dumb.''</p>
        <p>She laughed.</p>
        <p>''Everyone better watch out.''</p>
        <p>But although Stevenson can smile about it now, she admitted that the last year has been painful. Learning lessons her friends in college have not yet studied, Stevenson said she has been immersed in a crash course on maturity. ''It's rough,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''In the last year, it's been kind of crazy,'' she said. ''You have your personal life being on the front page, people in the street honking their horn going, 'Hey, what's up?' I like being well known. You just have to get used to it.''</p>
        <p>Now, she said, she has begun adjusting to this new life and her game has improved. She feels she is close and vowed she would win the Open in the next few years.</p>
        <p>''It's just a matter of time,'' she said as if by rote, then stopped, shaking her head. ''I keep hearing this 'matter of time.' Hopefully, it will come very fast because I'm getting impatient.''</p>
        <p>TENNIS: U.S. OPEN -- NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
