<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Braves Give a Shot To a Kiwi</title>
    <meta content="30MINOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226478"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MINORS: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Luttrell, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Travis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1D81630F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Braves Give a Shot To a Kiwi</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM LUTTRELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Luttrell, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Notebook article on minor league baseball focuses on Travis Wilson, New Zealand softball player signed by Atlanta Braves in 1996 without ever having played baseball; tables of minor league standings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Travis Wilson never played in Little League. He never played high school baseball. For that matter, growing up in Christchurch, New Zealand, he never played baseball at all. And yet, in the summer of 1996, the Atlanta Braves sent their Melbourne, Australia, scout to check out Wilson, and a few weeks later they had him under contract.</p>
        <p>Wilson, 19 at the time, was a world-class fast-pitch softball player for the New Zealand national team. He had caught the Braves' eye while winning a tournament in Michigan, and when he got back home he heard from the scout.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Travis Wilson never played in Little League. He never played high school baseball. For that matter, growing up in Christchurch, New Zealand, he never played baseball at all. And yet, in the summer of 1996, the Atlanta Braves sent their Melbourne, Australia, scout to check out Wilson, and a few weeks later they had him under contract.</p>
        <p>Wilson, 19 at the time, was a world-class fast-pitch softball player for the New Zealand national team. He had caught the Braves' eye while winning a tournament in Michigan, and when he got back home he heard from the scout.</p>
        <p>''I had watched baseball on cable, on ESPN, growing up,'' Wilson said this week from Myrtle Beach, S.C., where he plays second base for the Class A Pelicans in the Carolina League. ''My only way to get to be a baseball player was to play softball. I always had a dream of making it to the major leagues, but realistically, the chances were slim. But everything fell into place.''</p>
        <p>The move to a bigger field and a smaller ball started out with some bumps that Wilson, now 23, has worked hard to smooth out. One of the things he had to get used to was swinging a wooden bat instead of an aluminum one.</p>
        <p>''That was a big adjustment,'' he said, laughing. ''I still remember when the scout first threw to me, getting jammed. With a wooden bat you've got to hit it in the sweet spot or you're not getting any leeway.''</p>
        <p>Wilson, a right-handed batter, hit .215 in 1997 in the rookie-ball Appalachian League.</p>
        <p>''Initially, it was really difficult; I struggled hitting the curveball,'' he said. ''I learned an awful lot that first year, about being away from home, the ins and outs of baseball -- the road trips and taking care of yourself. Since then, I haven't looked back.</p>
        <p>''Initially, people thought, 'What's this softballer doing over here?' Once they saw I had the basic skills and the desire, they warmed to me.''</p>
        <p>After batting .330 in a second year of rookie ball, Wilson hit .309 with 20 doubles, 11 home runs and 63 runs batted in for Class A Macon. He accomplished that in just 90 games before he broke his wrist in July 1999. This year, Wilson is hitting .274 with 12 homers and 62 R.B.I. and has decent gap power. He has, however, struck out 105 times in 467 at-bats while walking just 16 times.</p>
        <p>''It hasn't been easy for him,'' Myrtle Beach Manager Brian Snitker said of Wilson's transition from softball. ''He's a real mature kid. It's one of those things where you don't realize that he only has three years of baseball under his belt. He's a lot more aware of what's going on. Sometimes, I think he's been playing baseball for a lot longer than he has been.''</p>
        <p>Snitker said batting coaches are working with Wilson on identifying pitches and studying release points.</p>
        <p>In softball, the reaction time is even less than it is in baseball, said Wilson, who compared the 88-miles-per-hour pitches he saw from 45 feet to 95-m.p.h. fastballs from 60 feet, and there's not too many guys in the league who can throw that.</p>
        <p>Wilson's quick hands might be his best physical attribute, according to Snitker, but his best tool is his perspective.</p>
        <p>''He's got a real good realistic approach to the game,'' the manager said. ''He's not like some of these kids who have these crazy expectations and then get all upset when things don't work out that way.''</p>
        <p>NEW YORK-PENN LEAGUE</p>
        <p>New Jersey's Chris Morris broke the franchise record for walks in a season last week with his 48th. Chris Richards walked 47 times for the Cardinals in 1995. Morris has stolen 40 bases in 50 attempts. ... The Cardinals' Dan Moylan reached base for the 38th straight game Monday night with a single and a walk in a 2-1 victory over Hudson Valley.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL LEAGUE</p>
        <p>The Yankees activated the infielder D'Angelo Jimenez from the 60-day disabled list over the weekend and assigned him to Columbus. Jimenez, coming back from a fractured neck, is batting .255 with a homer and four R.B.I. in 15 games, including a rehabilitation stint. ... The Clippers' Randy Keisler allowed one hit over nine scoreless innings Sunday but didn't get a decision when Columbus lost to Louisville, 1-0, in 10 innings. ... Keisler's teammate Ted Lilly also got a no-decision in a 3-0 loss to Louisville despite tying a team record with 15 strikeouts in eight scoreless innings. ... Pawtucket extended its streak of games with a home run to 14 when Dernell Stenson hit a fifth-inning grand slam in an 8-6 loss to Buffalo.</p>
        <p>INDEPENDENT LEAGUES</p>
        <p>The Newark Bears re-signed the infielder Sharnol Adriana. Last season, Adriana led the Bears with a .334 average and led the Atlantic League with 140 hits. A 29-year-old from the Netherlands Antilles, Adriana was a 15th-round pick of the Toronto Blue Jays in 1991, and had been playing in the Class AAA Mexican League this year.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Jason Fingers, a right-handed reliever for Spokane in the Class A Northwest League, recorded his first professional save. Fingers is the son of the Hall of Fame reliever Rollie Fingers. ... The St. Petersburg Devil Rays scored a 12-7 victory Monday night over Vero Beach in their last home game ever. Two Florida State League clubs, St. Petersburg and Kissimmee, will cease operations after this season as part of a Class A realignment.</p>
        <p>JIM LUTTRELL</p>
        <p>MINORS: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
