<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Good Apple</title>
    <meta content="30WELL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226305"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="EATING WELL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apples</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burros, Marian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Eating Well</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E2DC1F31F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1056" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Good Apple</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marian Burros</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burros, Marian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marian Burros's Eating Well column on using apples to cut the amount of butter, cream and othee fats in a recipe; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I SUPPOSE you could call it an apple epiphany. I was trying a recipe that called for apples, apple butter and apple cider because it's that time of year: the early apples are turning up at roadside stands and farmers' markets. Having grown bored with apples from storage by the end of winter, I look at these with the pleasure associated with the first strawberry of spring or the first peach of summer.</p>
        <p>My epiphany came with the first bite of this apple-three-ways dish of pork, mustard, onions and red wine. There is no cream, no butter and only a modest amount of oil, but it tasted surprisingly satisfying. It never occurred to me that something rich was missing, because it wasn't.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I SUPPOSE you could call it an apple epiphany. I was trying a recipe that called for apples, apple butter and apple cider because it's that time of year: the early apples are turning up at roadside stands and farmers' markets. Having grown bored with apples from storage by the end of winter, I look at these with the pleasure associated with the first strawberry of spring or the first peach of summer.</p>
        <p>My epiphany came with the first bite of this apple-three-ways dish of pork, mustard, onions and red wine. There is no cream, no butter and only a modest amount of oil, but it tasted surprisingly satisfying. It never occurred to me that something rich was missing, because it wasn't.</p>
        <p>For most cooks, it is easiest to reach for butter and cream, but for certain dishes, those that become more interesting when subtle flavoring is added, an apple is by far the better choice.</p>
        <p>This discovery made me feel even more kindly toward apples, which otherwise offer modest nutritional value. They have small amounts of vitamins A and C, selenium and potassium, and are a reasonable source of fiber. At least for now. One day scientists may learn that apples are a storehouse of micronutrients that make them a worthy competitor of the cantaloupe. Think of what they now know about ketchup and how its cooked tomatoes are loaded with lycopene, a phytochemical that appears to reduce the risk of prostate cancer.</p>
        <p>But neither ketchup nor cantaloupe provides the ingredients often missing in dishes low in fat and calories: rich taste.</p>
        <p>The pork with three forms of apple had  intensity, but also subtlety because the sweetness was balanced by the wine and  mustard. It is included in Alison Becker Hurt's book, ''Kitchen Suppers'' (Doubleday, 1999). For the most part, the recipes are not from her well-known restaurants, Alison on Dominick in New York or Alison by the Beach in Bridgehampton. They are ones she cooks at home, and while the book hardly features low-fat or low-calorie dishes, she never goes overboard on fat.</p>
        <p>The way apples add richness was confirmed by another dish I tried, a squash soup thickened with potatoes and seasoned with roasted carrots and onions, garlic and thyme. It has wonderful earth tones, its richness coming from its complexity. The soup, from ''Out of the Earth'' by Kerry Downey Romaniello (Spinner Publications, 1999), is as satisfying as anything laced with cream.</p>
        <p>Cooking apples with the skin on provides more body in dishes where richness and heartiness are the object. Apples are not interchangeable. For the pork, I would choose tart-sweet apples, like Macintosh, Gravenstein or even Granny Smith, types that hold their shape and do not dissolve into sauce. Stay away from Delicious. For the soup, any apple with a nice balance of sweet and tart works well, like a Paula Red, a variety that has just started appearing.</p>
        <p>Right now you can compare the flavor and texture of fresh apples. There were 10 varieties where I shopped last week. But fresh apples do not have a long season. Before you know it, your apples will be from storage, which makes them mealy, fit only for sauce.</p>
        <p>Both the soup and the pork reflect the change in seasons, with cooler nights when warm savory food seems just right.</p>
        <p>APPLELY PORK CHOPS  Adapted from ''Kitchen Suppers'' by Alison Becker Hurt (Doubleday, 1999)  Time: 20 minutes</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons olive oil  1 2/3 cups chopped onion  2 medium tart apples</p>
        <p>1/4 cup unsweetened apple butter  2 tablespoons Dijon mustard  2 small pork tenderloins, about 1 1/2 pounds total  2 large cloves garlic, minced  1 cup full-bodied red wine</p>
        <p>1/2 cup sparkling apple cider.</p>
        <p>1. Heat nonstick pan large enough to hold all ingredients, until it is very hot. Reduce heat to medium high, and add the oil and the onion. Saute until it begins to brown.  2. Wash, core and coarsely chop apples, and add to onion as it cooks.</p>
        <p>3. Mix apple butter and mustard. Wash, dry and cut the tail from the pork. Slice remaining pork into 1-inch-thick pieces, and slather with the apple butter-mustard mixture.</p>
        <p>4. When the onion and apple have softened, add the garlic and cook for 30 seconds. Push the onion mixture to one side. Add the pork, and brown well on both sides.</p>
        <p>5. Add the wine and cider, stir and cook down a little. Reduce heat; cook a minute or two longer, until pork is only slightly pink.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>CREAMY SQUASH SOUP  Adapted from ''Out of the Earth'' by Kerry Downey Romaniello (Spinner Publications, 1999)  Time : 1 hour 40 minutes</p>
        <p>3 pounds butternut, buttercup, Delicata or Hubbard squash, halved and seeded Olive oil  3 carrots, peeled  2 medium onions, halved but not peeled  Salt and fresh black pepper to taste 5 cloves garlic, peeled  4 apples, cored but not peeled, cut in  1/2-inch chunks  1 pound red or white potatoes, peeled, cut in  1/2-inch-thick slices  2 large sprigs thyme, plus extra for garnish  2 quarts chicken or vegetable stock.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 400 degrees. Place  squash, cut side down, in baking pan lightly coated with olive oil. Toss carrots and onions in a little oil and salt. Add to pan with squash or place in separate pan. Roast vegetables until tender: carrots and onions 40 to 50 minutes; squash about an hour.</p>
        <p>2. Scoop flesh from squash and place in 6- to 8-quart pot with carrots. Peel onions and add to the pot with garlic, apples, potatoes, 2 sprigs thyme and stock. Add water if needed to cover ingredients. Bring to a boil. Lower heat and simmer until potatoes are falling-apart tender, about 30 minutes</p>
        <p>3. Puree soup in batches; return to pot and season with salt and pepper. Reheat very slowly before serving. Leftovers may be refrigerated or frozen; add a little water or stock when reheating.</p>
        <p>Yield: about 10 cups.</p>
        <p>EATING WELL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
