<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Steak and Chips, and a Side of Politics</title>
    <meta content="Y30LOB$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/30/national/30LOBB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Caucus Room (Washington, DC, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boggs, Thomas H Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barbour, Haley</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcauliffe, Terry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gray, C Boyden</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burros, Marian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Downey, Thomas J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Luntz, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE1DA1630F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="899" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Steak and Chips, and a Side of Politics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIAN BURROS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burros, Marian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caucus Room steakhouse opens in downtown Washington, DC, with roster of 65 owners from world of high-powered lobbyists and high-tech industry; photo; lobbyist Thomas H Boggs Jr and former Republican chairman Haley Barbour hold largest shares, $100,000 each; other bipartisan investors include Terry McAuliffe, C Boyden Gray, Thomas Downey, Frank Luntz and major Internet executives (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Back in the old days, before Microsoft met the Justice Department, people in the computer business could not tell a lobbyist from a congressman. (Hint: one wears tasseled loafers.)</p>
        <p>Now the lobbyists and the high-tech executives are so close they have gone into business together. This week, the Caucus Room, a steakhouse, opens in downtown Washington at Ninth and D Streets N.W. under 65 partners whose rosters of political connections, high-tech interests, and in some cases both, are longer than a Manhattan wine list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Back in the old days, before Microsoft met the Justice Department, people in the computer business could not tell a lobbyist from a congressman. (Hint: one wears tasseled loafers.)</p>
        <p>Now the lobbyists and the high-tech executives are so close they have gone into business together. This week, the Caucus Room, a steakhouse, opens in downtown Washington at Ninth and D Streets N.W. under 65 partners whose rosters of political connections, high-tech interests, and in some cases both, are longer than a Manhattan wine list.</p>
        <p>Thomas H. Boggs Jr., a prominent lobbyist, and Haley Barbour, former chairman of the Republican National Committee and now in the lobbying  business, hold the largest shares, $150,000 each. Ted Leonsis, a top executive at American Online, and Jon Ledecky, another Internet entrepreneur, are also investors.</p>
        <p>It is a bipartisan bunch: Terry McAuliffe, President Clinton's top fund-raiser; C. Boyden Gray, a former counsel to President Bush and now with the law firm Wilmer, Cutler &amp; Pickering; Thomas Downey, a former Democratic congressman and  now a lobbyist; Richard Burt, the former ambassador to Germany;  and Frank Luntz, a Republican pollster. Even the Senate sergeant-at-arms, James Ziglar, has a share in the $3.3 million restaurant with mahogany paneling and marble floors, not so subtle reminders of the hallowed halls of Congress.</p>
        <p>At first blush, opening a restaurant seems an unlikely get-rich-quick scheme. The failure rate is high. But the Caucus Room quickly became the hottest investment in town and was oversubscribed in four days.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of like an I.P.O.,'' said Mr. Boggs, but one about contacts, not money. ''It's a downtown watering hole and a place to make deals,'' he said. ''And it's time for the techies and politicians to realize they are in the same world. Pre-Microsoft, techies thought Washington wasn't something they had to worry about.''</p>
        <p>Raul J. Fernandez, founder, chairman and chief executive officer of Proxicom Inc., an Internet company that does business with the Fortune 500 companies, agrees. ''All tech companies have a level of sensitivity to educating the Hill,'' said Mr. Fernandez, who once worked for Jack Kemp, a former Republican congressman and Bob Dole's running mate in 1996.</p>
        <p>''I don't have an issue right now that I have to have Tommy or Haley help me out, but I want to stay in touch with those people,'' Mr. Fernandez said, adding he could not think of a better way to do that than investing in their political hangout.</p>
        <p>''Ted and Jon and I are in this from a business standpoint,'' Mr. Fernandez said. ''It's going to provide meeting rooms that are not available today. I hope being an equity owner will move me up the list when I need one of those rooms.'' Mr. Fernandez has invested $50,000.</p>
        <p>And for a lobbyist, owning a restaurant where lobbyists take their clients sounds like a perfect setup. As John F. Jonas, a partner in Mr. Boggs's firm, Patton Boggs, and a partner in the restaurant, explained it: ''You are billing them for your time, and they pay for the meal. In  that way it's sort of a sweetheart deal.''</p>
        <p>Some of the partners say they are also in it for the status. ''People probably invest in restaurants for the same reason they invest in thoroughbreds or race cars,'' Mr. Jonas said. ''It has panache to be able to say I have an interest in a restaurant. Hopefully, the people in the restaurant will be a little nicer to you. You won't have to beg for a table or sit in the back corner and have the kitchen door slam into you.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Leonsis, who burst onto the Washington scene when he bought the city's hockey team, the Capitals, and a minority interest in its basketball team, the Wizards, said in an e-mail message that he became a partner because he ''needed a place to be assured of having some privacy when I dine with partners such as Michael Jordan.'' He added, ''Becoming a partner in a restaurant was on my list of 101 things to do before I  die.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barbour hoots at what he calls  this ''psychic benefit stuff.'' ''My psychoanalysis is a little dull from drinking bourbon for 40 years,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One might ask whether Washington actually needs another steakhouse. But for lobbyists, apparently, you cannot have too many steak houses.</p>
        <p>''The food will be good but it won't be the finest French restaurant,''  Mr. Jonas said. But, he added: ''I don't think a great French restaurant would be a hangout for politicians and lobbyists because many of them are not of the fine French ilk. Steak is safe food. You don't have to think about it.''</p>
        <p>But you do have to think about how much. Surf and turf at the Caucus Room will cost $59.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
