<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AT&amp;T Shares Up on Speedy At Home Deal</title>
    <meta content="Y30PHO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">At&amp;t Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Exciteathome</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Standard &amp; Poor's Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Firstcom</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Depalma, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E2DF1630F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="690" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AT&amp;T Shares Up on Speedy At Home Deal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO with ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romero, Simon; Depalma, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>AT&amp;T's stock rises on news that company has incorporated ExciteAtHome into its operations more quickly than expected, suggesting a faster move to high-speed Internet services; Standard &amp; Poor's puts company's debt on review for a possible downgrade, citing management miscues and costly acquisitions; AT&amp;T Latin America merges with FirstCom, a South American telecommunications company, to form a specialized broadband communications provider (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT&amp;T's stock rose yesterday on the news that the company had incorporated Excite@Home into its operations more quickly than expected, suggesting a speedier move into high-speed Internet services.</p>
        <p>But it was not all good news for AT&amp;T investors. Standard &amp; Poor's said yesterday that it had put the company's debt on review for a possible downgrade, citing management miscues and costly acquisitions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT&amp;T's stock rose yesterday on the news that the company had incorporated Excite@Home into its operations more quickly than expected, suggesting a speedier move into high-speed Internet services.</p>
        <p>But it was not all good news for AT&amp;T investors. Standard &amp; Poor's said yesterday that it had put the company's debt on review for a possible downgrade, citing management miscues and costly acquisitions.</p>
        <p>After the stock markets closed on Monday, AT&amp;T said that it had increased its voting stake in Excite@Home to 74 percent from 56 percent, giving it a controlling interest.  AT&amp;T will now include in its own results the figures for Excite@Home, a broadband provider based in Redwood City, Calif. The companies had been expected to consolidate their financial results in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>''AT&amp;T has thrown a life preserver to Excite,'' said Emily Meehan, an analyst at the Yankee Group, a communications consulting company. ''Now it remains to be seen whether Excite will bleed profits from AT&amp;T or get turned around.''</p>
        <p>Investors bid AT&amp;T's stock up $1.13, to $32 yesterday, but the shares remain deeply depressed, off nearly 50 percent from the 52-week high in November. The company is said to be considering a number of ways to bolster the stock.</p>
        <p>S.&amp; P., the credit-rating agency, cited concerns about AT&amp;T's costly acquisitions of TCI and MediaOne, which made it the nation's largest cable television operator, as major reasons for putting the stock on its watch list for possible downgrade.</p>
        <p>''This isn't a fait accompli, but it shows we're very concerned about the general direction of AT&amp;T,'' said Rick Siderman, senior telecommunications credit analyst at Standard &amp; Poor's. Still, it is not clear if any downgrade will increase AT&amp;T's borrowing costs, because Moody's Investors Service already rates AT&amp;T lower than S.&amp; P.</p>
        <p>S.&amp; P. said that AT&amp;T's long-term debt could be cut more than one notch below its double-A- rating and its short-term rating of A-1+.</p>
        <p>In addition, S.&amp; P. expressed concerns about ''operational and management miscues'' in AT&amp;T's core businesses of long-distance service, which has been squeezed by fierce competition, and its wireless services -- concerns echoed by others.</p>
        <p>''Management has gone from little room for error to almost none,'' said Pascal Aguirre, principal in the business strategy group at Renaissance Strategy Worldwide.</p>
        <p>Closing the Excite@Home transaction early will have little impact on the company's earnings projections for the entire year, stock analysts said. But for the third quarter, AT&amp;T's earnings will be reduced by an estimated 5 cents. Operating earnings will be 35 to 38 cents a share, the company said, down from its previous target of 40 cents to 43 cents a share.</p>
        <p>Excite@Home lost an estimated $2.5 billion last year on revenue of about $500 million and continues to lose money this year, according to Renaissance Strategy.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T picked up another company yesterday that did little to improve its bottom line immediately but gave it a solid footing in Latin America. AT&amp;T Latin America, which was formed by AT&amp;T last year, merged with the South American telecommunications company FirstCom to form Latin America's newest specialized broadband communications provider.</p>
        <p>FirstCom, whose stock had been traded on the Nasdaq, has served businesses and other high-volume customers in major cities in Chile, Colombia and Peru. During the first six months of this year, it posted a net loss of $32.4 million, or $1.06 a share. Patricio Northland, FirstCom's chief executive, attributed the losses to the heavy build-out of the company's fiber optics network in the three countries.</p>
        <p>The new AT&amp;T Latin America stock began trading on Nasdaq yesterday and closed virtually unchanged at $17.38. Since the regional company was formed last year, AT&amp;T Latin America has aggressively moved into the region, by acquiring Netstream in Brazil and Keytech LD in Argentina.</p>
        <p>Mr. Northland, who is now chief executive of AT&amp;T Latin America, said the company had identified 22 business centers in Latin America where it would focus its marketing efforts. It already has a substantial presence in 10 of them.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
