<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Craving Food That Can Kill, or at Least Bite</title>
    <meta content="30BOOK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BY THE BOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bilger, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Ted</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Noodling for Flatheads (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/By the Book</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E1DB1F31F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="640" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Craving Food That Can Kill, or at Least Bite</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TED LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Ted</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ted Lee reviews Burkhard Bilger's Noodling for Flatheads: Moonshine, Monster Catfish and Other Southern Comforts; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIS year's most fascinating food book, ''Noodling for Flatheads: Moonshine, Monster Catfish and Other Southern Comforts,'' is not at first glance a book about food. There are no mouth-watering photographs; in fact, the  only photo is on the cover, an unappetizing shot of writhing catfish, thorny mouths agape. The lone recipe in 250-odd pages is for ''sugar liquor,'' a potent moonshine distilled from sugar, malt, Fleischmann's yeast and horse feed.</p>
        <p>The book, by Burkhard Bilger (Scribner, $24), is a collection of powerful essays about the people who keep vanishing Southern traditions alive, and because foodways are among the South's most enduring regional distinctions, five of the eight essays are about food. Mr. Bilger, German-born but Oklahoma-reared, has assembled a cast of food devotees who would shock and enthrall  the most jaded urban epicure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIS year's most fascinating food book, ''Noodling for Flatheads: Moonshine, Monster Catfish and Other Southern Comforts,'' is not at first glance a book about food. There are no mouth-watering photographs; in fact, the  only photo is on the cover, an unappetizing shot of writhing catfish, thorny mouths agape. The lone recipe in 250-odd pages is for ''sugar liquor,'' a potent moonshine distilled from sugar, malt, Fleischmann's yeast and horse feed.</p>
        <p>The book, by Burkhard Bilger (Scribner, $24), is a collection of powerful essays about the people who keep vanishing Southern traditions alive, and because foodways are among the South's most enduring regional distinctions, five of the eight essays are about food. Mr. Bilger, German-born but Oklahoma-reared, has assembled a cast of food devotees who would shock and enthrall  the most jaded urban epicure.</p>
        <p>One of them, Steve Rector, is willing to die for his favorite dish. Like more than a few rural Kentuckians, he hunts squirrels for their brains, long considered a delicacy. In 1997, two Kentucky neurologists posited a link between Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease, a variant of mad cow disease, and eating squirrel brains. Mr. Rector knows that every bite is a risk. Health officials no longer allow him to serve the brains he cooks in demonstrations at the state's annual folklife festival, but he continues to hunt squirrels and eat their brains. ''You gotta die of  somethin', '' he said.</p>
        <p>In the title essay, Mr. Bilger spends a day with a former high school classmate, Lee McFarlin, who catches catfish using his fingers as both bait and hook. ''Noodling'' is  slang for this method of fishing; ''flatheads'' are a variety of catfish that don't bite as hard as ''blue cats.'' Yes, catfish have teeth, and Mr. Bilger loses some skin  noodling a 25-pound flathead.</p>
        <p>Why doesn't Mr. McFarlin use a lure? Because bare fingers work just as well, and maybe even better.</p>
        <p>Tim Patridge, in the essay ''Low on the Hog,'' endures a less physical challenge to satisfy his passion for chitlins, a k a chitterlings, or hog intestines. At Scholars, his restaurant and teaching center at Morris Brown College at Atlanta, he teaches Continental cuisine and soul food. But chitlins were once slave rations, and their gamy aroma can be a painful reminder. When Mr. Patridge steams up his kitchen with a potful, his student chefs steer clear.</p>
        <p>Like all Mr. Bilger's cooks, Mr. Patridge has an enviable closeness to his ingredients.</p>
        <p>''Nobody has any idea in America where their food comes from,'' the manager of a  chicken processing plant tells Mr. Bilger in ''Enter the Chicken,'' an essay on cockfighting, as he takes the author on a gruesome tour of the plant. Mr. Bilger's subjects know exactly where their food comes from, and their taste for certain foods has become an almost physical need over a lifetime, borne of harvesting these foods themselves, on their own land. Mr. Patridge was 14 when he slaughtered his first hog. Mr. McFarlin noodled his first fish when he was 8. Mr. Rector has hunted squirrel since he was 6.</p>
        <p>Progress has turned these foods into fringe indulgences. In Atlanta, hot dogs have replaced chitlins in some soul food joints. In Kentucky, coal mining and development have all but obliterated the nut trees that sustained squirrels. Noodlers fear that the Army Corps of Engineers' dredging of rivers deprives them of catfish.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bilger's book is not a catalogue of dying traditions. His lyrical narratives thrum with energy and affection. They celebrate cravings as being deeply personal, utterly illogical and irrepressibly alive.</p>
        <p>BY THE BOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
