<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To the Tape For Confessions</title>
    <meta content="MB234327" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV NOTES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Confessions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Court TV (Network)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Confessions (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE0D91630F933A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To the Tape For Confessions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Court TV will begin showing new series featuring videotaped confessions of criminal offenders but will bow to critics who found it inappropriate to show confessions as form of entertainment; series debut will be followed by panel discussion and other similar discussions may follow subsequent episodes; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Early last week Court TV announced it would begin showing a new series featuring the videotaped confessions of murderers, rapists and other offenders.</p>
        <p>The program, Court TV executives said, would feature segments from the confessions -- recorded by district attorneys and the police during the course of criminal investigations -- accompanied by crime scene photographs and eerie video of the locations where the incidents had taken place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Early last week Court TV announced it would begin showing a new series featuring the videotaped confessions of murderers, rapists and other offenders.</p>
        <p>The program, Court TV executives said, would feature segments from the confessions -- recorded by district attorneys and the police during the course of criminal investigations -- accompanied by crime scene photographs and eerie video of the locations where the incidents had taken place.</p>
        <p>It will run for half an hour and have neither a host nor a legal analyst, the executives said, adding that those looking for further explanation and interpretation of the confessions could find some on the Court TV Web site (www.courttv.com). ''Confessions'' is to have its debut on Sunday night, Sept. 10, at 10.</p>
        <p>By producing such a program, executives said, they knew they were inviting controversy.</p>
        <p>But it seems Court TV may have gotten more than it bargained for. In the days after the announcement, the network was heavily criticized throughout the media, with many saying it was inappropriate to show criminals' confessions as entertainment.</p>
        <p>Disputing Court TV's argument that the series was intended to give the public a better idea of how the criminal justice system works, critics said it could not successfully do so without offering its viewers analysis or explanation.</p>
        <p>A Los Angeles city councilman, Nate Holden, demanded that Court TV not show the program, warning that it could spur copycat crimes. The New York Times, in an editorial, referred to it as ''a rank appeal to prurience and the thrill of violence, motivated by the network's desire for an audience-grabbing hit.''</p>
        <p>On Monday Court TV announced it would make a concession to its critics.</p>
        <p>Henry Schleiff, the Court TV chairman, said the series premiere would be followed by a half-hour panel discussion about the confessions, featuring experts in crime and psychology. It is possible there will be similar panel discussions following subsequent episodes, but that, Mr. Schleiff said, will be determined later.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schleiff said that when it makes its actual debut, the program could also have further explanation of the various cases that would run somewhere on the screen while the confessions are playing.</p>
        <p>In the pilot episode the confessions are introduced with tersely worded introductions detailing the charges and followed with terse conclusions describing the outcomes.</p>
        <p>''The most important thing here is that Court TV prides itself on being responsible,'' Mr. Schleiff said. ''And where there is valid concern, I think, we're responding to that in a responsible way.''</p>
        <p>Nancy Ruhe-Munch, executive director of the National Organization of Parents of Murdered Children, said the announced changes did not satisfy her.</p>
        <p>''The only thing that would appease me is not to air these confessions,'' she said. ''How much pain do they think family members need to go through?''</p>
        <p>Stephen Gillers, a law professor at New York University who specializes in legal ethics and had described the program as voyeuristic, said he thought the changes could improve it, depending on how they are done.</p>
        <p>''If it is just a veneer, it is not enough,'' he said. ''If it is a real effort to deal with the legal issues, then I think it could be valuable.''</p>
        <p>JIM RUTENBERG</p>
        <p>TV NOTES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
