<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Compassion and Hope in 60 Miles of Shared Moments</title>
    <meta content="13ESSA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilgoren, Jodi</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Essay</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Breast Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E7DD143EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1742" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Compassion and Hope in 60 Miles of Shared Moments</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JODI WILGOREN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilgoren, Jodi</byline>
      <dateline>FORT DEVENS, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jodi Wilgoren article on taking part in 3-day, 60-mile walk to raise money and awareness for breast-cancer treatment and research; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The clock on the gymnasium wall was stuck at 10 minutes before 6.</p>
        <p>I discovered this when the hundreds of tired, angry women sprawled around me on the hard floor burst into applause as one of our fallen comrades was wheeled in on a gurney, covered eyebrows to toenails in what appeared to be a big sheet of tinfoil. She joined the other dehydrated souls huddled on Army cots, each wrapped like a giant baked potato in the thin aluminum blankets that keep you from descending into shock, and I realized that the clock hadn't budged since we arrived a half-hour before.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The clock on the gymnasium wall was stuck at 10 minutes before 6.</p>
        <p>I discovered this when the hundreds of tired, angry women sprawled around me on the hard floor burst into applause as one of our fallen comrades was wheeled in on a gurney, covered eyebrows to toenails in what appeared to be a big sheet of tinfoil. She joined the other dehydrated souls huddled on Army cots, each wrapped like a giant baked potato in the thin aluminum blankets that keep you from descending into shock, and I realized that the clock hadn't budged since we arrived a half-hour before.</p>
        <p>We were sitting in the hot, stuffy fitness center on the closed Army base, waiting out a June thunderstorm that threatened our campsite with tornado-force winds and hail. Most of us had not showered; only a handful had eaten dinner. Thus began the 15th hour of a day that had dawned with a 4 a.m. wake-up call and stretched 18.72 miles, on foot, from Fitchburg, Mass., through Leominster and Lancaster, to the false Promised Land of Devens.</p>
        <p>This was not a forced march. Unbelievable as it seemed at the moment -- forever etched in my head as 5:50 p.m. -- we had signed up for this, a 60-mile trek over three days, to raise money and awareness for breast-cancer treatment and research. We knew we'd be sleeping outside, bathing in trailers. We expected the blisters and bunions. But nobody mentioned anything about being packed in an airless gym, sore and sweaty, waiting for spaghetti.</p>
        <p>''Think of this as part of an experience of a lifetime,'' a perky blonde staff member shouted through a megaphone. ''We're hoping this will only last a couple of hours.''</p>
        <p>At opening ceremonies that morning, Dan Pallotta, who runs the company that stages this and six other such walks around the country as well as six bike rides on behalf of AIDS, had urged us to ''slow down to the speed of compassion, where moments exist.'' It all sounded horribly hokey to my cynical journalist's ears, but then there I was, holding hands with my circle of walking buddies, tears trailing our cheeks as we thought about why we were there.</p>
        <p>My story was on the back of my T-shirt: SURVIVORS! I had written across the shoulders. Underneath, the names of my mother, who had a mastectomy for pre-cancerous tumors, then chemotherapy for a lymphoma discovered during surgery; my aunt, who spent a year in chemo and radiation; and my cousin, just 30 years old, who that very day was having reconstructive surgery from her mastectomy.</p>
        <p>It was my friend, Janice Page, who had told me about the walk. On her sleeves, we wrote ''Patty, 1949-1984,'' in memory of her sister. Another sister, Nancy Merenda, and their cousin, Susan Page, also walked with us, as did a friend of their family.</p>
        <p>''I don't really know why I'm doing this,'' the friend, 31-year-old Nancy Emens, said as we walked the first day, behind a woman whose T-shirt proclaimed ''184 Days Chemo Free'' and a man whose shirt had a silk-screened picture of his wife, Ginny Thurston, who died last year at age 73.</p>
        <p>''I have a mother,'' Nancy continued. ''I have sisters. I'm a woman.''</p>
        <p>There it was. A moment. Priceless, like they say on those credit card commercials. And they kept happening.</p>
        <p>*At 2:02 p.m. on Day 1, when we walked by the Lura A. White School in Shirley, Mass., an 18th-century town, and every student was on the sidewalk, hands outstretched to slap us five.</p>
        <p>*When we dragged ourselves into Pit Stop 4 that afternoon and found the Broadway Babes (the crew picked a corny theme to distract us at each of the watering holes scattered along the route) singing, to the ''Hello, Dolly!'' tune, ''So no kvetching, keep on stretching, you can walk some more.''</p>
        <p>*When I was sitting in the blister line, waiting to have my heel drained (more than a full syringe!) and the nurses grabbed their cameras to document one particularly mangled foot.</p>
        <p>*When the last walker limped in, sneakers in hand, near 7 p.m. on Day 2, and 50 other walkers were waiting to greet her. And when Andy Massa, who turned 81 over the weekend, arrived at lunch to an ovation.</p>
        <p>*When a walker danced an Irish jig during the talent show, 40.26 miles behind her, 19.60 more to go.</p>
        <p>*When we stood in line for the Port-a-Johns on Day 3, shouting out the lyrics to Gloria Gaynor's ''I Will Survive.''</p>
        <p>*When we passed two little girls in matching overalls, doing cheerleader routines for us, and I realized we were walking so they might not have to.</p>
        <p>*And when I walked with Nancy Merenda, who is 57, and, as the closing ceremonies started at 5 p.m. on June 4, would be celebrating the third anniversary -- to the minute -- of her surgery for ovarian cancer.</p>
        <p>Nancy is a nurse, so she knew what she had, which often makes it worse. Not only had her younger sister, Patty, been stolen too young by cancer, but Patty's husband had succumbed to it in his 40's, and another sister's husband died of melanoma at 41. Their dad died of cancer; so did a cousin. As we walked, Nancy told me she sometimes thought she had been dealt the disease so she could prove that someone in her family could survive it.</p>
        <p>Nancy, who shattered the fund-raising minimum of $1,800 by collecting more than $6,000, had been training for the walk for months. But she wasn't sure, almost until the moment she did it, that she would be able to finish.</p>
        <p>''There was a time I couldn't walk from the garage to the hospital,'' Nancy whispered. She could laugh, now, about how she and her 20-something son had taken turns shaving each other's heads while she was in chemo, but she still cried as she recalled packing up her Christmas decorations and labeling them for her daughter. ''I thought,'' she said, ''I wouldn't make it to Christmas.''</p>
        <p>Over the past decade, it has become increasingly chic to walk, run or ride long distances for a cause. Seems like there is some group with matching T-shirts parading through Central Park every Sunday; pink, red ribbons everywhere.</p>
        <p>The Race for the Cure, another breast cancer event, started in 1983; now there are some 100 sites, plus offshoots, like Ski for the Cure. There are walks for multiple sclerosis; races for leukemia; a walk and roll, whatever that means, to cure paralysis; the Mount McKinley Breast Cancer Climb; and the mother of all walk-a-thons, sponsored by the March of Dimes, which has raised more than $1 billion over 32 years to fight birth defects.</p>
        <p>This three-day walk, sponsored by Avon, was born in 1998 in Southern California and now has seven sites, including a Bear Mountain to Manhattan trip in October. The events have raised $20 million for early-detection programs, treatment for uninsured women, psycho-social support for patients and their families and research. In Boston, there were 2,533 walkers -- 2,386 women -- and 391 crew members, who raised $8 million, $4.7 million of which goes to the charities. The woman who raised the most, $34,000, was Kate Neave, who last year married a man who lost his first wife to breast cancer; her stepdaughter, Jessica, 8, volunteered at the walk, wearing a T-shirt that said, ''In memory of one mom, in support of another.''</p>
        <p>The route was windy and woodsy, passing historic sites like Louisa May Alcott's home and the battlefields of Lexington and Concord, then along the Charles River (though we also spent some time on highway shoulders, with Office Max and Applebee's as scenery). There were two basic rules: no running, no whining.</p>
        <p>It is the magnitude of the thing, the seeming impossibility, the sheer ridiculousness of it all -- spending 8, 9, maybe 12 hours a day just putting one foot in front of the other -- that is the point. You walk 60 miles in three days to see if you can, to show you can. Nancy kept wondering if she would hit a wall and be able to walk no farther; just like the wall she often felt she was pounding her bald head against while fighting cancer.</p>
        <p>I didn't train, figuring I'd been walking nearly 29 years, and, besides, who had the time? I stupidly bought my shoes only five days before setting out. So I was scared I wouldn't make it -- and would have to admit it in the newspaper.</p>
        <p>The thing is, you can walk 60 miles. Sure, it hurts; even Janice, who finished the Boston Marathon in 3 hours 46 minutes, had sore feet. So you push. Because you're surrounded by women who've had it so much harder than you. Because your body has never had to fight this hard, but it might. Because your mother, the survivor, is waiting for you at the closing ceremonies in Cambridge.</p>
        <p>We walked into Rockwell Cage at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology at about 3:40 p.m. to prepare for the final steps. It was another stuffy gym, packed with screaming women wearing their new ''victory'' T-shirts, pink for the more than 300 breast cancer survivors, navy for the rest of us. I checked the clock on the wall and, incredibly, it was stuck at 10 minutes before 6.</p>
        <p>It seemed forever since that Fort Devens floor, where my friends and I played Rummy 500 as others slept or read, mindlessly munched Doritos, or gave strangers foot massages. We had come a ways.</p>
        <p>Soon we trod outside, rows and rows of us. Dan Pallotta's syrupy baritone poured out over the sound system, and we strode down down the field, fists high above our heads to endless applause. As we stood screaming in the crowd, Nancy tapped my shoulder, held up her hand, fingers spread wide, and mouthed, ''It's 5 o'clock.''</p>
        <p>What a moment.</p>
        <p>ESSAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
