<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Small World of Hard Rock, Mocked</title>
    <meta content="13TRAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206990"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Toyota Comedy Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prieboy, Andy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'Albert, Rita</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">White Trash Wins Lotto (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E5DC143EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Small World of Hard Rock, Mocked</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN POWERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powers, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Powers reviews Andy Prieboy's musical show White Trash Wins Lotto, staged by Rita D'Albert and narrated by Prieboy; show is part of Toyota Comedy Festival; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''White Trash Wins Lotto'' is cruel comedy. The show, which made its way to P.S. 122 Friday and Saturday as part of the Toyota Comedy Festival, keenly mocks insipid hard rock and the industry that promotes it, using the story of W. Axl Rose, the Guns 'n' Roses singer who went from obscurity to superstardom to hermitlike retreat, as its main embodiment.</p>
        <p>''White Trash'' has won a zealous following in Los Angeles, where its jokes about nasty moguls and dim-bulb rockers ring particularly true. It is the West Coast equivalent of ''Hedwig and the Angry Inch,'' uniting rock and theater fans, although its guitar-free music sounds more like Gilbert and Sullivan than rock.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''White Trash Wins Lotto'' is cruel comedy. The show, which made its way to P.S. 122 Friday and Saturday as part of the Toyota Comedy Festival, keenly mocks insipid hard rock and the industry that promotes it, using the story of W. Axl Rose, the Guns 'n' Roses singer who went from obscurity to superstardom to hermitlike retreat, as its main embodiment.</p>
        <p>''White Trash'' has won a zealous following in Los Angeles, where its jokes about nasty moguls and dim-bulb rockers ring particularly true. It is the West Coast equivalent of ''Hedwig and the Angry Inch,'' uniting rock and theater fans, although its guitar-free music sounds more like Gilbert and Sullivan than rock.</p>
        <p>But this is not just another rock musical. It is really a critique of musicals themselves and of artistic aspiration, which can quickly turn to desperation and lead to shocking things.</p>
        <p>Like the writing of a musical, for example. ''White Trash'' featured a three-piece band and 12-member cast in stirring production numbers inventively staged by Rita D'Albert, but it always returned to the perch of its creator, Andy Prieboy, the foil and sly antihero in a story that was really his own.</p>
        <p>Mr. Prieboy was once an aspiring rock god. He still looked that part, narrating the show from behind his keyboard in a Victorian suit, moppy hair and a sardonic grin, like a gothic rock version of the ghostly William Holden in ''Sunset Boulevard.''</p>
        <p>Solo and in the band Wall of Voodoo, Mr. Prieboy noted, he had recorded dark, emotional pop. But his record label dropped him. He retreated to his studio, trying to write a career-saving hit. Through his wall he heard not rock anthems but show tunes. His neighbors hoped to be the next Lloyd Webber and Rice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Prieboy started daydreaming about the next ''Grease'' or ''Rent.'' He expected his own world of Hollywood rock would be its subject. If someone was going to reduce his scene to Broadway schmaltz, why not him?</p>
        <p>''White Trash'' is the story of Mr. Prieboy elaborating on that thought. Restaging the cliches of hard rock, from the death cult surrounding Jim Morrison to the nerdlike ambience of a guitar store, within the cliches of the musical -- show-stopping dancing and bombastic choruses -- Mr. Prieboy has satirized both. The show is more than a lark; it's a basic challenge to the conventions of the musical. Even the exciting hits of the recent rock-musical revival like ''Hedwig'' and ''Rent'' ultimately honor sentiment. Trite or profound, the passion these shows melodiously invoke is absolute.</p>
        <p>In contrast, ''White Trash'' explores hollowness. Axl, played with brilliant innocuousness by Brian Beacock, did not really develop. He just intermittently emerged to deliver another balladic power surge. ''I sing to bring a light into this confusion,'' he wailed, radiant, merging the empty rock star and the even emptier Broadway belter.</p>
        <p>The other cast members took on multiple roles that were also double-edged archetypes. Heavy metal strippers became ''Gigi''-style chorus girls. Midwestern youths migrating to Hollywood transformed into stomping ''Oklahoma'' types. Sleazy record executives resembled the salesman of ''Music Man.'' These odd juxtapositions delivered a useful shock.</p>
        <p>This approach undid the musical formula from within. Instead of sentiment, ''White Trash'' celebrated cynicism -- the serious darkness of a man who has been through rock's wringer. The conversion of Mr. Prieboy's bile into redeeming humor was the real plot here and by playing it out, ''White Trash'' offered something new.</p>
        <p>The intense sarcasm was satisfying, but it did have its limits. As he continues to develop the show, which will surely get a bigger production in New York, Mr. Prieboy might leaven  his contempt with the emotions he holds in such disdain. Corniness got its comeuppance in ''White Trash,'' but the paradox was that it could have used a dash of what it scorned.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
