<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First Battle Of Cancer: Deep Denial</title>
    <meta content="13CASE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206979"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CASES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jauhar, Sandeep (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Cases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Breast Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DB163EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First Battle Of Cancer: Deep Denial</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANDEEP JAUHAR, M.D.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jauhar, Sandeep (Dr)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Sandeep Jauhar articleon denial that drives some women to delay seeking treatment for breast cancer (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The woman, in her 70's, answered my questions with a shrug of resignation, as if we were talking about the price of beef or the inevitable loss of youth, not her breast cancer. Her words and body language conveyed a clear message: it was no big deal.</p>
        <p>The tumors had sprouted on her left breast like mushrooms in a dank forest: different shapes, sizes and colors. As they were mostly on the underside of her breast, she claimed not to notice them. Like the doctor in Solzhenitsyn's ''Cancer Ward,'' I wanted to ask her: ''Why didn't you come earlier? Why come here when you are practically a corpse?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The woman, in her 70's, answered my questions with a shrug of resignation, as if we were talking about the price of beef or the inevitable loss of youth, not her breast cancer. Her words and body language conveyed a clear message: it was no big deal.</p>
        <p>The tumors had sprouted on her left breast like mushrooms in a dank forest: different shapes, sizes and colors. As they were mostly on the underside of her breast, she claimed not to notice them. Like the doctor in Solzhenitsyn's ''Cancer Ward,'' I wanted to ask her: ''Why didn't you come earlier? Why come here when you are practically a corpse?''</p>
        <p>All cancers provoke denial, but something about breast cancer drives some women to such extreme denial that when they first see a doctor, tumors are literally growing out of their breasts. The literature on the subject is vast and has been accruing for at least 30 years.</p>
        <p>Exactly what provokes this response is not clear, but studies show that fears of disfigurement, dependency and death play big roles. A 1991 study of some 2,000 Nigerian breast cancer patients, for example, showed that fear of mastectomy was the most common reason for delays.</p>
        <p>Breast cancer kills: 50,000 American women will die of it this year, and it kills more ruthlessly the longer treatment is delayed. At Stage 1, the least serious of four levels, when cancer is confined to the breast, the five-year survival rate is 85 percent. At Stage 4, when it is widespread, the rate is below 20 percent.</p>
        <p>Despite this sobering fact and major efforts to educate women about the disease, studies show that a third or more of women who feel a breast lump delay seeking help for at least three months.</p>
        <p>Delay can occur for a number of reasons. Some women can't afford a doctor.  Others don't want to see one because of bad experiences. And sometimes people, especially the elderly, attribute abnormal physical signs, like a lump, to aging.</p>
        <p>A 1991 study showed that poor, elderly black women receiving care at public hospitals were almost four times as likely to go to a doctor with late stage tumors as younger, more affluent white women going to private hospitals.</p>
        <p>But psychological factors, particularly denial, surely contribute to delay. In small doses, denial has its advantages, mitigating severe anxiety and depression. But when denial extends more than a few months, it rapidly becomes harmful as tumors grow and spread.</p>
        <p>The patient in her 70's is a retired registered nurse. When she first felt a lump several years ago, cancer didn't occur to her. ''I didn't think about it,'' she said. ''It didn't hurt or feel like anything.''</p>
        <p>It grew to the size of a Ping-Pong ball before she showed it to a doctor.</p>
        <p>At the time, it was painless and surrounded by healthy tissue. If she had had it removed then, in an early stage, and received radiation and hormonal treatment, she probably would have had about a 50 percent chance of cure. But, she said, a biopsy proved inconclusive, and she was all too ready to forget about the problem. She left America soon afterward for her native South America, where her terminally ill husband had wanted to go to die. While there, she said, the tumor shrank and disappeared.</p>
        <p>But it's not just patients who delay treatment; sometimes, inadvertently, it's their doctors. Failure to diagnose breast cancer is the most common cancer misdiagnosis, resulting in the most legal claims against doctors and the second most money paid out, behind cases involving brain-damaged infants, according to a 1995 study by the Physician Insurers Association of America.</p>
        <p>Since most breast tumors are benign, doctors can easily mistake a malignant tumor for a benign cyst, especially in young women. Also, often there is no lump, just an itch, or nipple retraction, or discharge. And mammograms aren't foolproof: they can miss up to 20 percent of breast cancers.</p>
        <p>When the woman returned to North America two years later, the fronds of tumor were beginning to sprout from her breast. Friends and family insisted that she see a doctor; she ignored them. Several months later she developed severe pain where the cancer had metastasized to her hip. She took ibuprofen for months without relief, still refusing to see a doctor until the pain became unbearable.  Then, when she heard the diagnosis, she said she was surprised.</p>
        <p>Exactly what provokes denial remains a mystery. A large part of the answer is undoubtedly fear, which overwhelms and paralyzes. Fear not only of cancer and death, but of mastectomy and disfigurement. Fear of, as the writer Audre Lorde described, ''the absence of that beloved swelling I had come so to love over 44 years.''</p>
        <p>CASES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
