<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Some Girls, a Rainbow May Still Not Be Enough</title>
    <meta content="13GIRL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shange, Ntozake</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Faison, George</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">For Colored Girls Who...(play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DC143EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="535" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Some Girls, a Rainbow May Still Not Be Enough</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawrence Van Gelder reviews revival of Ntozake Shange's play For Colored Girls Who Have Considered Suicide/When the Rainbow Is Enuf, directed by George Faison; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the 25 years since the New Federal Theater production of ''For Colored Girls Who Have Considered Suicide/When the Rainbow Is Enuf,'' much has changed. And nothing at all.</p>
        <p>So the return of Ntozake Shange's choreographed poem of the tribulations and triumphs of black women, in revival at the American Place Theater, provides a salutary reminder of what has gone before, what still is and what remains to be accomplished.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the 25 years since the New Federal Theater production of ''For Colored Girls Who Have Considered Suicide/When the Rainbow Is Enuf,'' much has changed. And nothing at all.</p>
        <p>So the return of Ntozake Shange's choreographed poem of the tribulations and triumphs of black women, in revival at the American Place Theater, provides a salutary reminder of what has gone before, what still is and what remains to be accomplished.</p>
        <p>Performed under the sensitive direction of the Tony Award-winning George Faison by a talented cast of seven women to the accompaniment of moody and propulsive music by the percussionist Kimati Dinizulu and Rene McClean on saxophone and reeds, ''For Colored Girls'' remains potent, timely, emotionally charged theater.</p>
        <p>Riding on the rhythmic eloquence of language, lighted by humor, fueled by dance and dense with incident and insights that are the stuff of serious sociology and lurid headlines, this theater piece has lost no relevance.</p>
        <p>By turns funny, seductive, reflective, exultant and nightmarish, it is filled with tales of love and loss, sisterhood, betrayal and brutality, hopes raised and warped and crushed.</p>
        <p>Here once more, among others, are the girl who loses her virginity on prom night; the account of date rape; the tough seductress left weeping in her bed at dawn; the 8-year-old inspired by a library book about Toussaint L'Ouverture, the Haitian rebel slave leader; the haunted woman in the streets of Harlem; and the battered woman and the monstrous lover who claims her children.</p>
        <p>Again it can be argued that the men of ''For Colored Girls'' are uniformly the villains of the piece, that the resort to religion at the conclusion makes too facile an ending. And it can also be argued that ''For Colored Girls'' makes no claim to balanced reportage and that for some in despair, God is hope.</p>
        <p>The lives examined in ''For Colored Girls'' exemplify an imperfect world. Till that world improves, Ms. Shange's work reflects reality and remains pertinent.</p>
        <p>FOR COLORED GIRLS WHO HAVE CONSIDERED SUICIDE/WHEN THE RAINBOW IS ENUF  By Ntozake Shange; directed and choreographed by George Faison; sets by Walt Spangler; costumes by Ann Marie Hould-Ward; lighting by Robert Perry; sound by Janet Kalas; production stage manager, C. Renee Alexander; production manager, Pamela J. Traynor; general management, Theater Management Associates Inc., Ashton Springer and Laura Williams; associate producer, Charles West. Presented by DIA Theatrical Inc., Nicholas C. Litrenta and Mary-Evelyn Card. At the American Place Theater, 111 West 46th Street, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>WITH: Eleanor McCoy (Woman in Red), Novella Nelson (Woman in Brown), Lizan Mitchell (Woman in Purple), Jackee (Woman in Blue) Carol-Jean Lewis (Woman in Green), Katherine J. Smith (Woman in Orange) and J. Ieasha Prime (Woman in Yellow).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
