<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Health Care, Where Hope Is Still a Thing With Feathers</title>
    <meta content="13SALA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206998"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salamon, Julie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Health Care Crisis: Who's at Risk? (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DC143EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Health Care, Where Hope Is Still a Thing With Feathers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE SALAMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salamon, Julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Julie Salamon reviews PBS television documentary Health Care Crisis: Who's at Risk;? photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 1947 President Harry S. Truman declared, ''All Americans should have the opportunity for universal good health.'' Congress defeated his health care initiative, which was denounced as ''socialism.''</p>
        <p>In 1993 President Bill Clinton declared, ''This health care system of ours is badly broken.'' He urged Congress, within a year, to produce legislation guaranteeing health care to every citizen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 1947 President Harry S. Truman declared, ''All Americans should have the opportunity for universal good health.'' Congress defeated his health care initiative, which was denounced as ''socialism.''</p>
        <p>In 1993 President Bill Clinton declared, ''This health care system of ours is badly broken.'' He urged Congress, within a year, to produce legislation guaranteeing health care to every citizen.</p>
        <p>As you may recall, that didn't happen. So now, despite a long run of economic prosperity, about 44 million people in this country have no health insurance, and 38 million more have inadequate coverage.</p>
        <p>This situation seems well worth considering, especially in an election year. ''Health Care Crisis: Who's at Risk?,'' a one-hour documentary tonight on PBS, does a clear, thoughtful job of explaining the hows and whys of this confounding problem, if not what exactly to do about it.</p>
        <p>The producer Fred Silverman uses a once-classic journalistic style: he surveys academics, doctors, policy experts and ordinary folks to present a helpful overview of a complex matter. There are no re-creations or other efforts at forced drama (though he did bring in Blythe Danner to narrate off camera). In this summer of so-called ''reality'' shows, it's reassuring to turn to an authentic inquiry into an important subject.</p>
        <p>This plain style provides its own kind of drama. ''If we had set out to design the worst system that we could imagine, we couldn't have imagined one as bad as we have,'' says Marcia Angell, a physician and editor in chief of The New England Journal of Medicine.</p>
        <p>She's referring to managed care, the system developed in the 1980's to control spiraling health care costs. Health maintenance organizations and insurance companies rather than doctors began to determine the scope of a patient's treatment. ''It's an unethical system,'' Dr. Angell says on the program. ''Doctors have to convince themselves this chest X-ray they'd like to get maybe isn't necessary.''</p>
        <p>We meet Mara Gilbert, a 13-year-old leukemia patient, whose treatment was often jeopardized while her oncologists waited for the required referrals from her primary care physician. Her parents became poor credit risks because their insurance company wasn't paying the hospital bills, even though none of the procedures requiring payment were contested. (Happily, Mara's isn't a tragic example: she appears to be thriving after her treatment.)</p>
        <p>Patients covered by programs like Medicare have been caught short. Take the case of the elderly Marine Corps veteran who had a transplant almost 10 years ago. Medicare covered the first year of postoperative medication, and then he was left with an annual bill of $13,000 to $15,000. Without the medicine, his body would be very likely reject its alien heart.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Silverman and his team don't simplistically lay all blame on big business or the government. They try to put the travails of uninsured patients into historic and economic context. Experts explain that while technological progress has improved health care, there have not been attendant economic and legislative advances to help pay for new procedures. Also, doctors have tended not to consider whether the benefit of tests justified the costs.</p>
        <p>Some general solutions are offered: H.M.O.'s should lower their administrative costs and consider lowering profit margins. The government should devote more money to health care coverage. But it's the devilish details that have stalled reform. Those lay in the hands of the  country's leaders. Given the track record there, hope requires a big leap of faith.</p>
        <p>HEALTH CARE CRISIS  Who's at Risk?  PBS, tonight  (Channel 13, New York, at 10)</p>
        <p>Produced, directed and written by Fred Silverman; Howard Sharp, editor and co-writer; Joel Shapiro, director of photography; original score by Michael Bacon; Michele Demak Epstein and Sasha Waters, associate producers; Blythe Danner, narrator. Produced by Issues TV.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
