<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South Africa Close To Being Cup Host</title>
    <meta content="13SOC.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207141"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bell, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DB153EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1057" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South Africa Close To Being Cup Host</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK BELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bell, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Soccer notebook column; politically charged international minuet to decide which of five nations will play host to 2006 World Cup soccer tournament enters end game and it appears that South Africa is in strong position to land tournament (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The politically charged international minuet to decide which of five nations will play host to the 2006 World Cup has entered the end game and it appears that South Africa is in a strong position to land the tournament.</p>
        <p>On July 6 in Zurich, the 24-member FIFA executive committee will choose from among England, Germany, South Africa, Brazil and Morocco. The first nation to get 13 votes will be the tournament host.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The politically charged international minuet to decide which of five nations will play host to the 2006 World Cup has entered the end game and it appears that South Africa is in a strong position to land the tournament.</p>
        <p>On July 6 in Zurich, the 24-member FIFA executive committee will choose from among England, Germany, South Africa, Brazil and Morocco. The first nation to get 13 votes will be the tournament host.</p>
        <p>South African officials have acknowledged discussions with Brazil, promising to support Brazil for the 2010 World Cup if the South American nation drops its bid for the 2006 event. It is also expected that the Brazilians will deliver the two other South American votes (Nicolas Leoz of Paraguay and Julio Grondona of Argentina) to South Africa.</p>
        <p>The eight European members of the committee are expected to split their votes between England and Germany. Representatives from Saudi Arabia and Tunisia are expected to vote for Morocco, a fellow Muslim nation. With the three South American votes, three votes from Africa, two of a possible three from Concacaf (the region that includes the United States), three from Asia (Qatar, Thailand and South Korea), plus the support of Joseph Blatter, the FIFA president, South Africa could win the bid on the first ballot.</p>
        <p>United States Men</p>
        <p>The world has begun to look a bit bigger for the United States men's national team.</p>
        <p>The Americans won nothing of real significance in the Nike U.S. Cup after beating the depleted national teams of Mexico and South Africa, and tying Ireland. The United States cannot be concerned with the composition of the opposition. What is important, however, is that under the direction of Coach Bruce Arena the United States looks more professional, plays as a more cohesive unit and has the best pool of available players in the sport's long history in this country.</p>
        <p>''The big thing for national teams is that they need games to play together and to come together,'' Arena said at Giants Stadium after his team's 3-0 victory over Mexico on Sunday.</p>
        <p>The United States does not have any matches on its schedule between now and the start of World Cup qualifying games on July 16 at either Guatemala or Antigua. The players will be on vacation until they reconvene for training the first week in July.</p>
        <p>''We have a good group of guys,'' Arena said. ''The difficult thing is getting the team together. It's been frustrating over the past two years, but at least now we have a strong nucleus.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, United States officials announced that the qualifying match against Costa Rica on Oct. 11 would be played at Crew Stadium in Columbus, Ohio. The other United States home matches will be played on Aug. 16 (against Barbados) in Foxboro, Mass., and Sept. 3 at Robert F. Kennedy Stadium (against Guatemala or Antigua) in Washington.</p>
        <p>United States Women</p>
        <p>The United States women's national team will have precious little respite from international play after winning the Pacific Cup in Australia.</p>
        <p>The 1-0 victory over the host nation on Sunday gave the Americans the championship on goal differential (plus-16 to plus-9) over China in the six-nation tournament.</p>
        <p>Next up is the first Concacaf Women's Gold Cup later this month. The United States will play Trinidad and Tobago (June 23 in Hershey, Pa.), Costa Rica (June 25 in Louisville, Ky.) and Brazil (June 27 in Foxboro, Mass.) The final will be played at Foxboro on July 3.</p>
        <p>After that tournament, the women embark on an ambitious, and perhaps tiring, trip to Europe. The first stop is Germany for a four-nation tournament (Germany, China, Norway and the United States) from July 16 to July 22 to celebrate the 100th anniversary of the German federation. Then it is on to Norway for two games (July 27 and July 30). In mid-August, the United States will play host to the Glory Tour with games against Russia, Canada and Brazil.</p>
        <p>All of that is preparation for the defense of its Olympic title in Sydney, Australia, in a first-round group that includes Norway, Chile and Nigeria beginning on Sept. 14 in Melbourne.</p>
        <p>Corner Kicks</p>
        <p>Canada advanced to the semifinal round of regional World Cup qualifying with a 0-0 tie against Cuba late Sunday in Winnipeg, Manitoba. Canada had won the first leg, 1-0. The Canadians join Mexico, Panama and Trinidad and Tobago in the next round. Two nations will advance from the group to the final qualifying group.  Guatemala moved a step closer to joining the United States, Costa Rica and Barbados in the semifinals with a 1-0 victory in Antigua. The return match in Guatemala City will be played on Saturday.  The former Cosmos star Giorgio Chinaglia and Carin Jennings-Gabarra, a member of the first United States women's World Cup champion in 1991, were named to the National Soccer Hall of Fame in Oneonta, N.Y., and will be inducted on Oct. 28.  League officials in Italy decided to push back the beginning of the season to Oct. 1 because of the Olympics in Australia. The Italian season usually begins in late August or early September. The 2000-1 season will not end until June 17.  The U.S. Open Cup will kick into high gear tomorrow when 30 teams play for a berth in the third round. The 87-year-old competition is worth $100,000 to the winner. The MetroStars travel to North Carolina to play the Wilmington Hammerheads of the D3 developmental league and the D3 New Jersey Stallions will play Major League Soccer's Miami Fusion in Fort Lauderdale, Fla. The defending champion Rochester Raging Rhinos will play at the Pittsburgh Riverhounds in a matchup of A-League clubs. Fox Sports World has acquired rights to televise a quarterfinal match, both semifinals and the final on Oct. 22 in the United States and around the world.</p>
        <p>JACK BELL</p>
        <p>SOCCER: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
