<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Setback Leaves Lakers In Disarray</title>
    <meta content="13LAKE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207086"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="N.B.A. FINALS: LAKERS VS. PACERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EEDD153EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Setback Leaves Lakers In Disarray</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses problems besetting Los Angeles Lakers following loss to Indiana Pacers in third game of NBA championship series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The small forward is pouting, the shooting guard is still smarting and the all-millennium center is recovering painful memories from the foul line.</p>
        <p>Glen Rice wants more minutes and shots, Kobe Bryant needs his sprained left ankle to recover soon, and Shaquille O'Neal covets the kind of confidence that will prevent him from missing 10 free throws, as he did Sunday in the Los Angeles Lakers' 9-point loss to the Indiana Pacers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The small forward is pouting, the shooting guard is still smarting and the all-millennium center is recovering painful memories from the foul line.</p>
        <p>Glen Rice wants more minutes and shots, Kobe Bryant needs his sprained left ankle to recover soon, and Shaquille O'Neal covets the kind of confidence that will prevent him from missing 10 free throws, as he did Sunday in the Los Angeles Lakers' 9-point loss to the Indiana Pacers.</p>
        <p>''I just have to step up and make them,'' said O'Neal, who made only 3 of 13 shots from the foul line in the Lakers' 100-91 loss in Game 3 of the National Basketball Association finals. ''I've never made excuses for that part of my game and I never will. I'll hit them. I'm not worried.''</p>
        <p>The Lakers are still 48 hours away from true concern. But if they are not reeling, they need immediate attention -- at least before the Conseco Fieldhouse implodes again on Wednesday night in Game 4.</p>
        <p>If the Pacers can knot the series at two games apiece, all of the Lakers' playoff demons will start swirling anew. With a lead of two games to one, the Lakers' emotional state is about as fragile as the health of Bryant's ankle.</p>
        <p>After missing Game 3, the 21-year-old Wunderkind guard eschewed crutches today and walked with barely a limp. Bryant said he would probably play, but Coach Phil Jackson was much more cautious and would make no guarantees about Bryant's return to the lineup.</p>
        <p>''There is a question about Kobe coming back,'' Jackson said. ''There was still quite a bit of pain in the joint today. We'll still have to wait and see. I don't know if he'll be out on the floor even standing to shoot today or not.''</p>
        <p>Privately, the Pacers think Jackson's prognosis is a bit extreme. They expect to see Bryant play in a game that could swing the pendulum either way. A victory by the Pacers would not only tie the series, but it would also give them an opportunity to become the first home team since the 2-3-2 format began in 1985 to win the three middle games. Game 5 is Friday night.</p>
        <p>The Lakers are treating their meltdown in Game 3 as a small rut on their way to the franchise's first title since 1988. But Jackson has genuine issues to work out, including how to best use Rice's talents and assuage his complaints about sitting on the bench for nearly the entire fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>''It's obvious,'' Rice said today when asked whether he should become the team's second offensive option in Bryant's absence. ''It shouldn't really be a discussion. It's pretty much written down in ink. Any time your second option goes out and you've got a so-called third option, he should move up to the second option, shouldn't he?''</p>
        <p>Jackson had his own thoughts on the matter.</p>
        <p>''We came out in the third quarter, Glen had a real struggle that third quarter,'' he said. ''I just went to Rick Fox because we needed some defense and change of venue, and with that group out there we got back in the game. So, you stay with who plays.''</p>
        <p>Rice, who played 27 passive minutes and scored 7 points on 3-for-9 shooting, said: ''He'll probably tell you he was going with defense. I think if you look at it at that time, we didn't have that much offense going as well. The only person that was really doing scoring was Shaq. I was expecting to get a lot more touches but it just didn't happen.''</p>
        <p>O'Neal even chimed in.</p>
        <p>''I was disappointed a little bit that our best shooter was on the bench,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Informed of Rice's displeasure, Jackson said: ''I have no comment for that. That's the way he saw the game.''</p>
        <p>The rift between Jackson and Rice is an old one, born of Jackson's belief that Rice is not much of a rebounder nor a great defender and therefore has little long-term value in the Lakers' scheme.</p>
        <p>An even more ancient issue is O'Neal's troubles from the line. He attempted a record 39 free throws in Game 2, making 19. But with the crowd waving balloons and hollering, his 3-for-13 performance from the line Sunday was near abominable.</p>
        <p>''It's mental with Shaquille,'' Jackson said. ''Obviously, Shaq has a flaw in his stroke, and it's congenital or it's due to an accident or a broken wrist as a kid. He can't get the ball underneath his arm, so there's basically a flaw in his stroke. When he's shooting well, that's about the maximum he could ever shoot with the kind of shot he has.''</p>
        <p>During an annual address at the finals, Commissioner David Stern was emphatic that no rule changes would be implemented to prevent teams from intentionally fouling O'Neal and sending him to the free-throw line.</p>
        <p>So for now, the N.B.A.'s most valuable player and commodity has to concentrate even harder and sink the most fundamental shot in basketball. Unless that happens -- and unless Rice channels his frustration toward the Pacers and Bryant begins breaking down defenses again -- the Lakers could be in for a long, forgetful week in Indianapolis.</p>
        <p>O'Neal was reminded today that he has said he would make free throws when they counted, along with the fact that if he had made all his free throws the Lakers would have won. O'Neal was then asked if he looked at that as the difference in the game.</p>
        <p>''Yeah,'' he said. ''Yeah. Yeah.''</p>
        <p>N.B.A. FINALS: LAKERS VS. PACERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
