<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Front Row</title>
    <meta content="13FRON$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellafante, Ginia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4D9143EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Front Row</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ginia Bellafante</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Front Row column on growing popularity of fashion-related web sites; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This Thurdsay night, when the Council of Fashion Designers of America meets at Lincoln Center to honor itself and eat chicken, the group will dole out an award for the world's most compelling fashion-related Web site, the first time the council is offering such a prize. One might think that fashion had finally fallen in love with technology. But one would be wrong.</p>
        <p>Stan Herman, president of the council, said that the new award comes as a result of ''wanting to do something for the sponsors.'' One of the major sponsors for Thursday's American Fashion Awards is Style365.com, a site that specializes in design-oriented links.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This Thurdsay night, when the Council of Fashion Designers of America meets at Lincoln Center to honor itself and eat chicken, the group will dole out an award for the world's most compelling fashion-related Web site, the first time the council is offering such a prize. One might think that fashion had finally fallen in love with technology. But one would be wrong.</p>
        <p>Stan Herman, president of the council, said that the new award comes as a result of ''wanting to do something for the sponsors.'' One of the major sponsors for Thursday's American Fashion Awards is Style365.com, a site that specializes in design-oriented links.</p>
        <p>Just how out of sync fashion culture is with cyberlife became clearer still when Fern Mallis, the fashion group's executive director, went casting about for nominees in the fresh dot-com category. Ms. Mallis began by soliciting suggestions from the same 70 fashion directors, editors and retailers who supply lists of contenders for the other fashion awards. Her calls became a dead end, however.  ''People would say, 'The truth, is I don't really have a computer,' '' Ms. Mallis recalled. ''I want to say that I was surprised, but I wasn't.'' So she asked Web designers.</p>
        <p>Whatever its claims to forward-thinking-ness and however self-amplified its worship of the modern, the fashion world is essentially a technophobic place. Some use the excuse that conjuring up wardrobes is essentially a genteel undertaking that doesn't lend itself to images of people sitting in front of keyboards. If you had wanted to send an e-mail message to someone at Christian Dior as late as February, say, you would have had little luck. Employees in the New York office were given e-mail just three months ago. ''We were late in getting it because of a wiring problem in the building,'' said Courtney Moss, vice president of public relations at the company. By the standards of the fashion industry, however, Dior was not exceedingly late. Celine and Barneys New York, for example, received e-mail only in the past six months.</p>
        <p>Robin Kramer, head of the store-design and fashion consultancy firm KramerHutchison, says she is consistently surprised by the ways in which the fashion business trails the worlds of architecture and design in terms of a willingness to exploit technology. ''I think it's very behind,'' Ms. Kramer said, recalling the days, just over four years ago, when she was an executive at Calvin Klein and worked in a division that didn't have computers. ''They tracked invoices by hand,'' Ms. Kramer said of the routine in the store-design division where she worked. ''I used to say, 'Hey, could someone get me an abacus?' ''</p>
        <p>Fashion's cyber queasiness plays out on the World Wide Web, where it is difficult to find visually remarkable sites having to do with clothes. At www .Gucci.com, one might expect to find a Web site as trend-setting as the brand itself. But it's a visually flat corporate-image site with pictures of current Gucci magazine ads and bits of information like what a coup it was for Gucci's president, Domenico De Sole, to buy back the company's watch license. Go to www.Prada.com and you will find only a photo and a banner that reads ''Opening soon.'' Calvin Klein and Comme des Garcons have no Web presence at all.</p>
        <p>It was with this situation in mind that Ayshe Farman-Farmaian and her brother Farhad Farman-Farmaian, partners in a downtown Web design firm called Digital Form, decided to seek fashion houses as potential clients. So far, Digital Form has designed a Web site for Cacharel, and one for Oscar de la Renta in which current collections can be viewed. The team is also putting up a site for Versace.</p>
        <p>''You see these people who go to the shows,'' Mr. Farman-Farmaian said, ''and they're sitting there sketching. They could be using digital cameras and using e-mail more creatively to send images.''</p>
        <p>His sister, a graduate of the Media Lab at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, believes that slow-footedness isn't necessarily a bad thing, particularly when it comes to selling expensive clothes over the Web. Boo.com, the much-hyped online fashion store, came to little and shut down a few weeks ago. ''As a tool for branding,'' Ms. Farman-Farmaian said, ''the Web can't be underestimated.'' But she added, ''A lot of e-commerce experiments have failed, so it isn't necessarily foolish for designers to be cautious.''</p>
        <p>For a technological culture to evolve completely within the fashion world, designers, the factories and the stores would have to embrace advances simultaneously. At Kate Spade, the label's head of product development, Pamela Bell, said the company had installed CAD, the computer-assisted design program. But Ms. Bell said, ''It's basically not in use.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
