<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Agent Says Pirro Overdrew Personal Account and Used Company Funds for Family Bills</title>
    <meta content="13PIRR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207088"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Internal Revenue Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pirro, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pirro, Albert J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pirro, Jeanine (Dist Atty)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dennehy, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EEDD153EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Agent Says Pirro Overdrew Personal Account and Used Company Funds for Family Bills</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Internal Revenue Service agent John Dennehy, reinforcing argument that Albert J Pirro Jr intentionally tried to evade taxes, testifies that Pirro avoided using his own personal account to pay for personal items; admits, during cross-examination, that Pirro's companies had improperly deducted only $884,798 out of $16.35 million in total deductions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reinforcing the argument that Albert J. Pirro Jr. intentionally tried to evade taxes, an agent for the Internal Revenue Service said today that Mr. Pirro avoided using his own personal account to pay for personal items even though his checkbook balance was frequently more than sufficient and had at least $100,000 in overdraft protection.</p>
        <p>Testifying for the fifth straight day in Mr. Pirro's federal tax-fraud trial, the agent, John Dennehy, said that Mr. Pirro had overdrawn his personal account on several occasions -- including as much as $100,313.66 in December 1991 -- apparently without repercussions from his bank. Moreover, Mr. Dennehy said that Mr. Pirro used corporate accounts to pay bills in the early and mid-1990's, including bills for furniture ($2,140), his family's utilities ($1,232) and a painter ($500), even though there  was at least $40,908 in his own checking account during each of those transactions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reinforcing the argument that Albert J. Pirro Jr. intentionally tried to evade taxes, an agent for the Internal Revenue Service said today that Mr. Pirro avoided using his own personal account to pay for personal items even though his checkbook balance was frequently more than sufficient and had at least $100,000 in overdraft protection.</p>
        <p>Testifying for the fifth straight day in Mr. Pirro's federal tax-fraud trial, the agent, John Dennehy, said that Mr. Pirro had overdrawn his personal account on several occasions -- including as much as $100,313.66 in December 1991 -- apparently without repercussions from his bank. Moreover, Mr. Dennehy said that Mr. Pirro used corporate accounts to pay bills in the early and mid-1990's, including bills for furniture ($2,140), his family's utilities ($1,232) and a painter ($500), even though there  was at least $40,908 in his own checking account during each of those transactions.</p>
        <p>But under intense cross-examination from Robert J. Giuffra Jr., one of Mr. Pirro's lawyers, Mr. Dennehy acknowledged that after several years of investigations, the government concluded that Mr. Pirro's companies had improperly deducted only $884,798 out of $16.35 million in total deductions, or 5.4 percent.</p>
        <p>''In my book, being right 95 percent of the time is pretty good,'' Mr. Giuffra later told Judge Barrington D. Parker Jr., with the jury out of earshot.</p>
        <p>The government wrapped up its case today against Mr. Pirro, the husband of Jeanine F. Pirro, the Westchester County district attorney, and his brother and accountant, Anthony G. Pirro.</p>
        <p>The brothers are accused of improperly deducting more than $1.2 million of Albert Pirro's personal expenses as business write-offs, thereby lightening Albert Pirro's tax liability by more than $400,000.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, both Mr. Giuffra and Roger L. Stavis, Anthony Pirro's lawyer, scored points by forcing Mr. Dennehy to acknowledge that most of Albert Pirro's corporate deductions were legitimate, that Albert Pirro signed few of the checks he is accused of improperly deducting, and that Anthony was not the only accountant who tackled Albert Pirro's voluminous tax returns.</p>
        <p>Today, an assistant United States attorney, Cathy Seibel, came out swinging to present a point-by-point rebuttal of the defense's main arguments.</p>
        <p>Marinating her questions with plenty of sarcasm, Ms. Seibel first asked Mr. Dennehy whether the dozen or so errors pointed out by Mr. Giuffra in a summary of Mr. Pirro's deductions affected his calculations of how much Mr. Pirro owed. No, Mr. Dennehy responded.</p>
        <p>Then, referring to how one of Albert Pirro's businesses, AJP Management Group, a licensed real estate broker, produced a cable television program for Mrs. Pirro when she was a county judge, Ms. Seibel asked, ''Is producing a TV show for the spouse's wife an ordinary and necessary expense of a licensed real estate broker?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuffra objected -- something he did so frequently this morning that he spent almost as much time standing as sitting.</p>
        <p>Judge Parker agreed, scolding Ms. Seibel for being argumentative.</p>
        <p>It could have continued, but Judge Parker denied the government's request to ask Mr. Dennehy more questions.</p>
        <p>With that, the prosecution rested, the defense said that it would present its first witness Tuesday morning and Judge Parker told jurors that the trial should conclude by week's end. But once the jury exited, there was more legal jousting.</p>
        <p>For one thing, both Mr. Giuffra and Mr. Stavis asked Judge Parker to dismiss the case, on the ground that the government had failed to prove that the Pirros had conspired to evade taxes. The judge refused.</p>
        <p>And Elliott B. Jacobson, the government's lead prosecutor, tried to introduce documents showing that Albert Pirro was not exactly ''like any layman off the street or a babe in the woods'' on tax law, as he said the defense had implied.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jacobson suggested that since he could remember the basics of his own tax law classes from 20 years ago (at Harvard), then Mr. Pirro could certainly remember a few things from his days, too (at Albany).</p>
        <p>Again, the judge refused.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
