<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parents Try to Reclaim Their Children's Time</title>
    <meta content="Y13FAM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207030"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wayzata (Minn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belluck, Pam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Minnesota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Minnesota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E4D8143EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parents Try to Reclaim Their Children's Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAM BELLUCK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belluck, Pam</byline>
      <dateline>WAYZATA, Minn.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents of Wayzata, prosperous suburb of Minneapolis, are calling for slowdown in afterschool activities out of concern that children may be missing out on character-shaping family rituals by spending too much time away from home; want scheduling of afterschool programs to be deferential to family meals, family trips and family celebrations; hope to start national movement, in which such programs downshift children's schedules, softening frenetic way of life that grips many American children; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has seeped into this vibrant suburb of Minneapolis just as it has from Scarsdale to Santa Monica, overwhelming parents and overtaking children's lives: the schedule.</p>
        <p>Soccer practice, dance class, play rehearsal, Boy Scouts. Be at Tuesday football practice or be benched in Saturday's game. First graders carry daily planners. Family vacations, not to mention family dinners, take a back seat to basketball. And it has become cachet at cocktail parties to compare whose kids are the busiest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has seeped into this vibrant suburb of Minneapolis just as it has from Scarsdale to Santa Monica, overwhelming parents and overtaking children's lives: the schedule.</p>
        <p>Soccer practice, dance class, play rehearsal, Boy Scouts. Be at Tuesday football practice or be benched in Saturday's game. First graders carry daily planners. Family vacations, not to mention family dinners, take a back seat to basketball. And it has become cachet at cocktail parties to compare whose kids are the busiest.</p>
        <p>Now some parents in Wayzata (pronounced wye-ZETA), a prosperous, purposeful community of high-achieving, energetic children and color-coded family calendars, have decided that it is all too much.</p>
        <p>They are concerned that too little time with parents means that children are missing the stabilizing, character-shaping experiences of rituals like suppertime conversations and family outings. And, especially in the wake of school shootings, in which the killers' parents often seemed to know little about their children's lives, they are worried that the influence of peers and the media and commercialism may be outweighing the influence of parents.</p>
        <p>In a grass-roots effort unlike anything else in the country, parents and community leaders here are calling for a slowdown. A few months ago, they began asking coaches, dance instructors, churches and leaders of youth groups to cut back on practices, rehearsals and meetings. They want a loosening of polices that penalize children for missing practice or tell families not to vacation during spring break. And in scheduling and attitude, they want programs to be deferential to family meals, family trips and family celebrations.</p>
        <p>As an incentive, the group, which has attracted dozens of families and calls itself Family Life 1st, will begin bestowing a ''seal of approval'' on groups this summer that become family-friendly, hoping that such programs will be as eager to display the seal as they are trophies.</p>
        <p>But the larger mission is to start a national movement, in which such programs -- and parents themselves -- downshift children's schedules, softening the frenetic way of life that grips many American children and letting families reclaim popcorn nights, puzzle marathons and visits to Aunt Jane. To do that, they have to confront concerns that cutting back will hurt children's futures or the quality of programs.</p>
        <p>''We're losing our kids to over scheduled hyperactivity,'' said William J. Doherty, a professor of family social science at the University of Minnesota who inspired the Wayzata movement last year.</p>
        <p>''It's a question of balance,'' Professor Doherty continued. ''Dance and karate, these are all good things. Parents are not making appointments with drug dealers for their children. But we want parents to say, 'Am I overdoing the providing of activity opportunities and underdoing the providing of family time?' ''</p>
        <p>Barbara Carlson, a mother of four and one of the movement's leaders, said Wayzata was even planning workshops about making dinners and other family activities fulfilling because parents have said, '' 'If I get this time with my family, you have to show me what to do with my kids.' ''</p>
        <p>At a time when the variety of children's activities has exploded, with higher levels of success at younger ages, families get swept into a kind of extracurricular extravagance, trying to give children the chance to excel, or at least participate, in whatever interests them.</p>
        <p>At Kristin Bender's house, where commotion of the ''I can't find my cleats'' variety reigns as her three children rush to participate in three different sports programs simultaneously, she shoehorns in family time by having everyone meet near the sports fields for half an hour.</p>
        <p>Margaret Roddy's son Drew, 17, a basketball player, has been benched for taking a family vacation.</p>
        <p>In one week recently, Kris Frank drove 200 miles, mostly shuttling to hockey and dance.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes I'm in the car from 3 p.m. till 7 or 8 -- go and drop and pick and drop -- without being able to take a breath once,'' she said. ''This has finally snowballed to the point where people say wait a minute. We're all screaming, 'Help!' ''</p>
        <p>Of course, putting family ahead of extracurricular pursuits is complicated. Children like these activities and parents risk disappointing them by restricting participation. And parents value them because they teach virtues like teamwork and persistence, and keep children out of trouble and away from less enriching pastimes. Coaches and program directors are judged on their programs' success, creating pressure to schedule more practices and year-round playing seasons, and discourage talented children from scaling back.</p>
        <p>In and around Wayzata, a town of 4,000 people about 12 miles west of downtown Minneapolis on the northern shore of Lake Minnetonka, there is no shortage of skepticism.</p>
        <p>''In theory I support it 100 percent,'' said Greg Rye, who said that because his 9-year-old son Michael's soccer takes up four days a week, the boy often eats ''on the fly.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Rye worries that if Michael misses a season or does not play on the more competitive traveling teams, he may be denied opportunities later.</p>
        <p>''If Michael doesn't get to play soccer in high school because he didn't get involved early, then the person who would potentially be harmed down the road is my son,'' said Mr. Rye, a school board member. ''The one thing I won't do is make my kid's future a test case.''</p>
        <p>Ann and Barry Vermeer, with two extremely busy children, favor relaxing policies that, for example, now require that their son John, 17, not miss more than two rehearsals of the school musical. Obeying that policy means that medical checkups must take place during school hours and that John cannot visit colleges next fall.</p>
        <p>But the Vermeers and others fear consequences if no other towns follow suit. If Wayzata's teams cut a practice a week, wouldn't the competition get better? Couldn't that drive good players and coaches from Wayzata?</p>
        <p>''If the quality is going to go down, you are going to have difficulty retaining people who want to excel,'' said Mr. Vermeer, a lawyer. And less competitive programs ''can hurt your chance for a college scholarship.''</p>
        <p>Several students said they might be overscheduled, but were happy.</p>
        <p>''When I have a busier schedule, I become more organized and more focused,'' said Nnennia Ejebe, 17. ''And even if the activities cut back, you can still avoid your parents.''</p>
        <p>Sunia Hartmann, 18, said she believed ''sports and activities are a little stricter than they need to be.''</p>
        <p>''But what I notice about myself,'' Ms. Hartmann said, ''is I choose to be this busy.''</p>
        <p>Some program directors say it would be hard to set limits.</p>
        <p>''Impossible,'' said Marv Miller, manager of the Dance Shoppe, a competitive dance studio. ''Why would we cut back? We're a privately owned for-profit organization.''</p>
        <p>Tim McKee, a football coach who avoids practicing on Wednesday, which is church night, said, ''If you could get all the football programs in the state of Minnesota to agree to this, I'd be the first one to sign.''</p>
        <p>But he added that ''some people think we're not practicing enough.''</p>
        <p>Aware that it might be misconstrued as a backlash against extracurricular programs, Family Life 1st is trying to involve coaches, clergy and others in the planning, and emphasizes that parents must make sure children attend programs they register for.</p>
        <p>Some coaches and others are supportive. Gordy Engel, a longtime leader of community sports, said he was trying to discourage a basketball coach from adding a second weekly practice and starting a second grade traveling team.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Dave Hoadley, youth pastor at St. Philip the Deacon Lutheran Church, says his church schedules too many youth activities.</p>
        <p>And Brad Anderson, the Wayzata High School football coach who believes that starting too young or practicing too much can kill the joy of the game, said, ''If enough parents think it's worthwhile, programs will take notice -- as long as it's not time just turned over for the family to do Nintendo or turn on the TV set.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Doherty, whose books, ''Take Back Your Kids'' and ''The Intentional Family,'' discuss the importance of family rituals and how the culture of consumerism and individualism has convinced parents that they must ply children with activities to keep them happy, urges parents to withstand such pressures.</p>
        <p>''We're so focused on the child as an individual,'' he said. ''But there's a ton of research to support that if a kid doesn't have good family connections, nothing else comes close to taking the place of that.''</p>
        <p>Several parents said the shootings at Columbine High School in Littleton, Colo., an affluent community not unlike Wayzata, had made them more concerned about spending time with their children. Bugs Peter schmidt, who encouraged her son Max, 12, to quit Boy Scouts and summer soccer, said she recalled hearing that the killers' parents had attended all their ballgames, which seemed like good parenting but was really parenting from the sidelines.</p>
        <p>''That's not a solution anymore,'' said Mrs. Peterschmidt, a cake decorator. ''We want to give our kids rituals and slowing down and hopefully a base. There's no guarantee that if your child is doing soccer and Boy Scouts and this and this that they're going to be successful in life.''</p>
        <p>Greg Baufield, whose family started keeping track of how often members ate together, said his daughter Lauren, 11, would have to choose between soccer and dance.</p>
        <p>''These are your children,'' Mr. Baufield said. ''You only get a few years with them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
