<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nassau to Cut $52 Million From Budget</title>
    <meta content="13NASS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207065"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E3DE153EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nassau to Cut $52 Million From Budget</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, N.Y., June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nassau County, NY, officials clear first hurdle in their path to receiving $105 million state bailout by agreeing to cut more than $52 million from county's deficit-ridden 2000 budget; cuts, far from draconian measures many people had feared, are spread over many county departments and rely heavily on less onerous measures such as hiring freeze, loss of jobs through attrition and incentive packages to get county employees to quit their jobs; agreement, however, calls for deep cuts in county's Police Department (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nassau County officials cleared the first hurdle in their path to receiving a $105 million state bailout by agreeing today to cut more than $52 million from the county's deficit-ridden 2000 budget.</p>
        <p>The cuts, far from the draconian measures many people had feared, are spread  over many county departments and rely heavily on less onerous measures like a hiring freeze, the loss of jobs through attrition and incentive packages to get county employees to quit their jobs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nassau County officials cleared the first hurdle in their path to receiving a $105 million state bailout by agreeing today to cut more than $52 million from the county's deficit-ridden 2000 budget.</p>
        <p>The cuts, far from the draconian measures many people had feared, are spread  over many county departments and rely heavily on less onerous measures like a hiring freeze, the loss of jobs through attrition and incentive packages to get county employees to quit their jobs.</p>
        <p>But the agreement calls for deep cuts in the county's Police Department and reductions that bring in less money but are of  symbolic importance to a county whose government is often seen as wasteful. These include selling county vehicles and eliminating meal stipends that were paid to nonunion employees.</p>
        <p>And far more painful cuts are looming. Even as county leaders finish trimming the 2000 budget, they must find $70 million more in reductions for the 2001 budget. Then they must find another $70 million for 2002 and still another $70 million for 2003.</p>
        <p>This otherwise wealthy county must adhere to the strict schedule to qualify for a fiscal recovery plan proposed last month by Gov. George E. Pataki. If the county keeps its end of the bargain, the state will provide $105 million in aid over the next five years and create a special authority to refinance county debt on more favorable terms. If the county fails, the authority will take control of Nassau's finances out of the hands of its elected officials.</p>
        <p>The Nassau County Legislature is expected to convene here in an emergency session  Tuesday evening to pass a ''home rule message,'' which is needed before the State Legislature can enact the fiscal recovery plan. Leaders in Albany agreed on the major points of the plan last Thursday but are still drafting the final version of the bill.</p>
        <p>Even without the final bill in place, county leaders had to begin making the spending cuts it calls for. In addition to worrying about the state, the county must worry about Wall Street. Standard &amp; Poor's, the credit-rating agency, has threatened to downgrade Nassau's bonds to junk status if the county's finances do not improve by June 30.</p>
        <p>So representatives of Nassau County's bitterly divided government negotiated throughout the weekend on spending cuts and met here this afternoon to present their agreed-upon plan to the governor's special adviser on the county, Frank G. Zarb.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zarb, who sent the county leaders back to the drawing board last week after their original plan relied too heavily on cuts that would not recur in 2001, did not comment on today's agreement. But county officials said that he accepted the proposal that was given to him here at the Garden City Hotel and urged them to keep working on future cuts.</p>
        <p>The final agreement is made up of more than 60 proposals, most of which save less than $1 million, and some of which have already been enacted. The deal was worked out over the weekend by County Executive Thomas S. Gulotta, a Republican; Judith A. Jacobs, the Democratic presiding officer of the County Legislature; John J. Ciotti, the Republican deputy minority leader; and their staffs.</p>
        <p>It calls for major reductions in the Police Department: cutting overtime by nearly $5 million; cutting $480,000 by eliminating some senior administrative positions and $452,000 more by redeploying senior police officials. At the county jail, it would use video teleconferencing to reduce the costs of taking inmates back and forth to court and would hire civilians to do work now done by higher-paid corrections officers.</p>
        <p>Two sticking points that had complicated negotiations were solved with compromises. The first involved layoffs. Republicans in the Legislature and Mr. Gulotta both raised objections to a proposal by legislative Democrats that would have eliminated 56 nonunion positions, including the jobs of a number of political appointees. The Republicans favored using incentives for early retirements over layoffs.</p>
        <p>The savings plan that was agreed upon calls for using incentives to entice people to quit their jobs, even those who have held the positions for only a few years and are not eligible for early retirement. But if the plan does not yield $589,707 in savings this year and $2.3 million next year, the county will lay off workers.</p>
        <p>The other sticking point involved the cuts that have already been made to the private agencies that provide social services for the county. Mr. Gulotta had threatened further cuts, while Democrats had said they wanted to restore some of the financing that was already cut. In the end, the parties agreed to restore some money, but not as much as the Democrats had first hoped. The restorations were $1 million this year and $2.5 million next year.</p>
        <p>Some of the proposals need state approval, including a new hotel tax and a new tax on ticket sales, but officials said that they expected the state to approve most of them.</p>
        <p>Even as the county is trying to encourage more people to retire, the savings plan was endangered at the last minute on Sunday when county officials learned that their estimate of the number of police officers planning to retire this year was way too low.</p>
        <p>The problem is their severance packages: police officers routinely get hefty sums for unused vacation time when they retire. Roughly 200 officers are now expected to retire this year, which would cost the county an unexpected $12 million in severance packages and unused vacation time.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
