<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oil Prices Surge Past $31 With No Sign of OPEC Intervention</title>
    <meta content="Y13OIL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Refineries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Saudi Arabia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Algeria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Midwestern States (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perciasepe, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kenderdine, Melanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Algeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Algeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DD153EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1160" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oil Prices Surge Past $31 With No Sign of OPEC Intervention</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>FRANKFURT, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>World oil prices surge to more than $31 a barrel, highest level in three months, on growing uncertainty whether OPEC ministers will decide to increase production at their next meeting in nine days; motorists in US are paying highest prices in decade for gasoline; in some areas, motorists are already paying more than $2 a gallon and possibility that OPEC production might not rise has caused new concern among large oil-importing nations about overall prospects for easing gasoline prices; Saudi Arabia, world's largest producer, wants to increase production and bring prices down; more aggressive members like Iran and Algeria want to keep prices high; in London, Brent crude rises $1.63 a barrel, or 5 percent, to $31.21; in New York, light sweet crude rises $1.54 a barrel, or 5.1 percent, to $31.74; US officials, including Robert Perciasepe, of Environmental Protection Agency, and Melanie Kenderdine, of Energy Department, meet with refiners that supply gasoline to Midwestern states; motorists in Midwest are paying highest prices for gasoline; graph; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>World oil prices surged to more than $31 a barrel today, the highest level in three months, on growing uncertainty whether OPEC ministers will decide to increase production at their next meeting in nine days.</p>
        <p>Oil prices are significantly higher now than they were in late March, after the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries, which controls nearly half of the global oil supply, decided to raise its official production limit by about 1.7 million barrels a day, or 7 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>World oil prices surged to more than $31 a barrel today, the highest level in three months, on growing uncertainty whether OPEC ministers will decide to increase production at their next meeting in nine days.</p>
        <p>Oil prices are significantly higher now than they were in late March, after the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries, which controls nearly half of the global oil supply, decided to raise its official production limit by about 1.7 million barrels a day, or 7 percent.</p>
        <p>That increase, reached only after Iran angrily but unsuccessfully rebelled, was supposed to bring modest relief to gasoline consumers. But as the summer driving season begins, the production increase has been more than offset by rising demand and depleted gasoline inventories in the United States, the world's largest consumer of oil and one of the biggest importers of foreign oil.</p>
        <p>Motorists in the United States are already paying the highest prices in a decade for gasoline. Last week, the United States Energy Department predicted that gasoline prices would average $1.50 a gallon this summer, though declining as the vacation season wound down. But in some areas, motorists are already paying more than $2 a gallon, and the possibility that OPEC production might not rise has caused new concern among large oil-importing nations about the overall prospects for easing gasoline prices.</p>
        <p>From the importers' view, the most pessimistic piece of information about OPEC's intentions came late last week, when the 11-nation group did not invoke a production increase that was meant to happen automatically once the 20-day average for oil prices exceeded $28 a barrel.</p>
        <p>That leaves OPEC leaders once again divided along almost exactly the same lines now as they were three months ago.</p>
        <p>Saudi Arabia, the world's biggest producer, wants to increase production and bring prices down. More aggressive members like Iran and Algeria want to keep prices high.</p>
        <p>''Effectively, what is going on now is the politics of OPEC, and really it is quite traditional politics,'' said Raad Alkadiri, an analyst at the Petroleum Finance Company in Washington, an oil-business consulting company.</p>
        <p>Even with a fresh Saudi warning today that oil prices are too high, traders bid up the price of the benchmark grades of crude to the highest since OPEC's last meeting in March. In London, Brent crude rose $1.63 a barrel, or 5 percent, to $31.21. In New York, light sweet crude rose $1.54 a barrel, or 5.1 percent, to $31.74.</p>
        <p>At least for the moment, the United States Government is keeping a low profile. It has not issued any statements urging OPEC members to reach a particular decision, in contrast to the highly public lobbying campaign waged three months ago by the secretary of energy, Bill Richardson.</p>
        <p>As so often in the past, oil prices and the internal workings of OPEC have confounded forecasters and oil traders for the last few months.</p>
        <p>At OPEC's tumultuous last meeting, Saudi officials managed to push through a modest rise in production.</p>
        <p>In what was seen primarily as a form of insurance if prices started to fall too quickly, OPEC ministers also agreed on automatic changes, up or down, of 500,000 barrels a day if oil prices moved outside a band of $22 to $28 per barrel.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, when the 20-day average price was nearing the upper limit of that range, OPEC's president, Ali Rodriguez of Venezuela, announced that the cartel would probably invoke a production increase. But OPEC delegates later decided to postpone a decision until their June 21 meeting. On Sunday, OPEC's secretary general, Rilwanu Lukman, said the automatic price change ''was always an informal plan,'' and that the group would probably make no decisions before its meeting next week in Vienna.</p>
        <p>Industry analysts say Saudi officials were never comfortable with an automatic mechanism, because they feared losing their grip.</p>
        <p>Saudi Arabia's oil minister, Ali Naimi, predicted that OPEC would have to increase production to bring prices down to a more stable level.  But some Saudi officials evidently believe that the increase might need to be more than 500,000 barrels a day. By allowing the automatic increase to take effect, analysts said, Saudi officials would be in a weak political position to argue the need for additional production increases.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, other cartel members are lobbying against deciding on any increase until at least September. The Dow Jones news agency quoted Algeria's oil minister, Chakib Khelil, as saying that OPEC is unlikely to raise output either before or at the Vienna meeting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khelil added that OPEC probably would raise output by 1.2 million barrels in September. But traders reacted by pushing prices up, because the comments suggested little quick relief for replenishing the dwindling crude-oil supplies available to refiners.</p>
        <p>''Inventories are very low and the market is indeed very tight,''said Gary N. Ross, head of PIRA Energy, an industry research firm in New York. Mr. Ross was one of many forecasters who had predicted that prices would drop to about $24 a barrel. ''I admit it,'' he acknowledged, ''the expected buildup in stocks during the second quarter was less than we expected.''</p>
        <p>Even if OPEC does decide to increase production next week, consumers may not notice the impact for weeks or months. The Middle Eastern Economic Survey, a respected industry publication, reported today that member countries exceeded their official quotas in May by about 588,000 barrels a day. Iraq, which is an OPEC member but is not subject to the quotas, increased its production by 400,000 barrels as well.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Gasoline Prices Soar</p>
        <p>By The Associated Press</p>
        <p>Federal officials met for two hours with refiners yesterday, and the Environmental Protection Agency's top air pollution official said he heard no good explanation for soaring gasoline prices in Midwest cities where new requirements require cleaner-burning gas.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency and the Energy Department said field inspectors were sent to the Milwaukee and Chicago areas to investigate price increases in recent weeks of 30 to 50 cents a gallon. They focused on both refining and distribution, one official said.</p>
        <p>At the White House, Joe Lockhart, the press secretary, said the Midwest ''price hikes seem to be out of whack,'' and added that any evidence of price-gouging investigators found would be turned over to the Federal Trade Commission for further investigation.</p>
        <p>Officials from eight major oil refineries sat in on the E.P.A. and  Energy Department meeting, and further sessions were held later with individual companies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
