<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GOLF: A Birth, a Death And a Burning Desire; Mickelson Wants to Win the U.S. Open, Badly</title>
    <meta content="13MICK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207078"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mickelson, Phil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4DD153EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GOLF: A Birth, a Death And a Burning Desire; Mickelson Wants to Win the U.S. Open, Badly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Golfer Phil Mickelson discusses his preparations for US Open golf championship; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some of the most moving experiences in Phil Mickelson's life and career have taken place during the past 12 months.</p>
        <p>He engaged in a classic final-round duel last June with Payne Stewart, losing the United States Open by one stroke, after Stewart made a remarkable 18-foot putt on the last hole. Less than 24 hours later, Mickelson was in an Arizona hospital, watching his wife, Amy, give birth to their first child, Amanda Brynn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some of the most moving experiences in Phil Mickelson's life and career have taken place during the past 12 months.</p>
        <p>He engaged in a classic final-round duel last June with Payne Stewart, losing the United States Open by one stroke, after Stewart made a remarkable 18-foot putt on the last hole. Less than 24 hours later, Mickelson was in an Arizona hospital, watching his wife, Amy, give birth to their first child, Amanda Brynn.</p>
        <p>Last fall, Mickelson was part of the biggest comeback in Ryder Cup history, when the United States rallied from 4 points down on the final day to defeat Europe, 15-13. Mickelson celebrated that improbable victory with his teammates, including Stewart, who had great passion for the Ryder Cup, and for life in general. But less than three months later, Stewart was dead, killed with five other people in a plane crash in October.</p>
        <p>Now Mickelson is preparing for another compelling scene -- this week's United States Open, which begins Thursday at the historic Pebble Beach Golf Links in California. Pebble Beach is a place revered for its beauty, but it is also known for producing some of golf's finest theater. How fitting would it be for Mickelson, a California native, to capture his first major championship at Pebble Beach? How emotional would it be for Mickelson, one year after his showdown with Stewart, to succeed the friend who died as the next Open champion?</p>
        <p>Those questions were posed to Mickelson recently, as he anticipated another dramatic week. Winning the Open would be the high point of his career, the defining moment for a player who has the talent to win a major, but who has failed to reach that goal. But as badly as Mickelson craves a victory in a major, in hindsight, he would not change the outcome of what happened last year in Pinehurst, N.C., when Stewart won for the last time, and Mickelson was denied his first major.</p>
        <p>Call it destiny. Call it fate. Whatever it was, Mickelson has learned to accept it.</p>
        <p>''Looking back on last year's Open, I don't have the regret you might think,'' Mickelson said. ''I wanted deeply to win the U.S. Open, probably more than any other player out there. I'm an American player. I haven't won a major. And when Payne made that putt, it was a very disappointing feeling to lose the U.S. Open.</p>
        <p>''However, in light of what has happened, I wouldn't change it even if I could. I look at last year now as a great triumph for the man Payne Stewart, and a tribute to the memory of Payne Stewart. To me, that takes away all the disappointment.</p>
        <p>''In addition, all the disappointment I felt that Sunday disappeared the very next day, with the birth of our child. If Payne hadn't made that putt, we would have gone into a playoff the next day, and I wouldn't have been able to make the playoff anyway, because that's when my wife's water broke. I would have never missed the birth of my child. I would have never forgiven myself if that had happened. Some things happen for a reason. Things happened that day for a reason.''</p>
        <p>Now there are reasons to think Mickelson can win this year's Open. He has won three times since February, playing more consistent golf than anyone not named Tiger Woods.</p>
        <p>Mickelson plays well at Pebble Beach, where he won the 1998 AT&amp;T Pebble Beach National Pro-Am.</p>
        <p>And while some players have wilted when challenged by Woods, Mickelson has shown resolve in their head-to-head battles. Mickelson stopped Woods's six-tournament winning streak in February, making birdies on four of the final six holes to beat Woods by four strokes at the Buick Invitational. Mickelson also defeated Woods by one stroke at the 1998 Mercedes Championships.</p>
        <p>With four victories this year, including a victory at Pebble Beach, Woods is clearly the man to beat.</p>
        <p>But Mickelson will start the Open believing that if he plays well enough, he can overcome anything, or anyone.</p>
        <p>''The win in San Diego this year was important, not because I beat Tiger, but because I needed to get some positive feedback from the hard work I put in during this off-season,'' Mickelson said. ''It wasn't intimidating being chased by Tiger, but it was intense. It's always intense competing against a player like that, because you don't ever expect him to falter.</p>
        <p>''Last year was the first year I didn't win on tour. I was very disappointed. I felt my game had deteriorated from 150 yards in. So I went back to my old wedges. I worked harder. I find now that I don't have to manipulate the club as much to get the shot I want. My play this year has been much more consistent.''</p>
        <p>Part of that consistency comes from contentment. Mickelson relishes his new role as a father, and he is usually accompanied on the road by his wife, Amy, and their daughter, Amanda, who will turn a year old on June 21.</p>
        <p>''I think Phil's very happy now, and it shows in his game,'' said Tom Lehman, one of Mickelson's friends on the Tour. ''When Phil wants to be at the golf course, and he's focused, he's very tough to beat. When he's frustrated, or isn't motivated to play, it shows in his game. But right now, everything seems just right with him.''</p>
        <p>The subplot of Mickelson and the birth of his daughter added an unusual element of drama to last year's Open. Amy Mickelson had a difficult pregnancy, and by the week of the Open, she was confined to bed, due to deliver any day. Mickelson almost decided not to play, and Amy remembers her husband's words as he left the house.</p>
        <p>''He said, 'I'm going to come home with the U.S. Open trophy, we're going to have the baby, and it's going to be the best week of our lives,' '' Amy said. '' 'I'm not leaving you like this just so I can finish in the top 10.' ''</p>
        <p>With that resolve, Mickelson played a United States Open that would have been good enough to win, if not for Stewart's brilliance.</p>
        <p>Mickelson's caddie, Jim Mackay, carried a beeper in Mickelson's bag the entire week, and if Amy had given word that she had gone into labor, Mickelson was prepared to leave.</p>
        <p>In the tense final round, Mickelson and Stewart played together. They traded superb shots, but Stewart had an incredible day putting, needing only one putt on five of the last six greens.</p>
        <p>People will long talk about Stewart's Open-clinching putt at No. 18, but he made a putt that was even more miraculous on No. 16 -- a near-impossible uphill, 25-foot putt that broke left to right, then right to left. That putt kept Stewart tied with Mickelson. Then Stewart took the lead for good at the par-3 17th, hitting a tremendous 6-iron tee shot to 4 feet. Mickelson also hit an excellent tee shot at No. 17 to 8 feet, but he missed the putt, giving Stewart the upper hand when he made his 4-footer for birdie.</p>
        <p>Then came the climactic 18th hole. Amy was more than 2,000 miles away, watching on television with her feet elevated, hoping she would not go into labor while her husband was trying to win his first major.</p>
        <p>''It was one of the most emotional days you could ever imagine, thinking about Phil, thinking about the baby, not being able to be with him, wondering how it would end,'' Amy said.</p>
        <p>It ended when Stewart made his now-famous winning putt, giving Stewart his second United States Open title, and his final tournament victory. Stewart and Mickelson congratulated each other on the 18th green, as Stewart grabbed Mickelson's face with both hands and reminded him how special it was that he was about to become a father. Thinking a million thoughts, Mickelson took a flight home to Phoenix that night, in time to be with Amy when she went into labor the next day.</p>
        <p>''Phil didn't sleep at all that night after the Open, replaying the whole round in his mind,'' Amy said. ''But the next day, it was like all the pain went away when Amanda was born. In hindsight, the timing couldn't be any better.''</p>
        <p>Almost a year later, Mickelson now wants to win his first major, something he believes he should have done long ago.</p>
        <p>Why hasn't he?</p>
        <p>''My lack of patience is clearly what has prevented me from winning majors,'' said Mickelson, one of golf's most aggressive players on the course. ''That's the same quality that has allowed me to win a lot of tournaments. But in major championship conditions, when conditions are so severe, I need to back off and try not to birdie every hole. I also have to make crucial putts.''</p>
        <p>Mickelson will turn 30 years old on Friday, and he, David Duval and Colin Montgomerie have grown weary of hearing themselves described as ''the best players who have not won a major.''</p>
        <p>''By now, I figured I would have won at least one major,'' Mickelson said. ''Is it a burden? No. Right now, it's a fun challenge. Now if it doesn't happen, it could be a real problem. I'm still young enough that I have many more opportunities. However, I think by the time you turn 37 or 38, you've pretty much established the legacy you're going to leave.''</p>
        <p>Stewart has already left a legacy, and his absence will be felt by all of his friends this week.</p>
        <p>''He thinks about Payne a lot,'' Amy said. ''Everyone who has played out here for any amount of time has memories of Payne, because he had such an outgoing personality. Everybody shared a laugh with him. Everybody has had an intense moment with him.''</p>
        <p>For Mickelson and Stewart, their intense moment occurred a year ago at Pinehurst, a memory that Mickelson will always have. And after what happened a year ago, is it crazy to think that fate could smile on Mickelson this year at Pebble Beach?</p>
        <p>''Well, I think that's a nice thought,'' Mickelson said, smiling. ''I'm definitely not opposed to it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
