<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Supreme Court Roundup; The Justices Make It Easier To Win Suits for Job Bias</title>
    <meta content="13SCOT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207087"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Property</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tongass National Forest (Alaska)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Glacier Bay National Park (Alaska)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramdass, Bobby Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska/Glacier Bay National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EEDD153EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1213" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Supreme Court Roundup; The Justices Make It Easier To Win Suits for Job Bias</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Linda</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Supreme Court, in important job discrimination case, rules unanimously that plaintiff can prevail, even in absence of smoking-gun evidence of discrimination, by showing that an employer's innocent-sounding explanation for its action is lie; upholds, 5-4, death sentence for convicted murderer Bobby Lee Ramdass, who argued that he had right to have his jurors informed that because of his earlier criminal convictions, he would be ineligible for parole if the sentenced him to life in prison rather than death; invokes 'original jurisdiction' to resolve disputes between state and federal government over ownership of underwater land within boundaries of Tongass National Forest and Glacier Bay National Park and Preserve (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ruling in an important job discrimination case, the Supreme Court held unanimously today that a plaintiff can prevail, even in the absence of smoking-gun evidence of discrimination, by showing that an employer's innocent-sounding explanation for its action was a lie.</p>
        <p>A number of lower federal courts had required more than that, making discrimination suits subject to dismissal before trial, or reversal after a favorable jury verdict, if the plaintiff did not have actual proof that an employer's motive was discrimination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ruling in an important job discrimination case, the Supreme Court held unanimously today that a plaintiff can prevail, even in the absence of smoking-gun evidence of discrimination, by showing that an employer's innocent-sounding explanation for its action was a lie.</p>
        <p>A number of lower federal courts had required more than that, making discrimination suits subject to dismissal before trial, or reversal after a favorable jury verdict, if the plaintiff did not have actual proof that an employer's motive was discrimination.</p>
        <p>The court held today that even in the absence of concrete evidence of discrimination, proof that the employer's explanation is just a pretext can itself be sufficient proof, either as circumstantial evidence or as the basis for an inference that discrimination was the real reason.</p>
        <p>The decision, with an opinion by Justice Sandra Day O'Connor, overturned a ruling by the federal appeals court in New Orleans that a 57-year-old man's claim of age discrimination, accepted by a jury, failed for lack of sufficient evidence.</p>
        <p>The case resolved several issues about the sufficiency of evidence in discrimination cases, quite technical in form but likely to prove highly significant in practical application. Under a doctrine known as ''pretext-plus,'' meaning that plaintiffs who had shown an employer's explanation to be a pretext still had to come up with concrete evidence of their own, many lower courts were dismissing discrimination cases on motions for summary judgment before trial or, as in this case, were overturning jury verdicts.</p>
        <p>While the Supreme Court had never endorsed the pretext-plus rule, the justices had allowed it to become entrenched in courts around the country before suddenly agreeing last November to use this case, Reeves v. Sanderson Plumbing Products, No. 99-536, to examine the issue.</p>
        <p>While this was an age discrimination case, the same analysis applies to the litigation of race and sex discrimination cases brought under Title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 as well as cases brought under the Americans With Disabilities Act.</p>
        <p>Under rules the court developed in the 1970's for handling discrimination cases, a plaintiff first has to present a ''prima facie case,'' evidence suggesting that an adverse employment action like a dismissal or a refusal of promotion was due to a discriminatory reason. At that point, the burden shifts to the employer to offer a ''legitimate, nondiscriminatory reason'' that explains the action. Then the plaintiff has a chance to show that the legitimate reason was not the real one but was merely a pretext.</p>
        <p>The principal question in the case was what happens then. Can there be a finding of liability at that point, or does the plaintiff have the additional legal burden of producing actual evidence of discrimination? While liability can never be automatic, Justice O'Connor said, it is permissible to find it at that point.</p>
        <p>The judge or jury ''can reasonably infer from the falsity of the explanation that the employer is dissembling to cover up a discriminatory purpose,'' Justice O'Connor said, adding, ''Moreover, once the employer's justification has been eliminated, discrimination may well be the most likely alternative explanation, especially since the employer is in the best position to put forth the actual reason for its decision.''</p>
        <p>The issue was important because job bias is often hidden; proving it depends on inference and circumstantial evidence. For this reason, employers have argued on behalf of the ''pretext-plus'' standard that without it, disgruntled employees can too easily affix a discrimination label on actions that are nondiscriminatory and fully justified.</p>
        <p>The plaintiff in this case, a manager at a plumbing supply manufacturer in Mississippi, sued his employer for age discrimination after he was dismissed and replaced by a younger man. Before the dismissal, Mr. Reeves had been subjected to comments to the effect that he was old enough to have come over on the Mayflower, although the comments were not made in the context of the actual dismissal. The employer maintained that the dismissal was due to Mr. Reeves's failure to keep accurate records, but the jury rejected this defense and awarded him nearly $100,000.</p>
        <p>Justice O'Connor said today that in overturning the verdict, ''the Court of Appeals erred in proceeding from the premise that a plaintiff must always introduce additional, independent evidence of discrimination.''</p>
        <p>With five decisions today, the court now has 12 cases remaining for decision before it completes its term. These were among other actions today:</p>
        <p>Death Penalty</p>
        <p>By 5 to 4, the court upheld a death sentence for a convicted murderer in Virginia who argued that he had a right to have his jurors informed that because of his earlier criminal convictions, he would be ineligible for parole if they sentenced him to life in prison rather than death.</p>
        <p>Shortly after the prisoner, Bobby Lee Ramdass, was convicted and sentenced to death for the 1992 murder, the Supreme Court ruled, in an unrelated case from South Carolina, that jurors contemplating a death sentence must receive such information at the defendant's request.</p>
        <p>While the court has made that decision capable of being applied retroactively, the Virginia Supreme Court ruled that in this case, Mr. Ramdass would not have been eligible for the instruction because one of his prior convictions had not become final, making him nominally eligible for parole in 25 years. He then received a writ of habeas corpus from a Federal District Court in Alexandria, but the United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit, in Richmond, overturned that ruling in a decision the justices affirmed today.</p>
        <p>The decision, Ramdass v. Angelone, No. 99-7000, will have little effect on other Virginia prisoners, because the state subsequently eliminated parole for all convicted murderers sentenced to life in prison, and the State Supreme Court has required that jurors be informed of this if the defendant so requests.</p>
        <p>Justice Anthony M. Kennedy wrote a plurality decision that was joined by Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist and by Justices Antonin Scalia and Clarence Thomas. Justice O'Connor concurred in a separate opinion.</p>
        <p>Justice John Paul Stevens wrote a dissenting opinion that Justices David H. Souter, Ruth Bader Ginsburg and Stephen G. Breyer joined. They said there was an ''acute unfairness'' in permitting Virginia to use the defendant's criminal record to establish his ''future dangerousness'' for purposes of the death penalty while relying on a technicality -- the absence of a final judgment for one crime -- to keep information about parole away from the jury.</p>
        <p>Alaska Suit</p>
        <p>Invoking its ''original jurisdiction'' to resolve disputes between states or between a state and the federal government, the court accepted a case filed by Alaska against the United States to resolve the ownership of underwater land within the boundaries of the Tongass National Forest and the Glacier Bay National Park and Preserve.</p>
        <p>The question in the case, Alaska v. United States, No. 128 Original, is whether the federal government kept the thousands of acres when Alaska became a state in 1958 or whether the area passed to the state under any of several legal theories. At issue are fishing rights, rather than the oil and gas deposits that were at stake in an Alaska boundary case the court decided several years ago involving the Beaufort Sea.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
