<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Village, Guitars And Hootennannies: Stuff for a Museum?</title>
    <meta content="13HOOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E1DE153EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="635" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Village, Guitars And Hootennannies: Stuff for a Museum?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SISARIO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a bit of their erstwhile casualness, a group of veterans of the Greenwich Village folk music scene of the 50's and 60's are trying to establish a museum dedicated to the long-gone world of guitars, coffee houses, and social activism.</p>
        <p>They don't have money, plans, a site, or even an agreed-upon concept, but they do include some of the brightest lights of the era, and tomorrow night at 8 they will kick off their drive in earnest with a benefit concert at the Great Hall at Cooper Union. Among the performers will be Pete Seeger, Judy Collins, Odetta, Josh White Jr., David Amram and John Sebastian.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a bit of their erstwhile casualness, a group of veterans of the Greenwich Village folk music scene of the 50's and 60's are trying to establish a museum dedicated to the long-gone world of guitars, coffee houses, and social activism.</p>
        <p>They don't have money, plans, a site, or even an agreed-upon concept, but they do include some of the brightest lights of the era, and tomorrow night at 8 they will kick off their drive in earnest with a benefit concert at the Great Hall at Cooper Union. Among the performers will be Pete Seeger, Judy Collins, Odetta, Josh White Jr., David Amram and John Sebastian.</p>
        <p>A second fund-raising concert, with more recent Village performers, is planned for the fall.</p>
        <p>Art D'Lugoff, owner of the defunct Village Gate, which had been at the center of the scene, has spent the last year and a half forming a nonprofit corporation, and building up support and a board for what would be called the Folk Music Museum in Greenwich Village. The members include Ms. Collins and Paul Colby, owner of the Bitter End, another mainstay of the era, which is still in operation on Bleecker Street.</p>
        <p>The organizers are hoping to set up a center of 50,000 square feet that would include exhibition spaces, archives, rehearsal and performance spaces, a music school, a cafe and a shop for music and books. The museum's founders say they will honor the spirit of folk music at its broadest and embrace the sounds of the many ethnic groups of the city.</p>
        <p>But where the center would be is an open question. So is how much it would cost. Maybe a few million dollars, a few of the organizers say, maybe $10 million, maybe much more. ''A lot,'' said Ronald D. Cohen, a board member who is a a history professor at Indiana University Northwest, in Gary.</p>
        <p>And where will they get the money? ''We don't have a sugar daddy yet,'' Mr. Cohen said. ''We don't have a Paul Allen. But there are a lot of people who have made a lot of money off this music.''</p>
        <p>In addition to planning drives for individual donations and members, the board is looking for grants and corporate sponsors.</p>
        <p>''We hope people don't turn us aside because we don't have everything together,'' Mr. D'Lugoff said recently. ''We're getting our decks in order.''</p>
        <p>The board members have somewhat different ideas about the museum's focus.</p>
        <p>Ms. Collins envisions it as a ''historical, moving multimedia support system'' that will emphasize performance and rehearsal spaces and replicate the community of the Village coffee shops and musicians' gatherings of the 1950's and 60's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seeger has more concrete thoughts. ''Leadbelly's guitar is what they should get,'' he advised. But that is a problem for now. ''His niece has it, and she wants $100,000 for it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Nora Guthrie, the daughter of Woody Guthrie, who runs the Woody Guthrie Archives on West 57th Street in Manhattan and was consulted about the museum, is not interested in memorabilia or cafes and gift shops. She wants an emphasis on archives, and so far the museum has none, though the personal collections of Mr. D'Lugoff, Mr. Cohen and some of the others involved will probably find a home there.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seeger, for one, is optimistic. ''I bet if you started a collection and said who will put in the first $10 to buy Leadbelly's guitar, you'd get a million people.''</p>
        <p>Tickets for the concert, which are tax-deductible, are $30. They can be purchased at the Bitter End box office at 147 Bleecker Street or by calling (212) 673-7030.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
