<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deadly Mistakes</title>
    <meta content="13TUE2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000614T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E4D8143EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="565" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deadly Mistakes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says study by Columbia University criminologists of administration of death penalty, which found astonishing amount of error and corruption in way capital punishment is meted out in America, is indictment of multi-tiered review process as well as Supreme Court and Congress; says it should intensify debate over capital punishment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A team of lawyers and criminologists at Columbia University has taken a close look at America's administration of the death penalty and found an astonishing amount of error and corruption in the way capital punishment is meted out.</p>
        <p>Led by Prof. James Liebman of Columbia Law School, the study reviewed appeals in all capital cases over a 23-year period -- from the Supreme Court's reinstatement of the death penalty in 1973 through 1995. Among its key findings is that fully 68 percent of all death sentences were overturned on appeal because of mistakes by incompetent defense counsel, the withholding of evidence by police and prosecutors, or other prejudicial error. In fact, some experts say, the real error rate is probably a lot higher, since an incompetent lawyer would be unlikely to do the work necessary to preserve legal and factual issues for appeal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A team of lawyers and criminologists at Columbia University has taken a close look at America's administration of the death penalty and found an astonishing amount of error and corruption in the way capital punishment is meted out.</p>
        <p>Led by Prof. James Liebman of Columbia Law School, the study reviewed appeals in all capital cases over a 23-year period -- from the Supreme Court's reinstatement of the death penalty in 1973 through 1995. Among its key findings is that fully 68 percent of all death sentences were overturned on appeal because of mistakes by incompetent defense counsel, the withholding of evidence by police and prosecutors, or other prejudicial error. In fact, some experts say, the real error rate is probably a lot higher, since an incompetent lawyer would be unlikely to do the work necessary to preserve legal and factual issues for appeal.</p>
        <p>State appellate courts threw out 47 percent of death sentences. Subsequent federal review found flaws in 40 percent of the remaining cases. Some death-penalty advocates say that these figures show that the courts are diligent in catching mistakes. But an error rate of that magnitude, when the issue is life and death, is intolerable. One can only wonder how many mistakes the multi-tiered review process fails to catch.</p>
        <p>The numbers are also an indictment of the Supreme Court and Congress, which have lately reacted with frustration to the lengthy delays between convictions and executions by scaling back the traditional review process. Just yesterday, for example, a closely divided Supreme Court made it harder for death row inmates to obtain federal relief when a state court denies their right to defend themselves against prosecutors' assertions that they will endanger society unless executed. This was a retreat from a 1994 ruling that defendants are entitled to explain to the jury that they would pose no danger because they would be ineligible for parole if sentenced to life in prison.</p>
        <p>It is hardly reassuring that fully 75 percent of the people whose capital sentences were overturned by state courts because of serious error were found upon retrial to deserve a sentence less than death. An additional 7 percent were found to be innocent of the capital crime. The study also reveals vast discrepancies in the use of the death penalty by different states, recalling the sort of caprice the Supreme Court criticized when it halted the death penalty in 1972.</p>
        <p>A big problem, notes Professor Liebman, is the intense pressure on prosecutors in the immediate aftermath of a much-publicized murder to seek the death penalty and win, and the similar pressure felt by juries in such cases to convict. Prosecutors rarely suffer consequences when convictions are overturned many years later because of withholding of evidence or other abuse, so the incentive for restraint is minimal.</p>
        <p>This report should serve to intensify the public debate over capital punishment. By documenting an error rate that would be intolerable in any other government program, Professor Liebman and his colleagues have shown just how unreliable death-penalty justice really is.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 14, 2000, Wednesday  A front-page article on Monday about a study of appeals in death penalty cases r eferred incorrectly in the opening paragraph to one finding. As noted elsewhere in the article, the study -- covering the United States from 1973 to 1995 -- fou nd that in capital-case appeals, two out of three sentences were set aside, not two out of three convictions.</p>
        <p>A Public Lives profile yesterday about the main author of the study, and an edi torial yesterday about capital punishment, included other erroneous references t o the finding. It covered only those death sentences that were appealed, not all  death sentences.</p>
        <p>The Monday article and the editorial also misstated the year that the Supreme C ourt reinstated the death penalty. After overturning death penalty laws in 1972,  the court began to reinstate revised versions in 1976. Some that were approved by the court had been redrafted in 1973, but the court did not reinstate the pen alty that year.</p>
        <p>The Monday article included an erroneous percentage from a draft of the study, for capital cases in which state courts found error. It was 47 percent, not 46.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 14, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A front-page article on Monday about a study of appeals in death penalty cases r</p>
        <p>eferred incorrectly in the opening paragraph to one finding. As noted elsewhere</p>
        <p>in the article, the study -- covering the United States from 1973 to 1995 -- fou</p>
        <p>nd that in capital-case appeals, two out of three sentences were set aside, not</p>
        <p>two out of three convictions.</p>
        <p>A Public Lives profile yesterday about the main author of the study, and an edi</p>
        <p>torial yesterday about capital punishment, included other erroneous references t</p>
        <p>o the finding. It covered only those death sentences that were appealed, not all</p>
        <p>death sentences.</p>
        <p>The Monday article and the editorial also misstated the year that the Supreme C</p>
        <p>ourt reinstated the death penalty. After overturning death penalty laws in 1972,</p>
        <p>the court began to reinstate revised versions in 1976. Some that were approved</p>
        <p>by the court had been redrafted in 1973, but the court did not reinstate the pen</p>
        <p>alty that year.</p>
        <p>The Monday article included an erroneous percentage from a draft of the study,</p>
        <p>for capital cases in which state courts found error. It was 47 percent, not 46.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
