<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="13DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EFDF153EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>H.M.O.'s Ruled Not Liable In U.S. Court for Some Suits  The Supreme Court spared managed health care from a potentially fatal legal attack, ruling unanimously that the financial incentives that health maintenance organizations give doctors to hold down costs do not make the H.M.O.'s liable to suits in federal court for violating a duty to put their patients first.</p>
        <p>The decision leaves such lawsuits in the province of state courts, while at the same time handing back to Congress the issue of patients' rights as a matter of federal policy. The ruling was not likely to be the court's last word, with questions not presented in the case remaining to be resolved. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>H.M.O.'s Ruled Not Liable In U.S. Court for Some Suits  The Supreme Court spared managed health care from a potentially fatal legal attack, ruling unanimously that the financial incentives that health maintenance organizations give doctors to hold down costs do not make the H.M.O.'s liable to suits in federal court for violating a duty to put their patients first.</p>
        <p>The decision leaves such lawsuits in the province of state courts, while at the same time handing back to Congress the issue of patients' rights as a matter of federal policy. The ruling was not likely to be the court's last word, with questions not presented in the case remaining to be resolved. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>The Hidden Costs of Stock Options  Stock options have made many Americans wealthy over the last decade, but less understood is how stock options have benefited the companies that offer them, in some cases cutting their tax bills to nearly nothing. But when stocks stop rising, some economists and investors warn, companies and their shareholders will pay a heavy price for something they thought was a free lunch. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Fall on Earnings Worries  Uncertainty about second-quarter earnings helped drag down stock prices. Leading the way was Citrix, which adapts software for computer networks. The company said its earnings would fall short of expectations, and its shares fell $18.9375, to $22.25. The Nasdaq composite index fell 106.93 points, or 2.8 percent, to 3,767.91, its biggest loss since May 23. The Dow Jones industrial average slipped 49.85 points, or 0.5 percent, to 10,564.21. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index was off 10.95 points, or 0.8 percent, to 1,446. [C12.]</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq stock market plans to announce this morning that it will offer investors a new way to trade New York Stock Exchange-listed securities off the floor of the Big Board. [C12.]</p>
        <p>Credit Card Antitrust Trial Begins  Government antitrust officials began efforts to prove in court that Visa and MasterCard, the world's two biggest credit-card networks, limit competition with each other and their rivals to the detriment of consumers. [C11.]</p>
        <p>A $1 Billion State Farm Dividend  State Farm, the largest car insurer, said it was giving customers an unexpected dividend of just more than $1 billion because of better-than-expected earnings in 1999. But State Farm's after-tax profits were actually greater in 1998, and it paid no dividend on those results, leading analysts to wonder if it was an effort to counter market share erosion. [C26.]</p>
        <p>More Executive Changes at G.E.  General Electric announced another round of promotions in preparation for the retirement next April of its chairman, John F. Welch Jr. The company named Ronald R. Pressman, left, to be chief executive of the GE Employers Reinsurance Corporation and be a senior vice president. John Krenicki Jr. moved up to chief executive of GE Transportation Systems and Tanya D. Fratto became vice president of GE Superabrasives. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Justice Rebukes Microsoft Request  The Justice Department rebuked Microsoft in a court filing, saying the company's request for a stay of the trial judge's ruling against it was actually a disingenuous attempt ''to manipulate the court'' and thwart taking the antitrust case directly to the Supreme Court. [C2.]</p>
        <p>London Diamond Listing Is Halted  Oryx Natural Resources, a diamond-mining company with ties to the governments of Congo and Zimbabwe, was forced to shelve plans to list its shares on the London Stock Exchange less than 24 hours before the stock was to begin trading. It was not clear when -- or even if -- the company would be able to restart its planned stock offering. [C4.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
