<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="13FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207092"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E6DC153EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1200" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-16</p>
        <p>Korean Leaders Begin First Summit Meeting  President Kim Dae Jung of South Korea arrived in the North Korean capital, Pyongyang, and began talks with the North's leader, Kim Jong Il, 50 years to the month since the start of the Korean War.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Syrian Power Struggle  The funeral planning for President Hafez al-Assad was overshadowed by reports that Mr. Assad's exiled brother, Rifaat, had proclaimed himself the rightful heir to power. The president's son, Bashar, has been backed by the ruling elite.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-16</p>
        <p>Korean Leaders Begin First Summit Meeting  President Kim Dae Jung of South Korea arrived in the North Korean capital, Pyongyang, and began talks with the North's leader, Kim Jong Il, 50 years to the month since the start of the Korean War.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Syrian Power Struggle  The funeral planning for President Hafez al-Assad was overshadowed by reports that Mr. Assad's exiled brother, Rifaat, had proclaimed himself the rightful heir to power. The president's son, Bashar, has been backed by the ruling elite.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Iran Defector Is Called a Fraud  The C.I.A. and the F.B.I. were said to have concluded that a man claiming to be an Iranian defector and the mastermind of the Lockerbie bombing is an impostor.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>China Envoy in Belgrade  Li Peng, the leader of China's Parliament, denounced NATO's air war in a speech to Yugoslavia's Parliament, saying the American-led alliance had violated the United Nations charter. Mr. Li also met with President Slobodan Milosevic.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Putin Names Chechnya Leader  President Vladimir V. Putin appointed a Muslim cleric to govern Chechnya, a move intended to legitimize the Russian intervention in the breakaway republic and to help the Kremlin tighten its grip there.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Greek Proposal on Terrorism  Greece will propose a European Union initiative to Britain to combat terrorism, a Foreign Ministry spokesman said, adding that the killing of a British military attache in Greece last week had made a case for joint action.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Gunmen Kill 7 in Mexico Ambush  Seven police officers were killed on a rural road in the troubled state of Chiapas, an official said, adding it was not known whether Zapatista guerrillas had a role in the attack.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>U.N. Offices in Congo Are Hit  Hundreds of rock-throwing demonstrators attacked United Nations offices in recent days, officials said. They said the attacks appeared to reflect a government-inspired campaign, with President Laurent Kabila hardening his resistance to internationally supported political talks about the country's future.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A18-24</p>
        <p>H.M.O.'s Win Big Ruling On Liability to Lawsuits  The Supreme Court unanimously ruled that financial incentives that H.M.O.'s give doctors to hold down costs do not make H.M.O.'s liable to suit in federal court for violating a duty to put their patients first.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The justices, ruling in a job discrimination case, unanimously held that a plaintiff can prevail, even in the absence of smoking-gun evidence of discrimination, by showing that an employer's innocent-sounding explanation for its action was a lie.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Nuclear Data Missing From Lab  Computer drives holding nuclear weapons data and other sensitive data disappeared from a Los Alamos National Laboratory vault.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bigger Surplus, Bigger Plans  Projections of the federal budget surplus are likely to be revised upward by as much as $1 trillion, leading Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush to prepare differing claims to the windfall.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>TV Ads Dominating Politics  Campaign advertising so overwhelms political news coverage on local television across the country that on many stations the campaign is evolving into an almost exclusively paid enterprise, according to two studies to be made public today.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Compensating Nixon's Estate  The Justice Department will pay $18 million in compensation to former President Richard M. Nixon's estate for presidential papers, photographs and tape recordings that were seized after his resignation in 1974.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Effort to Sway Tobacco Jury  The chief executive of Philip Morris, Michael Szymanczyk, testified in a Miami courtroom in an effort to dissuade a jury from recommending a huge punitive judgment in a class-action suit by Florida smokers.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Scientology Prosecution Ends  Florida prosecutors dropped criminal charges against the Church of Scientology in the death of a church member. Officials said an amended autopsy report made it no longer possible to prove the charges.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>A Second Body Is Identified  Investigators identified a former prison librarian as one of five women whose bodies were found last week in barrels on property owned or rented by John Edward Robinson, an ex-convict from Olathe, Kan.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-14</p>
        <p>Senate Race Remains Tight Despite New G.O.P. Entry  Hillary Rodham Clinton has the support of 44 percent of likely voters, compared with 39 percent for Representative Rick A. Lazio, a difference of no statistical significance, a New York Times/CBS News Poll found. When undecided voters were pushed for a preference, Mrs. Clinton led, 49 percent to 43 percent, again a statistically insignificant difference.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mayor Giuliani is now viewed favorably by nearly half of New York State voters --the highest personal rating he has received as mayor.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>2 Arrests in Park Attacks  The police said two men, ages 23 and 24, had been arrested in a series of sexual attacks on women by a mob of young men who were roaming Central Park on Sunday evening.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Inquiry Into Illegal Pesticides  State, city and federal officials expressed concern about the proliferation of illegal pesticides, which are often highly effective but pose health risks, especially to children.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Budget Cuts in Nassau  Nassau County officials cleared their first hurdle to receiving a $105 million state bailout by agreeing to cut more than $52 million from the county's deficit-ridden 2000 budget.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>A Dangerous Substance  Homocysteine, a substance in the blood that is associated with animal protein, may rival cholesterol in heart disease and play an important role in other health problems. The way to reduce it is to eat less meat and take B vitamin supplements.</p>
        <p>F1</p>
        <p>Lawsuit Over Lyme Vaccine  Three patients sued SmithKline Beecham, maker of the Lyme disease vaccine, saying it had given them a severe form of arthritis.</p>
        <p>F6</p>
        <p>Health &amp; Fitness</p>
        <p>F7</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B14-15</p>
        <p>Irving Anker  New York City's schools chancellor who guided the system through a chaotic period marked by large-scale layoffs, labor unrest, corruption and struggles over integration in the mid-70's, he was 88.</p>
        <p>B15</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-28</p>
        <p>Orchestras Set to Go Online  Sixty-six of the most prestigious American symphony orchestras and opera and ballet companies have reached an agreement with the musicians union that allows them to turn to the Internet as a prime distribution vehicle for their work.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Price of Oil Rises Again  World oil prices surged to more than $31 a barrel, the highest level in three months, on growing uncertainty over whether OPEC ministers would decide to increase production at their next meeting, on June 21.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Credit Card Antitrust Trial  The government began efforts to prove in federal court that Visa and MasterCard, the world's two biggest credit-card networks, limit competition with each other and their rivals to the detriment of consumers.</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: The two Koreas, talking; deadly mistakes; last-minute reforms for Albany -- fixing campaign finance, restructuring the courts.  Columns: Gail Collins.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E8</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>D7</p>
        <p>Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
