<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Broadway for Devils, But Plenty of Parking</title>
    <meta content="13DEVI$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207112"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Continental Airlines Arena (East Rutherford, NJ)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1DC153EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="453" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Broadway for Devils, But Plenty of Parking</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Devils decide to hold their Stanley Cup victory party in parking lot of Continental Airlines Arena (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Setting themselves up for another round of late-night television ridicule, the New Jersey Devils have decided to hold their Stanley Cup victory party in the parking lot of the Continental Airlines Arena on Wednesday evening, repeating the rally held for their last championship in 1995.</p>
        <p>Two days after their championship victory over the Dallas Stars, the Devils and the New Jersey Sports and Exposition Authority tonight put to rest rumors that the team would be showered with ticker tape in Newark, where a new Devils stadium is scheduled to be built in the next few years, or that they would take a more linear romp through the low-rise commercial sprawl of Route 17.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Setting themselves up for another round of late-night television ridicule, the New Jersey Devils have decided to hold their Stanley Cup victory party in the parking lot of the Continental Airlines Arena on Wednesday evening, repeating the rally held for their last championship in 1995.</p>
        <p>Two days after their championship victory over the Dallas Stars, the Devils and the New Jersey Sports and Exposition Authority tonight put to rest rumors that the team would be showered with ticker tape in Newark, where a new Devils stadium is scheduled to be built in the next few years, or that they would take a more linear romp through the low-rise commercial sprawl of Route 17.</p>
        <p>While some diehard fans said they did not care either way, others had hoped for a little more pageantry.</p>
        <p>''Marching around a parking lot is sort of pathetic,'' said Victor Delvecchio, 23, a Devils fan from Roselle Park, as he waited for a train in Newark's Pennsylvania Station. ''But being Jersey and all, we don't have much choice.''</p>
        <p>Unlike the New York Rangers, who enjoyed ticker tape and the adulation of a million fans as they paraded up Broadway in 1994, the Devils have always been cursed by the awkwardness of playing in the Meadowlands. Despite their reputation as a first-rate team and a Stanley Cup champion, they  still struggle to fill all 19,000 seats during home games.</p>
        <p>The Devils have suffered from an inferiority complex since arriving from Colorado in 1982. Although the team's relative youth may be part of the problem, the more daunting obstacle to greater glory, it seems, is their home base, a swamp-bound arena surrounded by highways, gas stations and retail stores.</p>
        <p>Still, they are not the first New York-area franchise challenged by geography.</p>
        <p>When the Giants won the Super  Bowl in 1987, the team staged an outdoor pep rally at their stadium in East Rutherford in the middle of winter.</p>
        <p>And for their Stanley Cup victories in the early 1980's, the Islanders, who play in Nassau County, paraded along Hempstead Turnpike as a chorus of car horns filled the air.</p>
        <p>The Devils' party five years ago inspired a spate of jokes as well as a character on ''Seinfeld'' known for his hysterical devotion to the team.</p>
        <p>In announcing Wednesday night's festivities, John McMullen, the team's owner, said the Meadowlands parking lot made sense because it was a familiar spot for fans.</p>
        <p>Anthony Doyle, 31, a fan from East Brunswick, described the previous Devils parade as one of the best moments of his life.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't matter where they do it,'' he said. ''It's about showing your respect and sharing the good times.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
