<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush and Gore Revise Plans To Match a Growing Surplus</title>
    <meta content="13SURP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207122"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE BUDGET ISSUE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Homeland Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E6DB153EF930A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1254" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush and Gore Revise Plans To Match a Growing Surplus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Projections of federal budget surplus are likely to be revised upward by as much as $1 trillion, leading presidential contenders Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush to prepare differing claims to windfall; Gore aides say he will continue emphasizing debt reduction, and intends to make case that with surplus growing spending more on major programs is vital element of any plan to invest in nation's future; Bush aides say he will suggest using any additional surplus to help reduce national debt or help pay for system of personal investment accounts within Social Security (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Projections of the federal budget surplus are likely to be revised upward by as much as $1 trillion in coming weeks, leading Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush to prepare differing claims to the windfall.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Gore, more money means new initiatives to encourage savings and improve education, health care and environmental protection, as well as to speed his plan to reduce the national debt, his aides said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Projections of the federal budget surplus are likely to be revised upward by as much as $1 trillion in coming weeks, leading Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush to prepare differing claims to the windfall.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Gore, more money means new initiatives to encourage savings and improve education, health care and environmental protection, as well as to speed his plan to reduce the national debt, his aides said.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Bush, it is a chance to assert that his plans for a big tax cut, the creation of private investment accounts within Social Security and a national missile defense program are not only affordable but would also leave plenty of money for additional debt reduction, his aides said.</p>
        <p>Analysts in both parties and private economists said they expected the Congressional Budget Office and the White House's Office of Management and Budget to raise their 10-year surplus projections soon by at least $500 billion, with some estimates running as high as $1 trillion. Most of the increase is expected to come from the non-Social-Security segment of the budget, the part that is up for grabs in political terms.</p>
        <p>Depending on what assumptions are made about the path of government spending, current estimates of the surplus outside of the Social Security program range from $750 billion over the next decade to nearly $2 trillion. Social Security is projected to run a surplus of another $2.3 trillion in that time, and the two parties have agreed to use that money to reduce the national debt.</p>
        <p>Should the new surplus estimates match expectations, they would continue a trend in which projections of the nation's fiscal condition have grown increasingly bright over the last several years, giving both parties a chance to press for their priorities after decades when deficits constrained policy proposals.</p>
        <p>The Congressional Budget Office is preparing to release its updated surplus projections as early as the end of the month, although the release could be delayed until mid-July. The White House has not disclosed when it will release its new budget outlook, though it is expected to be in the next month. But both presidential campaigns are already preparing to use the new numbers to highlight their differences over how best to sustain and take advantage of the nation's prosperity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore will begin setting out his ideas in a speech in New York on Tuesday, the kickoff to a campaign swing in which he plans to emphasize that fiscal prudence has played a major role in bringing the economy to where it is today, his aides said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore will continue to emphasize debt reduction. But with the surplus growing, he intends to make a case that spending more on education, health care and the environment is a vital element of any plan to invest in the nation's future. And he will offer some modest tax cuts of his own, including a program, still under development, that would give tax breaks to people with low and moderate incomes to encourage higher rates of savings.</p>
        <p>''This election is going to revolve around the fundamental question of how do we responsibly use our budget prosperity,'' said Chris Lehane, Mr. Gore's spokesman.</p>
        <p>''Do we use it as a foundation to reach for the stars by addressing issues like Social Security, Medicare, education, the environment and health care?'' Mr. Lehane said. ''Or do we squander it on a tax cut for the wealthy, a trillion dollar Social Security privatization plan and an enormous Star Wars defense system?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides said their calculations also suggested a big upward revision in the surplus, but they said they would not offer any new programs or tax cuts. Rather, they said, they would use any additional surplus to help reduce the national debt or to help pay for a transition to a system of personal investment accounts within Social Security.</p>
        <p>''If voters have a choice between a Democrat and a Republican in Washington when the money comes in, they can be more confident that the money will go to debt reduction under Bush, because the history of the Democrats is that they will spend it,'' said Ari Fleischer, Mr. Bush's spokesman.</p>
        <p>Advisers to Mr. Bush said the new numbers would insulate them against Mr. Gore's persistent attacks on the Republican as fiscally irresponsible. They said that Mr. Bush's plans could be paid for even within the budget forecasts the campaign has been using for the last month, and that there was no question they would be affordable under the coming projections.</p>
        <p>''This would alleviate any and all concern that the tax plan did not fit within the budget and did not leave substantial room for a comprehensive package that would include Social Security reform,'' said John F. Cogan, an economist at the Hoover Institution at Stanford University who advises Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>The surplus projections are likely to rise for several reasons. The economy has grown faster than projected this year, meaning that gross domestic product will be bigger than anticipated in coming years, so that even steady rates of taxation will generate bigger than projected revenues.  And the economy has been growing at a healthy rate with low inflation and strong productivity growth for so long that budget estimators are beginning to incorporate slightly more optimistic economic assumptions into their outlook. The stronger the outlook, the higher the tax revenues and the bigger the surplus.</p>
        <p>There is some risk to any surplus projection from a steep economic downturn or a plunge in the stock market, the source of much of the recent surge in tax revenues. But even taking those risks into account, analysts say the surplus is likely to remain large for years to come. Economists at Credit Suisse First Boston in New York concluded recently that ''massive surpluses and retirement of Treasury debt are 'baked in the cake' almost no matter what the economy does over the next 10 years.''</p>
        <p>This presidential election is the first since the 1960's in which voters are contending with neither the memory of a recent recession nor the restrictions imposed by large budget deficits. The candidates and their parties -- and probably the voters -- are still catching up to the politics of prosperity, and a large increase in the surplus projection would no doubt hold political opportunities and pitfalls for both sides.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Gore has worked hard to position himself as the guardian of the strong economy and the candidate of fiscal responsibility, any shift he makes toward new spending programs will leave him vulnerable to attacks by Mr. Bush as a traditional Democratic big spender.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Gore's aides are convinced that using the nation's moment of robust fiscal health to deal with problems other than the debt is justified on policy grounds and politically popular as well. If Mr. Bush tries to argue against steps to improve education, clean up the water and air, protect open spaces and improve access to health care, he will be right where Mr. Gore wants him, one adviser to the vice president said today.</p>
        <p>To the degree that the new numbers make his plans look affordable, Mr. Bush has much to gain. But the revisions could make it more difficult for him to argue that the federal government needs to shrink in size and influence, one of the ideological cornerstones of his campaign.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE BUDGET ISSUE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
