<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Official and Airlines to Meet About Delays and Cancellations</title>
    <meta content="Y21AIR$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224352"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slater, Rodney (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7DA113EF932A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="461" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Official and Airlines to Meet About Delays and Cancellations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Transportation Sec Rodney Slater, troubled by growing outcry from airline passengers over record number of flight delays and cancellations, summons airline executives, union leaders and airport officials to meeting in Washington to discuss problem (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A record number of flight delays and cancellations has prompted officials in Washington to call an unusual meeting on Monday in the hopes of finding ways to ease conditions for beleaguered air travelers.</p>
        <p>In the face of a growing outcry from airline passengers, Transportation Secretary Rodney Slater has summoned airline executives, union leaders and airport officials to discuss ways to improve airline travel.  Officials from eight major airlines have said they will attend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A record number of flight delays and cancellations has prompted officials in Washington to call an unusual meeting on Monday in the hopes of finding ways to ease conditions for beleaguered air travelers.</p>
        <p>In the face of a growing outcry from airline passengers, Transportation Secretary Rodney Slater has summoned airline executives, union leaders and airport officials to discuss ways to improve airline travel.  Officials from eight major airlines have said they will attend.</p>
        <p>The delays and cancellations, coming at the peak of vacation season, have fueled a debate that the nation's air system may be approaching gridlock. With 48,448 delayed flights, June was the worst month ever for on-time performance, the Federal Aviation Administration said. In July there was a slight improvement, with 44,401 delays, but that was still far more than the 25,672 recorded in the same month two years ago. Those figures do not reflect the thousands of flights that were canceled.</p>
        <p>Officials said today that they hoped the meeting would help forge a consensus among the various parts of the nation's air system on how to deal with the problem and end months of finger-pointing.</p>
        <p>''The hope is that the secretary can use his power and influence to help the groups to come together and walk away with specific action items for the different groups,'' said Mary Trupo, a spokeswoman for Mr. Slater.</p>
        <p>Ms. Trupo added that the meeting was intended to highlight, and hopefully build on, some successes in recent months, like the slight decrease in delays in July from June.</p>
        <p>Problems with the nation's air travel have grown as the number of passengers has increased. The already overloaded air system has been further buffeted by stormy weather and labor problems.</p>
        <p>United Airlines, the world's biggest carrier, is locked in a dispute with pilots who are refusing overtime shifts. United has cut 4,800 flights this summer and is dropping 2,000 flights next month.</p>
        <p>Last week, Mr. Slater flew to Chicago to meet with both sides of the United dispute but appeared to do little to advance a resolution.</p>
        <p>The two federal agencies that monitor the airlines, the Federal Aviation Administration and the Department of Transportation, have also been criticized. A study released by the department's inspector general in July found that since 1988 the F.A.A. and the Department of Transportation had underestimated the amount of time lost by passengers by a total of 247 years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
