<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cocaine Quietly Reclaims Its Hold as Good Times Return</title>
    <meta content="21COCA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leduff, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E3DA113EF932A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1329" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cocaine Quietly Reclaims Its Hold as Good Times Return</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE LeDUFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leduff, Charlie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cocaine is re-emerging as the recreational drug of choice among affluent New Yorkers in their 30's and 40's; it is not bought on shady street corners anymore, but rather in bars, which all have their coke dealers and delivery services; rebound of cocaine is traced to the prosperity brought by booming stock market and to decline in cocaine prices caused by worldwide glut in cocaine market (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is a nice little jazz bar in the East Village. The drinks are a fair price and the mix of people is good. The only problem is that it's tough to get into the bathroom.</p>
        <p>This agitated a silver-haired college professor named Jason who was in the bar on Thursday night. He crossed his legs. He uncrossed them. Reaching the point where he could wait no longer, the professor walked out onto 13th Street and ducked behind a trash bin. He had to have that snort of cocaine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is a nice little jazz bar in the East Village. The drinks are a fair price and the mix of people is good. The only problem is that it's tough to get into the bathroom.</p>
        <p>This agitated a silver-haired college professor named Jason who was in the bar on Thursday night. He crossed his legs. He uncrossed them. Reaching the point where he could wait no longer, the professor walked out onto 13th Street and ducked behind a trash bin. He had to have that snort of cocaine.</p>
        <p>''It's getting harder and harder to use the toilets in the bars because there are so many people in the toilets doing everything except using the toilets,'' said Jason, 45, who said he first tried cocaine two years ago at a Manhattan party. ''If you dope-tested the top of every toilet tank in the city, I bet half would test positive for cocaine.''</p>
        <p>At a time when the names of increasingly popular pharmacological drugs -- most notably MDMA or Ecstasy -- and a few of the old standards like heroin are in the news, little attention is being paid to the drug that is re-emerging as the narcotic of choice among New York's pinstripe and cocktail set. Cocaine.</p>
        <p>While a good many cocaine users and experts maintain that the drug never really went away, and national surveys and other numbers suggest that cocaine use is at least holding steady, there is strong anecdotal evidence to suggest that powder cocaine use is edging up as it undergoes a renaissance among the well-dressed and well-fed in New York City.</p>
        <p>Daytop Village, the largest drug-rehabilitation program in the city, reports that 45 percent of its 2,000 white- and blue-collar outpatients were treated for using powder cocaine in 1999, compared with 30 percent in 1990.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, cocaine-related emergencies in New York City increased by 21 percent from 1990 to 1998, according to the Drug Abuse Warning Network. According to Jonathan Porteus, a clinical psychologist at Daytop, those emergencies range from heart palpitations to lethal overdoses.</p>
        <p>''Cocaine is back for the 30- and 40-year-olds,'' said Avery Mehlman, the deputy bureau chief of narcotics for the Brooklyn district attorney. ''Crack is considered to be highly addictive and synonymous with people down on their luck. Powder cocaine, due to its higher price, implies a certain social strata. It's become the drug of choice for the so-called recreational user.''</p>
        <p>If anything has changed, it is the culture of cocaine. It is not bought on a shady street corner anymore, and its use is less and less clandestine. ''Every bar's got a coke dealer, and everybody has a delivery service,'' said Andrew M., an independent filmmaker who sat in the corner of a bar in Chelsea sipping a cosmopolitan and snorting cocaine from the palm of his hand.</p>
        <p>''And then you have your spots that sell cocktails and coke,'' he said. ''The coke bars are becoming the people's choice because you don't know who's monitoring your pager anymore.''</p>
        <p>Andrew M. was referring to the cocaine service that he could beep to have drugs delivered to his Upper East Side apartment. That is until federal agents from the Drug Enforcement Administration broke it up in January, arresting four people and seizing a notebook listing the names, addresses and phone numbers of more than 2,000 customers all over Manhattan. The addresses included major financial institutions and apartments on the Upper East and West Sides, SoHo and Chelsea.</p>
        <p>''It's a bunch of yuppies mostly,'' said an agent with the federal drug agency. ''Lawyers and business types. White people with too much time and money on their hands. I've got to say, though, it was a pretty smooth operation.''</p>
        <p>The rebound in cocaine use can be traced to two causes, and both have their roots in money, said Rick Curtis, a professor of anthropology at John Jay College of Criminal Justice, who studies patterns in urban drug use. Not surprisingly, Professor Curtis said, the boom times on Wall Street have spurred the use of the drug, and so have falling cocaine prices. There is a worldwide glut in the cocaine market, and when the authorities confiscate 1,500 pounds, as they did this month in the Bronx, it makes the newspapers, but it hardly makes a difference in the supply or the demand.</p>
        <p>Two decades ago, a kilogram of cocaine sold for a wholesale price of $40,000, experts say. Today it goes for $20,000 to $25,000 wholesale. Translated into consumer prices, half a gram costs $25; a gram, $50; and an ''eight ball,'' 3.5 grams, $150. The average price for a gram of cocaine in 1990 was $100, Professor Curtis said.</p>
        <p>''It's the dot-com crowd driving it,'' he said. ''It's the hip art and money crowd, the Wall Street people looking for a kick. There is new money to burn, and it's the 30- to 40-year-olds who remember the kick.''</p>
        <p>But gone are the days of wide-collar Huk-A-Poo shirts, gum sole shoes and coke spoons hanging from gold neck chains. Gone are the times when a patron of Danceteria ordered a drink while snorting dust off the bar. The police have made it too difficult for that, with antidrug efforts like the crackdown on nightclubs, Operation Condor and the Model Block programs. It is too hard to binge because cocaine cannot be bought on street corners 24 hours a day, 7 days a week, experts say.</p>
        <p>What has taken the place of the disco are dinner parties and dark corners of bars, Jason said. On Thursday night, he tours the Manhattan and Brooklyn powder scenes. At 11 p.m., there is a birthday party in the East Village. It is the hip crowd: writers, actors, academics. They are all white, and a black kid arrives from uptown. He is paid $150 for the cocaine and $20 for the cab fare. He stays for a beer, smiles sideways and is gone. The birthday speech is made and the birthday song is sung and then the cocaine is passed around on a compact disc case.</p>
        <p>''It's not like it's crack,'' says a writer for New York magazine. ''Sneaking off into the bathroom is so over. I mean, how does anyone expect to drink all night without a little pick-me-up to balance it off?''</p>
        <p>As the party starts to peter out around 2 a.m., a half-dozen partygoers, including the writer and the professor, make a beeline for Brooklyn, where there is a chummy little club that features cocaine and cocktails in plastic cups. The place is known from Chelsea to Astoria, Queens, and the bartender, Marilyn, says the clientele was once exclusively Puerto Rican gangsters.</p>
        <p>''But just like everywhere else, they got gentrified out,'' Marilyn says. ''There's too much money to be made on these people.''</p>
        <p>The bar is interesting, not for its decor, which is glass and red paint. It is the fact that there is a bond broker at the bar wearing a candy-striped oxford and loafers, and he looks so much like an undercover cop that everyone has gotten sick of asking him if he is an undercover cop.</p>
        <p>''Hey, my money and my nostrils are as good as anyone else's,'' says the broker, Larry L. ''I don't make it a habit of coming here. I mix it up. Chelsea, Astoria. I've got my spots.''</p>
        <p>Which is the second interesting thing about this bar. To snort cocaine in the bathroom is absolutely verboten, Marilyn says. The doors do not lock because management prefers that people use the toilets for corporeal reasons. Instead, there is a large phone booth in the back corner with a draw curtain. Perhaps six strangers can fit inside.</p>
        <p>Yet, snorting illegal substances out in the open from the palms of their apartment keys does not bother the Thursday night crowd. ''After a while, everybody knows everybody in here,'' Larry says.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
