<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E-Commerce Report; Advertisers are turning to specialists to handle their e-mail marketing campaigns.</title>
    <meta content="21ECOM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/21/technology/21ECOMMERCE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224304"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Flonetwork</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stellin, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/E-Commerce</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Operations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/E-Commerce Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1D7103EF932A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1302" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E-Commerce Report; Advertisers are turning to specialists to handle their e-mail marketing campaigns.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Susan Stellin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stellin, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>FloNetwork and other companies arise to help e-mail marketers handle the challenges they face, which range from privacy issues, like getting permission to send e-mail to customers, to technical hurdles in composing, sending and tracking large volumes of mail; complexity of delivering customized messages is one of main reasons marketers choose to work with a technology company specializing in e-mail services; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMONG Internet companies struggling to retain customers they have worked so hard to get, e-mail marketing is seen as the next best thing to being on the home page each time a customer goes online.</p>
        <p>For openers, e-mail is a relatively inexpensive marketing tool, ranging from a penny to a quarter for each message, compared with $1 to $2 for each piece for direct-mail campaigns in the actual world. Moreover, e-mail provides immediate results, no small factor in an industry where speed is critical.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMONG Internet companies struggling to retain customers they have worked so hard to get, e-mail marketing is seen as the next best thing to being on the home page each time a customer goes online.</p>
        <p>For openers, e-mail is a relatively inexpensive marketing tool, ranging from a penny to a quarter for each message, compared with $1 to $2 for each piece for direct-mail campaigns in the actual world. Moreover, e-mail provides immediate results, no small factor in an industry where speed is critical.</p>
        <p>Best of all, the results of an e-mail campaign can be measured, right down to the number of people who opened the message, clicked on each link, made a purchase or forwarded the e-mail to a friend -- that is, assuming the sender has the technology to track all of this data.</p>
        <p>And therein lies the catch. Conducting an effective e-mail campaign is a lot more complicated than opening a new message in an e-mail program, copying a list of customer names, typing an offer and clicking the ''send'' button. In fact, those who manage e-mail marketing efforts say the challenges range from basic privacy issues, like getting permission to send e-mail to customers, to technical hurdles in composing, sending and tracking large volumes of mail.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, an industry has emerged to help marketers manage their e-mail strategy, from companies that function as application service providers, housing the infrastructure to deliver and track e-mail campaigns, to those that license or sell software to run e-mail campaigns. According to Forrester Research, the market for these types of services will reach $4.8 billion a year by 2004, up from $156 million in 1999.</p>
        <p>One of the dozens of companies hoping to benefit from this opportunity is FloNetwork, an application service provider in Toronto offering e-mail campaign management. The company, which has been in business since 1993, has been focusing on e-mail services since 1998 and now has 185 clients, including J. Crew, Continental Airlines and Buy.com.</p>
        <p>Regina Brady, vice president of strategy and partnerships at FloNetwork, said many clients had initially handled their e-mail marketing efforts in-house, but turned to a vendor as their needs outgrew their ability to handle them.</p>
        <p>As examples of the issues e-marketers face, Ms. Brady cited formatting marketing messages so they can be read by a variety of e-mail software, developing a system to track the response to each campaign, and dealing with the volume of incoming mail that results from a mass mailing, including messages that bounce back because of invalid addresses and requests to be removed from a mailing list.</p>
        <p>''All of that is in-bound mail that most people don't think about,'' she said. ''It's not sexy, but it's a real fact of life.''</p>
        <p>Another hurdle is establishing relationships with the major Internet service providers. To stem the sheer volume of unsolicited commercial mail their members receive, many services have systems that detect and even block bulk mailings sent into their networks. As a result, Ms. Brady said, mass mailers often have to demonstrate they are legitimate enterprises to make sure their e-mails reach the intended recipients.</p>
        <p>''At first, we'd call AOL to say, 'We're going to be sending out a million messages to AOL customers on behalf of XYZ company,' '' she said. ''And they'd say, 'Great, thanks for letting us know.' After a while we ended up establishing more formalized procedures.''</p>
        <p>FloNetwork and its competitors also offer technology enabling clients to customize e-mail messages for each recipient. For example, Barnesandnoble.com, which works with FloNetwork and another e-mail service provider, CheetahMail, originally handled its e-mail efforts in-house, offering customers the option to sign up for e-mail newsletters on topics such as ''fiction'' or ''bestsellers.'' When Barnesandnoble.com decided to tap into its customer database and send e-mails targeted to customers based on that information, it chose to work with a vendor.</p>
        <p>''That's when we really needed a partner because we wanted to work with someone with strong technology,'' said Roe Johnson, Barnesandnoble.com's director of online marketing. ''By using dynamic content personalization, we're able to send someone who lives near Union Square an announcement about a book signing in that store.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the complexity of delivering customized messages is one of the main reasons marketers choose to work with a technology company specializing in e-mail services. For Wine.com, an Internet wine retailer that merged last week with Wineshopper.com, the ability to send highly targeted e-mail messages to customers has sharply improved the effectiveness of the company's marketing.</p>
        <p>Jim LaBelle, vice president of marketing for Wine.com, said that when the company started doing e-mail marketing, it sent an e-mail newsletter showcasing the same selection of wines to its entire customer base. Working with Digital Impact, an e-marketing services provider based in San Mateo, Calif., Mr. LaBelle said the company was able to use its database on customers' purchase history to create customized e-mail messages based on the type of wine or price range each shopper purchased.</p>
        <p>''If we've found one of our customers only buys Italian reds above $20, why barrage him with other ideas?'' Mr. LaBelle said. The more personalized approach, he noted, ''has resulted in a doubling of the revenue yielded from each newsletter.''</p>
        <p>William Park, chairman and chief executive of Digital Impact, said this type of return on investment is what his company emphasizes when approaching prospective clients.</p>
        <p>''The cost of ownership is huge for companies doing it themselves because they don't have economies of scale,'' Mr. Park said. Among those costs are sophisticated hardware and software systems to handle both outbound and inbound e-mail, Internet service charges, and marketing and research employees to analyze data and fine-tune campaigns.</p>
        <p>The company works with more than 140 clients, including Fidelity, Travelocity and Tower Records, and sent more than 400 million messages last quarter on their behalf. Digital Impact typically charges 2 to 5 cents per e-mail message sent, depending on the degree of personalization required and the volume of mail the client sends.</p>
        <p>Mr. Park acknowledged that many companies are hesitant to outsource their e-mail marketing efforts to a vendor. ''When we are competing to win business,'' he said, the in-house technology department is ''generally the biggest competitor.''</p>
        <p>One company that manages its own e-mail campaigns is eHobbies.com, a privately held Web site for hobbyists based in Santa Monica, Calif. The site, which features 11 hobby categories, sends two mailings a month to members who have signed up to receive e-mail newsletters in a particular category.</p>
        <p>Seth Greenberg, vice president of online marketing for eHobbies, said the company decided to purchase e-mail software from MessageMedia, rather than rely entirely on third parties for its e-mail efforts. One of the main reasons for that decision, he said, was a reluctance to share customer information with a third party.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't that comfortable exposing our database to an outside vendor,'' Mr. Greenberg said. Purchasing software to use in-house also allowed eHobbies to have more control over the process of sending mailings, he said.</p>
        <p>Although he acknowledged that handling everything in-house has required more employees, and that there have been ''some growing pains,'' Mr. Greenberg said he was happy with the results, citing high click-through rates and purchases in response to the e-mail campaigns.</p>
        <p>What works for a particular company, he said, depends in part on internal resources. ''We're fortunate to have the talent to be able to do this in-house,'' he said. ''Not everybody has that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
