<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campaign Aides Set Tone For Next Big Test in Race</title>
    <meta content="Y21ELE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224325"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEBATES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shrum, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hughes, Karen P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4DE113EF932A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1165" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campaign Aides Set Tone For Next Big Test in Race</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>AUSTIN, Tex., Aug. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Shrum, senior adviser to Vice Pres Al Gore accuses Gov George W Bush of trying to dodge, or at least minimize,impact of presidential debates; Bush top aide Karen P Hughes says Bush is ready and willing to debate, but is still mulling over details; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A senior adviser to Vice President Al Gore accused Gov. George W. Bush today of trying to dodge -- or at least minimize the impact of -- presidential debates, while one of Mr. Bush's top aides said the governor was ready and willing but still mulling over the details.</p>
        <p>''I think George Bush wants to engineer these debates so the fewest number of people see them,'' said Bob Shrum, the Gore adviser, on the ABC News program ''This Week.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A senior adviser to Vice President Al Gore accused Gov. George W. Bush today of trying to dodge -- or at least minimize the impact of -- presidential debates, while one of Mr. Bush's top aides said the governor was ready and willing but still mulling over the details.</p>
        <p>''I think George Bush wants to engineer these debates so the fewest number of people see them,'' said Bob Shrum, the Gore adviser, on the ABC News program ''This Week.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shrum was referring to the fact that while Mr. Bush had pledged to participate in three debates, he had not agreed specifically to the three proposed by the bipartisan Commission on Presidential Debates, which has sponsored all the presidential debates since 1988.</p>
        <p>Karen P. Hughes, director of communications for the Bush campaign, said on the same program that the governor was simply giving himself time to consider more than 40 debate invitations from an array of potential sponsors.</p>
        <p>''Governor Bush is committed to debating,'' Ms. Hughes said.</p>
        <p>This inevitable debate over debates, conducted in slightly raised and sometimes overlapping voices on the Sunday morning talk programs, was the opening of a new chapter in the presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>The certain high point of this phase will be the televised face-to-face encounters between Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush. And the weeks leading to those events are already giving rise to aggressive public posturing, febrile  private negotiations and all-out efforts by each campaign to make sure its candidate ultimately enters the arena with just the right buildup.</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign has been portraying Mr. Bush as a neophyte frightened of any format that requires him to give lengthy answers and stray beyond sound bites. Mr. Gore's advisers repeatedly note that Mr. Gore has, either formally or informally, agreed to dozens of debates, even though such a number is almost logistically unimaginable.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign moved to blunt that line of attack late last week by announcing that Mr. Bush and his running mate, Dick Cheney, would agree to a combined five debates, a ''modern-day record,'' as Ms. Hughes put it.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hughes and other officials with the Bush campaign have also been talking loudly about what a fierce debater Mr. Gore is, a clear attempt to lower the expectations for Mr. Bush to the point where he is guaranteed to exceed them.</p>
        <p>And campaign officials have been busily analyzing and deconstructing videotapes and transcripts of Mr. Gore's debates back to 1988, when he ran for the Democratic presidential nomination, a senior adviser to Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>With the help of the Republican National Committee, the adviser said, the Bush campaign has assembled a thick book of research into Mr. Gore's debate performances and has even diagrammed Mr. Gore's typical debate response: an expression of empathy for the issue at hand, followed by an explanation of the remedy he is offering, followed by a pointed attack on his opponent's record or proposal.</p>
        <p>And the Bush campaign months ago recruited Senator Judd Gregg, Republican of New Hampshire, to prepare for and play the part of Mr. Gore in debate rehearsals. Mr. Gregg did the same for Jack Kemp, the Republican vice-presidential nominee in 1996, before his debate with Mr. Gore that year.</p>
        <p>The debates have begun to loom larger with the emergence of signs that the race between Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore is tightening. A USA Today-CNN-Gallup poll released today showed Mr. Gore moving from a 16-point disadvantage against Mr. Bush before the Democratic National Convention to a 1-point advantage after the convention.</p>
        <p>That poll, which had a sampling error of plus or minus four percentage points, reflected interviews on Friday and Saturday with 697 likely voters. It put Mr. Gore, who had the support of 47 percent of respondents, and Mr. Bush, with 46 percent, in a four-way contest with Ralph Nader, with 3 percent, and Patrick J. Buchanan, with 2 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's advisers said today that they had always expected that Mr. Gore would get an enormous bounce immediately after his convention and that the race would be close to even around now. They said that the more meaningful polls would come in several weeks, around Labor Day.</p>
        <p>The competing pitches and warring put-downs as aides to Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush stormed the television airwaves this morning provided a tidy preview of the campaign to come.</p>
        <p>On the topic of fiscal responsibility, Mr. Gore's advisers moved to defend the amount of spending the vice president had outlined in his convention speech, while Mr. Bush's advisers defended the size of the Texas governor's proposed tax cut of $1.3 trillion over 10 years.</p>
        <p>Karl Rove, the chief strategist for the Bush campaign, said on the NBC program ''Meet the Press'' that Mr. Bush, who has yet to offer a detailed plan for overhauling Medicare or creating a new prescription drug benefit for the elderly, would be tackling those issues shortly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove said the campaign's budget projections for the next decade showed that Mr. Bush still had ''$900 billion for additional spending and for deficit reduction'' after his tax cut. ''More than enough,'' he said, for a program to expand prescription drug coverage.</p>
        <p>''I think our proposals total up to about $400-and-some-odd billion thus far,'' Mr. Rove said. ''We have close to $500 billion unspent.''</p>
        <p>The two campaigns also tangled over which party and which politicians deserved the blame for the unfinished business of the Clinton administration on issues like Medicare and Social Security.</p>
        <p>William M. Daley, the chairman of the Gore campaign, who also appeared on ''Meet the Press,'' told Mr. Rove: ''I would just say that Newt Gingrich and the Republican leadership in the House and Senate over the last eight years haven't been exactly willing to work with President Clinton or Vice President Gore, and that's one of the reasons why we've had a stalemate on important issues.''</p>
        <p>In response, Mr. Rove said: ''To some degree, Mr. Daley's right. But the buck stops on the president's desk.''</p>
        <p>''Look,'' Mr. Rove added, ''the vice president claims that he's been part of every important decision over the last eight years. I can think of very few more important decisions than what is the tone with which we're going to approach our relationships with Congress.''</p>
        <p>On ''This Week,'' Mr. Shrum, the Gore aide, said the Bush campaign was not eager for debates because Mr. Bush did not want to have a substantive discussion of issues.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hughes shot back: ''That's just outrageous.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEBATES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
