<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tourism Flowing Upriver to the Hudson Valley</title>
    <meta content="21HUDS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000823T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bed-and-Breakfast Lodgings</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson Valley (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foderaro, Lisa W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Bed and Breakfasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Hudson Valley</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE5DA113EF932A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tourism Flowing Upriver to the Hudson Valley</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA W. FODERARO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Foderaro, Lisa W</byline>
      <dateline>MILLBROOK, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tourism is growing in New York's Hudson Valley, which was once in shadow of New York City and New England; hotel and bed-and-breakfast receipts climbed to $301 million in 1998 from $178 million a decade earlier; studies indicate that foreign visitors make up a small percentage of the total, but anecdotal evidence suggests that their numbers are rising; boosters say further growth is inhibited by shortage of hotels and inns, insufficient state money for promotion and a marketing strategy that pits counties in region against one another; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like more and more tourists these days, Glynis and John Seale, an English couple who live on the edge of the Cotswolds, decided to venture off the well-trodden sidewalks of Manhattan and make their way up the Taconic Parkway to travel the quiet back roads to a vineyard here in the heart of the Hudson Valley.</p>
        <p>It was not their first trip to the region, and between sips of chardonnay and pinot noir in the tasting room of the Millbrook Winery, the rows of vines in the afternoon sun visible through a Palladian window, they rhapsodized about the valley's attributes. ''We're very keen on history, and we're interested in the links'' to Winston Churchill and Great Britain, said Mrs. Seale, while her husband likened the countryside to ''parts of Wales and Scotland.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like more and more tourists these days, Glynis and John Seale, an English couple who live on the edge of the Cotswolds, decided to venture off the well-trodden sidewalks of Manhattan and make their way up the Taconic Parkway to travel the quiet back roads to a vineyard here in the heart of the Hudson Valley.</p>
        <p>It was not their first trip to the region, and between sips of chardonnay and pinot noir in the tasting room of the Millbrook Winery, the rows of vines in the afternoon sun visible through a Palladian window, they rhapsodized about the valley's attributes. ''We're very keen on history, and we're interested in the links'' to Winston Churchill and Great Britain, said Mrs. Seale, while her husband likened the countryside to ''parts of Wales and Scotland.''</p>
        <p>Tourism officials say the Seales represent the new face of tourism in the Hudson Valley. After years of getting lost between the hyperkinesis of New York City and the tranquillity of New England, the Hudson Valley seems to have finally arrived. The amount of money spent on lodging has almost doubled in 10 years, and visitors no longer hail strictly from places like Delaware and New Jersey.</p>
        <p>''A lot of the historic sites have guest books and we're seeing people from all over,'' said Susan H. Cayea, president of Hudson Valley Tourism, a state-financed group that three years ago began publishing its guides in four languages. ''Some of us can track the origin of the person on our Internet sites, and on any given day, particularly on the Hudson Valley tourism site, you'll find Finland, Australia, Japan -- a wide variety of people.''</p>
        <p>Some 25 million people a year visit the Hudson Valley, according to official estimates, and their spending adds about $2.5 billion to the local economy. While it is hard to track the growth in tourism, hotel and bed-and-breakfast receipts in 1998 climbed to $301 million from $178 million a decade earlier. Studies indicate that foreign visitors make up a small percentage of the total, but anecdotal evidence suggests that their numbers are rising.</p>
        <p>Some people in the tourism industry say more needs to be done before the Hudson Valley becomes a true international destination. They cite a shortage of hotels and inns, insufficient state money for promotion and a marketing strategy that they say pits counties against one another.</p>
        <p>''The state gives each county money to promote itself, and that leaves a fragmented message,'' said Burns Patterson, a spokesman for Historic Hudson Valley, a nonprofit organization in Tarrytown that owns and operates historical sites. ''Right now a visitor from Germany or Japan trying to get information about the Hudson Valley would have difficulty finding the right source for general information.''</p>
        <p>Officials at Hudson Valley Tourism say more money is needed for promotion, pointing out that their annual allotment from the state fell steadily after reaching a peak in 1988 and is only now rebounding. But they dispute that competition exists between counties, whose individual travel guides, they say, are a necessary supplement to the regionwide guide.</p>
        <p>''It's 150 miles of river and if we were to put down every restaurant and every bed-and-breakfast and every site, you'd have the New York phone book, and nobody wants to lug that around on vacation,'' Ms. Cayea said.</p>
        <p>Another potential problem for tourism is Gov. George E. Pataki's push to build power plants in the valley, which cultural organizations and environmental groups have criticized.</p>
        <p>Winding through the verdant Hudson Highlands, the river is cleaner than it has been in years, a fact that many say has contributed to the valley's rebirth. Congress designated the Hudson Valley an American Heritage Area in 1996, while two years ago President Clinton named the Hudson an American Heritage River.</p>
        <p>But even naysayers agree that a growing regional identity has crystallized, a crucial step.</p>
        <p>Once a collection of counties north of New York City that shared a river and little else, the Hudson Valley has acquired a shared consciousness, much like the Napa Valley in California. Unlike the Napa Valley, which is defined mostly by wine and food, the Hudson Valley offers a varied landscape, drawing visitors for its scenic beauty, history, architecture, arts, antiques, food and wine.</p>
        <p>Signs that the 10 counties between New York City and Albany have started to be seen as one include ''The Hudson River Valley Cookbook,'' recently published by the chef Waldy Malouf, as well as a handful of coffee-table photography books and travel guides focused on the region. There is even a Hudson Valley board game modeled after Monopoly, called Hudson Valley in a Box.</p>
        <p>''Suddenly, there's an identity,'' said Lynn Hazelwood, who until recently was editor of Hudson Valley Magazine. The magazine has grown since its inception in 1972 into a glossy monthly available at supermarkets as far south as Westchester County.</p>
        <p>Foreign visitors say that while not all of their compatriots have heard of the Hudson Valley, certain attractions here were widely known back home. The Seales, for example, said many British were familiar with the Franklin D. Roosevelt historic site in Hyde Park. And a group of Chinese graduate students at the University of Chicago said at West Point that they were familiar with the United States Military Academy from movies like ''Patton.''</p>
        <p>''West Point is very famous in China,'' said Bright Liu, 33, standing in the visitors center at the academy a day after he and his classmates had explored New York City.</p>
        <p>The dozens of historical sites in the Hudson Valley are perhaps the biggest draw for tourists. West Point alone has an estimated three million visitors a year, with 750,000 people going through the visitors center, said Nils Anderson, a spokesman for the academy.</p>
        <p>Among the many 19th-century homes overlooking the river and open to the public for tours are Olana, the home of the Hudson River School painter Frederic E. Church, and the opulent Vanderbilt Mansion.</p>
        <p>A new Hudson River waterfront map, listing 300 sites and attractions on either side of the river, was published in the spring by Hudson Valley Tourism. ''We printed 30,000 maps, thinking they would last us two years,'' Ms. Cayea said. ''They lasted us a month.''</p>
        <p>A surge of interest greeted the 1994 opening of Kykuit, the Rockefeller estate outside Tarrytown, with an entire season's worth of tickets -- 50,000 -- selling out before opening day.</p>
        <p>''We were caught off guard,'' said Mr. Patterson of Historic Hudson Valley, which runs the visitors program there. ''It created a sensation overseas. It's just a very private, legendary family, and the fact that their home was opening was in some ways saying that their family story was going to be told for the first time.''</p>
        <p>Tourists also seem to want to take a piece of the past home. That may explain why once-faded industrial cities like Hudson, as well as little-known villages like Millbrook, have reinvented themselves as antique-and-boutique centers, joined by a half-dozen others, from Saugerties in Ulster County and Cold Spring in Putnam County to Tarrytown in Westchester County.</p>
        <p>''It was a struggle 20 years ago -- a lot of the stores were empty,'' said Antonia Salvato, a dealer who owns the Millbrook Antiques Mall, which opened in 1979. She now represents 30 dealers and recently began to advertise in an English trade publication, The Antique Dealer Newspaper.</p>
        <p>The ubiquity of antique shops is one of the reasons the Seales have returned to the Hudson Valley. ''Antiques in the United Kingdom are very expensive, and it's hard to get bargains,'' Mr. Seale said. ''Here, you think, 'My goodness me, that would be four or five times the price in England.' ''</p>
        <p>The Culinary Institute of America in Dutchess County, the nation's leading cooking school, had long put the region on the map in terms of food. But a number of restaurants that could go toque to toque with some of Manhattan's best have emerged in the last decade. Many make a point of relying on locally produced vegetables, meats, cheeses and wines, a trend reflected in some Manhattan restaurants like Mr. Malouf's Beacon.</p>
        <p>There are signs, too, that the arts are establishing a significant presence in the Hudson Valley. Already, there is the Storm King Art Center, an outdoor sculpture museum on 500 acres in Mountainville, and the Bard Music Festival, now in its 11th season in Annandale-on-Hudson.</p>
        <p>Next year, the Dia Center for the Arts, a $20 million space for the exhibition of large-scale works, is to open in an abandoned paperboard factory in Beacon. In 2002, Bard College plans to open a 100,000-square-foot performing arts center designed by Frank Gehry on its campus in Annandale-on-Hudson, for opera, dance and theater productions.</p>
        <p>''It will absolutely solidify the Hudson Valley's reputation as a cultural destination,'' Mark Primoff, a spokesman for Bard College, said of the center.</p>
        <p>Charles A. Gargano, chairman of the Empire State Development Corporation, said the state recognized the importance of tourism in the Hudson Valley when it chose to highlight the region in television advertisements for the first time two years ago.</p>
        <p>''There's a huge interest in cultural and historic sites,'' he said. ''That's what a lot of families are interested in doing now. West Point is there, Hyde Park is there, and we think that the Hudson Valley has the best opportunity for growth because of its proximity to New York City.''</p>
        <p>But the growth in tourism could be hindered by the one thing the Hudson Valley does not seem to have enough of: beds.</p>
        <p>''To truly become an international destination,'' said Mr. Patterson of Historic Hudson Valley, ''you can't make people work so hard to find a room.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 23, 2000, Wednesday  An article on Monday about the growth of tourism in the Hudson Valley misstated Gov. George E. Pataki's position on industrial development there. While he has pushed to build industrial plants in the Hudson Valley, he has not advocated building power plants there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 23, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on Monday about the growth of tourism in the Hudson Valley misstated Gov. George E. Pataki's position on industrial development there. While he has pushed to build industrial plants in the Hudson Valley, he has not advocated building power plants there.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
