<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Take Advantage of Dodgers' Giveaways</title>
    <meta content="Y21MET$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224344"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Dodgers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDC113EF932A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Take Advantage of Dodgers' Giveaways</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Los Angeles Dodgers, 9-6; photo (M)6</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the ninth inning of a close game, there was nobody sitting in the front row of seats beside the camera box near the Mets dugout at Dodger Stadium. So when Mark Grudzielanek hit a foul pop and Mets catcher Mike Piazza tumbled over the fence to catch it, he landed on concrete.</p>
        <p>A phalanx of Mets bolted from the dugout. Piazza was bruised, but fine. He emerged with the ball in hand, and Manager Bobby Valentine congratulated him. Moments later, Armando Benitez finished off a 9-6 Mets victory. The Dodgers had handed them the game in the eighth, and it is hard to blame their fans for leaving the scene.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the ninth inning of a close game, there was nobody sitting in the front row of seats beside the camera box near the Mets dugout at Dodger Stadium. So when Mark Grudzielanek hit a foul pop and Mets catcher Mike Piazza tumbled over the fence to catch it, he landed on concrete.</p>
        <p>A phalanx of Mets bolted from the dugout. Piazza was bruised, but fine. He emerged with the ball in hand, and Manager Bobby Valentine congratulated him. Moments later, Armando Benitez finished off a 9-6 Mets victory. The Dodgers had handed them the game in the eighth, and it is hard to blame their fans for leaving the scene.</p>
        <p>The Mets have won 21 of their last 27 games, and have not lost two games in a row in a month; as Valentine noted, they made their own breaks in the decisive inning. With the score tied, 6-6, Mike Bordick and Darryl Hamilton singled off Terry Adams to open the eighth. Lenny Harris bounced a ball back to Adams, and, as Harris said, ''Everything collapsed right there.''</p>
        <p>Bordick was running from third on contact, and broke for home. Adams threw to third baseman Adrian Beltre, who was closest to Bordick, and Beltre threw the ball to the plate. But his throw floated high over catcher Todd Hundley's head, skipping to the backstop.</p>
        <p>Two runs scored there, and another came in after Grudzielanek let a grounder scoot through his legs. The Mets gave a three-run lead to John Franco and Benitez, and the game was essentially over.</p>
        <p>''Nobody is foolish enough to believe people are invincible or can't be gotten to, but there's no doubts when that situation arises,'' Mets first baseman Todd Zeile said. ''I think everyone's as confident as could be in those guys.''</p>
        <p>Franco worked a perfect eighth and Benitez a perfect ninth for his 33rd save. Turk Wendell (6-4) pitched two innings for the victory, and Dennis Cook got an important out to end the fifth after the Dodgers had taken a lead off Bobby J. Jones.</p>
        <p>''We have confidence every time,'' said Benitez, who, like Franco, has not allowed an earned run since June 21. ''I can trust all those guys in the bullpen, and they can trust me.''</p>
        <p>The Dodgers cannot trust themselves. They are one game over .500 since trading Piazza to the Florida Marlins in May 1998, and just two games over .500 this season despite a $98 million payroll. ''We can't make the plays when we need them,''  Dodgers Manager Davey Johnson said. ''You can't be a championship club that way.''</p>
        <p>The Mets are looking more and more like a champion team, despite trailing the Atlanta Braves by one and a half games in the National League East. On a day when Piazza -- who also collided with the concrete back wall to make a catch in the second inning -- went 0 for 5, teammates like Harris picked him up.</p>
        <p>Harris was 2 for 4 with a home run that briefly gave the Mets a lead in the sixth inning. He romped around the bases after his home run, tearing through a lineup of high-fives as he returned to the dugout. He is 35 years old and his energy is boundless.</p>
        <p>''When you get late in the season, you need someone to kind of get guys going, get people pumped up,'' Hamilton said. ''It was flowing with him today. He was excited.''</p>
        <p>It was a measure of this game's wildness that so much action happened in the ninth spot of the Mets' order, which was first occupied by Jones, who is 0 for 31 this season.</p>
        <p>Jones came up in the second inning with a runner on second and one out. He struck out, but Hundley missed the pitch and Jones reached first on a passed ball. A single by Harris knocked in a run, and when Hundley threw wildly to center on a stolen base attempt, Jones scored to put the Mets ahead, 4-0.</p>
        <p>Hundley made amends in the bottom of the inning with the first of his two home runs, and a run-scoring double by Shawn Green cut the Mets' lead to 4-3 in the third. They seemed poised to break things open in the fourth, when Jones came up as the leadoff batter and walked.</p>
        <p>Darren Dreifort looked distraught, removing his cap and wiping his brow. He walked Harris on four pitches, and Derek Bell sacrificed the runners. But Dreifort got tough, striking out Edgardo Alfonzo -- who  had slugged an opposite-field, two-run homer in the first inning -- and getting Piazza to fly to the warning track in center field.</p>
        <p>That was the second of three times Piazza flied to the center-field track; other Mets had to do the bashing today. That happened in the sixth, when Bubba Trammell pinch-hit for Cook, who had relieved Jones after a single by Eric Karros gave the Dodgers a 5-4 lead in the fifth.</p>
        <p>Dreifort fell behind Trammell, 2-0, and Trammell crushed a sinker into the left-field bullpen for his second homer since joining the Mets. Harris followed with a home run deep into the bleachers in right, finishing Dreifort's erratic outing and putting the Mets up, 6-5.</p>
        <p>In the seventh, a single by Green eluded Harris in left field, and Harris's error brought in a run to tie the score. But Wendell picked Green off second -- ''If he slides, he's probably safe,'' Wendell said -- and the Dodgers had scored for the last time. Franco and Benitez made sure of that.</p>
        <p>''We know how good our bullpen is,'' Hamilton said. ''If we can give it to those guys, we're sitting pretty.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
