<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METROPOLITAN DIARY</title>
    <meta content="21DIAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224310"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EFD6103EF932A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METROPOLITAN DIARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Enid Nemy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Recently, I awoke early, with butterflies in my stomach. I put on a sport jacket and tie and got on the subway. I looked around at the clothing of the men and women making their way to work, wondering where they were headed and what awaited them at their destination.</p>
        <p>As I scanned the crowd, I became fixated with my own reflection in the window of the car. I began to scrutinize myself in my makeshift mirror. Did I get a good shave today? Is the part in my hair straight? What is that red dot emerging on my forehead?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Recently, I awoke early, with butterflies in my stomach. I put on a sport jacket and tie and got on the subway. I looked around at the clothing of the men and women making their way to work, wondering where they were headed and what awaited them at their destination.</p>
        <p>As I scanned the crowd, I became fixated with my own reflection in the window of the car. I began to scrutinize myself in my makeshift mirror. Did I get a good shave today? Is the part in my hair straight? What is that red dot emerging on my forehead?</p>
        <p>After the fifth or sixth time I adjusted my tie, the woman next to me gave me a warm smile and said, ''You look fine.'' Somewhat shocked, but mostly embarrassed, I managed to get out the words, ''It's my first day.'' Her face broke out in a grin indicating that she had been in the same situation once herself and that she understood my case of nerves. She didn't say another word, but it was comforting to know I was not alone in my anxiety.</p>
        <p>As I arrived at the door to my new job, I paused, took a few deep breaths, thought about what she had said, and only checked myself briefly before embarking on my newest adventure.</p>
        <p>JAKE RUBIN</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>I don't know if these various signs that I have seen should be considered oxymorons or simply self-contradictory terms. Or maybe it's just a matter of the big print giveth and the little print taketh away.</p>
        <p>Large print: ''GRAND OPENING.'' Small sign on door: ''Closed.''</p>
        <p>Large print: ''3 BARBERS, NO WAITING.'' Small sign inside shop: ''Be Patient!''</p>
        <p>Large sign at swimming pool: ''LIFEGUARDS ON DUTY.'' Small notification closer to pool: ''Swim at your own risk.''</p>
        <p>Large sign at supermarket checkout counter: ''CASH ONLY.'' Small sign at register: ''Make checks payable to. . . .''</p>
        <p>Large sign at entrance to one section of a parking lot: ''DO NOT ENTER.'' Smaller notice farther on: ''Keep to the right.''</p>
        <p>Large sign in gas station: ''FREE AIR.'' Smaller sign on air pump: ''Deposit one dime or two nickels.''</p>
        <p>ERNEST G. D'AMATO</p>
        <p>Arline Julius, who is in her 70's, was at the ticket window of a Long Island Rail Road station asking for a ticket to New York. The clerk looked blank. She amended the request to ''one way to Penn Station.'' Still no response. Becoming increasingly perplexed, she next tried ''to Manhattan.'' This time she added that she would like the senior-citizen rate. The clerk smiled and handed over a ticket, and she realized what he had been waiting for. ''Why didn't you remind me?'' she asked. ''I keep out of trouble this way,'' he replied.</p>
        <p>THE GOLDEN YEARS</p>
        <p>When vision blurs, I sharpen my intuition.</p>
        <p>When strength wanes, I practice resolve.</p>
        <p>As the world darkens, I imagine light.</p>
        <p>And as the future dims, I enjoy the moment.</p>
        <p>MORTON R. GOLDMAN</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>During OpSail 2000, I visited the tall ships docked near the Intrepid museum on my lunch break. Perhaps the most memorable moment, and one that demonstrates the good will of New Yorkers, came during my walk back along 43rd Street.</p>
        <p>An older gentleman, looking somewhat anxious, appeared next to me and asked for directions to a subway station. Clutched in a grimy hand, he had a number of belts like those one would see under a car's hood. I provided directions, was thanked profusely and then received a hurried explanation that brightened the rest of my day.</p>
        <p>The man had been visiting the Romanian tall ship and overheard sailors expressing concern about some damaged and badly needed engine part. He had taken it upon himself not only to investigate the problem but to locate the part, a rather specialized engine belt, in Queens. He was heading for the subway to take him there.</p>
        <p>My look of surprise prompted him to remind me, in no uncertain terms, that the Romanians were our guests and that New York City knows how to treat guests.</p>
        <p>JIM BIEBER</p>
        <p>Richard Harbert spotted an apparently homeless man sitting atop a shopping cart loaded with an array of bulging plastic bags and other belongings. The perch was some three or four feet above the sidewalk. The man wasn't the usual panhandler. There was no cup in sight; he simply held up a brown corrugated cardboard sign that read ''TELL ME OFF FOR $2.'' Mr. Harbert said he was tempted for a moment, but he was in too good a mood to take advantage of the offer.</p>
        <p>STRIVE</p>
        <p>Earnest seedling strives,</p>
        <p>yearning aloud for the sun's warm kiss.</p>
        <p>Love me.</p>
        <p>CYNTHIA-MARIE PHILLIPS</p>
        <p>Marie E. Klein was a recipient of this birth announcement sent by her daughter, Heather Klein:</p>
        <p>''Born at 3.50 p.m. on Aug. 2 and weighing in at about 3 ounces was our very first bouncing baby tomato. Tomato and plant were both doing well until the tomato was consumed as the prize ingredient in a jolly good bacon, lettuce and tomato sandwich at approximately 5.15 p.m.</p>
        <p>''Future siblings are expected; their delivery dates appear imminent judging from their pink cheeks!</p>
        <p>''I know you are as excited as I am about this wonderful news. But please, gifts are not required or expected. Just knowing that you share my joy is gift enough.''</p>
        <p>Peter M. Rowe was one of the passengers who enjoyed this announcement from Alvin Brock, the driver, as the No. 10 bus neared the end of its route at Pennsylvania Station:</p>
        <p>''I'd like to take this time to say</p>
        <p>that I hope you had a good day</p>
        <p>and everything went your way</p>
        <p>and thank you for riding the M.T.A.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brock told Mr. Rowe that he used the past tense in the afternoon and the future tense in the morning.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
