<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A company's ad is rejected for coasting on the momentum of the Olympic Games.</title>
    <meta content="21ADCO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000822T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224296"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PacificHealth Laboratories</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Usa Today</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Olympic Committee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stamler, Bernard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E5D7103EF932A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A company's ad is rejected for coasting on the momentum of the Olympic Games.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bernard Stamler</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stamler, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>USA Today declines to run ad for Endurox R4, a sports drink made by PacificHealth Laboratories, in a special Olympic Glory section of the newspaper; this touches off debate between PacificHealth and US Olympic Coimmittee, which owns rights to all the various Olympic trademarks and complained to USA Today about the ad; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S called ''ambush marketing,'' and it refers to advertisers' attempts to capitalize on a sponsorship event without actually becoming sponsors. And with official sponsorships for the Summer Olympic Games selling for stratospheric sums, it is hardly surprising to officials at the United States Olympic Committee that the Games have frequently been targets of ambush.</p>
        <p>Examples abound, involving advertisers large and small. American Express, for example, told viewers in 1992 that they ''didn't need a Visa'' to visit Barcelona, Spain, where the rival credit card company Visa was an official sponsor of the Summer Games. And Wendy's used former Olympic athletes to push its burgers during the 1998 Winter Olympics in Nagano, Japan, where the official fast-food sponsor was McDonald's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S called ''ambush marketing,'' and it refers to advertisers' attempts to capitalize on a sponsorship event without actually becoming sponsors. And with official sponsorships for the Summer Olympic Games selling for stratospheric sums, it is hardly surprising to officials at the United States Olympic Committee that the Games have frequently been targets of ambush.</p>
        <p>Examples abound, involving advertisers large and small. American Express, for example, told viewers in 1992 that they ''didn't need a Visa'' to visit Barcelona, Spain, where the rival credit card company Visa was an official sponsor of the Summer Games. And Wendy's used former Olympic athletes to push its burgers during the 1998 Winter Olympics in Nagano, Japan, where the official fast-food sponsor was McDonald's.</p>
        <p>Such shenanigans have consistently drawn the ire of the Olympic committee. But they do not typically cause an ad to be pulled from circulation.</p>
        <p>With the 2000 Olympic games in Sydney, Australia, only weeks away, however, that is exactly what happened to a small company called PacificHealth Laboratories.</p>
        <p>PacificHealth, a five-year-old publicly traded health food company based in Woodbridge, N.J., tried to run an ad in a special ''Olympic Glory'' section in the Aug. 3 edition of USA Today, promoting Endurox R4, a sports drink. The cost of the ad, prepared by PacificHealth's agency, Alan Taylor Communications, would be ''a large chunk'' of the company's annual advertising budget, according to Dr. Robert Portman, PacificHealth's chairman.</p>
        <p>But the Olympic committee, which got wind of the ad from a PacificHealth press release, objected. And on Aug. 1, USA Today decided not to publish the ad. The decision touched off a debate between PacificHealth and the committee about just how far non-Olympic sponsors can go in their efforts to harvest a bit of Olympic glory without paying for the right to do so.</p>
        <p>The answer is not all that clear.</p>
        <p>By federal law, the committee owns the rights, including the licensing rights, to all the various Olympic trademarks, including the words ''Olympics,'' ''Olympiad'' and ''Paralympic,'' as well as the five interlocking Olympic rings. Moreover, to protect those rights, the so-called Ted Stevens Olympic and Amateur Sports Act, the law that charters the United States Olympic Committee and which was last revised in 1998, allows the committee to bring civil actions against nonlicensees for the use of ''any combination or simulation of those words tending to cause confusion or mistake, to deceive, or to falsely suggest a connection'' with the committee or the Olympic games.</p>
        <p>The committee, of course, is a vigorous defender of its rights. The reasons are obvious: according to Mike Moran, the committee's spokesman, the money it receives for commercial sponsorships provides some 70 percent of the committee's revenue and amounted to roughly $70 million this year alone. No one pays that kind of money without an exclusive and, presumably, that's what the Coca-Cola Company thought it was getting when it agreed to pay for its Powerade to become the official Summer Olympics sports drink.</p>
        <p>So what of the ad for Endurox R4, another sports drink?</p>
        <p>Among other things, it features a replica of the three-step stand where winning athletes receive their medals and that is emblazoned with the words ''Sydney 2000.'' It also has an endorsement from the ''Olympic triathlete'' Jennifer Gutierrez and an offer of free product samples to ''the 600 U.S. Athletes going to Sydney.'' It makes claims about the efficacy of the drink as a performance-enhancer, saying that its use would allow athletes to ''go for the gold every day.'' Still, the word ''Olympics'' is never used. Nor are the Olympic rings depicted.</p>
        <p>That doesn't matter, according to Mr. Moran. ''We absolutely believe that the ad infringes on our rights,'' he said, adding that the rights of the Sydney Organizing Committee to the words ''Sydney 2000'' may also have been violated. At the very least, he said, the ad skirted Rule 45 of the International Olympic Committee charter, which bans athletes like Ms. Gutierrez from endorsing nonofficial products during the time that Olympic games are being played.</p>
        <p>Nonsense, replied Dr. Portman of PacificHealth. He contends that the U.S.O.C. is grasping at straws, having at first objected to the ad on grounds that Endurox contained substances that were banned by Olympic rules. (Mr. Moran, the U.S.O.C. spokesman, acknowledges that the drink contains no such substances, notwithstanding the committee's initial concerns.) And though Dr. Portman acknowledged that the ad was ''very close to the line,'' he nevertheless insisted that PacificHealth and Endurox did not cross it. ''The copy for the ad was consistent with copy guidelines regarding product advertising and the Olympics,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But there are no such guidelines, said Mr. Moran, only the Ted Stevens Act. And the ad is not acceptable, he said, in light of that law's provisions.</p>
        <p>That may not be enough to satisfy Dr. Portman. But, apparently, it was enough for USA Today.</p>
        <p>''We never comment on what we do with any specific ad,'' said Steve Anderson, a spokesman for the newspaper. ''But if we think an ad is libelous, fraudulent or just in poor taste, then we are not going to accept it.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING  Correction:  August 22, 2000, Tuesday  The Advertising column in Business Day yesterday, about an advertisement for PacificHealth Laboratories that exploited the Summer Olympic Games, misidentified the company's advertising agency. It is Linett &amp; Harrison; Alan Taylor Communications is its public relations firm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 22, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>The Advertising column in Business Day yesterday, about an advertisement for PacificHealth Laboratories that exploited the Summer Olympic Games, misidentified the company's advertising agency. It is Linett &amp; Harrison; Alan Taylor Communications is its public relations firm.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
