<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Aching Hampton Says He'll Skip Start</title>
    <meta content="Y21NOT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224368"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: METS NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hampton, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamilton, Darryl</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEFDA113EF932A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Aching Hampton Says He'll Skip Start</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Injured New York Mets pitcher Mike Hampton throws lightly in outfield but is not recovered enough to throw in bullpen; outfielder Darryl Hamilton, who has arthritic toe, does not start for Mets (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Hampton said Saturday that if he felt better today, he expected to work a bullpen session. If things went well, Hampton might then be cleared to start on Tuesday in San Diego.</p>
        <p>This morning, the plan changed. Hampton, who left his start last Thursday because of a stress fracture in his right ribs, threw lightly in the outfield and did feel better. But he did not throw in the bullpen, and he will not start on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mike Hampton said Saturday that if he felt better today, he expected to work a bullpen session. If things went well, Hampton might then be cleared to start on Tuesday in San Diego.</p>
        <p>This morning, the plan changed. Hampton, who left his start last Thursday because of a stress fracture in his right ribs, threw lightly in the outfield and did feel better. But he did not throw in the bullpen, and he will not start on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''No,'' Hampton said, when asked if he will make the start. ''Maybe over the weekend. We'll come up with it.''</p>
        <p>Pat Mahomes, who threw six and two-thirds effective innings in a spot start last week, would be the logical candidate to fill in. The Mets have little flexibility on their roster, making it difficult to recall Grant Roberts or Bobby M. Jones from Class AAA Norfolk.</p>
        <p>Hampton's injury, which he believes stems from a high school football game 11 years ago, is not the kind that worsens the more he pitches. The Mets believe it is simply a question of how well Hampton can tolerate the pain.</p>
        <p>''I think they want to give it a few more days to heal,'' Hampton said. ''I guess if I'm feeling a lot better after two days with not a lot of activity, maybe a few more might get us further down the road.''</p>
        <p>Manager Bobby Valentine said he would make a final decision on Hampton's status Monday.</p>
        <p>Hamilton Hurting</p>
        <p>Outfielder Darryl Hamilton, who has not gone more than a day without starting since coming off the disabled list on Aug. 9, sat for the second game in a row today. Lenny Harris started in left field.</p>
        <p>Hamilton has experienced discomfort in his arthritic left big toe since playing a game on wet grass during the Mets' last homestand. He singled as a pinch-hitter in the seventh inning and was removed for a pinch-runner.</p>
        <p>''I don't want it to be an issue every day,'' Hamilton said. ''It's going to be there the whole year, and I understand that. I have good days and bad days. Hopefully, I can hold on to the good days so later in the year, I can go out for a good amount of time.''</p>
        <p>Wallace Quiet on Future</p>
        <p>Like Manager Bobby Valentine and General Manager Steve Phillips, the Mets' coaches all have contracts that expire after this season. Dave Wallace, the pitching coach, could be attractive to other teams, and a report in The Los Angeles Times said the Dodgers want to bring him back. Wallace coached for the Dodgers from 1995-97.</p>
        <p>Last winter, Phillips would not allow other teams to interview Wallace, who was under contract. ''I like Dave, and he's an important member of our organization,'' Phillips said today.</p>
        <p>Wallace was noncommittal about whether he wanted to return to the Mets. ''Steve and Fred have been very good to me,'' he said, referring to Phillips and Fred Wilpon, the co-owner. ''I don't really concern myself with that stuff. We've got six tough weeks ahead of us. Those are my only concern.''</p>
        <p>Wallace, who came to the Mets as an adviser to Phillips, joined Valentine's staff after three coaches were fired last June. Asked about his relationship with Valentine, Wallace said, ''Since we've started working together, things have kind of moved along pretty good.''</p>
        <p>First in a While</p>
        <p>The right-hander Bobby J. Jones lasted four and two-thirds innings today, the first time he has failed to pitch five innings since returning from an assignment to Class AAA Norfolk. He is 7-2 with a 3.26 earned run average in 11 starts since then.</p>
        <p>Eight More Left On</p>
        <p>Although the Mets have continued to pile up victories, there is one area where they could use a great deal of improvement. The Mets stranded eight more base runners today, running their league-leading total to 950. The Atlanta Braves, whom the Mets now trail by a game and a half in the National League East standing, have stranded 889 runners this season.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: METS NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
