<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ACCORD IS REACHED FOR MOST WORKERS IN PHONE WALKOUT</title>
    <meta content="21VERI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Verizon Communications</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Communications Workers of America</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E2DA113EF932A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ACCORD IS REACHED FOR MOST WORKERS IN PHONE WALKOUT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romero, Simon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Two unions representing most of striking telephone workers reach contract agreement with Verizon Communications, nation's largest telecommunications employer; secure 12 percent wage increase over three years; win right to more easily organize workers in company's wireless division, where fewer than 50 of 32,000 employees belong to union; secure company's promise that union telephone workers will be given opportunity to do more work in fast-growing areas, like installation of high-speed Internet lines, activity for which company intended to use nonunion contractrors until now; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The two unions representing more than 86,000 striking telephone workers reached a contract agreement yesterday with the nation's largest telecommunications employer, Verizon Communications, for about two-thirds of the strikers, indicating that organized labor still has a place in the New Economy.</p>
        <p>Although about one-third of the union locals had still not signed off on the settlement last evening, the company and the union leaders said the 15-day strike was effectively over. They said union workers in the region affected by the strike -- 12 states from Maine to Virginia and the District of Columbia -- could return to their jobs in New York and New England as soon as this morning, although workers in states such as New Jersey and Pennsylvania are still waiting for their local presidents to approve the contract.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The two unions representing more than 86,000 striking telephone workers reached a contract agreement yesterday with the nation's largest telecommunications employer, Verizon Communications, for about two-thirds of the strikers, indicating that organized labor still has a place in the New Economy.</p>
        <p>Although about one-third of the union locals had still not signed off on the settlement last evening, the company and the union leaders said the 15-day strike was effectively over. They said union workers in the region affected by the strike -- 12 states from Maine to Virginia and the District of Columbia -- could return to their jobs in New York and New England as soon as this morning, although workers in states such as New Jersey and Pennsylvania are still waiting for their local presidents to approve the contract.</p>
        <p>The first task for Verizon will be to work down a backlog of telephone repair orders that has risen to 90,000 -- one-third more than normal -- since the strike began Aug. 6</p>
        <p>Under the three-year contract agreement, the Communications Workers of America and the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers secured numerous concessions from Verizon, which is the nation's largest provider of wireless and local telephone services, with 260,000 employees around the nation.</p>
        <p>The unions secured a 12 percent wage increase, over three years, for a work force that was already one of the best paid in the telecommunications industry. The average hourly base pay for a customer service representative in New York, $26, would increase to $29.25 in the contract's third year, for example. And in a new-economy wrinkle, each of Verizon's union workers will receive a small grant of stock options.</p>
        <p>But the broader significance of the agreement, and the reason the negotiations have been closely watched throughout the high-technology industry, involves issues that go beyond wage and benefit concerns.</p>
        <p>The unions have won the right to more easily organize workers in Verizon's wireless division, where fewer than 50 of the division's 32,000 employees belong to a union. The unions also secured Verizon's promise that union telephone workers will be given the opportunity to do more work in fast-growing areas like the installation of high-speed Internet lines -- an activity for which Verizon has tended to use nonunion contractors until now.</p>
        <p>Those were key points for the unions because wireless and Internet communications are growing much faster than the conventional telephone business.</p>
        <p>''This contract is a breakthrough not just for our members who work at Verizon but for workers throughout the telecommunications industry,'' Larry Mancino, vice president of the Communications Workers of America, which represents about 72,000 of the striking employees, said yesterday .</p>
        <p>The unions also secured agreements on several other issues that reflected worker anxieties in the new economy, which is characterized by big corporate mergers and an entrepreneurial ethic in which the shorthand ''24/7'' -- meaning 24 hours a day, seven days a week -- symbolizes the relentlessness of work in today's economy.</p>
        <p>Verizon was created by Bell Atlantic's acquisition of the GTE Corporation and through the formation of a wireless venture with Vodafone AirTouch of Britain. And union employees, particularly in the Northeast, had been worried about the prospect of the company transferring work to lower-paying parts of the country.</p>
        <p>The unions, especially customer service representatives, had also sought relief from job stress brought by long periods of work with few breaks and frequent mandatory overtime.</p>
        <p>Verizon agreed to greater job stability for union members by limiting the number of employees whose jobs could be moved to a different region to 0.7 percent of the union workers in a given geographic area each year. The measurement would be based on a geographic area as small as a county, as the unions wanted, instead of an across-the-board number, as the company wanted.</p>
        <p>On job-related stress, Verizon agreed to give customer service representatives and telephone operators up to five 30-minute periods each week during which they can do work other than taking calls. And mandatory overtime for customer service representatives and operators would be reduced. For example, operators who are single mothers will be limited to as few as 7.5 hours a week in some areas, down from as much as 20 hours before the strike.</p>
        <p>Verizon (pronounced Vuh-RISE-en) was under various pressures to settle the strike, which the company had apparently expected to be only a token few-day walkout. It had come at the busiest time of the year for the consumer telecommunications industry, when many students were about to return to college and would require new telephone and Internet access service.</p>
        <p>Shortly before the strike began, the company also started a major advertising campaign to make people aware of its new name. And lately, concern over the company's earnings have pushed Verizon's share price close to a two-year low. Since the strike began, Verizon's stock has fallen more than 10 percent. It closed at $42.4375 on Friday.</p>
        <p>''We're glad to put this strike behind us and move on,'' the company's chief executive, Ivan Seidenberg, said yesterday in an interview. ''I would say that every one of the unions' issues was legitimate going forward. We've strengthened the fiber of our company over the long term with this agreement.''</p>
        <p>What remains to be seen is how the agreement will be viewed elsewhere in labor circles, by other big telecommunications companies and by Wall Street.</p>
        <p>''This is one of the most wide-reaching contract settlements the industry has seen,'' said Jeffrey Kagan, an independent analyst of the telecommunications industry. ''It'll be interesting to see whether this will result in a more qualified work force or a ball and chain around the company's leg.''</p>
        <p>The unions' right to organize Verizon's wireless division may end up as the strike's most significant outcome. The unions won an important concession allowing them to organize by card check, which permits a given work site to join a union if a majority of its employees sign cards saying they wish to do so. The process is faster and less bureaucratic than holding elections.</p>
        <p>Under this part of the agreement, the employees at a work location would join the union if 55 percent signed up through the cards.</p>
        <p>The wireless agreement applies only to workers in the strike region, where about one-quarter of the 32,000 employees of the Verizon Wireless division are located.</p>
        <p>The agreement would include technicians, customer service representatives and employees who work as customer sales representatives in the wireless division's retail stores.</p>
        <p>Making it easier to organize Verizon's wireless work force could have broad implications for the nation's wireless industry, which is one of the fastest-growing parts of the new economy and which so far has remained a primarily nonunion business.</p>
        <p>Of course, there is no certainty that the majority of workers in parts of Verizon Wireless that are not covered by the settlement or at other wireless companies -- or in other high-growth, high-technology industries, for that matter -- are eager to unionize.</p>
        <p>But some union advocates are optimistic.</p>
        <p>''For us, the parallel issues are glaringly apparent,'' said Marcus Courtney, co-founder of the Washington Alliance of Technology Workers, a Seattle organization affiliated with the Communications Workers of America. The Washington Alliance has already organized a small number of employees at companies that include Microsoft and Amazon.com.</p>
        <p>''This will make our efforts easier, because it shows that the largest company in a key high-tech industry is not off limits,'' Mr. Courtney said. ''Now we can hold up this example that says, 'Your voice can be heard.' ''</p>
        <p>And as in the Verizon strike, the future of union organizing efforts in high-technology companies is not expected to focus on wages as much as on issues like job security, benefits, overtime, work-related stress and even stock options.</p>
        <p>''The questions have been raised,'' said Stanley Aronowitz, a professor of sociology at the City University of New York who has studied labor issues. ''In the 30's, no one took workers' complaints seriously until the G.M.'s and U.S. Steels were organized.''</p>
        <p>Already in the wireless industry, where Verizon will try to compete with other companies that are mostly nonunion, there are inklings that organizing can be viable.</p>
        <p>At SBC Communications, which will soon operate the nation's second-largest wireless carrier in a venture with BellSouth, the same kind of card-check organizing Verizon has agreed to has been permitted for nearly three years. So far, more than 5,000 of SBC's wireless employees out of a potential 12,000 eligible are union members, the C.W.A. says.</p>
        <p>And at AT&amp;T Wireless, the third-largest wireless carrier, the union won the right last year to card-check organizing, although elections must be held several days after the cards are gathered -- a potential union impediment not included in the Verizon agreement.</p>
        <p>THE AGREEMENT  Highlights of Contract</p>
        <p>LENGTH OF CONTRACT -- Three years.</p>
        <p>ORGANIZATION -- The unions will be able to organize more easily in Verizon's wireless division, and union members will have the opportunity to do more work in fast-growing areas like the installation of high-speed Internet service.</p>
        <p>COMPENSATION -- A 12 percent raise over the life of the contract: 4 percent in the first year, 3 percent in the second and 5 percent in the third. In addition, full-time employees will receive 100 stock options and part-time workers will receive 50. A profit-sharing plan tied to that of the chief executive will provide payouts up to $1,000 a year.</p>
        <p>JOB STABILITY -- The number of Verizon employees who can have their jobs transferred to a different region as a result of the Bell Atlantic-GTE merger is limited to seven-tenths of 1 percent each year.</p>
        <p>JOB STRESS -- Customer service representatives and operators will receive up to five 30-minute periods each week in which they can do work other than taking calls.</p>
        <p>OVERTIME -- Mandatory overtime is lowered for most customer service representatives and operators.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
