<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Tiger Triumphed The Hogan Way</title>
    <meta content="21ANDE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pga Championship</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hogan, Ben (1912-97)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">PGA Championship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E1DA113EF932A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1266" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Tiger Triumphed The Hogan Way</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dave Anderson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>LOUISVILLE, Ky.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>sports</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS a youngster, Tiger Woods taped a list of Jack Nicklaus's accomplishments on the wall of his room. And after having played with Nicklaus in the first two rounds of the 82nd Professional Golfers' Association Championship, he was asked: if he could play with two other golfers of history in a mythical foursome, who would they be?</p>
        <p>''Hogan and Jones,'' he said quickly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS a youngster, Tiger Woods taped a list of Jack Nicklaus's accomplishments on the wall of his room. And after having played with Nicklaus in the first two rounds of the 82nd Professional Golfers' Association Championship, he was asked: if he could play with two other golfers of history in a mythical foursome, who would they be?</p>
        <p>''Hogan and Jones,'' he said quickly.</p>
        <p>Bobby Jones died before Tiger Woods was born, but when Woods, after winning the 1997 Masters as a PGA Tour rookie, arrived to play in the Colonial in Fort Worth, he hoped to meet Ben Hogan, who was ill at home there. Valerie Hogan didn't want Tiger to see her husband in his condition, but she arranged for him to take Tiger's phone call.</p>
        <p>''I don't know what they talked about,'' she would say before her death in 1999, ''but I heard Ben say, 'I feel the same way about you, Tiger.' And when Ben died two months later, I received the nicest note from Tiger.''</p>
        <p>And now Tiger Woods has finally met Ben Hogan in golf's history books. With his P.G.A. victory in a theatrical three-hole playoff with Bob May yesterday, Woods, the reigning United States Open and British Open champion, is the first golfer to win three major titles in one season since Hogan won the Masters and the two Opens in 1953.</p>
        <p>For all his dazzling shots yesterday, Woods really won the Hogan way, the hard-work way.</p>
        <p>Whenever other golfers asked Hogan for his secret, the little Texan would say, ''The secret is in the dirt,'' meaning the dirt below the grass of the practice range and the practice green. Nobody in his era worked any harder to hone his talent than Hogan did. And for all of Woods's gifts, nobody works any harder now than he does.</p>
        <p>In the dirt is where Woods won this P.G.A. -- in the dirt of Valhalla Golf Club's practice range and practice green long after sunset Saturday.</p>
        <p>''I didn't leave the putting green until 8:56,'' Woods said, alluding to tuning his game with his swing guru, Butch Harmon. ''I worked on my swing and my putting. I tried to feel a little more steady over the ball and let the toe of the blade release a little better.</p>
        <p>''Then today, I hit a lot of good putts early in the warm-up. It didn't carry over to the golf course initially, but at least I was hitting good, solid shots. It was just a matter of time before the putter would come around, and it did.''</p>
        <p>After two bogeys in the first six holes, Woods suddenly found the putting touch that he developed Saturday night. With seven birdies in the last 12 holes that produced a 31 on the back nine and a five-under-par 67, he forced the three-hole playoff that he won with by one stroke by one-putting for a birdie and two pars.</p>
        <p>He had won the United States Open by 15 strokes and the British Open by 8 strokes, but he won this P.G.A. in much the same way he won the P.G.A. a year ago at Medinah No. 3 outside Chicago, where he won by one stroke in a back-nine shootout with Sergio Garcia of Spain.</p>
        <p>''I knew stepping up on 18,'' Woods said of the 72nd hole in yesterday's duel, ''that I had to make birdie to win the championship or force a playoff. Par wasn't going to get it done. And the way the day had been going, I expected Bob to make that putt on 18, so when he made it, I had to make mine.</p>
        <p>''So that is the mental preparation for it,'' he said of his 5-foot putt, ''to step up there and play that putt -- a ball outside the left from a short distance like that -- and know that you have to trust your stroke and the break and stay committed. When it goes in, it really feels pretty good.''</p>
        <p>With his fifth major title at age 24, Woods has also won four out of the last five majors. He's not the best golfer in history yet; he'll need to surpass Nicklaus's record of 18 major titles to deserve that accolade, but he has the time and the talent to surpass the Golden Bear's total.</p>
        <p>''What Tiger is doing right now,'' Nicklaus said after watching Woods shoot 66-67 in the two rounds they played together, ''I think he is a better player than I ever was.''</p>
        <p>That's powerful praise from the golfer who is generally considered to be the best ever with six Masters, four United States Opens, three British Opens and five P.G.A. titles.</p>
        <p>''Tiger is doing it with regularity and he is doing it with so much left in him, so much more power to burn,'' Nicklaus said. ''I don't think I have ever seen anybody do what he is doing that much within himself. He doesn't have to extend himself at all.''</p>
        <p>Woods, however, did need to extend himself against May, who until the weekend here had been a virtual unknown on the tour.</p>
        <p>''When I was playing,'' Nicklaus said, ''I always had Arnold Palmer, Gary Player, Lee Trevino, Tom Watson, guys that won quite a few majors. They were not afraid to win a tournament. Tiger not only has the ability to be so much better than the other guys, but the other guys are not sure they can win. He's got everything sitting in front of him, plus that factor that is a big factor.''</p>
        <p>Nicklaus mentioned another factor, that Woods is using clubs and balls that are much more high-tech than when the Golden Bear was at his best.</p>
        <p>''I never hit my irons anywhere near as hard as Tiger hits his irons, nor as far,'' Nicklaus said. ''I never tried to. I hit my irons basically the same distance now as I did in my prime; maybe not the 1-iron and the 2-iron, but 25 years ago I hit a 5-iron 175 yards and I hit a 5-iron 175 yards now.</p>
        <p>''But when Tiger is hitting 175 yards, it's a 7-iron or 8-iron, most likely an 8-iron. That is just a different way of playing.</p>
        <p>''I'm not sure you can do that with the golf ball we used to play with because it had so much spin on it. Today you can tailor a golf ball to your game a little bit more than you could then. You can get a low spin-rate ball, whatever you want. We couldn't do that.''</p>
        <p>As much as Nicklaus enjoyed watching Woods play, he also enjoyed Woods the young man.</p>
        <p>''He's a pleasant young man to play with: he couldn't have been nicer,'' Nicklaus said. ''He has a good sense of humor. He enjoys joking around a little bit. If I'm passing the baton, I couldn't pass it to a nicer young man who is obviously the cream of the crop right now by a mile.''</p>
        <p>And a young man with the Hogan work ethic.</p>
        <p>''When I look at the videotape,'' Tiger Woods said, alluding to yesterday's duel, ''I already know what I need to work on, but maybe I'll see something else to work on.''</p>
        <p>Ben Hogan would understand that.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
