<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lucky Loser in Qualifying Becomes Tired Winner of the Bronx Classic</title>
    <meta content="21TENN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ghi Bronx Tennis Classic</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Hyung Taik</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hollander, Sophia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Willems, Reginald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E1DC113EF932A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lucky Loser in Qualifying Becomes Tired Winner of the Bronx Classic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOPHIA HOLLANDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hollander, Sophia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hyung Taik Lee wins GHI Bronx Classic tennis tournament, defeating Reginald Willems (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hyung Taik Lee trudged to his car the afternoon of Aug. 11, tired and mildly depressed. Lee had just lost in the quarterfinals at a men's tennis Challenger event in Binghamton, N.Y., and missed making the main draw for his next tournament, the GHI Bronx Classic, by one spot. The qualifiers started play the next day.</p>
        <p>So Lee, a 24-year-old Korean, drove straight to the Bronx, hoping he would not get lost because his English is shaky, finally arriving at 2 a.m. He lost in a grueling qualifying championships.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hyung Taik Lee trudged to his car the afternoon of Aug. 11, tired and mildly depressed. Lee had just lost in the quarterfinals at a men's tennis Challenger event in Binghamton, N.Y., and missed making the main draw for his next tournament, the GHI Bronx Classic, by one spot. The qualifiers started play the next day.</p>
        <p>So Lee, a 24-year-old Korean, drove straight to the Bronx, hoping he would not get lost because his English is shaky, finally arriving at 2 a.m. He lost in a grueling qualifying championships.</p>
        <p>But when a player pulled out of the tournament with an eye problem, Lee became the lucky loser. And he began to win.</p>
        <p>Yesterday afternoon, Lee neatly dispatched Reginald Willems of Belgium, 6-4, 6-1, in front of more than 400 people crowded into the sunny stands at Crotona Park.</p>
        <p>How did he feel after gaining 50 ranking points, $7,200 and a Challenger championship after nearly not making the tournament?</p>
        <p>''Very tired,'' Lee, laughing, said through an interpreter. ''Every day, every day I'm getting better.''</p>
        <p>In the women's final, 17-year-old Daniela Hantuchova of Slovakia coolly contained No. 1-seeded Jing Qian Yi of China, 6-4, 6-4.</p>
        <p>Yi, ranked 74th, was hampered by a swollen pinkie, which was caught in a car door three weeks ago, tearing half the nail off. Her backhand fizzled and she hit shot after shot into the net, alternately yelling ''Patience!'' and ''Why!'' after her mistakes.</p>
        <p>Hantuchova, ranked 164th and unseeded, was quietly confident, repeatedly drawing Yi to the net, then powering the ball by her. Yi lost the final game at love. Hantuchova pumped her fist and then shook it in the air, her stoic face melting into a broad smile.</p>
        <p>''I made a decision that I am going to fight for every ball,'' Hantuchova said. ''I'm just so happy that I win. From the first point, I felt really confident. The whole week I played really good.''</p>
        <p>Hantuchova will play in the United States Open qualifying, which begins tomorrow. Yi is in the main draw.</p>
        <p>After the men's singles final, Lee rested for less than two hours as the women played. Then he strode back onto the court to compete with his countryman Yong-Il Yoon in the doubles final against Petr Luxa of the Czech Republic and Wesley Whitehouse of South Africa, who had never played together before this tournament.</p>
        <p>The laid-back Luxa and the emotional Whitehouse, who repeatedly slammed their rackets to the ground and groaned after mistakes, powered their way past Lee and Il-Yoon, 3-6, 6-3, 6-2.</p>
        <p>''He must have serious back problems from carrying me this week,'' Whitehouse told the crowd after the victory. Later he said: ''Petr kept me calm, knew how to talk to me. I have a new friend.''</p>
        <p>In the women's doubles final, Surina De Beer of South Africa and Nana Miyagi of Japan successfully defended their championship, defeating Alexandra Fusai and Emilie Loit of France, 5-7, 6-4, 6-4.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
