<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Civil Liberties Head Protests Searches at Parks</title>
    <meta content="21SEAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224333"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Search and Seizure</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Harris Park (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Civil Liberties Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stern, Henry J (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siegel, Norman</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herszenhorn, David M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Search and Seizure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E6DC113EF932A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Civil Liberties Head Protests Searches at Parks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HERSZENHORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herszenhorn, David M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Norman Siegel, director of New York Civil Liberties Union, accuses city's police and parks departments of allowing unconstitutional security searches of people entering public parks to attend concerts and other privately organized events; is barred from free salsa concert at Harris Park in Bronx for refusing to open his bag for inspection and undergo search by a hand-held magnetometer; Comr Henry J Stern acknowledges that parks department does not have uniform security guidelines for promoters of private events; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The director of the New York Civil Liberties Union accused the city's police and parks departments yesterday of allowing unconstitutional security searches of people entering public parks to attend concerts and other privately organized events.</p>
        <p>To make his point, the director, Norman Siegel, went to Harris Park in the Bronx yesterday afternoon (after notifying The New York Times and a television station) and demanded entry to a free salsa concert without opening his bag for inspection or being subjected to a hand-held magnetometer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The director of the New York Civil Liberties Union accused the city's police and parks departments yesterday of allowing unconstitutional security searches of people entering public parks to attend concerts and other privately organized events.</p>
        <p>To make his point, the director, Norman Siegel, went to Harris Park in the Bronx yesterday afternoon (after notifying The New York Times and a television station) and demanded entry to a free salsa concert without opening his bag for inspection or being subjected to a hand-held magnetometer.</p>
        <p>As police commanders looked on, private security guards at the park entrance refused Mr. Siegel's request. A lawyer for TG Productions, the concert promoter, said that a Parks Department permit gave the company the right to set the rules.</p>
        <p>''You are supposed to uphold the law and protect our rights,'' Mr. Siegel told the officers. ''My rights are being violated.''</p>
        <p>Kristie Velasco, the promoter's lawyer, replied, ''You are absolutely allowed to go in, but everybody is being searched.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Siegel refused to submit to a search, and remained outside.</p>
        <p>He said the searches yesterday and at a concert in Harris Park after the Bronx Puerto Rican Day parade on Aug. 6 raised serious questions about the private use of public parks and about Fourth Amendment search-and-seizure protections.</p>
        <p>The parks commissioner, Henry J. Stern, acknowledged that his department did not have uniform security guidelines for promoters. Each event is evaluated individually, he said, adding, ''We require security as we believe it is needed.''</p>
        <p>''Obviously, when they are doing Verdi,'' Mr. Stern said, ''there is no need for the security that you might need at a rock concert. The middle-aged people in the opera, nobody is going to hurt a fly.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, the agency does not have a uniform policy regarding which permits are granted, or when a donation and other fees, as the agency calls them, are required for the use of city property. Promoters of major commercial events, like the scheduled Sting concert in Central Park, can end up paying more than $1 million.</p>
        <p>Small events often involve only a $25 permit fee. Technically, a permit is required for all events with more than 25 people. Larger events may require a signed contract with the city. ''There is no magic number,'' Mr. Stern said. ''There is sort of a common-sense approach.''</p>
        <p>One firm rule, Mr. Stern said, is that no events are allowed that could damage the grass.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern said there had been no previous objections to the security arrangements, either from promoters required to carry them out or from the people subjected to them. ''Usually it's not a controversy because everybody wants a secure event,' he said.''</p>
        <p>Security guards yesterday confiscated six knives, a canister of mace and several beers. But Mr. Siegel said that the city's ad hoc approach left room for abuses, including racial profiling. He said safety could be achieved without drastic search measures and suggested that the City Council hold hearings to develop uniform guidelines.</p>
        <p>And he said it bothered him that many concertgoers welcomed the searches. ''The expectation of your civil liberties is lowered substantially because of events like this,'' he said. ''People lose their civil liberties in this incremental way.''</p>
        <p>But at Harris Park yesterday, many in the crowd, which included families with young children, said they appreciated the security. ''It's a good thing,'' said Maria Pabon. ''Nobody wants to get shot at. We came here to have fun.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
