<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y08BRI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220978"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4D8103CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="982" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Savannah Waring Walker</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>YUGOSLAVIA: TERROR CHARGES FOR 4 WESTERNERS -- The Yugoslav Army says it will press terrorism charges against two Canadians and two Britons arrested in Montenegro last week. Britain has described its two citizens, Adrian Prangnell and John Yore, as policemen helping to train a new force in Kosovo. They were traveling with the Canadians, Shaun Going, who also worked in Kosovo, and his nephew Liam Hall. Like many Westerners visiting Montenegro, the four did not have Yugoslav visas. Dutch officials are also seeking access to four of their nationals arrested some three weeks ago in Serbia and accused of plotting to kidnap President Slobodan Milosevic.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>YUGOSLAVIA: NEW MILOSEVIC CHALLENGER -- Formalizing the breach in opposition ranks and dimming chances of voting out Mr. Milosevic, a coalition chose a new challenger, Vojislav Kostunica, left, to run against him. Most opposition parties endorsed Mr. Kostunica, a moderate nationalist. But the Serbian Renewal Movement, the single largest opposition party, chose another candidate, the Belgrade mayor, Vojislav Mihajlovic.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>YUGOSLAVIA: TERROR CHARGES FOR 4 WESTERNERS -- The Yugoslav Army says it will press terrorism charges against two Canadians and two Britons arrested in Montenegro last week. Britain has described its two citizens, Adrian Prangnell and John Yore, as policemen helping to train a new force in Kosovo. They were traveling with the Canadians, Shaun Going, who also worked in Kosovo, and his nephew Liam Hall. Like many Westerners visiting Montenegro, the four did not have Yugoslav visas. Dutch officials are also seeking access to four of their nationals arrested some three weeks ago in Serbia and accused of plotting to kidnap President Slobodan Milosevic.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>YUGOSLAVIA: NEW MILOSEVIC CHALLENGER -- Formalizing the breach in opposition ranks and dimming chances of voting out Mr. Milosevic, a coalition chose a new challenger, Vojislav Kostunica, left, to run against him. Most opposition parties endorsed Mr. Kostunica, a moderate nationalist. But the Serbian Renewal Movement, the single largest opposition party, chose another candidate, the Belgrade mayor, Vojislav Mihajlovic.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: CHECHEN SAID TO SURRENDER -- Russia said a senior Chechen guerrilla, Ibragim Khultygov, had surrendered, a move heralded as evidence that the rebels were tiring of the 11-month-old war. Mr. Khultygov was described as the security chief in the Chechen government set up after Russia's defeat in the 1994-96 war. There was no rebel confirmation.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>ROMANIA: REFORMER TO RUN -- Theodor Stolojan, 56, a former prime minister and free-market reformer, announced that he would run for president in November against Ion Iliescu, the former Communist who was president until 1996. Mr. Iliescu served from 1990 to 1996, when he was beaten by Emil Constantinescu, the current head of state. Mr. Constantinescu's unexpected withdrawal last month left the governing coalition searching for a candidate.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>VENEZUELA: LEADER'S WORLD TOUR -- President Hugo Chavez has arrived in Saudi Arabia on the first leg of a tour that includes stops in every member nation of the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries. He said the main goal of his trip was to coordinate the details of an OPEC meeting in Caracas next month, but King Fahd said his country and Venezuela also wanted to continue limits on oil exports in order to maintain prices at $30 a barrel.</p>
        <p>Larry Rohter (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>INDIA: PRONOUNCEMENT ON KASHMIR -- Reassuring hard-liners, and perhaps straining the cease-fire process, Prime Minister Atal Behari Vajpayee told Parliament that while peace talks with one of Kashmir's militant groups were without conditions, no decision would be outside the framework of the Constitution -- which precludes the possibility of permitting Kashmir's secession from India.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>INDIA: FLOOD VICTIMS -- Flooding in eastern India has claimed more than 120 lives and left more than 2.5 million people homeless, authorities said. The state of Assam has been hardest hit.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>CHINA: INTERNET POLICE -- New police units will monitor the Internet, the official New China News Agency reported. Local governments in at least 20 Chinese provinces and cities have reportedly established groups to maintain order on computer networks. China is embracing the Internet for e-commerce but remains wary of its role in disseminating politically sensitive information. Internet experts say the country is fighting a losing battle trying to keep tabs on the country's Internet users, now 17 million strong.</p>
        <p>Craig S. Smith (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFGHANISTAN: TALIBAN FORCES ADVANCE -- Afghanistan's ruling Taliban movement progressed toward the opposition's main bastion of Taloqan after capturing a key northern town, Afghan sources said. Taliban forces were reported to have seized most of Bangi district, which leads to Taloqan, the capital of Takhar Province, one of the last two areas that are controlled by the rebel commander Ahmad Shah Masood.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: WITHDRAWAL OF ENVOYS -- Ehud Barak decided to replace Israel's envoys to Britain, France and South Africa, public radio reported, because they are loyalists of Foreign Minister David Levy, who quit Mr. Barak's government last week. The prime minister will replace Eliyahu Ben-Elisar, ambassador to Paris; Dror Zeigelman, ambassador to London; Uri Oren, ambassador to Pretoria; and Shmuel Sisso, consul general in New York. He also decided to replace the envoy to Switzerland, Yitzhak Meir, a member of the National Religious Party, which walked out of his coalition over peace negotiations last month.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>IRAN: PRESS CRACKDOWN -- Bolstered by an order on Sunday from Iran's supreme leader that undercut hopes of greater press freedom, hard-liners arrested a liberal journalist, Ahmad Zeidabadi, and shut down a reformist weekly newspaper, Cheshmeh Ardebil. The tension threatened to worsen a political rift between the supreme religious leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, and supporters of the reformist president, Mohammad Khatami. The president's supporters had pushed for laws guaranteeing greater press freedom, but debate on the legislation was by Ayatollah Khamenei's intervention.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>BURUNDI: REBEL AMBUSH -- Twenty-seven soldiers and five civilians were killed over the weekend in a rebel ambush near Bujumbura, Burundi's capital, casting a shadow over peace talks reconvening in Arusha, Tanzania. Most of the dead were officer cadets from the Higher Institute of Military Staff returning from a sporting event, military sources said.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
