<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israeli Rabbi Sets Off a Political Firestorm Over the Holocaust</title>
    <meta content="Y08ISRA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yosef, Ovadia (Rabbi)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burns, John F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E3D7103CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israeli Rabbi Sets Off a Political Firestorm Over the Holocaust</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burns, John F</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Aug. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rabbi Ovadia Yosef, 80-year-old spiritual leader of Shas Party which controls key bloc of 17 seats in Israel's 120-member Parliament outrages many Israelis by claiming in sermon that six million Jews who perished in the Holocaust died because they were reincarnations of sinners; later backtracks by calling victims pure and complete saints; despite angry outcry from rabbis, politicians and Jewish leaders worldwide, many voices in Israel dismiss remarks as ramblings of bellicose old man with long record of provocations; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 80-year-old spiritual leader of a major religious political party outraged many Israelis with a sermon over the weekend in which he said the six million Jews who perished in the Holocaust died because they were reincarnations of sinners, and he sought today to calm the storm.</p>
        <p>In a new sermon today, the spiritual leader, Rabbi Ovadia Yosef, offered no explicit apology for his remarks, made in a broadcast on Saturday. But the Baghdad-born rabbi, the pre-eminent figure in the Shas Party, which holds a key bloc of 17 seats in Israel's 120-member Parliament, appeared to backtrack from his earlier statement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 80-year-old spiritual leader of a major religious political party outraged many Israelis with a sermon over the weekend in which he said the six million Jews who perished in the Holocaust died because they were reincarnations of sinners, and he sought today to calm the storm.</p>
        <p>In a new sermon today, the spiritual leader, Rabbi Ovadia Yosef, offered no explicit apology for his remarks, made in a broadcast on Saturday. But the Baghdad-born rabbi, the pre-eminent figure in the Shas Party, which holds a key bloc of 17 seats in Israel's 120-member Parliament, appeared to backtrack from his earlier statement.</p>
        <p>''Six million Jews, among them one million children, were killed by the wicked Nazis,'' he said. '' All were holy and pure and complete saints.''</p>
        <p>The new sermon, carried like the earlier one by a party-controlled radio station and relayed by satellite overseas, contained no hint of contrition for remarks about the peace efforts that insulted Palestinians.</p>
        <p>The rabbi said on Saturday that Prime Minister Ehud Barak, by ''bringing snakes beside us'' with the compromises he had put forward at the recent Camp David talks, had demonstrated that he had ''no brains.''</p>
        <p>Despite the outcry from rabbis, politicians and Jewish leaders around the world, many voices in Israel dismissed the earlier remarks as the ramblings of a bellicose old man with a long record of provocations. A commentary today in Yediot Ahronot, the country's most widely circulated newspaper, described him as ''an aging political hack who has lost control of his tongue.''</p>
        <p>But other Israelis were less ready to dismiss the remarks, and not only because of the deep offense they caused. Rabbi Yosef remains important to the peace efforts, if only because his party of strictly observant Orthodox Jews may determine whether Mr. Barak succeeds in rebuilding his shattered coalition government.</p>
        <p>Even as the controversy raged, officials in Mr. Barak's Labor Party confirmed today that contacts were continuing to lure the Shas Party back into the governing coalition that began to disintegrate last month over the peace talks at Camp David.</p>
        <p>Shas and two other rightist parties quit in protest against Mr. Barak's peace plans, prompting other defections that have left the prime minister, by the estimate of many Israeli commentators, with the assured support of barely a third of Parliament.</p>
        <p>Some commentators said Mr. Barak, in careful comments on Sunday about Rabbi Yosef's Holocaust remarks, had pandered to the rabbi so as not to spoil the chances of Shas's rejoining the government, or at least backing efforts to revive peace talks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak said the remarks were unworthy of Rabbi Yosef's status, and added, ''His words could harm the memory of those who perished in the Holocaust and could hurt the feelings of their families and the feelings of the entire nation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak's restraint brought a chorus of criticism. ''Any pursuit by Ehud Barak of the blasphemous rabbi, from this moment on, should be considered as unconscionable kowtowing, as the abandonment of any semblance of self-respect and as groveling for the seats that will give this government another few months,'' said Shalom Yerushalmi, a columnist in Maariv, another major paper.</p>
        <p>As printed in today's English-language editions of the newspaper Haaretz, Rabbi Yosef said this: ''The six million Jews, all those poor people who were lost at the hands of those evil ones, the Nazis, may their names be blotted out -- was it for nothing? No. This was all the reincarnation of earlier souls, who sinned and caused others to sin and did all sorts of forbidden acts. They returned in reincarnation in order to set these things right, and received, those poor people, all those torments and troubles and deaths under which they were killed in the Holocaust.''</p>
        <p>Bannered in newspaper headlines and given top billing in radio and television newscasts, they became the principal talking point wherever Israelis gathered. Although Rabbi Yosef has been at the center of controversy before, commentators said they could recall no occasion in the country's 52 years of independence when an Israeli public figure had caused such an outcry.</p>
        <p>One of the harshest condemnations came from Yosef Lapid, 68, a member of Parliament and a Holocaust survivor whose father perished in a death camp. ''When I hear Rabbi Yosef's words, I feel that my father was murdered a second time,'' said Mr. Lapid, who is the leader of the secularist Shinui Party. ''If an important rabbi in Israel comes and says that six million Jews who died in the Holocaust were sinning souls, it's tantamount to his saying that Hitler was doing holy work.''</p>
        <p>Others saw the remarks as a reflection of the divisions between Ashkenazic Jews, whose families lived in Central and Eastern Europe, and Sephardic Jews, mainly from the Middle East and North Africa, whose political power has grown. Shas draws much of its support from working-class Sephardim, a fact alluded to by Mr. Lapid. ''It seems that Rabbi Yosef wanted to say that Ashkenazis sinned and that is why they died in the Holocaust,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Still others said they feared that the remarks could encourage anti-Semites who deny that the Holocaust occurred. Other critics saw Rabbi Yosef's remarks about Palestinians as an attempt to complicate the peace efforts further.</p>
        <p>But if the rabbi intended to impede the peace negotiations by insulting Palestinians, the signs today were that he had failed. Israel Radio and Agence France-Presse reported that Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, had told reporters in the Persian Gulf emirate of Abu Dhabi that President Clinton could set up a new summit meeting after the Democratic Party convention ends on Aug. 17.</p>
        <p>But officials in Mr. Barak's office, quoted today by Israel Radio, said it was ''premature'' to talk of a new summit meeting. An American official with firsthand knowledge of the Camp David talks said the United States would not be ready to call a new summit meeting without ''an indication that something has changed'' in the negotiating stands of the two sides.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
