<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Interests; High Noon at Gore Gap</title>
    <meta content="08COLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220973"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Gail</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Gail Collins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1D9103CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Interests; High Noon at Gore Gap</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GAIL COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Gail</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gail Collins Op-Ed column on Sen Joseph Lieberman says he is perfect match as running mate for Vice Pres Al Gore; notes Lieberman's low key style and ability to rise above party politics; recalls his years in Connecticut legislature (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>My early years in journalism were spent searching for colorful things to say about Joseph Lieberman.</p>
        <p>I have here a list of the best and worst members of the Connecticut state legislature circa 1978. Mr. Lieberman was sixth-best. Most of the people who came in ahead of him are either dead or lobbyists, so when it came to potential running mates from the Nutmeg State, Al Gore pretty much got the pick of the litter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>My early years in journalism were spent searching for colorful things to say about Joseph Lieberman.</p>
        <p>I have here a list of the best and worst members of the Connecticut state legislature circa 1978. Mr. Lieberman was sixth-best. Most of the people who came in ahead of him are either dead or lobbyists, so when it came to potential running mates from the Nutmeg State, Al Gore pretty much got the pick of the litter.</p>
        <p>Connecticut magazine compiled the list, but I was in charge of the lively prose. This is the lead I came up with: ''Senate Majority Leader Joseph Lieberman is a man who's given a whole new meaning to the term 'low key.' '' In another profile, I noted that the then 35-year-old Mr. Lieberman was one of those guys who look middle-aged at 30, and would still look middle-aged at 80. He's become fond of quoting that in recent years.</p>
        <p>This is one laid-back Democrat, a subtle mix of interesting and boring that solves almost all the main problems facing Al Gore except how to get anybody to listen to the convention speeches. It's a perfect match. Mr. Gore can be stiff but not pompous. Mr. Lieberman can be pompous but not stiff. And who else would qualify as a compelling, thinking-outside-the-box choice without looking more exciting than the top of the ticket?</p>
        <p>The running-mate-to-be seemed positively giddy yesterday afternoon, and giddy is not normally one of his adjectives. ''I can't think of a place I'd rather be at this momentous time of my life than with you, the working people of Connecticut,'' he told a convention of the state A.F.L.-C.I.O. in Hartford. Then he launched into reminiscences of Connecticut labor leaders of yore, the late Gov. Ella Grasso, his parents and his salad days in the State Senate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman won his first race  when he was only 28, so the 10 years he spent as a state senator shaped him as a politician. It was a peculiar time in Connecticut history. Every state legislature has a moment when it gets golden. (Well, maybe not Alabama.) You hit a stretch where the people who get elected seem unusually smart, and the good-government tools like open meetings and public hearings and full floor debates actually work the way they're supposed to. Connecticut was golden like that in the 1970's, and the result was a rather extraordinary level of bipartisanship that seems to have marked Mr. Lieberman for life.</p>
        <p>''There was a great deal of civility there. we had open caucuses and the Democrats came into our caucus room to discuss tax policy,'' said Lewis Rome, a lawyer who was Senate minority leader at the time and calls the senator ''a moral force.'' (Mr. Rome, by the way, finished first in that best-legislator poll.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman's ability to rise above party politics is his biggest strength as a legislator, and he probably couldn't have learned it if he'd spent his formative years in the House of Representatives of the 1990's. ''If he has any detractors in the Senate it's because of his bipartisanship,'' said Senator Charles Schumer of New York, who describes Mr. Lieberman as ''almost a Gary Cooper type in the Senate.'' (Becoming the first Jewish candidate on a national ticket is nice. But every male politician's fantasy is being called the Gary Cooper of the Senate.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman has been much more daring as a U.S. senator than he was when he was younger. He used to have one of those careful, work-your-way-up careers. He lost a bid to become lieutenant governor,  then ran for Congress in 1980. He was defeated by Larry DeNardis, the current president of the University of New Haven, who recalls that the campaign was so issue-oriented even the League of Women Voters got tired of hearing them debate.</p>
        <p>He became attorney general and then made the first big, risky move of his career in 1988 when he ran against Senator Lowell Weicker. ''Before a big speech he'd drop down and do push-ups to get his blood running,'' said Marla Romash, who was the campaign communications director.</p>
        <p>This is an excellent potential bonding tool for the campaign, in which Al Gore is known to do stomach crunches during long flights. Perhaps instead of the traditional post-convention whistle-stop tour, they could travel from one athletic field to another. In your heart, you know they're fit.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
