<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yanks Get Canseco, but the Question Is Why?</title>
    <meta content="08JOSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Devil Rays</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Canseco, Jose</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knoblauch, Chuck</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sojo, Luis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Ryan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0D6103CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1301" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yanks Get Canseco, but the Question Is Why?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees acquire Jose Canseco on waivers from Tampa Bay Devil Rays, apparently to keep him off rival team; place Chuck Knoblauch on disabled list; re-acquire Luis Sojo in trade; will drop Ryan Thompson from roster; tables of team turnover and of Canseco's career statistics; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees wanted Jose Canseco in the past and could not get him. They finally got him yesterday, acquiring the slugger on waivers. But they don't really want him or need him; they just wanted to make sure he wasn't going to play for somebody else.</p>
        <p>Canseco, beset by injuries in his career, is a struggling 36-year-old designated hitter who cannot be used in the outfield because of defensive deficiencies. The trouble is, the Yankees might have as many as five players who would be most effectively deployed as a designated hitter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees wanted Jose Canseco in the past and could not get him. They finally got him yesterday, acquiring the slugger on waivers. But they don't really want him or need him; they just wanted to make sure he wasn't going to play for somebody else.</p>
        <p>Canseco, beset by injuries in his career, is a struggling 36-year-old designated hitter who cannot be used in the outfield because of defensive deficiencies. The trouble is, the Yankees might have as many as five players who would be most effectively deployed as a designated hitter.</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre, who gushed over the previous deals for Denny Neagle and David Justice, was far more reticent about this move. ''I'm a little stunned,'' he said after the Yankees' 8-5 loss to Seattle yesterday afternoon, their third straight defeat. ''I'm a little surprised. I don't have an opinion one way or another.''</p>
        <p>Torre was asked how much Canseco will be used. ''I don't know,'' he said, without elaborating.</p>
        <p>George Steinbrenner, the Yankees' principal owner, said of his executives: ''I think they got caught up in something they didn't think about, but I'm behind my people. I'm totally supportive of what they did. I'm happy the man is coming here, and I'm hoping he does the job for me.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees, meanwhile, placed second baseman Chuck Knoblauch on the disabled list because of inflammation in his right elbow, reacquired the veteran utility infielder Luis Sojo in a trade and will take outfielder Ryan Thompson off the 25-man roster. Canseco and Sojo are expected to arrive before tonight's game against Oakland.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, the Yankees have added Justice, Neagle, designated hitter Glenallen Hill, outfielder Luis Polonia, infielder Jose Vizcaino and pitcher Dwight Gooden. Now they have a spare part named Canseco. ''I think I can play shortstop, and a little bit of third base,'' Canseco said. ''I really don't know how I'm going to fit in there.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees paid $20,000 for Canseco, who has 440 career homers,  after claiming him on waivers from the Tampa Bay Devil Rays. The Yankees will also pay a little less than $1 million in salary for this season, as well as incentive payments he might soon achieve. These are the costs for the Yankees' procedural aggressiveness, for placating the championship obsession of Steinbrenner, who has been particularly interested in Canseco in recent years.</p>
        <p>Canseco hammered 46 homers for Toronto in 1998 and 34 homers in 113 games for Tampa Bay last year, in a season cut short by back surgery,  and has not been the same player since. He averaged one homer for every 14.85 at-bats before the operation. He has averaged one homer every 26.8 at-bats and a strikeout for every 3.4 at-bats since then.</p>
        <p>But he has been a huge star in his controversial career, and Steinbrenner loves stars. When the Yankees were struggling for offense in late May, Steinbrenner asked the Yankees' officials if it would be worthwhile to acquire Canseco. Tampa Bay's asking price was high and the Yankees turned elsewhere, trying to deal for Juan Gonzalez and Sammy Sosa before eventually getting Justice.</p>
        <p>Shane Spencer wrecked his knee the day before the All-Star Game break, however, and the Yankees were back in the market for a right-handed hitter. Before getting Hill on July 23, General Manager Brian Cashman called Chuck LaMar, the general manager of the Devil Rays, and asked if Canseco was available. LaMar repeated his high demand, and Cashman traded for Hill, who has been highly effective, banging four homers in 25 at-bats, including a solo shot in yesterday's loss to the Mariners.</p>
        <p>After the July 31 trade deadline, teams began filling the waiver wire with players; no player can be traded in August or September unless he is sent to the team that makes the claim, or unless he has cleared waivers. As always, Cashman aggressively placed claims, some because the Yankees have a genuine interest in a player, and some because they wanted to prevent players from going to another team.</p>
        <p>Tampa Bay placed Canseco on waivers last Thursday. The order of waiver claims is based on won-loss records, worst to best, and the Yankees were 11th among 29 teams, with Oakland, Seattle and the Chicago White Sox picking behind them. Teams submit waiver claims on the same day without knowing if another team has placed a claim.</p>
        <p>So Cashman had to weigh the pluses and minuses of claiming Canseco. If Cashman passed on Canseco, then there was a chance a team with a better record could land him or that he could clear waivers and be traded to a Yankee rival, such as Toronto. If that happened, Steinbrenner presumably would have been apoplectic.</p>
        <p>If Cashman gambled and claimed Canseco, then Tampa Bay could choose to withdraw Canseco from waivers and keep him, thereby making it impossible for the Devil Rays to trade him the rest of the season. The Devil Rays' other option was to simply let the Yankees keep Canseco. Last year, the Yankees placed a claim on Chicago's Frank Thomas, and for a couple of days, the White Sox debated whether to give Thomas, with his huge contract, to the Yankees before they withdrew him from waivers just before the deadline.</p>
        <p>So Cashman decided to place a claim on Canseco, along with 47 other claims, and on Friday, LaMar called to tell him the Yankees had the pre-eminent claim. For two days, the Yankees rebuffed LaMar's requests to work out a trade, probably in the hope that LaMar would keep Canseco.</p>
        <p>But LaMar called Cashman at 11 a.m. yesterday to say he was giving Canseco to the Yankees. Torre learned about the transaction just before the start of the game yesterday and was surprised. A cameraman told Derek Jeter about the move just before the start of the game. Reliever Mike Stanton, a former teammate of Canseco, heard the news while listening to the game on the radio in the clubhouse, and when Stanton went to the bullpen in the fifth inning, he told the other relievers.</p>
        <p>Canseco was a controversial figure in the early part of his career, but he has matured and will not likely threaten the Yankees' chemistry. But now Torre must figure out a way to use Canseco. The manager's preference is for Justice to be his designated hitter, to save the wear and tear on his legs, a priority considering that Justice has hit 29 homers this year. Torre can't use Canseco without playing Justice in the outfield. He can't play Canseco without benching Hill. To make room for Canseco, the Yankees had to dump Thompson, who is their only true backup center fielder.</p>
        <p>Unless Torre completely diminishes Hill's role, it would seem Canseco's primary job will be as a pinch-hitter. The Yankees also have the option of trying to pass Canseco through waivers and unloading him, and even if Cashman doesn't want Canseco, then he will at least have the luxury of sending him to a particular destination. ''We'll see how he does,'' Cashman said. ''He might wind up playing a key role.''</p>
        <p>''We all know what Jose Canseco is capable of,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Canseco's salary is $3 million for this year, and he will receive $175,000 if he reaches 300 plate appearances, $175,000 more if he reaches 350 plate appearances, $200,000 for 400 plate appearances and $250,000 for 450 plate appearances. There is a club option for 2001, at $4 million.</p>
        <p>Canseco is nearing 300 plate appearances but may not get many more, playing for a team that really doesn't want or need him.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
