<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shoplifting on a Grand Scale: Luxury Wear Stolen to Order</title>
    <meta content="08DRES$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220975"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shoplifting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Eastern States (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trebay, Guy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E7D8103CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shoplifting on a Grand Scale: Luxury Wear Stolen to Order</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUY TREBAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Trebay, Guy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Law enforcement officials see rise in shoplifting of luxury apparel; say semiorganized crime syndicates, many of them South American, have begun operating along East Coast in urban centers and at upscale suburban malls; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From the look of it, a person with identity issues had done some heavy shopping. Tossed on a bed in a Brooklyn apartment were a $600 Vuitton Broadway satchel, two $600 burgundy quilted polyester nylon skirts from Chanel, a $545 scarf with the block-lettered Chanel logo worked into the weave and two pairs of blunt-toed $425 Prada Nero shoes for men. None of the garments matched. But that did not matter. The apartment was a way station on a convoluted route of distribution, and the clothes did not yet have owners. Unless, that is, you count the retailers they were stolen from.</p>
        <p>''These are going right out to Manhattan,'' said Angie E., a transgendered person who pilfers clothing for a living. The apartment is hers. ''I use this fence in the diamond district,'' Ms. E said. ''There's two brothers. They're the ones that sell it. I just mop the stuff and get my little cut.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From the look of it, a person with identity issues had done some heavy shopping. Tossed on a bed in a Brooklyn apartment were a $600 Vuitton Broadway satchel, two $600 burgundy quilted polyester nylon skirts from Chanel, a $545 scarf with the block-lettered Chanel logo worked into the weave and two pairs of blunt-toed $425 Prada Nero shoes for men. None of the garments matched. But that did not matter. The apartment was a way station on a convoluted route of distribution, and the clothes did not yet have owners. Unless, that is, you count the retailers they were stolen from.</p>
        <p>''These are going right out to Manhattan,'' said Angie E., a transgendered person who pilfers clothing for a living. The apartment is hers. ''I use this fence in the diamond district,'' Ms. E said. ''There's two brothers. They're the ones that sell it. I just mop the stuff and get my little cut.''</p>
        <p>Mopping, or shoplifting, is no new development on the retail scene. But large-scale shoplifting of luxury goods to order may be. Although criminal law does not distinguish between shoplifting and other kinds of larceny, law enforcement officials say that theft to order of luxury brands appears to be a growth sector. ''They're going for the upscale stores,'' said Joe Morrash, a detective assigned to a stolen-property task force with the Alexandria, Va., police. ''They're stealing in volume and selling to fences and underground boutiques.'' At one drab single-family home in Queens, Detective Morrash said, the New York police uncovered over $500,000 in stolen clothes in 1998. ''The inside looked like Macy's,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Macy's isn't the only target of enterprising thieves. As label culture signals social arrival, even crooks are getting into the act. ''It's a society where everybody's got their Fendi and their Chanel and their Vuitton,'' said Gerald Dupree, 39, a Brooklyn maintenance worker who said he left a career as a semiprofessional shoplifter when he broke a longtime heroin habit four years ago. ''You've got to keep pace.''</p>
        <p>It is a breathtaking pace. In a survey conducted by the University of Florida, retail ''shrinkage'' -- as shoplifting is euphemistically called in the business -- was shown to have caused losses exceeding $8.9 billion in 1997, the last year for which figures are available.</p>
        <p>Recently, police officials say, an increasing number of semiorganized crime syndicates, many of them South American, have been operating along the Eastern Seaboard, in urban centers and at upscale suburban malls. ''It's not normal shoplifting anymore, where they're stealing one or two items,'' said Andrew McColl, a Washington-based agent for the Federal Bureau of Investigation, who heads a task force on property crime. ''They're going for the leather coats, the luxury items. The last arrest we made at Tysons Corner mall here, they had $100,000 in goods.''</p>
        <p>It is not hard to imagine running up a total like that when you consider the tagged prices of what the thieves are now after. ''You can order a Chanel suit in size 10, and there are people who can mop it and fences who have the goods,'' Mr. Dupree said. Such suits typically cost around $4,000.</p>
        <p>Angie E. is a thief whose audacity has led her, by her own account, to steal satchels from Louis Vuitton, baguette bags from Fendi, shoes from Prada and scarves from Hermes, things that are often kept in glass cases or under lock and key. She is, as Mr. Dupree said, ''one of the ever-famous fierce girdle bandits of New York,'' a term referring to the practice of stuffing stolen goods into underclothes. ''One thief I know put a whole mink in a girdle,'' Mr. Dupree asserted. Another, he said, would ''go into a jewelry counter and, you know how they have chains hanging on display racks?'' He paused. ''She could just lift the chains up all at once and drop them down her sleeves.''</p>
        <p>At Saks Fifth Avenue last week a salesman said, ''If you don't nail it down, they're going to take it.'' He was recounting an episode in July, when a woman grabbed six $200 Coach bags from a counter near the main Fifth Avenue exit and bolted. Although the bags were equipped with acoustomagnetic sensors, designed to trigger an alarm, that did not serve as a deterrent. ''Do you think they care about the sensors?'' asked the salesman, who, like most of the retailers I interviewed, did not want to be identified. ''They're in, they're out, it's fast. Who's going to chase them for the bags? The bags are insured.''</p>
        <p>The subject of shoplifting is an abiding taboo. Only one of a dozen luxury store managers in Manhattan I spoke to would consent to discuss shrinkage on the record. The response of Ellen Hopfinger, manager of the Versace store on Fifth Avenue, was typical. ''It's not something we would ever talk about,'' Ms. Hopfinger said. ''I used to work at another luxury store, Armani, and no one talks about it, ever.''</p>
        <p>The reasons are various, explained Bruce Van Kleek, a member of the Loss Prevention Advisory Council at the National Retail Federation. ''It points to internal problems, high turnover, people coming and going all the time,'' he said. Public admissions about shoplifting problems can also, of course, give potential thieves a heads up.</p>
        <p>''It's sick that you have to write about these things,'' said Stephanie Greenfield, a retailer who attributes a low level of shrinkage at her two Scoop stores in Manhattan to security guards posted at every entrance. Still, she said: ''It's going to happen. Look at the economy. Everybody wants stuff. I don't think it's only people who can't afford it. I think there's a prejudice that people don't steal on all class levels, all income levels. There's a mistake people make only looking at one type of crowd.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Van Kleek added that shoplifters ''come in all shapes and sizes, from the 10-year-old stealing a comic book to sophisticated criminal gangs.'' The innovation, Detective Morrash said, is that inroads are being made on the luxury goods trade by professional gangs with greater levels of sophistication and, yes, of taste. ''The South Americans are only doing upscale stores now,'' he said. ''The Limited, Nordstrom, Lord &amp; Taylor, Bloomingdale's.''</p>
        <p>Goods obtained by one Chilean syndicate, the Washington police reported, were later used to stock a ''legitimate'' Los Angeles boutique. ''We had six guys who'd stolen $150,000 in three days,'' Detective Morrash said. ''They move around the major cities like L.A., New York, Washington and Chicago.''</p>
        <p>They rent hotel rooms and getaway cars. They use sophisticated signaling methods as they go into department stores, to rake designer clothes into bags. One group compiled a written manual for its ''contractors,'' advising them on the fine points of shoplifting both on and off the sales floor. ''Never wander around with any of the pieces you are planning to take,'' read a copy of these guidelines that I obtained, ''because not only will the salespeople want to help you or hold them for you or put them in a dressing room for you, all of which defeat your purpose, but it gives security a chance to count how many you have.''</p>
        <p>For all that, the method remains simple. ''Why worry about alarms going off or electronic tags or radio tags?'' Detective Morrash asked. ''Speed is what makes them successful. They can get in and roll the merchandise up and run before anyone knows.''</p>
        <p>By the time an alarm sounds, most professional thieves are gone. In Manhattan particularly, where shoppers are made uneasy by excessive security and surveillance, shoplifters often have preferred exits from their favorite stores. ''The Madison Avenue side of Barneys,'' Ms. E. said, citing an example. ''The Fifth Avenue entrance to Saks. I did a job at Pink's,'' the London shirtmaker with a branch on Madison Avenue and 53rd Street. ''They had $165 Sea Island shirts and a side door with nobody around,'' she continued. ''I got six. Everybody's always complaining that they can't find anyone to wait on them. I say: 'Thank you. Let's keep it that way.' ''</p>
        <p>An assistant manager at Pink, who would not give his name, responded, ''That's sad, but that's New York.''</p>
        <p>Shoplifters have been known to line shopping bags with foil or duct tape to thwart sensors. But Mr. Van Kleek of the retail federation said that the spate of successful theft owed less to cunning than to new levels of brazenness.</p>
        <p>It is a view that Mr. Dupree, the former thief, confirmed. The secret of success, he said, is a formula that rings of business motivational seminars: ''You go in there thinking, 'This is mine and I'm taking it with me.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
