<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Named After a Dish, It's a Spicy Carnival</title>
    <meta content="08KITC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220953"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lincoln Center Out of Doors Festival</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pareles, Jon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5DB103CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Named After a Dish, It's a Spicy Carnival</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jon Pareles reviews third annual Kitchrie, a concert of music and dance developed by indentured laborers from India in the Caribbean, at Damrosch Park, part of Lincoln Center Out of Doors; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nobody can resist a carnival for long, or so it seemed at Kitchrie 2000 on Sunday night at Damrosch Park.</p>
        <p>When indentured laborers from India went to Trinidad, Guyana and Suriname in the second half of the 19th century, they brought traditional music and dance with them. And under the Caribbean sun, where Indians lived alongside Africans and Europeans, those traditions went through changes, taking on new rhythms and earthier moves. The fusion made its way into traditionalist concert music and dance, a style called tan sangeet, and went on to spawn its own carnival music, chutney.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nobody can resist a carnival for long, or so it seemed at Kitchrie 2000 on Sunday night at Damrosch Park.</p>
        <p>When indentured laborers from India went to Trinidad, Guyana and Suriname in the second half of the 19th century, they brought traditional music and dance with them. And under the Caribbean sun, where Indians lived alongside Africans and Europeans, those traditions went through changes, taking on new rhythms and earthier moves. The fusion made its way into traditionalist concert music and dance, a style called tan sangeet, and went on to spawn its own carnival music, chutney.</p>
        <p>Both were on the program on Sunday night for the third annual Kitchrie, which is named after a spicy Caribbean dish. As part of Lincoln Center Out of Doors, it was presented by the Caribbean Cultural Center, working with another New York City organization, the Rajkumari Cultural Center.</p>
        <p>Tan sangeet looks back to northern  Indian classical and folk music. Its songs are sung in Hindi and refer to deities like Ganesh and Krishna. They alternate between sustained improvisatory passages, with voice and harmonium trading elaborate phrases, and straightforwardly catchy melodies for voice, sitar and harmonium, pushed along by rhythms from the two-headed dholak hand drum.</p>
        <p>In some of the songs, performed by an ensemble including the singers and harmonium players Sampat Dino Boodram and Errol Balkissoon, the odd meters of Indian tradition survived; others bounced along in 4/ 4 time, with strutting rhythms augmented by the dhantal, a metal rod like an unbent triangle. Often, two dhantals supplied brisk syncopations -- like the brake drums used in Trinidadian steel-drum bands -- while the dholak improvised, responding to the voice and the beat as in Indian music.</p>
        <p>The dances are based in Kathak tradition, with quick footwork, delicately traced arm gestures and ethereal twirls; four dancers, choreographed by Romanee Kalicharan, moved together like a chorus line with short solo interludes. Radha Singh sweetly sang a song in which the divine Radha complained to her consort Lord Krishna that his flute playing was driving her crazy; it was a graceful dance duet that, in the couple's echoed motions, suggested she didn't mind all that much. Under the African influence, Indo-Caribbean dance movement descended to torso and hips. As the music moved toward chutney, Denyse Baboolal shimmied, pumped her hips, even rolled on the stage.</p>
        <p>A chutney band, the Angels, took over for the second part of the concert, joined for one song by a group of drummers and dancers from Ghana. Their songs were soca (soul-calypso) tunes about winin' and grynin': winding and grinding the hips in Carnival revelry. And while a drum machine supplied the soca beat, Indian elements were embedded in the music and on top of it. The Angels' singers, two men, growled and belted like other soca singers, but some of their lyrics were in Hindi; their percussionist switched between congas and dholak, with sputtering cross-rhythms above the soca beat. Two guest singers, Ms. Singh and a leading chutney singer, Ramrajie Prabhoo, also sang with the Angels.</p>
        <p>In Indian style they sang at the top of their range, with airy tone and unpercussive phrasing, using microtonal South Asian flourishes. But Ms. Prabhoo worked her hips and instructed listeners to ''drop your waist and win','' with Ms. Baboolal by her side showing just how to do it. Unfortunately, the Angels had spent so much time exhorting the audience to get up and dance -- which was discouraged by Lincoln Center's security until the whole crowd rose at once -- that Ms. Prabhoo ended up compressing her songs into a 10-minute medley.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
