<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Portugal's Dinosaurs Get Their Due at Last</title>
    <meta content="08PORT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220945"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Portugal</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Howe, Marvine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Portugal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Portugal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E3DC103CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1551" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Portugal's Dinosaurs Get Their Due at Last</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARVINE HOWE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Howe, Marvine</byline>
      <dateline>LISBON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Portuguese government is acting to protect country's rich array of dinosaur fossils and tracks, which are threatened now by forces of erosion and development; until now, people who unearth a dinosaur egg or even a complete skeleton in Portugal are not obliged to inform authorities and may dispose of them any way they wish; Portuguese have been aware of large fossil footprints on certain cliffs since Middle Ages but gave them religious significance; there has been a surge of fossil discoveries from Late Jurassic in what is known as Lusitanian Basin along Atlantic coast; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the urging of eminent Portuguese paleontologists, the government is acting to protect the country's rich array of dinosaur fossils and tracks, threatened now by the forces of erosion and development.</p>
        <p>Many of the fossils turned up along the Atlantic coast of Portugal. Among recent finds were a dinosaur nest with scores of eggs, several containing embryos; a skull with well-preserved neck vertebrae of a theropod, a carnivorous bipedal dinosaur;  and the world's longest track way left by sauropods, giant plant eaters that walked on all fours. But dinosaur fossils and tracks have long been noticed there, though people did not always realize what they were.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the urging of eminent Portuguese paleontologists, the government is acting to protect the country's rich array of dinosaur fossils and tracks, threatened now by the forces of erosion and development.</p>
        <p>Many of the fossils turned up along the Atlantic coast of Portugal. Among recent finds were a dinosaur nest with scores of eggs, several containing embryos; a skull with well-preserved neck vertebrae of a theropod, a carnivorous bipedal dinosaur;  and the world's longest track way left by sauropods, giant plant eaters that walked on all fours. But dinosaur fossils and tracks have long been noticed there, though people did not always realize what they were.</p>
        <p>Prominent paleontologists like Martin G. Lockley of the University of Colorado, Philippe Taquet of the Museum of Natural History in Paris, Jose Bonaparte of the Argentine Museum of Natural Sciences have recognized the exceptional value of these fossils and have worked with Portuguese scientists on a number of scientific papers in connection with these discoveries.</p>
        <p>''Portugal is a showcase for dinosaur resources now that we know they have good bones, tracks, eggs and embryos,'' Professor Lockley said in an interview during the International Dinosaur Conference in Lisbon in 1998. He pointed out that tracks and the vertebrate record ''are very sparse globally'' from the Middle Jurassic -- 175 million years ago -- and, until recently, there were surprisingly few reports of well-preserved track ways from the Late Jurassic or 145 million years ago.</p>
        <p>''Up to present, there exists a legal void concerning our paleontological resources,'' Prof. Miguel Telles Antunes of the Nova University at Lisbon, who heads the scientific group, said in an interview last month. For example, he said, people who unearth a dinosaur egg or even a complete skeleton in Portugal are not obliged to inform the authorities and may dispose of them any way they wish.</p>
        <p>To remedy the situation, Jose Mariano Gago, minister of science and technology, said in an interview that the government planned to set up a National Council for Paleontology under his ministry by October. The government is also studying proposals for the establishment of museums to protect the most important track sites.</p>
        <p>Finally, paleontology, including studies on the protection of paleontological resources, has been established as a new separate research field with financing from the National Science Foundation. Portuguese scientists have complained that despite the national wealth in fossils, paleontology and paleobiology of dinosaur studies were limited to a couple of hours in connection with a master's degree in biology.</p>
        <p>Actually, the Portuguese have been aware of large fossil footprints on certain cliffs since the Middle Ages but had given them a religious significance. For example, according to a 13th century legend, footprints up the steep cliff at Cape Espichel, south of Lisbon, were made by a giant mule that rescued the Virgin from Lagosteiros Bay and carried her up the steep cliff to safety. A popular shrine to Our Lady of the Mule was built at the cape.</p>
        <p>In 1976, Professor Antunes identified the footprints as those of a giant theropod of the Late Jurassic Portlandian age. In fact, he said, the Lagosteiros cliffs are one of the richest sites in Europe for dinosaur tracks from the Lower Cretaceous, about 70 million years ago.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, there has been a surge of fossil discoveries from the Late Jurassic, 145 million years ago, in what is known as the Lusitanian Basin.</p>
        <p>Lourinha, an ancient farm town near the coast, is the site of the most impressive fossil discoveries and its small museum, established in 1980, contains the most varied and best-preserved paleontological collection in the country. Lourinha is also the home of the Ethnological and Archeological Group of Lourinha, known by its Portuguese acronym as GEAL (pronounced JAY-al). Like the museum, GEAL was formed by the Mateus family (no relation to the wine producers).</p>
        <p>It was Isabel Mateus, an amateur speleologist, who made a major discovery in 1993 on a seaside cliff at Paimogo, north of Lourinha, when she chanced upon a large cluster of eggs while walking with her 3-year-old daughter, Marta.</p>
        <p>She immediately recognized the black oval eggs as belonging to dinosaurs, even though they were largely broken into fragments.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Mateus, her husband, Horacio, a retired government tax employee, their son Octavio, a biology student, and a number of villagers painstakingly excavated and cleaned six large blocks containing more than 100 eggs. In the process, over three summers, they found some eggs with embryos and many tiny bones, adult theropod teeth and fragments of three crocodile-like eggs.</p>
        <p>Later with help from Professor Antunes and Professor Taquet, the Mateuses identified the Paimogo eggs as theropod remains, dating from the Upper Jurassic and resembling those found in the Upper Jurassic of Colorado.</p>
        <p>''With the Paimogo discovery, we have the extremely rare opportunity to correlate a shell morphotype with taxonomically identified dinosaur bones,'' Professor Taquet said at Lisbon's First International Meeting on Dinosaur Paleobiology in 1998. He called the clutches ''exceptional'' because dinosaur eggs in Jurassic beds are very rare, generally come in smaller clutches of 12 to 24 eggs and rarely contain embryos.</p>
        <p>Now studying for a doctorate in paleontology, with a fellowship from Nova, Octavio Mateus, 25, is trying to determine if there is a relationship between the eggs and the incomplete skeleton of a theropod found earlier by a local farmer. An exuberant fossil-hunter, Octavio also supervises dozens of volunteers in summer fieldwork and handles foreign relations for GEAL.</p>
        <p>His sister Marta, now 11, is a born fossil-hunter and came upon a well-preserved theropod skull in hard sandstone near Lourinha in 1997, which is still under study.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile Horacio Mateus, 50, runs the museum and is organizing a nationwide campaign to promote it.  ''We dream of creating a great museum of natural history in Lourinha,'' Mr. Mateus said in an interview. He said the existing museum was filled with specimens from the region.</p>
        <p>Before Paimogo appeared on the world's paleontological map, Portugal had attracted international attention with the discovery of several important dinosaur track sites. The most spectacular tracks -- and the only site organized for visits -- are those in Serra d'Aire Park, near the Roman Catholic sanctuary of Fatima. A score of long track ways with some 1,000 giant elliptical footprints can be seen clearly on the floor of a limestone quarry, as if a herd of dinsaurs had passed through only yesterday.</p>
        <p>Classified as a natural monument in 1996, the Fatima site includes the longest known sauropod track way in the world, measuring 147 meters. The track makers have been identified as brontosaurs, which go back 175 million years. At that age, according to Professor Lockley, they are ''the oldest known wide-gauge sauropod footprints.''</p>
        <p>Vanda dos Santos, 32, a Portuguese geologist who has worked with Professor Lockley, told the paleobiology conference that there were at least 20 Jurassic sites with sauropod track ways in Portugal, or one-third of the world's total known Jurassic sites.</p>
        <p>Cretaceous track sites are less significant in Portugal, she said, except for the Carenque track way, which is one of the longest in Europe at 141 meters.</p>
        <p>What is known as the Battle of Carenque took place in 1992, after it was found that dinosaur tracks lay in the path of a highway construction project in a Lisbon suburb. Two tunnels were built for the highway under the tracks, at great cost.</p>
        <p>The tracks are covered with latex until a museum is built over them.</p>
        <p>The 1998 International Dinosaur Conference designated Portugal as a productive field for paleontological studies. John R. Horner, a conference participant from Montana who found the first eggs with embryos in the United States in the late 1970's, emphasized the importance of the Paimogo eggs, which he said were the first dinosaur eggs with embryos found in Europe and provided valuable material for research.</p>
        <p>A conference organizer, Galopim de Carvalho, who heads the Natural History Museum, paid tribute to the foreign specialists ''who have come here to do what we cannot do for lack of means.'' He urgently appealed to the authorities to develop paleontological studies and provide museums for the most important track sites, like the Fatima site, which could be lost if not protected.</p>
        <p>While the Portuguese are working out ways to protect their paleontological treasures, help could come from the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, or Unesco. Science and Technology Minister Gago announced that ''general agreement'' had been reached with Unesco to name a Portuguese site as a Geoparque, a classification created last year for the protection of natural resources.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
