<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bear Stearns Settles Case Accusing It of Bad Advice</title>
    <meta content="Y08BEA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cadnetix Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bear Stearns Cos</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daisy Systems Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E3DC113CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bear Stearns Settles Case Accusing It of Bad Advice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bear Stearns Companies pays $30 million to settle lawsuit over its role as adviser to Daisy Systems Corp in its ill-fated purchase of Cadnetix Inc in 1989; in 1998, a jury in California awarded $108 million in damages to shareholders of both companies, which are now defunct; a judge reduced that to $36 million (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bear Stearns Companies has closed the books on one of the darker chapters in its history as an investment bank by writing a check for $30 million.</p>
        <p>Bear Stearns, the sixth-biggest United States securities firm, paid that amount to settle a lawsuit over its role as an adviser on an ill-fated takeover, lawyers involved in the case said yesterday. The case sent tremors through Wall Street two years ago when a federal jury in California found the firm was negligent in the way it advised its client, the Daisy Systems Corporation, on a 1989 purchase of Cadnetix Inc.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bear Stearns Companies has closed the books on one of the darker chapters in its history as an investment bank by writing a check for $30 million.</p>
        <p>Bear Stearns, the sixth-biggest United States securities firm, paid that amount to settle a lawsuit over its role as an adviser on an ill-fated takeover, lawyers involved in the case said yesterday. The case sent tremors through Wall Street two years ago when a federal jury in California found the firm was negligent in the way it advised its client, the Daisy Systems Corporation, on a 1989 purchase of Cadnetix Inc.</p>
        <p>The jury awarded $108 million in damages to the shareholders of the two companies, both of which are now defunct. That was easily the biggest award against an investment bank for giving bad advice in a merger or acquisition, and it held up other bankers' opinions to the scrutiny of jurors, securities law experts said.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for the creditors of Daisy Systems, a software company, had argued that Bear Stearns contributed to the failure of the companies by telling them that it was ''highly confident'' that it could line up financing for the highly leveraged transaction, said John Coffee, a law professor at Columbia University, who testified as an expert witness in the original trial. When the firm failed to arrange bank loans, Daisy Systems had to borrow at interest rates higher than it could afford, Mr. Coffee said.</p>
        <p>The judge later reduced the award to $36 million, but Bear Stearns and the bankruptcy trustee for Daisy Systems appealed that decision. Then, as those appeals headed for a midsummer hearing, Bear Stearns agreed to settle the case for even less. It paid $30 million and withdrew a bankruptcy court claim for $2.5 million in investment banking fees, said J. Thomas Hannan, a lawyer in San Francisco for the trustee.</p>
        <p>''It's a lot better than paying out $108 million -- and they had use of the money for two years,'' said James Linn, a lawyer in Oklahoma City who defended Bear Stearns. ''Bear Stearns wanted to be rid of the case, and the plaintiffs wanted to be rid of the case.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Linn also defended Bear Stearns in a case in which a wealthy, Canadian currency trader won a $167 million award against the firm in May. A hearing for an appeal of that judgment, for which the firm took a $96 million charge against its earnings last quarter, is scheduled for Sept. 28 in United States District Court in Manhattan, Mr. Linn said.</p>
        <p>By settling, Bear Stearns averted the possibility of having to pay much more, even having the original $108 million award restored, Mr. Coffee said. But, he added, the firm also ruled out the chance of having an appellate panel completely throw out the original decision by finding there was not sufficient evidence to hold Bear Stearns liable.</p>
        <p>''People in the investment banking industry who weren't facing this liability were hoping that it would be reversed,'' Mr. Coffee said.</p>
        <p>They fear increased liability for what they say in the ''fairness opinions'' they render on all mergers and acquisitions, he said. Corporate directors insist on having investment bankers sign off on proposed transactions to shield them from liability if shareholders sue.</p>
        <p>''Investment bankers make very high fees for giving these opinions,'' in part, because ''the law places great weight on obtaining these opinions,'' Mr. Coffee said. ''As a matter of public policy, we want some risk of liability to attach to these opinions or else they're likely to be fabricated.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hannan, the lawyer for the trustee, said the case was notable because ''two companies died but the creditors will recover'' some of their losses and because it laid down guidelines for the responsibilities of investment bankers in mergers and acquisitions. Mr. Coffee said the jury had found that investment bankers, like doctors in medical matters, play a pivotal role in mergers and can be liable for malpractice.</p>
        <p>The settlement is unlikely to have much of an effect on Bear Stearns's earnings because the firm had already set aside money to cover the larger, original damage award and will be able to use what is left of that reserve to cover other legal costs.</p>
        <p>''There could be some reversal'' of the legal reserve in the next quarter, said Joan Solotar, an analyst at Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette, ''but I would not imagine that it would be a total reversal. They could either fully release the reserve or find some other use for it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
