<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Indonesia's Quirky Leader Apologizes and Pledges Order</title>
    <meta content="08INDO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wahid, Abdurrahman (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mydans, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEFDB113CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1346" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Indonesia's Quirky Leader Apologizes and Pledges Order</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mydans, Seth</byline>
      <dateline>JAKARTA, Indonesia, Aug. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Indonesia's Pres Abdurrahman Wahid apologizes in state of the union speech for falling short of expectations as country struggles to build working democracy and says he will name executive minister to bring order to his flailing administration; says he will concentrate more on foreign affairs in future and create sort of prime ministerial post to handle day-to-day domestic administration; admired for his integrity, democratic ideals and intellect, he has drawn constant criticism for disorganized and impulsive leadership style (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A newly humble President Abdurrahman Wahid apologized today for falling short of expectations as Indonesia struggles to build a working democracy and said he would name an executive minister to bring order to his flailing administration.</p>
        <p>In a state of the nation speech that opened a restive annual parliamentary session, Mr. Wahid said he would concentrate more on foreign affairs in the future and create a sort of prime ministerial post to handle day-to-day domestic administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A newly humble President Abdurrahman Wahid apologized today for falling short of expectations as Indonesia struggles to build a working democracy and said he would name an executive minister to bring order to his flailing administration.</p>
        <p>In a state of the nation speech that opened a restive annual parliamentary session, Mr. Wahid said he would concentrate more on foreign affairs in the future and create a sort of prime ministerial post to handle day-to-day domestic administration.</p>
        <p>Admired for his integrity, democratic ideals and intellect, Mr. Wahid has drawn constant criticism for his disorganized and impulsive leadership style. The harshness of the attacks reflects what many analysts call the political immaturity of a nation whose growth was stunted by three decades of authoritarian rule under former President Suharto.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahid has made foreign affairs something of a hobby, visiting 30 countries -- some of them several times -- during his 10 months in office even as Indonesia is battered by economic collapse, sectarian violence, separatist movements and political disarray.</p>
        <p>The president, 60, who is virtually blind, has talked in the past of delegating daily administration to a chief of staff. He had his speech read by an aide today as he sat nearby, occasionally dozing off. He said today that the new ministerial post would be part of a broad reorganization of his bloated and feuding cabinet, which is widely expected to include the creation of a new, more focused and professional economic team.</p>
        <p>''He is not comfortable with details, so he will need somebody to run day-to-day governance for him,'' said Sarwono Kusumaatmadja, a cabinet member who is minister of maritime affairs.</p>
        <p>After clashing repeatedly with the noisy legislature over the last months, Mr. Wahid suddenly changed tack today, as he often does, and was contrite.</p>
        <p>''To all the people of Indonesia, I humbly apologize for being unable to solve fully the prevailing problems during the last 10 months,'' he said. ''Rest assured, however, that we would work even harder to strive for more accomplishments.</p>
        <p>''I am really more than willing to do whatever necessary to improve the performance of the government by adopting proper policies and strategies and sharpening agendas and priorities.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahid's speech, lasting nearly 90 minutes, was a powerful tour of the political scene, laying out his vision for a tolerant, inclusive, democratic nation and echoing many analysts in blaming the current problems on the aftermath of Mr. Suharto's 32-year rule.</p>
        <p>Mr. Suharto, 79, who was forced from office in May 1998, was charged with corruption last Thursday, and the case is expected to be presented to a court this week.</p>
        <p>The day's session was also a demonstration of the chaotic new openness and personal quirkiness that have supplanted Mr. Suharto's dour style and harsh grip on all aspects of national affairs.</p>
        <p>After opening -- as always -- with a joke or two, Mr. Wahid said that his political secretary, Marislam Simanjuntak, would deliver his speech for him.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Wahid, who tends to fall asleep at public meetings, dozed off several times during the reading of his own speech. In what appeared to be a planned tactic, an adjutant woke him each time by handing him a hard candy to suck on.</p>
        <p>In a clear signal that the Suharto years are over, the assembly began with a clamor of shouts as a dozen or so of the 700 delegates sought to make procedural points with cries of ''Interruption! Interruption!''</p>
        <p>The interruption is a parliamentary motion that allows delegates from the floor to be heard. During Mr. Suharto's tenure, this break with enforced unanimity was almost never heard; indeed it led at least once to the expulsion of a member from the assembly.</p>
        <p>There was widespread speculation today that the new executive manager would be a prominent former lieutenant general, Susilo Bambang Yudhoyono, a military reformer who is now the minister of mines and energy.</p>
        <p>But members of the government said that Vice President Megawati Sukarnoputri, a powerful figure who leads the country's largest party, might want the job for herself.</p>
        <p>Such a development, they said, could complicate government by creating competing power centers. Though Mrs. Megawati is not herself an aggressive manager, she has created a respected minicabinet of her own.</p>
        <p>Throughout the morning today, Mrs. Megawati, whose passivity contrasts with Mr. Wahid's puckishness, showed no expression, busying herself with wiping her neck and her glasses with a small cloth and rattling a small fan beside her face.</p>
        <p>Today's session was remarkable for one other development: the excitement was confined to the Parliament chamber. This is the first major political event since Mr. Suharto's departure that has not been accompanied by turmoil and bloodshed on the streets.</p>
        <p>Though security forces prepared, as they have in the past, with a huge contingent of nearly 30,000 soldiers and police officers, there were no mass rallies. The small orange buses with students dancing on the roofs, the face-offs with riot police, the stone-throwing and baton charges of past demonstrations were conspicuously absent.</p>
        <p>''I think things will stay calm,'' said Mr. Sarwono. ''It has become very hard to mobilize and agitate the people now because the public is sending strong signals that they want stability.''</p>
        <p>In this respect, perhaps, Mr. Wahid has made headway as he seeks to calm the nation. Analysts agree that most of the problems for which he absorbs the blame run deep and defy quick solution.</p>
        <p>Having acknowledged his shortcomings, Mr. Wahid, in his prepared speech, strongly affirmed the ideals that are the banner of his administration as it seeks to pull Indonesia toward cohesion and cooperation and away from the bloodshed and fragmentation that threaten it in the wake of Mr. Suharto's departure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahid noted that he had taken the difficult step of bringing the politically powerful military under civilian control, had promoted human rights and permitted a free and open press, had taken steps to combat government corruption and had worked to nurse an economic recovery.</p>
        <p>In addition, he said, he had opened negotiations with separatist movements in Aceh and Irian Jaya.</p>
        <p>A number of these actions have had decidedly mixed results. The military remains divided and restive with a breakdown in the chain of command that has contributed to horrific bloodshed in the Maluku Islands, where more than 3,000 people have been killed in the past 18 months.</p>
        <p>Violence also continues in Aceh and Irian Jaya.</p>
        <p>Corruption remains widespread, and Mr. Wahid himself has come under attack for several questionable deals and allocations of funds. And the faltering economy -- which precipitated Mr. Suharto's fall -- has not been healed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahid's promised government changes could directly address this problem. Although analysts say some economic fundamentals now appear stronger, the currency has continued to slide in value and foreign investors have stayed away. This has largely been because of political uncertainties that have been aggravated by Mr. Wahid's unpredictable style and the disarray of his economic management.</p>
        <p>Although the parliamentary session -- which will last until Aug. 18 -- was preceded by a surge of political squabbles and calls for his impeachment, most prominent politicians now say they will give the president another chance to bring his administration under control.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarwono said there was no chance now that an impeachment motion would go forward, as some legislators have warned. ''Nil. Zero. Hot air,'' he said of the possibility.</p>
        <p>But there is a high probability of more hot air. The legislature is angry, divided, filled with muscle-flexing and political agendas. There are still 11 days to go before the session ends. The legislators' turn to take the floor begins on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
