<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Logging's Shift South Brings Concern on Oversight</title>
    <meta content="08TIMB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221027"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Logging Industry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pacific Northwestern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Carolina</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tennessee</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Virginia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Logging Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DE113CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Logging's Shift South Brings Concern on Oversight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>UNION MILLS, N.C.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Timber companies, in major shift, step up logging operations in South where they face less regulation than in carefully monitored forests of Pacific Northwest; timber harvests in North Carolina, Tennesee and 11 other Southern states increased by 50 percent from 1977 to 1997, from 6.8 billion cubic feet to 10.2 billion cubic feet and trend has accelerated; states from Virginia west through Texas account for two-thirds of 16 billion cubic feet of timber harvested in US; federal officials and industry critics attribute geographic shift, at least in part to relative permissiveness of South where most forests are in private hands and where logging is subject to few regulations; nearly 70 percent of 214 million acres of forest in South is held by private, nonindustrial owners, with additional 20 percent owned by forest products industry; logging industry in North Carolina, where logging on private land does not require state approval, discussed; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a major shift, timber companies have stepped up logging operations in the South, where they face less regulation than in the carefully monitored forests of the Pacific Northwest.</p>
        <p>Timber harvests in North Carolina, Tennessee and 11 other Southern states increased by 50 percent from 1977 to 1997, from 6.8 billion cubic feet to 10.2 billion cubic feet, according to the draft of a federal report, the Southern Resources Assessment. And the trend has accelerated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a major shift, timber companies have stepped up logging operations in the South, where they face less regulation than in the carefully monitored forests of the Pacific Northwest.</p>
        <p>Timber harvests in North Carolina, Tennessee and 11 other Southern states increased by 50 percent from 1977 to 1997, from 6.8 billion cubic feet to 10.2 billion cubic feet, according to the draft of a federal report, the Southern Resources Assessment. And the trend has accelerated.</p>
        <p>Today, the states from Virginia west through Texas account for two-thirds of the 16 billion cubic feet of timber harvested in the United States.</p>
        <p>Industry officials said almost all of the logging in the South had been conducted responsibly. And they point to the very forests now being cut as an example of that stewardship. Most Southern forests, they said, were logged extensively as long as a century ago and then cut again in successive logging cycles.</p>
        <p>Federal officials and industry critics said the geographic shift reflected, at least in part, the relative permissiveness of the South, where most forests are in private, not public, hands and where logging is subject to few regulations.</p>
        <p>In general, Southern states have given free rein to logging on private land, in contrast to the West, where state regulations are stricter and where the abundance of federally owned forests means that cutting must meet tight federal guidelines.</p>
        <p>Nearly 70 percent of the 214 million acres of forest in the South is held by private, nonindustrial owners, with an additional 20 percent owned by the forest products industry.</p>
        <p>In North Carolina, which is typical of Southern states, logging on private land does not require state approval, and the state does little to monitor the extent of timber harvests.</p>
        <p>As a result, federal officials and industry critics said, they are seeing several troubling trends. For the first time, softwoods like pine are being harvested faster than they can be replaced, and projections in the Southern Resources Assessment suggested that the more valuable hardwoods face a similar fate.</p>
        <p>Officials also pointed to a wider use of clear-cutting operations that have laid bare vast tracts of forest.</p>
        <p>The relentless appetite for wood is being fed by an economy that has produced a strong market for construction. Small towns like Union Mills in western North Carolina have felt the boom in the form of chip mills, like the one here owned by the Willamette Industries Inc. of Portland, Ore., that grind wood into chips for making paper. More than 100 such mills have sprung up across the South in the past 15 years, most since 1995.</p>
        <p>Among those concerned about the shift in logging has been the chief of the United States Forest Service, Mike Dombeck. Over the past 20 years, Mr. Dombeck said in a speech in June to a group of writers, a huge surplus in the growth of timber over harvests in the South has been all but eliminated.</p>
        <p>''The issue is a question of basic sustainability,'' Mr. Dombeck said. ''Harvest levels cannot exceed growth if forests are to continue providing healthy fish and wildlife habitats, clean and pure drinking water, and scenic beauty.''</p>
        <p>In the South, according to federal estimates, the growth deficit is widest on land owned by the timber industry, which is about 20 percent of the forests and where removals in 1997 exceeded growth by 15 percent.</p>
        <p>Even in cases where forests are being replanted, as is encouraged but rarely required in Southern states, it is often with varieties like the fast-growing loblolly pine, a tree that is a valuable commercial crop but one that biologists say is less likely to promote animal habitat than the natural mixed forests.</p>
        <p>Timber industry officials said that the concerns are groundless and that most logging was being conducted with an eye to the future health not only of the forests but of the industry.</p>
        <p>They also acknowledged that in isolated cases, too much timber had been cut too fast with too little thought about what replaced the existing forest. But logging, they said, was the only way to clear old, marginal timber and make way for healthier, newer trees.</p>
        <p>''You have a resource that's getting old, and its growth is slowing, and the removals are increasing,'' said Bob Slocum, executive vice president of the North Carolina Forestry Association, an industry group. ''So you might have a period where your removals are exceeding the growth.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Slocum said it was important to remember that the timber in the South was extensively cut in the early 20th century and that it is again time for harvesting.</p>
        <p>''I would argue that the more important issue is what happened to the land after the harvest,'' he said. ''If it stays in forestry, you're going to be O.K. But if you pave it over, if you replace it with a Home Depot or Wal-Mart, it's going to be lost.''</p>
        <p>Industry critics have cited the speed and scope of the logging in the 13 states as their main concerns.</p>
        <p>''The basic fact is that the Southeastern states were ill prepared in the extreme for this incredible acceleration of timber products,'' said Lark Hayes, who, as a senior lawyer for the Southern Environmental Law Center has helped lead an effort to impose greater controls over timber operations.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, Missouri, under Gov. Mel Carnahan, imposed a two-year moratorium on permits for chip mills. North Carolina is also considering a moratorium, as part of a study ordered by Gov. Jim Hunt.</p>
        <p>But it is in small communities like Union Mills where the newest outrage can be heard.</p>
        <p>''We're not a bunch of tree huggers, and we do want to use the forest,'' Caroline J. Edwards, a seventh-generation North Carolina resident who works as a soil scientist and forest management consultant, said in the county seat town of Rutherfordton, N.C., not far from Union Mills. ''But we want to use it wisely.''</p>
        <p>Shannon A. Buckley, who as district procurement forester for Willamette in western North Carolina has been at the center of the local fight, offered a contrasting view that restrictions of logging would be a blow to property rights.</p>
        <p>''It's all got to come from a willing seller,'' Mr. Buckley said of the 300,000 tons of wood chips the mill could produce each year for Willamette's expanding papermaking operations in Kentucky and Tennessee. ''If the landowners don't want to sell the wood, it's not going to happen.''</p>
        <p>Nationally, groups like the Southeast Forest Project have tried to pressure Vice President Al Gore, as an environmental advocate and a native of Tennessee, to address concerns about chip mills and Southern forests.</p>
        <p>In his comments, Mr. Dombeck has been careful to point out that the widespread private ownership of Southern forests means that there may be little the government can do.</p>
        <p>''These are not public lands I'm talking about, and we will not try to regulate private forest land,'' Mr. Dombeck said in a recent speech to members of the American Forest and Paper Association. ''I challenge you, the world's foremost leaders in private forest management, to show leadership on this issue.''</p>
        <p>The Southern Resources Assessment, which should be completed next year, is expected to provide a more detailed look at Southern forests. But one picture of the transformation can be gleaned from periodic estimates by the Forest Service, which tries to gauge the nation's timber supply.</p>
        <p>In 1977, the studies show, the growth of timber stock in the South exceeded harvests by 75 percent. But by 1997, the most recent year for which statistics are available, the gap had dropped to less than 5 percent, as harvests increased and growth declined.</p>
        <p>Among softwoods regionwide, a large surplus in 1977 changed to a deficit of 10 percent. Among hardwoods like oak, hickory and poplar, the surplus has also dropped, prompting researchers to warn that those woods will also fall into deficit within the next decade if the current increase in logging remains unchecked.</p>
        <p>And though 20 years ago, about 15 percent of the nation's timber production came from national forests, mostly in the Northwest, that figure has dipped below 5 percent, driven by a series of federal decisions aimed at protecting the environment, and in particular by the 1994 Northwest Forest Plan, crafted to meet a court-ordered directive to save the endangered spotted owl.</p>
        <p>As across most of the country, logging in the South takes place far from the cities and the Interstate.</p>
        <p>But the view from the air can offer a more vivid picture, exposing one checkerboard after another, with patches of natural forest interspersed by tracts razed to the bare earth, and by others whose uniform green was a telltale sign of a the planting of a single variety of tree.</p>
        <p>On one recent afternoon, in the rugged terrain of the Cumberland Plateau, not far from Chattanooga, in southeastern Tennessee, the extent of the leveling was particularly vivid and appeared to support the findings of one federal research project whose conclusions suggested that in particular cases, the broad-brush estimates might not reflect the severity of timber loss.</p>
        <p>''It's very clear that, more broadly, no one really yet knows exactly what is going on,'' said Jonathan Evans, a biologist at the University of the South who is director of the federal project, which focused on impoverished, rural Grundy County and found that the county lost 12 percent of its hardwood habitat from 1981 and 1998.</p>
        <p>Among particular points of dispute is whether the chip mills are part of the problem. Only 32 of the more than 150 chip mills existed before 1985, but timber industry officials say the increase represents a step toward efficiency, by making it possible to ship pulpwood to paper mills as chips, instead of as logs.</p>
        <p>''There's a demand out there that's going to be met,'' said Mr. Slocum of the forestry association.</p>
        <p>As a corollary benefit, foresters like Mr. Buckley say, the mills provide a market for scrap wood that otherwise would have little commercial value, thus encouraging an overhaul they say is necessary to make way for healthier forests.</p>
        <p>But environmental groups and their allies see the mills more as instruments of an assault on Southern forests whose only guide is the corporate bottom line.</p>
        <p>The Dogwood Alliance, a group formed to the protect Southern forests, has estimated that more than 1.2 million acres of forest a year, or about 1,500 square miles, is needed to feed the chip mills now in operation.</p>
        <p>In operations of that scale, the critics said, neither time nor attention is given to selective logging measures aimed at promoting natural habitat.</p>
        <p>''Personally, I've always waited until the trees get big, and only then do I saw them,'' said Rodney Robbins, 44, a third-generation logger from Union Mills. ''But these timber companies only see one way of doing things: they just want to go in and mow everything down.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
