<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Apple Circus Cries Foul at Ringling's New Holiday Show</title>
    <meta content="08CIRC$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221036"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Circuses</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bryant Park (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Damrosch Park (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ringling Bros and Barnum &amp; Bailey Circus</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Big Apple Circus</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Glenn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Mark (Public Advocate)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Circuses</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EEDD113CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Apple Circus Cries Foul at Ringling's New Holiday Show</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Glenn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City will let Ringling Brothers and Barnum &amp; Bailey circus present high-end, one-ring, family-oriented circus in tent in Bryant Park during Thanksgiving and Christmas holidays for first time; show will compete with Big Apple Circus, holiday entertainment tradition in Damrosch Park; Ringling hopes to turn profit; Big Apple, nonprofit group, sees threat to its future and urges city to reconsider; Public Advocate Mark Green says he urged city to reschedule Ringling show because conflict risks diminishing both events, interview; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>And now, ladies and gentlemen and children of all ages, direct your attention to the stupendous holiday war between two big-top circuses.</p>
        <p>For the first time the City of New York will permit the Ringling Brothers and Barnum &amp; Bailey Circus to raise a custom-made Italian tent in Bryant Park to present a high-end, one-ring, family-oriented circus during the Thanksgiving and Christmas holidays. After eight months of deliberation, the mayor's office, the Parks Department and the Bryant Park Conservancy have given Ringling their blessing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>And now, ladies and gentlemen and children of all ages, direct your attention to the stupendous holiday war between two big-top circuses.</p>
        <p>For the first time the City of New York will permit the Ringling Brothers and Barnum &amp; Bailey Circus to raise a custom-made Italian tent in Bryant Park to present a high-end, one-ring, family-oriented circus during the Thanksgiving and Christmas holidays. After eight months of deliberation, the mayor's office, the Parks Department and the Bryant Park Conservancy have given Ringling their blessing.</p>
        <p>But for 23 years a feisty hometown show, the Big Apple Circus, has become a holiday entertainment tradition by raising its custom-made French tent in Damrosch Park at Lincoln Center to present its own upscale, one-ring, family-oriented circus.</p>
        <p>The Ringling show hopes to turn a profit, and Big Apple -- a nonprofit organization -- is crying foul.</p>
        <p>''It could be an enormous financial blow to us, because the Lincoln Center season is key in providing income for the Big Apple Circus,'' said Alan B. Slifka, a Big Apple board member who was its first board chairman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Slifka said ''it is possible that we could be driven out of existence,'' adding that ''we hope that this decision will be reconsidered by the mayor as the serious threat to our circus that it is.''</p>
        <p>Mark Green, the public advocate, wrote a letter last week to Rudy Washington, deputy mayor for Business Services and Community Development, urging the city to reschedule the performance of the Ringling one-ring show because ''we are dealing with a small potential audience, and this conflict risks diminishing both events,'' he said in an interview.</p>
        <p>The new circus, called Barnum's Kaleidoscape, was created 16 months ago by Ringling and has visited 12 American cities.</p>
        <p>Kenneth Feld, Ringling's 51-year-old producer and chief executive, said Kaleidoscape would be ''the ultimate Christmas ornament for New York City,''  referring to the champagne-colored tent with its red stars and stripes. The elaborately produced, $10 million show offers the comforts of crushed-velvet padded seats with backs, and red-carpeted hardwood flooring, as well as premier ''couch'' seating at $75 a head.</p>
        <p>Customers will be welcomed by costumed ticket-takers and ushers, and will be encouraged to buy not only cotton candy and popcorn, but also high-end fare ranging from panini sandwiches to designer water.</p>
        <p>''It is the right kind of entertainment for that time of year,'' said Michael Fuchs, chairman of the Bryant Park Restoration Corporation, the nonprofit group that oversees the park.</p>
        <p>The Kaleidoscape crew will erect its reception tent around the fountain in Bryant Park. Like all attractions using the park, Ringling is contractually obligated to replace any damaged grass or shrubbery.</p>
        <p>Kaleidoscape will also return part of every ticket sale to the Bryant Park Restoration Corporation, the total amounting to ''several hundred thousand dollars,'' Mr. Feld said.</p>
        <p>Several city managers with knowledge of the deal said that Ringling had guaranteed the park a minimum of $200,000 for the run.</p>
        <p>At Lincoln Center, Big Apple will hold the debut of its new show, ''Clown Around Town,'' from Oct. 19 through Jan. 7, charging $18 to $62 for seats. The show features 12 horses and 2 dogs; some 120 of its 140 performers and crew members live in the city.</p>
        <p>Kaleidoscape will charge $20 to $75 for seats. It will raise its tent on Nov. 16 and have its debut on Nov. 21, two days before Thanksgiving Day. The closing performance will be New Year's Eve. It has 62 performers, 54 crew members, 8 horses and 27 geese. Only the show's musical composer, Linda Hudes, is a New Yorker.</p>
        <p>Paul Binder, the 57-year-old founder and artistic director of Big Apple, said he did not want to be quoted ''in a sour grapes way'' about Kaleidoscape, which he has seen and said is ''extraordinary.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Binder added: ''I love the show, and I love the performers in that show. I am only sorry that they have chosen to compete with us.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Slifka was not as sanguine. ''For New York to invite Ringling in to crush the Big Apple Circus,'' he said, ''it's almost as if the city invited a for-profit opera company to come in and compete with the Metropolitan Opera.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fuchs said that ''we weren't trying to harm the Big Apple Circus,'' adding that the city ''no longer puts money into Bryant Park, so we are dependent on the money we can bring in,'' namely, fees for such activities as fashion shows, concerts and movie-screening nights.</p>
        <p>Mr. Feld's personal connection with Mr. Fuchs helped cement the deal. The Kaleidoscape proposal ''seemed to our staff so out of the ordinary that it sort of got turned down automatically,'' said Mr. Fuchs, formerly the president of HBO.</p>
        <p>But he said that when Ringling came back to him: ''I knew Ken, and I said we'd look into it. The more we got into it, the more we thought it was a good idea.''</p>
        <p>Ultimately, he said, the go-ahead was given by the office of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani during the last few weeks. Parks Commissioner Henry J. Stern declined comment.</p>
        <p>''Initially I was concerned about elephants and lions in the park,'' said Deputy Mayor Washington, who explained his involvement by saying that the approval was ''a parks function, and parks reports to me.''</p>
        <p>''But when we learned that it would be geese, and horses, that wasn't a problem,'' he said. ''We deal all the time with mounted police.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Washington said that Big Apple ''shouldn't be upset,'' because ''it's not as if each show will have an audience of 20,000 people.'' He added, ''The audiences for each circus are so small that everyone can do well, and help our economy.''</p>
        <p>Big Apple plays to 450,000 annual circusgoers in Damrosch Park, paying several hundred thousand dollars a year to Lincoln Center for the privilege. Big Apple estimates that it turns back a third of its $19 million yearly budget to city community programs, health institutions and charities. ''Any money that Feld takes out of our box office,'' Mr. Binder said, ''is lost to the children and the families of the city of New York.''</p>
        <p>For years Big Apple has done fund-raisers for city charities and other nonprofits like Mount Sinai and Montefiore Hospitals. It runs the Big Apple Circus Clown Care Unit, which sends 25 trained clowns into seven city hospitals to perform for sick children.</p>
        <p>It teaches circus arts to inner-city schoolchildren and gives free performances for blind and hearing impaired children and donates 50,000 free tickets to poor children.</p>
        <p>Mr. Slifka, a principal at a Manhattan investment management firm, contended that Ringling chose New York ''to cripple the Big Apple Circus.''</p>
        <p>''There are probably 50 other cities that Ringling could invade that don't have not-for-profit circuses,'' he said. ''The only reason for them to come at Christmastime is to compete with us.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Feld said he chose the city because ''New York is the ultimate goal of any entertainment attraction.'' He hopes it will attract attention for future additional Ringling one-ring shows intended to tour the United States and foreign countries.</p>
        <p>Ringling, however, has its own claim to New York tradition. ''Its three-ring circuses have played in Manhattan back into the last century,'' said Greg Parkinson, a circus historian who is the executive director of the Circus World Museum in Baraboo, Wis., ''and there was P. T. Barnum's American Museum,'' a forerunner of the Ringling show established in Lower Manhattan in 1842.</p>
        <p>The arrival of Kaleidoscape will be ''the first time that Ringling has pitched a tent in Manhattan,'' Mr. Feld said, as the Ringling show has for decades occupied Madison Square Garden in its various incarnations. Big Apple bills itself as the city's original tented circus, since of the 18 circuses that played New York before its arrival, all performed in buildings.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Slifka termed the battle of the circuses David and Goliath, Big Apple, which was founded in 1977, is hardly an impoverished neophyte. It bolsters its $19 million budget with  yearly tours to nine cities including Atlanta, Boston, Chicago and Washington. Nevertheless, Mr. Slifka said that Big Apple ''operates on a very tight budget.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Parkinson, the historian, said that in the winter season, ''Paris is able to support five competing circuses, which all seem to do well.'' He added: ''I can understand Big Apple's sensitivity to the arrival of another one-ring circus in New York, but a competitive rivalry could lead to near-record sales for both circuses. New York is a very big city.''</p>
        <p>If Mr. Feld brought Kaleidoscape to Manhattan in the spring, he would be competing with his own three-ring extravaganza, scheduled to return to Madison Square Garden next March 30.</p>
        <p>The holidays were ''the only time Bryant Park was available,'' Mr. Feld said, given the summer and fall fashion shows and the peak occupancy by visitors during the summer, ''and it is the time of year when people want to see things.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Fuchs of Bryant Park Restoration said that ''for our purposes they could come in during February,'' adding, ''we felt O.K. about any time in the winter.''</p>
        <p>Kaleidoscape will feature David Larible, who was for years a star clown of Ringling's three-ring performances, as well as Sylvia Zerbini, who performs on the trapeze and with horses, and Alex Petrov, a wire walker who balances a spangled lady atop his head on a 12-foot pole.</p>
        <p>Ringling executives have confirmed that Mr. Feld spent $10 million to start Kaleidoscape, but several circus marketing experts said under the condition of anonymity that the company had spent more than $20 million thus far on its one-ring venture without turning an overall profit, partly because of the show's elaborate sets and its luxury seating, which require transport by a staggering 50 trucks.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Feld insisted that Kaleidoscape ''is going to be a major profit center for this company.''</p>
        <p>And although Ringling has only a one-year contract to bring the circus to Bryant Park, Mr. Feld said that Kaleidoscape hopes to return ''year after year.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
