<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Murder Rate In New York Sliding Back</title>
    <meta content="08CRIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221014"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EEDF113CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1315" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Murder Rate In New York Sliding Back</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISSA GOOTMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City's murder rate, after a surge that alarmed the Police Department and brought about an expensive and aggressive street enforcement campaign, has begun to slide back down.</p>
        <p>The upturn in homicides, which by the end of last year was 6 percent above the count from 1998, had put the department on the defensive and loomed as a potential political liability for Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, who had made crime reduction his most important accomplishment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City's murder rate, after a surge that alarmed the Police Department and brought about an expensive and aggressive street enforcement campaign, has begun to slide back down.</p>
        <p>The upturn in homicides, which by the end of last year was 6 percent above the count from 1998, had put the department on the defensive and loomed as a potential political liability for Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, who had made crime reduction his most important accomplishment.</p>
        <p>But recent department statistics show that the homicide rate has flattened, with this year's murder count, which was 413 as of yesterday, an even match with the corresponding period in 1999.</p>
        <p>The numbers looked even better just last week, with homicides down 1 percent for the first seven months of this year, compared with the same period last year, but the rate edged up slightly this weekend, when the city had one of its most violent nights of the year, with six people fatally shot or stabbed throughout the city late Saturday night into early Sunday. By the end of July, there had been 392 murders, compared with 396 by the end of July 1999.</p>
        <p>The emergence of a flat murder rate belies a more marked decline, given that at the beginning of the year, the police were still facing a rise in homicides. By the end of March, the city had 13 percent more murders than in the first three months of last year. That the weekend's onslaught of slayings did not push this year's homicide count over the total from last year at this time illustrates that, blips and spurts aside, the situation is stabilizing.</p>
        <p>''The crime rate,'' Mr. Giuliani said yesterday, ''is down all over the city, even with the violence over the weekend, which occasionally, unfortunately you deal with.''</p>
        <p>''There is a sense of relief that we've turned the trend around,'' said Garry F. McCarthy, the deputy police commissioner of operations. ''Although it's not the bellwether crime -- the bellwether crime is robbery -- it's obviously the most important.''</p>
        <p>The police credit the drop to Operation Condor, an antinarcotics program begun in late January. The program has come under intense criticism for its high cost, for saturating neighborhoods with narcotics teams and for increasing the number of arrests for petty offenses. The police say they have since broadened the program to take aim at crimes against drivers of taxicabs and livery cabs and to add uniformed street patrols focusing on quality-of-life offenses like jumping subway turnstiles and peddling without a license.</p>
        <p>So far, at least $41 million has been spent on the program; police officers working under its banner have made 53,933 arrests in the course of about 100,000 overtime shifts. In its latest, broadest incarnation, the police say, Operation Condor is not so much a new strategy as a redoubling of the department's regular enforcement efforts in the neighborhoods that need it most.</p>
        <p>Critics are reluctant to credit the program for the decline in homicides, saying the numbers are small, the downward curve is new, and the murder rate could simply be fluctuating based on forces that have little to do with law enforcement.</p>
        <p>''I think the Police Department has done a lot to reduce crime, but I'm not sure that they can take all the credit,'' said Karim Ismaili, an assistant professor of criminal justice at St. John's University in Queens. ''If the economy goes on a slide and if some other drug market or underground economy flourishes, we're going to see an increase.''</p>
        <p>One problem in attributing the drop to police work alone is that in the Bronx, where Operation Condor has been as active as it has in any other borough, the murder rate was 57 percent higher in the first seven months of this year than in the same period of 1999. The Bronx was the only borough that had a decline in the number of murders last year, but through July, there were 124 murders there, up from 79 in the first seven months of 1999. The Bronx recorded one of those homicides during the weekend, when one person was shot to death at a block party at which seven other people were wounded by gunfire.</p>
        <p>Police officials said they were puzzled by the Bronx statistics. ''Whatever we've done there, it has not succeeded,'' Mr. McCarthy said, ''so it's time for us to change gears there and try something else.''</p>
        <p>The department says the drop is still a powerful piece of evidence that the city remains safe. While overall crime was down 8 percent last year, the 6 percent rise in killings took center stage, illustrating the extent to which grim homicide figures can eclipse favorable trends in other types of crime. A body count is as solid a figure as exists, and no other number is as incontrovertible or as closely watched.</p>
        <p>The police also mentioned a possible broader pattern. Officials say that as the murder rate in New York has declined 70 percent in the last decade, to levels last seen in the 1960's, the patterns of murder have changed, restoring the classical understanding of the crime as personal, not random.</p>
        <p>The gradual return of past murder patterns marks the end of a time when drug-related street violence bucked conventional thinking about the context and circumstances of homicide, criminologists and police officials say.</p>
        <p>''If you look at the long-term picture, it becomes obvious why the city of today barely resembles the New York City of 10 years ago,'' Police Commissioner Howard Safir said. ''Ten years ago, innocent people were being killed in gun battles right on the city's streets.'' Mr. Safir is expected to announce today that he is leaving the job by the end of this month, officials said.</p>
        <p>According to the police, only one bystander was killed during the first half of this year, a figure that includes both people caught in cross-fire and victims whom a killer mistook for someone else. In the first half of 1990, 101 bystanders were killed, the police said.</p>
        <p>There has also been a decline in the proportion of homicides that take place on the streets: 39 percent during the first half of this year, down from 55 percent in the same period in 1990, the statistics indicate. And the percentage of murders that took place inside private homes (as opposed to public housing projects) rose slightly, to 29 percent for the first six months of this year from 27 percent in the first half of 1990.</p>
        <p>The experts generally concur that the statistics reflect a real trend. ''I think it's fair to say that murder today is less random than in the past,'' said Jeffrey Fagan, a professor at Columbia University's Mailman School of Public Health. ''Whether that's because of changes in the drug markets or in the way people conduct their everyday life or because there's a fear of police, no one knows.''</p>
        <p>Alfred Blumstein, a criminologist at Carnegie Mellon University, said he had no doubt that the overall portrait of murder had changed, becoming ''much more diffuse, much less concentrated in a small number of places'' than a decade ago. ''It may well be time,'' he said, ''to rethink the tactics for dealing with the kinds of homicides that are left, which are in many cases tougher to deal with but may call for a different set of approaches.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
