<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Picket Lines Swell and Telephone Disruptions Spread in Strike</title>
    <meta content="Y08PHO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vandalism</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Verizon Communications</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Communications Workers of America</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vandalism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E6DE113CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Picket Lines Swell and Telephone Disruptions Spread in Strike</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romero, Simon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Strike by more than 86,000 workers of Verizon Communications intensifies as problems with local consumer telephone service begin to spread and picket lines swell in a 13-state region stretching from Maine to Virginia; chances of a quick resolution appear to grow more distant as negotiators hit a snag on several issues; business customers appear to be relatively unaffected by the strike, but residential service in scattered areas is knocked out by incidents of vandalism; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A strike by more than 86,000 workers of the nation's biggest telecommunications employer intensified yesterday as problems with local consumer telephone service -- some of it a result of vandalism -- began to spread and picket lines swelled in a 13-state region stretching from Maine to Virginia.</p>
        <p>Chances of a quick resolution to the strike, which began on Sunday, appeared to grow more distant as negotiators hit a snag on several issues, according to people close to the negotiations taking place at the L'Enfant Plaza Hotel in Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A strike by more than 86,000 workers of the nation's biggest telecommunications employer intensified yesterday as problems with local consumer telephone service -- some of it a result of vandalism -- began to spread and picket lines swelled in a 13-state region stretching from Maine to Virginia.</p>
        <p>Chances of a quick resolution to the strike, which began on Sunday, appeared to grow more distant as negotiators hit a snag on several issues, according to people close to the negotiations taking place at the L'Enfant Plaza Hotel in Washington.</p>
        <p>Members of the Communications Workers of America and the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers are striking against Verizon Communications, the company which was formed by the recent merger of Bell Atlantic and GTE Communications.</p>
        <p>On the walkout's second day, about 14,500 union members were picketing outside 550 telephone company buildings in the region. That was more than than five times the number of workers walking picket lines on Sunday.</p>
        <p>While business customers appeared to be relatively unaffected by the strike yesterday, residential service in scattered parts of New York and other Eastern cities was knocked out by incidents of vandalism, which police officials said might have been strike related. In New York alone, the police department reported more than 70 such incidents.</p>
        <p>Emergency services continued to function normally, along with other parts of Verizon's network that are automated. But delays in repairs and installations seemed inevitable even as Verizon (pronounced va-RISE-en) dispatched some 30,000 managers to fill in for striking employees. Workers remain on the job at the company's nonunion Verizon Wireless unit, the nation's largest cellular telephone company.</p>
        <p>Strikers seemed determined to stay on the picket lines as negotiators in Washington continued discussing a range of issues that include forced overtime and the loss of jobs from mergers. One issue, extending union representation to workers in the company's fast-growing wireless and Internet access businesses,  could potentially alter organized labor's role in high-tech industries that are fueling the economy's expansion.</p>
        <p>''We're going to be here till we get what we want,'' Ella Simmons, a striking telephone operator, said as she picketed outside a call center in Washington yesterday.</p>
        <p>The C.W.A., which represents 72,000 of the striking employees, said that the biggest gap between labor and management involved the union's effort to limit the number of jobs that can be shifted from one region to another as a result of Bell Atlantic's takeover of GTE.</p>
        <p>''My family doesn't want to get uprooted any more than yours does, but this company doesn't care about that possibility,'' said Richard Leath, 50, who works as a line splicer for Verizon in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Verizon has amended an earlier proposal that had called for 6 percent of its work force to potentially be forced to move or lose their jobs as a result of the Bell Atlantic-GTE merger. The latest offer from the company would set that figure at 4 percent.</p>
        <p>But the union is seeking a figure closer to the half of a percentage point it was guaranteed after Bell Atlantic acquired Nynex in 1997.</p>
        <p>Among other issues, the two sides have yet to reach an agreement over how to make it easier for the union to organize workers at Verizon Wireless, which has 32,000 employees and is seen as the fast-growing part of the company and the area where the best jobs may be found in the future.</p>
        <p>The union filed a complaint last month with the National Labor Relations Board over an incident the C.W.A. contends took place at a Verizon Wireless call center in Woburn, Mass.</p>
        <p>According to the complaint, management representatives, in what would be a violation of the law, told employees they could not distribute union literature or discuss unionization anywhere on the premises of the center, which has about 300 employees.</p>
        <p>The National Labor Relations Board is reviewing the complaint, a process that could take months or even years. ''I'd be very surprised to find out we acted illegally'' said Eric Rabe, a spokesman for Verizon.</p>
        <p>Efforts to organize Verizon's wireless division are being closely watched elsewhere, because so far the nation's wireless industry has had few union workers.</p>
        <p>As negotiators continued with talks that were expected to last late into the evening, the relative lack of network disruptions reflects the high degree of automation in modern telecommunications networks.</p>
        <p>More than 98 percent of the calls that the 25 million business and residential customers in the strike region place on the Verizon network take place with no human assistance.</p>
        <p>Any disruptions yesterday were  ''nothing big, nothing more than normal,'' said Rob Wilson, a spokesman for the Massachusetts Department of Telecommunications and Energy, the state's utilities regulator, which fields complaints about telephone service from consumers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
