<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Man of Steady Habits -- Joseph Isador Lieberman</title>
    <meta content="08LIEB$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000809T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221076"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE MAN IN THE NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDB113CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Man of Steady Habits -- Joseph Isador Lieberman</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Sept. 3, 1998, Joseph I. Lieberman stood up in the United States Senate to speak about Bill Clinton. They had been friends and Democratic allies for 30 years, but the president had finally admitted having an affair with Monica S. Lewinsky. Anger, resentment, a sense of betrayal: the bitter emotions had wracked the nation, and were about to find a powerful voice in the Senate.</p>
        <p>''Such behavior is not just inappropriate -- it is immoral,'' Mr. Lieberman said, abandoning for a principle a man who had campaigned for him in his first political race for the Connecticut Senate in 1970.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Sept. 3, 1998, Joseph I. Lieberman stood up in the United States Senate to speak about Bill Clinton. They had been friends and Democratic allies for 30 years, but the president had finally admitted having an affair with Monica S. Lewinsky. Anger, resentment, a sense of betrayal: the bitter emotions had wracked the nation, and were about to find a powerful voice in the Senate.</p>
        <p>''Such behavior is not just inappropriate -- it is immoral,'' Mr. Lieberman said, abandoning for a principle a man who had campaigned for him in his first political race for the Connecticut Senate in 1970.</p>
        <p>''It is harmful, for it sends a message of what is acceptable behavior to the larger American family,'' he added. ''I fear the president has undercut the efforts of millions of American parents trying to instill in our children the values of honesty.''</p>
        <p>With those hard words, Mr. Lieberman, the first Orthodox Jew to serve in the Senate, became the first Senate Democrat to denounce the president's behavior. While he ultimately voted to acquit Mr. Clinton in his impeachment trial, the episode strongly reinforced his reputation as a maverick, often at odds with party leaders, and as a moral compass in the wastelands of politics.</p>
        <p>It was apparently with those traits of pragmatic independence and personal integrity in mind that Al Gore yesterday tapped the 58-year-old Mr. Lieberman as his running mate, a choice widely seen as Mr. Gore's boldest stroke yet to distance himself from President Clinton and the scandal-tainted Clinton administration, and one to spark his campaign before the start of the Democratic convention in Los Angeles next week.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Lieberman is expected to help Mr. Gore rid himself of Mr. Clinton's baggage, his selection also carries a risk, for he would be the first Jew named to a major national ticket. The weeks to come may show whether Mr. Lieberman's faith will raise questions in the same way that John F. Kennedy's Catholicism became a focus in the 1960 presidential election: whether religion might affect his performance as vice president, for example, or the policies of a Gore -- or Lieberman -- administration toward the Middle East.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman, who describes himself as an observant Jew, strictly observes the Sabbath, from sundown on Fridays to sundown on Saturdays. While his religion ostensibly prohibits working, riding in vehicles and other activities during the Sabbath, Talmudic scholars say that exceptions are allowed for Jews to act to preserve human life or on behalf of the needs of the community.</p>
        <p>In public life for more than three decades, Mr. Lieberman has shunned campaigning and purely political activities on the Sabbath, but has considered it his duty to attend legislative sessions, to vote and to sit in on important public meetings. In 1988, he refused to attend the Democratic convention that nominated him for the Senate, but has often walked five miles to the Senate from his home in Georgetown. He has cast 75 votes on Saturdays.</p>
        <p>Presumably he would not refuse to attend his own inauguration should a Gore-Lieberman ticket win. Jan. 20, 2001 is a Saturday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman has been a staunch Senate supporter of Israel, but has also backed arms sales to Saudi Arabia. And he has often found himself in the company of Senate Republicans. In 1991, for example, he was one of 10 Democrats to support American involvement in the Persian Gulf war, and he was among the Democrats who favored the deployment of American troops in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to do what I think is right on every issue, and not feel obliged to vote a particular way because it's the party line or because people expect me to,'' he said in an interview.</p>
        <p>In his 12 years in the Senate, Mr. Lieberman has acquired a reputation for steady habits, family values and faithfulness to his beliefs -- a moderate who carefully deliberates options, sometimes agonizing over them publicly, and often seems to be striking a balance between conservative and liberal instincts.</p>
        <p>On the liberal side, he has voted for abortion rights, gun control, tax increases, welfare reforms, consumer protections and civil rights legislation. On environmental issues, he helped draft clean air laws, wrote the Pollution Prosecution Act of 1990, exposed lax security measures in nuclear power plants and supported minimum-wage increases and laws to protect whistle-blowers.</p>
        <p>On the conservative side, he has been far more enthusiastic than most Democrats concerning military spending. As a member of the Senate Armed Services Committee, he has had a weather eye out for Connecticut's many military industries. Among other things, he has supported development of an antimissile defense system.</p>
        <p>Not one to toe a party line, Senator Lieberman broke ranks with Democrats in 1997 during the Senate hearings on campaign finance, which investigated fund-raising abuses by the Clinton-Gore campaign in 1996. Other Democrats lobbed softball questions at administration witnesses, but Mr. Lieberman asked tough questions and tried to position himself as objective and above the fray.</p>
        <p>He also has been conservative on so-called family values and related issues. He supported tuition vouchers, for example, that would allow parents to send their children to private schools at taxpayer expense. And while some of his colleagues have dubbed him the ''conscience of the Senate,'' he has also been criticized as something of a moralizer.</p>
        <p>In 1998, Senator Lieberman and the former secretary of education, William J. Bennett, began handing out Silver Sewer Awards to draw attention to the producers of sexually explicit and violent films, music, television programs and video games. Critics were quick to note, in a recent financial disclosure form, that the senator had stock in some of the organizations he had criticized.</p>
        <p>He also pushed for electronic devices that permit the blocking of television programs that parents find offensive, has monitored a system of voluntary ratings to guide children's television viewing and has denounced rap music with lyrics that celebrate violence and drug use.</p>
        <p>Senator Lieberman is not an electrifying orator. Associates say his politics and personality are too moderate; his speeches tend to be heavy with facts and figures. But having run for offices since he sought his ninth-grade class presidency, he is poised in public and at times passionate about the issues.</p>
        <p>Joseph Isador Lieberman was born in Stamford, Conn., on Feb. 24, 1942, the son of Henry Lieberman, a liquor-store owner and realtor, and Marcia Manger Lieberman. He attended public schools in Stamford and Yale University in New Haven, where he graduated with a bachelor of arts degree in 1964. In 1967, he received his law degree at Yale.</p>
        <p>For two summers during his college years, he worked in Washington as an intern, once for Senator Abraham A. Ribicoff of Connecticut and once for the Democratic National Committee. After practicing law for several years, Mr. Lieberman, at the age of 28, ran successfully for the State Senate in 1970.</p>
        <p>A campaign volunteer was Bill Clinton, then a 24-year-old Yale law student. (Mr. Lieberman returned the favor in 1992, becoming the first senator outside the South to endorse Mr. Clinton for president.) After a decade in the state senate, the last six as majority leader, Mr. Lieberman gave up his seat to run for Congress, but lost.</p>
        <p>In 1982, though, he won election as Connecticut's attorney general by a wide margin. He gained popularity as an advocate for consumers and environmental issues, and was overwhelmingly reelected in 1986. Halfway through that term, he ran an uphill but successful campaign to unseat Senator Lowell P. Weicker Jr., the three-term Republican.</p>
        <p>Early in Mr. Lieberman's Senate career, a pattern became apparent. Mr. Lieberman voted with Democrats on civil rights and environmental issues, but joined Republicans on several high-profile issues, like military spending and foreign policy.</p>
        <p>In 1991, he first voiced support for the confirmation of Clarence Thomas as an associate justice of the Supreme Court, but eventually voted against him. His varying stances, however, did not appear to harm his standing with Senators on either side of the aisle, many of whom say they respect his independence, or with the voters. He was re-elected in 1994 with 67 percent of the vote.</p>
        <p>Senator Lieberman has written five books, including ''The Scorpion and the Tarantula,'' a 1970 account of early failures in controlling nuclear proliferation, and ''In Praise of Public Life'' (2000), written with Michael D'Orso.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman and his wife, the former Hadassah Freilich, have each been married twice. His first marriage, to Elizabeth Hass, whom he met in 1963 when they were interns in Senator Ribicoff's office, ended in divorce in 1981. They had two children, Matthew, now 32, and Rebecca, 31. He and Hadassah married in 1983, and she brought a son from her previous marriage, Ethan, 24. The couple also have a daughter of their own, Hana, 12, and two grandchildren.</p>
        <p>The Liebermans, who have homes in New Haven and Georgetown, are not lovers of the social scene in Washington, preferring quiet dinners at home. He jogs to keep in shape, and reads voluminously, including the Bible daily. He attends services in the capital at Kesher Israel.</p>
        <p>The rabbi there, Barry Freundel, is a friend, and said of the senator: ''He's not afraid to put life's most important things in front of politics.''</p>
        <p>PROFILE  Joseph Isador Lieberman</p>
        <p>BORN -- Feb. 24, 1942, Stamford, Conn.  HOMETOWN -- New Haven</p>
        <p>EDUCATION -- Stamford High School; B.A., L.L.B., Yale.</p>
        <p>CAREER HIGHLIGHTS -- 1971-81, Connecticut state senator; 1975-81, State Senate majority leader; 1983-89, Connecticut attorney general; 1989-present, United States senator from Connecticut; committee member, Armed Services, Environment and Public Works, Small Business, Governmental Affairs; 1999-present, ranking Democrat, Governmental Affairs Committee; 1995-present, chairman, Democratic Leadership Council. Author of five books, most recently ''In Praise of Public Life.''</p>
        <p>FAMILY -- Married to the former Hadassah Freilich; they have one daughter together, Hana, 12; from previous marriages, he has a son, Matt, 32, and a daughter, Rebecca, 31, and she has a son, Ethan, 24.</p>
        <p>OTHER INTERESTS -- Studying the Torah, reading, following the New York Yankees.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE MAN IN THE NEWS  Correction:  August 9, 2000, Wednesday  The front-page Man in the News article and a thumbnail biography yesterday about Senator Joseph I. Lieberman misspelled his middle name and the surname of his first wife. His middle name is Isadore, not Isador. His wife was Elizabeth Haas, not Hass.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 9, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>The front-page Man in the News article and a thumbnail biography yesterday about Senator Joseph I. Lieberman misspelled his middle name and the surname of his first wife. His middle name is Isadore, not Isador. His wife was Elizabeth Haas, not Hass.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
