<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Late Mets Lightning: Bell Ties It, Then Abbott Wins It</title>
    <meta content="08METS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221083"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Houston Astros</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Houston Astros</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5DA113CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1009" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Late Mets Lightning: Bell Ties It, Then Abbott Wins It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, Aug. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Houston Astros, 6-5; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Derek Bell crossed home plate and walked slowly to the Mets' dugout, staring purposefully into the stands at Enron Field. The Houston Astros' new home is enemy territory for Bell, a former Astro, who was booed heavily tonight, and he was scanning for his biggest ally: his mother, Chestine, for whom he always tries to hit a home run.</p>
        <p>Bell's glare did not have malice to it, but that does not mean he was happy with the 36,356 fans. Bell had just ripped a two-out, bases-empty homer in the ninth inning to tie the score and get Mike Hampton off the hook for a loss. He pounded his chest with his fist as he returned to the dugout, a gesture that told himself, ''I did it, now let's move on.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Derek Bell crossed home plate and walked slowly to the Mets' dugout, staring purposefully into the stands at Enron Field. The Houston Astros' new home is enemy territory for Bell, a former Astro, who was booed heavily tonight, and he was scanning for his biggest ally: his mother, Chestine, for whom he always tries to hit a home run.</p>
        <p>Bell's glare did not have malice to it, but that does not mean he was happy with the 36,356 fans. Bell had just ripped a two-out, bases-empty homer in the ninth inning to tie the score and get Mike Hampton off the hook for a loss. He pounded his chest with his fist as he returned to the dugout, a gesture that told himself, ''I did it, now let's move on.''</p>
        <p>The teams moved on to extra innings, and in the 11th, Kurt Abbott homered off reliever Jason Green to give the Mets a hard-fought 6-5 victory that featured high drama involving three major players from last December's trade between the teams.</p>
        <p>''It was nasty booing, but that's Houston fans for you,'' Bell said. ''They don't appreciate nothing. New York fans, they really appreciate the way I play hard every day.''</p>
        <p>Armando Benitez pitched one and one-third hitless innings to even his record at 3-4.</p>
        <p>Bell's homer was the most dramatic. Bell, who spent five years with the Astros, is sensitive and eager to be liked, but he is unpopular with fans in Houston. He has thrived since the deal.</p>
        <p>Bell was hitless in his first four at-bats, but with two outs in the ninth inning, he blasted Octavio Dotel's first pitch off a facade some 12 feet above the 404-foot sign on the wall in left-center.</p>
        <p>Bell and Hampton came to the Mets in a deal last December for outfielder Roger Cedeno (out with a hand injury), Dotel and a minor leaguer. Hampton knocked in two runs, but he allowed five over seven innings and stood to be the losing pitcher until Bell homered off Dotel, the Astros' new closer.</p>
        <p>Hampton said he would have been more nervous had his friend and former teammate Craig Biggio been the Astros' leadoff hitter. But Biggio is injured, Hampton got the leadoff man Julio Lugo on a groundout, and he was on his way with nerves intact.</p>
        <p>''Once I made the first pitch and got on a roll, I really didn't think about anything but trying to get a win,'' Hampton said.</p>
        <p>Abbott, playing because second baseman Edgardo Alfonzo strained his groin in the ninth inning, lined a homer onto a pavilion high above left-center field. It was the fourth homer this year for the little-used infielder, who is happy to have any kind of role on a team that has won 11 of its last 13 games.</p>
        <p>''This team is so good and we're playing such good baseball, you don't think about yourself,'' Abbott said.</p>
        <p>Hampton is aware of the leverage he will have this winter, when he will be 28 years old and the best starting pitcher on the free-agent market. He should command well more than $10 million per year and has done nothing to undercut his market value by stating a preference about where he will go.</p>
        <p>Still, when pressed on the subject over the weekend, Hampton acknowledged that the fact that pitchers do not hit in the American League will ''probably be part of my decision.''</p>
        <p>Interleague play limits that factor, he said, but Hampton sounded half-serious when he said, ''If I go to the American League, I've got to get a clause in my contract that I get at least 20 at-bats a year, not including interleague play.''</p>
        <p>Hampton, who received a warm reaction from the fans, takes his batting average seriously. He hit .311 last year to lead all National League pitchers, and his average has been around .300 this year. He came into the game at .288, and went over .300 in the second inning.</p>
        <p>With two outs and Benny Agbayani and Jay Payton on base after walks, Hampton grounded a single up the middle, scoring a run. It was the Mets' first hit, and Hampton had another in him two innings later.</p>
        <p>After a bases-empty homer by Robin Ventura gave the Mets a 2-1 lead in the third, the Mets put runners on first and third on hits by Agbayani and Payton. With one out, Hampton chopped a ball about 50 feet up the third-base line. It was not hit well, but it illustrated Hampton's philosophy on hitting: when you put the bat on the ball, he has said, something good can always happen. This time, it did.</p>
        <p>Third baseman Chris Truby charged the ball, but by the time he threw it, Jeff Bagwell had come off first base, conceding a single to Hampton.</p>
        <p>Truby's throw bounced in the dirt and got past Bagwell, and Payton followed Agbayani home on the throwing error to give the Mets a 4-1 lead.</p>
        <p>A single by Bagwell cut the Mets' lead to 4-2 in the fifth, and with two outs and two on, Hampton walked the dangerous Moises Alou on four pitches, loading the bases for Truby.</p>
        <p>With a 2-2 count, Hampton tried a sinker, low and away. It was a good pitch, but Truby reached down and popped it to right center. The ball carried well, landing between the outfielders and surprising Hampton, who was walking off the field, thinking the ball would be caught. Manager Bobby Valentine blamed himself for not shading Payton toward right, where he could have caught a ball that dropped in for a three-run double that gave Houston a 5-4 lead.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
