<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Affairs; A Whole New World</title>
    <meta content="08FRIE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221033"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Thomas L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George Prescott (Former Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E2DD113CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Affairs; A Whole New World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Thomas L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas L Friedman Op-Ed column say foreign policy advisers to Gov George W Bush are all those of his father, experts in a world that no longer exists; says that for Gov Bush, if elected, to base international policy on old assumptions would be to court disaster; says United States is no longer a cold-war superpower, but a singular hyperpower with both an unrivaled military and an unrivaled information economy, and that if Bush tries out unilateralist policies talked about by his advisers, he will face a ferocious reaction from envious US rivals and allies alike; comments on implications of globalization, Internet interconnectivity and surplus economy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the 1976 election campaign, Jimmy Carter vowed to withdraw U.S. troops from South Korea. When Mr. Carter won, the first words he had to eat were his vow to withdraw U.S. troops from South Korea, as Congress and the allies revolted against him.</p>
        <p>Should George W. Bush win, it is useful to consider how different a world he and his foreign policy advisers would confront from the last time Colin Powell, Dick Cheney, Condi Rice and Paul Wolfowitz were in office with President Bush eight years ago. The book on Governor Bush is that while he doesn't know much about the world, his advisers -- who were all his father's advisers -- are experts. That is true, but many are experts in a world that doesn't exist anymore: We do not have a cold-war global system anymore, we don't have a cold-war military and we don't have a cold-war public. In short, this ain't your father's foreign policy. The players may be the same, but the world isn't. Here are five things President Bush could never have taught his son about the world:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the 1976 election campaign, Jimmy Carter vowed to withdraw U.S. troops from South Korea. When Mr. Carter won, the first words he had to eat were his vow to withdraw U.S. troops from South Korea, as Congress and the allies revolted against him.</p>
        <p>Should George W. Bush win, it is useful to consider how different a world he and his foreign policy advisers would confront from the last time Colin Powell, Dick Cheney, Condi Rice and Paul Wolfowitz were in office with President Bush eight years ago. The book on Governor Bush is that while he doesn't know much about the world, his advisers -- who were all his father's advisers -- are experts. That is true, but many are experts in a world that doesn't exist anymore: We do not have a cold-war global system anymore, we don't have a cold-war military and we don't have a cold-war public. In short, this ain't your father's foreign policy. The players may be the same, but the world isn't. Here are five things President Bush could never have taught his son about the world:</p>
        <p>1. While America was certainly a superpower when President Bush left office, its economy was just coming out of stagnation and the Soviet Union had just collapsed. Today, America is not just a superpower, it's a hyperpower, with both unrivaled military might and an information economy that is the envy of the world.</p>
        <p>What's new in all this is that while other countries still call for U.S. leadership, they envy and resent America more than ever. No one wants to be America's enemy, but few want to be perceived as its friend. And what that means is that if Mr. Bush tries out some of the more macho-unilateralist policies talked about by his advisers -- such as abrogating the ABM treaty or sponsoring an uprising in Iraq -- he will face a ferocious reaction from U.S. rivals and allies alike.</p>
        <p>For instance, because of U.S. economic sanctions on Iraq, Saddam Hussein is now more popular than ever on the Arab street. Indeed, I am sorry to report, a huge cheer would go up from the Arab street today if Iraq were to acquire nuclear weapons to counterbalance the U.S. and Israel.</p>
        <p>2. President Bush had to manage the waxing military power of China, the waning military power of the Soviet Union and the soaring economic power of Japan. What U.S. foreign policy is about today is managing the weakness of China, the weakness of Russia and the weakness of Japan, as all three go through the wrenching internal adjustments to globalization that have made their possible collapse more threatening to us than their strength. In the Bush years, U.S. officials liked to say ''We lead, Japan pays.'' Now we must lead and pay.</p>
        <p>3. The Internet did not exist as a foreign policy tool when President Bush left office. Today, it's huge. Jody Williams won the Nobel Peace Prize for organizing a global ban on land mines -- against the wishes of the major powers -- using e-mail. If Governor Bush really did try to abrogate the ABM treaty unilaterally, and cram it down the throats of the Russians and Europeans, I believe it could trigger a Seattle-like, Internet-driven, mass-based, anti-nuclear protest against the U.S. -- identical to the popular movement in Europe today against America's genetically modified foods. This could make it impossible for any NATO ally to cooperate with the U.S. on missile defenses.</p>
        <p>4. America was a deficit country when President Bush left office, and now it is a surplus country. That means that the Republican ethos of steadily cutting back government, and the foreign affairs budget, is not only unnecessary, it's reckless, and it will be perceived by the world as increasingly selfish.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it's easy for the Bushies to sneer that they won't be the world's 911 or global cops, but such aloofness is much harder in practice now that America is so dominant. As the Clintonites discovered, we are now held responsible for everything, but Americans don't want to die for virtually anything. So finding ways to make a sustainable difference in places such as Kosovo or Rwanda is a lot harder than uttering a sound bite.</p>
        <p>5. Globalization: The speed, interconnectivity and economic impact of global markets today is much greater than eight years ago. If Mr. Bush does try a deep tax cut that the markets perceive as reckless, their judgment on him will be nasty, brutish and swift -- swifter than he may ever imagine.</p>
        <p>Other than that -- nothing's changed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
