<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After 7 Years Off, Swimmer Returns at 33</title>
    <meta content="08SWIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS: THE ROAD TO SYDNEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torres, Dara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E0DF113CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After 7 Years Off, Swimmer Returns at 33</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, Aug. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Dara Torres, 33, who resumed swimming career last year after seven-year retirement and is set to compete at Olympic trials; she comments, interview; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some people leave tickets for Elvis at sporting events. The swimmer Dara Torres leaves them for Alfonse M. D'Amato. The man once known wryly as Senator Pothole has apparently became Senator Swimming Hole.</p>
        <p>Torres is one of the more remarkable stories at the Olympic trials, which begin here on Wednesday. Having earned two gold medals on American relay teams, she retired after her third Summer Games in 1992 and did not swim competitively for seven years, becoming instead a fashion model, television commentator, spokeswoman for the Tae-Bo workout infomercials and the first athlete to appear in the Sports Illustrated swimsuit issue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some people leave tickets for Elvis at sporting events. The swimmer Dara Torres leaves them for Alfonse M. D'Amato. The man once known wryly as Senator Pothole has apparently became Senator Swimming Hole.</p>
        <p>Torres is one of the more remarkable stories at the Olympic trials, which begin here on Wednesday. Having earned two gold medals on American relay teams, she retired after her third Summer Games in 1992 and did not swim competitively for seven years, becoming instead a fashion model, television commentator, spokeswoman for the Tae-Bo workout infomercials and the first athlete to appear in the Sports Illustrated swimsuit issue.</p>
        <p>Last summer, the 6-foot, 160-pound Torres decided to resume her swimming career. She is trying to become the first American to swim in four Olympics. And in a sport often given over to teenagers, she is swimming faster than ever at age 33, having overcome the rust of a long layoff and a battle with bulimia that left her forcing herself to throw up even during the 1988 Summer Games in Seoul, South Korea.</p>
        <p>As she began her comeback, Torres said she met D'Amato, the former United States Senator from New York, on an airplane, and they began talking about his granddaughter's swimming achievements. They became friends, she said, and D'Amato even attended one of her meets in suburban Washington and helped her get an endorsement deal with Speedo. She got him tickets for the Olympic trials, but a business commitment will keep him away, she said.</p>
        <p>''He's almost like a father figure, an awesome friend,'' Torres said.</p>
        <p>What D'Amato will miss is one of the most unlikely resurgent careers in sport. It is exceedingly rare, perhaps unprecedented, for a swimmer to resume a career at an elite level seven years after having ended it. Yet, Torres this summer has set an American record of 24.73 seconds in the 50-meter freestyle and has become a medal candidate next month at the Summer Olympic Games in Sydney, Australia.</p>
        <p>Torres will swim three freestyle events and the 100-meter butterfly at the trials, which has ratcheted up the competitive tension in the women's sprints. This is where the United States has its greatest depth: Torres; Jenny Thompson, a five-time Olympic relay champion; Amy Van Dyken, who won four gold medals at the Atlanta Olympics; and Angel Martino, who has won six Olympic medals over a long career.</p>
        <p>Van Dyken said she was very surprised at how fast Torres was able to come back. ''I think it's great for the sport,'' Van Dyken said. ''It's wonderful that she's showing people in their 30's can be better than ever.''</p>
        <p>For a while, Torres trained with Thompson at Stanford University with Coach Richard Quick, who is also head coach of the United States women's Olympic team. Last December, it was decided that the two swimmers should train at different times because, as Quick said, Torres and Thompson were trying to swim an Olympic final every day in practice.</p>
        <p>Torres agreed with the decision.</p>
        <p>''If you are training for the same event, every day, twice a day, both going after the same thing and only one is going to get there, it can be very intense,'' Torres said. ''We're friends. We're not like enemies. I just think, in a way, it's better to keep us apart so there wouldn't be as much intensity in the workouts.''</p>
        <p>Why the comeback? A friend had planted the seed in her head, Torres said, and it began to blossom. ''I couldn't get it out of my head,'' she said. On July 7, 1999, she jumped back into the pool, believing that her long legs and elegant stroke would serve her as well as they had early in her career. Quick took one look at her form and said, ''We don't swim like that anymore.''</p>
        <p>He changed her style, having Torres look at the bottom of the pool instead of straight ahead. And he taught her to gain power from the beginning of her stroke instead of the end.</p>
        <p>She hired a personal trainer and changed her diet, eating more protein for muscle enhancement instead of carbo-loading as she had in the past. She also does flexibility training that involves two men walking on her back and her legs -- mashing, she calls it -- to relax her muscles before and after she swims. The new Speedo bodysuits also help reduce drag in the water and are said to improve performances by up to 3 percent, which can be significant in races decided by hundredths of a second.</p>
        <p>Such is the tarnished history of women's swimming that any spectacular performance brings the inevitable suspicion of drug use. Torres said she had spoken to Quick recently about how skepticism had come to cloud great achievement.</p>
        <p>''It's too bad,'' Torres said. ''Why do people have to emphasize drugs because someone does something really fast? I don't have words to describe it. It infuriates me. People think that because drugs are used so much in sport. Everyone has a conscience; for me, I know I've done everything I can do to get where I am the right way. I'm ready to swim fast.''</p>
        <p>To counter cheating in the sport, Torres said, she and Thompson work with Glen Luepnitz, a physician and nutritionist who has devised a regimen of legal supplements and amino acids that produce quick recovery from hard workouts and build muscle during tapering for competitions. ''He keeps us up with people who are cheating without cheating,'' Torres said.</p>
        <p>As a recovering bulimic, she admitted that she became unnerved at first when she packed 20 pounds of new muscle onto her frame. ''I don't think you're ever completely over it,'' Torres said. ''It freaked me out. Then I said, 'No, it's muscle, you need that.' Everything is in perspective.''</p>
        <p>And pointing toward a medal in Sydney.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS: THE ROAD TO SYDNEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
