<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees Have Plenty of Clout in Television Rights</title>
    <meta content="08SAND$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Msg Network</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Texas Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E7DB113CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1195" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees Have Plenty of Clout in Television Rights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees's lucrative ties with Madison Square Garden Network discussed in light of team's effort to further exploit value of its television rights and MSG's effort to retain rights; changes in corporate ownership and executive leadership have altered ties over years; table of data on current and proposed television deals; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than any team in sports, the Yankees have taken extraordinary advantage of the lucrative and escalating value of their television rights.</p>
        <p>In late 1988, the team selected Madison Square Garden Network's $493.5 million bid for its television rights over WPIX-TV's and SportsChannel's. The deal astonished the sports and television industries because the sum exceeded that paid to carry the local games of any team anywhere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than any team in sports, the Yankees have taken extraordinary advantage of the lucrative and escalating value of their television rights.</p>
        <p>In late 1988, the team selected Madison Square Garden Network's $493.5 million bid for its television rights over WPIX-TV's and SportsChannel's. The deal astonished the sports and television industries because the sum exceeded that paid to carry the local games of any team anywhere.</p>
        <p>Even before a game was televised, MSG paid the Yankees $50 million. Annual fees began modestly, at $7.5 million in 1989, but rose to $29.1 million by 1991 and are peaking this season at $50.7 million.</p>
        <p>MSG's cash has fueled the spending that made the Yankees the first baseball team with a $100 million payroll. The deal also transformed MSG from a partial-year network with Knicks and Rangers games into a potent regional force.</p>
        <p>Now, 12 years later, with the MSG deal expiring after this season, the Yankees are seeking to exercise the full power of their television rights. To exploit the Yankees' potential, the team proposed to start a network with the International Management Group that would guarantee it approximately $900 million in television revenue through 2010.</p>
        <p>That audacious maneuver provoked MSG to sue the Yankees in State Supreme Court last month, alleging that the team had breached a clause in their 1988 agreement that ensured MSG the ''right of last refusal'' to match any outside offer.</p>
        <p>A judge last Monday ruled that there was no basis on which MSG could match the offer and enjoined the Yankees from pursuing the I.M.G. deal in its current form. But Justice Barry A. Cozier did not stop the team from pursuing other offers as long as it let MSG match them.</p>
        <p>The Yankees viewed the ruling as a positive development, saying the decision immediately attracted new suitors seeking to invest in the New York Sports Network, or Newco. The team has hired Morgan Stanley to calculate Newco's full value; how much the investment bank values it beyond the $90 million-a-year average rights payments will determine if MSG can or will match the offer.</p>
        <p>Over the past two decades, changes in corporate ownership and executive leadership have altered the Yankees-MSG relationship. When the Yankees were carried on SportsChannel New York from 1982 to 1988, SportsChannel was owned by Cablevision and MSG by Paramount Communications.</p>
        <p>Cablevision and MSG were enemies, largely reflecting a bitter dispute that deprived Cablevision subscribers of Rangers, Knicks and Yankees games from 1988 to 1989. Bob Gutkowski, MSG's president and later the president of Madison Square Garden, was frequently at odds with Charles F. Dolan, Cablevision's chairman.</p>
        <p>Despite their differences, Cablevision and Paramount tried to merge SportsChannel and MSG in 1993, Gutkowski said in an affidavit filed in the Yankees-MSG case.</p>
        <p>In 1994, Cablevision and the ITT Corporation acquired the Garden, which includes the arena, MSG Network, the Knicks and the Rangers. Soon after, Gutkowski was fired and Dave Checketts replaced him. Cablevision acquired ITT's share of the Garden in 1997, the same year it sold a portion of the Garden to Rupert Murdoch to create Fox Sports Net. Two years later, in an attempt to guarantee the Yankees' presence on MSG in perpetuity, Cablevision attempted to buy a majority stake in the team. But the deal foundered.</p>
        <p>How seriously George Steinbrenner, the Yankees' principal owner, contemplated a Yankee network is unknown. But the MSG contract gives the Yankees the option to exploit television rights as they choose, after 2000, although it requires the Yankees to let MSG match any offer.</p>
        <p>The financial advantages of a Yankee network were raised in a March 1998 letter to Steinbrenner -- from none other than Gutkowski, by then the president of the Marquee Group, a sports marketing firm.</p>
        <p>Gutkowski wrote that a Yankee network would give the Yankees ''total control over every aspect of the network's operations.'' Estimates of $916 million in network revenue through 2010, Gutkowski told Steinbrenner, ''will provide you with additional leverage in your negotiations with Cablevision.'' In seeking to ''work on your behalf,'' Gutkowski added, ''As you know, George, we've both been there and done that.''</p>
        <p>By last winter, after the Yankees merged with the Nets, it was obvious that YankeeNets had ruled out selling the Yankee television rights to anyone, including MSG, and that a new network was the only alternative.</p>
        <p>''The concept of a Yankees-owned network is not some recent concoction designed to thwart MSG's contractual rights,'' Harvey Schiller, the chairman of YankeeNets, said in affidavit filed in the MSG lawsuit.</p>
        <p>Yankee officials broached the network idea with Cablevision last year, and again as recently as April 5, but Cablevision showed no interest in investing in a network that would compete with MSG and eventually carry Nets and Devils games, which are now televised by Cablevision-run Fox Sports New York.</p>
        <p>The impact of the Yankees on MSG has been enormous. MSG's subscriber base has grown from 2.3 million to 7.6 million since it acquired Yankee rights. Checketts said in his affidavit that Yankee advertisers buy commercial time for Knicks and Rangers games, and revenue from Yankee games softens the blow of falling ad sales if the Knicks and Rangers falter. The Yankees' clout, he said, is ''incalculable, irreplaceable and unpredictable.''</p>
        <p>Knowing the value of those benefits, the Yankees wanted them -- and made the deal with Trans World International, I.M.G.'s television unit.</p>
        <p>The Yankees would receive 95 percent ownership of the network, and T.W.I. 5 percent. T.W.I. would provide a program archive, equipment, facilities and a guarantee to make up for revenue shortfalls.</p>
        <p>The Yankees would reap $65 million next season from Newco; fees would reach $119 million in 2010.</p>
        <p>The Yankees and T.W.I. completed their agreement on July 5 and forwarded it that day to MSG, framing it as an offer that complied with MSG's right. Rather than matching or rejecting it within seven days, MSG sued to enforce its rights.</p>
        <p>''The so-called 'offer' is a sham,'' MSG charged in its complaint.</p>
        <p>Checketts said that MSG, ''for the past 12 years, has expended enormous sums of money and resources to be in a position to exploit the Yankees' television rights.''</p>
        <p>To buttress their case, the Yankees enlisted Gutkowski, who negotiated the 1988 deal for MSG. He disagreed with MSG's view of the contract.</p>
        <p>Gutkowski's role irked Kenneth Munoz, the Garden's general counsel, who said in an affidavit that Gutkowski's statements should be ''viewed in the context of his dismissal from MSG and his desire to assist the Yankees Partnership to form a new network.''</p>
        <p>Ultimately, Cozier's preliminary injunction against the Yankees never mentioned Gutkowski's position. Cozier ruled that MSG could not match the Yankees' offer because it demanded that MSG accept the same 5 percent stake in Newco that T.W.I. would receive, without getting any Yankee television rights.</p>
        <p>''Any bona fide offer must encompass exploitation rights to 100 percent of the Yankee games,'' he ruled, then added, ''You can't give half a loaf for what is a full loaf.''</p>
        <p>For now, Yankee games continue to be shown on MSG. But next season, Steinbrenner may have a network of his own -- and more money than ever to spend on players.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
