<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Minus Shooting Guard, Nets May Have No Shot</title>
    <meta content="08NETS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221013"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gill, Kendall</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EEDF113CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Minus Shooting Guard, Nets May Have No Shot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kendall Gill's expected defection to Los Angeles Lakers threatens to leave New Jersey Nets without star shooting guard team will need to make playoffs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nets have 10 players on their active roster, and Lucious Harris is the only shooting guard.</p>
        <p>That disturbing fact is threatening to undermine what could become a potentially solid season. The anticipated defection of Kendall Gill to the Los Angeles Lakers has left the Nets in a desperate backcourt situation. While Harris is a decent all-around player and nice reserve, he is not a legitimate starter, especially in a conference where shooting guard is the glory position.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Nets have 10 players on their active roster, and Lucious Harris is the only shooting guard.</p>
        <p>That disturbing fact is threatening to undermine what could become a potentially solid season. The anticipated defection of Kendall Gill to the Los Angeles Lakers has left the Nets in a desperate backcourt situation. While Harris is a decent all-around player and nice reserve, he is not a legitimate starter, especially in a conference where shooting guard is the glory position.</p>
        <p>You can compete in the East with a mediocre center, but your 2-guard needs to have some dazzle if you expect to vie for a playoff spot. Besides Miami, which offset its lack of a top-flight 2 with center Alonzo Mourning, the starting shooting guards on last season's playoff teams were Allen Iverson, Eddie Jones, Allan Houston, Reggie Miller, Ray Allen, Jerry Stackhouse and Tracy McGrady. If the Nets do not solve their problem by the start of the season, they could be in for another second-rate campaign.</p>
        <p>Look at how dismal they were without Kerry Kittles, who is expected to miss the entire season because of a knee injury, during the first 14 games last year. It was Kittles's return in early December that jolted them from a 2-15 start.</p>
        <p>''We're in a deep hole without Kerry because we really need some scoring from the perimeter,'' General Manager John Nash said. ''We're not as devastated as you might think, but you can't lose a player like Kerry Kittles and have nothing to show for it and feel like it's a good off-season.''</p>
        <p>Yet the Nets are on the verge of doing just that. They can forget about filling their void via free agency because every shooting guard worth mentioning besides Miller, Isaiah Rider and Jon Barry is committed to another team. Obtaining Miller is not realistic, and the mischievous Rider would wreak destruction on a young team like the Nets. As for Barry, he is likely to re-sign with Sacramento, which is willing to pay him much more than the $1.2 million the Nets have to spend.</p>
        <p>''We're certainly not going to limit ourselves to looking at only players who are free agents,'' Rod Thorn, the team president, said. A trade is the Nets' only hope. Until Gill's signing with the Lakers is official -- he had hoped to do it yesterday, but Jerry West's retirement as executive vice president for basketball operations may have delayed it -- the Nets will continue to pursue sign-and-trade possibilities with Los Angeles. A third team, perhaps Toronto, which may be willing to part with Doug Christie, will probably have to get involved because the Lakers have yet to offer anyone of interest to the Nets.</p>
        <p>There is a slim chance the Lakers will give up the disgruntled Glen Rice for Gill and Jamie Feick, a rebounding power forward who would fill a great need for the Lakers, but that is unlikely. And besides, Rice is not a shooting guard but a small forward.</p>
        <p>The leading candidate to be traded by the Nets is Feick. They tried hard to deal him before last season's trade deadline, and last week's acquisition of forward/center Aaron Williams makes him even more expendable. The 6-foot-7-inch Feick should have some value on the market since he showed himself to be one of the league's top rebounders last season. He was in the top five for much of the season before a decrease in playing time -- because of his poor defense -- began to work against his average. Even so, Feick finished with an average of 9.3 rebounds in 27.7 minutes a game. His relatively light six-year, $15 million contract also makes him attractive.</p>
        <p>The Knicks and the Nets might have something to talk about since Feick's ability to rebound would seem to entice the Knicks, who are stacked in the backcourt. Before joining the Knicks last August, General Manager Scott Layden attempted to sign Feick as a free agent for the Utah Jazz, offering him the same contract as the Nets. A deal involving Erick Strickland would be the logical choice if the clubs decided to deal. If the Nets are unable to obtain a sound starting 2-guard, Thorn, who has been praised as a terrific hire, may come under scrutiny for two of his decisions.</p>
        <p>First, he passed on St. John's guard Lavor Postell in the second round of the draft, instead taking the raw and unproven Soumaila Samake, a 7-2 long-term project, with the 36th pick. Postell, who stood out in last month's summer league in Boston, was selected three slots later by the Knicks. Thorn also went public with the Nets' pursuit of Ron Mercer and other shooting guards, angering Gill, who felt snubbed because the team went after other players before making him an offer.</p>
        <p>While acknowledging the significance of the situation, Nash said the Nets would not move hastily simply to fill their space in the backcourt.</p>
        <p>''Anything's possible in this business, but we have nothing imminent and I don't know that there will be anything imminent by training camp,'' Nash said. ''Oftentimes, filling a need is a work in progress that requires some patience.''</p>
        <p>And perhaps some prayers.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
