<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City Issues Slate of Safety Rules for Large Parades</title>
    <meta content="08PARA$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Indian-American Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Indian-Americans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Andy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E7DA113CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City Issues Slate of Safety Rules for Large Parades</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Andy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City, responding to accidents that killed three revelers at 1999 West Indian American Carnival parade, issues safety rules for large parades; rules include ban on alcohol sales along parade routes, requirement that police officer ride in every parade truck, mandatory training for parade marshals and wheel guards for trucks; West Indian parade organizers welcome most rules, but say rumors about alcohol ban has already spurred breweries and beer distributors to cut sponsorship of parade (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>City Hall officials yesterday issued a set of safety rules for large parades in response to accidents that killed three revelers at last year's West Indian American Carnival parade.</p>
        <p>The rules include a ban on alcohol sales along parade routes, a requirement that a police officer ride in every parade truck, mandatory training for parade marshals and obligatory wheel guards for trucks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>City Hall officials yesterday issued a set of safety rules for large parades in response to accidents that killed three revelers at last year's West Indian American Carnival parade.</p>
        <p>The rules include a ban on alcohol sales along parade routes, a requirement that a police officer ride in every parade truck, mandatory training for parade marshals and obligatory wheel guards for trucks.</p>
        <p>The organizers of the West Indian parade, a colorful extravaganza that draws about two million people to Eastern Parkway in Brooklyn each Labor Day, welcomed most of the rules, some of which give legal teeth to precautions they already take.</p>
        <p>But they objected to the alcohol ban, saying that rumors about it had already prompted sponsors who brew and distribute beer to cut their donations to the parade. ''Alcohol has never caused the death of anybody at the West Indian parade,'' said Jean Alexander, the marketing director for the West Indian American Day Carnival Association, which organizes the parade, the city's largest street procession. ''It's almost as if we're Peter, paying for Paul.''</p>
        <p>At last year's parade, two 11-year-old dancers were killed and another child was hurt when a van lurched forward and pinned them against a sound truck blasting Trinidadian soca music. A few hours later, an 18-year-old man frightened by a snake that someone was holding backed into the street and was struck and killed by a sound truck.</p>
        <p>The next day, city officials and the police said they would take steps to prevent such accidents. Officials from the mayor's office and the Police Department met with the organizers over several months to come up with the new rules.</p>
        <p>Some of the rules are closely tailored responses to last year's deaths, including a ban on motorized support vehicles like the supply van that struck the children, and a directive to the police to have pet owners remove ''any animals which may cause spectators fear or alarm.''</p>
        <p>Others, like the alcohol ban, seemed more broadly aimed.</p>
        <p>Deputy Mayor Rudy Washington, who was on the committee that developed the rules, explained that even though it was illegal to drink alcohol on a public street, vendors associated with parades had generally been able to get temporary permits to sell beer or wine along the route. The new rule, he said, resolves that inconsistency.</p>
        <p>The alcohol ban is separate from a proposal the city is considering to ban alcohol at stationary street fairs.</p>
        <p>Ms. Alexander said that she believed the city was cracking down on alcohol consumption because of the sexual assaults that followed the National Puerto Rican Day Parade in June, a charge denied by Sunny Mindel, a spokeswoman for Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>Ms. Alexander also said the police have been closing down fund-raising parties involving the sale of beer by the clubs that make the elaborate, glittery costumes for the West Indian parade, which can cost thousands of dollars apiece. ''This is going to result in not so many pretty costumes on the parkway,'' she warned.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
