<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>11% Visitor Rise Makes City No. 2 U.S. Tourist Destination</title>
    <meta content="08TOUR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221012"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sidewalks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Times Square (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipton, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDF113CF93BA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>11% Visitor Rise Makes City No. 2 U.S. Tourist Destination</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City reports it welcomed estimated 36.7 million visitors in 1999, up 11 percent from 1998, making it second most popular destination for United States travelers; says visitors spent some $15.6 billion; Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani hails gain and predicts further gain, news conference; admits tourists add to congestion; backs proposal to widen Times Square sidewalks; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City welcomed an estimated 36.7 million visitors last year, an 11 percent rise from the previous year, generating billions of dollars in sales for city businesses and supporting several hundred thousand jobs, but also intensifying congestion on city streets and sidewalks, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The figures, compiled from federal surveys and a tourism research concern, earned New York City a second-place ranking nationwide as a destination for United States travelers, pushing Las Vegas down to the No. 3 spot. Orlando maintained its top ranking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City welcomed an estimated 36.7 million visitors last year, an 11 percent rise from the previous year, generating billions of dollars in sales for city businesses and supporting several hundred thousand jobs, but also intensifying congestion on city streets and sidewalks, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The figures, compiled from federal surveys and a tourism research concern, earned New York City a second-place ranking nationwide as a destination for United States travelers, pushing Las Vegas down to the No. 3 spot. Orlando maintained its top ranking.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani pointed to the numbers yesterday as further proof of the city's improved reputation within the United States and around the globe as a safe, family-friendly place to visit.</p>
        <p>''The numbers are staggering,'' Mr. Giuliani said, adding that the total number of visitors should hit 38.4 million this year, up from 28.5 million in 1995. ''This means a tremendous number of jobs and tremendous benefits to citizens of the whole city.''</p>
        <p>The tourists, business travelers and others visiting the city spent an estimated $15.6 billion last year at hotels, restaurants, stores, cultural institutions and countless other locations, according to the survey, released by NYC &amp; Company, the city's convention and visitors bureau.</p>
        <p>That spending generated an estimated $2.9 billion in local, state and federal tax revenues, and supported about 275,000 jobs. But even Mr. Giuliani, ever the booster for New York City, acknowledged yesterday that the flood of tourists had its costs.</p>
        <p>''The bad side is we are very crowded,'' Mr. Giuliani said, speaking at a Times Square news conference, while crowds of tourists pressed up against a window to get a glimpse of the mayor. ''But the last time I was in Los Angeles you could not move, on all of those, what do they call them, 'freeways,' 'stopways,' . . . 'parking lots.' So I think we are in better shape than some other cities, even with the tremendous amount of tourism we have.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani yesterday endorsed the idea, already under consideration by city planners, of widening sidewalks in parts of Times Square and making other changes to try to reduce traffic and pedestrian congestion at the increasingly popular tourist spot. ''You can hardly move on the sidewalks,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Visitors from outside the United States made up about 20 percent of the total last year, with tourists from Britain, Canada, Germany, Japan and France topping the list of international visitors. Overall international visits to the city rose to about 6.6 million last year, up 9 percent, according to data attributed by NYC &amp; Company to the federal government.</p>
        <p>But the strongest growth has been from within the United States.</p>
        <p>Nationally, domestic travel increased by an estimated 3.2 percent last year, according to D. K. Shifflet &amp; Associates of Falls Church, Va., a company that collects travel information from about 100,000 households each year. In New York City, visits increased by 11.6 percent, a growth rate faster than at all but 3 of the nation's top 10 tourist destinations, a spokesman for D. K. Shifflet said.</p>
        <p>These tourists are packing city hotels, which added more than 1,000 rooms last year, with 3,000 more on the way.</p>
        <p>''How are we going to see everything we want to see?'' said Sheila Haas, an Illinois teacher visiting with her husband, who was busy videotaping and photographing Times Square yesterday, as Mr. Giuliani wrapped up his announcement of the new tourism numbers. They then headed off to the Museum of Modern Art.</p>
        <p>A large part of the increase in visitors comes from families traveling to the city, such as Joanne and Rick Sweeney of Boston, who brought their three children to New York this week, the first such family vacation to the city. The trip has been fascinating, said Mr. Sweeney, a software manager, but he is not planning a move to the city. ''It is a great place to visit,'' he said in Times Square. ''But I would not want to live here. The stress level is a couple of notches higher than I can bear.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
