<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Springtime in July for Crunchy Young Garlic</title>
    <meta content="19GARL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Garlic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenmarkets (NYC)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Paltz (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baldwin, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradley, Ray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Garlic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE7DB103BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1977" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Springtime in July for Crunchy Young Garlic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH BALDWIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baldwin, Deborah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ray Bradley harvests garlic at his farm in New Paltz, NY, and rushes it to Greenmarket in New York during the very brief season for young garlic; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOT day, hard time getting out of the city. By the time we got to New Paltz, N.Y., the sun was halfway down, and Ray Bradley, a modest farmer with a big-city resume, had already been at work 11 hours.</p>
        <p>At the distant end of a long, skinny plot of raggedy green stalks, Mr. Bradley was a Coppertone blur in a stained T-shirt and baseball cap. He was overseeing three field hands and half a dozen city slickers who had driven hours for the privilege of a great day in the country: the July 1 garlic harvest at the Bradley Farm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOT day, hard time getting out of the city. By the time we got to New Paltz, N.Y., the sun was halfway down, and Ray Bradley, a modest farmer with a big-city resume, had already been at work 11 hours.</p>
        <p>At the distant end of a long, skinny plot of raggedy green stalks, Mr. Bradley was a Coppertone blur in a stained T-shirt and baseball cap. He was overseeing three field hands and half a dozen city slickers who had driven hours for the privilege of a great day in the country: the July 1 garlic harvest at the Bradley Farm.</p>
        <p>Picking garlic is slow work: you have to bend and yank the bulbs one by one out of the cakey soil. Every so often, the pickers gathered their smelly bundles and moved toward Mr. Bradley's truck, a 1984 heap with so much soil on the floor you could probably throw down a few kernels and raise corn. By sundown the back of the truck was buried in light-bulb-white garlic heads so fresh that it seemed a shame to eat them.</p>
        <p>Garlic may be available year-round, but the season for young garlic is terribly short, only a few weeks in spring and early summer. During that time, growers like Mr. Bradley rush to farmers' markets and restaurants with crates of naked-looking new bulbs, soil still clinging to their roots and stalks, their nearly skinless, barely formed cloves as crunchy as Granny Smith apples.</p>
        <p>For some customers, it is a thrill simply to see garlic that is not in a cardboard container. Others are charmed by garlic nipped before it has reached adulthood and conveying spring in all its senses. For the time-pressed cook, new garlic has a more practical payoff: there is no need to remove annoying raspy skins, as with mature garlic. You can slice and saute an entire head like an onion. Its flavor can be mild or strong, but either way, garlic is an excellent candidate for poaching in soups, roasting alongside meats and pureeing for mashed potatoes, aioli and the like.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley, one of about 20 farmers selling new garlic at New York City's Greenmarkets, came to farming through haute cuisine's back door, as a chef in some of the city's top restaurants. He is a Connecticut native whose father grew garlic, and whose mother refused to cook with it. Mr. Bradley, 47, studied forestry and logged in Maine and Oregon. But he had always been interested in cooking and, in the late 1970's, became a kitchen grunt, peeling carrots for a chef who circulated between Clearwater, Fla., and Cape Cod, Mass.</p>
        <p>The culinary arts, calling for equal parts of physical endurance and precision, suited Mr. Bradley. Next, he moved to New York, where he perfected his skills cooking alongside his childhood friend David Bouley at restaurants like Le Cirque and Montrachet. When Mr. Bouley opened a restaurant of his own in 1987, Mr. Bradley served as sous-chef. He also helped hammer the place together, Mr. Bouley recalled last week, as he scuttled between his current restaurants, Danube and Bouley Bakery.</p>
        <p>But for Mr. Bradley, the gourmet grind proved as tough as carting timber out of the Cascades, and in 1993 he decided to get into the less heated business of providing the provisions. He tried being a middleman, tracking down hard-to-get ingredients for name kitchens. Then he began growing the goods himself, renting seven flood-prone acres in the Hudson River Valley on the Wallkill River near New Paltz, where farmers have tilled the loamy soil since the 1670's. He chose organic methods, mainly because he had no stomach for chemistry. The trick, he figured, was to find crops that would thrive in his inexperienced care.</p>
        <p>Garlic, it turned out, is a survivor. Maybe bugs don't like how it smells. Raised organically, garlic ''is smaller, but it tastes great and lasts longer,'' Mr. Bradley said. Within three years, he was specializing in a variety called German porcelain, which comes from the branch of the garlic family known as hard-neck because the bulb has a stiff central stem.</p>
        <p>In October, Mr. Bradley plants cloves from the biggest bulbs culled the previous year. (If he sells down his stocks, he buys seed from Charles Bishop, a friend and fellow Greenmarket purveyor, who plays ant to Mr. Bradley's grasshopper.) Come spring, the cloves send up long green shoots, which curl like a pig's tail. Garlic farmers chop them off to discourage the plants from concentrating on flower production. More important, the shoots yield a by-crop called scapes, which make a nice side dish sauteed in a little butter or olive oil.</p>
        <p>The scapes, which are mild and look like Asian string beans, have a surprisingly long shelf life, and Mr. Bradley and Mr. Bishop sell them all summer, along with tons of garlic. (Mr. Bradley is at the Amsterdam Avenue and 97th Street Greenmarket on Fridays and at Grand Army Plaza in Brooklyn on Saturdays. Mr. Bishop is at Bowling Green on Thursdays and in St. George, on Staten Island, on Saturdays.)</p>
        <p>By September, the garlic has lost weight and begun to resemble the dried garlic sold in stores.</p>
        <p>In recent years, word of Mr. Bradley's garlic harvest has gotten around, and a couple of carloads of amateur garlic hounds arrive in time to help, pocketing a few pounds for personal use and praying that the former chef will offer them dinner. Last year, he put out roasted lamb marinated in garlic and olive oil, a dish he likes to garnish with fresh garlic chips, or croutons. (Thinly slice some new garlic, and fry in butter and olive oil until crisp.) He also likes to separate new cloves and sprinkle them with olive oil, baking them in a moderate oven until they begin to soften, then caramelizing them in a saute pan with a bit of olive oil.</p>
        <p>During the summer, Mr. Bradley works the farm until sundown before Greenmarket days and heads for the city at about 3 a.m. In the co-pilot seat is a sleepy 120-pound Labrador named Grizzly.</p>
        <p>A stream of customers came by the Grand Army Plaza Greenmarket, near Park Slope, on the Saturday after the harvest began, many clearly pleased to catch up with a favorite vendor. Some shoppers seemed perplexed by a table piled with garlic so new that it was still attached to its umbilical stems. Others made beelines to Mr. Bradley's signature impulse item: homemade garlic dog biscuits.</p>
        <p>And there were those, like John Policastro, the chef at the nearby Garden Cafe, who had other things in mind. Mr. Policastro makes a seasonal soup using Mr. Bradley's bulbs and early fingerling potatoes, garnishing it with scape-flecked creme fraiche. Anna Klinger, the chef at Al Di La in Brooklyn, makes soup out of Mr. Bradley's garlic, with chicken stock and little else, and she grills Mr. Bradley's scapes and serves them in a fresh garlic dressing made with anchovies, chili pepper and olive oil.</p>
        <p>New garlic is old hat in Berkeley, Calif., where Chez Panisse and its adjoining cafe celebrate Bastille Day every July with an all-garlic menu. Fresh garlic is ''usually sweeter, without an acrid taste,'' Russell Moore, one of the chefs, said, estimating that 450 guests went through 70 to 80 pounds of it last Friday.</p>
        <p>New England is still catching up with Northern California, but ''10 years ago, garlic got very popular,'' said Mr. Bishop, 57, a former aerospace engineer who dedicates three acres of his Susquehanna Valley farm near the Pennsylvania line to garlic. He credits a September garlic festival in Saugerties, N.Y., with stimulating interest in fresh garlic. No one knows how much is harvested in New York State annually, but Mr. Bishop thinks he will pull four tons this year, selling three and holding back the rest for seed stock.</p>
        <p>Last week, he started harvesting the first of four varieties, a no-name soft-neck with a possibly Alsatian provenance, which he brought from Germany eight years ago. His other varieties include the German porcelain, which he describes as ''beautifully impressive,'' with a strong flavor and a high sugar content.</p>
        <p>''It is sweeter when you bake it,'' he said. (Wrap a head in foil with a bit of vinaigrette and push it around the periphery of a hot Weber grill until it begins to collapse.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley, despite his culinary background, prefers even simpler preparations. ''Just slice up the fresh garlic and saute it in butter until it caramelizes,'' he said. ''It goes great on steak.''</p>
        <p>For side dishes he suggested, ''Chop up some scapes and saute them, and add them to mashed potatoes.'' Another idea: ''Cut a baguette down the middle, open it up and put some olive oil on it. Broil it. Add minced garlic, salt and pepper, Parmesan. Close it up, wrap it in foil and bake it.''</p>
        <p>By the time we loaded the car and left New Paltz, we had enough new garlic to keep ourselves in garlic bread for months. We pointed the car south and drove until we got to a busy crosstown street. We double-parked, hopped out and opened the trunk, which reeked. A man driving by leaned out the window -- a real New Yorker, who wants you to know he doesn't miss a thing -- and yelled: ''Hey! Is that fresh garlic?''</p>
        <p>We took it upstairs and started cooking.</p>
        <p>NEW GARLIC PUDDING SOUFFLE  Adapted from ''Chez Panisse Cafe Cookbook'' by Alice Waters (HarperCollins, 1999)  Time: 1 hour 30 minutes</p>
        <p>4 tablespoons ( 1/2 stick) butter, more for greasing ramekins</p>
        <p>1/4 cup flour  1 1/2 cups milk, slightly warmed  Salt and fresh-ground black pepper  2 sprigs fresh thyme  1 medium onion, peeled and diced</p>
        <p>1/2 pound new garlic, sliced, about 1 cup (see note)  Pinch cayenne</p>
        <p>1/2 cup grated Gruyere cheese  3 large eggs, separated</p>
        <p>1/3 cup heavy cream.</p>
        <p>1. Melt 3 tablespoons butter in pan over medium-low heat. Stir in flour, and cook for a few minutes; do not brown. Add milk a little at a time, whisking to keep mixture smooth. Add  1/2 teaspoon salt and thyme. Reduce heat to very low, and simmer until sauce is medium-thick, about 20 minutes. Stir frequently to prevent sticking. Remove from heat, and discard thyme. Set aside.</p>
        <p>2. Melt remaining butter over medium heat. Add onion, and saute until translucent. Add new garlic, 1 teaspoon salt and  1/4 cup water. Reduce heat to low. Simmer until garlic is soft and water has nearly evaporated, about 10 minutes. Cool, then puree in a food processor. Stir puree into sauce. Add cayenne, Gruyere and black pepper to taste. Mix well, and adjust seasonings; sauce should be highly seasoned. Lightly beat egg yolks, and add to sauce. Mix well.</p>
        <p>3. Heat oven to 400 degrees. Butter six 1-cup ramekins. Beat egg whites until they form soft peaks, then fold into sauce. Fill ramekins, and place in a deep baking dish. Pour hot water to halfway up sides of ramekins. Bake until souffles are golden brown on top, about 20 minutes. Remove from water bath. Cool, then unmold, placing in a shallow baking dish, top side up. Souffles can be held at room temperature for a few hours.</p>
        <p>4. Heat oven to 425 degrees. Pour cream over souffles. Bake until cream bubbles and souffles are puffed, 6 to 8 minutes. Serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>Note: For cup of garlic,  3/4 cup sliced leeks,  1/4 cup chopped scallions and 3 chopped garlic cloves may be substituted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
