<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Just Another Task in Paradise</title>
    <meta content="19WCOL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Workplace" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215980"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LIFE'S WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belkin, Lisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E7DC133BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Just Another Task in Paradise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA BELKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belkin, Lisa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lisa Belkin's Life's Work column on taking a 'working' vacation with her husband; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN you read this I will be on vacation. But that doesn't mean I won't be working. I'll have my laptop with me, and, with luck, I'll be able to tap into my e-mail. After all, this column has to be edited.</p>
        <p>My husband and I have a tradition of working while playing. It began on our Hawaiian honeymoon, when Bruce spent the plane ride reading medical journals and I was awakened at an ungodly hour by this newspaper's magazine section so I could answer questions from a fact checker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN you read this I will be on vacation. But that doesn't mean I won't be working. I'll have my laptop with me, and, with luck, I'll be able to tap into my e-mail. After all, this column has to be edited.</p>
        <p>My husband and I have a tradition of working while playing. It began on our Hawaiian honeymoon, when Bruce spent the plane ride reading medical journals and I was awakened at an ungodly hour by this newspaper's magazine section so I could answer questions from a fact checker.</p>
        <p>Then there was the memorable summer on Block Island when I had to finish the final draft of a book and Bruce had a grant application due. We were sharing a rental house with Bruce's sister and her husband, and, between the four of us, we'd brought four cell phones, three laptops and a fax machine.</p>
        <p>This does, I admit, seem to go against the basic meaning of the word ''vacation,'' and I realize that other couples handle things differently.</p>
        <p>Cathy Seibel, for instance, is an assistant United States attorney who refuses to even think about work while on vacation. Her staff, she says, knows that she wants to be called only ''if the safety of the republic is in question,'' and, thankfully, that hasn't happened yet. But Ms. Seibel's husband, Dr. Barron Lerner, is a self-diagnosed work addict. A physician and medical historian at New York Presbyterian Hospital, he feels that time spent away from work is time spent worrying about work piling up -- in other words, only by working can he relax.</p>
        <p>In the days before laptops, Ms. Seibel and Dr. Lerner would venture to Cape Cod for just a week at a time because she grew agitated if he worked and he grew agitated if he didn't. Then, with the coming of the e-mail era, they agreed to be daring and try a two-week vacation, but first they established some carefully crafted ground rules. He was allowed to work. But only during one of the two weeks. And only at night after their two children were asleep. ''You have to do what fits each person's desires and neuroses,'' Dr. Lerner said.</p>
        <p>It is an evolving compromise. There is some question, for instance, about whether e-mails fall under the no-work-during-daylight clause.</p>
        <p>''I regard that as work, absolutely, but he regards it as an activity of daily living,'' Ms. Seibel said.</p>
        <p>And there are varying interpretations of what counts as vacation literature, too. Dr. Lerner is hoping that the new 581-page biography of the legendary physician Sir William Osler ''could qualify as a beach book.''</p>
        <p>Gail Wiggin, founder of aabalone[red], a consulting and marketing communications firm in Darien, Conn., sees vacation as a badly timed interruption of work. In the old days, she says, she would spin herself into a frenzy in the hours before V-Day, trying to tie up all the loose ends at work and at home. Now she takes what she calls the dot-com .mom vacation, which means scheduling her family's departure 24 hours ahead of her own, then spending that full day ''at warp speed,'' working virtually nonstop.</p>
        <p>''I don't have to cook, eat, answer the telephone or be sociable,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Knowing that ''every tiny bit of work is done'' means she can put that work aside for a while, and on her most recent trip, a family reunion in New Hampshire, she ''decided not to even plug in the brand new rocket ship PowerBook from which I had hitherto been inseparable.'' The dot-com.mom approach is effective, she cautions, only if you apply it on the other end, too -- leaving vacation a day before everyone else and spending 24 hours excavating your desk.</p>
        <p>I can't see that either of these solutions will work for us. Ms. Wiggin's plan, for instance, requires a marriage in which only one spouse has an over-enmeshed relationship with work.</p>
        <p>At our house we would spend so much time jockeying to be the one who stayed home that I don't think we'd ever actually leave on our trip. Because the disturbing fact is, neither of us really minds taking some work along. The laptop doesn't mar our vacation so much as it permits us to take one. If I could not have finished my book on Block Island, I couldn't have gone to Block Island. How lovely, then, that technology allows me to work in a hammock.</p>
        <p>LIFE'S WORK This column about the intersection of jobs and personal lives appears every other week. Lisa Belkin's e-mail address is Belkin@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">This column about the intersection of jobs and personal lives appears every other week. Lisa Belkin's e-mail address is Belkin@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
