<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oils Like These Don't Just Grow on Trees</title>
    <meta content="19OIL.$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215996"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oils and Fats</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fabricant, Florence</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oils and Fats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E6DA103BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="941" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oils Like These Don't Just Grow on Trees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabricant, Florence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Florence Fabricant on Novizio and other premium olive oils from Italy and elsewhere introduced at recent Fancy Food Show in Manhattan; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a world awash in olive oil, it is hard to imagine a new one that could merit singling out. But several olive oils, and one innovative grapeseed oil, are worthy of the attention of the serious cook. None are cheap, so they are probably not for dishes in which a supermarket brand  will do. But if you have a wardrobe of olive oils for different purposes, you might consider some of these.</p>
        <p>For one of them, you'll need your freezer. It's Novizio, an extra virgin olive oil from the Antinori wine family of Tuscany and Martini Bernardi, an olive oil producer, also of Tuscany. Along with 100 other oils, it was introduced last week at the Fancy Food Show, a trade exhibition in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a world awash in olive oil, it is hard to imagine a new one that could merit singling out. But several olive oils, and one innovative grapeseed oil, are worthy of the attention of the serious cook. None are cheap, so they are probably not for dishes in which a supermarket brand  will do. But if you have a wardrobe of olive oils for different purposes, you might consider some of these.</p>
        <p>For one of them, you'll need your freezer. It's Novizio, an extra virgin olive oil from the Antinori wine family of Tuscany and Martini Bernardi, an olive oil producer, also of Tuscany. Along with 100 other oils, it was introduced last week at the Fancy Food Show, a trade exhibition in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The oil, pressed in Tuscany from green olives grown in Apulia, is flash frozen as soon as it is bottled. The purpose of the unusual process, said Alessia Antinori, a daughter of Piero Antinori, the winery owner, is to ''make very fresh olive oil available all year.'' The oil has a lively freshness and is extremely fragrant, with floral notes and a peppery aftertaste.</p>
        <p>Novizio must be thawed before its first use (this can take several hours, so plan ahead) but if stored in a cool dark place, it is supposed to retain its vibrant qualities and brilliant green color for a month. After that, these qualities will begin to diminish, but it still will be an excellent oil. Do not try to refreeze it once it has thawed. (One complaint is that the bottle has a standard wine cork, which makes resealing difficult.)</p>
        <p>Freshness is critical to the quality of olive oil. Better oils have a harvest date listed on their labels, and should be used within a year, preferably six months, of purchase.</p>
        <p>Whether consumers will be willing to pay the higher price for the extra freshness promised by Novizio remains to be seen.  This oil has such a fresh taste that it would be delicious drizzled on ripe tomatoes or over grilled wild striped bass. Dean &amp; DeLuca, 560 Broadway (Prince Street), and Grace's Marketplace, 1237 Third Avenue (71st Street), are expected to have the oil by the end of the month, with an 8.7-ounce bottle priced at around $15 and a 17.5-ounce bottle at $25.</p>
        <p>Another oil, named the best new product at the show, is ruby grapefruit olive oil by O, a company in San Rafael, Calif., whose citrus-flavored organic extra virgin oils are made by crushing the whole fruit and olives together. The company already makes olive oils blended with blood oranges, Tahitian limes and Meyer lemons. The newest oil is rich, with hints of tart and sweet. Because pink grapefruit is such a splendid complement for sweet seafood like shrimp, scallops and red snapper, this oil would provide a lovely finishing touch to the preparation, or could dress a salad served alongside. It will be available in specialty shops next month for about $18 an 8.8-ounce bottle.</p>
        <p>Supremo, of Hayward, Calif., also has a line of flavored organic extra virgin olive oils, which it makes by infusing the oils with citrus peels. They have piquant notes of lemon, lime and orange zest, making them good for dishes like cold tomato soup, but they are less complex than O's oils. A 6.4-ounce bottle will sell for $10 next month.</p>
        <p>Another citrus oil is the Meyer lemon extra virgin olive oil made by Da Vero in Healdsburg, Calif. This oil is made like O's, by crushing the fruit and olives together. It tastes more of olives than fruit, and the citrus adds only a subtle, pleasantly bitter presence. It's tailor-made for steamed or grilled asparagus, or to trace over sheep's milk cheese. The oil, in a 12.7-ounce bottle, is sold for $20, plus shipping, by Katz and Company in Napa, Calif., (800) 676-7176.</p>
        <p>A more unusual newcomer is Salute  Sante's cold-pressed extra virgin grapeseed oil, which is made from grapeseeds that have not been allowed to ferment after the grapes are pressed for wine. Unlike typical grapeseed oils, which are pale and fairly neutral tasting, this one, made by Food &amp; Vine in Napa, is greenish and somewhat more viscous and has a sweet, floral aroma and a mellow, slightly fruity taste. It is also unfiltered, which gives it the richer color, yet it's not cloudy with sediment. Like most grapeseed oils, it does not solidify when refrigerated, so you don't get clumps in your salad dressing or marinade, which you might if you used olive oil.</p>
        <p>But this is a jewel-box oil, in a dark bottle  with gold leaf on the label, which costs $30 for eight ounces (www.grapeseedoil.com); it will be in stores this fall. So use it sparingly, as a seasoning for salmon poached in white wine, in a sauce for leeks vinaigrette or on a tender salad scattered with walnuts and pears.</p>
        <p>In this age of specialization, Food &amp; Vine is now developing varietal grapeseed oils. First on the list is chardonnay, so the oil can match your glass of wine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
