<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Aw-Shucks Facade, and Food With Style</title>
    <meta content="19REST$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215989"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Grocery, The (Brooklyn Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimes, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E3DB103BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1167" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Aw-Shucks Facade, and Food With Style</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Grimes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Grimes reviews The Grocery, Brooklyn restaurant; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BY the time I made my final visit to the Grocery, I was used to the ritual. At some point in the meal, I knew, Charles Kiely, one of the two chefs, would approach the table and stand silently, with drooping shoulders and a depressed expression, like a young Tim Conway. Bad news was coming.</p>
        <p>''We overcooked the duck,'' he said one evening. Sigh. The visit before, it had been a scallop special that arrived several scallops short, but with an unadvertised halibut fillet. ''I guess I got caught,'' Mr. Kiely said mournfully. ''Eleven people ordered the special and we ran out, so I tried to come up with something else.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BY the time I made my final visit to the Grocery, I was used to the ritual. At some point in the meal, I knew, Charles Kiely, one of the two chefs, would approach the table and stand silently, with drooping shoulders and a depressed expression, like a young Tim Conway. Bad news was coming.</p>
        <p>''We overcooked the duck,'' he said one evening. Sigh. The visit before, it had been a scallop special that arrived several scallops short, but with an unadvertised halibut fillet. ''I guess I got caught,'' Mr. Kiely said mournfully. ''Eleven people ordered the special and we ran out, so I tried to come up with something else.''</p>
        <p>The Grocery likes to project the image of the little restaurant that could, a struggling Brooklyn storefront operation where things can and will go wrong, but in a way that makes you laugh. Don't be fooled by the act. Despite serious service problems, it is a focused, high-quality restaurant that, in fits and starts, rises to heights that make it much more than a nice neighborhood spot.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiely and Sharon Pachter own the Grocery and do the cooking. Both have done tours of duty in Manhattan  at Savoy and at Gotham Bar and Grill. Both know how to shop. Many restaurants sell themselves as market-driven, but the Grocery follows through on the pledge. Fresh produce, good fish and flavorful meat are the foundation of the Grocery's cuisine, an internationalized style of bistro cooking with an Italian insistence on pristine ingredients. To drive the point home, each table is adorned with a raw root vegetable instead of flowers. The kitchen's idea of an amuse-bouche is to lightly saute coin-size slices of turnip, carrot, potato, zucchini and radish, stack them in a neat pile and add a little splash of rice vinegar. It sends a message. The taste adventure here is about purity.</p>
        <p>A big bowl of steamed Manila clams, so often tasteless and tough, get loving treatment from Mr. Kiely and Ms. Pachter, who cut back severely on the broth, a heady garlic-herb essence accented with sorrel, that soaks through a scattering of buttered croutons without weakening their chewy texture. Seared tuna, another appetizer, gets the lightest possible dusting of cumin, a note that's amplified in a cumin-yogurt sauce. A bright-red pile of shaved beets, tart and sweet, sends this little dish right into orbit.</p>
        <p>The Grocery does not strain for effect. The revised and corrected version of the duck breast, when it finally arrived, was winningly simple, served on a bed of fluffy bulgur soaked in a well-reduced, very fruity red-wine sauce punctuated by black currants and bits of carrot. A grilled whole trout was nicely complemented by a light dill vinaigrette, crispy spatzle and unadorned green beans. Baked halibut, bland and unimpressive on my first visit, got some fine-tuning and moved to the head of the class, a sizable block of firm, snowy meat, swathed in a rich sauce of creme fraiche and broth, flavored with tiny chunks of smoked, salty bacon and sliced fava beans.</p>
        <p>Given the very high standards of my favorite dishes, it was doubly disappointing to work through some mediocrities on the very short menu of six appetizers and six entrees. Duck confit wrapped in a buckwheat crepe was surprisingly flavorless. Risotto with spring vegetables is a mushy middle-of-the-roader, an almost neutral background for the dandyish squash-blossom fritter that adorns it. The fritter needs its own show. Grilled flank steak reminded me of cafeteria food, tough slices of meat surrounding a swamp of stewed peppers, onions and rice.</p>
        <p>The menu finishes strong with excellent, homey desserts with an exotic touch here and there, like the sour cream and lemon grass sorbet that accompanies a plum upside-down cake. Two steamed puddings vie for supremacy. Chocolate pudding, moistened with rum and sherry and packed with bits of walnut and coconut, seems unbeatable: a moist, blackish tower of strength lavished with coconut cream and a glistening chocolate sauce. It cannot quite compete, however, with the steamed ginger pudding, a spicy dream of a dessert, surrounded with poached nectarines and a puff of vanilla whipped cream.</p>
        <p>The Grocery has the charm and the drawbacks that make many of Brooklyn's restaurants a pleasure-pain trade-off. It's in a small, simple storefront, and seating is cramped. In warm weather, the backyard garden, with its spreading fig tree, offers relief from the crowded, very noisy conditions in the dining room. In either location, prepare to wait. And wait. So long that, by the time dessert arrives, the root vegetable on the table has begun to soften. The kitchen cannot really cope with a full house, but the food is good, so the house is almost always full.</p>
        <p>This leads to one gaffe after another. Once a bottle of wine is opened and the first round is poured, you might never see it again. One evening, in the long interval between appetizer and main course, a waitress appeared with the duck crepe and set it down in front of me. ''I think I've already eaten this,'' I said. The waitress was unfazed. ''You're going to eat it again,'' she said and then walked away. We sorted things out eventually.</p>
        <p>My advice is to take a good book. The food will arrive. Honest. And Mr. Kiely will show up at least once to throw one of those sorrowful glances that remind you that you're not the only one in the world with problems. Sure it's an act. But the Grocery is good enough to let him get away with it.</p>
        <p>The Grocery  * [Rating: One Star]</p>
        <p>288 Smith Street, Brooklyn; (718) 596-3335</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE: A tiny storefront dining room with garden in back, serving new American bistro fare with an emphasis on fresh ingredients.  SOUND LEVEL: Very loud in the dining room; quiet in the garden.  RECOMMENDED DISHES: Steamed clams in garlic-herb broth, seared tuna with beet relish and cumin yogurt, duck breast with warm bulgur salad, baked halibut with fava beans and bacon, steamed chocolate pudding, steamed ginger pudding, plum upside-down cake.  SERVICE: Friendly but very slow and fumbling.  WINE LIST: A modestly priced, eclectic 35-bottle list, with nine wines by the glass.  PRICE RANGE: Dinner, appetizers, $6 to $8; entrees, $16 to $19; desserts, $6 to $7.  HOURS: Monday through Thursday, 6 to 10 p.m. Friday and Saturday, 6 to 11 p.m.  CREDIT CARDS: Visa and MasterCard.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: One step down to garden. Restrooms not wheelchair accessible.</p>
        <p>WHAT THE STARS MEAN:</p>
        <p>(None) Poor to satisfactory  * Good  ** Very good  *** Excellent  **** Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>Past restaurant reviews from The New York Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics, are available on New York Today: www.nytoday.com</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
