<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putting a New Italian Spot to the Ninth Avenue Test</title>
    <meta content="19UNDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215986"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="$25 AND UNDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Locanda, La (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asimov, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E6DB103BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putting a New Italian Spot to the Ninth Avenue Test</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eric Asimov</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eric Asimov reviews La Locanda, Italian restaurant in Midtown Manhattan (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK has so many Italian restaurants that anybody hoping to open another should have to take an entrance exam, as if applying to colleges. The test would consist of one simple question: What will your restaurant offer that all those others do not?</p>
        <p>For La Locanda, a bright little storefront restaurant that opened in Clinton about three months ago, the owners might have responded like this: ''On Ninth Avenue, an area already replete with generic Italian menus, La Locanda will not only serve pastas and meat dishes that stand out for their simplicity and flavor, but also offer an enticing and unusually arranged wine list.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK has so many Italian restaurants that anybody hoping to open another should have to take an entrance exam, as if applying to colleges. The test would consist of one simple question: What will your restaurant offer that all those others do not?</p>
        <p>For La Locanda, a bright little storefront restaurant that opened in Clinton about three months ago, the owners might have responded like this: ''On Ninth Avenue, an area already replete with generic Italian menus, La Locanda will not only serve pastas and meat dishes that stand out for their simplicity and flavor, but also offer an enticing and unusually arranged wine list.''</p>
        <p>I would call that an honest answer, free of exaggeration and false claims, though I would offer some marginal comments. First, skip the antipasti. With dishes like dry bruschetta, carpaccio and prosciutto and melon, they are the least interesting part of the menu. Start instead with the basket of bread and focaccia, freshly baked at La Locanda's bakery, Il Forno, which is just around the corner. The bread is particularly good with a scoop of lentils, served in a little bowl where they've been marinating in garlic and herbs.</p>
        <p>Second, try one of the large and alluring salads, like insalata rifredda ($9), essentially an Italian version of the frisee salad, a bistro classic, made with goat cheese and cubes of pancetta, which are crisp on the surface and soft within, having absorbed some of the salad's delicious balsamic vinaigrette. Or try a refreshing insalata di riso ($8), a mound of rice concealing mozzarella and summer vegetables within, dressed with olive oil and herbs.</p>
        <p>Pastas can be excellent, either as a shared appetizer or as a main course. The chef, Ivan Beacco, who formerly cooked at Borgo Antico in Greenwich Village, is refreshingly unfussy in his approach, allowing simple combinations of flavors to speak for themselves without muddying them with extra ingredients.</p>
        <p>Penne alla Genovese ($12.50) is perfectly al dente, with carrots, celery and onions cooked until meltingly sweet and flavored with a sprinkle of herbs. Orecchiette with broccoli rape and house-made sausage ($13) is excellent, with the mellow meat rounding off the bitterness of the green, while linguine with tiny clams and garlic ($14.50) sounds familiar but is given an unusual, breezy quality by a careful addition of herbs. Only spaghetti with cherry tomatoes and onions ($11) failed to impress; the tomatoes created so much liquid that the rest of the dish drowned.</p>
        <p>Mr. Beacco's meat dishes also benefit from his restraint, which seems to make up for a tendency toward overcooking. His sliced leg of lamb ($18), served like all the main courses with roasted potatoes and sauteed broccoli rape, is past the point of pink, but the sauce, simply lamb juices and herbs, imbues the meat with flavor. The same is true of veal shoulder ($17), which is no longer pink but is aromatic and delicious in its sauce of herbs, white wine and veal juices, and grilled calf's liver ($18.50), served with caramelized onions and balsamic vinegar, which sweetens the liver's earthy flavor. Fish dishes are not as resilient, alas, and careful saucing cannot revive salmon ($18) once it is overdone.</p>
        <p>Service is buoyant and friendly, but (depending on whether you're in a hurry) either very slow or pleasantly relaxed. The wine list is large for this sort of restaurant and worth noting. It divides bottles into four price categories and includes good choices at both $20 and $26 a bottle.</p>
        <p>Because La Locanda has its own bakery, it makes its own desserts, some of which are quite good, another thing that sets it apart from many inexpensive Italian restaurants. Skip tiramisu and profiteroles, and opt instead for the rustic blueberry tart ($5) or the compact French-style strawberry tart ($5).</p>
        <p>When all is said and done, La Locanda passes the test.</p>
        <p>La Locanda</p>
        <p>737 Ninth Avenue, near 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 258-2900.</p>
        <p>BEST DISHES: Frisee salad; rice salad; penne with celery, carrots and onions; orecchiette with broccoli rape and sausage; linguine with clams and herbs; sliced leg of lamb; veal shoulder; roasted pork with green olive and mustard sauce; sauteed calf's liver; blueberry tart; strawberry tart.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE: Appetizers, $7.50 to $11; pastas and main courses, $11 to $21.50.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS: All major cards.</p>
        <p>HOURS: Monday through Saturday, noon to 3 p.m., 5 to 11:30 p.m. Closed Sundays in July and August.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: Step at entrance; restrooms are small and entryway is narrow.</p>
        <p>$25 AND UNDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
