<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sun Finally Heats Up And So Does Virenque</title>
    <meta content="19TOUR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216063"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CYCLING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abt, Samuel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Virenque, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armstrong, Lance</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E1DC113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="707" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sun Finally Heats Up And So Does Virenque</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAMUEL ABT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Abt, Samuel</byline>
      <dateline>MORZINE, France, July 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Virenque wins 16th stage of Tour de France; Lance Armstrong remains overall leader (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Richard Virenque  ''Ree-shar,'' in a wail, to nearly every adolescent in France -- finally gave his fans something concrete to celebrate today.</p>
        <p>Virenque, the controversial French star, shone with only secondary magnitude through the first 15 of 21 daily stages in this 87th Tour de France. But his Technicolor dreams came true on the last of three days in the Alps as he powered away on the final climb, negotiated a tricky curve that wiped out his one companion and easily finished first.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Richard Virenque  ''Ree-shar,'' in a wail, to nearly every adolescent in France -- finally gave his fans something concrete to celebrate today.</p>
        <p>Virenque, the controversial French star, shone with only secondary magnitude through the first 15 of 21 daily stages in this 87th Tour de France. But his Technicolor dreams came true on the last of three days in the Alps as he powered away on the final climb, negotiated a tricky curve that wiped out his one companion and easily finished first.</p>
        <p>The leader of the Polti team and five-time winner of the king of the mountains jersey in the Tour, Virenque credited the return of a hot sun. Not that hot, actually -- temperatures atop the last of five climbs barely reached 20 degrees Centigrade (68 degrees Fahrenheit) -- but at least this was no longer the Tour of Frigid France, as it has been since the start on July 1.</p>
        <p>''I like hot weather,'' Virenque said. ''I like the sun. I ride best in hot weather.''</p>
        <p>While the forecast until the finish in Paris on Sunday is for continuing sun and heat, there are only small hills left to be climbed and Virenque seems destined not to win a sixth climbing jersey, tying the record. He ranks third in that subdivision.</p>
        <p>For the moment, though, he fulfills another goal: In fifth place over all, he is the highest-ranking Frenchman behind the continuing leader, Lance Armstrong, the defending champion and chief of the United States Postal Service team.</p>
        <p>Armstrong, a Texan, did not have a good day. ''The hardest day of my life on a bike,'' he called it after he finished eighth, 2 minutes 1 second behind the winner.</p>
        <p>''The problem was a fringale,'' Armstrong explained, using the French word for what is called ''the bonk'' in English. In any language, it translates into a sudden loss of energy.</p>
        <p>''I didn't eat enough and on the last climb had no energy,'' he said. On the narrow alpine road, his team car could not get to him to supply nourishment and he had no teammate with him to drop back and fetch it.</p>
        <p>Armstrong started that climb, the 11.8-kilometer (7.3-mile) Joux Plane in fine position just behind an early breakaway that was leading the stage. He was about a third of the way up, riding with Virenque and Jan Ullrich, the German in second place, when he began to fall back.</p>
        <p>His face strained and his pedaling uneasy for the first time in this Tour, Armstrong continued to lose ground. Soon he was a minute behind his two former companions.</p>
        <p>''I just tried to limit my losses,'' he said afterward. ''I told myself to just stay in control and don't panic.''</p>
        <p>Mission accomplished. His lead over Ullrich, who finished second in the stage, shrunk two minutes to a still-safe 5:37.</p>
        <p>Virenque is fifth, 7:36 behind, with Christophe Moreau of Festina, also a Frenchman, sixth, 8:22 behind. In their fight for the dubious honor of top Frenchman, Moreau holds the advantage since he is a fine time trialer and a long race against the clock is scheduled Friday.</p>
        <p>Virenque was timed in 5:32:20 for the 196.5-kilometer (122-mile) 16th stage from Courchevel, a speed of 35 kilometers an hour (about 22 m.p.h.). Ullrich was 24 seconds slower, with Heras third, 27 seconds behind the winner.</p>
        <p>The major wipeout of the day was Marco Pantani, the fine Italian climber and leader of the Mercatone Uno team, who won the Tour in 1998. Possibly stung by Armstrong's criticism of him on Monday as a whiner and ingrate, Pantani attacked on the first of the day's climbs, far earlier than he usually does.</p>
        <p>He built a lead of nearly two minutes, as if he was determined to show Armstrong who really is boss, then Pantani fell apart. By the final climb, he was at the tail end of the main group. Soon he was going uphill at the speed of somebody on a bicycle heading for the grocery.</p>
        <p>CYCLING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
