<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Region Braces for Spraying to Battle the West Nile Virus</title>
    <meta content="19NILE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216142"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anvil (Pesticide)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Scourge (Pesticide)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Staten Island (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershaw, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E6D7113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="998" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Region Braces for Spraying to Battle the West Nile Virus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH KERSHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershaw, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>People of Staten Island brace themselves for spraying with pesticide in response to signs of West Nile virus there; Westchester County officials will also begin spraying same chemical, Anvil; Suffolk County is spraying with Anvil and another chemical, Scourge; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As residents of Staten Island braced themselves yesterday for spraying with the pesticide Anvil in response to signs of West Nile virus there, Westchester County officials announced that they would also begin spraying the same chemical tomorrow.</p>
        <p>''This was a very difficult decision personally for me to make,'' Andrew J. Spano, the Westchester County executive, said yesterday after a pool of mosquitoes had tested positive for the disease. ''We want to reduce the use of pesticides in the county, and I have said over and over again it was our goal to avoid having to use them.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As residents of Staten Island braced themselves yesterday for spraying with the pesticide Anvil in response to signs of West Nile virus there, Westchester County officials announced that they would also begin spraying the same chemical tomorrow.</p>
        <p>''This was a very difficult decision personally for me to make,'' Andrew J. Spano, the Westchester County executive, said yesterday after a pool of mosquitoes had tested positive for the disease. ''We want to reduce the use of pesticides in the county, and I have said over and over again it was our goal to avoid having to use them.''</p>
        <p>The announcement in Westchester came a day after New York City officials said that they would begin spraying the ground across half of Staten Island starting tonight because two dead crows had tested positive for the virus, which the authorities said sickened 62 people in the region last year, killing 7.</p>
        <p>In the city, where the outbreak began last year in northern Queens, no mosquitoes have tested positive for the virus.</p>
        <p>City health officials have urged hospitals to send the blood of anyone even remotely suspected of having the virus for analysis, and a Health Department spokeswoman said that dozens of samples had been tested so far and all had come back negative. Last night, officials at St. Vincent's Hospital on Staten Island said that a 71-year-old man admitted last week with symptoms of a general infection was now being tested for the virus.</p>
        <p>''Some of the symptoms fit, but unfortunately West Nile has pretty generic symptoms,'' said William McCann, a hospital spokesman. ''But once we found that there there were dead crows on Staten Island that did test positive, our infectious disease specialists said that this could very well be a case.'' He said the test results were expected by the end of the week.</p>
        <p>In Suffolk County on Long Island, where infected birds and mosquitoes were found, spraying of Anvil and another pesticide, Scourge, began Monday night and was scheduled to continue last night. In New York City and in Westchester, officials will use trucks to spray Anvil, part of a class of pesticides known as synthetic pyrethroids, which mimic the natural pesticide produced by chrysanthemum flowers. Scourge, a pesticide from the same family, may also be used if more spraying is needed in other parts of the city, officials said.</p>
        <p>For the residents of Staten Island preparing for the spraying yesterday, news that their neighborhoods would be sprayed was greeted with a mixture of relief and worry. ''I wish we didn't have this problem at all, but I'd rather have the spray than have the mosquitoes,'' said Kelly Zappalorti, who lives in Rossville and has a 6-year-old son whom she has already taken to a doctor once, fearing he had contracted the virus from mosquitoes in Wolf's Pond Park.</p>
        <p>Angela Amari, 36, of New Springville, said: ''I have mixed feelings. The spray could hurt people, but it could also help people. The virus is something a perfectly healthy person could become extremely sick with. It's a double-edged sword.''</p>
        <p>Several environmental experts said those pesticides tend to have fewer health effects on humans than Malathion, the pesticide that was used during a spraying campaign last year that drew vociferous opposition from environmental groups.</p>
        <p>In April, city officials said they would no longer use Malathion, which affects the central nervous system in mosquitoes and, in large enough doses, in humans. It is generally considered more toxic than the pesticides that are being used this year, officials from the Environmental Protection Agency said.</p>
        <p>The synthetic pyrethroids ''are generally not as potent or toxic chemicals to humans,'' Steven Johnson, the agency's deputy administrator for the office of Prevention, Pesticides and Toxic Substances, said.</p>
        <p>However, he added: ''No pesticide is 100 percent safe. These are intended to kill insects. So people need to use common sense and precaution.''</p>
        <p>Anvil and Scourge are extremely toxic to fish and will not be sprayed in lakes, ponds or other areas containing live fish, officials said.</p>
        <p>Nina Habib Spencer, a spokeswoman for the E.P.A., said the maximum amount of Anvil that can be sprayed legally, 0.0036 of a pound per square acre, is ''enough to kill mosquitoes but a very low dose where humans are concerned.''</p>
        <p>Still, health and environmental officials said the pesticides, which are absorbed through mosquitoes' respiratory systems, could aggravate respiratory problems like asthma in people, and could also cause minor skin, throat and eye irritations.</p>
        <p>And officials encouraged all residents of areas being sprayed to stay indoors and keep their pets inside during the spraying hours, keep windows closed and air-conditioners, which could allow the pesticide to enter their homes, turned off. Officials also urged residents to wash any toys or equipment left outside before use.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
