<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earnings at Coke Bottler Narrowly Beat Expectations</title>
    <meta content="Y19COKE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216043"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coca-Cola Enterprises</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hays, Constance L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E7DD113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earnings at Coke Bottler Narrowly Beat Expectations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE L. HAYS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hays, Constance L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coca-Cola Enterprises says second-quarter profit rose 26 percent, narrowly beating analysts' expectations; profit increased to $131 million compared with $104 million in year-earlier quarter; revenue rose 8 percent, to $4.03 billion from $3.8 billion (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In results that narrowly beat analysts' expectations, Coca-Cola Enterprises said yesterday that its second-quarter profit rose 26 percent.</p>
        <p>Profit from operations at the company, Coca-Cola's largest bottler, increased to $131 million, or 31 cents a share, compared with $104 million, or 24 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In results that narrowly beat analysts' expectations, Coca-Cola Enterprises said yesterday that its second-quarter profit rose 26 percent.</p>
        <p>Profit from operations at the company, Coca-Cola's largest bottler, increased to $131 million, or 31 cents a share, compared with $104 million, or 24 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier.</p>
        <p>In the most recent period, a one-time charge of $12 million for layoffs in Britain, where Coca-Cola Enterprises is struggling with lower-priced Coke products in what has been one of its more lucrative businesses, made net income $123 million, or 29 cents a share. Results in the period a year earlier included a $103 million charge for recalling products from France and Belgium, making net income $34 million, or 8 cents a share.</p>
        <p>Analysts had expected the company to earn 28 cents a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial.</p>
        <p>Revenue rose 8 percent, to $4.03 billion from $3.8 billion, though sales volume declined in North America, its largest market, and in Britain, another major market.</p>
        <p>''They were slightly ahead because of higher pricing in North America and higher sales costs, but it was nothing to write home about,'' said Bill Pecoriello, a beverage analyst for Sanford C. Bernstein.</p>
        <p>Volume in North America, which accounts for most of the bottler's sales, continues to be uncertain. While revenue per case increased 5 percent, consumers seemed to be balking at higher prices charged in supermarkets, where until recently Coke and Pepsi were locked in a price war that kept the cost of six-packs and two-liter bottles low.</p>
        <p>Coke and its archrival are betting that higher prices will eventually be accepted by consumers, but so far consumers seem reluctant. Sales of store-brand soda, which is cheaper, have increased at double-digit rates this year, according to data compiled by Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette. The soft-drink category is up 2.5 percent for the year, while store-brand soda has grown 9.5 percent.</p>
        <p>Volume growth is essential to Coca-Cola's earnings growth. The company's chairman has said he expects volume to increase 5 percent to 6 percent worldwide this year, and rise 7 percent to 8 percent next year.</p>
        <p>''We continue to expect full-year volume in North America to be flat to up 1 percent versus the prior year,'' said John R. Alm, Coca-Cola Enterprises' president and chief operating officer. Coca-Cola Enterprises, which is 40 percent owned by Coca-Cola, accounts for 74 percent of Coke's North American sales in bottles and cans.</p>
        <p>In a conference call with analysts in May, Mr. Alm warned that domestic volume would increase just 1 percent to 2 percent this year, while estimates had been 2 percent to 3 percent. After he made that announcement, his company's share price plummeted $6.9375, to $15.625, a 52-week low. Shares of Coca-Cola were dragged lower as well, losing $3, to $48.9375.</p>
        <p>The newly lowered volume estimates did not take a toll on the stock yesterday. Shares of Coca-Cola Enterprises rose yesterday by just less than $1, to close at $18.4375. Coca-Cola is holding a conference call today to discuss its own second-quarter results, which are being announced this morning.</p>
        <p>The bottler's sales were up 5 percent in the more lucrative vending area, the company said. In Europe, sales rose 15.5 percent in the quarter, although the second quarter of last year was a particularly bleak one, in which Coke products were pulled from store shelves and production halted in Belgium and France because of contamination fears.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
