<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="19TRAN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E2D7113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>AMERICAN LEAGUE  CLEVELAND INDIANS -- Purchased the contract of LHP Cameron Cairncross from Akron of the Eastern League. Designated LHP Andrew Lorraine for assignment.  DETROIT TIGERS -- Placed OF Juan Gonzalez on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to July 6.  KANSAS CITY ROYALS -- Activated 2B Carlos Febles from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned RHP Brett Laxton to Omaha of the PCL.  NEW YORK YANKEES -- Placed RHP Orlando Hernandez on the 15-day disabled list. Recalled RHP Darrell Einertson from Columbus of the International League.  TAMPA BAY DEVIL RAYS -- Activated DH Jose Canseco from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned OF Randy Winn to Durham of the International League.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>AMERICAN LEAGUE  CLEVELAND INDIANS -- Purchased the contract of LHP Cameron Cairncross from Akron of the Eastern League. Designated LHP Andrew Lorraine for assignment.  DETROIT TIGERS -- Placed OF Juan Gonzalez on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to July 6.  KANSAS CITY ROYALS -- Activated 2B Carlos Febles from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned RHP Brett Laxton to Omaha of the PCL.  NEW YORK YANKEES -- Placed RHP Orlando Hernandez on the 15-day disabled list. Recalled RHP Darrell Einertson from Columbus of the International League.  TAMPA BAY DEVIL RAYS -- Activated DH Jose Canseco from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned OF Randy Winn to Durham of the International League.</p>
        <p>National League  PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES -- Recalled C Gary Bennett from Scranton/Wilkes-Barre of the International League. Activated LHP Mark Holzemer from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned RHP David Coggin and RHP Steve Schrenk to Scranton.  PITTSBURGH PIRATES -- Activated OF Bruce Aven from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned OF Chad Hermansen to Nashville of the PCL.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  CHARLOTTE HORNETS -- Signed C Jamaal Magloire.  MILWAUKEE BUCKS -- Signed G Michael Redd to a two-year contract.  SACRAMENTO KINGS -- Signed F-C Jabari Smith.  VANCOUVER GRIZZLIES -- Signed F Stromile Swift to a three-year contract.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  DETROIT LIONS -- Signed CB Marquis Walker to a one-year contract.  MIAMI DOLPHINS -- Signed S Chris Bayne and DE David Hoelscher.  MINNESOTA VIKINGS -- Signed RB Marvin Welch.  NEW YORK GIANTS -- Waived CB Conrad Hamilton.  ST. LOUIS RAMS -- Promoted wide receivers coach Al Saunders to associate head coach, and running backs coach Bobby Jackson to offensive coordinator.  SAN DIEGO CHARGERS -- Signed QB JaJuan Seider and CB Damen Wheeler to two-year contracts.  TENNESSEE TITANS -- Signed RB Eddie George to a six-year contract extension.  WASHINGTON REDSKINS -- Signed OT Chris Samuels to a six-year contract.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  ATLANTA THRASHERS -- Agreed to terms with D David Harlock on a two-year contract.  CHICAGO BLACKHAWKS -- Signed F Valeri Zelepukin.  COLUMBUS BLUE JACKETS -- Named Gerard Gallant assistant coach.  PHOENIX COYOTES -- Announced the resignation of Bill Lesuk director of scouting.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
