<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="19FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216144"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E5D7113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1090" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Clinton Delays Trip As Peace Deadline Looms  In an effort to finalize a Middle East peace accord, President Clinton delayed his trip to Japan by one day and will stay at Camp David with the Israeli Prime Minister Ehud Barak and the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, the White House announced.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Help for AIDS Fight in Africa  The United States plans to offer sub-Saharan African nations $1 billion in loans annually to finance the purchase of American AIDS drugs and medical services.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Clinton Delays Trip As Peace Deadline Looms  In an effort to finalize a Middle East peace accord, President Clinton delayed his trip to Japan by one day and will stay at Camp David with the Israeli Prime Minister Ehud Barak and the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, the White House announced.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Help for AIDS Fight in Africa  The United States plans to offer sub-Saharan African nations $1 billion in loans annually to finance the purchase of American AIDS drugs and medical services.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>British Law on Web Privacy  The British government is set to enact a law giving authorities broad powers to intercept and decode e-mail messages and other communications between companies, organizations and individual citizens.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Chinese-Russian Summit  The presidents of China and Russia denounced the United States's proposed missile defense program in a joint statement and vowed to strengthen a strategic partnership between their nations.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Chechen Leaders Quarrel  The Chechen leaders appointed by Moscow quarreled bitterly among themselves, underscoring the difficulties Russia has encountered in establishing a Chechen government.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Serbian Protest in Kosovo  Thousands of Serbs, angry over the arrest of a Serb accused of attacking Kosovo Albanians, blocked roads into their part of ethnically divided Mitrovica and staged rallies to demand the suspect's release.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Khmer Rouge Officer Acquitted  Chhouk Rin, a former Khmer Rouge commander accused in the 1994 murders of three Western tourists, was acquitted when a court ruled that he was covered by a law granting amnesty to guerrilla defectors.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>New Fiji Government on Hold  The swearing-in of Fiji's Cabinet was postponed after the island's new president was reported ill.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-23</p>
        <p>Senate Passes Tax Cut For Married Couples  The Senate passed a tax cut for married couples, 61 to 38. The measure would reduce taxes for nearly all married couples by $248 billion over the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Buchanan May Take Over Party  Patrick J. Buchanan now stands on the verge taking full control of the Reform party, which he joined less than a year ago after abandoning his Republican roots. His ultimate triumph depends upon what happens at a hastily called session of the Reform national committee, planned for Aug. 8.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>California Electric Deregulation  In one of the most ambitious plans ever under electrical deregulation, every piece of California's system of 174 dams, 99 reservoirs, 68 power plants, 380 miles of artificial waterways and hundreds of thousands of acres of land could be auctioned off by sometime next year. The move has raised concerns about how the need for providing electrical power would be balanced against the need to protect the environment.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Inquiry of Soldier's Death  An Army investigation of events surrounding the murder of a gay private by a fellow soldier at a base in Kentucky has exonerated all officers of blame and concluded that no climate of homophobia exists at the base, Pentagon officials said.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>More Scrutiny for Gore  Representative Dan Burton urged Justice Department lawyers to question Vice President Al Gore about a remark that he made on a videotape of a White House coffee in December 1995.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Early Testing of Cholesterol  A study has found that even men under the age of 40 with high cholesterol run an increased risk of heart disease and premature death, underscoring the importance of early screening and preventive treatment.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>State to Take Monkey From a Brooklyn Family  The state has won permission to take Cookie, a diana monkey, from the home of a Brooklyn family and place her into an animal rescue program at the Detroit Zoo. Neighbors have threatened to fight Cookie's forced removal to the end.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New Jersey Governor's Race  Senator Robert G. Torricelli has all but officially declared his candidacy for the Democratic nomination for governor, setting off a pitched battle with Mayor James E. McGreevey of Woodbridge, the party's nominee in 1997, for the support of officials across New Jersey.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton on Health Plans  Hillary Rodham Clinton, at a news conference at Columbia-Presbyterian Center in Manhattan, presented her plan to extend health insurance to millions of Americans, including 1.1 million New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>Mayor Giuliani defended his former opponent in the Senate race, saying that he believed Mrs. Clinton when she denied making an anti-Semitic slur in 1974.</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-10</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>New Kennedy Center President  Michael Kaiser, the New York theater and ballet manager who helped rescue Royal Opera House at Covent Garden in London from a financial crisis, is about to be named president of the Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, a Kennedy Center official said.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Paul Coverdell  An influential Senate Republican leader from Georgia, he was 61.</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-26</p>
        <p>C.P.I. Up Slightly  The Consumer Price Index jumped by 0.6 of a percent in June, the Labor Department reported. The rise comes as rising oil and natural gas prices squeeze nearly every household.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Aetna Falls Short  Aetna said that it would not meet second-quarter earnings forecasts because its health care costs were rising faster than expected. Surprised investors drove down Aetna's stock price.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Job Cuts at Merrill Lynch  Merrill Lynch &amp; Company officials said that the firm will eliminate about 1,800 jobs, mostly at its brokerage operations in New Jersey. An internal announcement of the job cuts came after Merrill said its second-quarter earnings rose 34 percent.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Markets Close Down  The Nasdaq was down 97.50, or 2.3 percent, to 4,177.17; the Dow fell 64.35, or 0.6 percent, to 10,739.92, and the S.&amp; P. 500 fell 16.75, or 1.1 percent, to 1,493.74.</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A24-25</p>
        <p>Editorials: A pro-choice chance for Mr. Bush; cell phones and safety; the struggle over certified teachers; leaving environmental law alone.</p>
        <p>Columns: Paul Krugman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E7  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D7</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
