<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Aetna Says Rising Costs Will Lead It to Miss Earnings Forecasts</title>
    <meta content="Y19AETN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aetna Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ing Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donaldson, William H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freudenheim, Milt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E6DC113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1043" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Aetna Says Rising Costs Will Lead It to Miss Earnings Forecasts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MILT FREUDENHEIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freudenheim, Milt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Aetna, nation's biggest health insurance company, says it will not meet second-quarter earnings forecasts because its health care costs are rising faster than expected; surprised investors drive down Aetna's stock price; announcement raises questions about Aetna's plans to reorganize and sell its nonhealth units to ING Group; chief executive William H Donaldson says operations will be tightened to increase efficiency; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aetna, the nation's biggest health insurance company, said yesterday that it would not meet second-quarter earnings forecasts because its health care costs were rising faster than expected. Surprised investors drove down Aetna's stock price.</p>
        <p>Some analysts said the announcement raised questions about Aetna's plans to reorganize and sell its nonhealth units to the ING Group of the Netherlands. Final agreement on the sale of Aetna's international and financial services units still has not been reached, people close to the deal said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Aetna, the nation's biggest health insurance company, said yesterday that it would not meet second-quarter earnings forecasts because its health care costs were rising faster than expected. Surprised investors drove down Aetna's stock price.</p>
        <p>Some analysts said the announcement raised questions about Aetna's plans to reorganize and sell its nonhealth units to the ING Group of the Netherlands. Final agreement on the sale of Aetna's international and financial services units still has not been reached, people close to the deal said.</p>
        <p>Although ING was not directly concerned with the results in Aetna's main health business, some analysts said the earnings announcement could give ING a psychological advantage in the negotiations.</p>
        <p>Aetna said its second-quarter earnings would be 85 to 95 cents a share, well below analysts' estimates of $1.20 a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial, which tracks company earnings.</p>
        <p>The company said medical costs in its core commercial health maintenance organizations rose 10 percent to 12 percent in the second quarter, as members spent more time in hospitals, emergency rooms, outpatient surgery centers and doctors' offices. It promised to provide more information on the problems when it reports quarterly earnings on Aug. 4.</p>
        <p>Shares of Aetna dropped $9.25, or 13.7 percent, to $57.375, before rebounding to close at $59.6875, down $6.9375. The stock had declined $4.0625 on Monday after speculation that a sale to ING would be completed failed to materialize over the weekend.</p>
        <p>ING and Aetna have not commented except to confirm that talks are under way.</p>
        <p>Most health insurance stocks also dropped on the Big Board yesterday. Cigna declined $3.4375, to $98.0625. The UnitedHealth Group lost $3.6875, to $83.25. But Wellpoint Health Networks gained $2.1875, to $85.0625.</p>
        <p>Analysts said the problems faced by Aetna, based in Hartford, were unique as it struggles to integrate acquired companies, soften its aggressive culture and replace several departing senior health insurance executives.</p>
        <p>Aetna has said that it is searching for a new chief executive to run its health plan business, which it intends to spin off as a separate company.</p>
        <p>''Nobody's really minding the store,'' said Roberta Goodman, a health care analyst at Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>William S. McKeever, an analyst at PaineWebber Securities, said Aetna faced ''more challenges than anyone else in the industry.''</p>
        <p>Costs were also rising in its money-losing Prudential Health Care unit and Medicare H.M.O.'s. Aetna said recently that it would close unprofitable Medicare H.M.O.'s with 355,000 members in 11 states next year.</p>
        <p>William H. Donaldson, who took over as chief executive in February, said Aetna was ''very disappointed with this increase'' in costs. He said operations would be tightened to increase efficiency and fix or exit markets and products that do not meet financial and strategic goals.</p>
        <p>Aetna plans to start raising health care premiums for a minority of customers whose contracts open for change in the fourth quarter. Contracts for most big employers started on Jan. 1 and for many municipalities on July 1.</p>
        <p>James A. Lane, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney, said the announcement had damaged the confidence that investors had placed in Mr. Donaldson, a former Wall Street banker.</p>
        <p>Noting that Mr. Donaldson had said earlier that annual earnings would exceed $4.80 a share this year, Mr. Lane said his ''credibility is now defunct, at least for the short term.'' Mr. Lane lowered his own 2000 earnings estimate to $3.75 a share from $4.95.</p>
        <p>Herbert A. Denton, an investment manager who is president of Providence Capital, said the earnings report was ''a huge pie in the face to investors.''</p>
        <p>He added that ''in retrospect, Aetna might have been well advised to conclude a deal in June, ahead of the earnings report.''</p>
        <p>''It gives ING and other would-be acquirers of Aetna's financial services a psychological edge,'' Mr. Denton said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Goodman at Merrill Lynch said Aetna had reported in a Securities and Exchange Commission filing that it had underestimated its costs in the second half of 1999, which may have led to misjudgments about this year's costs. H.M.O.'s typically project costs and set their rates for the year during the preceding summer. But the companies do not begin to learn their actual costs until the next June or July.</p>
        <p>Analysts said the costs might have swelled after Mr. Donaldson made clear he wanted to improve relations with doctors, hospitals, patients and consumers, who want flexibility to decide on their care. Like other health insurers, Aetna faces a host of lawsuits filed by plaintiff's lawyers who hope to bring class actions on behalf of patients and doctors.</p>
        <p>Aetna had angered doctors by forcing them to choose between accepting low-paying, tightly controlled H.M.O. patients or giving up all Aetna patients.</p>
        <p>But Joyce Oberdorf, a spokeswoman for Aetna, said that the operating changes intended to placate doctors that Mr. Donaldson had announced in Texas, Connecticut and Virginia were not reflected in the second-quarter earnings. They did not begin until this month.</p>
        <p>She added that the company's intention was to eliminate policies that ''may be perceived as obstacles or may create hassles'' with providers of health care ''and do not add to Aetna's ability to monitor quality of care and control costs.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lane at Salomon said the problems with earnings could complicate negotiations to sell the financial and international units. ''The company could have a hard time obtaining lender and creditor approval for debt restructuring necessary to consummate significant divestitures in light of the operational trends in its largest health business,'' he said.</p>
        <p>People close to the ING-Aetna talks have said that Aetna is seeking to transfer $2.75 billion of long-term debt to ING as part of a $7.75 billion deal for the nonhealth units.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
