<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hernandez Goes on the D.L.; Gooden Goes in the Rotation</title>
    <meta content="19PINS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Orlando</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E5D8113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="980" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hernandez Goes on the D.L.; Gooden Goes in the Rotation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees pitcher Orlando Hernandez is placed on disabled list with sprained right elbow (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Orlando Hernandez uttered ''no problem'' and trotted away when asked about the condition of his sprained right elbow on Monday. But there was enough of a problem that the Yankees placed him on the 15-day disabled list yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Yankees have been concerned with Hernandez's elbow since he was ripped for eight runs in an 11-9 loss to the Florida Marlins last Thursday. Manager Joe Torre said Hernandez's velocity was down and that he looked tentative.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Orlando Hernandez uttered ''no problem'' and trotted away when asked about the condition of his sprained right elbow on Monday. But there was enough of a problem that the Yankees placed him on the 15-day disabled list yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Yankees have been concerned with Hernandez's elbow since he was ripped for eight runs in an 11-9 loss to the Florida Marlins last Thursday. Manager Joe Torre said Hernandez's velocity was down and that he looked tentative.</p>
        <p>Hernandez is unhappy about the continuing complications involving his elbow. ''I don't know to what degree I'm injured,'' he said before last night's game. ''But I'm going on the disabled list, so they must think I'm hurt.''</p>
        <p>Hernandez said he was ''not really worried,'' but he admitted that he has not recovered since he first injured the elbow while allowing nine runs in the first inning against the Chicago White Sox on June 18. The Yankees did not put El Duque on the disabled list after that incident, but they will now send him to Tampa, Fla. and conduct M.R.I.'s on both his elbow and his back, which has also bothered him this year.</p>
        <p>''I'm not sure that it's as much pain as it's something that doesn't feel right,'' said Manager Joe Torre. ''I don't know that he's in excruciating pain. I just don't think he feels the freedom he'd like to in his arm.''</p>
        <p>General Manager Brian Cashman conceded that Hernandez had told the team he felt fine after resting for 12 days and then returning to register victories over the Tampa Bay Devil Rays and the Mets. But Cashman said Hernandez ''just doesn't feel right.'' Apparently, Hernandez has not felt right for a month. ''I guess he was experiencing some things and sucked it up at the time,'' Cashman said.</p>
        <p>By sidelining Hernandez, the Yankees will insert Dwight Gooden into the rotation. Roger Clemens will replace Hernandez as the starter against Detroit tonight, Andy Pettitte will pitch on three days' rest tomorrow afternoon and Gooden will start Friday night against Tampa Bay. David Cone gets the chance to end a 12-start streak without winning on Saturday and Denny Neagle will return for his second start on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Still, while Torre said that the Yankees had sent Hernandez to the disabled list ''to protect him from himself,'' the right-hander's condition is unsettling. Not only is Hernandez's absence troubling, but so is the mystery about his injury.</p>
        <p>The Yankees first called Hernandez's injury a sprained elbow, but Cashman declined to characterize it yesterday and the team called it ''mild discomfort.'' When outfielder Roberto Kelly first injured his elbow in the spring, the Yankees called it a sprain. Kelly later underwent season-ending surgery.</p>
        <p>Hernandez's d.l. stint is retroactive to July 14, so he is eligible to be activated on July 29. Hernandez has already had two M.R.I.'s on his elbow and has been examined by a back specialist, but the tests did not show any structural damage. Cashman said he hoped that El Duque is simply beset by ''major discomfort'' and not some more serious injury.</p>
        <p>Hernandez admitted he was angry, apparently because he only expected to miss one start and not go on the d.l. ''I'm not going to drive myself crazy, over it,'' said Hernandez, who has an 8-7 record with a 4.57 earned-run average. Darrell Einertson was recalled from Class AAA Columbus to replace him on the roster.</p>
        <p>Gooden, who started and defeated the Mets 11 days ago, then had a strong outing in relief on Sunday, will get another start against the Devil Rays, who released him on May 25. Gooden laughed and said he would be going for ''bragging rights'' against his hometown team. But he reiterated his desire to help the Yankees in any capacity.</p>
        <p>''The main thing is I'm happy to be back in the major leagues,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The White Talks</p>
        <p>The Yankees are exploring several options to add a left fielder and have had lengthy discussions with the Montreal Expos about Rondell White. While the Expos have asked the Yankees for Class AAA infielder Alfonso Soriano and Class AA pitcher Randy Keisler, one Montreal official said nothing was imminent with the Yankees or any other team. The Expos are also talking trade with Seattle and Atlanta.</p>
        <p>While White would obviously be an upgrade over Ryan Thompson, the Yankees are hesitant to part with Soriano. White might also be more expensive than even George Steinbrenner wants to pay to buttress left field; he makes $4 million this season and has a $4 million option for next year.</p>
        <p>The 28-year old outfielder is batting .307 with 11 homers and 54 runs batted in, but he has been on the disabled list three times in the last two seasons. He is there now, with a hamstring injury.</p>
        <p>''We're having talks, but there's nothing to report at this moment,'' said Cashman.</p>
        <p>Rehab Start for Mendoza</p>
        <p>Ramiro Mendoza, on the disabled list with a weak right shoulder, will make a rehabilitation start in Tampa today. Mendoza is likely to make two minor league outings before rejoining the Yankees in Baltimore and can be activated next Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Allen Watson, who has a dislocated shoulder, was also sent to Tampa to continue his treatment and rehab.</p>
        <p>Old-Timer's Day Sept. 2</p>
        <p>The Yankees have rescheduled Old-Timer's Day for Sept. 2, the Saturday of Labor Day weekend. The ceremonies will start at 2:30 p.m., followed by a 4:35 game against Minnesota. The annual reunion of former Yankees was rained out last Saturday.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
