<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Neagle's Debut Earns Cheers In the Bronx</title>
    <meta content="19YANK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216123"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0D8113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Neagle's Debut Earns Cheers In the Bronx</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Philadelphia Phillies, 3-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Denny Neagle stood as rigid as a Marine in the eighth inning last night as he contemplated his next pitch. There was noise reverberating from every nook and cranny of Yankee Stadium because many of the 40,013 fans were standing along with him, and Neagle loved it. Loved the sounds, the atmosphere and the situation.</p>
        <p>Neagle went into his windup, fired a slider and Bobby Abreu missed it for strike three, causing it to get even louder and zanier in the Bronx. The fans gave Neagle his second standing ovation in two innings after he ended the eighth so stylishly, and then the newest Yankee heard the fans yelling his name, the sweetest chant a player can hear.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Denny Neagle stood as rigid as a Marine in the eighth inning last night as he contemplated his next pitch. There was noise reverberating from every nook and cranny of Yankee Stadium because many of the 40,013 fans were standing along with him, and Neagle loved it. Loved the sounds, the atmosphere and the situation.</p>
        <p>Neagle went into his windup, fired a slider and Bobby Abreu missed it for strike three, causing it to get even louder and zanier in the Bronx. The fans gave Neagle his second standing ovation in two innings after he ended the eighth so stylishly, and then the newest Yankee heard the fans yelling his name, the sweetest chant a player can hear.</p>
        <p>''Den-ny! Den-ny!'' It was a memorable welcome for Neagle to the Yankees, to the Stadium and to a percolating pennant race as he tamed the Philadelphia Phillies, 3-1, in his pinstripe debut. Tugging at his uniform pants or jersey, blowing into his left hand on a muggy 85-degree night and working both sides of the plate efficiently, the left-hander Neagle pitched eight dependable innings in beating Curt Schilling and making his first day on the job one to savor.</p>
        <p>''You want to get that first one under your belt and let the guys know this is why they got you,'' Neagle said. ''Make a statement and say: 'This is what I'm here to do. Go out there and pitch you guys, hopefully, to another postseason victory.' ''</p>
        <p>The Yankees were giddy, too. With Orlando Hernandez having gone on the disabled list yesterday because of a sprained right elbow and with David Cone having gone 12 starts without a victory, the Yankees needed their newest pitcher to give them a timely boost. The Yankees sent four prospects to the Cincinnati Reds last Wednesday because they felt that Neagle is a necessary piece to help guide them back to the World Series. Last night, Neagle held the Phillies to one run and five hits, struck out three and walked two, and made the Yankees look shrewd for acquiring him.</p>
        <p>''He was magnificent,'' George Steinbrenner said, as the team owner walked through the clubhouse. ''He hadn't pitched in 11 days. Tremendous.''</p>
        <p>Joe Torre celebrated his 60th birthday by watching a National League-type game that took only 2 hours 29 minutes. Like his boss, Torre heaped adulation on Neagle. ''That was an old-fashioned game where a pitcher came out and threw strikes and dominated the game,'' the Yankee manager said.</p>
        <p>Schilling, whose name pops up in trade rumors several times a month, was better than Neagle for part of the night. The Yankees did not get a hit until there were two out in the fourth inning, but they supplied the most important hits of the game in the fifth and sixth.</p>
        <p>David Justice led off the fifth by lining a homer into the front row of seats in right field. It was Justice's 24th homer of the season, his third as a Yankee and his fourth in 27 career at-bats against Schilling.</p>
        <p>After Chuck Knoblauch walked and Derek Jeter singled with one out in the sixth, Bernie Williams rapped a triple to left-center field to drive in both and put the Yankees ahead, 3-0. That gave Williams 87 runs batted in, but more important it allowed Neagle to pitch more aggressively.</p>
        <p>''Now you can throw strikes, allow a homer and it's not life or death,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>This game was about pitching and about the funny and talented Neagle, who had warmed up several paces from Monument Park in the bullpen in left-center field, near the monuments he had spoken about reverentially on Monday. When he started walking to the dugout, a wall of sound followed Neagle and he later called the experience ''an incredible rush.''</p>
        <p>Neagle is a fly-ball pitcher who quickly showed that that he should greatly benefit from the dimensions of the Stadium by securing eight flyouts to center or left. He used a strong fastball to set up his changeup and slider, and barely blinked when the Phillies had runners in four of the first five innings; he did not permit a hit in seven at-bats with runners on base.</p>
        <p>After Ron Gant drilled a changeup for a homer and Philadelphia's only run in the eighth, Neagle struck out Abreu for the third out to earn another ovation and elicit the ''Den-ny! Den-ny!'' chants.</p>
        <p>From 300 feet away in right field, Paul O'Neill saw how Neagle frustrated the Phillies by making sure every one of his 116 pitches had a purpose. ''You know there's got to be some kind of jitters in Yankee Stadium when you put on the uniform and go to the mound,'' O'Neill said. ''All the things that go with being traded. Sometimes, it's too much for people. He was ready. You could tell.''</p>
        <p>Mariano Rivera pitched the ninth inning for his 22nd save and saved the game ball for Neagle. Some Yankees teased Neagle, who had been with the team for six days, for finally doing something besides being their best cheerleader. Like everything else that happened in Neagle's first start with the Yankees, he loved it.</p>
        <p>''Obviously,'' Neagle gushed, ''I don't think I could have written a better script.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
