<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Philharmonic and Muti Say He Won't Be the One</title>
    <meta content="19PHIL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muti, Riccardo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guenther, Paul B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Masur, Kurt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozinn, Allan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E0D8103BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Philharmonic and Muti Say He Won't Be the One</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Philharmonic ends intense courtship of conductor Riccardo Muti to replace Kurt Masur as music director when his contract expires after 2001-2 season; Muti says he could not devote time required to major American music directorship; board chairman, Paul B Guenther, says number of weeks is not issue; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After an intense courtship that led many people in the music world to assume that Riccardo Muti would be named the next music director of the New York Philharmonic, spokesmen for both the conductor and the orchestra said yesterday that the marriage was off.</p>
        <p>Both sides said the discussions ended amicably on Monday evening when Mr. Muti concluded that he could not devote the time required to a major American music directorship. Typically that means conducting about 14 subscription weeks as well as tours and taking on some administrative duties and maintaining a public image. Mr. Muti is said to have offered 8, 10 and 12 weeks of conducting in his his first, second and third seasons. In a telephone interview, Paul B. Guenther, the chairman of the Philharmonic board, said the number of weeks was not at issue but he would not say what was.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After an intense courtship that led many people in the music world to assume that Riccardo Muti would be named the next music director of the New York Philharmonic, spokesmen for both the conductor and the orchestra said yesterday that the marriage was off.</p>
        <p>Both sides said the discussions ended amicably on Monday evening when Mr. Muti concluded that he could not devote the time required to a major American music directorship. Typically that means conducting about 14 subscription weeks as well as tours and taking on some administrative duties and maintaining a public image. Mr. Muti is said to have offered 8, 10 and 12 weeks of conducting in his his first, second and third seasons. In a telephone interview, Paul B. Guenther, the chairman of the Philharmonic board, said the number of weeks was not at issue but he would not say what was.</p>
        <p>The Philharmonic must now reopen its search for a successor to Kurt Masur, who became the music director in 1991 and whose contract ends after the 2001-2 season. The search has been under way since early 1998, when the orchestra's board announced that the contract extension it was then offering to Mr. Masur, who celebrated his 73rd birthday yesterday, would be his last.</p>
        <p>Other conductors believed to be on the Philharmonic's short list before the focus moved to Mr. Muti are Mariss Jansons, the music director of the Pittsburgh Symphony and the associate principal conductor of the St. Petersburg Philharmonic in Russia, and Christoph Eschenbach, the chief conductor of the NDR Symphony in Hamburg.</p>
        <p>Mr. Guenther would not discuss those or other potential candidates, saying only that ''they are certainly eminent in the field and would be logical people to talk to.'' He added that the Philharmonic had had what he called ''ongoing discussions with a number of conductors.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Muti, 58, is the director of La Scala in Milan, and a regular guest conductor of the Vienna and Berlin Philharmonics, relationships that he intended to maintain even if he took the Philharmonic podium. His decision is not entirely surprising: he is known to prefer working in Europe and to dislike frequent trans-Atlantic travel. Those, at any rate, were among the principal reasons he gave for leaving the Philadelphia Orchestra in 1992 after 12 years there.</p>
        <p>Mr. Muti was in Milan yesterday and could not be reached, but his spokeswoman in New York, Mary-Lou Falcone, released a statement from him that said, ''After thoughtful discussions with the New York Philharmonic, I realized that due to my commitments at La Scala and elsewhere, I don't have the time necessary to do what I would like to do artistically with the New York Philharmonic.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Guenther appeared to accept Mr. Muti's decision with an almost philosophical detachment.</p>
        <p>''He loves the orchestra, and I think he was intrigued by the possibility of directing it,'' Mr. Guenther said. ''But La Scala is his other love, and I think in the end he didn't feel he could serve two masters. To be able to stand up and say, 'I don't think I could do this the way I think it should be done' took courage on his part.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Muti and Mr. Guenther said they hoped Mr. Muti would continue to be a guest conductor. He is scheduled to spend two weeks with the Philharmonic in 2002.</p>
        <p>The board never fully explained its decision not to continue with Mr. Masur: his performances have won fairly consistent critical praise, and he is widely credited with having raised the standard of performance considerably. He becomes the principal conductor of the London Philharmonic later this year.</p>
        <p>The board's action put the orchestra in the market just as several of the top American orchestras were searching for music directors. With Mr. Masur heading into his 70's, the board may not have wanted to let the moment and the talent pass.</p>
        <p>But the prospect of achieving an orderly transition, as the board put it at the time, in 1998, may not be easily achieved. Although the Cleveland Orchestra, the Atlanta Symphony and the Cincinnati Symphony have recently ended their conductor searches, the Philadelphia Orchestra and the Boston Symphony are also in the market for music directors.</p>
        <p>The Philharmonic had hoped to announce a new director before Labor Day, but no one at the orchestra will now to commit to a deadline. Conductors' schedules are usually arranged several seasons in advance, and appointments at major orchestras are typically announced two seasons before they take effect.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
