<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Noncandidate McCain Is Still Running Hard</title>
    <meta content="Y19MCC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216071"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennet, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E1DB113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1113" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Noncandidate McCain Is Still Running Hard</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BENNET</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bennet, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John McCain, who has been busy on campaign trail on behalf of host of Congressional candidates since abandoning his presidential race in Mar, plans to lead his old campaign team and some 60 journalists to Republican National Convention; holds wide range of activities he plans for convention are not aimed at overshadowing what he holds is clearly Gov George W Bush's event, interview; Bush's advisers hold McCain's star power will benefit Bush by drawing attention of independent voters (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John McCain seems to be working harder at not running for president than some guys -- we won't mention names -- do in actually campaigning for the job.</p>
        <p>Since abandoning the race for the Republican nomination in March, he has campaigned in so many states, for so many Congressional candidates and raised so much money, that his aides have lost track of all three.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator John McCain seems to be working harder at not running for president than some guys -- we won't mention names -- do in actually campaigning for the job.</p>
        <p>Since abandoning the race for the Republican nomination in March, he has campaigned in so many states, for so many Congressional candidates and raised so much money, that his aides have lost track of all three.</p>
        <p>And now, with a we're-puttin'-the-band-back-together mix of nostalgia and anticipation, he is starting up his Straight Talk Express to take himself, his old campaign team and about 60 journalists to the Republican National Convention in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>There, he plans to lead a town-hall meeting, to hold a joint news conference with MTV V.J.'s, to make appearances on Comedy Central and ''Face the Nation,'' to throw a party for 600 friends and so on. To record the doings for ABC's ''Good Morning America,'' his wife, Cindy, plans to carry the ''Cindy-cam.''</p>
        <p>''I'm trying very hard not in any way to offend any of the Bush people or overshadow what is clearly Governor Bush's event,'' Mr. McCain said in an interview Monday at his Senate office, where he arrived illuminated by a CNN camera light.</p>
        <p>Advisers to Gov. George W. Bush profess not to be offended in the slightest. They say that Mr. McCain's star power can now only benefit them, by drawing the attention of independent voters.</p>
        <p>If there is to be any dissent at the convention, which begins on July 31, it is not likely to come from the scrappy Arizonan who used to say of Governor Bush that ''if he's a reformer, I'm an astronaut.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain said that even when he appeared in Philadelphia on July 30 at a planned ''shadow convention,'' which will also feature antagonists of the right like the comedian Al Franken, he will promote Mr. Bush as devoted to ''reform of education, of the military, of our strategic posture nuclear-weapons-wise, health care, etc.''</p>
        <p>Though they have spoken a few times by telephone, Governor Bush and Senator McCain have not appeared together since May 9, when Mr. McCain endorsed his former opponent in Pittsburgh. But Mr. McCain said in the interview that he intends to campaign alongside Mr. Bush after the convention and again in September and October.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. McCain seemed at times less than thrilled with his bridesmaid's role. He looked down and spoke softly when asked to describe his level of enthusiasm for Mr. Bush's candidacy. ''My enthusiasm is very high,'' he said. In the interview, he became animated only when discussing the high points of his campaign, which he recalled with ''nostalgia and pleasure.''</p>
        <p>At the staff level, resentment, if not contempt, lingers on both sides, but the two camps are learning to work together. Sniping that used to take place in the open, then anonymously, is now done strictly in secret. ''I'm sure the true backbiting now is limited to completely off-the-record, which is progress,'' said John Weaver, a wry adviser to Mr. McCain. But, he said, ''You'll never see the two staffs go on vacation together.''</p>
        <p>In his subdued tones, Mr. McCain praised Mr. Bush as running ''an increasingly centrist campaign.''  From Mr. Bush's perspective, the benefits of comity are obvious. According to public polls, Mr. McCain remains more popular than Mr. Bush or Vice President Al Gore, as the senator's aides are quick to point out. He is particularly beloved by the swing groups of independent and undecided voters needed by both candidates. Representative Thomas M. Davis III, who is leading the Republican drive to retain the House, said that even party regulars clamor for  Mr. McCain. ''Now that he's no longer a threat, they've kind of embraced him,'' he said. ''He's everywhere from Florida to Mississippi to New Hampshire. He's the man.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain said that he wants comity because he is a loyal Republican. ''I was very concerned about, and should be concerned about, giving the appearance of being a bad loser,'' Mr. McCain said. ''I don't think that's helpful to me, to Governor Bush, or to the party. And frankly, I didn't want to be a bad loser.''</p>
        <p>After dropping out of the race, Mr. McCain formed a political action committee, Straight Talk America, to promote his agenda. He is creating a Center for Conservative Reform to add some intellectual heft to it. His aides acknowledge that the PAC could serve as the basis for a future presidential bid, should Mr. Bush stumble. But while Mr. McCain said, after a long pause, that he did not know if he would ever run for president again, he called the prospect unlikely. He said he did not want to be picked as vice president and did not expect to be.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's aides studied how failed Republican nominees, including Ronald Reagan in 1976, approached the party's conventions. But they took more cues from the supportive role that Gen. Colin L. Powell played in 1996. After first receiving the go-ahead from the Bush camp, Andrew Card, the co-chairman of the convention, invited Mr. McCain to speak during a meeting on June 20. He said he told Mr. McCain that he was seeking ''political celebrities,'' not politicians.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain does not plan to deliver anything like the jeremiad at the 1992 convention by Patrick J. Buchanan, who rallied the party to religious and cultural ''war'' and helped sink the re-election bid of Mr. Bush's father. Mr. McCain's speech at 10:30 on the convention's second night, will be devoted to Mr. Bush's chosen theme, ''Strength and Security With a Purpose,'' and will probably not even mention the senator's signature issue, campaign finance reform, aides said. No one asked Mr. McCain to show his speech to the convention organizers ahead of time, according to all parties, but he plans to do so.</p>
        <p>Mr. Card said that, while Mr. McCain's bus trip was not part of the plan for the convention, there was ''no danger'' of Mr. Bush's being upstaged. Mr. McCain will not even be in the audience when Mr. Bush accepts the nomination. He plans to leave on the convention's third day, Wednesday morning -- a sign not of pique, organizers and supporters insist, but of self-abnegation.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
