<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets' Harris Rolls Up Sleeves, and Gives Piazza a Hand</title>
    <meta content="19METS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toronto Blue Jays</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7D7113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets' Harris Rolls Up Sleeves, and Gives Piazza a Hand</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, July 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Toronto Blue Jays, 11-7 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Piazza is enjoying perhaps his finest season, and time after time, his home runs have lifted the Mets in crucial spots. Lenny Harris, in his third stint as a teammate of Piazza's, said the trouble comes when the Mets rely too heavily on their All-Star catcher. In the last two games, Harris seems to be on a crusade to prove the point.</p>
        <p>Harris, a 36-year-old utility man, has gotten a chance to play third base and bat first, and he sparked the Mets again tonight with a leadoff home run. Harris scored two more runs and added a run-scoring single as the Mets downed the Toronto Blue Jays, 11-7.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mike Piazza is enjoying perhaps his finest season, and time after time, his home runs have lifted the Mets in crucial spots. Lenny Harris, in his third stint as a teammate of Piazza's, said the trouble comes when the Mets rely too heavily on their All-Star catcher. In the last two games, Harris seems to be on a crusade to prove the point.</p>
        <p>Harris, a 36-year-old utility man, has gotten a chance to play third base and bat first, and he sparked the Mets again tonight with a leadoff home run. Harris scored two more runs and added a run-scoring single as the Mets downed the Toronto Blue Jays, 11-7.</p>
        <p>Piazza had the game's most memorable hit, a 426-foot grand slam in the fifth inning that broke a 3-3 tie and made Bobby J. Jones the winner despite an unsteady outing. But it was Harris who kept things lively throughout, just as he did on Monday, when his three hits and two stolen bases led to an extra-inning victory.</p>
        <p>''He makes everybody feel important and believe they're a big part of this club, which they are,'' Piazza said of Harris. ''I know I have a big job on this club, but it's impossible for me or anybody else to do it alone.''</p>
        <p>Derek Bell, who bats second, was Harris's crony, going 3 for 4 with a homer and four runs scored.</p>
        <p>Harris drew a leadoff walk in the fifth, then stole second off Chris Carpenter. Two more walks followed, and Carpenter fell behind Piazza, 2-1. His next pitch was a fastball down in the strike zone, and Piazza belted it to left-center field, where it struck a clock above a Skydome restaurant.</p>
        <p>Manager Bobby Valentine said it was one of the hardest-hit balls he has ever seen. ''I think Mike's was still going out when it hit the clock,'' Valentine said. ''It hadn't quite reached its apex.''</p>
        <p>The homer was Piazza's 28th of the year and his third grand slam, tying a Mets record for slams in a season. While Robin Ventura gets considerable attention for his bases-loaded success (he has .356 career average with 14 grand slams), Piazza may be even more dangerous. He has 12 career slams, and a .386 career average with the bases loaded.</p>
        <p>Piazza was hitless in his other at-bats tonight; the home run came on his only good swing. ''Fortunately, I made it count,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Harris, who is starting at third for the injured Ventura, is making his chance count. Valentine put him in the leadoff spot on Monday to take pressure off the rookie Melvin Mora, who was also balancing regular shortstop duties. In the last two games, Harris has three stolen bases, or one more than Rickey Henderson had in his first 26 leadoff starts this year.</p>
        <p>It is a sampling -- and Valentine has a strong distaste for anointing players, as he puts it -- but Harris is likely to stay at the top of the order as long as he is hot. ''He's a part of the team and he's playing very good,'' Valentine said. ''You want to keep the good players playing.''</p>
        <p>John Franco and Armando Benitez are two good players Valentine did not want to use tonight. The late-inning relievers pitched on Monday, and with an 11-5 lead heading into the bottom of the eighth, Valentine brought in Rich Rodriguez for the game's last six outs.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez could retire only two hitters. Jose Cruz smashed a triple and scored on a sacrifice fly, then Shannon Stewart hit his major league record-tying fourth double and scored on a single. After getting an out on a fielder's choice, Rodriguez gave way to Franco.</p>
        <p>''You come into a situation like that, you don't want to walk anybody,'' said Rodriguez, who had to warm up quickly after the Mets broke the game open in the top of the inning. ''You come in to throw strikes, and that's what I did.''</p>
        <p>Valentine said he did not want Rodriguez to face the slugger Carlos Delgado; a two-run homer would have cut the lead to 11-9, and Valentine ''didn't want to play a two-run game.'' Franco got Delgado to pop up, and Benitez worked a 1-2-3 ninth.</p>
        <p>Like Rodriguez, Jones struggled early and was forced to accept a demotion to Class AAA Norfolk in June. But Jones has gotten much better results since his return, with a 2.73 earned run average in five starts before tonight's.</p>
        <p>The wind was blowing out at Skydome, which aided hitters but helped make Jones's curveball sharper. He released the pitch higher than usual to take advantage of the wind.</p>
        <p>Still, this was Jones's worst outing since he came back. He allowed five runs in six-plus innings, and nine of Toronto's 10 hits off him were for extra bases. After pitching well his last three starts but not winning any, Jones will take the victory.</p>
        <p>''It makes up for the ones where you pitch great and you lose it or get outpitched,'' Jones said. ''That's the funny part of this game.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
