<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ventura Will (Won't) Be Back Soon</title>
    <meta content="19SHEA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216122"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: METS NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ventura, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D8113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="454" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ventura Will (Won't) Be Back Soon</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, July 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Status of injured New York Mets third baseman Robin Ventura discussed (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets believe third baseman Robin Ventura will be back from the disabled list in two weeks. Ventura said he expects the same thing, but he is not sure.</p>
        <p>''I don't think you have any way of knowing anything,'' said Ventura, who has a bruised rotator cuff. ''There's no game plan right now. I know eventually there will be one, but I'm just trying to get the strength back before we can move on from there.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mets believe third baseman Robin Ventura will be back from the disabled list in two weeks. Ventura said he expects the same thing, but he is not sure.</p>
        <p>''I don't think you have any way of knowing anything,'' said Ventura, who has a bruised rotator cuff. ''There's no game plan right now. I know eventually there will be one, but I'm just trying to get the strength back before we can move on from there.''</p>
        <p>Mets officials have insisted that this injury is unrelated to the surgery Ventura had on the shoulder last December, when he had cartilage removed. Ventura said there was nothing wrong with the rotator cuff then, but he was not sure exactly where his shoulder was operated on.</p>
        <p>The Mets' head trainer, Fred Hina, citing a new policy for which he gave no explanation, said he could no longer speak to the news media. Ventura may very well be out for only two weeks. But if it is in the strategic interest of the Mets for something not to become public, General Manager Steve Phillips will go to great lengths to protect that information.</p>
        <p>If Ventura's injury is worse than the Mets are letting on, it stands to reason that they will add an infielder before the July 31 trading deadline. Jim Duquette, the assistant general manager, and Manager Bobby Valentine insist that Todd Zeile will not be moved from first base to third, where Lenny Harris and Matt Franco can fill in. But Zeile has years of experience as a third baseman, and it may be easier to acquire a first baseman near the deadline and simply shift Zeile to third.</p>
        <p>The Mets have had discussions with Texas, which will make first baseman David Segui available in a week if it determines it is out of the American League wild-card race.</p>
        <p>Reed Encouraged</p>
        <p>When Bobby Valentine asks the right-hander Rick Reed about how he thinks he has pitched, Valentine knows he will get an honest answer. Reed lasted only five innings in his return from the disabled list Monday, allowing five runs and matching a career high with five walks, but he told Valentine he was pleased.</p>
        <p>''I always try to get the positive out of everything,'' Reed said. ''The last two and a half innings, I was pitching the way I'm supposed to pitch. The stuff is there. It's just a matter of getting consistent.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: METS NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
