<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Burmese Boy Rebels Languish in Jungle</title>
    <meta content="19BURM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Karens (Ethnic Minority)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Myanmar</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Thailand</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">God's Army (Burmese Rebel Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mydans, Seth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Htoo, Luther</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Htoo, Johnny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bleibtreu, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Myanmar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Thailand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Myanmar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Thailand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EEDD113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Burmese Boy Rebels Languish in Jungle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mydans, Seth</byline>
      <dateline>BANGKOK, July 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Burmese rebels in God's Army, rag-tag group inspired by Luther and Johnny Htoo, 12-year-old twins, are languishing during rainy season in makeshift camp inside Thai border; boys complain to American journalist Jason Bleibtreu that they are short of food and supplies; rebels are on run from both Thai troops and forces of Myanmar, where they are splinter faction of ethnic Karen insurgency; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rains have come and spirits are a little low for God's Army, the rag-tag Burmese insurgency that draws its inspiration from twin 12-year-old soldiers.</p>
        <p>Coughing, scratching themselves and seeming bewildered by the world around them, the boys met in a jungle camp recently with an American journalist and complained that they were short of food and supplies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The rains have come and spirits are a little low for God's Army, the rag-tag Burmese insurgency that draws its inspiration from twin 12-year-old soldiers.</p>
        <p>Coughing, scratching themselves and seeming bewildered by the world around them, the boys met in a jungle camp recently with an American journalist and complained that they were short of food and supplies.</p>
        <p>Swinging short machetes, the boys were helping to build bamboo and thatch huts in a clearing when the journalist, Jason Bleibtreu, having trekked through the mountains, arrived to photograph and film them as he had done once before, in April.</p>
        <p>Despite their claims of supernatural powers, the boys, Johnny and Luther Htoo, seemed as passive and childlike as ever, relying on a sort of nanny named Rambo to help them answer questions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bleibtreu: ''What are your plans now?''</p>
        <p>Rambo to Johnny: ''We still have our plans. Tell him.''</p>
        <p>Johnny: ''Now? We still have our plans.''</p>
        <p>God's Army made headlines in January when 10 of its members staged a suicidal raid on a hospital in the Thai border town of Ratchaburi, holding hostage more than 800 patients and medical workers before being shot dead by security forces.</p>
        <p>Since then, remnants of the group of no more than 200 fighters have been on the run from both Thai troops and the forces of Myanmar, the former Burma, where they are a splinter faction of an ethnic Karen insurgency.</p>
        <p>But they told Mr. Bleibtreu that the little camp where he met them in a remote stretch of mountains was in fact just inside the border of Thailand. It seemed for the moment that even their pursuers had lost interest in them.</p>
        <p>A number of the fighters apparently have drifted away to refugee camps along the border that shelter Karen civilians fleeing the conflict inside Myanmar. No more than 30 fighters -- half of them teenage boys -- accompanied the twins in their jungle camp.</p>
        <p>Dressed in military-style fatigues but looking frail and undernourished in Mr. Bleibtreu's videotape, the boys spent most of their energy smoking fat cheroots. At one point, Johnny sucked alternately on two of them, one in each hand.</p>
        <p>On his previous visit, Mr. Bleibtreu met only with Luther. This time, with both boys present, he said he detected a hint of sibling rivalry.</p>
        <p>''Luther was moody and looked like he was a little bit upset that Johnny was getting the attention this time,'' Mr. Bleibtreu said. ''Between the two of them, Johnny is a brighter bulb, more talkative and outgoing. When I started paying attention to Johnny, Luther got up and left and was in a bad mood.''</p>
        <p>More than once when he was filming Luther, Mr. Bleibtreu said, the child raised a machete at him in what seemed to be a threatening way.</p>
        <p>Johnny also seemed edgy about the attention his brother had received.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bleibtreu: ''What kind of weapons do you like?''</p>
        <p>Johnny to Rambo: ''Did he ask these questions during his last visit?''</p>
        <p>Rambo: ''He asked.''</p>
        <p>Johnny: ''What was the answer?''</p>
        <p>As with most of Mr. Bleibtreu's questions -- on both visits -- there never was a coherent answer. It was not clear that the boys had much of an idea what the journalist was doing there or what an interview was all about.</p>
        <p>The uneducated sons of a peasant farmer, they have been venerated as the reincarnations of ancient Karen heroes since they were small boys and their words are received as the wisdom of oracles.</p>
        <p>They -- or their followers -- claim that the boys command 400,000 invisible soldiers, and that they can change shape, predict the future and walk through minefields unscathed.</p>
        <p>It is a strange life for a small boy to be carried everywhere on the shoulders of armed men and handed a lit cheroot whenever he murmurs, ''I want a smoke.''</p>
        <p>It seems a lonely life as well.</p>
        <p>''Of course, we would like to see our parents,'' Johnny said.</p>
        <p>And he looked on listlessly from his regal perch on Rambo's lap as a group of armed boys raced through the campsite, as if at a summer camp, playing a game of tag.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bleibtreu: ''What games do you like to play?''</p>
        <p>Johnny: ''I don't know how to play.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
