<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Microsoft's Profits Advance 9% With Help of Portfolio Earnings</title>
    <meta content="Y19SOF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216102"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lohr, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EFD9113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Microsoft's Profits Advance 9% With Help of Portfolio Earnings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE LOHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lohr, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Microsoft Corp says fiscal fourth quarter profits rose more than 9 percent, even though revenues were flat; earnings rose to $2.4 billion compared with $2.2 billion in year-earlier quarter; revenues were $5.80 billlion, up $40 million from year ago (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Microsoft Corporation slightly beat Wall Street's expectations yesterday as its quarterly profits rose more than 9 percent, even though revenues were flat.</p>
        <p>The leading software company had its biggest lift in its fiscal fourth quarter from a surge in earnings from its swelling portfolio of cash and equity investments. Microsoft executives cautioned that investment earnings should drop in the current quarter. But they then delivered an optimistic outlook for the current fiscal year, which begins this month, saying the company expects revenues to rise 15 percent the next year with earnings gaining roughly 10 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Microsoft Corporation slightly beat Wall Street's expectations yesterday as its quarterly profits rose more than 9 percent, even though revenues were flat.</p>
        <p>The leading software company had its biggest lift in its fiscal fourth quarter from a surge in earnings from its swelling portfolio of cash and equity investments. Microsoft executives cautioned that investment earnings should drop in the current quarter. But they then delivered an optimistic outlook for the current fiscal year, which begins this month, saying the company expects revenues to rise 15 percent the next year with earnings gaining roughly 10 percent.</p>
        <p>''We feel very, very good entering the next fiscal year,'' said John Connors, the chief financial officer.</p>
        <p>The quarterly results, according to analysts, suggest that Microsoft seems to be skillfully handling the uncertainties it faces in its business and on the legal front. It is in the midst of a transition in its product markets as its new Windows 2000 operating system is adopted gradually by corporate customers, at a time when the business market for computers has been sluggish.</p>
        <p>''It's a slow but steady transitionary quarter from Microsoft sprinkled with some optimism for the future,'' said Richard Sherlund, an analyst at Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Microsoft has also just begun a longer-term shift in strategy as more and more of its business will come from selling software as Internet services -- an initiative the company announced last month, called Microsoft.Net. That effort, analysts note, will require significant investments by the company, though it will not yield substantial revenues for at least another year.</p>
        <p>During a conference call with analysts yesterday, Mr. Connors referred only obliquely to the federal court ruling in April that Microsoft was a monopolist that had repeatedly violated the nation's antitrust laws. In listing the challenges the company had tackled during the quarter, he mentioned the ''unprecedented level of news on the legal front.''</p>
        <p>All sanctions against Microsoft -- including an order to split the company in two -- have been stayed pending appeals, which could take a year or more. In part because of the uncertainties raised by the antitrust case, Microsoft stock fell by nearly 50 percent in the first five months of this year, from a 52-week high of $119.09375 a share on Dec. 30 to $60.375 on May 26. Yesterday it finished at $78.50, up 31.25 cents. The earnings announcement came after the market had closed.</p>
        <p>For the quarter, Microsoft earnings rose to $2.4 billion, or 44 cents a share. The consensus per-share estimate among 24 analysts polled by First Call/Thomson Financial, which tracks corporate earnings, was 42 cents a share.</p>
        <p>In the comparable quarter a year earlier, Microsoft reported earnings of $2.2 billion, or 40 cents a share.</p>
        <p>Microsoft's revenues for the most recent quarter were in line with analysts' expectations at $5.80 billion, though up a mere $40 million from the year-earlier quarter.</p>
        <p>Microsoft continues to garner an increasing share of its quarterly profits from gains on its sizable investment portfolio rather than from current operations. In the June quarter, the company reported investment earnings of more than $1.1 billion, or 31 percent of its pretax profits. In the year-earlier quarter, Microsoft's investment earnings added $485 million to its pretax profits, representing 14 percent of the total.</p>
        <p>In fact, Microsoft's pretax earnings from operations actually declined in the most recent quarter to $2.5 billion, compared with $2.9 billion a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Mr. Connors said that the company's investment earnings would be somewhat cyclical and that its contribution in the next quarter would likely be ''significantly lower'' than in the June quarter.</p>
        <p>Still, he told analysts that ''you should expect strong investment income from Microsoft'' in the future generally.</p>
        <p>Part of the explanation is that Microsoft's business is a money machine that piles up cash far faster than the company spends it. And the added money in the company coffers earns dividends. At the end of June, cash and marketable securities reached $23.8 billion, up from $17.2 billion a year earlier.</p>
        <p>In addition, Microsoft has a $17.8 billion portfolio of equity investments in technology companies, which are typically business partners of Microsoft. In fiscal 2000 alone, Microsoft made 100 such investments totaling $5.4 billion. If those companies are acquired, for example, Microsoft must sell its stake and report the gain as portfolio earnings.</p>
        <p>Analysts have been closely following the quarterly results for signs of how Windows 2000, the new operating system introduced earlier this year, is selling. Windows 2000 refers both to a new version of Microsoft's desktop operating system for corporations and new server software for running corporate networks and Web sites.</p>
        <p>Mr. Connors declined to give much detail on Windows 2000 sales, beyond saying the company is ''quite satisfied'' with early deployments in big companies including General Motors, Royal Dutch/Shell Group, Xerox and Motorola. Last month, the Defense Department announced that Windows 2000 would be the technology platform for its ''integrated warfare system'' on the Navy's next generation of aircraft carrier, the CVN-77, known as the ''smart carrier.''</p>
        <p>The consumer market is carrying the personal computer market, Mr. Connors noted, with year-to-year growth of roughly 15 percent. Business demand is still sluggish in part because of the falloff in spending following the widely anticipated Year 2000 problem.</p>
        <p>Most analysts expect the September quarter, a traditionally slow one for business purchases, to be not particularly significant as a sign of whether corporate demand is picking up or how well Windows 2000 is doing. ''It looks like we'll have to wait until the December quarter to get a really solid reading on where things stand,'' said Mr. Sherlund of Goldman, Sachs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
