<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y19BRIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216018"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E2D6103BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="911" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>RWANDA: GENOCIDE CENSUS  Authorities have started a nationwide census aimed at establishing a realistic figure for the number of people killed during the central African country's 1994 genocide. Protais Musoni, secretary general in the ministry of local government, said a team of 1,600 investigators had been appointed to carry out the 10-day mission. At least half a million Tutsi and moderate Hutu are believed to have been killed by extremist Hutu.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>SWAZILAND: MINISKIRTS AND AIDS  Swaziland will ban miniskirts in schools starting next year to try to halt the spread of AIDS, a government official said. The aim is to put a stop to sexual relationships between teachers and their female pupils in a country where at least one quarter of the population is infected with H.I.V. Schoolgirls are widely blamed for enticing teachers with their short skirts.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>RWANDA: GENOCIDE CENSUS  Authorities have started a nationwide census aimed at establishing a realistic figure for the number of people killed during the central African country's 1994 genocide. Protais Musoni, secretary general in the ministry of local government, said a team of 1,600 investigators had been appointed to carry out the 10-day mission. At least half a million Tutsi and moderate Hutu are believed to have been killed by extremist Hutu.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>SWAZILAND: MINISKIRTS AND AIDS  Swaziland will ban miniskirts in schools starting next year to try to halt the spread of AIDS, a government official said. The aim is to put a stop to sexual relationships between teachers and their female pupils in a country where at least one quarter of the population is infected with H.I.V. Schoolgirls are widely blamed for enticing teachers with their short skirts.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>BURUNDI: PEACE TALKS  African leaders begin two days of talks in Tanzania today intended to end the seven-year civil war in Burundi. The meeting in the northern town of Arusha will bring together 19 leaders of Burundi's warring factions, including for the first time those of armed rebel groups. A Tanzanian spokesman said the presidents of Tanzania, Uganda, Kenya, Rwanda, Burundi and Zambia would also attend, along with Prime Minister Meles Zenawi of Ethiopia.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>YUGOSLAVIA: 10 CHARGED IN ARKAN KILLING  Ten people were charged in the killing of Zeljko Raznatovic, the Serbian warlord and underworld don known as Arkan, the public prosecutor's office in Belgrade announced. Mr. Raznatovic, facing United Nations war crimes tribunal indictments, was shot dead in a hotel on Jan. 15. Prosecutors said four people have been charged with shooting Arkan, while six others face charges of assisting the killers. One of the accused will be tried in absentia.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: CHARLES DENIES WEDDING PLAN  Prince Charles has formally denied that he intends to marry his longtime mistress, Camilla Parker-Bowles. His office lodged a complaint with the Press Complaints Commission over a Sunday Times of London article that said the couple was exploring marrying in Scotland, where the church is more open to remarriage of those who have been divorced. ''By making this complaint, we hope it will formally lay down, on St. James's Palace-headed notepaper, that there is to be no wedding,'' a court official told the paper.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: CRIME ON RISE  Crime figures for England and Wales rose 3.8 percent, with robberies up 26.1 percent and violent crimes rising by 12.6 percent, the government reported. Home Secretary Jack Straw said alcohol was a key contributing factor in the higher number of street crimes, but his Conservative counterpart, Ann Widdecombe, told the House of Commons that the blame lay with the Labor Government and the dwindling number of police officers.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: SPENDING PLAN  Gordon Brown, the treasury head, announced a $65 billion three-year spending package for schools, transportation, the police and other public services intended to throw Conservatives off balance in the opening round of campaigning for an election next year. Mr. Brown said the money was available because of Labor's success in sustaining stable public finances, but the Tory treasury spokesman, Michael Portillo, said the announcement represented old style ''tax and spend'' tactics that would put the economy at risk.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>ITALY: PRINCELY OFFER  The man who would be Italy's crown prince offered to apologize publicly for the wrongs committed by the Savoys in an effort to get around a 1946 law that bans all male members of Italy's former royal family from setting foot in the country. Emanuele Filiberto di Savoia, 28, grandson of Italy's last king, has been lobbying to be allowed to visit Italy, even for a short period. The Savoys ruled Italy from 1861 to the end of Mussolini's dictatorship; the monarchy was abolished in 1946.</p>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>MALAYSIA: ANWAR VERDICT DATE  A judge said he would announce his verdict on Aug. 4 in the sexual misconduct trial of former Deputy Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim. ''Now, my headache starts,'' said Judge Ariffin Jaka as he closed the final hearing in the politically volatile case.</p>
        <p>Seth Mydans (NYT)</p>
        <p>INDONESIA: TAKING SIDES  A military spokesman admitted that members of the armed forces have taken sides in the religious massacres that have taken thousands of lives in the Maluku islands. The spokesman, Rear Air Marshal Graito Usodo, said it was ''inevitable'' that soldiers would ''act emotionally'' and disobey orders.</p>
        <p>Seth Mydans (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>GUYANA, SURINAME: BORDER DEADLOCK  Talks aimed at resolving a border dispute over oil exploration ended in deadlock in Kingston, Jamaica. There had been optimism that the two countries would resolve a century-old  dispute that erupted again on June 3 when Suriname gunboats evicted a Canadian-owned oil rig from a disputed area. The dispute  revolves around which side of the Corentyne River, which divides the two countries, marks the official border as it extends out to sea.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>IRAN: TOUCH OF COLOR  Iran has eased the Islamic dress code for elementary schoolgirls in Tehran, making way for ''bright, happy colors'' in place of the traditional black. ''Under the new guidelines, elementary students can wear bright, happy colors such as light blue, beige, pink, light green and yellow in school,'' the education ministry said. ''The move is to brighten the mood and raise hope among students, and preserve their psychological health.''</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>Compiled by Terence Neilan</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
