<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rapping on Poe's Door, A Hint of Nevermore; Anger in Village Over N.Y.U. Tower Plan</title>
    <meta content="19NYU.$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Judson Memorial Church (NYC)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greenwich Village (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">McKim, Mead &amp; White</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siegal, Nina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Poe, Edgar Allan (1809-49)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Graduate Schools and Students</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D9113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rapping on Poe's Door, A Hint of Nevermore; Anger in Village Over N.Y.U. Tower Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NINA SIEGAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siegal, Nina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Preservationists and Greenwich Village neighborhood groups fight to save two historic treasures, house where Edgar Allan Poe once lived and town house renovated by McKim, Mead and White, which are scheduled for demolition to make way for 13-story building for New York University School of Law; argue that law school building will eviscerate part of Village's heritage and replace it with tower that will obscure views of landmark Judson Memorial Church, which sold town house to university; law school says new building is critical to school's survival; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Behind the landmark Judson Memorial Church, which frames the sky south of Washington Square Park through its ornate campanile, there is a quaint, if somewhat dilapidated, block of mustard and red brick houses.</p>
        <p>Preservationists say two historic treasures reside on this unassuming Greenwich Village swath: a house where Edgar Allan Poe once lived and a town house renovated by McKim, Mead and White.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Behind the landmark Judson Memorial Church, which frames the sky south of Washington Square Park through its ornate campanile, there is a quaint, if somewhat dilapidated, block of mustard and red brick houses.</p>
        <p>Preservationists say two historic treasures reside on this unassuming Greenwich Village swath: a house where Edgar Allan Poe once lived and a town house renovated by McKim, Mead and White.</p>
        <p>By the end of the summer, the stretch of four-story to six-story buildings on West Third Street between Thompson and Sullivan Streets will most likely be gone.</p>
        <p>And, to the dismay of city preservationists and neighborhood groups, it may be replaced by a 13-story building for the New York University School of Law.</p>
        <p>Residents of the Village and preservationists have long criticized university construction projects that they considered to be insensitive to the scale and historic character of the area, and a handful of N.Y.U. projects under way this year had already added fuel to residents' complaints.</p>
        <p>But the law school's plan to erect a 13-story multipurpose building on West Third Street, which preservationists argue will eviscerate a part of the Village's heritage and replace it with a tower that will obscure views of the Judson Church, has inflamed tensions.</p>
        <p>''They're transforming Washington Square and changing the neighborhood's character by constructing buildings that are huge and really unattractive,'' said Aubrey Lees, a member of the Committee to Save Washington Square, a neighborhood group.</p>
        <p>Several of the city's leading preservation groups, like the Municipal Arts Society and the Landmarks Conservancy, as well as the Mystery Writers of America, have written to the law school, pleading with administrators to reconsider their plans. And the groups have tried to protect the buildings by seeking landmark designations. But residents of the buildings have been told to be out by July 31, and university officials said demolition could begin posthaste.</p>
        <p>University administrators argue that the new buildings are critical to the school's survival. ''These decisions we are making are not window dressing,'' said John H. Beckman, a spokesman for the university. ''They are part and parcel of a plan that began 30 years ago when N.Y.U. took a good hard look at itself and realized it couldn't survive as a commuter school. What you're seeing now is a latter part of that process.''</p>
        <p>John Sexton, dean of the law school, said the new building on West Third Street will include needed faculty offices, classrooms and student lounges. He said the school is reaching out to neighbors to come up with a mutually acceptable plan.</p>
        <p>''We want to build a building that belongs in the neighborhood, that looks good in the Village, and we will do so in consultation with the community,'' Mr. Sexton said. ''But we do not accept the views of preservationists who say nothing can ever change.''</p>
        <p>The university told its neighbors at community board meetings in December that it would build on West Third Street, shortly after the law school purchased the Judson House, a Greek Revival town house on the corner of West Third and Thompson, from the Judson Church for $3.6 million.</p>
        <p>Peter Laarman, senior minister of the church, said the house had become a financial burden, costing about $17,000 a year to maintain. The church sold the house to the university because the law school promised to give the church space in the new building, and to consult with congregants on the building's design.</p>
        <p>''The proposed structure maintains the open sky behind the church itself,'' Mr. Laarman said, ''and it won't be a disaster by any means.''</p>
        <p>The parcel completed a puzzle the university had been piecing together for at least two years: with this property, it owned every lot on the southern half of the block.</p>
        <p>In February, the university began meeting with neighborhood groups and preservation advocates to discuss the project and present design sketches. But many of the people who attended the meetings said that the discussions began too late because officials had already decided to tear down the historic structures.</p>
        <p>One of the buildings to be razed is the little red brick house at 85 West Third Street, where Poe lived in 1844 and 1845. Poe's early literary life was marked by a ''conspicuous lack of success,'' wrote historian Jeff Finlay in ''The Encyclopedia of New York,'' (Yale University Press, 1996). When Poe arrived in New York in 1844, he moved repeatedly from one East Broadway boardinghouse to another.</p>
        <p>In the fall of 1844, Poe moved into two rooms at the back of 85 Amity Street, now West Third, a block from the park which he hoped would help speed the recovery of his consumptive wife, Virginia, who died a year later. During his stay there the American Review published his poem ''The Raven,'' to international acclaim. He also helped to start and edit the Broadway Journal, a New Yorker of its day. And he began writing one of his most noted short stories, ''The Cask of Amontillado.''</p>
        <p>Poe lived close by several literary salons, like the Waverly Place home of Anne Charlotte Lynch, who held soirees with guests like Ralph Waldo Emerson and Herman Melville.</p>
        <p>Poe, who sometimes gave readings of his new works at such gatherings, alienated himself from the Village literary crowd when his unflattering portrayal of its members in ''The Literati of New York'' was published in 1846. But by then he was ensconced in the country, in what is now the Bronx, in a small cottage that would become a city landmark.</p>
        <p>Some Poe scholars argue that the house on West Third Street is a more important site.</p>
        <p>''Scholars across this country have been enormously anguished about losing this house,'' said Burton R. Pollin, a professor emeritus of City University who has written 12 books on Poe.</p>
        <p>But New York University's resident Poe scholar, Kenneth Silverman, who wrote ''Edgar A. Poe: Mournful and Never-Ending Remembrance'' (Harper Collins, 1991), said the house had been significantly altered in the 154 years since Poe lived there.</p>
        <p>The lower exterior of the building, he said, only vaguely resembles its 19th century counterpart, as the stoop was removed and the entrance shifted.</p>
        <p>''I would hate to have anyone go by there today and say, 'Now, I have an idea of how Edgar Allan Poe lived,' '' Mr. Silverman said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sexton said he ''finds it hard to take seriously any claims that this building is special.'' He said he suspects preservationists are using the Poe house as an excuse to halt construction.</p>
        <p>Other preservation groups, like the Society for the Architecture of the City and the Landmarks Conservancy, have focused their energies on saving the Judson House. Originally three separate Greek Revival houses, the buildings were merged and redesigned in the 1890's by McKim, Mead and White, which also designed the Judson Church.</p>
        <p>David Garrard Lowe, an architectural historian who wrote ''Stanford White's New York'' (Watson-Guptill, 1992), said the house is a perfect example of colonial revival, the architectural style that the novelist Edith Wharton admired in her writings about the Village.</p>
        <p>This spring, Poe scholars asked the city's Landmarks Preservation Commission to designate the Poe house as a landmark to protect it from demolition, but after considering the documentation, the agency declined to hold a hearing. Last week, the New York State Office of Historic Preservation announced that it had determined that the Judson House was eligible for listing in the state and national registers of historic places. But such a designation would not necessarily protect the house from demolition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sexton said the architects of the new building, Kohn Pedersen Fox, are still considering preservationists' concerns. ''But,'' he added, ''the fact of the matter is that it is literally impossible to maintain those buildings and go along with our program.''</p>
        <p>The West Third Street project is the second N.Y.U. building plan that has chafed some university neighbors this year.</p>
        <p>In January, the school completed demolition of the modernist Loeb Student Center, built in the 1950's on Washington Square South, to make way for the Helen and Martin Kimmel Center for University Life, designed by Kevin Roche, who has designed several recent additions to the Metropolitan Museum of Art.</p>
        <p>The old student center, Mr. Beckman said, was an embarrassment because it could not even accommodate half the students' requests for club meeting spaces.</p>
        <p>Some neighborhood groups fought Kimmel, which will be wider at its base and at its top than its predecessor, but the same height. One group, the Committee to Save Washington Square, filed suit in New York Supreme Court to try to halt construction until the university studied the impact it might have on the Village. The case was dismissed and is under appeal.</p>
        <p>Longtime neighborhood residents say the planning for the student center has been reminiscent of that of a building across the street -- the Elmer Holmes Bobst Library, a red sandstone hulk on Washington Square South. The library was built in the 1960's despite widespread neighborhood protest.</p>
        <p>Construction has also irked some neighbors at Union Square, where the university built a 14-story dormitory last year, and where another 18-story dormitory is going up now.</p>
        <p>The chief complaint with all these projects has been that the school does not adequately solicit neighborhood participation in the planning process.</p>
        <p>''They call us in after the process has gone beyond where they can make substantial changes,'' said F. Anthony Zunino, president of the Greenwich Village Society for Historic Preservation. Referring to West Third Street, he said: ''That whole street has become institutionalized all the way from Broadway to the end of the park, except this one block. They are destroying the scale of the neighborhood every time they tear down part of the Village.''</p>
        <p>When the Washington Square neighborhood was first developed in the 1830's it became fashionable for its Federal and Greek Revival homes, most of them just a few stories high. The district had ''a kind of established repose which is not of frequent occurrence in the other quarters of the long, shrill city,'' wrote Henry James, who grew up there, in his 1881 novel, ''Washington Square.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Beckman said that although the university has met with neighborhood groups and preservation advocates, it is not required to consult with its neighbors on the developments because the construction is within legal zoning limitations.</p>
        <p>''Even though we had a desperate need for space, we did not seek any variances so we could build higher,'' he said. ''We completely understand that we live in a neighborhood which has an interest and a stake in the architecture.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
