<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Man Is Charged in Death Of Officer During Chase</title>
    <meta content="19COP.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motorcycles, Motor Bikes and Motorscooters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Manslaughter</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chivers, C J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelly, John M (Police Officer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tritto, Guido</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Manslaughter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motorcycles, Motor Bikes and Motorscooters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E6D7113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Man Is Charged in Death Of Officer During Chase</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. CHIVERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chivers, C J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Guido Tritto, Staten Island laborer with long record of arrests, is charged with second-degree manslaughter for what authorities say was his role in death of Police Officer John M Kelly, who died on July 17 after he crashed his patrol during high speed chase; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Staten Island laborer with a long record of arrests was charged with second-degree manslaughter yesterday for what the authorities said was his role in the death of Police Officer John M. Kelly, who died Monday after he crashed his patrol car during a high-speed chase.</p>
        <p>The laborer, Guido Tritto, 43, was also charged with reckless endangerment, possession of stolen property, leaving the scene of an accident and driving with a suspended license.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Staten Island laborer with a long record of arrests was charged with second-degree manslaughter yesterday for what the authorities said was his role in the death of Police Officer John M. Kelly, who died Monday after he crashed his patrol car during a high-speed chase.</p>
        <p>The laborer, Guido Tritto, 43, was also charged with reckless endangerment, possession of stolen property, leaving the scene of an accident and driving with a suspended license.</p>
        <p>The police said Mr. Tritto sped away from the shoulder of the Staten Island Expressway on a motorcycle about 1:20 p.m. Monday after Officer Kelly stopped him for speeding.</p>
        <p>The authorities said Mr. Tritto's flight, on a Suzuki motorcycle bearing stolen license plates, led to a chase that ended a mile and a half later on a service road when Officer Kelly lost control of his unmarked 1999 Chevrolet Lumina and slammed sideways into a utility pole. Mr. Tritto drove on, the police said.</p>
        <p>The officer suffered multiple injuries, including severe head wounds, and died hours later at St. Vincent's Hospital on Staten Island.</p>
        <p>Police Commissioner Howard Safir said detectives arrested Mr. Tritto at his home at 164 St. Mary Avenue yesterday morning after the police Crime Stoppers phone line received a tip that he was involved.</p>
        <p>He said the police had found the motorcycle involved in the chase and were investigating whether it, like the license plates, had been stolen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tritto's criminal record  reaches back to 1974, Mr. Safir said, including 15 arrests on charges of burglary, menacing, reckless endangerment, possession of stolen property and aggravated unlicensed driving. He was released from prison in 1994 after serving a sentence for burglary and grand larceny.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tritto had been working as a laborer for a plumbing supply business, his estranged girlfriend, Lisa Payne, said yesterday. His brother said he had had only infrequent contact with him in recent years and described Mr. Tritto as something of a loner.</p>
        <p>A woman in Mr. Tritto's building who described herself as the building's caretaker said that she knew something was amiss Monday when Mr. Tritto came home at 6 p.m. with his upper arm wrapped in bandages and his ever-present light-brown toupee missing from his head. The motorcycle was gone, too, she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Payne, 34, said that his troubles often involved the motorcycle.</p>
        <p>''That motorcycle was too big for him,'' she said. ''It was too powerful. People used to call him the fall man. He'd fall two or three times a day.''</p>
        <p>Officer Kelly, 31, the father of two young sons, was an eight-year veteran and part of an extended family of police officers. His wife, Patricia, and three of his brothers are city police officers, as are two of his wife's brothers, the authorities said. His funeral is scheduled for Friday.</p>
        <p>His brother Tom Kelly, a police scuba diver, stood in front of John Kelly's house yesterday, shaken with grief. ''My brother died doing something he loved to do,'' he said. ''He was dedicated to police work, and he was extremely, extremely good at what he did.'' With tears welling in his eyes, he said John Kelly left behind two sons ''who don't know that their daddy is never coming home.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Payne said that when she went to jail yesterday to take Mr. Tritto some clothes and took along their 4-year-old son, Armando, Mr. Tritto reached out and hugged the boy through the bars. ''He said, 'Daddy did a bad thing, and this is what happens when you do a bad thing, and Daddy will make it up to you when he gets out.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
