<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Merrill Lynch to Cut About 1,800 Jobs in Brokerage Business</title>
    <meta content="Y19BRO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Merrill Lynch &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Schwab, Charles, &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE1DB113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="722" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Merrill Lynch to Cut About 1,800 Jobs in Brokerage Business</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Merrill Lynch &amp; Co says it will eliminate about 1,800 jobs, mostly at its operations in New Jersey; says expenses are rising 25 percent, while revenue is going up 15 percent; reports second-quarter earnings of $902 million, up from $673 million in second quarter of 1999, but down 15 percent from first quarter of 2000; says it will split its shares 2-for-1 next month and raise its quarterly dividend 7 percent, to 32 cents a share; Charles Schwab &amp; Co reports operating income rose 17 percent in quarter, to $198.8 million from year ago; total revenue was $1.4 billion, up 26 percent from $1.12 billion a year ago; net income dropped 20 percent, to $137 million from $170 million year earlier (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Grappling with slowing growth in its brokerage business, Merrill Lynch &amp; Company officials said yesterday that the firm will eliminate about 1,800 jobs, mostly at its operations in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>An internal announcement of the  cuts, most of which are expected in the next few weeks, came after Merrill announced that its second-quarter earnings rose 34 percent, despite a slim increase in revenue from commissions and slower growth in the amount of money customers invested at the firm. Merrill took in just $11 billion in new money from customers in the United States, less than half the $26 billion in net new assets reported by the rival brokerage firm Charles Schwab.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Grappling with slowing growth in its brokerage business, Merrill Lynch &amp; Company officials said yesterday that the firm will eliminate about 1,800 jobs, mostly at its operations in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>An internal announcement of the  cuts, most of which are expected in the next few weeks, came after Merrill announced that its second-quarter earnings rose 34 percent, despite a slim increase in revenue from commissions and slower growth in the amount of money customers invested at the firm. Merrill took in just $11 billion in new money from customers in the United States, less than half the $26 billion in net new assets reported by the rival brokerage firm Charles Schwab.</p>
        <p>All told, Schwab took in $37 billion in assets last quarter, but about $11 billion of that came through the U.S. Trust Corporation, a New York-based money management firm that Schwab bought this year. Excluding charges related to acquisitions, Schwab's operating income rose 17 percent, to $198.8 million, or 14 cents a diluted share, from a year ago.</p>
        <p>Like Schwab, Merrill recorded its second-biggest quarterly profit, after an extraordinary first quarter. But Merrill's earnings gain was driven by increases in stock trading and underwriting and fees from advising  on mergers and acquisitions.</p>
        <p>Merrill earned $902 million, or $2.01 a diluted share, up from $673 million, or $1.57 a share, in the second quarter of 1999. Though down 15 percent from the first quarter of 2000, Merrill's earnings easily exceeded analysts' expectation of $1.70 a share, according to First Call/ Thomson Financial.</p>
        <p>Merrill also said that it would split its shares 2-for-1 next month and the firm raised its quarterly dividend 7 percent, to 32 cents a share. Shares of Merrill Lynch, which have risen 53.9 percent this year, fell $3.75 yesterday, to $128.25.</p>
        <p>Guy Moszkowski, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney, said Merrill's performance showed that ''the downturn has been more shallow in the trading and investment banking business than you might expect.''</p>
        <p>But in the brokerage business, he said, ''Schwab's inflows were extremely strong compared to Merrill's.''</p>
        <p>Addressing the employees of Merrill's brokerage operations yesterday afternoon, E. Stanley O'Neal, who runs that unit, said changes had to be made because brokerage expenses were rising 25 percent this year, while revenue was increasing at a 15-percent clip.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Neal told the employees that 900 full-time jobs in the brokerage unit would be eliminated beginning this week. Another 400 people who work for the firm as consultants and independent contractors will also lose their jobs and about 500 jobs will be eliminated through attrition. The job cuts amount to about 5 percent of the unit's 37,000 employees.</p>
        <p>He said the cuts would affect all segments of the brokerage operation, which is based in Plainsboro, N.J., but would have little effect in the branch offices. None of Merrill's 15,200 brokers will be laid off.</p>
        <p>Merrill's chief financial officer, Thomas Patrick, said Merrill hoped to reduce its costs by more than $150 million a year.</p>
        <p>While Merrill's employees were dealing with the firm's second round of layoffs in less than two years, workers at Schwab were cheering their firm's proven ability to attract assets even when the stock market is in turmoil.</p>
        <p>Despite the sharp sell-off in technology stocks in April, Schwab attracted 400,000 accounts and lost about 200,000. Its customers' trading activity declined sharply, to 288,000 trades a day, from 386,600 trades a day in the first quarter. And the average commission it received on each of those trades continued to slide, to $36.65 from $46.44.</p>
        <p>Including the operations of U.S. Trust and Cybercorp, an online trading unit it acquired this year, Schwab had total revenue of $1.4 billion, up 26 percent from $1.12 billion a year ago. But its net income dropped 20 percent to $137 million, or 9 cents a diluted share, from $170 million, or 12 cents a share, a year ago.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
