<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.M. Revamps Incentive Plan Even After Profits Rise</title>
    <meta content="Y19AUT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rebates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rebates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1DB113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.M. Revamps Incentive Plan Even After Profits Rise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, July 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>General Motors Corp revamps its sales discounts for third quarter, while announcing its profits inched up in second quarter instead of falling slightly, as had been expected; raises its rebates by $500 on wide range of vehicles, but also increases lowest available interest rates on its discounted auto loans to 3.9 percent from 0.9 percent; company reports income from continuing operations was up 1 percent in second quarter, to $1.754 billion from $1.73 billion a year ago; sales rose to $48.74 billion from $45.07 billion a year earlier (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>General Motors today revamped its sales discounts for the third quarter, while announcing that its profits had inched up in the second quarter instead of falling slightly, as had been expected.</p>
        <p>G.M. raised its rebates by $500 on a wide range of cars, minivans, sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks. But the company also increased the lowest available interest rates on its discounted auto loans, to 3.9 percent from 0.9 percent. Recent interest rate increases by the Federal Reserve have made it prohibitively expensive for automakers to continue subsidizing deeply discounted loans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>General Motors today revamped its sales discounts for the third quarter, while announcing that its profits had inched up in the second quarter instead of falling slightly, as had been expected.</p>
        <p>G.M. raised its rebates by $500 on a wide range of cars, minivans, sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks. But the company also increased the lowest available interest rates on its discounted auto loans, to 3.9 percent from 0.9 percent. Recent interest rate increases by the Federal Reserve have made it prohibitively expensive for automakers to continue subsidizing deeply discounted loans.</p>
        <p>The Chrysler unit of DaimlerChrysler A.G. changed its incentives last month to emphasize rebates at the expense of auto loans, while the Ford Motor Company quietly did so earlier this month on a limited basis. But neither program was as generous in rebates as the deals G.M. made available to its dealers today, which took effect immediately and will last through Oct. 2.</p>
        <p>Because less-affluent buyers tend to choose auto loans while those with greater wealth tend to prefer rebates, the shift away from loans is likely to drive some less-prosperous customers out of the market, cooling overall sales and slowing the economy slightly, auto executives said.</p>
        <p>''Are the Fed actions having an impact in terms of how we're taking our vehicles to market? I would say yes,'' said Kevin E. Costello, Ford Motor's finance director for North American marketing and revenue analysis.</p>
        <p>Costly incentives in the second quarter had led many investors and some Wall Street analysts to fear that G.M. would post weak financial results today. But the company's net income from continuing operations ended up rising 1 percent, to $1.75 billion from $1.73 billion a year earlier. The giant automaker's earnings per share jumped 10.2 percent, to $2.93 from $2.66. That is largely because nearly two months ago the company reduced the number of its shares, by offering shareholders in exchange some of its Class H shares, which track the earnings of its Hughes Electronics subsidiary.</p>
        <p>Financial analysts had forecast that G.M would earn $2.82 a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial. G.M. outperformed the estimates because its revenue from each vehicle stayed flat despite increasing discounts, analysts said. This was possible partly because customers ordered more optional equipment.</p>
        <p>''More people are buying leather seats, more people are buying sun roofs,'' J. Michael Losh, G.M.'s chief financial officer, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>G.M. announced its earnings before the opening bell today, while word of its new incentives did not dribble out until after the close of trading. G.M. stock climbed 44 cents, to close at $60.81.</p>
        <p>Scott F. Merlis, an investment banker specializing in auto companies at Wasserstein Perella Securities Inc., said that financial markets had been expecting more harm to second-quarter earnings from the discounts. ''The higher incentives are not leading to a devastation of the bottom line,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ronald Zarrella, the president of G.M.'s North American operations, said that the automaker's average price for each vehicle after incentives would be down by roughly half a percentage point for the full year despite flat prices in the second quarter. He blamed competitive pressures. The average net price fell seven-tenths of 1 percent in the first quarter. It was unchanged in the second quarter.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s sales rose to $48.74 billion in the second quarter from $45.07 billion a year earlier.</p>
        <p>G.M. spun off its giant Delphi auto parts subsidiary during the second quarter of last year. Including the profits from that discontinued operation in last year's second-quarter results would mean that G.M.'s earnings actually shrank 8.7 percent, from $1.92 billion a year ago. But financial analysts have tended to exclude the Delphi figures, viewing the spinoff as a splitting of G.M. rather than the closing of a subsidiary.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
