<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SENATE APPROVES TAX CUT TO HELP MARRIED COUPLES</title>
    <meta content="19TAX.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E6D9113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1318" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SENATE APPROVES TAX CUT TO HELP MARRIED COUPLES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Senate, 61-38, approves tax cut for married couples in Republican election-year push to highlight differences with Democrats over what to do with federal budget surplus; bill would cut income taxes for almost all married couples, whether or not they now pay marriage penalty, by total of $248 billion over next 10 years; Republican leaders say they will quickly reconcile bill with smaller bill passed by House; Pres Clinton says he will veto bill, in part because too much of cut will go to affluent; again offers to sign bill if Congress approves his plan to add prescription drug coverage to Medicare; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Senate passed a tax cut for married couples today, taking a big step in the election-year push by Republicans to highlight their differences with Democrats over what to do with the federal budget surplus.</p>
        <p>The vote was 61 to 38. Eight Democrats joined Republicans to approve the measure, which would reduce income taxes for nearly all married couples, by a total of $248 billion over the next 10 years. One Republican voted against the bill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Senate passed a tax cut for married couples today, taking a big step in the election-year push by Republicans to highlight their differences with Democrats over what to do with the federal budget surplus.</p>
        <p>The vote was 61 to 38. Eight Democrats joined Republicans to approve the measure, which would reduce income taxes for nearly all married couples, by a total of $248 billion over the next 10 years. One Republican voted against the bill.</p>
        <p>A similar though somewhat smaller measure passed the House earlier this year. Republican leaders said they would act quickly to meld the two versions and send the legislation to President Clinton.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said he would veto the bill, in part because too much of the cut would go to affluent taxpayers at a time when, he maintained, the needs of low- and middle-income people are not being met.</p>
        <p>But in an acknowledgment that tax reductions appear to be gaining political appeal as budget surplus projections grow, Mr. Clinton reiterated his willingness to negotiate a compromise under which he would accept a tax cut for couples of the scale sought by Republicans if Congress would accept his plan to add prescription drug coverage to Medicare.</p>
        <p>Republicans showed no inclination to take him up on the offer and said a veto would help them make their case that Democrats are standing in the way of popular tax cuts.</p>
        <p>The bill passed by the Senate was packaged by Republicans as a reduction in the ''marriage penalty,'' the quirk in the tax code that leaves many two-income couples paying a higher tax bill than they would if they had remained single.</p>
        <p>But it would cut taxes for almost all married couples, whether or not they now pay a marriage penalty. (It would not cut taxes for single people.)</p>
        <p>Republicans said the bill was good economic and social policy because it would help to eliminate what they see as an unfair levy on marriage while advancing their agenda of returning as much of the surplus as possible to taxpayers before it is spent by Washington.</p>
        <p>They said their case was only helped today by the release of new surplus projections from the Congressional Budget Office. The budget office said it now expected the surplus outside of Social Security to total nearly $2.2 trillion over the next 10 years, assuming that government spending grows in line with inflation. The projection is about $300 billion higher than an estimate made by the White House last month.</p>
        <p>''This bill is the centerpiece of our efforts to reduce the tax overpayment by American families,'' said the chairman of the Senate Finance Committee, William V. Roth Jr., Republican of Delaware. ''I would ask those who oppose this family tax relief, Just how big will America's budget surplus have to get before America's families deserve to receive some of their tax dollars back?''</p>
        <p>The Senate Republican leader,  Trent Lott of Mississippi, said the new surplus projections might allow Congress to phase in some of the provisions in the bill more quickly than planned. He said House and Senate negotiators would consider that issue as they worked to reconcile their differing versions of the legislation this week.</p>
        <p>Democrats said the bill suffered from a truth-in-advertising problem, since it would not completely eliminate the marriage penalty and would provide a tax cut even to couples, mostly those with only one working  spouse, who benefit from a marriage bonus -- that is, they pay a lower tax bill because they are married than they would if single.</p>
        <p>More important, Democrats said, Republicans have shown once again that their main goal is to provide tax breaks to upper-income people, even if doing so requires gambling the country's economic future on what the minority described as the dubious proposition that the surpluses will materialize as projected.</p>
        <p>''I think that the surplus projections are the fiscal equivalent of the dot-com stock market,'' said the Senate Democratic leader, Tom Daschle of South Dakota.</p>
        <p>Both the House and the Senate have now passed both the tax cut for married couples and the other main Republican tax bill this year, the repeal of the estate tax, which Mr. Clinton has also vowed to veto.</p>
        <p>Although polls have repeatedly found that voters do not see tax cuts as a priority, Republicans remain wedded to them ideologically and continue to put them at the heart of their political strategy. They say that individuals can better decide how to spend the money than government, and that leaving budget surpluses in Washington will lead inevitably to an increase in the size and reach of the federal government.</p>
        <p>Democrats acknowledged that specific tax cuts, including the bill passed today, had some political appeal, and they are increasingly offering their own tax agenda focused on providing tax breaks to low- and middle-income people. But they said the Republicans were heading for political trouble by weighting their tax cuts to the wealthy and ignoring middle-class concerns like the costs of college tuition and child care.</p>
        <p>The legislation passed today -- which under an arcane budget rule would technically require re-enactment after five years -- would increase the standard deduction for married couples filing jointly, starting next year, so that it is twice the standard deduction for single taxpayers.</p>
        <p>The deduction is adjusted each year for inflation. For this year, the standard deduction for couples filing jointly is $7,350, or 1.67 times the deduction for single people, $4,400. Excluding any change for inflation, the legislation would increase the deduction for couples filing jointly next year to $8,800.</p>
        <p>The bill would also gradually change the income levels covered by the two lowest income-tax brackets, 15 percent and 28 percent, so that the brackets for married couples filing jointly would grow to cover twice as much income as for single people.</p>
        <p>The brackets change each year to adjust for inflation. For this year, the 15 percent bracket covers the first $26,250 of income for single people and 1.67 times as much -- $43,850 --  for couples filing jointly. The 28 percent brackets pick up where the 15 percent brackets end, and under current law extend to $63,550 for single people and to 1.67 times as much, $105,950, for couples filing jointly.</p>
        <p>The legislation would increase the size of the brackets for couples filing jointly in steps over the next six years until they cover twice the income levels covered by the brackets for single people.</p>
        <p>The bill would also give a tax break to married couples who claim the earned-income tax credit, which is a rebate for low-income working people. And it would keep certain other tax credits for families, including the child and dependent care credits, from being reduced by the alternative minimum tax.</p>
        <p>The Democrats who voted for the bill were Senators Joseph R. Biden Jr. of Delaware, Robert C. Byrd of West Virginia, Max Cleland of Georgia, Dianne Feinstein of California, Bob Kerrey of Nebraska, Herb Kohl of Wisconsin, Mary L. Landrieu of Louisiana and Robert G. Torricelli of New Jersey. The Republican who broke with his party to vote against the measure was Senator George V. Voinovich of Ohio.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
