<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mrs. Clinton's Health Plan Expands on a Current Law</title>
    <meta content="19HILL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216088"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E2DA113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1150" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mrs. Clinton's Health Plan Expands on a Current Law</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER STEINHAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton presents her plan to extend health insurance to millions of Americans, including 1.1 million New Yorkers; plan hews closely to one proposed by Vice President Al Gore and could not be further in details and scope from ill-fated program she helped mastermind in early 1990's; would expand existing government program to insure children by loosening eligibility requirements and giving poor adults similar benefits (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton presented her plan yesterday to extend health insurance to millions of Americans, including 1.1 million New Yorkers. Her plan, which hews closely to the one proposed by Vice President Al Gore, could not be further in details and scope from the ill-fated program she helped to mastermind in the early 1990's.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton outlined her initiative in a news conference at Columbia-Presbyterian Center in Manhattan. Among other things, it would, expand an existing government program to insure children by loosening eligibility requirements and giving poor adults similar benefits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton presented her plan yesterday to extend health insurance to millions of Americans, including 1.1 million New Yorkers. Her plan, which hews closely to the one proposed by Vice President Al Gore, could not be further in details and scope from the ill-fated program she helped to mastermind in the early 1990's.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton outlined her initiative in a news conference at Columbia-Presbyterian Center in Manhattan. Among other things, it would, expand an existing government program to insure children by loosening eligibility requirements and giving poor adults similar benefits.</p>
        <p>''We will never be the kind of New York or America we should and can be if we do not figure out a way to provide quality affordable health care to every one of us,'' Mrs. Clinton said.</p>
        <p>In New York, more than 19 percent of people under 65, or 3.1 million people, lack health insurance, and the ranks of those without insurance have grown faster here than in the rest of the nation. A large part of them are the working poor who make too much money to qualify for Medicaid, but do not receive benefits from their employer or cannot afford to buy them. And despite a federal program that covers children, about 700,000 children in New York still lack insurance.</p>
        <p>The expansion of insurance and health care to all Americans was Mrs. Clinton's goal in the early 90's. Her plan for universal coverage was flattened by Congress in 1994 after determined lobbying by opponents.</p>
        <p>That plan put much of the burden of covering the uninsured on employers. But the plan presented yesterday by Mrs. Clinton, who is running for the Senate, returns much of the burden to the government and steers clear from visions of insuring the entire nation in one blow.</p>
        <p>''You may remember that seven years ago I had a few ideas about this topic,'' said Mrs. Clinton, who has taken to joking about her earlier failed effort and stressing that she has learned to take small steps toward change in one of the most complex policy issues in the country. She added: ''There are some people who don't think I should talk about health care at all. But how can you run for Senate and not?''</p>
        <p>Her opponent in the Senate race, Representative Rick A. Lazio, immediately criticized the plan, asserting that she did not reveal where the money to pay for such expansions would come from.</p>
        <p>His camp added that the federal government has shortchanged New York by not providing a fair share of federal funds for existing programs, and asserted that Mrs. Clinton should have influenced her husband in this area. ''Apparently, Mrs. Clinton is now keeping secrets about the financing of her health care scheme,'' a statement issued by the Lazio campaign said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton suggested that federal budget surpluses could be used to pay for her plan.</p>
        <p>The core of her proposal relied heavily on the Children's Health Insurance Program, a 1997 federal-state effort. In this program, the federal government gives states 65 percent of their costs to insure children from families whose income is no more than about $31,000 a year, for a family of four, or about 200 percent of the federal poverty line.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton proposes expanding that program to children in families living at an income level from 250 to 300 percent of the poverty line, or about $51,000 for a family of four. That would cost an additional $10 billion over 10 years.</p>
        <p>She would also like to see the program extended to parents of children living within this income bracket. The New York State Legislature recently passed a similar plan, known as Family Health Plus.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton said she also would make sure that all states use their money under the federal program, or face losing the federal matching funds. Many states have ignored the program altogether, or have not enrolled as many children as are eligible by making the process too cumbersome.</p>
        <p>In addition, she proposes giving a 25 percent refundable tax credit to people who are not insured through their jobs and need to buy insurance as individuals, and giving families whose incomes are above 300 percent of the poverty line a chance to buy Children's Health Insurance Program insurance at a rate cheaper than the market rates for individuals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has made similar proposals. His and Mrs. Clinton's plans differ mostly in their generosity. Her  proposals for establishing eligibility are a bit more lenient.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's plan is far removed from her notions of universal coverage in the early 1990's, which included a requirement that employers pick up 80 percent of the cost of any health care plan their workers chose.</p>
        <p>''This is very definitely going step by step rather than trying to do it in a big leap,'' said Assemblyman Richard N. Gottfried, chairman of the Assembly's Health Committee. ''In today's reality, I think getting there step by step is hard to avoid.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio has not yet released any specific proposal to deal with those who do not have health insurance. Mrs. Clinton's proposal came after Mr. Lazio's wife, Patricia, a nurse, began appearing in a television advertisement last week defending his record on health care issues in Congress. ''He has not exactly been silent on these issues,'' said a campaign spokesman, Michael Marr.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's advisers insisted that President Clinton has yet to make sure that New York gets its fair share of federal money. New York is indeed in danger of spending large amounts of state money on the Children's Health Insurance Program next year. Under the law, New York is to have 65 percent of the costs for its health insurance program reimbursed by the federal government,  up to $256 million. The law sets a timetable, in the fall, for states either to use their allocations or to relinquish what they haven't used to other states.</p>
        <p>Because New York has by far the largest such program in the country  -- 522,000 New York children are  enrolled -- it is well on its way to surpassing its cap. That means that New York might have to pick up the costs of additional enrollments.</p>
        <p>But many members of Congress would like to see states that have failed to spend their money get another two years to work out their programs before losing any funds. Health care experts say it is unlikely that the Clinton administration could find a way to release more money to New York for this program until these issues are resolved.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
