<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberties; Decoding Male DNA: Whassup?</title>
    <meta content="19DOWD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216086"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sex and the City (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5DA113BF93AA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberties; Decoding Male DNA: Whassup?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>PASADENA, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed column on the hopeless efforts of television executives to come up with a show that will do for men what Sex and the City does for women (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Desperate to catch up to the summer reality phenomenon, NBC-TV executives are close to a deal for a show called ''Chains of Love,'' in which a young woman selects four men from a pool of 100 prospects. The four men are then chained to the woman's wrists and ankles, two on each side, for a week, while she eliminates them one by one, until she gets to Mr. Right. Or perhaps Mr. Left. (No ball and chain jokes.)</p>
        <p>Questioned at the press tour here yesterday about the cheesiness of this program, which was a hit in the Netherlands, NBC's president of entertainment, Garth Ancier, protested that ''It's a relationship show.'' Once the laughter among the audience of TV writers died down, a chagrined Mr. Ancier added, ''That wasn't supposed to be funny.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Desperate to catch up to the summer reality phenomenon, NBC-TV executives are close to a deal for a show called ''Chains of Love,'' in which a young woman selects four men from a pool of 100 prospects. The four men are then chained to the woman's wrists and ankles, two on each side, for a week, while she eliminates them one by one, until she gets to Mr. Right. Or perhaps Mr. Left. (No ball and chain jokes.)</p>
        <p>Questioned at the press tour here yesterday about the cheesiness of this program, which was a hit in the Netherlands, NBC's president of entertainment, Garth Ancier, protested that ''It's a relationship show.'' Once the laughter among the audience of TV writers died down, a chagrined Mr. Ancier added, ''That wasn't supposed to be funny.''</p>
        <p>It is a truth universally acknowledged that romance and reality are mutually exclusive, but TV executives are obsessed with those two topics at the moment.</p>
        <p>When they are not negotiating for reality programs that create creepy Darwinian showdowns on a double-decker bus, in a prison, in a boot camp, in a hair salon, in an apartment of five girls and one houseboy who want to be celebrities, programmers are trying to come up with the male version of ''Sex and the City.''</p>
        <p>One network executive said that this season every network had three shows in development that aspired to be the male ''Sex and the City,'' pulling back the curtain on how men really talk about women, the same way the HBO hit lets men be privy to all that female post-game analysis.</p>
        <p>The men I know think you cannot reverse the formula. ''Men don't have any secrets,'' says one. ''And if they did, they wouldn't sit around talking about them in groups at brunch over cosmopolitans. It would not get much past 'Wow! Look at her.' And 'Whassup?' ''</p>
        <p>Just try to switch genders for this week's episode of ''Sex and the City,'' which is about the girls worrying about having too many sex partners. No man has ever been consumed with fear about being a slut.</p>
        <p>One attempt that will air this fall on ABC is ''Madigan Men,'' reteaming Broadway's ''Moon for the Misbegotten'' actors Gabriel Byrne and Roy Dotrice as a father and son in New York. Mr. Byrne plays a sensitive architect, the father of a teenage son, whose wife has left him for their nutritionist.</p>
        <p>The show's ridiculous premise is that Gabriel Byrne would find it hard to make his way in the New York dating scene, and that Irish men would talk to each other -- even for half an hour once a week over Guinness -- about their emotions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Byrne, who came to NBC with the idea, said he had been inspired by  the covers of women's magazines and by ''Sex and the City.'' ''What 'Sex and the City' does so wonderfully is it opened that secret world of women for examination by men,'' he says. ''It was incredibly fascinating to men because it looked like a secret door into a world that we knew nothing about.''</p>
        <p>Unfortunately for Mr. Byrne, the only door likely to be opened by this show is the one marked ''exit,'' since it focuses more on father-son angst and Irish proverbs (''A windy day is not the day for thatching'') than giving women tips on the male psyche and how to tame it.</p>
        <p>Fox may have better luck since it went straight to the source, Darren Star, the creator of ''Sex and the City,'' to design its new series about single men and their tempestuous dating behavior. ''The Street'' is about carnivorous, libidinous young stockbrokers working in a Wall Street firm, and their adventures with gorgeous bankers, Russian strippers/day traders, hermaphrodites and receptionists looking to climb by reading The Wall Street Journal.</p>
        <p>The secrets about men start spilling in the first show, when the firm successfully launches an I.P.O. for a company selling Ivy League sperm. ''Yale sperm is worth more than Penn sperm,'' says one partner, ''and anyone can tell you that.''</p>
        <p>Here at least we can learn some profound truths about men, what they talk about when they get together for a beer, what kind of women really appeal to them.</p>
        <p>''Xena?'' one guy asks another. ''Or Buffy?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
