<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Buchanan Hoping for Political Lift to Rival Physical One</title>
    <meta content="Y12BUC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/politics/12BUCH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229945"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REFORM PARTY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third-Party Moves (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Reform Party</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buchanan, Patrick J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third-Party Moves (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EEDA1638F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Buchanan Hoping for Political Lift to Rival Physical One</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>McLEAN, Va., Sept. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reform Party presidential candidate Patrick J Buchanan, on mend from gall bladder surgery, is laboring to regain edge but faces fight not so much against major party nominees as against fractiousness within party; his nine-month struggle for nomination is continuing into chaotic home stretch; he must deal with state-by-state skirmishes over ballot legitimacy that he never foresaw when he left Republican Party in Fall 1999; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With his  ''pitchfork brigades'' gone the way of his gall bladder, Patrick J. Buchanan, the persistent presidential candidate, was feeling well on the mend from surgery today when his doorbell rang and he was greeted with another subpoena from the tireless antagonists he has stirred in the Reform Party.</p>
        <p>''It's the Ross Perot people,'' Mr. Buchanan said, fairly sighing at the pains of fate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With his  ''pitchfork brigades'' gone the way of his gall bladder, Patrick J. Buchanan, the persistent presidential candidate, was feeling well on the mend from surgery today when his doorbell rang and he was greeted with another subpoena from the tireless antagonists he has stirred in the Reform Party.</p>
        <p>''It's the Ross Perot people,'' Mr. Buchanan said, fairly sighing at the pains of fate.</p>
        <p>After four weeks of medical recuperation and not a day out campaigning, the candidate is laboring to regain his edge. Yet he must resume a fight not so much against the major party nominees as within his fractious adopted party.</p>
        <p>The fresh Reform steed Mr. Buchanan envisioned saddling for himself has behaved more like a dragon threatening to devour his candidacy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buchanan's nine-month struggle for the Reform nomination is continuing into a chaotic homestretch. Now he must deal with state-by-state skirmishes over ballot legitimacy that he never foresaw when he left the Republican Party last fall.</p>
        <p>''I think Perot's funding all this,'' Mr. Buchanan said of the flurry of court challenges.</p>
        <p>He suspects that Mr. Perot, despite his associates' repeated denial of political involvement, continues to push the buttons of the party he created and is trying to rebuff Mr. Buchanan as a usurper.</p>
        <p>''Where else are they getting the money?'' Mr. Buchanan asked as he put the subpoena aside and focused on sweeter possibilities this week that might resurrect his candidacy, now moribund at 1 percent in the polls.</p>
        <p>''Vote Lazarus!'' the combative conservative exulted grimly. His laughter cracked forth here in his home in a sylvan enclave neighboring the Central Intelligence Agency's suburban compound.</p>
        <p>A touch of the old pugilist's gleam returned to a figure harrowed by hospitalization. Mr. Buchanan anticipates a victory on Tuesday from the Federal Elections Commission. The  commission, which is to rule on a challenge from anti-Buchanan Reformers, has received a staff recommendation that Mr. Buchanan is the legitimate nominee and deserves the party's $12.7 million in federal campaign funds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buchanan also hopes for favorable word soon in his own lawsuit challenging the decision to bar him from the presidential debates. He concedes that ''any chance to achieve something dramatic probably fades away'' if he loses the chance to compete in the debates' national television arena.</p>
        <p>Even if he wins the funding and debate victories, Mr. Buchanan expects court fights all the way to November from the Reform minority that bolted his nominating convention and endorsed John Hagelin, an Iowa physicist.</p>
        <p>Through it all, Mr. Buchanan maintains that he has no regrets about quitting the Republican Party. Four years ago, he electrified his supporters -- the ''pitchfork brigades'' -- with his upset victory in the New Hampshire primary. He switched parties last October after his renewed quest flatlined as Gov. George W. Bush of Texas moved for the Republican nomination.</p>
        <p>''Did you watch this year's Republican Convention?'' Mr. Buchanan asked about a party he feels has abandoned conservative bedrock to ape President Clinton's centrist techniques. ''Bush would have put me down in the basement with all the other conservatives. I still feel liberated.''</p>
        <p>Twelve pounds lighter than his usual trim, the candidate is promising his best shot for the remaining eight weeks -- providing he can get noticed. ''In American politics, that's a lot of time,'' he said. But he acknowledged that he had been unable to afford advertising and that all the court fees would cut into the federal subsidy even if he could gain it soon.</p>
        <p>He concedes he never imagined such a year as this has been.</p>
        <p>''Look, if we had gotten our money the day after the convention, and I'd have been healthy, we'd be about 5 percent now in the polls,'' he said. ''And if we got into the debates, we'd get far more than Ross Perot got in 1996,'' he added. Mr. Perot won 8 percent of the vote in 1996.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buchanan paused as he scratched behind the ears of Gipper, his 15-year-old house cat. ''Yeah, well, of all the words of tongue and pen,'' he said, ''The saddest of these is 'might have been.' ''</p>
        <p>He quickly substituted optimism for regret. ''Hey, Gipper, we may have the Secret Service back out in the driveway again,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buchanan, a history buff, cited the case of Frederick the Great suddenly delivered by absurd political accident to triumph after failing steadily at multiple wars. (A rival monarch died and was succeeded by a great admirer of his, who immediately signed a peace treaty.) ''And what did they say about Calvin Coolidge? His career was the clearest example ever seen of 'Providential intervention!' ''</p>
        <p>The recuperating candidate grinned; the cat purred.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of people who don't want us to be alive,'' Mr. Buchanan said, conspiring with Gipper at Providential intervention. ''At least that's a good feeling.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REFORM PARTY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
