<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From the Report on Violence</title>
    <meta content="Y12VTEX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/national/12VTEX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Trade Commission</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5DE1638F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From the Report on Violence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from executive summary of Federal Trade Commission's report on marketing of violent entertainment to children (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the executive summary of the Federal Trade Commission's report on the marketing of violent entertainment to children, which was commissioned by President Clinton:</p>
        <p>The self-regulatory programs of the motion picture, music recording and electronic game industries each address violence, as well as sexual content, language, drug use and other explicit content that may be of concern to parents. In keeping with the president's request, the commission focused on the marketing of entertainment products designated as violent under these systems. . . . The commission carefully examined the structure of these rating and labeling systems, and studied how these self-regulatory systems work in practice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the executive summary of the Federal Trade Commission's report on the marketing of violent entertainment to children, which was commissioned by President Clinton:</p>
        <p>The self-regulatory programs of the motion picture, music recording and electronic game industries each address violence, as well as sexual content, language, drug use and other explicit content that may be of concern to parents. In keeping with the president's request, the commission focused on the marketing of entertainment products designated as violent under these systems. . . . The commission carefully examined the structure of these rating and labeling systems, and studied how these self-regulatory systems work in practice.</p>
        <p>The commission found that despite the variations in the three industries' systems, the outcome is consistent: individual companies in each industry routinely market to children the very products that have the industries' own parental warnings or ratings with age restrictions due to their violent content. Indeed, for many of these products, the commission found evidence of marketing and media plans that expressly target children under 17.</p>
        <p>In addition, the companies' marketing and media plans showed strategies to promote and advertise their products in the media outlets most likely to reach children under 17, including those television programs ranked as the ''most popular'' with the under-17 age group, such as ''Xena: Warrior Princess,'' ''South Park'' and ''Buffy the Vampire Slayer''; magazines and Internet sites with a majority or substantial (i.e., over 35 percent) under-17 audience, such as Game Pro, Seventeen and Right On!, as well as mtv.com, ubl.com and happypuppy.com; and teen hangouts, such as game rooms, pizza parlors and sporting apparel stores.</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Of the 44 movies rated R for violence the commission selected for its study, the commission found that 35, or 80 percent, were targeted to children under 17. Marketing plans for 28 of those 44, or 64 percent, contained express statements that the film's target audience included children under 17. For example, one plan for a violent R-rated film stated, ''Our goal was to find the elusive teen target audience and make sure everyone between the ages of 12-18 was exposed to the film.'' Though the marketing plans for the remaining seven R-rated films did not expressly identify an under-17 target audience, they led the commission to conclude that children under 17 were targeted nonetheless. That is, the plans were either extremely similar to the plans of the films that did identify an under-17 target audience, or they detailed actions synonymous with targeting that age group, such as promoting the film in high schools or in publications with majority under-17 audiences.</p>
        <p>Music</p>
        <p>Of the 55 music recordings with explicit content labels the commission selected for its study, marketing plans for 15, or 27 percent, expressly identified teenagers as part of their target audience. One such plan, for instance, stated that its ''Target audience'' was ''Alternative/urban, rock, pop, hard-core -- 12-34.'' The marketing documents for the remaining 40 explicit-content labeled recordings examined did not expressly state the age of the target audience, but they detailed the same methods of marketing as the plans that specifically identified teens as part of their target audience, including placing advertising in media that would reach a majority or substantial percentage of children under 17.</p>
        <p>Games</p>
        <p>Of the 118 electronic games with a Mature rating for violence the commission selected for its study, 83, or 70 percent, targeted children under 17. The marketing plans for 60 of these, or 51 percent, expressly included children under 17 in their target audience.</p>
        <p>For example, one plan for a game rated Mature for its violent content described its ''target audience'' as ''Males 12-17 -- Primary; Males 18-34 -- Secondary.'' Another plan referred to the target market as ''Males 17-34 due to M rating (the true target is males 12-34).'' Documents for the remaining 23 games showed plans to advertise in magazines or on television shows with a majority or substantial under-17 audience. Most of the plans that targeted an under-17 audience set age 12 as the younger end of the spectrum, but a few plans for violent Mature-rated games targeted children as young as 6.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
