<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Johannesburg Journal; South Africa's New Poor: White and Bewildered</title>
    <meta content="Y12JOB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/world/12JOBU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229901"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swarns, Rachel L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7DE1638F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1268" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Johannesburg Journal; South Africa's New Poor: White and Bewildered</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL L. SWARNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swarns, Rachel L</byline>
      <dateline>JOHANNESBURG, Sept. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>White poverty has become new and growing problem in South Africa, where many whites who benefitted from racist employment practices of past now find themselves in dire economic straits; many face increasing competition for first time, particularly at lower rungs of work force, as companies that previously refused to hire blacks now seek them out in economy which is shedding thousands of jobs; between 1995 and 1999, ratio of unemployed whites increased from 3.4 percent to 6.8 percent; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Martin van Niekerk wakes with a start and his sleepy blue eyes wander lazily from the fraying curtains fluttering over the window to the sagging ceiling and the shabby walls lined with brown cardboard. And then he remembers.</p>
        <p>He is not at home. He has tumbled through a hole in the floor of his once predictable life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Martin van Niekerk wakes with a start and his sleepy blue eyes wander lazily from the fraying curtains fluttering over the window to the sagging ceiling and the shabby walls lined with brown cardboard. And then he remembers.</p>
        <p>He is not at home. He has tumbled through a hole in the floor of his once predictable life.</p>
        <p>The slaughterhouse where he weighed and priced animal skins for 17 years shut down in 1998. The clothing store where he later worked as a security guard closed abruptly three weeks ago. For days, he and his wife and three children slept in the street until they landed in this shelter, the Kempton Christian Action Settlement.</p>
        <p>And today he and the scores of men and women living here are members of a tiny but growing slice of South Africa's evolving society: They are unemployed, homeless and white.</p>
        <p>''My cell phone, I sell that,'' said Mr. van Niekerk, 38, as he guided a visitor through Shack No. G7, his temporary one-room home. ''And the iron. Even my wife, she sells our wedding rings. But it is not enough to pay the rent.''</p>
        <p>''This new South Africa is a very difficult place,'' Mr. van Niekerk admitted quietly as he sat heavily on his borrowed bed. ''I used to feel different. I used to feel like it was my country. You can't say it's your country anymore.''</p>
        <p>Being a white man in South Africa used to mean having a steady job, a house, a car, a certain respectability. For an overwhelming majority of white men, it still does.</p>
        <p>But for an increasing number of whites, there are startling new realities. Between 1995 and 1999, the ratio of unemployed whites increased from 3.4 percent to 6.8 percent, government statistics show.</p>
        <p>That is minuscule, of course, compared with the unemployment rate among the black majority -- about 35 percent -- after decades in which an all-white government denied educational and professional opportunities to blacks.</p>
        <p>The poor are still overwhelmingly black and the rich and working class are still overwhelmingly white. Still, stories like Mr. van Niekerk's send shivers through many whites, who account for about 10 percent of the population.</p>
        <p>Companies that once refused to hire blacks now seek them out. Whites are facing increasing competition, particularly at the lower rungs of the work force, as the economy sheds thousands of jobs.</p>
        <p>And Greyling Bezuidenhout, an organizer for the Mine Workers Union, fears that the future will only bring tougher times to a country that once reserved decent jobs for those with white skin.</p>
        <p>''There's a new problem in this country, and that's white poverty, but nobody want to talk about it,'' said Mr. Bezuidenhout, whose union represents 65,000 Afrikaners in mining, telecommunications and engineering.</p>
        <p>He acknowledges that whites benefited from the racist employment practices of the past. Some, he says, got by without being productive simply because they were white. But now, he adds, people are suffering for old government policies they did not actively support, and no one seems to care.</p>
        <p>''Minority rights are seen as politically incorrect,'' he said, as he shepherded a visitor through several homeless settlements for whites last week. ''At the end of the day, we have to look after ourselves. There's no one else to do it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bezuidenhout -- lanky and bearded, with bespectacled eyes that burn with his passion for helping the poorest of his people -- is on a mission that seems decidedly unpopular. He keeps a list of settlements and visits them regularly, keeping track of their problems and needs. But when he approaches big companies for donations, executives typically listen politely and decline, he says.</p>
        <p>Few businesses want to invest publicly in a whites-only venture, he said. As a result, places like the Kempton Christian Action Settlement, which opened several years ago, quickly fall into disrepair.</p>
        <p>''We don't condone the racism that has been done,'' Mr. Bezuidenhout said. ''But a lot of these guys were never supportive of the apartheid system. Now they pay for the past.''</p>
        <p>The forlorn wooden shacks here, all inhabited by parents with children, house 120 people. When the rains come, the water stands two inches above the floor. At night, the cold winds squeeze through cracks in the walls.</p>
        <p>Some whites here are prisoners of their insatiable thirst for drink and drugs. Others simply lost their grip on their working-class existence, falling out of modest but comfortable lives when factories closed or breadwinners fell sick.</p>
        <p>Mr. van Niekerk keeps a gold-framed certificate of his son's scholastic achievement hanging on the flimsy walls, a reminder that his children must continue to strive.</p>
        <p>And J. J. Wait holds on to his silver-plated watch, which ticks away the time in a world he no longer recognizes or understands.</p>
        <p>''I had a house worth 250,000 rand'' -- $35,000 -- ''and the bank took it back,'' said Mr. Wait, 42, who spent 10 years in the military police and eight as a security guard before he injured his back and lost his job.</p>
        <p>''Then followed my furniture, then my car,'' he said. ''I thought I'd work myself up, become a manager or something like that. But since the new government comes in, everything has fallen down.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wait says he lacks the proper certification to find a new security job, but he still blames his troubles on the end of apartheid, as many people do here. When he applies for jobs, he says, he is often told the slot is reserved for a black candidate.</p>
        <p>''Now, I'm not a racist,'' Mr. Wait cautioned hastily. ''My best friends in the army were black. But this government is doing nothing to help whites to improve their lifestyle.''</p>
        <p>In truth, many wealthy white business executives would say just the opposite. Earlier this year, a group of prominent Afrikaner executives issued a public declaration in support of President Thabo Mbeki, praising his fiscally conservative policies, which have reduced interest rates, inflation and the budget deficit.</p>
        <p>But that left the people here feeling more betrayed.</p>
        <p>Even the predominantly white opposition party now courts black voters, the homeless here grumble, while poor whites rummage through bags of second-hand clothing and dine from dented cans of vegetables.</p>
        <p>''You want to stand outside and scream, but it won't help,'' said Meie Erasmus, 51, a resident of Shack No. D7. She said her husband lost his job as a truck driver to a black who was willing to work for less.</p>
        <p>''We must accept how we are,'' she said, shaking her head. ''We can't do anything about it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. van Niekerk spends his time filling out job applications. It is a measure of his desperation that he is seeking manual labor, which for most whites is still unthinkable. ''I will even do a black man's work, just to get money,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But he would rather start over in a new country where he could feel like the man he once was. And when he gets depressed, he imagines a green land with vast, open spaces and room for a wandering people in search of a new home.</p>
        <p>''I think of Canada,'' Mr. van Niekerk said wistfully. ''Everything on TV, I like about Canada. But getting the money to get there, that's the problem.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
