<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Goldman Sachs to Acquire Top Firm on Trading Floors</title>
    <meta content="Y12GOL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/business/12GOLD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229979"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Goldman Sachs Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Spear Leeds &amp; Kellogg</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E0D71638F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="893" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Goldman Sachs to Acquire Top Firm on Trading Floors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Goldman Sachs Group confirms plan to acquire Spear, Leeds &amp; Kellogg, biggest trading firm on floors of nation's stock and options exchanges, for as much as $7.4 billion; will play $4.4 billion in stock and $2.1 billion in cash; Goldman expects to complete deal by end of year; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Goldman Sachs Group confirmed yesterday that it planned to make its most expensive acquisition to date by paying as much as $7.4 billion to buy Spear, Leeds &amp; Kellogg,  the biggest trading firm on the floors of the nation's stock and options exchanges.</p>
        <p>Goldman, one of the biggest securities firms on Wall Street, said it would pay $4.4 billion in stock and $2.1 billion in cash to acquire Spear, Leeds from its 54 partners. Goldman also will set aside another $900 million of its stock to retain Spear, Leeds employees after the purchase, which Goldman expects to complete by the end of the year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Goldman Sachs Group confirmed yesterday that it planned to make its most expensive acquisition to date by paying as much as $7.4 billion to buy Spear, Leeds &amp; Kellogg,  the biggest trading firm on the floors of the nation's stock and options exchanges.</p>
        <p>Goldman, one of the biggest securities firms on Wall Street, said it would pay $4.4 billion in stock and $2.1 billion in cash to acquire Spear, Leeds from its 54 partners. Goldman also will set aside another $900 million of its stock to retain Spear, Leeds employees after the purchase, which Goldman expects to complete by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Buying Spear, Leeds would give Goldman a much bigger presence in some businesses it seemed to have written off. Less than a year ago, Goldman officials were pushing for a restructuring of United States stock markets that would have hurt Spear, Leeds, and just a few months ago a Goldman executive called one of the main functions of Spear, Leeds ''unsustainable.''</p>
        <p>But now, Goldman's most senior executives are saying that Spear, Leeds will put Goldman Sachs at the forefront of a global boom in stock trading, no matter which direction the markets take. ''We think it's got the best technology,'' said Henry M. Paulson, Goldman's chairman and chief executive. ''We're assuming the markets are going to keep changing, and we're assuming that the U.S. market is going toward more electronic trading.''</p>
        <p>That trend has been in place for many years as trading on the all-electronic Nasdaq stock market has exploded, raising doubts about the future of auction markets like the one housed in the New York Stock Exchange's cavernous building at the corner of Broad and Wall streets in lower Manhattan. Late last year, Mr. Paulson himself called for changes in the way stocks are priced and traded, moves that would have threatened the existence of auction markets and the firms that keep them running.</p>
        <p>Spear, Leeds, one of the biggest private partnerships on Wall Street, is the biggest specialist, or operator of trading posts, on the floors of the New York and American stock exchanges as well as on the major options trading floors. In the nonstop auctions at those exchanges, specialists are responsible for maintaining orderly markets by matching up traders who want to buy certain securities with those who want to sell them.</p>
        <p>About one-third of the operating profit of Spear, Leeds comes from making markets on those trading floors, according to Goldman Sachs. But, in a cover story in Forbes magazine in May, Duncan Niederauer, a Goldman executive, described specialist-based auctions as unsustainable in an era of low-cost electronic communications.</p>
        <p>Goldman officials have not recanted those statements. But they clearly think there still is plenty of profit to be made in trading the old-fashioned way until it becomes clearer how and when the markets will change.</p>
        <p>''There is no such thing as a real bargain'' among the best financial companies, Mr. Paulson said, adding that Goldman ''wanted to pay a full and fair price.''</p>
        <p>Some analysts applauded the deal as a smart strategic move for a firm that is committed to being a leading provider of financial services to big customers.</p>
        <p>Joan Solotar, an analyst at Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette, was not concerned that the deal would increase Goldman's dependence on trading. ''They're not running the firm to smooth earnings,'' she said. ''If an investor wants a smooth earnings stream, he shouldn't invest in brokerage stocks.''</p>
        <p>Investors also seemed to approve of the transaction: Goldman's shares rose $8.06, to $132.31.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson said that Goldman might buy other specialist firms. He also said that Goldman would consider purchases that would add heft to its money-management operations. But he said the firm had little interest in acquiring either a brokerage firm, like Charles Schwab, or another investment bank.</p>
        <p>Goldman has always prided itself on its culture and Mr. Paulson said that Spear, Leeds was a close cultural fit, despite its history of violating the rules of the exchanges on which it trades. Spear, Leeds has repeatedly been fined and censured by exchanges and securities regulators for assorted transgressions, including failing to file timely reports of its short positions, or securities that it had sold but did not own.</p>
        <p>In one case in 1998, the National Association of Securities Dealers fined a unit of Spear, Leeds $950,000 and censured it after finding that the unit had intentionally delayed reports of some trades ''to secure a competitive advantage, protect its interests and maximize its profits or minimize its losses,'' according to N.A.S.D. records.</p>
        <p>Andrew Cader, a co-chief executive of Spear, Leeds, said that it was ''not surprising that we have fallen short of perfection,'' given the size of the firm's trading businesses. But he said the firm's management was ''very proud of its regulatory record, and we assume our new partners are.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson expressed no concern. ''We feel very comfortable with the people and their standards,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
