<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Flashbulbs and Interviews Are Safin's New Companions</title>
    <meta content="12TENN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/sports/12TENN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safin, Marat</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sampras, Pete</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4D81638F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Flashbulbs and Interviews Are Safin's New Companions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Russian tennis player Marat Safin in view of his victory over Pete Sampras in finals of US Open; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marat Safin rubbed his glassy hazel eyes yesterday afternoon, attacked by a barrage of flashbulbs for what seemed like the four billionth time since he won the United States Open only 17 hours earlier.</p>
        <p>The 20-year-old Moscow native leaned in front of a model Kremlin on the fourth floor of the Russian Tea Room, grinning with his trophy for a dozen jostling photographers. Moments before, he had stood outside with three giddy middle-age women holding Metropolitan Museum of Art bags, obliging their tourist cameras. He had put his arms up, striking a ''Marat Takes Manhattan'' pose in front of a taxi, at the driver's request.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Marat Safin rubbed his glassy hazel eyes yesterday afternoon, attacked by a barrage of flashbulbs for what seemed like the four billionth time since he won the United States Open only 17 hours earlier.</p>
        <p>The 20-year-old Moscow native leaned in front of a model Kremlin on the fourth floor of the Russian Tea Room, grinning with his trophy for a dozen jostling photographers. Moments before, he had stood outside with three giddy middle-age women holding Metropolitan Museum of Art bags, obliging their tourist cameras. He had put his arms up, striking a ''Marat Takes Manhattan'' pose in front of a taxi, at the driver's request.</p>
        <p>Safin's day began only an hour after he went to sleep, the euphoria from winning his first Grand Slam title almost immediately mixed in with the heaping obligations. He was afraid to drink coffee before appearing on ''CNN Live'' at 9 a.m, for fear the vodka still churning in his system would not appreciate such a wake-up call.</p>
        <p>Later, after taping the Charlie Rose show and an MSNBC program, Safin was gulping caffeinated soda at the Russian Tea Room, picking at the smoked fish and avoiding the borscht. After posing with four waiters in costume, Safin finally sighed. ''Please! Make it fast,'' he exclaimed. ''I cannot smile so much.''</p>
        <p>Flexing his mouth muscles yesterday seemed more difficult, and lasted longer, than his improbable straight-sets victory over the esteemed Pete Sampras. Safin could not explain why he dominated the winner of 13 Grand Slam titles, and he was still unable to comprehend it yesterday.</p>
        <p>''People didn't let me,'' he said. ''I need time, at least one day, to be alone with my friends. I need time to understand what I did. Right now, this is my job, but I hope I will have time to talk with myself.''</p>
        <p>He was not the only 20-year-old wishing to do so yesterday. Venus Williams, the United States Open women's champion, who won her second straight Grand Slam event, was caught in a similar whirlwind, appearing on three morning shows and running to appearances before flying back home to Florida. Today she leaves for the Sydney Olympics.</p>
        <p>Just as she was chatty with President Clinton on Saturday, Safin spoke with his new friend by phone Sunday, only a day after he was honored to meet him in person at Arthur Ashe Stadium. And the Russian president. Vladimir V. Putin, chipped in with his wired congratulations yesterday. ''A new tennis star has risen,'' he said in his message.</p>
        <p>When Safin finally left the National Tennis Center Sunday, he went to a dinner at Serafina in Manhattan, followed by the Soho club 357, where he met the rock singer Lenny Kravitz. Yesterday at 5 p.m., Safin taped ''Late Show With David Letterman''  before taking a 9 p.m. plane to Eastern Europe. Unbelievably, Safin has to be back on the court tomorrow, in Tashkent, Uzbekistan, for a tournament he committed to three months ago. ''He made an agreement. You have to be professional,'' said his agent, Gerard Tsbobanian. ''It has to be this way now.''</p>
        <p>Safin vaulted to No. 2 in the world and has expectations and responsibilities. He began to realize them this spring, when he became more disciplined in his practices (leaving the cell phone behind) and more concentrated, for the most part, on the court.</p>
        <p>Already, said Sampras, Safin is more powerful than he was when he won his first United States Open at 19. But Sampras also cautioned that Safin had to choose to become a legendary champion or just a one-hit wonder. Safin's advisers, most recently Aleksandr Volkov, have issued such warnings and Safin knows his duty.</p>
        <p>After Tashkent, Safin goes immediately to Sydney to compete in the Olympics for Russia. And then, he will return home to Monte Carlo, where Safin hopes his friends will take him out to celebrate, at least when he is not reflecting on his achievement.</p>
        <p>His apartment has no stunning view of the Mediterranean Sea, though. ''It's a wall. I will change that,'' Safin said, this time with a real grin.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
