<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Triathlon Tries to Shed Its Extreme Image</title>
    <meta content="12TRIA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/olympics/12TRIA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Triathlon</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarey, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Triathlon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Triathlon</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5DB1638F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1025" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Triathlon Tries to Shed Its Extreme Image</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Triathlon will debut as Olympic event during Sydney Games; triathletes are hoping their sport sheds its extreme image and finds its way into mainstream during 2000 Olympics; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whether you make the pilgrimage by way of Circular Quay or by way of the Royal Botanic Gardens, the Sydney Opera House, with its jutting shells, is the first-day objective of most tourists here.</p>
        <p>The Opera House will also be a major destination on Saturday (Friday, Eastern time), the first day of medal competition at the Summer Olympics, but the crowds will not be gawking at the unconventional architecture. They will gather on the shores of one of the world's more picturesque harbors to watch 48 women swim in the ocean, bike on the street and run through the park. The woman who does so the fastest will be awarded the first gold medal of the Sydney Games, and it is no coincidence that she will probably be Australian.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Whether you make the pilgrimage by way of Circular Quay or by way of the Royal Botanic Gardens, the Sydney Opera House, with its jutting shells, is the first-day objective of most tourists here.</p>
        <p>The Opera House will also be a major destination on Saturday (Friday, Eastern time), the first day of medal competition at the Summer Olympics, but the crowds will not be gawking at the unconventional architecture. They will gather on the shores of one of the world's more picturesque harbors to watch 48 women swim in the ocean, bike on the street and run through the park. The woman who does so the fastest will be awarded the first gold medal of the Sydney Games, and it is no coincidence that she will probably be Australian.</p>
        <p>''Australia's strength in triathlon was a pretty good factor in the scheduling,'' said the race director, David Hansen.</p>
        <p>But no matter who wins the competition, this will be the triathlon's Olympic debut. ''You couldn't ask for a better showcase,'' said Nick Radkewich, one of three Americans who will compete in the men's race on Sunday (Saturday, Eastern time). ''I really hope this brings us out into the mainstream.''</p>
        <p>NBC plans to feature both the women's and the men's races prominently in its first two nights of coverage from Sydney, but the mainstream may be too much to hope for in the United States, where the triathlon began. It is already a mainstream sport in Australia, where the best triathletes, like Michellie Jones and Miles Stewart, routinely earn six-figure annual incomes and appear on cereal boxes.</p>
        <p>''Even I get recognized in airports here,'' said Radkewich, a 29-year-old Notre Dame graduate who is ranked 55th in the world.</p>
        <p>The general perception of the triathlon may be that it is an oxygen-busting, masochist's delight. The Olympic event, though, is not nearly as full a day's work as is the Hawaii Ironman, the extreme version of the triathlon that was first contested in 1979 and grabbed most of the early attention devoted to the new sport. The Ironman comprises a 2.4-mile swim, followed by a 112-mile bike race and a marathon run (26.2 miles). In comparison, the Olympic triathlon is a sprint. In conventional Olympic style, it is based on the metric system: a 1,500-meter swim, followed by a 40-kilometer bike race and a 10-kilometer run.</p>
        <p>The Olympic distances were chosen to correspond to existing events in swimming, cycling, and track and field. ''It was a challenge for us in the early years of trying to get into the Olympics, because we were fighting the perception of triathlon as a freak sport,'' Tim Wilson, the executive director of Triathlon Australia, said.</p>
        <p>But whatever the demands and the distances, the goal remains the same: cross the finish line first. The decision to have Olympians cross it in front of one of the world's most famous buildings was made shortly after the triathlon received provisional Olympic status in 1994. That was too late to get on the Olympic program for the 1996 Games in Atlanta but it was just right for Sydney, which had already been awarded the 2000 Games.</p>
        <p>The initial plan had been to contest the triathlon in Homebush Bay and finish the event in the Olympic Stadium. Les McDonald, the president of the International Triathlon Union, thought the Opera House and the harbor would be an ideal backdrop, however, and he convinced the Sydney organizers and NBC, which was already planning to devote airtime to the Danish architect Joern Utzon's masterwork.</p>
        <p>Six World Cup triathlon events have already been held on site, and 11 of the 12 winners were Australians, most recently Peter Robertson in April. The favorite in the men's race at the Olympics, though, is Simon Lessing, a South African who left home at 18 because he was disenchanted with apartheid and who now represents Britain.</p>
        <p>The women's favorite is Jones, an Australian who is based in Carlsbad, Calif. The other two Australian women in the field, Loretta Harrop and Nicole Hackett, are also medal contenders. Like Jones, both are former world champions. Unlike Jones, who clinched her spot on the team by winning here in April, Harrop and Hackett were not certain they would be on the team until last Tuesday, when the Court of Arbitration for Sport finally dismissed the appeal of Emma Carney, another former Australian world champion. Carney believed she had not been treated fairly in the selection process and that either Harrop or Hackett should cede her place.</p>
        <p>There is clearly a glut of Australian triathlon talent, one that has inspired at least a dozen of the country's elite triathletes to compete for other nations.</p>
        <p>The athletes competing in both triathlons will begin by diving off a pontoon next to the Opera House into Farm Cove. After swimming, they will then bike and run through and around the lush gardens nearby. Because it is spring, not summer, in Sydney, water temperatures are cool enough (64 degrees on Sunday) to require wet suits. Since triathletes rarely compete in them, the wet suits make the transition from water to bike all the more awkward.</p>
        <p>There has been much discussion about sharks in the harbor, although Australian researchers say that cool water reduces the number of sharks. An increase in shark sightings and aggressive behavior by sharks earlier this year forced the Sydney organizers to adopt measures for the April triathlon to soothe the concerns of foreign competitors. During the Olympics, a team of divers equipped with antishark sonar devices and pods will patrol the water. But in reality, the chance of an attack is virtually nil. According to Hansen, there has not been a shark attack in Sydney between May and November in 208 years.</p>
        <p>''I guess NBC will provide the sharks,'' Radkewich joked.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
