<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Feet Stomp, Arms Flap, and Confidence Grows</title>
    <meta content="12STEP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/nyregion/12STEP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229961"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gospel Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nubian Gents</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, John W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Neill, Lamont</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gospel Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6D81638F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Feet Stomp, Arms Flap, and Confidence Grows</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN W. FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, John W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nubian Gents are all-male gospel step team that was founded by former Queens junior high school teacher Lamont O'Neill as way to reach young men who might otherwise be drawn to crime or drugs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Inside a makeshift locker room, 18 members of the Nubian Gents put on their game faces. Within a few minutes, the serious-looking young men in the black-and-bronze uniforms file into the hushed sanctuary of the Church of God of East Flatbush.</p>
        <p>They huddle at the front of the Brooklyn church, arms locked, whispering a prayer. Then, after an a cappella serenade by their coach and counselor, Lamont O'Neil, the Gents erupt. Three dozen feet rise and fall simultaneously. The floor rumbles. The team members clap behind their backs and between their legs. They flap and flail their arms, palms slapping thighs. Their voices saturate the sanctuary, filled largely with women and children, some of whom rise to their feet as the Gents step to a self-generated beat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Inside a makeshift locker room, 18 members of the Nubian Gents put on their game faces. Within a few minutes, the serious-looking young men in the black-and-bronze uniforms file into the hushed sanctuary of the Church of God of East Flatbush.</p>
        <p>They huddle at the front of the Brooklyn church, arms locked, whispering a prayer. Then, after an a cappella serenade by their coach and counselor, Lamont O'Neil, the Gents erupt. Three dozen feet rise and fall simultaneously. The floor rumbles. The team members clap behind their backs and between their legs. They flap and flail their arms, palms slapping thighs. Their voices saturate the sanctuary, filled largely with women and children, some of whom rise to their feet as the Gents step to a self-generated beat.</p>
        <p>''They, who wait on the Lord, shall renew their strength,'' the Gents chant.</p>
        <p>This is stepping, the rhythmic, foot-stomping, hand-clapping, choreographed dance style popularized by black fraternities. Except, it's gospel stepping. Mr. O'Neil, a former teacher at Junior High School 231 in Queens and a born-again Christian, considers it his tool for reaching young men who might otherwise be drawn to crime or drugs. With himself as the mentor and stepping as the hook, Mr. O'Neil says he hopes to provide something he seldom had while growing up: a positive male role model.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line is to teach them how to be men, how to become men, how to take responsibility, how to keep their word, how to perform at a standard of excellence,'' he said. ''A lot of it begins with confidence.''</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Neil believes that the Gents' performances, combined with hard work, practice and principles, can change young lives.</p>
        <p>''It's not just adapting secular and hip-hop style and bringing it into the church,'' said the Rev. M. Zidde Hamatheite, 29, the pastor of Gethsemane Baptist Church in Brooklyn, where the Gents performed at a street fair earlier this month. It's ''spiritually electrifying,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Neil started the step team in 1994. Members perform free at churches, youth rallies, street fairs and gospel concerts in the New York region, typically making six to eight appearances a month. For the past two summers, the Gents have also taken their show overseas. This summer, they performed in England, Holland and Germany.</p>
        <p>Like their leader, members say they are born-again Christians. In all, there are 24 Gents, males ages 9 to 17. Many come from homes without fathers, Mr. O'Neil said. For some, Mr. O, as they call him, is the next best thing.</p>
        <p>''We elevate our minds. We learn something new every time we go out,'' said Fabian Savino, 16, a Gent for the past four years. ''He's my father,'' he said of Mr. O'Neil. ''That's where I get my knowledge from.''</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Neil's age -- he is 31 -- helps him relate to the members of his group. ''In a way, he's young, so he might understand these things I'm going through,'' said Aaron Lyttle, 14, who has been a Gent for four months.</p>
        <p>Many of the Gents are Mr. O'Neil's former students from J.H.S. 231, where he was a Spanish teacher and dean of students. He left the school last year to become artistic director in charge of community outreach for New Life of New York City. This Christian-based, nonprofit youth organization now helps sponsor the Gents.</p>
        <p>While at the school, Mr. O'Neil noticed many boys wearing drooping pants, bandanas or soiled clothing, boys lacking the self-esteem to look someone in the eyes or hold a conversation without hanging their heads. They were in a place that Mr. O'Neil knew firsthand.</p>
        <p>His parents separated when he was 5. As a boy, he would peer through the window of his apartment in East New York for hours, waiting in vain for his father to appear, he recalled.</p>
        <p>''What I wanted to do was bring a type of fraternal organization to promote a level of unity, to create a brotherhood of sorts where I could counsel them, mentor them,'' Mr. O'Neil said.</p>
        <p>Stepping seemed like a means to that end. Mr. O'Neil learned a lot about it while attending graduate school at Pennsylvania State University and watching step shows by black fraternities. But would any of these young students be remotely interested in it?</p>
        <p>''I said, 'We're going to have a male step team, tryouts this afternoon,' '' Mr. O'Neil recalled announcing one day in the school's auditorium . '' 'We're going to be doing things like this.' '' With that, he said, he broke into a chant and began clapping and stepping. The audience roared.</p>
        <p>That afternoon, 70 boys signed up for the 231 Step Team, though some drifted away. Practice was demanding, and the group had strict rules which Mr. O'Neil patterned after Christian principles. The Gents do not allow cursing, drugs, gang activity or misbehavior.</p>
        <p>Four years after the step team started, it separated from J.H.S. 231 and became part of the New Life organization. Mr. O'Neil left it up to members to rename the team. Someone said, ''Nubian Gents'' -- Nubian, for their African heritage, and Gents, for their anticipated transformation.</p>
        <p>Their stories sound like testimonials at a Sunday service.</p>
        <p>''I was headed down a road of destruction,'' said Philip Holder, 14, a Gent for the past three years. ''I was involved in a lot of things I shouldn't have been involved in at a very early age.''</p>
        <p>Since joining the Gents, he has changed. No one knows that better than his mother, Vernal Holder.</p>
        <p>''He seems like a different person. He's calmer,'' she said. ''He's just turning into a very lovely young gentleman.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
