<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel Urges Monitoring of Chronic Diseases</title>
    <meta content="12SHEL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/science/12SHEL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229875"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pew Environmental Health Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hilts, Philip J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weicker, Lowell P Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5D71F39F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="546" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel Urges Monitoring of Chronic Diseases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP J. HILTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hilts, Philip J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pew Environmental Health Commission and 13 top public health groups propose that US set up system to count and monitor chronic diseases; Lowell Weicker Jr, commission chairman, deplores lack of basic data about environmental links that may trigger chronic diseases (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Pew Environmental Health Commission and 13 top public health groups have proposed that the United States establish a system to count and monitor chronic diseases like birth defects, asthma and Alzheimer's.</p>
        <p>A report from the health commission, based at the Johns Hopkins School of Public Health, said that while scientists had managed to map the human genome and could track infectious diseases with some speed and accuracy, they still lacked basic information about chronic diseases, like how often they occur, whom they afflict, where they frequently occur and the environmental factors associated with them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Pew Environmental Health Commission and 13 top public health groups have proposed that the United States establish a system to count and monitor chronic diseases like birth defects, asthma and Alzheimer's.</p>
        <p>A report from the health commission, based at the Johns Hopkins School of Public Health, said that while scientists had managed to map the human genome and could track infectious diseases with some speed and accuracy, they still lacked basic information about chronic diseases, like how often they occur, whom they afflict, where they frequently occur and the environmental factors associated with them.</p>
        <p>Lowell Weicker Jr., the commission chairman and the former governor of Connecticut, said, ''We responded quickly to the threat of West Nile virus, tracking and monitoring every report of infected birds and people, but 20 years into the asthma epidemic, this country is still unable to track where and when attacks occur and what environmental links may trigger them.''</p>
        <p>The report, endorsed by several public health groups, including the American Cancer Society, the American Lung Association and the American Public Health Association, noted that a survey conducted for the commission showed that Americans believe, erroneously, that chronic diseases are being monitored.</p>
        <p>The misperception comes from the small surveys done on different diseases that often suggest, for example, that a disease's occurrence is rising. But, said Dr. Thomas Burke, leader of the study that produced the report, surveys cannot give the vital information needed to help solve the  mystery of how diseases move and what may be causing them.</p>
        <p>Among the diseases and disorders that are not counted and tracked, but should be, the report said, are asthma, emphysema, birth defects, Alzheimer's, multiple sclerosis, cerebral palsy, autism, mental retardation, and a variety of cancers, especially childhood cancers.</p>
        <p>In addition, the report said, toxic agents that are not monitored, but which are suspected of causing disease, include pollutants like PCB's and dioxin, dangerous metals like  mercury and lead, and pesticides. The Environmental Protection Agency sets limits on how much of some of these substances can be put into the environment, but it does not track them and try to link their effects to human diseases.</p>
        <p>An example of the failure to monitor chronic diseases and possible environmental causes was the case of Libby, Mont., the report said. In that town of 2,700, an epidemic of respiratory diseases, including asbestosis, unusual cancers and emphysema,  has been unofficially noted for decades. Only this year did a federal investigation find that a vermiculite mine not far away had been releasing tons of tremolite for 50 years. Tremolite is a natural but rare and  highly toxic form of asbestos. Investigators estimate that 200 residents have died from diseases associated with the substance, and many more are ill.</p>
        <p>Active tracking of respiratory disease ''might have picked this up  much sooner, and started preventive activities 10 to 20 years ago,'' said  Dr. Henry Falk, administrator of the federal Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
