<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Montenegro Leaders Balk At Taking On Milosevic</title>
    <meta content="Y12MON$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/world/12MONT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229920"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Montenegro</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Djukanovic, Milo (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DD1638F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1541" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Montenegro Leaders Balk At Taking On Milosevic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>PODGORICA, Montenegro, Sept. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clinton administration expresses concern that Pres Slobodan Milosevic might move against Montenegro before or after Yugoslav elections on September 24; similar concerns exist in small republic, where Pres Milo Djukanovic has decided boycott elections, protecting Montenegro's political base while effectively handing Milosevic control over new federal Parliament; Djukanovic, Milosevic understudy who turned toward West in 1997, has spurned US efforts to get him to participate; says his coalition would break apart, and that to have vote would legitimize constitutional changes Milosevic rammed through without consulting Montenegro, Serbia's sister republic in what remains in Yugoslavia; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Clinton administration says it worries that President Slobodan Milosevic of Yugoslavia might move against Montenegro before or after the Yugoslav elections scheduled for Sept. 24.</p>
        <p>But in the small republic itself, where Montenegro's president, Milo Djukanovic, has decided to boycott the elections, there is less concern. The current situation seems to serve both Mr. Milosevic and Mr. Djukanovic fine, with the boycott protecting the Montenegrin's political base while effectively handing Mr. Milosevic control over the new federal Parliament.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Clinton administration says it worries that President Slobodan Milosevic of Yugoslavia might move against Montenegro before or after the Yugoslav elections scheduled for Sept. 24.</p>
        <p>But in the small republic itself, where Montenegro's president, Milo Djukanovic, has decided to boycott the elections, there is less concern. The current situation seems to serve both Mr. Milosevic and Mr. Djukanovic fine, with the boycott protecting the Montenegrin's political base while effectively handing Mr. Milosevic control over the new federal Parliament.</p>
        <p>Mr. Djukanovic, a Milosevic understudy who broke with the master and turned toward the West in 1997, spurned efforts by Washington to get him to take part.</p>
        <p>He argued that his coalition, optimistically named For a Better Life, might break apart, and that to have the vote would legitimize constitutional changes that Mr. Milosevic rammed through without consulting Montenegro, Serbia's sister republic in what remains of Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Djukanovic also rejected an American proposal that he run candidates for the federal Parliament -- even if they vowed not to serve -- to deny Mr. Milosevic an easy victory. ''I think Djukanovic is afraid of a vote,'' one American diplomat said. ''He's putting his own interests in Montenegro ahead of the larger interest, which is to defeat Milosevic.''</p>
        <p>In fact, says Drasko Djuranovic, the editor of the independent weekly Monitor, Mr. Djukanovic is betting on Mr. Milosevic's remaining in power, which he hopes will produce an independent Montenegro in the next few years -- the same bet being made by Kosovo's Albanian leaders.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Milosevic is beaten by the candidate of Serbia's democratic opposition, Vojislav Kostunica, it will be harder to get Western support for the further breakup of Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>''If Kostunica wins, he will offer a decent deal to Montenegro,'' said Zoran Predic, an editor with the private television station Elmag. ''If Milosevic disappears, the world's interest in Milo Djukanovic will also disappear.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Milosevic ''doesn't need a war after the elections, but a better position for negotiations with the West,'' suggested Ranko Krivokapic, a leader of an independence-minded party in Mr. Djukanovic's coalition. ''He may use Montenegro as a bargaining chip.''</p>
        <p>If the point of the early election is to give Mr. Milosevic new legitimacy, Mr. Krivokapic noted, he would be foolish to throw it away again by moving openly against Montenegro. Still, ''this is the Balkans and everything is possible,'' Mr. Krivokapic said. ''Milosevic could need a crisis, even before the election, and he could decide to do something in just a few days. Everything is prepared for various options.''</p>
        <p>There is much talk here of the Seventh Battalion of the Yugoslav Army, some 700 men who seem more like paramilitaries and who, it is thought, could help provoke civil strife, providing a pretext for the overthrow of Mr. Djukanovic without bringing about an overt Western military response.</p>
        <p>Slobodan Milic, an adviser to President Djukanovic, said Mr. Milosevic ''could seem completely clean'' and say: ''It's those crazy Montenegrins. We haven't sent a tank or a plane, so let me see what I can do.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Predic, from the independent television station, said the problem was that ''a significant minority here is fanatically pro-Milosevic, and another part that hates him wants to stay with Yugoslavia.''</p>
        <p>A referendum for independence remains too risky, said Mr. Djuranovic, the newspaper editor. ''Here in the Balkans the question isn't the opinion of the majority,'' he said. ''It's what the minority with guns will do, when they have the support of another country.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Djukanovic's government has officially discouraged the state media from reporting on the campaign, the president is allowing Montenegrins to vote in the election, trying to avoid an open conflict with the 35 to 40 percent of the population that favors unity with Serbia. Nor is Mr. Djukanovic pressing for an early referendum on Montenegrin independence.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Filip Vujanovic is accustomed to dancing around the question. ''We need to be very patient and careful, and a referendum should be taken as a last resort,'' he said in an interview. But if Mr. Milosevic wins, as Mr. Vujanovic is convinced he will, by manipulation if necessary, ''he will continue his destructive approach to Montenegro,'' he said. ''That's why if he's elected, in the next four years Montenegro will be at one point forced to ask the citizens for their answer in a referendum. But it's not our political decision to do it immediately.''</p>
        <p>''He won't willingly leave office,'' Mr. Vujanovic said of Mr. Milosevic, ''and then the Serbian people and the international community must work to push him out.''</p>
        <p>But not everybody in Montenegro is so against Mr. Milosevic. In Herceg Novi, a coastal town that voted out Mr. Djukanovic's coalition in local elections this summer, opting instead for the pro-Belgrade Socialist People's Party, there is skepticism about Mr. Djukanovic's real aims.</p>
        <p>''They want to get the names of the people who vote in the election, because every vote is like a vote to keep Yugoslavia together,'' said Jovan, a man of 50 who intends to vote, but for the Serbian opposition candidate, Mr. Kostunica. ''I worry about my pension.''</p>
        <p>Montenegro is divided, and Mr. Djukanovic's party and coalition are divided, said Zeljko Ivanovic, editor of the independent daily Vijesti. ''It's why Milosevic can sit and laugh. Whatever he's done to Montenegro, they just issue a statement.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Djukanovic wants independence, Mr. Ivanovic said: ''It's clear. He needs to be able to say, 'With Milosevic still in Serbia, we have no other option.' ''</p>
        <p>In the main, Mr. Djukanovic is simply being prudent, trying not to give Belgrade a pretext to provoke a civil war. In the meantime, Montenegro is building the institutions of statehood, including a banking system and an army.</p>
        <p>Besides the presence of the Yugoslav Army, pressure from Belgrade includes a blockade of trade, which cuts off Montenegro from Serbia's price-controlled food and other products and forces it to try to export abroad.</p>
        <p>Montenegro's turn to the German mark as its currency has protected it from the fall of the Yugoslav dinar, but it has also made prices more expensive and led to louder grumbling from the many unemployed in this republic of just 650,000 people. Not all of the jobless can work in Montenegro's black and gray economy, where smuggling goods to and from Italy is a way of life.</p>
        <p>There are so many stolen cars in Montenegro -- or cars bought cheaply in Europe and driven here, then declared stolen by their owners -- that the joke goes: ''Come and visit Montenegro. We have your car here waiting for you.''</p>
        <p>Montenegro's limbo as a quasi-state -- an independently minded part of Yugoslavia -- has meant that it cannot get direct aid from the World Bank or the International Monetary Fund. But because it is perceived as a bulwark against Belgrade, Montenegro does get millions of dollars in government aid from Europe and the United States to cover its budget deficit.</p>
        <p>As many as half of Montenegro's salaried workers are paid by the state, including the regular and special police forces, with their new Land Rovers, who number up to 30,000 men and have been built up, in part by trainers from Western armies, to counter the Yugoslav Army.</p>
        <p>There is little international oversight of how the foreign money is spent, said Arne Jan Flolo of the Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe. Everyone agrees that the privatization of government-run enterprises is anything but transparent or clean.</p>
        <p>There is currently a fight within the governing party over a fuzzy contract with the French hotel chain Accor to manage Montenegro's nicest seaside hotels.</p>
        <p>One huge aluminum plant, with all of its associated industries, represents half of Montenegro's gross domestic product, and much of the profit goes to a Swiss holding company that provided needed credits in 1998 -- a contract that Washington and the aluminum company itself are quietly trying to cancel.</p>
        <p>''Corruption is a time bomb ticking under the Djukanovic government,'' Mr. Flolo said. ''But the West doesn't want to hear about it. The international community is making a big mistake by not attaching conditions to its aid.''</p>
        <p>Nebojsa Medojevic, an economist, is a Djukanovic critic. ''The line here is that if you criticize Djukanovic you help Milosevic. It creates space for manipulation and is an excellent pretext to postpone any real economic reform. The problem is that the international community supports Djukanovic without reservation, despite dirty privatization and corruption.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Flolo said: ''There are free and fair elections here, but there is little transparency of decision-making. There is democracy from a distance, but you dig and there's a long way to go.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
