<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="12FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE2D61638F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1538" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-13</p>
        <p>Iraq Prohibits Entry Of U.N. Analysts  Secretary General Kofi Annan told the Security Council that Iraq would not allow independent experts into the country to assess the living conditions of Iraqis a decade after economic sanctions were imposed. In a report to the Council, Mr. Annan also said Iraq was barring another group of experts that he had wanted to send to devise ways to improve an oil-for-food program.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-13</p>
        <p>Iraq Prohibits Entry Of U.N. Analysts  Secretary General Kofi Annan told the Security Council that Iraq would not allow independent experts into the country to assess the living conditions of Iraqis a decade after economic sanctions were imposed. In a report to the Council, Mr. Annan also said Iraq was barring another group of experts that he had wanted to send to devise ways to improve an oil-for-food program.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Meeting on West Africa  Secretary General Kofi Annan met with officials of nine West African countries to coordinate efforts to resolve the crisis in Sierra Leone created by an insurgency and to defuse tensions between Guinea and Liberia, members of a regional group. The meeting came as the United Nations prepared to expand the Sierra Leone peacekeeping mission.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>European Fuel Price Protests  More than 1,000 gasoline stations across Britain were forced to close as groups of protesters, furious at high fuel prices, blockaded oil refineries, cutting off fuel deliveries and sending consumers rushing to the pumps to fill up their cars before the gasoline ran out. The protests by truck drivers, farm workers and taxi drivers were echoed by protests in Belgium, where truck drivers paralyzed the center of Brussels.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>New Details on Mideast Talks  Senior Clinton Administration officials provided details of a critical 90-minute meeting between the president and the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, in Manhattan last week that was intended to aid the badly flagging Middle East peace talks. Yesterday, Mr. Arafat flew to Egypt for a 90-minute meeting with President Hosni Mubarak that appeared to confirm the generally gloomy forecasts for the new talks.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Russia's New Champion  Russians glowed with pride over Marat Safin's victory at the United States Open, the first time that title has been held by a Russian. The acclaim comes even though he is an ethnic Tatar, a people often derided in Russia as Attila the Hun's henchmen, and even though he and his family left Russia four years ago to live in Spain.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>New Yorker's Trial to Resume  The civilian retrial of Lori Berenson, an American jailed in Peru on charges of collaborating with leftist guerrillas in a plot to attack Congress, will resume tomorrow, her new lawyer said. She was convicted by a military court in 1996.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>Opera Going Hollywood  Placido Domingo, the new artistic director of the Los Angeles Opera, said that George Lucas's special effects company, Industrial Light and Magic, would design a version of ''The Ring'' and that filmmakers would be asked to stage some operas.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-24</p>
        <p>U.S. Says Young Are Target Of Violent Entertainment  The Federal Trade Commission said the vast majority of the best-selling restricted movies, music and video games were deliberately marketed for children as young as 12. The commission chairman, Robert Pitofsky, was careful not to blame violent entertainment for the violence in society, though he allowed that exposure to violent materials ''does seem to correlate with aggressive attitudes, insensitivity to violence and an exaggerated view of how much violence occurs in the world.''</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Snag in Plea Agreement  A last-minute dispute between prosecutors and defense lawyers over the terms of a plea agreement delayed until at least tomorrow the release of the former Los Alamos scientist Wen Ho Lee, who has agreed to plead guilty to a single count of improperly downloading secret information.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>The plea agreement leaves unresolved an eight-year inquiry into how China obtained secret information on an advanced nuclear warhead.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Computer Security Flaws  More than a quarter of the government's major agencies failed a computer security review by the Government Accounting Office.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Study of Federal Death Penalty  A Justice Department review of the federal death penalty since its reinstatement in 1988 found disparities by race and geography in how United States attorneys handled death penalty cases. More than half the cases involved African-American defendants and only a handful of the 93 United States attorneys account for nearly half of all capital cases.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Dispute Over G.O.P. Ad  The word ''RATS,'' a fragment of the phrase ''bureaucrats decide,'' pops up in a frame of a Republican television commercial that assails Vice President Al Gore's proposal for a Medicare prescription benefit. The ad's producer asserted that what appeared to critics to be an effort to deliver a subliminal message had been ''purely accidental.''</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush told an elderly audience that his plans for Medicare and prescription benefits would give them control of their health care, while Mr. Gore's would give them ''a government-run H.M.O.''</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>The board of the N.R.A. declined to endorse Mr. Bush for president. Officials said members feared that Democrats would use the gun group's endorsement to attack Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore appeared on ''Oprah'' and portrayed himself to its largely female audience as a sensitive and devoted family man.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>U.S. Health Official Leaving  Nancy-Ann Min DeParle, the administrator of the agency that runs Medicare and Medicaid, is resigning on Oct. 1 to take a temporary job teaching at Harvard University.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Call for a Police Monitor  The Los Angeles Police Department needs more aggressive independent review and a permanent special prosecutor to investigate misconduct, according to a report commissioned by the police union.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-9</p>
        <p>Olympics in New York City? Boosters Make Their Pitch  NYC 2012, the committee organized to entice the Olympics to New York City in 2012, unveils its proposed venues for the Games today, presenting a list of almost 30 sites reaching from New Jersey to Long Island and including all five boroughs. The two largest projects would be an Olympic Stadium above the Long Island Rail Road yards on the West Side of Manhattan and a village for athletes along the East River in Queens.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Politics and Real Estate  The Manhattan Borough Board granted permission to Bhutan to buy a Midtown Manhattan townhouse for its United Nations mission, ending a three-year dispute that focused on the human rights record of the Buddhist kingdom in the Himalayas.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Senate Hopeful on Education  Representative Rick A. Lazio proposed spending $97.75 billion on education over 10 years, with substantial parts devoted to disabled students and programs to make teachers more accountable.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Mayor Giuliani faulted Mr. Lazio for having enthusiastically shaken the hand of Yasir Arafat in 1998.</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>Morning Show Off the Air  Fans and even some advertisers protested the decision to end the ''Rambling With Gambling'' morning talk show on WOR-AM radio.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B9-10</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>Extinction for Human Relative  Scientists say Miss Waldron's red colobus, a member of the primate order, the taxonomic group to which humans belong, has become extinct, the first such occurrence among primates in several centuries.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>AIDS Theory Not Supported  Tests fail to support a theory that the AIDS epidemic began with an experimental oral polio vaccine used in Africa more than 40 years ago that was made from chimpanzee tissue, scientists reported in London.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Health &amp; Fitness</p>
        <p>F7</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>College Aid Plan  California enacted a financial aid plan that guarantees needy high school students with good grades grants for full tuition at the state's public colleges and universities or nearly $10,000 a year for tuition at private institutions in the state.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-28</p>
        <p>Ford Engine Problem  Ford documents show that an array of company officials were aware of problems with a computerized ignition system that would shut car engines down if they got too hot. At the time, top company executives asserted to customers who complained about stalls and to regulators that there was no way to know what was causing the problem.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Procuring Parts Online  Federal antitrust regulators approved the establishment of an online venture, Covisint, that would let Ford, G.M., DaimlerChrysler, Nissan and Renault buy supplies through a single Internet portal.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Options Exchanges Censured  Federal regulators said the four major options exchanges agreed for years to restrain competition by not seeking to trade options already traded on other exchanges.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Home Heating Oil Price Rise  The price of home heating oil surged to a 10-year high, $1.0498 a gallon, up 5.49 cents, or 5.5 percent, as traders discounted the effect of a decision over the weekend by OPEC to increase crude oil production.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-10</p>
        <p>Jets Come Back to Win  Vinny Testaverde threw two fourth quarter touchdown passes to Wayne Chrebet and the Jets defeated the Patriots, 20-19.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: Unworthy pandering by Mr. Gore; a vanishing security case; tribulations and triumphs in sports; choices for the New York primary.  Columns: Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E8  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E7  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D9</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
