<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Efforts to Test Drugs on Children Hasten Drive for Research Guidelines</title>
    <meta content="12ETHI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/science/12ETHI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229890"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Placebos</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Food and Drug Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jetter, Alexis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weijer, Charles (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1D61F39F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1222" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Efforts to Test Drugs on Children Hasten Drive for Research Guidelines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEXIS JETTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jetter, Alexis</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Food and Drug Administration wants to make sure that researchers protect children participating in pediatric drug studies; advisory panel begins talks aimed at setting first guidelines for researchers on controversial use of placebos in drug trials for children; Dr Charles Weijer, panelist, holds it is wrong to submit children to risks while providing them no immediate benefit; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Researchers give a 6-year-old girl who suffers from asthma attacks a promising new drug in addition to her old medicine, then withdraw it to see how she will do without it. A depressed teenager enrolls in a study for an antidepressant, but does not know if he will get a sugar pill or the real thing. The parents of an epileptic youngster enroll her in a test of a new drug that has worked well in adults. But no one knows whether she will get the new medication, or the one that has worked only moderately well for her in the past.</p>
        <p>These quandaries, all based on actual experiences, are likely to be faced by an increasing number of parents, children and medical researchers around the country as the federal government steps up its efforts to test drugs on children.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Researchers give a 6-year-old girl who suffers from asthma attacks a promising new drug in addition to her old medicine, then withdraw it to see how she will do without it. A depressed teenager enrolls in a study for an antidepressant, but does not know if he will get a sugar pill or the real thing. The parents of an epileptic youngster enroll her in a test of a new drug that has worked well in adults. But no one knows whether she will get the new medication, or the one that has worked only moderately well for her in the past.</p>
        <p>These quandaries, all based on actual experiences, are likely to be faced by an increasing number of parents, children and medical researchers around the country as the federal government steps up its efforts to test drugs on children.</p>
        <p>Over the last three years, largely because of financial incentives that Congress has given pharmaceutical companies, pediatric studies of new drugs have boomed. In December, the Food and Drug Administration  will begin mandating that such tests be done on certain drugs, and the agency wants to make sure researchers protect child participants.</p>
        <p>''What level of discomfort or risk should a child in a study be exposed to?'' asked Dr. Steven Hirschfeld, a medical officer at the F.D.A.'s Center for Drug Research and Evaluation. ''If a child gets an asthma attack and starts to wheeze, are people willing to tolerate that to get complete information about a potentially helpful drug for children?''</p>
        <p>Today, an F.D.A. advisory panel met in Bethesda, Md., to begin discussions aimed at setting the first guidelines for researchers on the controversial use of placebos in drug trials for children. Placebos are sugar pills, injections or other treatments that resemble the drug that is being tested without having any of the same effects.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hirschfeld said that the particular vulnerability of children often makes placebo controls necessary. ''Children are not only very susceptible to their own expectations,'' he said in an interview. ''They are very susceptible to their parents' expectations.''</p>
        <p>But a panelist, Dr. Charles Weijer, a bioethicist and an assistant professor of medicine at Dalhousie University in Halifax, Nova Scotia, said it was wrong to submit children to risks while providing them no immediate benefit.</p>
        <p>''An investigator's chief concern ought to be the health and well-being of her patients,'' Dr. Weijer said at the hearing.</p>
        <p>And he also challenged the scientific value of placebos. ''The unethical use of placebo controls in clinical trials is the most widespread problem in medical research today,'' Dr. Weijer said in a telephone interview. The view that placebos provide scientific information that cannot be obtained in other ways ''is pure fantasy,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Dr. Weijer said new drugs should not be compared with placebos, but with drugs already used to treat the condition.</p>
        <p>The panel of 27 researchers that met today included several researchers from Europe who are working on international standards for clinical trials in children.</p>
        <p>''What you people decide will affect directly not only children in the U.S., but children in Europe and the world at large,'' said Francis Crawley, chairman of a group  working to set standards in Europe.</p>
        <p>Dianne Murphy, the associate director for pediatrics at the F.D.A.'s Center for Drug Evaluation and Research, said that use of placebos can reduce the number of children needed in a study and can ensure the most conclusive outcome. ''If you need a placebo trial to get an answer, and you don't do it, then you've wasted that child's blood, time and possible chance, in a trial that won't give them an answer,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Researchers agree on two points: Where there is no effective treatment, placebos may be appropriate. Where there is an established effective treatment for a life-threatening disease, neither children nor adults should be denied that treatment while testing a drug. That means all study participants are given the best current medicine.  Then, half are given the new drug as well, while the other half are given the placebo in what is called an ''add-on placebo trial.''</p>
        <p>But experts disagree on the ethics of withholding effective treatment from children when studying nonfatal conditions such as allergies or skin rashes. And there is no consensus for how to treat children with other serious ailments, such as depression, where the best treatment is unknown.</p>
        <p>That is an issue that researchers in the field face everyday. ''There is still not an established standard of care for the treatment of child depression,'' said Dr. Craig Donnelly, an assistant professor of psychiatry and pediatrics at Dartmouth Hitchcock Medical Center in Lebanon, N.H., who was not at the hearing.</p>
        <p>Dr. Donnelly is now engaged in a large study of child depression, in which five antidepressants, previously tested on adults only, are being tested on children. Half will receive the drugs and half placebos. All have been taken off their current medicine and are prohibited from receiving therapy.</p>
        <p>But they have weekly meetings with a psychiatrist, and if they become suicidal or exhibit serious symptoms, they are removed from the study.</p>
        <p>Some of the fear about abusing children as research subjects is rooted in grim experiments of the past. The Nuremberg Code, which sets global standards for research on humans, grew out of the world's moral revulsion against Nazi experiments on concentration camp prisoners, including many children. In the 1960's, the creator of the first effective vaccine against hepatitis B injected hepatitis-infected blood products into children, many of them mentally handicapped, at the Willowbrook State School for the Retarded in Staten Island, N.Y.</p>
        <p>''For a long time, the prevailing ethical view was that research is dangerous and people have to be protected from it,'' said Dr. David Wendler, a philosopher and bioethicist who directs the Unit on Vulnerable Populations at the National Institutes of Health. ''People were worried about exposing kids to potential risks. Now a lot of concern focuses on the placebo group, because they may be denied possible beneficial treatment.</p>
        <p>''But the big worry, particularly for little kids,'' is informed consent, said Dr. Wendler.</p>
        <p>At the moment, children under 7 are guided by their parents' decision about whether they should participate in a clinical trial. Children 7 to 14 can be asked for their ''assent,'' rather than informed consent, along with their parents, while teenagers 14 and older can weigh the possible risks and benefits and make up their own minds nearly as well as any adult, Dr. Wendler said.</p>
        <p>Kelson Pediatric Partners, based in Hartford, is one of a growing number of companies engaged in the new effort to test children. Kelson, the country's leading pediatric-practice management company, advertises on its Web site that it can provide drug researchers access to ''pediatric practices seeing over 1.5 million patient visits per year.'' The company's research sites in Massachusetts, Connecticut, New Jersey, Virginia, Florida and Utah have enrolled over 2,400 of their patients in 40 trials of vaccines, allergy drugs, analgesics, antibiotics and asthma treatments.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
