<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Amid Bumps and Spikes, A Labor of Friendship</title>
    <meta content="12RHOD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/olympics/12RHOD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beach Volleyball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhoden, William C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson-Jordan, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Annett</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Volleyball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volleyball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E7D81638F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Amid Bumps and Spikes, A Labor of Friendship</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William C Rhoden Sports of The Times column on Jennifer Johnson-Jordan and Annett Davis notes that they are vying to become first US women to win Olympic gold medal in beach volleyball; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a gorgeous morning at Bondi Beach, two solitary figures stepped inside the 10,000 seat arena built for Olympic beach volleyball competition. They stood and looked.</p>
        <p>All was quiet. High sun, deep blue sky and the Tasman Sea serving as a backdrop for the surfers riding the waves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a gorgeous morning at Bondi Beach, two solitary figures stepped inside the 10,000 seat arena built for Olympic beach volleyball competition. They stood and looked.</p>
        <p>All was quiet. High sun, deep blue sky and the Tasman Sea serving as a backdrop for the surfers riding the waves.</p>
        <p>Annett Davis and Jennifer Johnson-Jordan looked around the stadium, soaked up sights and sounds of a place that soon would be crazy with cheering and tension over a competition.</p>
        <p>For now there was peace.</p>
        <p>''It's really beautiful here early,'' Davis said yesterday. ''I want to enjoy it, and remember this place.''</p>
        <p>Davis and Johnson-Jordan, along with Misty May and Holly McPeak, are vying to become the first American women to win a gold medal in beach volleyball, a sport that made its Olympic debut at Atlanta in 1996.</p>
        <p>They are like thousands of other Olympians who have persevered, shouldered burdens and broken barriers to get here.</p>
        <p>Unlike many in the sport, Davis and Johnson-Jordan have made the trip as an unbroken unit. They also represent a bridge that links families, generations and memories. Davis's father is Cleveland Buckner, who played one season with the Knicks. But Buckner is part of enduring history. His claim to fame is that he once scored 33 points against Wilt Chamberlain in 1962 in Hershey, Pa. Unfortunately that was the afternoon Chamberlain scored 100 points.</p>
        <p>Johnson-Jordan's father is Rafer Johnson, who won the gold medal in the decathlon in 1960 Rome Games. The fathers have made it clear that these Games are about their children.</p>
        <p>''We're pleased and excited,'' Buckner said from California. ''But this is really about Annett and how hard she's worked. Who knew that it would ever get to this level? From getting her involved in something to keep her busy to reaching the Olympics, that's pretty special.''</p>
        <p>After graduating from U.C.L.A., where they were teammates, roommates and best friends, Johnson-Jordan and Davis decided to play beach volleyball rather than seek a spot on the United States women's indoor team. The two started out in the beach team format and played a handful of two-women tournaments in 1997 before switching full time in 1998.</p>
        <p>In a sport defined by frequent breakups and mercenary alliances, the greatest achievement of this tandem is having stayed together for nearly four years.</p>
        <p>''The initial decision to get together was not based on results or competition because we never played together,'' Jordan-Johnson said. ''We made the commitment before we had even played a tournament together. We didn't want to have to worry about being dumped or having to dump some one else. We just wanted to be able to relax in our environment. Making that commitment allowed us to do that. The commitment makes you more comfortable and trusting.''</p>
        <p>The international experience tested faith, friendship and commitment. In their first season on the world outdoor tour in 1997, they finished 93rd over all.</p>
        <p>''It was tough to hang in,'' Davis said.  ''Financially we weren't making any money. I was in the hole, but every month something would come along right on time that allowed us to pay our bills. I knew this was where I was supposed to be. I wasn't supposed to quit.''</p>
        <p>In a remarkably short span of three years, they have risen to the upper echelon of their sport. By 1999 they were ranked No. 2. Now they have a chance to be the first American women to win an Olympic medal in beach volleyball.</p>
        <p>There are times when Johnson-Jordan still can't believe it.</p>
        <p>''With each step that we've taken, ever since we knew we had qualified, this becomes a little more real,'' Johnson-Jordan said. ''It started with making the team and then getting our gear, going through processing, getting on the plane now arriving here at the venue. It's going to take more and more steps to feel like its here as we go to opening ceremonies, as we put our uniforms on for the first time.''</p>
        <p>The circle will be complete when her father and mother arrive in Sydney today. Johnson won his first Olympic medal in Melbourne in 1956; in 1984 he ignited the Olympic flame in Los Angeles. This week he will effectively pass the torch to his daughter.</p>
        <p>''It's not something that motivates me,'' Johnson-Jordan said ''It makes the whole experience that much more special. To be on the 2000 Olympic team 44 years after my dad won a medal in the same country is sentimental. It is.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
