<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Trend on the Sidewalks, and in the E.R.</title>
    <meta content="12SCOT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/science/12SCOT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229876"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Scooters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Helmets</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consumer Product Safety Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Villarosa, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E3D71F39F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="703" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Trend on the Sidewalks, and in the E.R.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA VILLAROSA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Villarosa, Linda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sales of foot-propelled scooters are booming, as are scooter-related injuries; children under 15 are sustaining 90 percent of injuries; Consumer Product Safety Commission warns that childern under 8 should not use scooters without close adult supervision; urges use of helmets, other protective gear; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lots of youngsters are zipping down sidewalks and darting through the streets on shiny, foot-propelled scooters, the must-have sports item for the under-15 set.</p>
        <p>They are everywhere, said Reyne Rice, director of the toy services division of the NPD Group, a marketing information company in Port Washington, N.Y., that tracks buying trends. Last year, scooter volume was negligible. For the first half of this year, it is already a $20 million business. Scooter sales are off the charts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lots of youngsters are zipping down sidewalks and darting through the streets on shiny, foot-propelled scooters, the must-have sports item for the under-15 set.</p>
        <p>They are everywhere, said Reyne Rice, director of the toy services division of the NPD Group, a marketing information company in Port Washington, N.Y., that tracks buying trends. Last year, scooter volume was negligible. For the first half of this year, it is already a $20 million business. Scooter sales are off the charts.</p>
        <p>But so are injuries, according to a report issued last week by the Consumer Product Safety Commission. The federal regulatory agency notes that emergency-room visits for injuries related to scooters have increased 700 percent since May. Data from the commission show 9,400 scooter-related injuries treated in emergency rooms so far this year, and 4,000 last month alone. These are not your grandmother's clunky scooters from the 1950's, said Ann Brown, the chairwoman of the commission. These models are lightweight and fast, but not easy to maneuver.</p>
        <p>Dr. Harold W. Kohl, director of the physical activity and nutrition program at the International Life Sciences Institute, Center for Health Promotion in Atlanta, is not surprised by the high injury rate. This is the same thing that happened when in-line skates were new. ''When Rollerblades first caught on,'' he said, ''you saw a spike in injuries. But once people became more skilled and also started wearing protective gear, the injury rate was lower. I expect the same thing to happen with the scooters.''</p>
        <p>Children, the primary users of scooters, are sustaining the most injuries, although some intrepid adults have also climbed aboard. The new report notes that 90 percent of injuries are to children under 15 and nearly one-third occur in children under 8.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the commission warns that children under 8 should not use scooters without close adult supervision. Younger children do not have the balance, stability or motor coordination of older teenagers, said Dr. Craig C. McKirgan, an orthopedic surgeon at the Center of Orthopedics and Sports Medicine in Indiana, Pa.</p>
        <p>''I have a 5-year-old that wants one,'' Dr. McKirgan said. ''I hate to be the mean old dad, but I'm going to wait.''</p>
        <p>Most injuries occur when children fall off the scooters. The toys have a narrow base, and with only two wheels, they can be very unstable, said Ms. Brown of the product safety commission. Her agency suggests riding scooters only on smooth, paved surfaces without traffic and avoiding water, sand, gravel or dirt. It is also best not to ride at night, she adds.</p>
        <p>The most important safety precaution, however, is to wear plenty of protective gear, which, according to the agency, would reduce the injury rate by 60 percent. Begin with a helmet, Ms. Brown said. ''You're already going to spend around $100 for a scooter; why not throw in another $35 for a helmet?'' she asked.</p>
        <p>Experts also recommend knee and elbow pads and wrist guards. ''In my practice, I've seen several fractured wrists from youngsters' falling off scooters,'' Dr. McKirgan said. ''When kids fall, they fall forward on outstretched hands. That can definitely produce fractures and dislocations.''</p>
        <p>But will scooter riders really suit up, stiff as cyborgs, in head-to-toe protective wear?</p>
        <p>Riley Hedin, 13, of Providence, Utah, said that he and his friends did. ''I always wear pads and a helmet,'' said Riley, who received his scooter a few months ago as an early birthday present. ''Where I live, there's a big hill,'' he said. ''If you get going too fast and lose control, you can get in a crash. I've fallen off a couple of times, so now I'm extra careful.''</p>
        <p>Cautious children like Riley should not have any problems with scooters, Dr. McKirgan said.</p>
        <p>''With any kind of activity, there's risk, so you always have to take precautions,'' Dr. McKirgan said. ''But while you don't want a high-risk product out there, I would hate to see a child not get to have fun. Ultimately, we have to let kids be kids.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
