<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Japanese Economy Expands For 2nd Consecutive Quarter</title>
    <meta content="Y12JAP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/business/12JAPA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tanikawa, Miki</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E0DD1638F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="478" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Japanese Economy Expands For 2nd Consecutive Quarter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKI TANIKAWA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tanikawa, Miki</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, Sept. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Japan's Economic Planning Agency says economy expanded 1 percent in April-June quarter, stronger-than-expected performance driven by higher government and consumer spending; result translates into annual growth rate of 4.2 percent; one of biggest surprises is 13.6 percent increase in government spending (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Japan's economy expanded 1 percent in the April-June quarter, the government said today, a stronger-than-expected performance driven by higher government and consumer spending.</p>
        <p>The result reported by the Economic Planning Agency translated into an annual growth rate of 4.2 percent and was the second consecutive quarter of expansion. Japan, the world's second-largest economy, has been struggling to overcome the worst prolonged downturn since the end of World War II.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Japan's economy expanded 1 percent in the April-June quarter, the government said today, a stronger-than-expected performance driven by higher government and consumer spending.</p>
        <p>The result reported by the Economic Planning Agency translated into an annual growth rate of 4.2 percent and was the second consecutive quarter of expansion. Japan, the world's second-largest economy, has been struggling to overcome the worst prolonged downturn since the end of World War II.</p>
        <p>Some private economists said the quarterly growth, coming after a 2.5 percent expansion in the January-March quarter, suggested that the recovery might be growing more solid, although it remained slow. Many had forecast that the economy would grow only seven-tenths of a percent in the April-June quarter.</p>
        <p>But there was no consensus on whether the data meant that Japan's recovery was gathering momentum. And the economic planning minister, Taichi Sakaiya, was cautious about interpreting the results, suggesting that they might reflect temporary stimulants that could dissipate later this year.</p>
        <p>One of the biggest surprises was a 13.6 percent increase in government spending in the quarter, which followed a 7.5 percent decrease in the January-March quarter.</p>
        <p>''The main difference between our forecast and the result was that there was a very, very big increase in public spending,'' said Jeffrey Young, chief economist with Nikko Salomon Smith Barney in Tokyo.</p>
        <p>But that component of the economic expansion will have to be replenished by the government through additional borrowing. Japan is already borrowing record amounts of money to finance public works projects to stimulate the economy, and the rising indebtedness led Moody's Investors Service to lower Japan's credit rating last week.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, there is a widespread expectation that Japan's political leaders will opt to borrow more money for public spending. After the release of the data today, Kiichi Miyazawa, the finance minister, said senior Japanese political officials had agreed on the need for a supplementary budget, although the size of it was undecided.</p>
        <p>Another unexpectedly strong source of economic expansion in the April-June quarter came from consumer spending, which rose 1.1 percent.</p>
        <p>Economists said that corporate earnings, which have been recovering for more than a year, are finally spilling over to consumer spending and wage growth. They said the April-June results now easily put within reach the government's forecast of 1 percent growth for the 2000 fiscal year, which ends March 31.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sakaiya, however, was cautious about reading too much optimism into the consumer spending data. He noted that it contained extraordinary elements, like the introduction of nursing care insurance.</p>
        <p>The rise in personal spending, moreover, was counterbalanced by a 3.3 percent decline in capital spending, which until recently had been a big component of economic growth.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
