<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Living and Learning At Dishwasher U.; Whirlpool Trainees Prepare for Real World</title>
    <meta content="Y12HOU$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/business/12HOUS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Whirlpool Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barboza, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1D71638F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Living and Learning At Dishwasher U.; Whirlpool Trainees Prepare for Real World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barboza, David</byline>
      <dateline>BENTON HARBOR, Mich.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Whirlpool Corp sends group of new hires to live together in large house, where during course of their stay they prepare more than 900 plates of food, wash no fewer than 120 bags of laundry and perform countless hours of loading and reloading of company's refrigerators, dishwashers and dryers; graph; chart; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tony Barbee has never enjoyed household chores. Even in college, he regularly brought his laundry home to Mother, and he shunned the stove in favor of the local Burger King or Kentucky Fried Chicken.</p>
        <p>Indeed, he knew so little about what goes on in the kitchen that when he applied for a job at Whirlpool, one of the world's largest makers of household appliances, he checked off the box that indicated the lowest level of cooking expertise: Hamburger Helper.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tony Barbee has never enjoyed household chores. Even in college, he regularly brought his laundry home to Mother, and he shunned the stove in favor of the local Burger King or Kentucky Fried Chicken.</p>
        <p>Indeed, he knew so little about what goes on in the kitchen that when he applied for a job at Whirlpool, one of the world's largest makers of household appliances, he checked off the box that indicated the lowest level of cooking expertise: Hamburger Helper.</p>
        <p>But for two months this summer, Mr. Barbee, now 30, and six other young recruits took part in an unusual training program that might be considered the corporate equivalent of reality-based television.</p>
        <p>Hoping to create a better work force, Whirlpool essentially sentenced a group of new hires to live together in a large house, where during the course of their stay they prepared more than 900 plates of food; washed no fewer than 120 bags of laundry; and performed countless hours of loading and reloading of the company's refrigerators, dishwashers and dryers.</p>
        <p>They smear white bags with mustard, relish and other stain-generating condiments, just to see if they can bleach them out; they prepare three times as much pasta as they need, simply to see how cooking in microwave and convection ovens differs from that in traditional ovens.</p>
        <p>With breaks for only a couple of weekend trips home, the learning experience is intense. Who knew, for example, that one of the company's newest dishwashers was so powerful that when an entire carrot cake was set among the dishes -- as it was during an experiment -- the cake would entirely evaporate and the dishes would still come out clean.</p>
        <p>''Company retreats have been around a long time, but two months living in a house, I've never heard of that,'' said Sonia Marciano, who teaches management and strategy at the Kellogg Graduate School of Management at Northwestern University. ''I guess there are some people who are going to say this is a way cool thing, especially when you're dealing with something as unsexy as appliances.''</p>
        <p>Company executives, however, insist that the reality-based training program is not a gimmick. Rather, they say, it is a more pragmatic and effective way of preparing its youthful marketing representatives than the lectures and slide shows that make up so many corporate initiations. Forcing the recruits, a diverse group of men and women, to use the full range of Whirlpool products night and day will produce a better informed and more consumer-friendly sales staff, the company says.</p>
        <p>''We want them to have a better appreciation of what a consumer goes through,'' said Jackie Seib, the company's national training manager.</p>
        <p>In a case of life imitating art -- or, at least, television -- Whirlpool modeled its program after ''The Real World,'' the popular MTV series that chronicles the experience of seven young people who live together for five months. Whirlpool's version is called ''The Real Whirled.''</p>
        <p>The undertaking may be one of the earliest indications of ways that pop culture, already a potent force in the advertising world, is now being mined for new management and training techniques, even at an 89-year-old company not often thought of as trendy. With a tight labor market and workers mindful of more relaxed cultures at dot-coms, some traditional companies are trying to be hip to retain and motivate employees.</p>
        <p>Merrill Lynch and McDonald's, for example, turn training sessions into mock versions of television game shows like ''Jeopardy'' or ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire,'' complete with a cheering section, a host and buzzers. There are also corporate training videos with titles -- ''Alien Encounter'' and ''Hunt for T-Rex,'' for example -- that reflect popular Hollywood movies.</p>
        <p>''These training sessions kind of morph into whatever's popular at the time,'' said David Stampf, a writer at Training magazine, which is based in Minneapolis.</p>
        <p>Two or three times a year, Whirlpool selects seven young people from around the country to live together for eight weeks in a leased, seven-bedroom house not far from its corporate headquarters here in Benton Harbor. The recruits will eventually be dispatched to train sales staffs at retailers like Sears and Lowe's to sell the company's appliances.</p>
        <p>And they had better be good. At the end of August Whirlpool said that weakening demand for home appliances in the United States and Europe was cutting sharply into profit margins. The recent decision by Circuit City stores to stop selling big appliances has also shaken up the company's profit forecasts. Whirlpool's stock has been down sharply, but has recently recovered somewhat, closing yesterday at $40.88.</p>
        <p>The new program is expected to build team spirit at Whirlpool, and also trust. At the house, there are no restrictions on the recruits' relationships with one another, no legal documents laying out guidelines for living together. But the most recent cadre formulated a makeshift list of house rules as they settled into cohabitation early this summer. Among them: ''Say what you feel,'' ''Don't let problems simmer,'' and ''If you make a mess, clean it up.''</p>
        <p>The participants do, however, have to agree to one important condition. They enter the program -- and accept the approximately $35,000-a-year training jobs -- not knowing until just days before their ''Real Whirled'' stint ends where they will be working. They only know that they will be based near a major American metropolitan center.</p>
        <p>The recruits spend their days mastering the company's household appliances, which are periodically swapped for different models, even that of a competitor, for comparison testing. There are written tests, oral presentations and almost daily quizzes on attributes and idiosyncrasies of washers, dryers and microwave ovens.</p>
        <p>Under the supervision of Kurt Gersonde, a training manager often on site from 7 a.m. until 6 p.m., they visit local stores to determine how well or not so well others are selling the company's appliances. They are sent out on house calls with a repair crew; visit the company's manufacturing plants; and go to research centers, to catch a glimpse of the future.</p>
        <p>But mostly, they stay at home. They cook up dishes to test the new Accubake oven. They splatter food on linens to determine if the Catalyst washing machine really does give clothes ''the whitest whites.'' And they leave pasta sauce and sticky noodles on plates when they load the new Kitchen Aid dishwasher to see how well it cleans away leftover bits of food.</p>
        <p>No other major appliance maker has anything like ''The Real Whirled.'' Maytag, for example, has a more traditional training program in which new employees watch videos, study manuals and are given instructions on using appliances.</p>
        <p>The idea emerged from a brainstorming session with James H. Gilmore, a consultant who has encouraged corporations to ''embrace theater'' in the workplace and create ''unique experiences'' that can transform the work force. Someone mentioned ''The Real World,'' and the idea of Whirlpool's own live-in training program was born.</p>
        <p>It was an ideal way to train new hires, Ms. Seib said, because ''we're hiring kids right out of college, and their expertise is lugging their clothes home to their mother.''</p>
        <p>The Whirlpool program is set here in the western part of the state, in a big, white clapboard home more Disney than MTV. There are green rooms, candy-colored fixtures, shades painted with butterflies, and lots of nooks and crannies.</p>
        <p>The first group shared a different house in late 1998. The fourth -- four men and three women, racially diverse and in their mid-20's -- finished up its tour late last month.</p>
        <p>There was Lindsey Williams, a 22-year-old graduate of Texas Christian University, who realized after college that her political ambitions would take longer to achieve than she wanted to wait. ''You can't graduate from college at 22 and become a congresswoman,'' she said. Instead, she followed her father, a longtime sales employee at Whirlpool.</p>
        <p>Richard Federico, 25, is the only recruit who is married. He also has two children, one of whom is proudly put on display on the screen saver of his laptop computer. After graduating third in a high school class of 10 people in Maine, he went to Liberty University, the school founded by the Rev. Jerry Falwell in Lynchburg, Va. After graduation, he decided to go into retailing and heard about the program through a friend.</p>
        <p>Salena Barone, a 24-year-old from Philadelphia, was the food expert in the group. She doled out daily advice on how to make the prescribed dishes right. And Tony Barbee, who botched a cake on Day 3, still managed to be a class favorite.</p>
        <p>There were mishaps -- a television on the blink during the video session on sexual harassment, for instance -- and some laughs: about Mr. Federico's ability to consume steaks and the time Ms. Barone became the target of sea gulls on the beach. There was the puerile, like the time Ms. Williams, during preparations for a test, was asked the main advantage of the Catalyst washer. Someone in the room blurted out that it was an aphrodisiac.</p>
        <p>And though there were some minor conflicts, the participants insist that real bonding took place. They studied for tests together, went to the beach, played volleyball and talked about race and culture.</p>
        <p>''Every person brings something to the table,'' said Brian Clark, 22, a recent graduate of the College of the Ozarks in Missouri and one of the participants.</p>
        <p>While there are usually a lot of budding romances on ''The Real World,'' that level of engagement did not take place here. ''I don't need to be sidetracked,'' one recruit said.</p>
        <p>Besides, the bosses at headquarters were not exactly clueless about the goings-on at the house.</p>
        <p>''Everyone's observing us,'' Ms. Barone said. ''I think that's what this is all about.''</p>
        <p>To the outside observer, the recruits could have been mistaken for ordinary roommates. One day in July, the group huddled in the kitchen to prepare a huge lunch. Ms. Williams chopped cucumbers, Mr. Barbee pulled chocolate chip cookies out of the oven and Ms. Barone prepared pasta. One dish of noodles was placed in the convection oven, another in the microwave. The results surprised even the cook.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to admit it,'' Ms. Barone confessed, '' but the microwave dish tastes better.''</p>
        <p>After the experience not only of cooking and cleaning but also of building relationships, the raw recruits of two months ago are now ready, they say, to take their ''Real Whirled'' experience to the, well, real world.</p>
        <p>''Business is about relationships anyway,'' Mr. Clark said. ''And being here, living with real people is the genuine article.'' Besides, he added: ''I cooked tangy cauliflower the other night and everybody loved it. My mom's freaking; she's like, 'This is excellent.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
