<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees Are Just Killing Time Until Postseason Comes Around</title>
    <meta content="12YANK$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/sports/12YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230040"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE6DE1738F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees Are Just Killing Time Until Postseason Comes Around</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Boston Red Sox beat New York Yankees, 4-0 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Yankees Manager Joe Torre carried a daily organizer for his business, these would be the first two lines on his to-do list:</p>
        <p>1. Bury Sox and Jays.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If Yankees Manager Joe Torre carried a daily organizer for his business, these would be the first two lines on his to-do list:</p>
        <p>1. Bury Sox and Jays.</p>
        <p>2. Fix Stanton.</p>
        <p>There might be a few other references, like resting David Justice and Bernie Williams or remembering to call the principal owner. But clinching a playoff berth and repairing Mike Stanton and the rest of the bullpen would be the priorities.</p>
        <p>Last night, the Red Sox beat the Yankees, 4-0, in a makeup of a rainout at Yankee Stadium, as one Cuban defector, Rolando Arrojo, pitched seven and one-third exceptional innings and beat his fellow defector, Orlando Hernandez. But Stanton and a couple of others pitched well in relief.</p>
        <p>The loss is merely a nick on the Yankees' formidable lead in the American League East: they are eight games ahead of Boston and Toronto, with the Blue Jays coming to town for a three-game series.</p>
        <p>Stanton had allowed 16 hits, 12 runs and 4 homers in his past four and one-third innings over six appearances before throwing a scoreless inning last night. ''Confidence is a funny creature,'' Stanton said. ''It's not something that's always there. It comes and goes, and it can come and go as quickly as one pitch.''</p>
        <p>Anybody who tells you they don't need a couple of good outings for confidence, Stanton added, ''is lying.''</p>
        <p>Stanton, Jeff Nelson and the closer Mariano Rivera essentially carried the pitching staff in the first months of the season, accumulating an unusually high number of innings and appearances. It is probably no coincidence that all three have had problems in the second half. In this era, teams cannot win in the postseason without effective bullpens, which is why Torre will concentrate on righting, resting and regulating his relievers in the final weeks of the regular season.</p>
        <p>So even with Arrojo dominating the Yankees in a game that was more one-sided than the score indicates, Torre made a point of getting Stanton on the mound. The left-hander has had slumps like this from time to time, problems created or perpetuated by his tendency to rush his delivery. Stanton has had little feel for his breaking ball in the last few weeks, has become too reliant on his fastball, and has gotten pounded.</p>
        <p>He entered the game to face the top of the Boston lineup: the left-handed hitting Trot Nixon, and the switch-hitting Jose Offerman and Carl Everett. Torre happened to be in his office when Stanton began pitching to Nixon and stayed to watch the at-bat on television, so he could see the location of Stanton's pitches.</p>
        <p>What Torre saw thrilled him. Stanton reached two strikes and then finished off Nixon with a breaking ball, Nixon flailing. Offerman and Everett struck out, as well -- Stanton's first hitless, scoreless inning since Aug. 17.</p>
        <p>''You're always worried about it,'' said Torre, referring to a slump like Stanton's, ''because you don't want it to keep happening. Do I have confidence in his ability to get out of it? Yes.''</p>
        <p>Stanton's potential importance to the Yankees in the playoffs cannot be understated. If the Yankees were to play Cleveland in the first round and relief were needed in the sixth, seventh or eighth innings, then Stanton would be called on to face the first three hitters in the Indians lineup -- the left-handed Kenny Lofton, and the switch-hitting Omar Vizquel and Roberto Alomar -- as well as the the sluggers Jim Thome and David Segui.</p>
        <p>If the Yankees played Boston, then Stanton would face the likes of Offerman, Everett and Troy O'Leary. If they faced the Blue Jays, Stanton would get Carlos Delgado and Brad Fullmer.</p>
        <p>''Stanton and Nelson bridge that gap to Rivera, and having them be consistent really takes Mo out of the mix for the eighth inning, which is what you really want,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Nelson has pitched better lately, and Stanton made a big stride against the Red Sox, in defeat.</p>
        <p>The biggest games Hernandez pitched in Cuba, he said last week, were the games in which he dueled Arrojo. El Duque pitched for Industriales and Arrojo was the ace of Villa Clara, and the stadiums filled and the atmosphere was tense.</p>
        <p>Arrojo was better last night, his stuff sharper, more explosive. Hernandez's fastball was exceptional in his previous start, in Kansas City; some of his teammates said they had never seen him use his fastball as aggressively as he did against the Royals, a good offensive team.</p>
        <p>But Hernandez's fastball had far less zip in the first inning last night, and the Red Sox hitters swung lustily, bashing about a half-dozen foul home runs, along with a couple that stayed fair.</p>
        <p>Hernandez walked Nixon leading off the game and then Offerman ripped a fastball for a two-run homer -- the first home run allowed by the Yankees since Sept. 3, a span of 66 innings.</p>
        <p>Manny Alexander slammed another two-run homer in the third, and Arrojo prevailed after that.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Yankees' pitching coach, MEL STOTTLEMYRE, has left the team for a more intensive part of his treatment for bone marrow cancer, a stem cell transplant, and he is not expected to rejoin the club this year. BILLY CONNORS is assuming Stottlemyre's responsibilities. Stottlemyre and team officials have known that there would come a time when Stottlemyre would have to leave his job, and he told Manager JOE TORRE and General Manager BRIAN CASHMAN about 10 days ago that the stem cell procedure -- in which cleansed cells are reintroduced into the body -- was scheduled this week. . . . Center fielder BERNIE WILLIAMS, bothered by a strained rib cage and a calf cramp, could rejoin the lineup Thursday, when the Yankees face Toronto's DAVID WELLS.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
