<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Voters Hope Senate Face-Off Clarifies Options</title>
    <meta content="12UNDE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/politics/12UNDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="UNDECIDED -- The First Debate" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230013"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gross, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harrison, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harrison, Cathy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwartz, Karl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Temkin, Dave</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E5DF1738F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Voters Hope Senate Face-Off Clarifies Options</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GROSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gross, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seventh article in series Undecided follows group of New York State voters as they make up their minds on which candidate to support for US Senate; Tom Smith, Cathy and Bob Harrison and Karl Schwartz are among many undecided voters who are counting on upcoming debate between Rep Rick A Lazio and Hillary Rodham Clinton to clarify murky situation; Dave Temkin says he wants to give Lazio fair hearing, but he intends to vote for Clinton; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tom Smith is one of many undecided voters counting on the Senate debate tomorrow night to clarify a murky situation. A fusillade of critical advertising by both candidates has angered him, Mr. Smith said, and he remains as confused as ever about the voting record of Representative Rick A. Lazio, the Republican latecomer to the race.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith has reservations about Hillary Rodham Clinton's character, as he has since the beginning of this pivotal contest. But his intense dislike of the first lady -- who faces a primary contest today with Dr. Mark S. McMahon -- has mellowed during the course of what he describes as her diligent, if sometimes plodding, campaign. And her positions are perfectly clear to him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tom Smith is one of many undecided voters counting on the Senate debate tomorrow night to clarify a murky situation. A fusillade of critical advertising by both candidates has angered him, Mr. Smith said, and he remains as confused as ever about the voting record of Representative Rick A. Lazio, the Republican latecomer to the race.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith has reservations about Hillary Rodham Clinton's character, as he has since the beginning of this pivotal contest. But his intense dislike of the first lady -- who faces a primary contest today with Dr. Mark S. McMahon -- has mellowed during the course of what he describes as her diligent, if sometimes plodding, campaign. And her positions are perfectly clear to him.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lazio remains an enigma to Mr. Smith, who works the overnight shift at a Wal-Mart near his home in Saugerties, N.Y. ''I still don't know much about him,'' he said. ''And the ads don't help at all.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio asserts that he has a record of Congressional achievement while the first lady is a blank slate. But Mr. Smith, and most of the other voters who have been sharing their decision-making process with The New York Times since February, do not see it that way. ''Being the first lady, she's been vocal about the things that are near and dear to her heart,'' said Mr. Smith, citing Mrs. Clinton's longstanding interest in health care, education and children's issues. ''But I need to know what he's going to do for me.''</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Lazio, he said: ''Sure, he has a record. But it all depends on how you read it. I can't tell if he voted his mind because of the needs of his constituents or if he was protecting himself and kissing up to whoever was in control. With the debate on Wednesday, maybe I'll get lucky and find out what he believes in, what he'll fight for.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith and his wife, Barbara, cannot afford cable television, and thus get nothing but snow on all but a few channels, so they will watch the debate at the local firehouse. Broadcast from Buffalo, the debate will be on NBC affiliates in New York at 7 p.m. and replayed on MSNBC at 10 p.m.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith is not alone in pinning his hopes on the debate. In interviews in recent days, a panel of undecided voters said the debate had major significance as the first face-to-face, unscripted moment of the race.</p>
        <p>''I can't wait to see it,'' said Cathy Harrison, a nurse from Amsterdam, N.Y., who was close to committing herself to Mr. Lazio two months ago but has since shifted her tentative allegiance because of Mrs. Clinton's more emphatic comments about the flagging upstate economy. ''It's a big one for me. I'm going to pay more attention to that than anything.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Harrison will tape the debate for her husband, Bob, a social studies teacher, so he can watch it when he gets home from back-to-school night. Doug Taggart's wife, in Cortlandt Manor in Westchester County, will do the same, since he has a late meeting at the financial services firm on Wall Street where he is a vice president.</p>
        <p>Karl Schwartz, a freelance computer consultant from Staten Island, says he plans to take notes, especially if the topic turns to medical research, his primary concern these days as his wife battles cancer.</p>
        <p>These six voters remain undecided as the race enters its final lap, all with their own pet issues, but all disheartened by the tone the campaign has taken since the withdrawal of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and the substitution of Mr. Lazio on the Republican ticket.</p>
        <p>They are the holdouts on a panel of 11 undecided voters, culled from early New York Times/CBS News polls. Two voters dropped out of the project in May, and three others say they have already made their decisions.</p>
        <p>The first to decide, as soon as the Republican candidate changed, was Tom Beck, a guidance counselor on Long Island, in the district that adjoins Mr. Lazio's, who had been a longtime admirer of the young congressman for a voting record that Mr. Beck said defies party stereotypes.</p>
        <p>Now, two others have cast their lots with Mrs. Clinton: Charlene Clinton, a Buffalo woman who recently returned to public assistance after losing her first job in many years, and Dave Temkin, a telecommunications expert from Queens.</p>
        <p>Both are lifelong Democrats who counted themselves among the undecided for different reasons.</p>
        <p>Ms. Clinton, by her own admission, has no interest in politics and did not even know who was running until the recent spate of television commercials. Now that she has the candidates straight, and their party affiliations, she will vote party-line as she always has, and as her parents did before her.</p>
        <p>Mr. Temkin, by contrast, is avid about labor and social issues, history and government, and delayed what he now says was an all-but-inevitable decision until he had carefully considered the Republican opposition.</p>
        <p>''Fairness and intelligence require that,'' he said, especially when the Democratic candidate, in this case Mrs. Clinton, is ''someone you don't have any particular trust and affection for.''</p>
        <p>''I needed to see if Lazio was something other than I thought he was: an undistinguished congressman with an undistinguished record, doing his party's bidding,'' Mr. Temkin added. ''I gave him a chance, but I sort of knew the answer all along.''</p>
        <p>Of Mrs. Clinton, he said, ''I don't think her character flaws will prevent her from being an effective senator,'' echoing others among this group who continue to dislike the first lady but no longer in a disqualifying way. ''When you look at what's going to come down the road in the Senate for the next four years, working-class people will be a lot better off with the conceivable Clinton voting record than the conceivable Lazio voting record.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Taggart, while still undecided, is also less concerned about Mrs. Clinton's flaws and more concerned about Mr. Lazio's blurry persona than he was two months ago. He said that the ''amount of vitriol'' directed at the first lady has left him with ''sort of a protective feeling'' toward her.</p>
        <p>He also has questions about Mr. Lazio, whose voting record in Congress, Mr. Taggart has read, shifted from middle of the road to more conservative when the Republicans won control of the House in 1994. ''Is that for personal gain, to make his way up the leadership charts?'' Mr. Taggart asked. ''Is he a conciliator or is he a panderer? Is he a malleable go-along-to-get-along kind of guy, or does he have convictions? And if so, what are they? ''</p>
        <p>Several of the undecided voters say questions like these have been totally obscured by the barrage of advertising, which has come from both sides but seems to be hurting Mr. Lazio more than Mrs. Clinton among this small group. All the voters complained bitterly of the ''mudslinging'' and said it made them ever more disdainful of the political process.</p>
        <p>''I'm tired of it,'' Mr. Schwartz said. ''Hopefully, other people are, too. Issues are too complex to be evaluated this way. It should be illegal.''</p>
        <p>A voter like Mr. Schwartz, with a single-minded interest in cancer research, will cast his ballot for whichever candidate cares more about that, no matter how disgusted he is by the advertising. For the moment, he said, that looks like Mr. Lazio.</p>
        <p>So, too, with the Harrisons, who are shopping for a senator with a plan to reverse the hemorrhaging of the upstate economy. Right now, Mrs. Clinton has the edge, they said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taggart, on the other hand, has a palette of interests, among them the general state of political discourse in America. The last time he was faced with this ''ugly'' a campaign, he said, was when Robert Abrams challenged Alfonse M. D'Amato for his Senate seat in 1992.</p>
        <p>''I view my vote as a reward, something to be won,'' Mr. Taggart said. After much agonizing, he did not cast a ballot in that race, because neither was ''worthy of it,'' he said. ''And that's not outside of the realm of possibility this time.''</p>
        <p>Undecided</p>
        <p>This is the seventh article in a series following a group of New York State voters from diverse backgrounds as they make up their minds on which candidate to support for the United States Senate.</p>
        <p>The previous articles were about the changed nature of the campaign after Representative Rick A. Lazio became the Republican Party's nominee; Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's dropped candidacy; the mayor's separation from his wife; his prostate cancer; how undecided voters gathered information; and their first impressions.</p>
        <p>Series articles are available at The New York Times on the Web at www.nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
