<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Landlord Is Charged in Slaying of Tenant</title>
    <meta content="12SLAY$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/12/nyregion/12SLAY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gootman, Elissa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hubrecht, Louis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kenna, Barbara B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E3DF1738F931A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Landlord Is Charged in Slaying of Tenant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISSA GOOTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gootman, Elissa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Police charge Madison Avenue landlord Louis Hubrecht with shooting and killing tenant Barbara B Kenna, but he says he fired in self-defense (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 69-year-old elementary school librarian was shot and killed yesterday by the landlord of the Madison Avenue brownstone where she had lived for more than 29 years, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>The police said the landlord, Louis Hubrecht, said he had fired in self-defense, shooting the librarian, Barbara B. Kenna, with a .38-caliber pistol after she tried to attack him with a hammer in the hallway outside his apartment. But Mr. Hubrecht was charged with second-degree murder last night, said Officer Cheryl Cox, a police spokeswoman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 69-year-old elementary school librarian was shot and killed yesterday by the landlord of the Madison Avenue brownstone where she had lived for more than 29 years, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>The police said the landlord, Louis Hubrecht, said he had fired in self-defense, shooting the librarian, Barbara B. Kenna, with a .38-caliber pistol after she tried to attack him with a hammer in the hallway outside his apartment. But Mr. Hubrecht was charged with second-degree murder last night, said Officer Cheryl Cox, a police spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kenna and Mr. Hubrecht, 65, had been in a protracted feud, the authorities said. Mr. Hubrecht lives on the third floor at 700 Madison Avenue, between 62nd and 63rd Streets, a five-story walkup. Ms. Kenna, who worked at Public School 2 in Chinatown, occupied the penthouse of the same building.</p>
        <p>The shooting occurred at 9:20 a.m., and Mr. Hubrecht called soon afterward to report it, the police said. Ms. Kenna was pronounced dead at New York Hospital. The authorities then tried to piece together the sequence of the morning's events and the longstanding animosity that apparently led to the shooting.</p>
        <p>The police also questioned a sister of Mr. Hubrecht's whom he called when the dispute began, but she was not charged, Officer Cox said.</p>
        <p>The police said that Mr. Hubrecht had summoned the sister, whom they did not identify, but a department spokesman was unsure whether she was present when the shooting occurred.</p>
        <p>Another sister lives in the building but was at work when the shooting took place, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hubrecht fired five times, hitting Ms. Kenna several times, the police said. A spokeswoman for the city medical examiner said an autopsy would be conducted today.</p>
        <p>A streak of blood marked the floor in front of Mr. Hubrecht's apartment yesterday afternoon, and a red-handled hammer lay nearby on the staircase to the fourth floor.</p>
        <p>A resident of the building, Louise Duncan, said the landlord and Ms. Kenna had argued angrily over rent and other matters for all the 15 years that Ms. Duncan had lived there.</p>
        <p>She said Ms. Kenna feared that Mr. Hubrecht wanted her to move out of her apartment, which a state official said was rent-controlled.</p>
        <p>''I think she thought he was bound and devoted to getting her to leave,'' Ms. Duncan said. ''Never in a million years did you think he or she would do anything violent,'' she said.</p>
        <p>At P.S. 2, where Ms. Kenna, a short woman with gray hair, had worked since at least 1970, her colleagues had expected her for work yesterday. Teachers expressed shock when they heard the news.</p>
        <p>''She had so much compassion for children,'' said Lily Liu, who runs the school's day care center. Ms. Liu said that she and Ms. Kenna sometimes ate lunch together, and that Ms. Kenna had spoken about her tense relationship with her landlord. ''She'd mention that it would bother her,'' Ms. Liu said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kenna had spent the summer computerizing the school library files without pay, co-workers said, and students praised her patience.  ''She'd never yell at students, even if they were bad students,'' said Sally Lau, 11, who graduated from the school last year.</p>
        <p>Housing Court has no record of a dispute between Ms. Kenna and Mr. Hubrecht, a clerk there said.</p>
        <p>And Dan D. Irizarry, a spokesman for the New York State Division of Housing and Community Renewal, said that his agency had no record that Ms. Kenna had filed any complaints against her landlord.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
