<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Missionary to England: Pakistani-Born Bishop</title>
    <meta content="Y12ANG$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221834"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Anglican Churches</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Niebuhr, Gustav</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nazir-Ali, Michael (Bishop)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carey, George (Archbishop)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E1DB153FF931A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1247" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Missionary to England: Pakistani-Born Bishop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUSTAV NIEBUHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Niebuhr, Gustav</byline>
      <dateline>ROCHESTER, England</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bishop Michael Nazir-Ali, head of Church of England's Rochester diocese, is among prelates mentioned as possible successor to Archbishop of Canterbury George Carey; is native of Pakistan and only non-Caucasion in Church of England to head diocese; Nazir-Ali photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For centuries the Church of England's cathedral here has greeted pilgrims as the next-to-last stop on the road to Canterbury. Signs inside still bid travelers welcome, indicating the route's enduring popularity.</p>
        <p>But these days some wonder whether Rochester's bishop might one day go to Canterbury himself -- not as a pilgrim, but as successor to the incumbent archbishop, whose retirement may not be that far off.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For centuries the Church of England's cathedral here has greeted pilgrims as the next-to-last stop on the road to Canterbury. Signs inside still bid travelers welcome, indicating the route's enduring popularity.</p>
        <p>But these days some wonder whether Rochester's bishop might one day go to Canterbury himself -- not as a pilgrim, but as successor to the incumbent archbishop, whose retirement may not be that far off.</p>
        <p>Such a move would make him the Church of England's spiritual leader, first among equals among bishops of Anglican churches worldwide, among them the Episcopal Church in the United States.</p>
        <p>It would be a historic transition, because Rochester's prelate, Bishop Michael Nazir-Ali, is a native of Pakistan. At 50 he already has the distinction of being the only non-Caucasian in the Church of England to head a diocese.</p>
        <p>In the last four decades, Christianity has grown rapidly in Africa and Asia, and with it the influence of African and Asian prelates. But if Europeans and Americans are to grasp the significance of the trend, it may have to be personalized through people like Bishop Nazir-Ali.</p>
        <p>And there are several like him. There is the Rev. Setri Nyomi, the Ghanaian who is the top official of the World Alliance of Reformed Churches, which includes the Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.). There is Mr. Nyomi's counterpart at the Lutheran World Federation, the Rev. Ishmael Noko, a Zimbabwean.</p>
        <p>And there is Cardinal Francis Arinze, a Nigerian who heads the Vatican's interfaith council. Within the Roman Catholic Church, whose African membership has more than doubled since 1975, the cardinal is considered to be among Pope John Paul II's possible successors.</p>
        <p>In an interview in his study -- a room with a fireplace, a window overlooking a garden, and many books -- the Cambridge-educated Bishop Nazir-Ali discussed his rise to influence. ''I've never actually applied for anything,'' he said. ''I've always been told to do it. I never thought I would have a ministry outside Pakistan.''</p>
        <p>His voice is heard well beyond Rochester, which lies east of London. The Guardian, a leading British newspaper, recently published an article he wrote calling attention to the persecution of Christians in some Islamic nations. In it he cited verses in the Koran supporting religious tolerance.</p>
        <p>The son of a Christian convert, the bishop has Shiite Muslim relatives. He speaks Arabic, Persian and Urdu, and is often invited to speak in British mosques.</p>
        <p>Bishop Nazir-Ali has had an increasingly visible presence among Anglican prelates since 1986, when Robert Runcie, then the archbishop of Canterbury, invited him to help plan the 1988 Lambeth Conference, the once-a-decade meeting of Anglican prelates worldwide.</p>
        <p>When the bishops met again in 1998, three years after he was named to head the Rochester diocese, Bishop Nazir-Ali presided over a conference committee concerned with Christian-Muslim relations and spoke about Islam in the world. ''It was a very learned talk,'' said Bishop Henry N. Parsley of Birmingham, Ala.</p>
        <p>Last March, Bishop Parsley invited Bishop Nazir-Ali to lecture and preach to Alabama Episcopalians. ''People in Montgomery and Birmingham were delighted,'' Bishop Parsley said. But asked about his colleague's ecclesiastical future, he said, ''Who knows, when you're talking about the next archbishop of Canterbury or the next pope?''</p>
        <p>Bishop Nazir-Ali has heard the speculation and, not surprisingly, is circumspect. ''I carry on with what I'm doing in the way I regard as best,'' he said. Rochester and Canterbury, neighboring dioceses, share major social work projects.</p>
        <p>The archbishop of Canterbury stands at the core of the British establishment, by protocol outranking even the prime minister. To live up to the job description, a prelate must function as local bishop, leader of a diverse and often divided national church, and head of a global religious association. Commenting on the responsibilities, the bishop said, ''Nobody in their right mind would seek such a job.''</p>
        <p>Others mentioned as candidates include Bishop Richard Charters of London, who is considered close to the royal family, and Archbishop Rowan Williams of Wales, who is admired as a theologian.</p>
        <p>The successor to the incumbent, Archbishop George Carey, will be chosen by members of a royal commission as well as the prime minister and Queen Elizabeth II. The decision may be years off. Archbishop Carey, who was chosen in 1991, can remain in office until he turns 70, in 2006. But he could step down sooner.</p>
        <p>Canterbury's Christian significance dates to 597, when a missionary monk named Augustine arrived to evangelize the Anglo-Saxons. One of his colleagues ventured west to the Medway River, becoming Rochester's first bishop.</p>
        <p>The diocese is economically varied, incorporating London's eastern flanks, agricultural areas and new towns. Dickens grew up within its boundaries. Now it contains an emerging religious diversity, with Mormons, New Age spiritualists and others, part of a wide challenge confronting the Church of England, whose problems might have daunted even Augustine.</p>
        <p>Church attendance has fallen. Anglican leaders speak of a society awash with ''pick and mix'' spirituality, in which people choose beliefs and practices to suit their private needs.</p>
        <p>To examine the church's place in this, Bishop Nazir-Ali headed a committee that published ''The Search for Faith'' (Church House Publishing, 1996). The book examined the history of ideas underlying contemporary thinking and suggested that the church find new ways to communicate the Gospel to a postmodern culture.</p>
        <p>The bishop has also been quoted as saying that the British might benefit from receiving missionaries.</p>
        <p>''Britain is a missionary situation,'' he said. ''There's no question about that. It's a lack of even basic knowledge of the Bible in the population. I was preaching at a Charles Dickens international conference, and I was saying: Dickens was immersed in the Bible. But now when students study Dickens in university, they have to be taught the Bible to understand Dickens.''</p>
        <p>The church, he said, ''needs help, in the sense of inspiration, enthusiasm, new eyes to see its mission.''</p>
        <p>It may also need self-confidence. At times members of the clergy inviting him to speak have urged him to avoid saying anything that might upset people. But he still feels, as he put it, that ''the world is willing to give us a hearing, as long as we're willing to say something.''</p>
        <p>He knows reactions can be hostile. Earlier this year the bishop, who is married and has two grown sons, touched off a furor by writing that the church should continue to teach ''that having children and their nurture is a basic good of marriage and not an optional extra.''</p>
        <p>One critic, representing an organization for ''non-parents,'' called his message ''too offensive for words.''</p>
        <p>But others were pleased. ''That Michael would say that warmed my heart,'' said Bishop Munawar K. Rumalshah, the head of a London missionary society and a friend for more than 30 years.</p>
        <p>Bishop Nazir-Ali's becoming archbishop, his old friend said, would have a big impact throughout the Anglican Communion -- would prove ''that there is no black and white in Jesus.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
