<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Night of Crazy, Lost and Impossible Love</title>
    <meta content="12HADA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Central Park Summerstage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pareles, Jon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Central Park Summerstage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5DE153FF931A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Night of Crazy, Lost and Impossible Love</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jon Pareles reviews Mexican cabaret performance presented at Central Park Summerstage; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Love, politics, shopping, sacrilege and tequila were all on the agenda for ''An Evening at Salon Mexico'' on Thursday night at Central Park Summerstage. It was a New York showcase for Liliana Felipe, Astrid Hadad and Eugenia Leon, who are mainstays of a El Habito, a long-running cabaret in Mexico City  where old-fashioned cabaret singing and performance art intersect.</p>
        <p>At Summerstage they put on a full-scale revue with elaborate carnival-like costumes, accompanied by a 25-piece orchestra and the Aguila y Plata mariachi band. To provide a little cabaret ambience, there were tables set up on Rumsey Playfield for Summerstage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Love, politics, shopping, sacrilege and tequila were all on the agenda for ''An Evening at Salon Mexico'' on Thursday night at Central Park Summerstage. It was a New York showcase for Liliana Felipe, Astrid Hadad and Eugenia Leon, who are mainstays of a El Habito, a long-running cabaret in Mexico City  where old-fashioned cabaret singing and performance art intersect.</p>
        <p>At Summerstage they put on a full-scale revue with elaborate carnival-like costumes, accompanied by a 25-piece orchestra and the Aguila y Plata mariachi band. To provide a little cabaret ambience, there were tables set up on Rumsey Playfield for Summerstage.</p>
        <p>Throughout the show, iconoclasm mixed with fondness for the past and jokes about Mexico's ambivalent attitudes toward the United States. The women sang about crazy love, lost love and impossible love, with their voices promising ardent sincerity while their attitudes and costumes brought a knowing irony. They sang about drowning their sorrows in tequila while Jesusa Rodriguez, who founded El Habito with Ms. Felipe and directed the staging on Thursday night, brought glass after glass.</p>
        <p>The women also had more mischievous songs: a giddy tribute to the pleasures of shopping, sung by Ms. Hadad as she wore a headdress shaped like the Eiffel Tower, and ''Cuando Yo Cumpla Ochenta'' about wrecking a church, sung by Ms. Felipe over the jaunty brass-band bounce of Mexican banda music.</p>
        <p>''Virgen de Media Noche'' was introduced as the song of ''a prostitute who seeks pleasure with men who come from the sea''; Ms. Hadad sang it wearing a Statue of Liberty headdress and using a flashlight as a torch.</p>
        <p>There were also jokes about immigration and a prayer to Uncle Sam, with lines like ''Give us this day our daily McDonald's'' and ''Forgive Cuba, as we forgive the marines.''</p>
        <p>The music embraced rural and urban Mexican styles including ranchera, bolero, son jaropo and norteno waltz as well as banda. But many songs also took up vintage Afro-Cuban styles like the danzon, guajira, rumba and son, with horns and saxophones cradling the voices. At times, the band jumped into rock or swing for a moment. And one Mexican ranchera switched to a Brazilian samba halfway through, as Ms. Hadad tossed confetti that was hidden in the brim of her sombrero.</p>
        <p>Ms. Felipe is a songwriter as well as a singer; her songs stretched old forms with wordplay and unexpected rhythms and harmonies. She brought a smoky, smoldering drama to her songs; Ms. Leon and Ms. Hadad had creamier voices, though both could let loose the sobs and imperious vibrato of old ranchera singers. Eduardo Garcia Barrios, the conductor and music director, brought out both the music's elegance and its underlying humor. For the show's finale, he also got the chance to smash a pinata.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
