<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Witches Express Relief As Vexing Case Is Closed</title>
    <meta content="12WITC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221858"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Witchcraft</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Patavino, Kerri Lynn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herszenhorn, David M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Occult Sciences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E3D7153FF931A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="716" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Witches Express Relief As Vexing Case Is Closed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HERSZENHORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herszenhorn, David M</byline>
      <dateline>BRIDGEPORT, Conn., Aug. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Witchcraft adherents in Connecticut express relief at end to case of Kerri Lynn Patavino; former school-bus driver and Wicca follower who was convicted in 1996 of having sexual realtionship with 14-year-old boy returns to court to admit guilt and ask that sentence be reduced; photo; six-year sentence is reduced by one year (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the relief of witches throughout Connecticut, the case of Kerri Lynn Patavino appears to be closed once and for all.</p>
        <p>In the case's final chapter, Mrs. Patavino, a 32-year-old former school-bus driver and follower of Wicca, the witchcraft religion, who was convicted in 1996 of having a sexual relationship with a 14-year-old boy, returned to court this week to admit her guilt and to request that her prison sentence be reduced.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the relief of witches throughout Connecticut, the case of Kerri Lynn Patavino appears to be closed once and for all.</p>
        <p>In the case's final chapter, Mrs. Patavino, a 32-year-old former school-bus driver and follower of Wicca, the witchcraft religion, who was convicted in 1996 of having a sexual relationship with a 14-year-old boy, returned to court this week to admit her guilt and to request that her prison sentence be reduced.</p>
        <p>The admission meant one last round of headlines in Connecticut newspapers about witchery and of stories recounting the prosecution's allegations that Mrs. Patavino, a mother of two, had used a boy on her bus route in rituals of sex and blood-drinking on a bed atop a large pentagram in her home in Monroe, Conn.</p>
        <p>Witches, who say their religion has more to do with nature worship than with dark, occult practices, say it is time for the case to fade away.</p>
        <p>''Whatever religion somebody is doesn't change the fact that you have folks who do rotten things,'' said Dawn Debbe, a witch in Hamden who teaches classes in Wicca and magic, including spell casting.</p>
        <p>''I don't think that the emphasis should have been on the fact that she is a witch,'' Ms. Debbe said. ''One of the things that bothered me a lot was that they had declared her in the headlines here as an alleged witch, which cracked me up because you never hear of an alleged Catholic or an alleged Lutheran.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Patavino was convicted of multiple counts of sexual abuse and risking injury to a minor and was sentenced to six years in prison. In exchange for her admission of guilt, prosecutors did not oppose her request for a shorter sentence. And on Tuesday, Judge Joseph T. Gormley Jr. cut the sentence by one year.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Patavino's lawyer, H. Jeffrey Beck, said his client was disappointed that the judge did not cut her sentence further. He said that religion had not factored into her appeal and was not discussed in the letter to the court in which she dropped her professions of innocence and accepted responsibility.</p>
        <p>Mr. Beck said that from conversations with Mrs. Patavino he understood her Wicca beliefs to be ''very positive.'' ''It's not flying around and broomsticks and devil-worship,'' he said. ''It's kind of an earthy religion, very holistic, that she practices, at least.''</p>
        <p>Although for a while Mrs. Patavino and her supporters asserted that she was being persecuted for her religion, Mr. Beck said that the state's evidence was strong and that she probably would have been convicted ''whether she was a witch or a werewolf.''</p>
        <p>After her arrest, several witches set up a defense fund and argued her cause in various online Wicca newsletters, one of which, ''Jane's Tidings,'' criticized the ''lurid publicity'' around the case ''that emphasized and cheapened her religion.''</p>
        <p>Local witches were equally critical this week. ''They emphasize the witch part all the time, which hurts any positive accomplishments that others have made,'' said Beverly Safko, the owner of The Magik Mirror, a witchcraft store in Milford.</p>
        <p>The total number of witches in Connecticut is not known, but Ms. Safko said she herself maintained a mailing list of about 800 people. And the Connecticut Wiccan Resource page lists more than two dozen covens and other witch groups in addition to the Pagan Community Church in Bridgeport.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors had alleged that Mrs. Patavino used the 14-year-old boy to celebrate ''The Great Rite,'' an act of ritual sex that is a central tenet of Wicca, symbolizing the male-female polarity in the universe. Witches say participation in the rite is always voluntary.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Debbe, not inclined to automatically approve the behavior of a fellow witch, noted that since ''children can't give consent,'' voluntary participation by the teenager was impossible.</p>
        <p>''I don't care if you are going to call it the Great Rite or what you are going to call it,'' she said. ''But religions also have to work within the guidelines of the law and the guidelines of the age of reason.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
