<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Annual Event May Be Canceled</title>
    <meta content="12HORS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221851"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE SHOW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Shows</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Horse Show</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horsemanship and Equestrian Events</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1D8153FF931A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="409" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Annual Event May Be Canceled</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Horse Show may be canceled because of changes in rules that would condense schedule (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A sanctioning crisis within the governing body of the National Horse Show at Madison Square Garden may cause the cancellation of the 117th annual event.</p>
        <p>''That is quite possible, and we're exploring all our options,'' said Alan Balch, the show's executive director.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A sanctioning crisis within the governing body of the National Horse Show at Madison Square Garden may cause the cancellation of the 117th annual event.</p>
        <p>''That is quite possible, and we're exploring all our options,'' said Alan Balch, the show's executive director.</p>
        <p>The show is scheduled to start on the night of Nov. 3 and end Nov. 5.</p>
        <p>This week the National Hunter/ Jumper Council objected to proposed changes in the American Horse Shows Association's rules that would have condensed the hunter division's activities from two days into one. But allowing one day for the hunter division violates the association's prize-money rules. ''We were open to making the event happen, but we needed some semblance of following the A.H.S.A. rules,'' said Tom Struzzieri, the council's president. The council is part of the A.H.S.A.</p>
        <p>The need for a condensed schedule was caused earlier this year when the Garden cut the National Horse Show from three and a half days to two and a half days.</p>
        <p>Balch said the council's objection was ''completely unanticipated'' because rules have been adapted in the past to accommodate varying conditions and scheduling at the Garden.</p>
        <p>''If they showed any flexibility, we could have made this work,'' Struzzieri said. He insisted that his objections to proposed rules for a one-day division event led to what he said was Balch's surprising announcement on Monday that he had canceled the entire show.</p>
        <p>But yesterday Balch denied that.</p>
        <p>''Only the hunter division has been canceled,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Balch said the jumpers and horsemanship classes would still compete, but that the horse show could be staged at another site with enough days in the schedule to accommodate the needs of the hunter division.</p>
        <p>The hunter division accounted for an estimated one-third of the activities at last year's show.</p>
        <p>The horse show has been a traditional event at the Garden since the late 19th century, but left the arena for the Meadowlands for seven years before returning in 1996. But the Garden reduced the six-day event to three and a half days. Because of scheduling priorities, the Garden informed the show last March that it had only two and a half days available for the show this year.</p>
        <p>HORSE SHOW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
