<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wackenhut Set to Build New Prison in South Africa</title>
    <meta content="Y12WAC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wackenhut Corrections Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cauvin, Henri E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFDA153FF931A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="511" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wackenhut Set to Build New Prison in South Africa</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRI E. CAUVIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cauvin, Henri E</byline>
      <dateline>PRETORIA, South Africa, Aug. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wackenhut Corrections Corp completes agreement to build and operate maximum-security penitentiary in South Africa (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Wackenhut Corrections Corporation, a world leader in private prison construction and management and a frequent target of industry critics, completed an agreement today to build and operate a 3,024-bed maximum-security penitentiary in South Africa.</p>
        <p>The prison, expected to be ready in about 18 months, is the first such venture in Africa for the company, which is based in Florida and operates prisons across the United States as well as in Britain, Australia, New Zealand and the Caribbean.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Wackenhut Corrections Corporation, a world leader in private prison construction and management and a frequent target of industry critics, completed an agreement today to build and operate a 3,024-bed maximum-security penitentiary in South Africa.</p>
        <p>The prison, expected to be ready in about 18 months, is the first such venture in Africa for the company, which is based in Florida and operates prisons across the United States as well as in Britain, Australia, New Zealand and the Caribbean.</p>
        <p>The 25-year-contract, which is valued by the government at about $245 million including the $45 million expense of the prison construction, was signed this morning during a 90-minute ceremony here in the capital. The cost of construction is to be financed by a consortium of South African banks.</p>
        <p>With South Africa's jails and prisons desperately overcrowded and the government struggling to find the money to build new ones, Wackenhut hopes the new prison, to be built in the far northern town of Louis Trichardt, is only the beginning of a long and lucrative relationship with South Africa.</p>
        <p>The leaders of South Africa share that hope, and for them, more is at stake than simply the success of a single prison. Besieged not only by high crime rates but by other social ills that require substantial financing and attention, the government is grappling with how to pay for more houses, schools, hospitals and prisons. Wackenhut, which saves governments money by running prisons more efficiently than they can, is seen in South Africa as a promising solution.</p>
        <p>So three years ago, the government began an experiment in privatization, soliciting bids to build and manage four prisons here. Wackenhut and its local partners, incorporated as South African Custodial Services, bid for the right to build three adult operations and won two, including the planned prison at Louis Trichardt.</p>
        <p>In choosing Wackenhut to operate at least one of them, South Africa is turning to a company that made itself a household name in the private prison industry and not always for good reason. Over the years, and even in recent months, the company has come in for criticism over how some of its prisons in the United States have been run.</p>
        <p>Authorities in Texas reclaimed control of a Wackenhut-run prison in Austin after a dozen former employees were indicted late last year on charges of sexually assaulting and harassing inmates. And earlier this year, authorities in Louisiana transferred the entire population of a juvenile prison run by Wackenhut after federal investigators contended that inmates were beaten and deprived of adequate food and clothes.</p>
        <p>South African officials say the safeguards they have incorporated into the contract will ensure that the new prisons are properly run.</p>
        <p>Overcrowding in the prisons is severe. Built to house about 100,000 inmates, the nation's prison system now holds more than 170,000. Prisoner escapes are common.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
