<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.M. Proposes An Online Site For Car Sales</title>
    <meta content="Y12ONLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221843"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hansell, Saul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EEDA153FF931A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1060" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.M. Proposes An Online Site For Car Sales</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAUL HANSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hansell, Saul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>General Motors proposes joint venture with its dealers to establish Web site offering cars made by other manufacturers as well as its own marques (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the biggest concession by an automaker that the Internet is transforming its business, General Motors has proposed a joint venture with its dealers to establish a Web site offering cars made by other manufacturers as well as its own.</p>
        <p>G.M. already has an elaborate site, called gmbuypower.com, that refers potential customers to its dealers. But a vast majority of online car shoppers have chosen sites offering all makes of cars, like Autobytel.com and CarPoint from Microsoft. Moreover, an increasing number of car buyers are using Internet services that post no-haggle prices, rather than require the customer to negotiate with a dealer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the biggest concession by an automaker that the Internet is transforming its business, General Motors has proposed a joint venture with its dealers to establish a Web site offering cars made by other manufacturers as well as its own.</p>
        <p>G.M. already has an elaborate site, called gmbuypower.com, that refers potential customers to its dealers. But a vast majority of online car shoppers have chosen sites offering all makes of cars, like Autobytel.com and CarPoint from Microsoft. Moreover, an increasing number of car buyers are using Internet services that post no-haggle prices, rather than require the customer to negotiate with a dealer.</p>
        <p>The details of G.M.'s new service depend on talks with its dealers, who have generally recoiled from posting their prices publicly. But most likely it will let customers  order cars at a set price, much as they can buy books from Amazon.com.</p>
        <p>In a letter this week to its dealers, Bill Lovejoy, G.M. group vice president for sales, said the company was looking to fight off the growing influence of the Web start-ups.</p>
        <p>''How do we -- General Motors and its dealer partners -- use the Internet to take on those intermediaries whose mission is to come between us?'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>Analysts said that if G.M. and its dealers decided to go forward, they would probably want to buy an existing auto sales site rather than build a new one. Given the fall in stock market prices, even the leader, Autobytel, has a market value of $100 million, pocket change for G.M.</p>
        <p>General Motors said it would consider an acquisition, but had not made a decision.</p>
        <p>G.M. and its dealers are increasingly worried that the new sites may wrest customer relationships away from them. That is crucial because dealers profit more from selling financing, insurance and service than from the cars themselves. And the Web sites all want to offer those services, too.</p>
        <p>''The dealers have a love-hate relationship with the Internet,'' said Chris Denove, a partner at J. D. Power &amp; Associates, an automotive marketing and research firm in Detroit. ''They are getting incremental business in the short run, but they fear that it will ultimately do to them what it has done to other middlemen like stockbrokers and travel agents.''</p>
        <p>J. D. Power estimates that more than half of all car buyers use the Internet to shop for cars -- looking up dealer invoice prices, for example. This year, it estimates, 4 percent of cars will be purchased online, up from 2.7 percent last year and 1.1 percent in 1998.</p>
        <p>In most cases, the car-shopping sites get fees from dealers for sending them customers. A few buy cars from the dealers and sell them at a markup.</p>
        <p>Analysts said G.M.'s new plan could remedy some of the problems that have hurt its site in the past.</p>
        <p>''Consumers prefer to use the sites that sell all make and models because they think they can get a better deal,'' Mr. Denove said. But he added that the plan requires an accord between G.M. and the dealers giving the manufacturer a role in selling cars, something that has caused explosive discord in the past. Earlier this year, G.M. withdrew a plan to buy up 10 percent of its dealerships so it could sell cars directly to consumers.</p>
        <p>At least some G.M. dealers familiar with its plan, however, praised it for including them in a way that G.M.'s previous efforts have not.</p>
        <p>''I think the majority of dealers will put their arms around this because they know the Internet is here to stay,'' said Gene Meyers, who owns Chevrolet dealerships in Paramus and Hawthorne, N.J. ''This should be a joint venture. They have the clicks, and we have the bricks.''</p>
        <p>Smaller dealers, which are still more reliant on personal relationships, have been more resistant to the carmakers' Internet initiatives.</p>
        <p>The company hopes to reach an accord with dealers in the next few months. And even before that it will start a test in one market of a crucial aspect of the proposed new company: an Internet site where customers can see the entire inventory of G.M. vehicles for sale in a region and true selling prices for them.</p>
        <p>''We need to move fast,'' said Mark T. Hogan, president of the company's electronic commerce unit, e-GM. ''The Internet is about launch and learn.''</p>
        <p>Several other carmakers have run tests to experiment with posted car prices, but none have offered a plan as elaborate as G.M.'s. Ford has purchased a partial stake in CarPoint, but that site is not favoring Fords over other cars. Rather, Ford plans to use Microsoft technology in a new site.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s proposal is complex. For one thing, manufacturers rarely try to sell competitors' products. But the Internet has made for some strange bedfellows. American Airlines controls Travelocity, a site selling tickets for all carriers. And Bertelsmann has agreed to buy CDNow, a site that sells music of all labels.</p>
        <p>As G.M. envisions it, the new site would not use the G.M. name and would offer information on all car models from neutral third-party sources. Customers who decided to purchase a G.M. car would find more detailed information and be able to complete the purchase online. Those who wanted to buy a Ford, for example, would probably be referred to the Ford site, or to a participating Ford dealer. (Many larger G.M. dealers own franchises to sell other makes, and they could get referrals from the new site for those cars.)</p>
        <p>Another potentially more contentions issue is G.M.'s plan for the new site to display the dealers' actual prices and inventory, as some sites already do. Dealers have been concerned about such systems, hoping to prevent online price wars.</p>
        <p>But some dealers familiar with G.M.'s proposal say they are not likely to fight it.</p>
        <p>''At the end of the day, the Internet hasn't compressed prices,'' said Jerry Seiner, the owner of 10 G.M. dealerships in Salt Lake City. ''We make so little money from new cars, there isn't much more you can cut.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
