<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bingo, Blood and Burial Plots In the Quest for Food Stamps</title>
    <meta content="12FOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221862"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Stamps</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bureaucratic Red Tape</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">America's Second Harvest</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Nina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bureaucratic Red Tape</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Stamps</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EED7153FF931A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bingo, Blood and Burial Plots In the Quest for Food Stamps</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NINA BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Nina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>America's Second Harvest, national network of food banks and advocacy groups, report concludes that food-stamp applications in most states have become so onerous that they are deterring needy people from applying for subsidies; finds that many of inquiries about income and assets have no connection to legal requirements for stamps but are either aggressive responses to federal mandates to deter fraud or part of recent state and local efforts to cut welfare costs by eliminating recipients; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In California, New York and 27 other states, people applying for food stamps are asked if they own a burial plot. Nebraska and Nevada want to know if applicants have sold their blood, and for how much. Hawaii demands garage-sale receipts, South Dakota wants documentation of bingo winnings, and Minnesota, on Page 20 of a 36-page eligibility application, asks if anyone in the household earns money from a paper route.</p>
        <p>Food-stamp applications in most states have become so onerous that they are deterring needy people from applying for the subsidies, a comprehensive analysis by a national network of food banks and advocacy groups has found. Many of the inquiries about income and assets have no connection to legal requirements for stamps but are either aggressive responses to federal mandates to deter fraud or part of recent state and local efforts to cut welfare costs by eliminating recipients.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In California, New York and 27 other states, people applying for food stamps are asked if they own a burial plot. Nebraska and Nevada want to know if applicants have sold their blood, and for how much. Hawaii demands garage-sale receipts, South Dakota wants documentation of bingo winnings, and Minnesota, on Page 20 of a 36-page eligibility application, asks if anyone in the household earns money from a paper route.</p>
        <p>Food-stamp applications in most states have become so onerous that they are deterring needy people from applying for the subsidies, a comprehensive analysis by a national network of food banks and advocacy groups has found. Many of the inquiries about income and assets have no connection to legal requirements for stamps but are either aggressive responses to federal mandates to deter fraud or part of recent state and local efforts to cut welfare costs by eliminating recipients.</p>
        <p>State administrators contend that they are simply complying with federal pressure to be tightfisted with taxpayers' money and properly enforcing the tougher rules passed by Congress in the 1996 welfare overhaul.</p>
        <p>But federal officials say the report, conducted by America's Second Harvest, the nation's largest food bank network, adds to their worries that such stringency may be one reason that 12 million people who need the benefits, and are eligible, are not getting them.</p>
        <p>Food-stamp use is plummeting at a faster rate than can be explained by economic growth. Since 1996, the number of people using food stamps has declined to 17.2 million people from 23 million, though a growing bipartisan consensus now holds that food stamps, like Medicaid, are supports needed to keep low-wage parents working.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes in this program we have not looked at the big picture,'' Agriculture Secretary Dan Glickman said in an interview about the survey, which will be released on Monday.</p>
        <p>''It's not my goal to keep hungry people out of the program -- that's a disgrace,'' Mr. Glickman said. ''But it's also my job to keep fraud down. It's tricky to balance those things.''</p>
        <p>The report, he added, ''is actually helpful. We are going to continue to work with the states to make sure that the income limits aren't ridiculous,'' and that antifraud techniques are not ''outside the bounds of what we ought to be doing.''</p>
        <p>Among the new sleuthing methods for countering fraud are parking-lot espionage in Tennessee, computerized credit checks in Delaware and Texas, and calls to employers and landlords in Alaska.</p>
        <p>''They don't want you to have nothing,'' a disabled woman of 56, who asked that her name not be used, whispered as she peered at the question about a burial space in the shabby waiting room of a food-stamp office in Harlem. ''It's none of their business. You want to tell the truth, but they make it so if you tell the truth, it don't help.''</p>
        <p>When the comment was repeated to the sponsors of the study, which examined application forms from all 50 states and a sampling from the nation's 3,143 counties, they said it underlined the unfairness of such questions, though they are not illegal.</p>
        <p>''She's afraid she'll go hungry if she's honest,'' Deborah Leff, president of America's Second Harvest, said of the woman's concern. ''Isn't that a mess?''</p>
        <p>Though the federal government finances and oversees the food-stamp program, states administer it, with wide variations. The shortest application, in Florida, is only a page, but most are more than 10 pages, and all warn that misleading answers are punishable by a stiff fine and up to 20 years in prison.</p>
        <p>Yet, the study found, many questions are unintelligible to the average applicant, and some are mind-boggling even to the researchers.</p>
        <p>''Are you or anyone in your household fleeing from New Jersey?'' Ohio's eight-page application asks. Researchers nicknamed the query the Soprano Clause, after the television drama about a Mafia family.</p>
        <p>''We live in Cleveland,'' said Sharon Davis, 39, a single mother of three who was laid off last month from her job as a machine operator and had spent most of the afternoon applying for food stamps. ''Why would they ask if you're from New Jersey?''</p>
        <p>In their defense, state administrators contend that all the questions -- including that one -- reflect local efforts to comply with a stream of federal dictates, including periodic crackdowns on fraud, stiff penalties on states that overpay even by $5, and new rules in the 1996 federal welfare legislation.</p>
        <p>To explain the so-called Soprano Clause, for example, Ohio food-stamp administrators pointed to a provision by Congress in the 1996 legislation. It excludes from the food-stamp program any fugitive from prosecution of a felony, which in New Jersey is called a ''high misdemeanor.'' To be safe, said Jon Allen, a spokesman for the Ohio Department of Job and Family Services, Ohio added an extra question just to cover New Jersey's terminology.</p>
        <p>By the same token, Nebraska, which was fined $1 million for food-stamp errors in a 1998 federal audit, asks about money from blood plasma donations and counts it against a family's food allotment -- which food-bank analysts say is simply wrong -- because in 1986 an obscure federal policy memorandum defined such money as earned income.</p>
        <p>As for burial plots, some state administrators justify questioning elderly applicants about them because a federal provision notes that only one grave per customer can be discounted when calculating a household's assets. To be eligible for food stamps at all, a household cannot have assets of over $2,000, or $3,000 for senior citizens, including checking and savings accounts and the value of any car above $4,650.</p>
        <p>Recent studies show that some people seeking food stamps have been turned away or cut off in a push to divert them from welfare -- sometimes illegally, as a federal court found in New York City last year. Many other people either do not know they are eligible or are discouraged by the requirements, especially in states that shortened eligibility to three months instead of a year, which is allowed by federal rules.</p>
        <p>Applications take an average of five hours and two visits, Agriculture Department figures show, and the benefit, only $73 a month per person on average, can be as low as $10. Ninety percent of households getting food stamps have income under the poverty line, or $14,150 for a family of three. Three-quarters have no countable assets. A typical family of three leaving the welfare rolls has an annual income of $11,500, according to one study, and qualifies for just under $150 a month in food stamps.</p>
        <p>Though many longer applications include questions relating to cash assistance and medical benefits, a recent study in Western and Southern states found that 78 percent of those seeking food stamps were not told when they qualified for the other programs.</p>
        <p>Agriculture Department officials are now urging outreach efforts, and this year, for the first time, they are offering modest rewards to states that increase participation. But state administrators see a certain hypocrisy in the new thrust.</p>
        <p>''The only message we have heard for years is accuracy; your error rate is what matters,'' Ann Sessoms, Minnesota's welfare reform manager, said. ''If you miss a plasma donation, if you miss a paper route, the state is held liable.''</p>
        <p>Only last September the Agriculture Department's quality-control arm praised the Tennessee Department of Human Services' ''Project Parking Lot,'' in which Nashville investigators patrol for cars whose blue-book value exceeds the $4,650 limit. They feed the license plate numbers into a computer listing people on the benefit rolls, and have cut off $3 million to $4 million in benefits as a result, according to Larry Evitts, the director of investigations.</p>
        <p>''That's crazy,'' said Stephanie Manning, who oversees a Nashville food pantry that limits aid to three boxes of groceries every six months. ''You can't eat your car.''</p>
        <p>Mike Harris, administrator of food stamps in Nebraska, said the dollar limit on cars, raised only by $150 since Congress set it 20 years ago, shows how states get stuck enforcing obsolete regulations.</p>
        <p>''You know what's happened to the price of cars,'' Mr. Harris said. ''It's like, come on, people!''</p>
        <p>In the latest enforcement trend, 11 states, including New York, Connecticut and New Jersey, either require electronic fingerprinting of food-stamp recipients or are planning it. Texas has contracted with computer information brokers who provide, among other tidbits, a listing of 10 neighbors who could be asked about an applicant's circumstances. Delaware pays $2 or $3 an inquiry for credit-card histories on applicants whose answers seem suspicious to a caseworker. Though privacy laws make it illegal to use credit information in a criminal case, William Garfinkel, director of audit at the Delaware Department of Health and Social Services, said that nothing barred using it to determine government benefits.</p>
        <p>''They count everything,'' Anna Santana, a divorced bookkeeper in Lincoln, Neb., said, citing a $25 gift certificate from her church for her three children's Christmas presents.</p>
        <p>Before qualifying for food stamps, she added, there were times when she fed them first, and ate only if they left something. But her older daughter, then 5, caught on.</p>
        <p>''She started cutting back on what she was eating,'' Ms. Santana recalled. '' 'I'm not hungry, Mommy, you need to eat, too.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Glickman said some state actions seemed overzealous, Congressional mandates notwithstanding. ''The irony here is that we don't ask farmers to do anything like we do our food-stamp recipients,'' he added, referring to federal farm subsidies.</p>
        <p>A few states stand out in the study as exceptions. Indiana, for example, has a two-page application that does not ask about burial plots, bingo or blood products. Federal audits last year found fewer mistakes in its calculations of benefits than in those of California, which squeezes 120 questions onto 21 pages. Indeed, the study found that there was no correlation at all between the length of a state's application and the accuracy of its payments.</p>
        <p>''Some states have shown a lot of good judgment and simplicity in complying with the requirements,'' Mr. Glickman said. ''Other states have gone down a much more complicated route. Our job is to try to help all the states run a simpler system.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
