<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clemens's New Deal Is Most Unusual</title>
    <meta content="12CLEM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clemens, Roger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E6DE123FF931A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clemens's New Deal Is Most Unusual</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>ANAHEIM, Calif., Aug. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses New York Yankees pitcher Roger Clemens's contract (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roger Clemens will sign an unusual multiyear contract extension that obligates him to play two years for the Yankees, for $30.9 million, and perhaps allows both sides to address peripheral issues.</p>
        <p>''We're very excited to lock up one of the greatest pitchers in baseball history,'' said Brian Cashman, the Yankees' general manager.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Roger Clemens will sign an unusual multiyear contract extension that obligates him to play two years for the Yankees, for $30.9 million, and perhaps allows both sides to address peripheral issues.</p>
        <p>''We're very excited to lock up one of the greatest pitchers in baseball history,'' said Brian Cashman, the Yankees' general manager.</p>
        <p>Clemens will receive a $5 million signing bonus, to be paid over the next two years, and a salary of $7.8 million in 2001 and in 2002. There is a third-year option for $10.3 million, with a twist. Clemens has the right to accept the option and play for the Yankees. Or he can reject the option and still collect $10.3 million. The Yankees hold a $7.2 million option for a fourth year that contains no guaranteed money.</p>
        <p>In the months that followed the Yankees' acquisition of Clemens in the spring of 1999, his agents and the Yankees reached an understanding on a two-year deal worth between $28 million and $30 million, according to several baseball officials. The two sides negotiated the final terms of the contract in the last three weeks, and the Yankees announced Clemens's contract as a three-year deal.</p>
        <p>With this structure, the annual average value of Clemens's deal is $10.3 million, and the Yankees -- always aware of the perception that they are contributing to baseball's salary escalation -- can say they are giving Clemens a deal worth much less than the $15 million-a-year deal signed by Kevin Brown with the Los Angeles Dodgers two years ago.</p>
        <p>There is nothing stopping Clemens from playing two more years, however, moving to within range of 300 victories -- he currently has 256 -- and then declining to play for the Yankees in 2003, and earning the $10.3 million anyway. He could then seek a new contract for 2003, with the Yankees or elsewhere.</p>
        <p>If Clemens were to play for the Yankees in 2003 under his new contract, he would effectively be playing for no monetary compensation, because he is guaranteed to make $30.9 million whether he plays two or three years with the Yankees; he would merely be playing to ensure his ties to the Yankee franchise.</p>
        <p>''At this point it looks like it's the final stop,'' Clemens said tonight. ''It's great to know I can stay with a great team.'' Clemens, who would have been eligible to be a free agent after this season, said the new contract has a limited no-trade clause, but said he wasn't sure of the details.</p>
        <p>Clemens, 38, sometimes labored in his first season with the Yankees, going 14-10 with a 4.60 earned run average in the regular season, but finished the year by winning the clinching game of the World Series. He started slowly again this year, and was placed on the disabled list June 10 with a strained groin.</p>
        <p>But since he came back July 2, Clemens has been dominant, winning all five of his decisions. He has made nine starts and allowed 43 hits, 21 walks and 14 earned runs in 56 1/3 innings, for a 2.24 E.R.A., and he has struck out 47. Joe Torre, the Yankee manager, has said he believes Clemens has pitched with more aggressiveness since being activated from the disabled list.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
