<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Drive Gathers Steam To Avert Trial For Pinochet</title>
    <meta content="Y12PINO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221836"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Torture</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chile</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krauss, Clifford</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pinochet, Augusto (Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Torture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EFDB153FF931A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Drive Gathers Steam To Avert Trial For Pinochet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krauss, Clifford</byline>
      <dateline>SANTIAGO, Chile Aug. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gen Augusto Pinochet and his supporters have started campaign to gain support to help him avert trial on charges of kidnapping, murder and torture (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since being stripped of his senatorial immunity on Tuesday, Gen. Augusto Pinochet and supporters have started a campaign to gain support to help him avert a trial on charges of kidnapping, murder and torture.</p>
        <p>The approach represents a shift from what had been a quiet, strictly legalistic defense before the Supreme Court, with lawyers arguing that the former dictator was too frail to instruct his lawyers adequately in a long trial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Since being stripped of his senatorial immunity on Tuesday, Gen. Augusto Pinochet and supporters have started a campaign to gain support to help him avert a trial on charges of kidnapping, murder and torture.</p>
        <p>The approach represents a shift from what had been a quiet, strictly legalistic defense before the Supreme Court, with lawyers arguing that the former dictator was too frail to instruct his lawyers adequately in a long trial.</p>
        <p>The effort, which appears to be orchestrated with conservative politicians, retired military officers and executives, is an attempt to galvanize the support of an estimated 30 percent of the country that still considers General Pinochet a hero whose coup in 1973 overthrew President Salvador Allende Gossens, a Socialist, and saved the country from Communism.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, 60 politicians and other supporters gathered around the general at his house to offer their support in an event that was carefully choreographed for Chilean television cameras. The general, smiling and carefully balancing himself with a cane, spoke for 10 minutes and promised a vigorous defense of his innocence and honor.</p>
        <p>''This is the ultimate obligation that I will assume before my conscience and my family,'' he said. ''I don't ask for anyone to accompany me. But those who want to help me can help me.''</p>
        <p>General Pinochet had kept a low profile since returning here in early March, not voting in the Senate, where he is a member-for-life under a Constitution written during his 17-year rule, or otherwise involving himself overtly in politics. He has stayed home, played with his grandchildren and consulted his lawyers.</p>
        <p>Now he says he is preparing ''a letter to the Chilean people'' that will justify his role in history. It is bound to be a polemic that may galvanize the right and surely outrage the left.</p>
        <p>A poll published this week by the Center of Studies on Contemporary Reality, a research center, indicates that 52 percent of Chileans support the Supreme Court decision to strip his immunity, with 35 percent opposed and the rest giving no opinion.</p>
        <p>Chilean society has been deeply divided on the case since General Pinochet was arrested two years ago in London on a Spanish warrant that sought to try him for a variety of serious criminal charges. Demonstrations have gradually decreased in size and emotion. But Chileans still express concerns that the case could upset the country's stability.</p>
        <p>General Pinochet's new gestures have been accompanied by a more public role in recent days by his wife, Lucia Hiriart, the grand dame of the Chilean right. At a public dinner on Thursday night, Mrs. Pinochet criticized the judicial investigation into her husband's involvement in human rights violations as ''entirely political, unjust and cowardly.''</p>
        <p>''Why didn't they judge him immediately after he left the presidency?'' Mrs. Pinochet asked. ''They waited until now when he is sick, old and without power. Is that just?''</p>
        <p>Commenting on the new campaign, Francisco Javier Cuadra, General Pinochet's chief of staff from 1984 to 1987 and a lawyer, said: ''Until now, the defense has been strictly juridical and in the hands of lawyers. I think from now on his defense will be more political.''</p>
        <p>Conservative business leaders have become more vocal on General Pinochet's behalf, suggesting that the legal proceedings are having negative effects on investment. ''The ruling will not alter Chile's political stability or social peace,'' said Hermann Von Muhlenbrock, president of the Metal Industries Association. ''But it will have an impact on future economic activities and in the decisions of certain investment groups.''</p>
        <p>President Ricardo Lagos, a Socialist who is moderate on economic affairs, has tried to encourage businesses to pump up investment as part of an effort to lift the country from a lingering recession. He has argued that the Pinochet case should have no economic repercussions.</p>
        <p>Judge Juan Guzman, the prosecuting judge in the case, is preparing a list of questions to interrogate General Pinochet. The judge is widely expected to draw up an indictment in October and then order a medical examination to test the general's mental state before a possible trial can begin.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
