<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California Upholds Rule For Pollutionless Car by '03</title>
    <meta content="Y09AUT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/09/national/09AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228984"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollack, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E3DF1139F93AA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California Upholds Rule For Pollutionless Car by '03</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollack, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>SACRAMENTO, Sept. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>California Air Resources Board votes unanimously to keep rule requiring that 10 percent of cars offered for sale in state starting in 2003 emit little or no pollution, goal industry says is unreachable; rule is expected to increase number of electric cars on road by huge amount in state and other states that have opted to follow California's pollution rules (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>California regulators voted today to keep a rule requiring that 10 percent of cars offered for sale in the state starting in 2003 emit little or no pollution, a goal that the industry has said is unreachable.</p>
        <p>The unanimous decision by the California Air Resources Board, which regulates air pollution in the state, is expected to increase the number of electric cars on the road by a huge amount, not only in California but also in New York, Maine, Massachusetts and Vermont, which have opted to follow California pollution rules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>California regulators voted today to keep a rule requiring that 10 percent of cars offered for sale in the state starting in 2003 emit little or no pollution, a goal that the industry has said is unreachable.</p>
        <p>The unanimous decision by the California Air Resources Board, which regulates air pollution in the state, is expected to increase the number of electric cars on the road by a huge amount, not only in California but also in New York, Maine, Massachusetts and Vermont, which have opted to follow California pollution rules.</p>
        <p>Automobile companies have argued strenuously that they cannot sell that many electric cars because such vehicles are too costly and can travel only about 100 miles before the batteries must be recharged, a process that takes several hours.</p>
        <p>The air agency estimates that under the rule upheld today, 22,000 electric cars would have to be sold in California in 2003, 10 times more than the 2,300 now on the road.</p>
        <p>''I think it's a train wreck waiting to happen,'' Samuel A. Leonard, a director of the public policy center at the General Motors Corporation, said of the rule, which he said would produce a minuscule improvement in air quality at tremendous cost.</p>
        <p>But the board, whose 11 members are appointed by the governor, said the rule was needed to cut pollution in the long term.</p>
        <p>''Our future depends on the continuing march to zero-emission vehicles,'' Alan C. Lloyd, the board chairman, said after a day and a half of public hearings here. ''We need to stay the course.''</p>
        <p>Progress toward nonpolluting cars, Mr. Lloyd said, would ''dramatically decrease or stop completely without a clear regulatory signal.''</p>
        <p>Still, the board instructed its staff to consider modifications to the plan to deal with the high costs of electric cars, which the staff estimated to be as much as $20,000 more than equivalent gasoline-powered cars. Automobile executives held out hope that the rule would still be changed by January, when the board is to consider the proposed modifications.</p>
        <p>''The train wreck is still a little bit further down the road and maybe we'll never get to that point,'' said Gloria Bergquist, spokeswoman for the Alliance of Automobile Manufacturers, a group that represents 13 car companies.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Lloyd said it was unlikely that the overall 10 percent goal by 2003 would be changed. It is more likely, agency staff members said, that the staff will look at more subsidies to help make the cars more affordable and desirable.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists hailed today's decision, saying it would prod development of pollution-free cars.</p>
        <p>''I think it is about as strong a statement as you can get,'' said Roland Hwang, co-director of the transportation program at the Union of Concerned Scientists.</p>
        <p>The state has been aggressive in air pollution controls because of the infamous smog problem in Southern California. And because of the huge size of California's car market, the California rules have been instrumental in prodding the automobile industry to develop cleaner vehicles.</p>
        <p>The original rules in 1990 called for 2 percent of the cars for sale in the state to be nonpolluting by 1998, 5 percent by 2001 and 10 percent by 2003, with the program to be reviewed every two years.</p>
        <p>In the previous two reviews in 1996 and 1998, the board removed the deadlines for 1998 and 2001, saying they were impractical. It also relaxed the rule for 2003. For the six largest manufacturers, only 4 percent of the cars offered for sale in 2003 have to have truly no emissions, a standard that can only be met right now by battery-powered electric cars.</p>
        <p>The rest of the 10 percent goal can be met by near-zero-emission vehicles, like extremely clean burning gasoline engines, natural gas engines or combined gasoline-electric hybrid vehicles.</p>
        <p>This year's review, which concluded today, was crucial because it is  probably the last time the rule can be changed before auto companies start designing and manufacturing the 2003 cars.</p>
        <p>Auto companies had hoped for another relaxation of the deadline, but environmentalists said that one more slip could effectively kill the program. They said the companies had not tried hard enough to sell the cars, or had even discouraged sales.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
