<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Venus Williams Outduels Hingis Into Final</title>
    <meta content="09TENN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/09/sports/09TENN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS: U.S. OPEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Venus</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hingis, Martina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davenport, Lindsay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dementieva, Elena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0DE1139F93AA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1332" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Venus Williams Outduels Hingis Into Final</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Venus Williams defeats Martina Hingis and Lindsay Davenport defeats Elena Dementieva to advance to finals of women's singles at US Open tennis championships; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was in the thick of the third-set delirium, and a desperate Venus Williams was churning her sinewy limbs as if they were oars to reach one sideline of the court and then sprint to the other.</p>
        <p>Each lunge produced amazed gasps from the witnesses inside Arthur Ashe Stadium yesterday. Each swashbuckling stab during this crucial ninth game only added to the tension. All the while, a meticulous Martina Hingis kept filling in the corners of the court as if applying a No. 2 pencil to a spreadsheet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was in the thick of the third-set delirium, and a desperate Venus Williams was churning her sinewy limbs as if they were oars to reach one sideline of the court and then sprint to the other.</p>
        <p>Each lunge produced amazed gasps from the witnesses inside Arthur Ashe Stadium yesterday. Each swashbuckling stab during this crucial ninth game only added to the tension. All the while, a meticulous Martina Hingis kept filling in the corners of the court as if applying a No. 2 pencil to a spreadsheet.</p>
        <p>It was a brilliant contrast of style in an unending rally. Finally, as the two grew drunk with fatigue, Williams sent up a shot that arched into the air like a flare from the stranded.</p>
        <p>This was Hingis's grand opening, her chance to get to match point in her semifinal at the United States Open. Trouble was, a bleary-eyed Hingis could not focus on the fuzzy blob.</p>
        <p>''I was looking for the ball,'' Hingis said. ''And I couldn't really see it. I couldn't believe it. I didn't do anything with that shot.''</p>
        <p>Instead of planting an overhead winner, she blocked it back to Williams. And instantly, Williams uncoiled a backhand passing shot down the line. It was 30-all, not 15-40, not the end, yet. A resilient Williams went on to hold her serve. She trailed, 4-5, and then ran off a string of three more games to deflate a crestfallen Hingis, 4-6, 6-3, 7-5.</p>
        <p>Once Hingis cracked her last shot of the match into the net, an almost stunned Williams twirled around the court, and uttered the words, ''Unbelievable, unbelievable.''</p>
        <p>But Richard Williams, the one who hatched his daughter's career from his vivid imagination, missed the end of a match that was so exaggerated in its high level of play, it was more like a tall tale. He did not get to see his daughter's wild advance into today's United States Open final, where she will play Lindsay Davenport, the other semifinalist winner from yesterday.</p>
        <p>He did not get to watch her fight back to win her 25th match in a row and become the second Williams sister in two years -- right after her younger sister, Serena -- to have a chance to grab another Grand Slam title for the family trophy case.</p>
        <p>In the ninth game of the third set, just after Venus Williams plopped a drop shot into the net at 15-15, a visibly rattled Richard Williams left his seat. Approached by reporters in the parking lot, he mumbled a few vulgarities and slipped into a car. At this point, his daughter had scrambled to go ahead, 6-5. So why the hostility, why the departure? Did he really have a business appointment, as one of his associates said, or was he too unsettled to stay by his daughter's side? Venus Williams didn't care.</p>
        <p>''I don't rely on my parents,'' she said. ''I have it all figured out.''</p>
        <p>Hingis thought she did, as well. When she stuck to her blueprint, the slightly built Hingis had the powerful Williams in tangles. Repeatedly, Hingis drilled ground strokes to the center of the court, trying to jam Williams and stunt her wicked windup. Often, that tactic produced unforced errors.</p>
        <p>But Hingis could not put enough depth on every shot, and she was spending too much time stabbing back floaters. With spellbinding accuracy, Williams moved forward and gobbled up the soft returns by ripping swinging forehand volleys into the open court.</p>
        <p>''All my swinging volleys were perfect,'' Williams said. ''Mostly winners, except for maybe one.''</p>
        <p>Williams pounded an amazing 51 winners in the match. But her aggression also produced 47 unforced errors. The more patient Hingis came up with only 13 winners, but had only 23 unforced errors. And there was one more statistical difference. Hingis, who had not double-faulted in her run at the United States Open, maintained that form. Williams struggled and hit five double faults.</p>
        <p>Two of those double faults were especially critical. On serve in the first set, with Hingis ahead by 5-4, Williams crushed a double fault into the net. It was set point. Abruptly, Hingis had the first set under her belt, 6-4. After blasting her way through the second set, Williams had another untimely hiccup on her serve in the third set. Once again, she double faulted on break point. This one gave Hingis a 3-2 lead and a path to the final.</p>
        <p>All Hingis had to do was hold on. If she had, she could have scored one for the meek against the mighty, and put one in the book for her alliance with Davenport against the Williams sisters. On Wednesday, Davenport ruined the possibility of an all-Williams final by eliminating Serena. On Thursday, Hingis congratulated her friend and told her, ''One to go.'' But Hingis could not hold up her end of the deal.</p>
        <p>''I heard Serena say the players don't want an all-Williams final because they don't like us,'' said Davenport, who survived the unseeded but battle-tough Elena Dementieva, 6-2, 7-6 (5), earlier yesterday afternoon. ''The players don't want it because they want to be in the finals. I don't want to see an all-Williams final when I feel I should be there.'' Obviously, Martina feels the same way.</p>
        <p>''We're not like sisters. We don't feel like we're ganging up on them or anything like that. We just have a nice relationship and get along well.''</p>
        <p>Venus Williams dismissed all the tag-team hubbub, and said, ''These days, it's like W.W.F. Wrestling.''</p>
        <p>But yesterday, her rivalry with Hingis was true theater. There was nothing phony or scripted about it; the match provided pure competition between two beautifully different players. Around every point, there was an unthinkable stroke, an unpredictable end to a point.</p>
        <p>In the ninth game of the third set, during the rally of Williams's career, all of the above unfolded. There was that helpless lob, just sitting there for Hingis to put away.</p>
        <p>''That was a long rally, a lot of running back and forth,'' Hingis said. ''Then you get an overhead. It's not easy. It looks so easy. But you miss it because you lose your balance. I was like, 'Don't miss it.' ''</p>
        <p>That is exactly what she did. Once Hingis failed to put the point away, Williams planted the winner that turned the game around.</p>
        <p>''I've gotten to have a pretty big heart these days,'' Williams said. ''I really didn't want to lose. I felt like I deserve to be in the finals. I needed to get it done.''</p>
        <p>MATCH POINTS</p>
        <p>This has been a big week for the Australian heartthrob LLEYTON HEWITT. Not only will he play PETE SAMPRAS in the semifinals today, but Hewitt and MAX MIRNYI, an unseeded team, also fought off the fourth-seeded ELLIS FERREIRA and RICK LEACH to take the United States Open doubles title, 6-4, 5-7, 7-6 (5). ''It's fantastic to have won my first Grand Slam title,'' Hewitt said. In the second round, Hewitt and Mirnyi upset TODD WOODBRIDGE and MARK WOODFORDE on their way to an improbable championship.</p>
        <p>TENNIS: U.S. OPEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
