<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Martin's Sprained Knee Could Slow Jets' Offense</title>
    <meta content="09JETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/09/sports/09JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Curtis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E0D71039F93AA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Martin's Sprained Knee Could Slow Jets' Offense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Sept. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>martin's sprained knee could slow jets' offense**Status of New York Jets running back Curtis Martin's sprained knee discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Curtis Martin remained stashed in the trainer's room today, away from prying eyes, his sprained left knee receiving treatment until the final moments before practice.</p>
        <p>Martin, the workhorse running back who is expected to provide much of the Jets' offense this season, has not gone full tilt in practice this week. He returned to the full practice today and was on schedule to play Monday night against New England. Coach Al Groh has acted as if he barely noticed that Martin was hurt, claiming as recently as Thursday that he had not even inquired about his star runner's health.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Curtis Martin remained stashed in the trainer's room today, away from prying eyes, his sprained left knee receiving treatment until the final moments before practice.</p>
        <p>Martin, the workhorse running back who is expected to provide much of the Jets' offense this season, has not gone full tilt in practice this week. He returned to the full practice today and was on schedule to play Monday night against New England. Coach Al Groh has acted as if he barely noticed that Martin was hurt, claiming as recently as Thursday that he had not even inquired about his star runner's health.</p>
        <p>''It's going to take more than a little knee sprain to keep him out of the game,'' center Kevin Mawae said of Martin. ''He's better at half speed than most guys in the league at full speed.''</p>
        <p>Martin sustained the sprain late in the second quarter of last Sunday's game in Green Bay, after a superb first half in which he rushed 18 times for 74 yards and caught three passes for 21 yards. With his knee wrapped, Martin slowed considerably in the second half, rushing 12 times for 36 yards and catching three passes for 13 yards. More alarming was that Bernie Parmalee, who missed much of training camp with a foot injury, looked listless in one series while Martin was on the bench. Parmalee lost a yard on his only rushing attempt and had two receptions for 10 yards.</p>
        <p>''There's a different perspective the coach has on a player in a circumstance Bernie was in, as opposed to the medical people,'' Groh said. ''The medical people are trying to get a player healthy for the first game. From a coach's perspective, there's a difference between healthy and ready. Players who miss a lot of camp, their readiness still is not what it would have been.''</p>
        <p>The Jets worked Parmalee, Jerald Sowell and Richie Anderson at running back this week in practice, but Groh said he had not decided who would fill in if Martin needs a rest against the Patriots at Giants Stadium.</p>
        <p>The Jets had looked around the National Football League before the start of the season in hopes of acquiring an experienced, top-flight running back. At one point, Bill Parcells, the director of football operations, said the Jets had some interest in the Redskins' Skip Hicks, a third-year back who rushed for 690 yards and 11 touchdowns in his first two seasons, primarily as a backup. But Groh said the Redskins had little interest in a deal and that his interest in bringing in a new back, who would have to learn the Jets' pass-protection schemes, has cooled. Mostly, though, Groh said the field of available backs was not enticing.</p>
        <p>''We talked about it and the reason we didn't do it is we couldn't find any,'' Groh said. ''Unless we were to find a top player -- I don't mean he has to be Eddie George -- but a pretty good player, and where are you going to find one of those? I think players we already have on our roster will do more for us than somebody we'd pick up on the outside.''</p>
        <p>Questions about Martin's durability are particularly pertinent this season because, after rushing for 1,464 yards last season, Martin has said he wants to carry more of the load. He wants to catch the ball out of the backfield to help make up for some of the receptions lost when wide receiver Keyshawn Johnson was traded to Tampa Bay. Martin touched the ball 36 times last Sunday, and even he said he had been surprised by how much work he got.</p>
        <p>But Martin has proved his toughness before. He was hampered by lingering leg injuries throughout the 1998 season, in which he rushed for 1,287 yards on 369 runs and caught 43 passes for 365 yards. Quarterback Vinny Testaverde said Martin had an unusual ability to ignore pain when he has to perform.</p>
        <p>''I don't worry about Curtis,'' Testaverde said. ''Once he decides that he's going to play, he'll block out anything that's bothering him. He played an awfully long time with the knee banged up and he played well. Once he makes up his mind, he's focused on his job and nothing else hinders him from doing his job.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Coach AL GROH said there was a good chance that if the new acquisition DAMON DUNN sees action Monday, it will be on both kickoff and punt returns. Dunn would replace DEDRIC WARD on punt returns and would take the place of either AARON GLENN or the rookie LAVERANUES COLES on kickoff returns. . . . Groh is not pleased with the work of kicker JOHN HALL, who missed field-goal attempts of 48 and 52 yards and who had all five of his kickoffs returned last Sunday in the Jets' 20-16 victory at Green Bay, for a total of 116 yards.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
