<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Politics Without Piety</title>
    <meta content="09WHEA$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/09/opinion/09WHEA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228965"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wheatcroft, Geoffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E3D81039F93AA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Politics Without Piety</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Geoffrey Wheatcroft</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wheatcroft, Geoffrey</byline>
      <dateline>BATH, England</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Geoffrey Wheatcroft Op-Ed article holds Europeans are puzzled by role of religion in American presidential race in light of collapse of organized Christianity across Europe; questions Sen Joseph I Lieberman's stress on religion (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Across the Atlantic, the role of religion in the American presidential race has been followed with a mixture of interest and polite puzzlement. What Europeans find so striking is not that there is a Jewish vice presidential candidate, but that Joseph Lieberman wears his piety on his sleeve, just like other American politicians of recent years.</p>
        <p>Nothing so vividly illustrates the gulf between America and Europe. After all, a Jewish leader is not new for Europe. France had a Jewish prime minister in 1936, England in 1868, and Spain, of all countries, in 1835, but none of them -- Leon Blum, Benjamin Disraeli or Juan Alvarez Mendizabal -- were devoutly observant, as Mr. Lieberman is. Indeed, Disraeli had been baptized as an Episcopalian, just like Barry Goldwater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Across the Atlantic, the role of religion in the American presidential race has been followed with a mixture of interest and polite puzzlement. What Europeans find so striking is not that there is a Jewish vice presidential candidate, but that Joseph Lieberman wears his piety on his sleeve, just like other American politicians of recent years.</p>
        <p>Nothing so vividly illustrates the gulf between America and Europe. After all, a Jewish leader is not new for Europe. France had a Jewish prime minister in 1936, England in 1868, and Spain, of all countries, in 1835, but none of them -- Leon Blum, Benjamin Disraeli or Juan Alvarez Mendizabal -- were devoutly observant, as Mr. Lieberman is. Indeed, Disraeli had been baptized as an Episcopalian, just like Barry Goldwater.</p>
        <p>Europe is the cradle of institutional Christianity, but today, institutional religion in Europe is on the point of collapse. Fewer than one French person in 10 goes to church even once a year, and the Roman Catholic church has never been less influential in the life of the nation.</p>
        <p>In my country, we have a Church of England ''by law established,'' with the queen as its supreme governor. And its services are now regularly attended by a mere 2 percent of the population. So it goes across Europe; the collapse of organized Christianity, for better or worse, can be seen from Ireland to Italy.</p>
        <p>Of the advanced industrial world, only in the United States does religion thrive. Polls have shown that a remarkable 40 percent of Americans claim to worship in various churches, synagogues and mosques.</p>
        <p>This gulf is reflected in politics on either side of the Atlantic. European politicians invoke God rarely if at all, and not many of them even pretend to be personally devout. Tony Blair is a pious High Episcopalian who often goes to Mass with his Catholic wife, but he is an exception. Indeed, only a minority of British prime ministers in the 20th century could be called Christians in any serious sense. Winston Churchill, for example, went to church on formal occasions, but was privately agnostic.</p>
        <p>Even in the days when European statesmen were more often privately inspired by faith, as Gladstone and Bismarck were in their different ways, they did not parade their religious devotion, as this year's presidential candidates have all felt obliged to do. The only one who didn't was Bill Bradley, and look where it got him.</p>
        <p>There was a time when an American politician could have publicly echoed the Italian nationalist Cavour's phrase about ''a free church in a free state.'' He might even have privately agreed with H. L. Mencken that you respect the other guy's religious faith in the way you respect his belief that his wife is beautiful and his kids are smart.</p>
        <p>No longer. Today, Mr. Lieberman continually calls on the Almighty and asserts that religion is the only true basis for morality, a claim that makes us very uneasy here. George W. Bush excites derision among English commentators when he says God is his favorite philosopher, and so does Al Gore when he says he asks himself, ''What would Jesus do?''</p>
        <p>What indeed? What would Jesus  do about the budget surplus, China trade or Sierra Leone? The gospels provide remarkably little guidance about practical conduct, certainly not in military or economic matters.</p>
        <p>No doubt European bafflement at American religiosity has overtones of condescension toward American cultural ''backwardness,'' a condescension that often thinly conceals envy and resentment. But in this case, the cynical Old World may have a point.</p>
        <p>Instead of preaching, Mr. Lieberman could simply say, ''I take my religion from the Torah and my politics from America.'' He could recognize that plenty of unbelievers lead highly moral lives and that some religious people don't. He might reflect on what his people went through in vehemently religious societies. He might note that his political career, like those of Disraeli and Blum, has benefited from the defeat of political sectarianism.</p>
        <p>And instead of saying that ''I'm going to keep doing what I'm doing because I believe it's the American way,'' he could acknowledge that the free exercise of religion is truly part of the American way -- and one of the blessings of a free, open and secular society.</p>
        <p>Geoffrey Wheatcroft is the author of ''The Controversy of Zion: Jewish Nationalism, the Jewish State and the Unresolved Jewish Dilemma.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Geoffrey Wheatcroft is the author of ''The Controversy of Zion: Jewish Nationalism, the Jewish State and the Unresolved Jewish Dilemma.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
