<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y09CAM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/09/politics/09CAMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E0DD1139F93AA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="894" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by B. Drummond Ayres Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE STATES</p>
        <p>RULING OUT BALLOT MEASURE  The Arizona Supreme Court says that a November ballot initiative that would have abolished the state's income tax is unconstitutional and must be stricken from the ballot. The court ruled Thursday without comment on the measure, Proposition 107, which would have phased out income taxes and required voter approval of any new taxes and fees. It also would have provided for identification on future ballots of all candidates for federal office who pledged to eliminate the federal income tax. A written court order on the ruling is to be handed down later. Opponents of the measure contended that it would have violated the requirement that amendments to the state constitution cover only a single subject. They also warned that the measure would have resulted in cutbacks in services from education to prisons.</p>
        <p>Todd S. Purdum (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE STATES</p>
        <p>RULING OUT BALLOT MEASURE  The Arizona Supreme Court says that a November ballot initiative that would have abolished the state's income tax is unconstitutional and must be stricken from the ballot. The court ruled Thursday without comment on the measure, Proposition 107, which would have phased out income taxes and required voter approval of any new taxes and fees. It also would have provided for identification on future ballots of all candidates for federal office who pledged to eliminate the federal income tax. A written court order on the ruling is to be handed down later. Opponents of the measure contended that it would have violated the requirement that amendments to the state constitution cover only a single subject. They also warned that the measure would have resulted in cutbacks in services from education to prisons.</p>
        <p>Todd S. Purdum (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS</p>
        <p>MORE MEDIA FOR BUSH  George W. Bush has agreed to permit media coverage whenever he is campaigning, as requested by 11 news organizations, including The New York Times, in a letter asking him to follow the practice of Al Gore and previous presidential nominees. Karen P. Hughes, Mr. Bush's communications director, said yesterday that the Texas governor decided to allow the expanded pool coverage except when he moved around Austin or went to his ranch in Crawford, Tex., or elsewhere in the state. Vice President Gore allows pool coverage when he travels, but does not routinely have such coverage in Washington, Ms. Hughes noted. She said Mr. Bush made the decision on Wednesday, before receiving a letter for news organizations. A pool is a small group of reporters and photographers selected to represent the rest of the traveling press corps.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>THE REFORM PARTY</p>
        <p>DECISION FAVORS BUCHANAN  Patrick J. Buchanan moved a step closer toward the $12.6 million in federal campaign funds awaiting the Reform Party's presidential candidate when the audit staff of the Federal Election Commission recommended to the six commissioners that he, not his rival, John Hagelin, get the money. The matter now goes before the commissioners at a public meeting on Tuesday. But even then, the loser has the right to ask the commission to reconsider, a process that could take as long as 15 days. Distribution of the money could be delayed further if the loser took the decision into federal court, as Mr. Hagelin said he intended to do.</p>
        <p>Michael Janofsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE GREEN PARTY</p>
        <p>NADER MARIJUANA  Ralph Nader, the Green Party presidential nominee, spoke out yesterday for the legalization of marijuana and an overhaul of ''self-defeating'' drug laws. Mr. Nader joined Gov. Gary E. Johnson of New Mexico, a Republican, in criticizing the war on drugs as a failure at a news conference in Santa Fe. ''Addiction should never be treated as a crime,'' Mr. Nader said. ''It has to be treated as a health problem.''</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
