<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>East Timor Athletes Enjoy Independence</title>
    <meta content="09TIMO$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/09/sports/09TIMO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229022"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">East Timor</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/East Timor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/East Timor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E2DC1139F93AA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="829" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>East Timor Athletes Enjoy Independence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on East Timor athletes preparing for Sydney Olympics; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the starting line, not the finish line, that once seemed beyond the reach of Aguida Amaral in the Olympic marathon. A year ago, she did not even have shoes, much less hope, to participate in the Summer Games.</p>
        <p>In August 1999, her island, East Timor, declared its autonomy from Indonesia, sparking a violent retaliation by militia seeking to prevent independence. Amaral joined hundreds of thousands who fled Dili, the capital of East Timor, and when she returned three weeks later under the protection of United Nations peacekeepers, her home had been looted and burned, as had countless other buildings and government offices. Her running shoes were charred, unusable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was the starting line, not the finish line, that once seemed beyond the reach of Aguida Amaral in the Olympic marathon. A year ago, she did not even have shoes, much less hope, to participate in the Summer Games.</p>
        <p>In August 1999, her island, East Timor, declared its autonomy from Indonesia, sparking a violent retaliation by militia seeking to prevent independence. Amaral joined hundreds of thousands who fled Dili, the capital of East Timor, and when she returned three weeks later under the protection of United Nations peacekeepers, her home had been looted and burned, as had countless other buildings and government offices. Her running shoes were charred, unusable.</p>
        <p>For months, Amaral continued to train in her bare feet, or in street shoes, with a desperate resolve. When her feet began to hurt, she ran on the soft sand of the beaches. Running was the one possession that had not been taken from her.</p>
        <p>''I was proud of my running,'' Amaral, 25, said. ''It was my hobby. That's why I continued.''</p>
        <p>Her persistence resulted in her being chosen as one of four athletes from East Timor to compete in the Sydney Games. Because the former province is still run by the United Nations and has no independent government, the athletes will compete as individuals, not as a national team. They will wear white uniforms and march behind the interlocking rings of the Olympic flag during the opening ceremony next Friday.</p>
        <p>The United Nations secretary general, Kofi Annan, and the Australian government persuaded the International Olympic Committee to make a special allowance for the athletes from East Timor -- two marathon runners, a boxer and a weight lifter -- to participate in the Games.</p>
        <p>Kevan Gosper, an I.O.C. delegate from Australia, has taken particular interest in the East Timor athletes. In June he traveled to Dili, asked the barefoot Amaral to stand on a white sheet of paper and traced the outline of her feet with a red felt pen. Gosper then folded the piece of paper in his briefcase and returned to Australia.</p>
        <p>''Shortly thereafter, a pair of running shoes appeared,'' said Frank Fowlie, a U.N. administrator, who is the leader of East Timor's Olympic group.</p>
        <p>The unlikely East Timor story is one of athletic perseverance and international brotherhood. It recalls the lofty ideals of an Olympic movement tarnished lately by scandals involving corruption and the use of performance-enhancing drugs. Even Gosper had been widely criticized earlier this year for securing for his daughter a preferred place in the Olympic torch relay.</p>
        <p>''None of these athletes has a chance to win a medal, but they will go home the richest athletes in what they gained, in what they were able to accomplish here,'' Fowlie said.</p>
        <p>A former Portuguese colony with 800,000 residents, East Timor was invaded by Indonesia in 1975 and annexed. When pro-Jakarta militia reacted violently to last year's vote for independence, Victor Ramos, a lightweight boxer, fled into the hills with his parents and his brothers and sisters, carrying a 130-pound sack of rice. The family made makeshift tents from the leaves of trees and foraged for fruits and vegetables to supplement everyone's meager diet.</p>
        <p>Last Sept. 11, with 20,000 other refugees as an informal wedding party, Ramos, who is 30, married Domingues in the hills above Dili. But when they returned home, he found that the boxing club where he trained had been gutted, and all the equipment had been destroyed. Ramos, who won a bronze medal at the 1997 Southeast Asia Games, was left to fashion his own equipment, making punching bags from inner tubes stuffed with sand.</p>
        <p>Martinho de Araujo, a weight lifter, also fled Dili during the violence. When he returned, his equipment, too, was unusable. In need of barbells to train, he improvised with metal rods stuck into paint cans that had been filled with cement. Anything came in handy -- scrap metal, parts from a truck transmission. Now, he is a week from his first international competition.</p>
        <p>Calisto da Costa will compete in the men's marathon. With a personal best of 2 hours 34 minutes, he has virtually no chance of winning. It is enough to be here.</p>
        <p>It is the same for Amaral in the women's marathon. She has never even heard of Tegla Loroupe, the world record-holder from Kenya and the Olympic favorite. Amaral has run only one race as long as 26.2 miles. Her time was 3:15, nearly an hour slower than Loroupe's best time. But that does not matter.</p>
        <p>''I know that if I try hard, I will get to the finish line,'' Amaral said.</p>
        <p>Getting to the starting line on Sept. 24 will be an equally impressive accomplishment. ''We want to tell the world that we are able to do it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
