<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sorry, Mother, But Get in Line For Your Money; Suit Says Steinberg Sons Failed to Repay Loans</title>
    <meta content="09STEI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/09/nyregion/09STEI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000923T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Reliance Group Holdings Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eaton, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinberg, Saul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinberg, Anne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinberg, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EEDB1139F93AA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1176" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sorry, Mother, But Get in Line For Your Money; Suit Says Steinberg Sons Failed to Repay Loans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE EATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eaton, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Saul Steinberg, whose insurance company Reliance Group Holdings is on brink of bankruptcy, is being sued by his mother for millions of dollars that she lent him; Anne Steinberg has filed suit in NYS Supreme Court in Manhattan demanding that her son repay almost $5 million that she says he borrowed from her; she also sues her son Robert for $1.5 million in debt that she contends came due in December; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is no secret that times are tough in the once-gilded world of Saul P. Steinberg, the portly plutocrat who with his third wife, Gayfryd, personified a 1980's sort of excess. After all, they sold the contents of their living room at public auction in May, and the insurance company that provided their lavish standard of living is on the brink of bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>But who would have guessed that things could come to such a pass: Saul Steinberg's mother says he owes her millions of dollars. And she is suing for it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is no secret that times are tough in the once-gilded world of Saul P. Steinberg, the portly plutocrat who with his third wife, Gayfryd, personified a 1980's sort of excess. After all, they sold the contents of their living room at public auction in May, and the insurance company that provided their lavish standard of living is on the brink of bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>But who would have guessed that things could come to such a pass: Saul Steinberg's mother says he owes her millions of dollars. And she is suing for it.</p>
        <p>Anne Steinberg, who bore Mr. Steinberg back in 1939, filed a lawsuit on Thursday in State Supreme Court in Manhattan, demanding that her son repay almost $5 million that she says he borrowed from her in 1997 and promised to repay on Dec. 31, 1999.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Steinberg also sued her son Robert, who for many years worked with Saul, for $1.5 million, a debt that also came due in December. Robert has failed to make his last two interest payments on the loan, according to letters filed in the case.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit was first reported yesterday by Bloomberg News.</p>
        <p>Mitchell P. Hurley, the lawyer representing Mrs. Steinberg, 83, would not  comment on the lawsuit or provide any information about his client, who unlike her son has not sought the spotlight. No one answered the telephone last night at Mrs. Steinberg's home in Palm Beach, Fla.</p>
        <p>But a letter from one of her lawyers to her sons' lawyer suggests that Mrs. Steinberg is worried about going broke. Her sole sources of income, according to the letter, which is part of the court filings, are the payments on the two loans and dividends from the stock of Reliance Group Holdings, the company Saul Steinberg founded in 1961.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately for her, Reliance stopped paying dividends this year. And the stock, which in December was worth almost $8 a share, now trades for less than 25 cents.</p>
        <p>Marvin J. Goldstein, the lawyer for the Steinberg sons, would not comment on the lawsuit; and neither, through a spokesman, would Saul, Robert or Reliance Group.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit is the latest twist in a tale worthy of Dickens -- or at least of the television show ''Dynasty.'' For the Steinberg clan has long been intimately involved in the affairs of Reliance, which was basically run as a family business even though it had public shareholders.</p>
        <p>The original family business was the Ideal Rubber Company of Brooklyn, which Saul's father, Julius, became president of in 1947 and where Saul worked after he graduated from the Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania. (At night, Saul tended a chain of subway newsstands.)</p>
        <p>When Saul was just 22, he started a company called Leasco, which leased out computers in the days when they were huge and hugely expensive.</p>
        <p>When the company went public in 1965, it and Mr. Steinberg became darlings on Wall Street, which was then in the throes of a stock market mania similar to the recent passion for technology stocks.</p>
        <p>Using his hot stock, Mr. Steinberg took over an insurance company called Reliance. And he began to announce other takeover efforts, aimed at companies including Chemical Bank, The New York Times and Disney, which paid him $60 million to go away. Critics called him a pioneer of ''greenmail.''</p>
        <p>Throughout it all, his family was by his side. Julius Steinberg was involved in founding Leasco, according to his obituary, and became an executive and director of Reliance. Saul's brother-in-law worked at Reliance and Robert Steinberg was, until November, president of Reliance. Mr. Steinberg's company also made a major investment in a financial magazine, Individual Investor, edited by his son, Jonathan.</p>
        <p>Members of the Steinberg family got big loans from Reliance, and also benefited from the unusually high dividends the company paid, even when it was not earning much money. (At one point members of the family owned about three-quarters of the stock; today, they control less than half.) The Steinberg brothers received multimillion-dollar salaries.</p>
        <p>Little is known about Anne Steinberg, other than that she was the wife of Julius Steinberg, and mother of Saul, Robert and two daughters, Roni Sokoloff and Lynda Jurist.</p>
        <p>When her husband died in 1978, Mrs. Steinberg became a trustee of four trusts that at the end of last year owned more than five million shares of Reliance stock. But the Steinbergs had a habit of borrowing against their stock, and in May, a Cincinnati bank announced it had sold more than a million shares of stock the trust had used to secure a loan.</p>
        <p>Few people outside of the insurance and investment worlds would care much about the Steinberg saga were it not that Mr. Steinberg and his wife successfully stormed New York high society in the 1980's. Their 34-room Park Avenue apartment was the setting for many lavish parties, at which guests were said to be astonished both by the red-and-gold color scheme in the living room and by Mr. Steinberg's large collection of paintings by the old masters.</p>
        <p>The wedding of Mr. Steinberg's daughter, Laura, to Jonathan Tisch, himself the child of a fabulously wealthy New York family, was the subject of breathless prose in all sorts of publications, as was the reception for 500 people at the Metropolitan Museum of Art. And who could forget Mr. Steinberg's 50th-birthday party, reported to cost $1 million, at which models posed as figures from his favorite paintings?</p>
        <p>The Steinbergs were also generous donors to schools and medical institutions, though his children's prep school once sued him -- and won --  for failing to make good on a $375,000 pledge.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Steinberg suffered a stroke in 1995, he and his wife retired somewhat from the social scene (which in any event is no longer as flamboyant as it was even a decade ago). The marriage of Mr. Steinberg's son, Jonathan, to Maria Bartiromo, a financial reporter and television personality, was held privately at the Steinbergs' home in Quogue, on Long Island.</p>
        <p>About a year ago, Reliance itself began to crumble.</p>
        <p>The company was heavily in debt (and poorly managed, some critics said), and it was caught up in a scandal involving insurance for workers' compensation. A company that stepped in to buy Reliance backed out this summer, suggesting to analysts that Reliance's problems were deeper than they appeared.</p>
        <p>The Steinbergs have been raising money by selling their assets; the stupendous penthouse apartment on Park Avenue went for about $35 million, the furnishings for $12 million. And they have been selling Reliance shares, too.</p>
        <p>But that may not be enough to satisfy their creditors, up to and including Mom.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 23, 2000, Saturday  An article on Sept. 9 about a lawsuit filed by Anne Steinberg against her son, the financier Saul Steinberg of Reliance Group Holdings, gave a misspelled name in some copies for the company he founded early in his career. It was Leasco, not Leaseco.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 23, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Sept. 9 about a lawsuit filed by Anne Steinberg against her son, the financier Saul Steinberg of Reliance Group Holdings, gave a misspelled name in some copies for the company he founded early in his career. It was Leasco, not Leaseco.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
