<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clemens Dismantles Red Sox With a Revitalized Fastball</title>
    <meta content="09YANK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/09/sports/09YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EFDB1139F93AA3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1095" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clemens Dismantles Red Sox With a Revitalized Fastball</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Sept. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Boston Red Sox, 4-0; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 122nd and final pitch thrown by Roger Clemens tonight was a 96 mile-an-hour fastball, and when Carl Everett swung and missed, Clemens glared briefly at the Red Sox center fielder before strolling toward the Yankees' dugout. Somebody should have rolled out a carpet in his path.</p>
        <p>Clemens descended the steps, accepting congratulations, and some of the Yankees sensed that for the first time, Clemens allowed himself to enjoy the moment. He had completely overpowered and effectively buried a division rival in a crucial September game, shutting out the Red Sox for eight innings -- and in Fenway Park, where fans who taunted him pitilessly last fall were left to do nothing but murmur. Clemens may be 38, but he is pitching as if he were 24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 122nd and final pitch thrown by Roger Clemens tonight was a 96 mile-an-hour fastball, and when Carl Everett swung and missed, Clemens glared briefly at the Red Sox center fielder before strolling toward the Yankees' dugout. Somebody should have rolled out a carpet in his path.</p>
        <p>Clemens descended the steps, accepting congratulations, and some of the Yankees sensed that for the first time, Clemens allowed himself to enjoy the moment. He had completely overpowered and effectively buried a division rival in a crucial September game, shutting out the Red Sox for eight innings -- and in Fenway Park, where fans who taunted him pitilessly last fall were left to do nothing but murmur. Clemens may be 38, but he is pitching as if he were 24.</p>
        <p>Mariano Rivera threw the final inning as the Yankees beat the Red Sox, 4-0, pushing the Red Sox seven games behind them in the standing, the Yankees' largest lead of the year. David Justice drove in the Yankees' first two runs, Derek Jeter the last two.</p>
        <p>The game was delayed for several minutes in the ninth inning after the Yankees' Ryan Thompson smashed a line drive off the face of Boston pitcher Bryce Florie. With a gash under his right eye and blood pouring from that cut, his nose and his mouth, Florie stepped onto a cart and was taken away for treatment.</p>
        <p>Clemens is 12-6, with 259 career victories. The Red Sox went 0 for 5 with runners in scoring position tonight; in Clemens's 15 starts since June 9, opposing hitters are 9 for 88 (.102) with runners in scoring position. ''He's been like a locomotive,'' said Joe Torre, the Yankees' manager. ''He's gotten stronger and stronger.''</p>
        <p>Late this afternoon, Jorge Posada pulled a white leather glove over his left hand. Then Posada peeled short, wide strips from a roll of white medical tape, wrapping them over the top of the glove, over the knuckle that hinges the hand and thumb. In a few hours, Posada would shove this whole contraption into a catcher's mitt, protection against the impact of Clemens's fastball.</p>
        <p>The Red Sox weren't so fortunate; they could not hide from Clemens's revitalized fastball. His legs and back are healthy, and his fastball was clocked at 98 m.p.h. once tonight, 97 m.p.h. a couple of other times, more consistently at 95 to 96 m.p.h., thumping loudly against Posada's mitt.</p>
        <p>Maybe there was a river of adrenaline pumping through Clemens, rather than just a steady stream, for this was his first game in Boston since the Red Sox hammered him for five runs in two innings in a playoff game here last October, and Fenway fans taunted him mercilessly. Mel Stottlemyre, the Yankees' pitching coach, said it was the worst he had ever seen any player booed in a place where he had once been a star.</p>
        <p>But Torre and Posada and others thought the location of this game was mostly incidental to how he pitched tonight; he has been pitching so well for so long, his last loss occurring in June. Clemens had been so tense before the playoff game last fall, like ''a caged lion,'' Torre said, and before tonight's game he had appeared relaxed, watching the televised tennis match between Venus Williams and Martina Hingis.</p>
        <p>Boston's swings were more like half-swings. Clemens was throwing so hard and when they tried to catch up to his fastball, he sometimes mixed in his split-fingered fastball and they found themselves flailing at pitches in the dirt. ''Unreal,'' Posada said. ''He was unreal.''</p>
        <p>The first real good Red Sox swing came with one out in the third inning, when Lou Merloni smashed a liner to right-center. Center fielder Clay Bellinger dived and missed the ball, which rolled to the wall. Paul O'Neill threw to the cut-off man Derek Jeter, who turned and fired toward third.</p>
        <p>With a good throw, Merloni would have been out easily. But Jeter's throw skipped low and past third baseman Scott Brosius. Clemens, backing up third base, went to his knees awkwardly to intercept the ball before it went into the dugout, knocking it aside and scrambling to pick it up before it trickled down the steps. Clemens's pants were torn over the left knee -- he was breathing hard from the play -- and he summoned Posada and second baseman Chuck Knoblauch to the mound to buy him some time to rest.</p>
        <p>Runner at third, one out. Clemens walked Trot Nixon on five pitches; it was as if Clemens had pitched around him to get to the next hitter, Jose Offerman. ''I turned over a fastball right there, threw a two-seamer and just tried to keep it down,'' Clemens said.</p>
        <p>Offerman chopped it back to the mound, and Clemens turned and threw to second, where Jeter stepped on the bag and fired to first -- an inning-ending double play.</p>
        <p>Each time Clemens throws a fastball, the effort causes his lips to part and he bears his teeth, his mouth guard visible in a menacing grimace. But there was no question Clemens was enjoying himself immensely tonight. He covered first base on a ground ball to Tino Martinez to end the fourth inning, and after crossing the bag and getting the out, Clemens popped the umpire Fieldin Culbreth on the backside with his glove, a genial gesture.</p>
        <p>The Yankees' lead was a fragile 1-0 in the sixth and Clemens allowed a leadoff double to start that inning, but retired the next three batters. He was weary after seven innings, but wanted to stay in for one more, and Stottlemyre, the pitching coach, told him to empty the tank, to expend the rest of his energy.</p>
        <p>He got two outs and Everett came to bat, intent on at least unsettling Clemens, stepping out of the batter's box a couple of times. Clemens  pumped a high fastball with two strikes; Everett swung and missed. Ninety-six miles an hour, at age 38.</p>
        <p>Clemens walked off the mound, Red Sox fans grumbling. You could feel his presence in this park again, Luis Sojo said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
