<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>1956 vs. 2000? It's Deja Vu All Over Again, Except for When It's Not</title>
    <meta content="21HIST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/21/sports/21HIST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Dodgers (Defunct Team)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Glenn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E6DC1E3EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>1956 vs. 2000? It's Deja Vu All Over Again, Except for When It's Not</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Glenn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article compares 1956 Subway World Series between New York Yankees and Brooklyn Dodgers and atmosphere surrounding current World Series between Yankees and New York Mets; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During a desperately contested presidential election, in the media and cultural capital of the world, in a boom town where Broadway theaters were flourishing and entrepreneurs were pioneering a fledgling new video industry, New Yorkers took to the subways to cheer on pennant winners from rival boroughs as they waged World Series war.</p>
        <p>The year, of course, was 1956.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During a desperately contested presidential election, in the media and cultural capital of the world, in a boom town where Broadway theaters were flourishing and entrepreneurs were pioneering a fledgling new video industry, New Yorkers took to the subways to cheer on pennant winners from rival boroughs as they waged World Series war.</p>
        <p>The year, of course, was 1956.</p>
        <p>There are enough similarities between Eisenhower-era Gotham and millennial New York to suggest that the intervening 44 years have been a valley to the peaks that were two Subway Series. In both of these baseball snapshots, New York stands revealed as a pre-eminent world city in its economic, artistic and athletic heyday. Both are times when city residents actually do have good reason to arrogantly assume that they are at the center of the universe.</p>
        <p>And yet, a comparison of today's MetroCard Series with the last subway-token Series finds a chasm separating Ed Sullivan's New York from Regis Philbin's. It's not just that day games have been transformed into night games, that city workers' blue collars have been morphed into white, that suburbanites once desperate to leave are now desperate to score a city co-op, or that a white-skinned town has now become more demographically diverse.</p>
        <p>New York in 1956 was a complex, before-the-economic-deluge city in a complicated time when schoolchildren did hydrogen-bomb duck-and-cover drills under their desks, where blacklisted writers worked under pseudonyms in the era of the silent generation, and where blacks, Hispanics, Asians and women were not encouraged to apply.</p>
        <p>''The cold war was at its zenith, heading toward the 1962 missile crisis, there was the specter of McCarthyism and a nascent civil rights movement,'' said Ken Burns, the documentary film historian.</p>
        <p>The contemporary roster of political and social ills notwithstanding, Mr. Burns and several historians suggest that New York and the nation as a whole confront a more palatable menu of disasters.</p>
        <p>''I think we live in a much simpler, and much calmer, time right now,'' said Mr. Burns, whose nine-episode series, ''Baseball,'' ran on Public Television in 1994. ''The enemies of good history are nostalgia and sentimentality.''</p>
        <p>Some of the other contrasts with 1956 are more obvious. It isn't only that most every male was sporting a fedora in 1956, or that the 15-cent price of a subway ride would be 10 times as much by the millennium. Series fans paid a top price of $10.50 for box seats in 1956 and spent only $2.10 to become bleacher creatures; this year, the ticket-price spread is $50 to $300 in some luxury boxes.</p>
        <p>The pre-suburbanized, pre-television-dominated, pre-automobile-oriented New York of 1956 was the nation's ''leading manufacturing city,'' said Dr. Kenneth T. Jackson, a professor of history at Columbia University, editor of the Encyclopedia of New York City. A premier port city in the pre-container era, New York was where the great liners still docked and the great trains still roared into the terminals.</p>
        <p>Employment was characterized ''by the white male union blue-collar worker,'' said Dr. Mike Wallace, a professor of history at John Jay College and co-author of ''Gotham: A History of New York to 1898,'' which won a Pulitzer Prize for history in 1999. ''Now the labor centerpiece involves white-collar, female, nonunion people of color.''</p>
        <p>During the last Subway Series, New York was a town where neighborhoods, parishes and ethnic communities were much more the center of life. The city's relationship with its baseball gods was also more intimate.</p>
        <p>''The connection between players and fans was more personal and exciting,'' given the localized nature of New York in 1956, said Doris Kearns Goodwin, the historian and political scientist, who was 13 when she avidly followed the last Subway Series.</p>
        <p>Back in that facial-hair-free era when ears were unpierced and tongues were unstudded, many players lived among the folks. In 1956, the Dodger legend Pee Wee Reese occupied a modest brick duplex on Barwell Terrace in Bay Ridge, pitcher Sal Maglie lived in Riverdale and many Yankees occupied an apartment hotel on the Grand Concourse in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>In their heyday, Dodger stars earned something like 10 times the $3,948 yearly average salary of the 1956 working man -- not an inconceivable difference, about $250,000 in today's dollars -- whereas even journeyman players bring down $2 million today.</p>
        <p>If there was more complexity in the tenor of those times, New York baseball in the 1950's seemed comfortingly uncomplicated. There was but one fierce loyalty and that was your family's, your neighborhood's, your borough's, team. Today it is baseball that has the high degree of difficulty, being but one option in a complex menu of sports entertainments. In the bloated new regional Big Apple, home-team allegiances are more shifting and fraught than ever.</p>
        <p>Languishing at the center of the new dynamic are the players themselves, all caught ''in the great celebrity hiding machine,'' as Roger Angell, who has written about baseball for The New Yorker since 1962, put it in an interview. ''Today we look at them with the glazed-over interest that we apply to all celebrities.''</p>
        <p>In contrast, even the 1950's stadiums themselves permitted minor-league intimacy. Gone are the days when fans could see (for free) the great expanse of sacred Yankee Stadium turf from the 161st Street subway platform. Gone are the afternoons when Alan M. Dershowitz, now a Harvard Law School professor, was able to camp out on the roof of his grandmother's house ''and see over the right-field wall at Ebbets.''</p>
        <p>Since phalanxes of rabid Mets and Yankees fans are front and center whenever the video-lights go on, passions today seem deep enough, but they aren't those of 1956. Traditional borough nationalism has attenuated in the decades since baseball was truly America's pastime. And many of both team's fans now come from the suburbs.</p>
        <p>But in the 1950's, ''the team you rooted for was as much a part of your identity as your religion was,'' Ms. Goodwin said.</p>
        <p>Such was the presence of the Dodgers and Yankees in 1956 that it took a significant act of will by neighborhood Benedict Arnolds to avoid rooting for the borough team.</p>
        <p>''Growing up in Brooklyn you were unable not to be a Dodger,'' said Sanford Teller, a Manhattan public-relations consultant who used to take the trolley from Borough Park to Ebbets Field. ''Giant fans were pummeled.''</p>
        <p>In Our Lady of Lourdes parish on the Upper West Side not far from the Polo Grounds, ''it was all Giants,'' said Peter Maas, the Manhattan author, who grew up in the neighborhood and attended the 1956 Series as a reporter for Collier's magazine. ''Ebbets Field seemed to be in the Middle East somewhere. The Yankees were too rich and we saw the Dodgers as an alien force.''</p>
        <p>The exception that proves the rule is that Brooklynite Yankee defector, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>In today's game, Latino fan rivalries are expected to add drama to the battle for New York. In 1956, the Hispanic player presence in the Series was limited, even though there were 650,000 Spanish-speaking residents in the city in 1956, 90 percent of whom were Puerto Rican. (The only Hispanic who played was the Havana-born Dodger Sandy Amoros; there were no Asians.)</p>
        <p>In 1956, ''the Dodgers were the Jewish and Italian and black team,'' according to Mr. Dershowitz, whose synagogue actually gave a blessing to the pitcher Sandy Koufax. ''The Yankees got their own borough, and the WASPs.''</p>
        <p>The borough loyalty of the 1950's may also be a casualty of fans' perception that today's Yankees and Mets are generic collections of hired millionaires.</p>
        <p>Patrick McEnroe, the 34-year-old sportscaster and tennis-league entrepreneur, grew up in Queens, 15 minutes from Shea Stadium, ''but I always rooted for the Yankees, and I knew other kids who did,'' he said. ''Maybe that tells you that there isn't as much identification with the teams, because so many players come and go.''</p>
        <p>New Yorkers may be glued to their pocket color televisions today, but the 1956 Series was a testament to the ubiquity of radio. ''You could walk down the street from house to house and never miss a single play of the game,'' Ms. Goodwin said.</p>
        <p>Though the first color-television sets were sold in 1954 (for $1,000) the 1956 donnybrook was, for the average fan, a black-and-white-screen, tin-foil-on-the-rabbit-ears experience. In a town where innovators were pioneering live television drama and comedy, ''network executive offices weren't worrying that the New York demographics were too insular and parochial for national audience ratings,'' said David Halberstam, author of ''Summer of '49'' and ''October 1964,'' who grew up seven blocks from Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>In autumn classics then, the game-day afternoon was exactly that: a day game. Life in the boroughs was a scene out of ''The Day the Earth Stood Still,'' when everything stopped. But thanks to evening scheduling, many millennial New Yorkers will be spared the crisis of every 1956 baseball Hamlet: to cut school or to call in sick at work?</p>
        <p>If the city of 1956 was an alternate universe, ''it is remarkable that New York has changed less than most other American cities since then,'' Dr. Jackson said. He said that Detroit and St. Louis lost half of their populations during the last four decades, while cities like Cleveland, Buffalo and Baltimore lost nearly a third. New York's population of 7.4 million isn't too much lower than that of 1956, if the number of illegal aliens is factored in.</p>
        <p>''In the '50's, the economy was booming, but people thought that the future was in the suburbs,'' Dr. Jackson said. ''Now there is a sense of energy in the city that is more appealing to young people than the suburbs.''</p>
        <p>But aspects of the lost New York live again. Already, the Series is a political opportunity (with the Republican Senate candidate, Rick A. Lazio, hyping the Mets, and Hillary Rodham Clinton, the Democrat, promoting the Bombers). It isn't the first time. In 1956, President Dwight D. Eisenhower arrived at the first game in an open campaign car and Adlai E. Stevenson, the Democratic nominee, was cheered at the next game.</p>
        <p>Just as writers, painters, photographers, designers, musicians and celebrity chefs have put millennial New York on the cutting edge of innovation, the Dodger-Yankee town was a festival of modern dance experimentation, abstract expressionism, bold Broadway musicals, culinary creativity pioneered by the likes of James Beard, transgressive jazz and doo-wop on the street corners.</p>
        <p>While the 14th Subway Series introduces a new generation to a 79-year-old city tradition, it will surely provoke a rush of memories for New Yorkers older than 50. ''It's feeling a lot like deja vu all over again,'' said Yogi Berra, reprising one of his more celebrated Yogi-isms.</p>
        <p>In the end, maybe the first Subway Series between the Yankees and the Mets is a triumph of continuity and revival for a city rich in both history and baseball. Or maybe it's just another occasion to brag.</p>
        <p>''We purport to be the best, and it's nice to see that actually validated,'' Mr. Maas said. ''The Subway Series is a symbol of New York's renaissance, and it will drive the rest of the country nuts.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
