<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The First 13 Stops</title>
    <meta content="21NYCHART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Dodgers (Defunct Team)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corio, Ray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E5DA1E3EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The First 13 Stops</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY CORIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Corio, Ray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article recalls past Subway Series between New York Yankees and either New York Giants or Brooklyn Dodgers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From 1921 through 1956, more than a third of the World Series played never left New York City. The Yankees won 10 of them, the Giants won 2 and the Dodgers won the other one as well as the hearts of underdogs everywhere.</p>
        <p>RAY CORIO</p>
        <p>'21  GIANTS vs. YANKEES  Giants win series, 5-3  (5 of 9 games)  The Giants had captured six pennants and one World Series. The Yanks' biggest prize was Babe Ruth a year earlier. But the Yankees were outplaying their landlords until Ruth hurt his arm sliding in Game 2. When it became infected, Ruth became ineffective, and the Giants popped the Champagne.  The Series  (teams shared Polo Grounds)  Game 1 Yankees, 3-0  Game 2 Yankees, 3-0  Game 3 Giants, 13-5  Game 4 Giants, 4-2  Game 5 Yankees, 3-1  Game 6 Giants, 8-5  Game 7 Giants, 2-1  Game 8 Giants, 1-0</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From 1921 through 1956, more than a third of the World Series played never left New York City. The Yankees won 10 of them, the Giants won 2 and the Dodgers won the other one as well as the hearts of underdogs everywhere.</p>
        <p>RAY CORIO</p>
        <p>'21  GIANTS vs. YANKEES  Giants win series, 5-3  (5 of 9 games)  The Giants had captured six pennants and one World Series. The Yanks' biggest prize was Babe Ruth a year earlier. But the Yankees were outplaying their landlords until Ruth hurt his arm sliding in Game 2. When it became infected, Ruth became ineffective, and the Giants popped the Champagne.  The Series  (teams shared Polo Grounds)  Game 1 Yankees, 3-0  Game 2 Yankees, 3-0  Game 3 Giants, 13-5  Game 4 Giants, 4-2  Game 5 Yankees, 3-1  Game 6 Giants, 8-5  Game 7 Giants, 2-1  Game 8 Giants, 1-0</p>
        <p>'22  GIANTS vs. YANKEES  Giants win series, 4-0  (plus one tie)  It was the Babe's bat that appeared to be in poor health this time as John McGraw's Giants repeated in a sweep. Ruth went 2 for 17 (.118) with no home runs. For the Giants, second baseman Frankie Frisch (.471) and third baseman Heinie Groh (.474) were Ruth-like, if not ruthless.  The Series  (teams shared Polo Grounds)  Game 1 Giants, 3-2  Game 2 *tied, 3-3  Game 3 Giants, 3-0  Game 4 Giants, 4-3  Game 5 Giants, 5-3  *Called because of darkness</p>
        <p>'23  GIANTS vs. YANKEES  Yankees win series, 4-2  The Giants' victories came at the newly opened Yankee Stadium on home runs by the aging Casey Stengel. He staggered home in Game 1 with an inside-the-park shot in the ninth, and he supplied the only run in Game 3, thumbing his nose while circling the bases. Ruth hit three homers in the series.  The Series  Game 1Y Giants, 5-4  Game 2P Yankees, 4-2  Game 3Y Giants, 1-0  Game 4P Yankees, 8-4  Game 5Y Yankees, 8-1  Game 6P Yankees, 6-4  Y Yankee Stadium  P Polo Grounds</p>
        <p>'36  GIANTS vs. YANKEES  Yankees win series, 4-2''  Ruth was gone, but not Tony Lazzeri, Lou Gehrig and Bill Dickey who were joined by a sensational rookie, Joe DiMaggio. Lazzeri's grand slam in Game 2 bent the Series the Yankees' way after the left-hander Carl Hubbell had Yankee batters bending in futility in the opener.  The Series  Game 1P Giants, 6-1  Game 2P Yankees, 18-4  Game 3Y Yankees, 2-1  Game 4Y Yankees, 5-2  Game 5Y Giants, 5-4  Game 6P Yankees, 13-5</p>
        <p>'37  GIANTS vs. YANKEES  Yankees win series, 4-1  Not even Carl Hubbell could tame the murderous row of Yankee hitters this time. They feasted on the Meal Ticket in the opener, chasing him during a seven-run sixth inning. The Yankees' southpaw counterpart, Lefty Gomez, won two games, including the clincher.  The Series  Game 1Y Yankees, 8-1  Game 2Y Yankees, 8-1  Game 3P Yankees, 5-1  Game 4P Giants, 7-3  Game 5P Yankees, 4-2</p>
        <p>'41  DODGERS vs. YANKEES  Yankees win series, 4-1  When Hugh Casey's pitch got away from catcher Mickey Owen, so did the Series for the Dodgers. Who in Brooklyn can forgot how Owen muffed a game-ending third strike in game 4 that would have evened the Series. Instead, Tommy Henrich reached first base and the Yankees scored four runs.  The Series  Game 1Y Yankees, 3-2  Game 2Y Dodgers, 3-2  Game 3E Yankees, 2-1  Game 4E Yankees, 7-4  Game 5E Yankees, 3-1  Y Yankee Stadium  E Ebbets Field</p>
        <p>'47  DODGERS vs. YANKEES  Yankees win series, 4-3  Cookie Lavagetto ended a no-hit bid by Bill Bevens with a dramatic two-out, game-winning pinch-double in the ninth for a Dodger victory in game 4. Two games later, Al Gionfriddo made a stunning catch of a drive by Joe DiMaggio to save another Dodger victory. Otherwise, it was all Yankees.  The Series  Game 1Y Yankees, 5-3  Game 2Y Yankees, 10-3  Game 3E Dodgers, 9-8  Game 4E Dodgers, 3-2  Game 5E Yankees, 2-1  Game 6Y Dodgers, 8-6  Game 7Y Yankees, 5-2</p>
        <p>'49  DODGERS vs. YANKEES  Yankees win series, 4-1  Allie Reynolds was a 1-0 winner in Game 1 on a walkoff homer by Tommy Henrich against Don Newcombe leading off the ninth. Preacher Roe was a 1-0 winner for the Dodgers in game two. But the Yankees walked off with the next three games behind the stout relief pitching of Joe Page and Reynolds.  The Series  Game 1Y Yankees, 1-0  Game 2Y Dodgers, 1-0  Game 3E Yankees, 4-3  Game 4E Yankees, 6-4  Game 5E Yankees, 10-6</p>
        <p>'51  GIANTS vs. YANKEES  Yankees win series, 4-2  Fresh off a miracle run to the pennant, the underdog Giants kept chugging until a grand slam by rookie Gil McDougald in game five derailed them. Steady pitching by Eddie Lopat and steady hitting by Phil Rizzuto helped get the Yankees back on track.  The Series  Game 1Y Giants, 5-1  Game 2Y Yankees, 3-1  Game 3P Giants, 6-2  Game 4P Yankees, 6-2  Game 5P Yankees, 13-1  Game 6Y Yankees, 4-3  P Polo Grounds</p>
        <p>'52  DODGERS vs. YANKEES  Yankees win series, 4-3  For the Yankees, Allie Reynolds won two games and saved another, while Vic Raschi won his two starts. For the Dodgers, Duke Snider hit four home runs and Gil Hodges went 0 for 21. For the record, Billy Martin's shoestring catch of an infield popup with two out and the bases loaded saved game seven.  The Series  Game 1E Dodgers, 4-2  Game 2E Yankees, 7-1  Game 3Y Dodgers, 5-3  Game 4Y Yankees, 2-0  Game 5Y Dodgers, 6-5  Game 6E Yankees, 3-2  Game 7E Yankees, 4-2</p>
        <p>'53  DODGERS vs. YANKEES  Yankees win series, 4-2  Billy Martin's bat doomed the Dodgers this time. The pugnacious Yankee second baseman went 12 for 24, hit two homers and knocked in eight runs. With his fifth title in five seasons, Casey Stengel earned the right to thumb his nose at all other managers.  The Series  Game 1Y Yankees, 9-5  Game 2Y Yankees, 4-2  Game 3E Dodgers, 3-2  Game 4E Dodgers, 7-3  Game 5E Yankees, 11-7  Game 6Y Yankees, 4-3</p>
        <p>'55  DODGERS vs. YANKEES  Dodgers win series, 4-3  Having missed the boat in five Subway Series against the Yankees, the Dodgers finally won a championship for Brooklyn. The home run hitting of Snider (4 more), a snazzy catch by Sandy Amoros in game seven and two superb outings by Johnny Podres brought smiles from Greenpoint to Canarsie.  The Series  Game 1Y Yankees, 6-5  Game 2Y Yankees, 4-2  Game 3E Dodgers, 8-3  Game 4E Dodgers, 8-5  Game 5E Dodgers, 5-3  Game 6Y Yankees, 5-1  Game 7Y Dodgers, 2-0</p>
        <p>'56  DODGERS vs. YANKEES  Yankees win series, 4-3  In what became the last stop of the century in the Subway Series, Don Larsen pitched a game for the ages. No Dodger reached base in Larsen's perfect game-five effort. Two games later, no Dodger scored as Yogi Berra's two homers backed the three-hit clincher by Johnny Kucks.  The Series  Game 1E Dodgers, 6-3  Game 2E Dodgers, 13-8  Game 3Y Yankees, 5-3  Game 4Y Yankees, 6-2  Game 5Y Yankees, 2-0  Game 6E Dodgers, 1-0  Game 7E Yankees, 9-0</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
