<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Respect for Age in Florida</title>
    <meta content="Y21ELD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/21/politics/21ELDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VOTERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenbaum, David E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Homeland Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EFD6113EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1291" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Respect for Age in Florida</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenbaum, David E</byline>
      <dateline>CLEARWATER, Fla., Oct. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush and Vice Pres Al Gore are running neck and neck in Florida, largest state still in contention with 25 electoral votes; both are hotly pursuing retirees as small shift of votes from age group can mean difference between winning and losing; are unlikely to swing many votes with appeals to seniors on matters like Social Security and Medicare as many show little inclination to vote as bloc based on self interest; elderly voters say Bush and Gore plans for Social Security and Medicare have left them more confused than comforted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pauline Bracken got home last Sunday to find a long message on her answering machine that began: ''Hello, this is Barbara Bush. I'm calling to tell you about my son George W.'s plan to protect Social Security.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Bracken, 70, a retired cigar worker in Tampa who has little other income besides her Social Security checks, said she smiled to herself as she listened and wished that her husband, who died last year, had been around to share a laugh about it. Then she erased the message and went about her business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pauline Bracken got home last Sunday to find a long message on her answering machine that began: ''Hello, this is Barbara Bush. I'm calling to tell you about my son George W.'s plan to protect Social Security.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Bracken, 70, a retired cigar worker in Tampa who has little other income besides her Social Security checks, said she smiled to herself as she listened and wished that her husband, who died last year, had been around to share a laugh about it. Then she erased the message and went about her business.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Bracken's friend Lilly Gatto, 81, said she was home when her call came and hung up after a couple of sentences, as soon as she realized it was a recording. ''I'm a Democrat,'' Mrs. Gatto said. ''Been one all my life, and that's how I'm going to vote this year.''</p>
        <p>The calls from Mrs. Bush -- tens of thousands were made last weekend to older voters across the state -- are but one example of an extravagant effort this year by both parties and the presidential campaigns to woo the votes of the elderly in Florida.</p>
        <p>The reason is clear. With 25 electoral votes, Florida is the largest state still in serious contention, and Gov. George W. Bush and Vice President Al Gore are running neck and neck here.</p>
        <p>In the last election, 42 percent of all Florida voters were older than 60, and a third were older than 65. Even a small shift in votes from this age group could mean the difference between winning and losing the nation's fourth-largest state.</p>
        <p>But the candidates and their campaigns are likely to be disappointed if they think they can swing many votes with appeals to seniors on matters like Social Security and Medicare.</p>
        <p>Three dozen retirees interviewed in the Tampa Bay area this weekend, for example, showed little inclination to vote as a bloc based on their self-interest, and said that the Bush and Gore plans for Social Security and Medicare left them more confused than comforted.</p>
        <p>''Look, we're from New England,'' said Bill Roberts, 66, who moved here from New Hampshire. He was having a beer at an outdoor table after a round of golf with Richard Mikszenas, 68, from Maine, and Leo Kelly, 65, from Boston.</p>
        <p>''Those guys over there,'' Mr. Roberts said, pointing at another table near the 18th green, ''they moved here from the South. There are Jews and Christians, blacks and whites, men and women, drinkers and teetotalers. We're all retired. But we all think differently.''</p>
        <p>One matter the people interviewed all say they have thought long and hard about is the question of Medicare coverage of prescription drugs. They are mostly people of modest means, and even many with insurance have steep out-of-pocket expenses for medicine.</p>
        <p>For instance, Mr. Roberts, who had a refrigeration business in Bow, N.H., said that he had some insurance coverage but paid more than $3,000 out of pocket every year for prescriptions for his wife and himself.</p>
        <p>John Hendrick, 78, who was a federal employee in Cleveland, said he had been paying about $3,000 a year for supplemental insurance and had recently switched to an H.M.O. Now, he said, he pays about $2,000 and most drugs costs are covered.</p>
        <p>But as much as they think and talk about it, the people interviewed cannot see much difference between Mr. Gore's proposal for prescription drug coverage and Mr. Bush's.</p>
        <p>''It's just too complicated to understand,'' said Bill Hinver, 81, a retired machinist from Pittsburgh. ''I mean, Bush has a plan and Gore has a plan. But they're just running for election, and they'll promise you everything and give you nothing.''</p>
        <p>On balance, Mr. Hinver, a committed Republican, said he thought Mr. Bush had a better drug proposal, but he could not explain why.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mikszenas, who worked in production control for General Electric, agreed that Mr. Bush's plan was probably better. But he added, ''It's just too complicated, and I don't pretend to understand it thoroughly.''</p>
        <p>Regardless, Mr. Mikszenas said, he intended to vote for Ralph Nader. He said he had voted for Ross Perot in the last two presidential elections.</p>
        <p>The fact is, there are big philosophical differences between the Gore and Bush drug plans. But it is not surprising that voters are confused, because comparing them line by line is impossible.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore would expand the government's Medicare program so that a drug benefit would be available voluntarily to all older Americans for an additional monthly premium. Mr. Bush would try to induce competition among private insurance companies to sell drug coverage to the elderly, with the government partly subsidizing the premiums.</p>
        <p>But retirees cannot figure which plan would help them more, because Mr. Bush has left many details unspecified, including what his basic benefit would be worth, what the deductibles and co-payments would be and what would happen if the government subsidy in his plan proved to be insufficient to get companies to offer the coverage.</p>
        <p>Academicians who study the voting patterns of the elderly said they were not surprised that those interviewed here were not voting as a monolith.</p>
        <p>''Basically, people don't become homogenized politically once they reach a certain age,'' said Robert Binstock, a professor of aging, health and society at Case Western Reserve University in Cleveland. ''People don't really identify themselves as older people when they make their voting decisions.''</p>
        <p>Still, taken as a group, elderly voters do vote somewhat differently than younger ones do. In Florida, a poll this month by Mason-Dixon Polling and Research found that voters 65 and older favored Mr. Gore, 51 percent to 37 percent. Younger voters favored Mr. Bush by approximately the same margin.</p>
        <p>Nationally, the latest New York Times/CBS News poll found no substantial difference in the presidential preferences of older and younger voters. But in the last three presidential elections, voters 60 and older were somewhat more likely than others to vote for the Democrat.</p>
        <p>There is some evidence that voting patterns of the elderly in Florida and elsewhere are shifting, as those who came of age politically during the Depression and World War II die and those whose political views were formed after the Roosevelt-Truman era retire.</p>
        <p>For example, in the 1998 election for governor here, a majority of voters 60 and older voted for the Republican candidate, Jeb Bush, who was elected, but a majority of those 65 and older voted for his Democratic opponent, Buddy MacKay.</p>
        <p>But when the presidential candidates think about Florida, they do not think about shifting patterns; they think about the raw numbers -- of the millions of votes at stake.</p>
        <p>Using records from driver's licenses, their campaigns have identified almost every elderly person in the state and have flooded them with mail and sent volunteers to knock incessantly at their doors. Household by household, the campaigns are arranging for transportation to the polls and passing out information about absentee ballots.</p>
        <p>''Every ad here has a senior bent to it,'' said Susan MacManus, a political scientist at the University of South Florida who is an authority on the elderly vote.</p>
        <p>Once they have lived in Florida long enough, retirees become inured to the courting. ''At first I was flattered,'' said Beverly Stone, 78, who moved here from Illinois about 15 years ago when her husband retired. ''But no longer. I just want it all to be over. Some days I think that if I see one more politician in an ad on TV, I'll shriek.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VOTERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
