<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abroad at Home; Bob And Weave</title>
    <meta content="21LEWI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/21/opinion/21LEWI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240436"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E7DB113EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abroad at Home; Bob And Weave</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Lewis Op-Ed column pays tribute to Gov George W Bush's campaigning skills that have made him formidable candidate; says key to his success became clear in three debates with Vice Pres Al Gore, in which demonstrated masterful technique of bobbing and weaving around issues that are difficult for him using 'fuzzy rhetoric' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By the ordinary logic of politics, the vice president of an administration that has given us the greatest prosperity in history should be way ahead in this election. That he is not is a tribute to the campaigning skill of George W. Bush. No one can doubt any longer that Mr. Bush is a formidable candidate.</p>
        <p>One key to his success became clear in the three debates with Al Gore. All politicians bob and weave around issues that are difficult for them. Governor Bush is a master of the technique.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By the ordinary logic of politics, the vice president of an administration that has given us the greatest prosperity in history should be way ahead in this election. That he is not is a tribute to the campaigning skill of George W. Bush. No one can doubt any longer that Mr. Bush is a formidable candidate.</p>
        <p>One key to his success became clear in the three debates with Al Gore. All politicians bob and weave around issues that are difficult for them. Governor Bush is a master of the technique.</p>
        <p>When they were debating a patients' bill of rights, for example, and Governor Bush was asked the difference between the candidates, he answered, ''Well, the difference is that I can get it done.'' That ducked the real issue of what the ''it'' was -- what such legislation should include -- and obscured the fact that he did not support the meaningful bill pending in Congress.</p>
        <p>He repeatedly argued that he could make things happen by putting partisanship aside, saying that the Clinton administration had had eight years and not achieved a patients' bill of rights and other things. With that rhetorical device, he blanked out the rabid Republican partisanship that has made Congress a graveyard of legislation and judicial nominations over recent years.</p>
        <p>Asked whether he would support a law barring job discrimination against gays and lesbians, Governor Bush replied, ''I don't hire or fire somebody based upon their sexual orientation.'' That is no doubt true, admirable -- and irrelevant to the question of legislation. As to that, he said gays and lesbians should not have ''special rights'': code words used by those who oppose equal rights legislation.</p>
        <p>His reason for avoiding questions of that kind is plain. Governor Bush's slogan is that he is a ''compassionate conservative,'' so he does not want to look unsympathetic to people who face discrimination or who are treated unfairly by medical insurance companies. But he also does not want to offend the Christian right or the insurance companies.</p>
        <p>Another facet of Governor Bush became evident in the debates. Once he has taken a position designed to fend off criticism, he sticks to it no matter how thoroughly it has been exploded.</p>
        <p>Long before the debates, he sought to stake out a distinct position on foreign and security policy by saying that the U.S. had troops in too many places around the world. ''I believe we're overextended in too many places,'' he said in the first debate.</p>
        <p>In the second debate, asked from which missions he would withdraw, the only thing he came up with was that we should convince ''our European friends to put troops on the ground'' in the Balkans. He was apparently unaware that the Europeans already have troops there: more than we do. There are about 10,000 Americans in a total of 66,000 peacekeepers.</p>
        <p>In the third debate he said again, ''I'm concerned that we're over deployed around the world.'' Undaunted by the facts -- the reality that he would not bring home our large forces in Japan, Korea or the NATO countries -- he stuck with a line that he thought sounded good.</p>
        <p>Another example of that dogged avoidance of reality is capital punishment. In the second debate he answered a question about hate crimes by saying, with seeming pleasure, that three Texas killers of a black man were ''going to be put to death.'' (Actually, only two had been sentenced to death.)</p>
        <p>A questioner in the third debate said Governor Bush ''seemed to overly enjoy'' the fact that Texas led the nation in executions. Mr. Bush said his job in the execution process was ''to ask two questions, sir. Is the person guilty of the crime? And did the person have full access to the courts of law? And I can tell you, looking at you right now, in all cases those questions were answered in the affirmative.''</p>
        <p>That is the position that Governor Bush has consistently taken. It just happens to be untrue. The way Texas provides lawyers for capital defendants is notoriously unfair. People have been convicted and sentenced to death after trials in which their lawyers were drunk or asleep -- and the courts of Texas have found no error in that outrage.</p>
        <p>When faced in the debates with particular facts about problems like Social Security or taxes, Governor Bush scorned them as ''Washington fuzzy math.'' But he is the master of fuzzy rhetoric.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
