<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Missing Chapter in the Bush Bio: A Modest Summer in Alaska</title>
    <meta content="Y21ALA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/21/politics/21ALAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alaska</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Alaska International Industries</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Jo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD8113EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1132" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Missing Chapter in the Bush Bio: A Modest Summer in Alaska</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JO THOMAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Thomas, Jo</byline>
      <dateline>FAIRBANKS, Alaska</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Despite scrutiny applied to Gov George W Bush's life during current presidential election, small chapter has largely escaped attention, namely, modest summer spent in Alaska in 1974 working for Alaska International Industries, airline-and-construction business, during oil-boom days when construction on 800-mile trans-Alaska pipeline was just beginning; Bush has discussed episode with few friends but not biographers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite the scrutiny applied to George W. Bush's life this election season, one small chapter has largely escaped attention. In an episode he has discussed with a few friends but not biographers, Mr. Bush spent the summer of 1974 working for a young airline-and-construction business in Alaska, during the oil-boom days when construction on the 800-mile trans-Alaska pipeline was just beginning.</p>
        <p>Bob Heath, who would bring him here to work in the noisy, chaotic airport offices of the young company, Alaska International Industries, recalls receiving a letter from an executive at a Houston construction company asking about a summer job for Mr. Bush, then 27 and halfway through two years at Harvard Business School.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite the scrutiny applied to George W. Bush's life this election season, one small chapter has largely escaped attention. In an episode he has discussed with a few friends but not biographers, Mr. Bush spent the summer of 1974 working for a young airline-and-construction business in Alaska, during the oil-boom days when construction on the 800-mile trans-Alaska pipeline was just beginning.</p>
        <p>Bob Heath, who would bring him here to work in the noisy, chaotic airport offices of the young company, Alaska International Industries, recalls receiving a letter from an executive at a Houston construction company asking about a summer job for Mr. Bush, then 27 and halfway through two years at Harvard Business School.</p>
        <p>Mr. Heath, who was vice president for finance at Alaska International, says he called the Houston executive with one question: ''Will he work?''</p>
        <p>Assured that Mr. Bush would, Mr. Heath replied, ''Ship him up.''</p>
        <p>''We had never heard of George Bush,'' Mr. Heath said recently.  ''Didn't have a clue.'' But Mr. Bush was a college graduate who had decided to pursue a business career,  ''and we could use all we could get our hands on.''</p>
        <p>The aviation arm of Alaska International had a colorful list of clients, including the Central Intelligence Agency and the shah of Iran. But Mr. Bush knew nothing about them, says Dan Bartlett, whom the Bush presidential campaign has placed in charge of dealing with the press on biographical matters.</p>
        <p>''The only thing he knew the company was doing was flying freight in C-130's to the north Alaskan slope,'' Mr. Bartlett said. ''That is the extent of his knowledge.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, who had been trained as a military pilot in the Texas Air National Guard before enrolling in business school, was given a desk job in the planning department of Alaska International, which was trying to cope with an avalanche of work.</p>
        <p>''As I remember,'' Mr. Heath said,  Mr. Bush ''was a great help in trying to figure out what we were going to be when we grew up. No one understood which move to make next. We were trying to structure the company.''</p>
        <p>What might seem puzzling about Mr. Bush's sojourn in Alaska is that it never comes up. His autobiography does not mention it. Nor do three other biographies of him published recently. Reporters on his campaign plane say they cannot recall his ever mentioning it, and many of his friends say they have never heard him refer to it.</p>
        <p>In his book, Mr. Bush recounts the summers he spent delivering mail at a law firm, working for a stockbroker, roughnecking on an offshore oil rig, helping out on a ranch and selling sporting goods. But there is no mention of Alaska.</p>
        <p>His experience there has now emerged in part because a leaflet that Republicans have circulated in the state on his behalf referred to him as ''a former Alaska resident.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bartlett, the Bush spokesman,  said he did not know why the summer job had not come up before in interviews with the governor.</p>
        <p>''I'm rarely asked about it,'' Mr. Bartlett said, although he did recall a recent query from an Alaska newspaper, The Juneau Empire, which ran a short account about it in September.</p>
        <p>As for why Mr. Bush himself so rarely mentions it, Mr. Bartlett said it was so long ago, so brief and so uneventful that it hardly ever seemed to the governor worth mentioning.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Bush arrived in Fairbanks, Alaska International Industries was a fledgling business whose holdings included Alaska International Air, an air cargo company that was loading its giant Lockheed-382 Hercules airplanes, the civilian version of C-130's, with construction equipment and supplies and flying them to pipeline workers 24 hours a day.</p>
        <p>''We used to haul the equivalent of the Berlin airlift every week,'' said Neil G. Bergt, a pilot and entrepreneur who was president of both the parent company and the airline.</p>
        <p>People who worked there recall that in addition to its aviation and construction work for the pipeline,  the company flew planes that carried food and mining equipment into Zambia and ambulances into Libya.</p>
        <p>It also ''flew a bunch of F-14 parts into a town in Iran for the shah,'' said Steve Scott, who worked as a loadmaster. And ''we helped build a military base in Oman.''</p>
        <p>A number of onetime employees say they found themselves doing contract work for the C.I.A.</p>
        <p>''I had a big reputation for doing C.I.A. work,'' Mr. Bergt said. ''It wasn't deserved. We did some.''</p>
        <p>In the summer of 1974, however, during the period Mr. Bush worked at the company, Alaska International Air was too busy flying supplies to the pipeline to take work outside Alaska, Mr. Bergt said. He said Mr. Bush ''wouldn't have known'' about the connections between Alaska International and the C.I.A., although he ''might have heard some talk around the company.''</p>
        <p>In 1974, Fairbanks was jammed with construction workers. Mr. Bush rented a room with kitchen privileges from Grace Danks, a widow who worked as a waitress and lived in a two-story house in a tidy neighborhood close to downtown.</p>
        <p>Sally Smith, a Democrat who is the new mayor of Juneau, was living in Fairbanks that summer and says she went out with Mr. Bush several times. They were introduced, she recalls, by Alex Miller, a Democrat who worked as a Washington lobbyist for Mr. Bergt.</p>
        <p>''Alex dedicated his life to trying to find the right person for me,'' Ms. Smith said. ''George was another in a succession of 'maybe Sally will like this one.' He told me, 'I know he's a Republican, but at least he comes from a political family.' ''</p>
        <p>''We went to the International Bar, kind of a hangout for people in the arts and people who write for the newspaper,'' she said. ''I remember we had a beer. That's all I remember.''</p>
        <p>Betsy Brenneman, who would later work as a journalist in Alaska, sat next to Mr. Bush at the wedding of two Harvard Business School graduates in Davenport, Iowa, in October 1976. The bride, who had been her college roommate, had told her of Mr. Bush's Alaska work.</p>
        <p>''I tried to make small talk,'' Ms. Brenneman said. ''I asked him about Alaska, particularly Juneau. I had never been there. I didn't know it rained all the time. What he said was,  'Juneau's O.K. if you like mildew growing between your toes.' ''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
