<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Willie Cook, 76, Lead Trumpeter With Gillespie and Ellington</title>
    <meta content="Y21COOK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Obituaries" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/21/national/21COOK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001101T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Willie Cook</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cook, Willie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Obituary (Obit)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Obituaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E7DB113EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="340" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Willie Cook, 76, Lead Trumpeter With Gillespie and Ellington</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Willie Cook, big band trumpeter, dies at age 76 (M)0</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Willie Cook, a lyrical lead trumpeter with a soft tone who played in big bands led by Jay McShann, Earl Hines, Dizzy Gillespie and Duke Ellington, died on Sept. 22 in Stockholm. He was 76.</p>
        <p>He died of heart failure at Maria Regina Hospice in Stockholm, his son Wambi said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Willie Cook, a lyrical lead trumpeter with a soft tone who played in big bands led by Jay McShann, Earl Hines, Dizzy Gillespie and Duke Ellington, died on Sept. 22 in Stockholm. He was 76.</p>
        <p>He died of heart failure at Maria Regina Hospice in Stockholm, his son Wambi said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cook was born in Tangipahoa, La., and grew up in East Chicago, Ind. He was an admirer of Louis Armstrong and Roy Eldridge. In the early 1940's he played with the 'Bama State Collegians, led by Claude Trenier, and he met McShann in 1943. It was with Hines's band, in which he played from 1943 to 1948, that he learned to write arrangements; he also worked with the Jimmie Lunceford Orchestra. In the next few years he also worked with Gillespie and Billie Holiday.</p>
        <p>In October 1951 Mr. Cook joined Ellington as a lead trumpeter, a role that requires stamina and doesn't allow much room for solos. With some breaks, he remained in the band for almost a decade.</p>
        <p>After returning to Ellington sporadically and otherwise freelancing in the 1960's, Mr. Cook gave up performing until the late 70's, and worked in a music store in Houston. He worked with B. B. King, Clark Terry and Count Basie in the late 70's; in 1982, on tour with Count Basie, he traveled to Sweden and decided to settle in Stockholm. He worked in Sweden for 11 years as a lead trumpeter with Gugge Hedrenius's Big Blues Band.</p>
        <p>In addition to his son Wambi, of Los Angeles, Mr. Cook is survived by his wife, Krystal; his mother, Laura Cook of East Chicago; another son, Taru, of Pittsburgh; a daughter, Tawana, of Takoma Park, Md; two brothers, Hosea, of Chicago, and Edward, of Hammond, Ind.; a sister, Shirley Cousins of East Chicago; 13 grandchildren; and five great-grandchildren.</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 1, 2000, Wednesday  An obituary of the jazz trumpeter Willie Cook on Oct. 21 misspelled his wife's given name. It is Christl, not Krystal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 1, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An obituary of the jazz trumpeter Willie Cook on Oct. 21 misspelled his wife's given name. It is Christl, not Krystal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
