<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="TRA22.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E7DA1E3EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="378" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Signed 1B Carlos Delgado to a four-year contract.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Signed 1B Carlos Delgado to a four-year contract.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  CHICAGO BULLS--Waived F Johnny Taylor.  NEW YORK KNICKS--Waived C Vladimir Stepania.  TORONTO RAPTORS--Signed F Tyrone Corbin. Claimed C Nick Sheppard off waivers from the Utah Jazz.</p>
        <p>International Basketball Association  BILLINGS RIMROCKERS--Signed F Darryl Barnes and F Robert White.  MAGIC CITY SNOWBEARS--Signed F Ryan Huntley.  SASKATCHEWAN HAWKS--Signed G Paul Webster and G Randy Bolden.  WINNIPEG CYCLONE--Signed C Adam McCanna.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  CLEVELAND BROWNS--Placed QB Tim Couch on injured reserve. Signed QB Kevin Thompson.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  ST. LOUIS BLUES--Signed F Justin Papineau. Re-signed F Derek Bekar and F Reed Low.  SAN JOSE SHARKS--Recalled D Greg Andrusak from Kentucky of the AHL.  PHOENIX COYOTES--Assigned C Daniel Briere to Springfield of the AHL.  VANCOUVER CANUCKS--Signed RW Trent Klatt to a two-year contract extension, through the 2002-03 season. American Hockey League</p>
        <p>KENTUCKY THOROUGHBLADES--Announced D Greg Andrusak has been recalled by the San Jose Sharks.  SAINT JOHN FLAMES--Signed G Sean Matile and loaned him to Providence.  SPRINGFIELD FALCONS--Acquired C Daniel Briere on loan from the Phoenix Coyotes.  ST. JOHN'S MAPLE LEAFS--Signed D Chad Allen.</p>
        <p>Central Hockey League  COLUMBUS COTTONMOUTHS--Signed F Craig Stahl, F Ricahrd Kazda, and F Denis Lamoureux. Placed F Ryan Brown on 14-day injured reserve.  HUNTSVILLE CHANNEL CATS--Signed D Brian Tutt.  MACON WHOOPEE--Signed C Per Fernhall, RW Bill Monkman and C Bryan Kennedy. Waived C Hiro Murakami and LW Mattias Wraak.  SAN ANTONIO IGUANAS--Transferred G Tony Palmeri to 14-day injured reserve. Activated G Rob Galatiuk from the suspended injured list.</p>
        <p>East Coast Hockey League  DAYTON BOMBERS--Added G Colin March to the roster. Activated D Doug Nolan from injured reserve. Waived F Shane Kuss. Placed F Kent McDonnell on seven-day injured reserve.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
