<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Roll 'Em: Yanks and Mets Ready for a Wild Ride</title>
    <meta content="21SERI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/21/sports/21SERI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240504"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EFDD1E3EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1226" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Roll 'Em: Yanks and Mets Ready for a Wild Ride</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses outlook for World Series between New York Yankees and New York Mets; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Subway Series begins tonight and the participants will be greatly relieved, because when the Yankees' Andy Pettitte throws the first pitch to the Mets' Timo Perez in Game 1, they will all be temporarily bunkered from the bombardment of ticket requests.</p>
        <p>Desperation to see the first World Series between city rivals in 44 years is setting in, and no connection is too remote. The Mets' general manager, Steve Phillips, received a call yesterday from the batboy of the Class A Columbia Mets -- the 1983 Columbia, S.C., Mets, a team for which Phillips played. ''So he hasn't seen you in 17 years, and you want tickets?'' the secretary for the general manager asked the former batboy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Subway Series begins tonight and the participants will be greatly relieved, because when the Yankees' Andy Pettitte throws the first pitch to the Mets' Timo Perez in Game 1, they will all be temporarily bunkered from the bombardment of ticket requests.</p>
        <p>Desperation to see the first World Series between city rivals in 44 years is setting in, and no connection is too remote. The Mets' general manager, Steve Phillips, received a call yesterday from the batboy of the Class A Columbia Mets -- the 1983 Columbia, S.C., Mets, a team for which Phillips played. ''So he hasn't seen you in 17 years, and you want tickets?'' the secretary for the general manager asked the former batboy.</p>
        <p>It has been 16,083 days since the end of the last Subway Series, when the Yankees shut out the Dodgers in the final game of the 1956 World Series, and a city is on edge. It has been five days since the Mets, who have lived in the shadows of their Bronx big brothers for most of the last decade, clinched the National League pennant. It's been four days since the Yankees, the nearest thing to a dynasty that baseball has seen in a quarter-century, wrapped up the American League.</p>
        <p>The players are eager. ''There is a lot of buildup,'' Yankees pitcher David Cone said, ''almost like a Super Bowl atmosphere.''</p>
        <p>Al Leiter, who started the last World Series game not won by the Yankees -- as a member of the Florida Marlins, in 1997 -- will face Pettitte. Managers of both teams announced starting lineups that included mild surprises.</p>
        <p>The Mets' Mike Piazza, the starting catcher for 124 games in the regular season, will be the designated hitter in Game 1, and Todd Pratt -- who has had one at-bat in this postseason -- will start at catcher.</p>
        <p>Pettitte is left-handed, and in explaining his decision, Mets Manager Bobby Valentine said Pratt was the best right-handed hitter among his reserves. Pratt is generally considered a better defensive catcher than Piazza. Pratt throws better, and so long as Pratt is going to play, it figures that he would be the catcher and Piazza the designated hitter. Because the Yankees will start right-handers in other games at Yankee Stadium, this is expected to be the only game Pratt starts.</p>
        <p>Valentine is using Pratt, 0 for 3 in his career against Pettitte, rather than Bubba Trammell, who is 7 for 18 (.389) against the Yankees left-hander, with three doubles and one homer. ''Todd Pratt's been a big part of our team for two years and more,'' Valentine said. ''I think he's as deserving as any person who's ever put on a uniform to play in a World Series game.''</p>
        <p>Piazza said, ''I know I'll get my action behind the plate before the series is over.''</p>
        <p>Jose Vizcaino will replace Luis Sojo as the second baseman for the Yankees. Sojo has started at second in every postseason game for the Yankees and has seven runs batted in, but Vizcaino, a switch-hitter, is 10 for 19 (.526) in his career against Leiter. ''He and Sojo are interchangeable for me defensively,'' Yankees Manager Joe Torre said, ''and I think what jumped out at me when I looked at the numbers is what he had done against Al.''</p>
        <p>Finding ways to beat Leiter and Mike Hampton, the Mets' other left-handed starter, is what the Yankees must do in this four-of-seven-game series if they are to become the first team since the Oakland Athletics of 1972, '73 and '74 to win three consecutive titles. The Yankees' starting lineup will include three veteran left-handed hitters who can all hit left-handers, but Leiter held lefties to a .118 batting average in the regular season, the second-lowest figure in the last 25 years, according to the Elias Sports Bureau.</p>
        <p>The Yankees, whose pitching staff is not as deep as the Mets', must again rely heavily on six pitchers -- Pettitte and the other starters Roger Clemens and Orlando Hernandez, and the relievers Jeff Nelson, Mike Stanton and Mariano Rivera. The Mets' lineup is filled with patient hitters, and Yankee starters need to be efficient.</p>
        <p>The Mets must break through against a tough, veteran Yankees team that fought back from a late-season slump to survive two playoff trials, and seems to be gaining momentum. The Yankees have won 12 consecutive World Series games; if the Yankees win Game 1, their streak will set a record.</p>
        <p>''They know how to win,'' Leiter said, ''and they've certainly shown it by winning championships.''</p>
        <p>The Series is filled with top players capable of performing at the highest level. Rivera, the Yankees' closer, has allowed one run in 10 World Series appearances. Piazza is one of the greatest offensive players of his generation, and the Yankees will try to pitch around him. Hernandez, who could start two or more games in this series, has pitched in 10 postseason games and the Yankees have won all of them.</p>
        <p>Timo Perez has been an explosive presence at the top of the Mets' lineup in October, and the Yankees know little about him; their pitchers gleaned the latest theories on how to get him out from the one-and-a-half-inch thick, black-jacketed scouting notebooks they studied yesterday. David Justice, who hit the home run that helped clinch a pennant for the Yankees on Tuesday, has played in the postseason more than any player in history. Even if the teams were not housed 10 miles apart, it would be a great matchup of stars and subplots.</p>
        <p>But both teams were sired by the same city, and the clans that follow them are distinct and divided. Yankees fans screamed at Leiter in downtown Manhattan the other night -- ''Just don't go to Madison Square Garden right now,'' Leiter advised some Mets followers -- and Cone has walked around the city and been impressed by all the baseball caps, both with the interlocking N's and Y's but absolutely dissimilar to the fans who wear them.</p>
        <p>As the Yankees finished batting practice yesterday afternoon, some of the Mets began to filter from their dugout and onto the field for their workout. Some coaches from the two teams chatted, and there were a few waves across the field by the players, but mostly, there was little contact. The Mets took infield practice and batting practice. Second baseman Edgardo Alfonzo stood behind the cage, stoic, a blank expression.</p>
        <p>Why so quiet? ''What do you think I'm feeling inside?'' Alfonzo asked, his face splitting into a grin. ''I'm about to play in my first World Series. I'm just trying to keep my emotions inside.''</p>
        <p>Alfonzo, and a city, will let loose tonight.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
