<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Shrine and a Bowl, But Both Are Home</title>
    <meta content="21STAD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/21/sports/21STAD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES -- THE STADIUMS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yankee Stadium (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shea Stadium (NYC)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feuer, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EEDE1E3EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Shrine and a Bowl, But Both Are Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses Yankee Stadium and Shea Stadium as they are readied for World Series between New York Yankees and New York Mets; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Baseball, the most nostalgic of games, is inherently reverent about the concept of home. The home team gives visitors first ups, but keeps the privilege of last licks and turning out the lights. The game's most majestic event is a journey of departure and return, the home run. Indeed, all batters seek to leave home plate, but the finest teams are those who bring them back to it most often. It's even shaped like a house.</p>
        <p>Home, of course, in baseball as in life, is also a tangible place. Its layout and furnishings, its location and atmosphere are shaped by the people who live there, and shape them in return. And with New York City itself looming as a house divided by the World Series that begins tonight between the Yankees and Mets, the stadiums the teams call home are revered in themselves, speaking volumes about the franchises and fans that inhabit them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Baseball, the most nostalgic of games, is inherently reverent about the concept of home. The home team gives visitors first ups, but keeps the privilege of last licks and turning out the lights. The game's most majestic event is a journey of departure and return, the home run. Indeed, all batters seek to leave home plate, but the finest teams are those who bring them back to it most often. It's even shaped like a house.</p>
        <p>Home, of course, in baseball as in life, is also a tangible place. Its layout and furnishings, its location and atmosphere are shaped by the people who live there, and shape them in return. And with New York City itself looming as a house divided by the World Series that begins tonight between the Yankees and Mets, the stadiums the teams call home are revered in themselves, speaking volumes about the franchises and fans that inhabit them.</p>
        <p>One is a shrine, a staunch horseshoe in steel and concrete completed in 1923 that became the fixture of a neighborhood and a renowned symbol of the Bronx. Yankee Stadium was built by Col. Jacob Ruppert, the owner of the Yankees, on the site of a decrepit lumberyard close to the Grand Concourse, then a fashionable boulevard rivaling Fifth Avenue. It was meant to be grand, meant to trump the Giants across the East River in upper Manhattan and their Polo Grounds (where the Yankees had been tolerated as co-tenants).</p>
        <p>It was the first ballpark to have an electric scoreboard, indeed the first to be known as a stadium (the major leagues' only older homes are Wrigley Field in Chicago and Fenway Park in Boston), and it exists today as a testament to an American sport and its most successful team. Yankee Stadium is an institution, a particularly New York one, and so are the Yankees. Both inspire awe, reverence and deep animosity.</p>
        <p>The other, Shea Stadium -- a circular structure featuring, when it opened in 1964, an abstract design of orange panels around the outside --  helped usher in the modern age of sports and entertainment. It distanced the Mets from their progenitive Yankee alternatives in the city, the Giants and Dodgers, creating a new home for a new fan base, and it was named for William A. Shea, a lawyer who headed a city committee appointed by Mayor Robert F. Wagner to help New York gain another major league team.</p>
        <p>Shea Stadium was built for an expansion team (the Mets began life at the old Polo Grounds in 1962) and soon took on a co-tenant, football's Jets, who moved in the first year, as well as events like rallies and concerts (the Beatles famously played there in 1965 and 1966), as it prefigured the multi-use stadiums that came to be sprinkled across the country.</p>
        <p>Located in Flushing Meadows, near the airports and the grounds of the 1964 World's Fair and with easy access to the highways extending into the Long Island suburbs, Shea -- with its Mets -- has long represented an outward-stretching, newcomer-welcoming, youthful, irreverent, let-us-into-the-party New York.</p>
        <p>Today, having coexisted for 36 years, the stadiums represent a shared culture as well as their separate ones. The city, which built Shea, now owns Yankee Stadium as well, having ended the weirdness of its ownership history by purchasing it, in 1971, from Rice University in Houston. Both have undergone renovations; the Yankees even played at Shea for two seasons in the 1970's while their stadium was being spruced up.</p>
        <p>Players have played for both teams and four men -- Casey Stengel, Yogi Berra, Dallas Green and Joe Torre -- have managed both. And interleague play has made the teams' annual crosstown visits a highlight of the regular season.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the Subway Series is the climax of a long, slow rapprochement.</p>
        <p>Some will dispute this, no doubt, but one result of this is that the current experience of watching a ballgame in one park is a good deal like watching a game in the other, in spite of the details that remain distinct.</p>
        <p>Yankee Stadium has better sightlines, particularly in the outfield; at Shea, beyond first and third base, the seats are peculiarly angled toward a spot just beyond second base. And there is also the annoyance of jets taking off from La Guardia. But Shea, with its outer walls open to the outside and wider corridors and ramps, is far more pleasant to walk around.</p>
        <p>The dank, claustrophobic corridors beneath the Yankee Stadium stands are downright creepy. In recent years, the stadium has had a reputation, rightly, for particularly crude fan behavior, with obscene chants and beer showers and a near-lawless incivility that kept a lot of parents from taking children to games, especially at night. Visits this season -- an unscientific report -- indicate things are improving, if not exactly Disneyesque. And Yankee Stadium has no monopoly on unpleasantness; the only time this reporter has ever been assaulted, anywhere, was in the Shea Stadium parking lot after Game 7 of the 1986 World Series.</p>
        <p>The one stadium element that preserves the initial distinctions between the two franchises is the music that blares over the loudspeakers. Shea Stadium has been known for adapting the enthusiasms of pop music for exhortatory purposes; during the National League Championship Series the current rap song ''Who Let the Dogs Out'' emerged as the most recent call to arms.</p>
        <p>The Yankees, however, stodgy to this day, are best known for playing Frank Sinatra's rendition of ''New York, New York'' at the conclusion of each game. Of course, Shea Stadium has no counterpart to Bob Sheppard, the Yankees' public address announcer for half a century, whose grave, shuddering intonations -- ''Your attention, please, ladies and gentlemen, now batting for the Yankees . . . '' -- provide the simplest, most eloquent of soundtracks for a grand tradition.</p>
        <p>Still, though denizens of one stadium or the other might be loath to acknowledge it, both ballparks create remarkably equivalent atmospheres. Each place holds a healthy mix of blue- and white-collar patrons, youthful loudmouths and grizzled mumblers, careful scorecard keepers bent on charting history, jittery worriers who shake their heads with every shift in momentum, and of course the defiantly prideful screamers, groaners, leapers and fist-shakers whose visceral instincts make the grandstand pulsate.</p>
        <p>In each the wandering vendors -- ''Hey peanuts, bag o' nuts!''; ''Last cawl fuh de al-ca-hawl!'' -- salt the air with baseball hip-hop. In each the raucousness quotient rises with the distance from home plate. Each exhibits the paucity of black faces that is a sportwide enigma but seems especially odd in New York.</p>
        <p>And in each, particularly lately, hometown pride and the torn loyalties of the city are prominently in evidence. As the Yanks defeated the Mariners and the Mets polished off the Cardinals this week, the crowd cheers echoed one another and their shared past: ''Ti-no!'' at Yankee Stadium, for the veteran first baseman Tino Martinez; ''Ti-mo!'' at Shea, for the rookie outfielder Timo Perez.</p>
        <p>In both parks, young -- and not so young -- women were clad in the jerseys of the teams' starriest stars, Derek Jeter and Mike Piazza. The citywide respect for both is evident.</p>
        <p>Most telling, in each stadium this week, as home fans indulged in their age-old exhortations -- ''Let's Go, Yank-ees''; ''Let's Go Mets'' -- they were answered in kind, a crossbred and rhythmic paean to the approaching great occasion.</p>
        <p>The story line for this Series is a splendid one, especially for two teams in more universally applicable opposition. Can the Yankees, an aging club fending off decline, summon the will for one last effort? Or have the younger Mets achieved their time?</p>
        <p>Maybe the stadiums have predictive powers; in recent years, Yankee Stadium, its tradition proving immovable, has resisted the efforts of the mayor and team owner to get it to yield its team to a new ballpark on the West Side of Manhattan or in New Jersey. Shea, however, appears doomed to the wrecking ball. But maybe that's just wishful thinking, to betray a bias.</p>
        <p>Indeed, whatever happens, what little there is to distinguish between Yankee and Shea Stadiums right now is overwhelmed by the sense of moment that they share and emanate.</p>
        <p>Enter each park. Take in the three decks of people, the expanse of pastoral greensward bathed in garish light against a black sky, all of it throbbing with baseball and New York. Buy a hot dog. Welcome home.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES -- THE STADIUMS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
