<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Dugouts, Opposites Distract</title>
    <meta content="Y21MAN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/21/sports/21MANA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240478"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torre, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Valentine, Bobby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2DF1E3EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1563" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Dugouts, Opposites Distract</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses contrasting styles of managers Joe Torre and Bobby Valentine as they prepare forWorld Series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 28-year-old utility player had been assured by the manager that he would make the Mets to start the 1979 season, so naturally he was incensed when the team released him in the final week of spring training. He was so incensed about feeling misled that he held a news conference the next day to discuss how he had been mistreated.</p>
        <p>The 38-year-old manager did tell the player that he would make the team, but, eight days after their conversation, he changed his mind. After re-evaluating the team, he did not think the energetic 28-year-old with diminishing abilities was among his 25 best players. So he delivered the sobering news and waited for an eruption.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 28-year-old utility player had been assured by the manager that he would make the Mets to start the 1979 season, so naturally he was incensed when the team released him in the final week of spring training. He was so incensed about feeling misled that he held a news conference the next day to discuss how he had been mistreated.</p>
        <p>The 38-year-old manager did tell the player that he would make the team, but, eight days after their conversation, he changed his mind. After re-evaluating the team, he did not think the energetic 28-year-old with diminishing abilities was among his 25 best players. So he delivered the sobering news and waited for an eruption.</p>
        <p>''Our meeting was, well, difficult,'' the manager said at the time.</p>
        <p>After being released, the player said: ''My chief complaint is the way it was done. Because of that, I might never be able to play baseball again.''</p>
        <p>Twenty-one years ago, the angry player in the Mets' spring training was Bobby Valentine; the young manager was Joe Torre. On March 24, 1979, Torre told Valentine that he could not keep him on the roster because of the presence of players like Kelvin Chapman and Joel Youngblood and because of his inferior defense at second base, which contrasted with what Valentine had heard several days earlier.</p>
        <p>Valentine was outraged, saying that he thought he had been ''Joe Torre's main man'' and that the move showed ''no professional courtesy,'' because it was made so close to opening day that other teams would be reluctant to sign him.</p>
        <p>Then, like now, Valentine's words were eloquent and biting, a player suddenly pondering the end of his career. Then, like now, Torre's words were diplomatic and careful, the manager of an awful team with one stressful chore finished.</p>
        <p>They will meet again tonight in a setting that neither of them could have envisioned 21 years ago, not as a bitter Valentine was scrambling for another job and not as a realistic Torre was scrambling to win with a poor team and keep his job. They will meet at Yankee Stadium as the Mets oppose the Yankees in the World Series, the first Subway Series since 1956. They will meet as managers, one trying to win his first title and one trying to win his third straight, both fighting against a piece of their past.</p>
        <p>''Joe was very fatherly to me when I was there,'' Valentine recalled this week. ''He's a good manager.''</p>
        <p>Torre said that Valentine ''always had fire in his eyes. He was always into the game when he played for me. I'm not surprised he became a manager.''</p>
        <p>Torre and Valentine are different men and different managers. The 60-year-old Torre is the smart uncle some players never had. He knows what they are experiencing, because he experienced it during his 17 seasons as a major leaguer and his 19 years as a manager with the Mets, Braves, Cardinals and Yankees.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Torre drives the bus around here,'' Yankees shortstop Derek Jeter said.</p>
        <p>The 50-year-old Valentine is the animated manager who is considered a terrific tactician and who agrees with that assessment. He outmanaged Dusty Baker of the Giants in the division series, he helped the Mets stop Tony La Russa's Cardinals in the National League Championship Series and he will soon become a richer man, because he is unsigned beyond this season. Valentine's baseball acumen has never been doubted, and once Rickey Henderson was released, the only player who publicly criticized him this season was Bobby M. Jones. That is one fewer than the number of Yankees -- Jeff Nelson and Tino Martinez -- who tweaked Torre.</p>
        <p>''We might not always agree,'' Mets third baseman Robin Ventura said, ''but we communicate a lot better to each other rather than through the papers. You say what you want to say and nobody is offended. He says things that might not sound good if someone else is listening, but I think we all realize we can talk to each other.''</p>
        <p>Torre is stoic; Valentine is fiery. Torre would never wear a fake mustache and sunglasses during a game; Valentine has done it twice. Torre's best source for information is Don Zimmer; Valentine's is the slick computer on his desk. Torre is cordial with reporters but keeps them at arm's length and rarely mentions their first names; Valentine is either friendly or feisty with reporters and knows their first and last names. Torre could retire tomorrow and be content; Valentine, forever chasing a title, will never be content without one.</p>
        <p>But there are similarities, too. They are both former major leaguers of Italian descent and they are both from the local area, with Torre hailing from Brooklyn and Valentine growing up in Stamford, Conn. While Torre was a 245-pound kid at St. Francis Prep who never thought he would be as good as his older brother, Frank, he became a full-time major leaguer at 21, made nine All-Star teams and once hit .363 in a season.</p>
        <p>Valentine might have been the greatest high school athlete in Connecticut history. He ran track and played baseball and football at Rippowam High School, rushing for 53 touchdowns in three years and getting recruited by more than 250 colleges. He was the Dodgers' first pick -- the fifth over all -- in the 1968 draft, and his only question was why the Mets had not chosen him first. Valentine fractured his right leg in two places running into the center-field fence in 1973, and the injury destroyed what was supposed to be a superb career. Valentine, a .251 lifetime hitter, became a manager after playing 62 games with Seattle in 1979.</p>
        <p>''I remember telling him in a restaurant in Santo Domingo that he couldn't cut it as a player anymore,'' Tommy Lasorda, the Dodgers' manager at the time, said. ''He cried, I cried, but it was the right thing to tell him. Now look at him.''</p>
        <p>In a season during which Valentine's behavior was pivotal in convincing the Mets that he deserved to remain as manager, Valentine was more like Torre than ever before. The Mets never said that they were monitoring Valentine's behavior, but it seemed obvious that he was peeking over his shoulder while also biting his tongue; he was almost free of controversy this season.</p>
        <p>''I think that Bobby had a lot of pressure on him this year,'' said Ralph Branca, the former Brooklyn Dodgers pitcher who is Valentine's father-in-law. ''I haven't talked to him about it, but I don't think he could be free and loose. I get the feeling he had to be circumspect. He couldn't do anything that might be obtrusive to other G.M.'s or organizations. He had to watch himself.''</p>
        <p>Could that have produced a manager who was more like Torre?</p>
        <p>''When I played for Torre, he was a calming influence,'' John Stearns, the Mets' bench coach, said. ''That's what Bobby has been this year, too. His reputation is not that of a calming leader. But he was this year. I was shocked. He didn't really yell at an umpire all year, except for one game against the Yankees, and he had a legitimate argument.''</p>
        <p>Valentine insisted that he was not as relaxed as Torre this season, but that he tried to be a settling influence to the Mets.</p>
        <p>Back when Valentine was released by the Mets, there was speculation that his outspoken ways might have made him a threat to Torre. Torre said there had been no personality conflict ''on my part.'' Valentine said then that he could not help it if his attitude was misunderstood.</p>
        <p>''Some players came to me and warned me that Joe might resent it,'' Valentine said at the time. ''But I was loyal to this team and to Joe Torre.''</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, both managers minimized the animosity surrounding Valentine's release in 1979. Valentine said that it had been a ''personal thing'' and that he had felt he was a better player than he actually was. ''Time heals all wounds,'' Valentine said.</p>
        <p>Torre, who was offered a coaching job by Valentine in 1988 when he was manager of the Texas Rangers, had not taken personally any of Valentine's harsh words upon leaving the Mets. ''I never fanned those flames,'' Torre said. ''You know it's emotional.''</p>
        <p>More emotions are likely to be unleashed tonight in the Bronx. The managers will stare across the field at each other, a longer distance than when Valentine used to stare across to the other end of the dugout and nod at Torre after he had made certain managerial decisions. There will be no nodding this time, just plotting. Two managers, different yet similar, trying to make the present perfect, while competing against a piece of their past.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
