<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Barak May Halt Peace Moves To Revamp His Government</title>
    <meta content="21MIDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/21/world/21MIDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240486"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Orme, William A Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E5DE1E3EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Barak May Halt Peace Moves To Revamp His Government</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG and WILLIAM A. ORME Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Orme, William A Jr; Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Oct. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Ehud Barak says he is prepared to take indefinite 'timeout' from Israeli-Palestinian peace effort; move will enable him to forge national emergency government with right-wing opposition; announcement follows deaths of 10 Palestinians in clashes with Israeli soldiers at checkpoints throughout West Bank that defied truce worked out in Egypt; Barak will not send representatives to Washington for new round of talks with Palestinians; suggests it is not worth Israel's time and effort to continue discussions with Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat, who he says is no longer partner in peace; speaks with Pres Clinton, who urges Arafat to do all he can to calm tensions; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak, elected on a platform of peacemaking, announced tonight that he was prepared to take an indefinite ''timeout'' from the Israeli-Palestinian peace effort. That would pave the way for him to forge a national emergency government with the right-wing opposition next week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak's announcement came at the end of one of the worst days of violence since the current conflict began raging three weeks ago, and on the eve of a weekend summit meeting of Arab leaders. After Palestinians confronted Israeli soldiers at checkpoints throughout the West Bank, 10 Palestinians were killed in clashes that defied the truce agreement forged early this week in Sharm el Sheik, Egypt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak, elected on a platform of peacemaking, announced tonight that he was prepared to take an indefinite ''timeout'' from the Israeli-Palestinian peace effort. That would pave the way for him to forge a national emergency government with the right-wing opposition next week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak's announcement came at the end of one of the worst days of violence since the current conflict began raging three weeks ago, and on the eve of a weekend summit meeting of Arab leaders. After Palestinians confronted Israeli soldiers at checkpoints throughout the West Bank, 10 Palestinians were killed in clashes that defied the truce agreement forged early this week in Sharm el Sheik, Egypt.</p>
        <p>While it would seem obvious that the peace effort is already frozen by the violence, Mr. Barak had until recently held out hopes of returning to the negotiating table. But after saying for weeks that Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, was no longer a peace partner, he suggested tonight his conclusion: It is not worth Israel's time or effort to continue talking to him.</p>
        <p>Specifically, an Israeli government spokesman said Mr. Barak would not send representatives to Washington in two weeks to meet Palestinian negotiators, as discussed in Egypt. This represents a blow to President Clinton, who worked hard to get the leaders to aim for a resumption of the negotiations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak said he had called Mr. Clinton tonight to tell him that he thought the truce agreement was failing and to alert him to his plans. ''I have no doubt he will understand,'' Mr. Barak said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton spoke with Mr. Arafat from aboard Air Force One today, urging him in a 15-minute call to do all he could to calm the tensions.</p>
        <p>''He stressed the need for everyone to do what they can to restore the calm,'' said Jake Siewert, the president's press secretary. ''Arafat said he's still committed to do what he can.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak gave two divergent interviews tonight on Israeli television. In one, he seemed to be saying unequivocally that he would call a timeout after the Arab League summit meeting, which begins on Saturday in Cairo. In the other, he implied that events between now and then could change his mind.</p>
        <p>In delaying the start of Israel's timeout, Mr. Barak was doing several things at once. He was giving the Palestinians more time to calm violent protests. He was putting pressure on moderate Arab leaders to exert their influence on Mr. Arafat.</p>
        <p>And he was signaling to them his inclination to form an alliance with Ariel Sharon, the opposition leader of the right-wing Likud Party, unless something happened to change his mind. Arab leaders hold Mr. Sharon responsible for provoking the recent violence by his visit three weeks ago to the plaza outside Al Aksa Mosque in Jerusalem's Old City.</p>
        <p>''Immediately after the summit, particularly if, as we see now, the Sharm conclusions are not preparing a quieting down, we will declare a timeout period in order to re-evaluate the situation,'' Mr. Barak said in one of the television interviews.</p>
        <p>Palestinians responded with anger to Mr. Barak's declaration. Saeb Erekat, a senior Palestinian official who has been suggesting for weeks that the Israeli leader was preparing an ''exit strategy from the peace process,'' said tonight that he had called it right.</p>
        <p>''Barak has reached a point where he is threatening the Arab leaders' meeting, linking his coming decisions to the Arab summit's decisions,'' he said on Voice of Palestine radio. ''This is a blatant threat that has never happened before.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Erekat also accused the prime minister of ordering his troops to use excessive force today in reaction to a firefight on Thursday outside Nablus. On Thursday, a settlers' hike provoked a gun battle, during which wounded settlers lay for hours on a steep hillside waiting to be evacuated. A 64-year-old rabbi bled to death, and he was buried today. A Palestinian man was also shot dead.</p>
        <p>''Yesterday he sent a herd of settlers under the protection of the Israeli Army, and then Barak threatened revenge,'' Mr. Erekat said ''That's exactly what happened today. He sought revenge. My martyrs: 10 dead and 279 injured people.''</p>
        <p>It is not yet clear if Mr. Sharon's Likud Party would agree to join Mr. Barak's faltering minority government. But Mr. Sharon had made it a condition that Mr. Barak take a break from the peace effort and distance himself from the concessions he was offering at the Camp David summit meeting in July.</p>
        <p>Two newspaper polls published today displayed contradictory results. One showed Israel's faith in Mr. Barak at a low; another showed him rallying as a result of the crisis. But neither showed a majority of Israelis behind him. One poll found the former Likud prime minister, Benjamin Netanyahu, trouncing Mr. Barak if elections were held now. The other found both Mr. Netanyahu and Mr. Sharon handily beating him.</p>
        <p>While many world leaders -- Arab leaders aside -- have been impressed with what they see as Mr. Barak's sober approach to peacemaking and crisis, Israelis have been rough on him for most of his tenure. They have attacked him for military-style leadership, communicating rarely with his ministers and the public, and moving from policy to policy.</p>
        <p>Now, some hold him responsible for provoking a crisis by pushing too hard to end the Israeli-Palestinian conflict. Some Israelis were content to linger in the interim peace period, in which tensions were low and the explosive final issues were left unresolved.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, the polls also showed that a majority of Israelis remain committed to the peace effort, although they feel increasingly insecure -- scared of terrorism, scared of the violence's reaching their streets, as it has in the Jerusalem neighborhood of Gilo.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Barak disclosed his inclination to suspend peace talks, helicopter gunships tonight hovered over suburban Jerusalem, joining army tanks below in an all-out assault on snipers firing into the Gilo neighborhood from a Palestinian town.</p>
        <p>Earlier today, Mr. Barak visited Gilo. Accompanied by Ehud Olmert, who is Jerusalem's mayor and a Likud Party leader, he inspected the tanks and concrete fortifications that the army has installed in the partly vacated neighborhood. When shots whistled through the neighborhood again tonight, Israeli tanks, in a rare use of heavy ordnance in a densely populated urban area, fired shells back at the Palestinian town.</p>
        <p>Throughout the West Bank and Gaza, sermons at Friday Prayer urged Muslim worshipers to protest against the continuing Israeli Army presence there. The demonstrations turned violent in Gaza and Ramallah, with protesters attacking Israeli Army posts with stones, gunfire and homemade gasoline bombs. The Israeli troops responded with tear gas and volleys of rubber-coated steel bullets.</p>
        <p>Near Tulkarm, in the West Bank, a busload of Israeli soldiers came under fire near a Palestinian security checkpoint. Six Israelis were seriously wounded. The shots were fired by the Palestinian police, Israeli Army spokesmen asserted. The Palestinian police there denied the charge.</p>
        <p>The deaths of 10 Palestinians today raised the toll from three weeks of fighting to at least 118, 7 of them Jewish Israelis and the rest Arabs.</p>
        <p>After an American-mediated meeting on Wednesday between Israeli and Palestinian military commanders, Mr. Barak's government had said it would ''test'' Palestinian compliance with the cease-fire agreement over the next 48 hours.</p>
        <p>Tonight, Israeli officials charged that the Palestinian Authority had failed to honor its commitments under the accord, while Palestinian officials reiterated accusations that Israel had continued to use excessive force against mostly unarmed rioters.</p>
        <p>In the interview tonight, Mr. Barak was asked if he had been overly influenced by his visit today to another former Likud prime minister, Yitzhak Shamir. Mr. Barak issued a tight smile, and indicated that he wanted to emulate Mr. Shamir's performance during the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>''The situation today in Israel reminds us of Shamir's situation with the Scuds exploding,'' he said. ''There were people saying: 'Attack, the Israeli army is strong. Show them.' And he didn't. We saw finally how smart Shamir was, how he wasn't dragged into things. That is how we will behave as well.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
