<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Slow Start Solved, Hampton Looks Inside for the Keys to Success</title>
    <meta content="Y21HAM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/21/sports/21HAMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hampton, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E6D6113EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1182" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Slow Start Solved, Hampton Looks Inside for the Keys to Success</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets pitcher Mike Hampton discusses preparing for World Series against New York Yankees; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The question was about what Mike Hampton has learned this year, about how he has changed. Hampton, a left-handed pitcher for the Mets, was about to let a visitor into his world, which does not happen too often.</p>
        <p>''I'm probably just better prepared to handle a lot of things,'' he said. ''This has been a growing experience all around. Not only is the situation magnified in New York, but being in the playoffs and going this far has been a lot more pressure games. You find out a little bit about yourself and how you're going to react in those situations.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The question was about what Mike Hampton has learned this year, about how he has changed. Hampton, a left-handed pitcher for the Mets, was about to let a visitor into his world, which does not happen too often.</p>
        <p>''I'm probably just better prepared to handle a lot of things,'' he said. ''This has been a growing experience all around. Not only is the situation magnified in New York, but being in the playoffs and going this far has been a lot more pressure games. You find out a little bit about yourself and how you're going to react in those situations.''</p>
        <p>What, Hampton was asked, has he learned about himself? At this question, Hampton retreated, shutting the door to his thoughts. Access denied.</p>
        <p>''Man, you can't just write my diary and everything,'' Hampton said. ''It's just stuff. People won't understand.''</p>
        <p>Understanding Hampton has been a difficult task, for his teammates and coaches as well as those who follow the team.</p>
        <p>He does not talk about where he will be next season, whether he will stay in New York or leave as a free agent. That question looms over him, as it did over Mike Piazza two years ago. The players are aware of Hampton's pending decision, and they do not know what it will be.</p>
        <p>''I'm proud to have played with him,'' said Piazza, the catcher. ''I don't know if it'll be only this year, but that remains to be seen. He's obviously a main reason why we're here.''</p>
        <p>The Mets would probably not be in the World Series without Hampton, who went 15-10 and was the most valuable player of the National League Championship Series, in which he beat St. Louis twice with 16 shutout innings. But for a while, it seemed as if the Mets could not win with him.</p>
        <p>Hampton walked nine on opening day in Japan. He pummeled the water coolers in the dugout at Colorado's Coors Field after his last start in April. When he struggled again five days later in San Francisco, he walked back to the team hotel alone, finding solace in his thoughts and putting his struggles in perspective. His record stood at 2-4 with a 6.52 earned run average.</p>
        <p>In his 29 starts since then, including the postseason, Hampton is 15-7 with a 2.37 E.R.A. He righted himself by himself.</p>
        <p>''I was still new to the team, so it was something I had to deal with myself,'' he said. ''I knew they felt for the way that I was throwing and always had confidence in me, but it was just something I had to deal with on my own.''</p>
        <p>Al Leiter, a fellow left-hander, did not know Hampton when Hampton played for Houston. He remembered him as stone-faced, an intense competitor not big on small talk or hugs behind the batting cage with opponents. Leiter, who struggled early in '99 before finishing strong, knew he could only subtly encourage his new teammate.</p>
        <p>''Any time a guy's struggling, everybody from everywhere is trying to give you their remedy to fix it,'' Leiter said. ''And really, internally, you pretty much know what you have to do that you haven't been doing. Mike is confident in the ability that he has, and he was able to right himself by staying the course.</p>
        <p>''Generally, it comes down to a confidence thing. You lose your confidence, you start throwing balls, you're in hitters' counts, you're not being as aggressive.''</p>
        <p>Hampton's confidence is extraordinary, and after his performance in the N.L.C.S., it will be soaring when he takes the mound at Yankee Stadium for Game 2 tomorrow. He is open to suggestions, saying he will keep learning for the rest of his life. But interaction with Hampton is much on his terms, the pitching coach Dave Wallace said, and supreme confidence is necessary to that approach.</p>
        <p>That is fine, Wallace said, even if not many pitchers are like that. ''You just encourage him, talk to him, try to be the part that he allows you to be,'' Wallace said.</p>
        <p>''He's pretty guarded in who he lets in and who he doesn't. Somewhere around the middle of May or so, your sense is that this is pretty nice and it's working O.K. But you can't force yourself on anybody.''</p>
        <p>As a coach, Wallace gets help from veterans like Leiter, who enjoys talking about pitching philosophy with younger members of the staff. Hampton helps, too, Wallace said, although less with philosophy and more with mind-set.</p>
        <p>The left-hander Glendon Rusch remembers throwing with Hampton before spring training and being pleased with how open and friendly he was. Rusch and Hampton have completely different styles; Hampton would rather give up a walk than a hit, Rusch the reverse. But Rusch has learned from him.</p>
        <p>''One thing I've learned is I don't have to give in as much,'' Rusch said. ''It's made me tougher to know that I can make my pitches, be confident in myself and do that at any time in the count, any part of the game.''</p>
        <p>That confidence has spread to the rest of the team. Whatever the Mets know about Hampton, they know this: when he pitches, he gives them a great chance to win. That is a major reason General Manager Steve Phillips traded for Hampton. The Mets needed another top-of-the-rotation starter and the swagger that such a pitcher would bring.</p>
        <p>''Oftentimes, the feel you have going into the game has an impact on the way you play,'' Phillips said. ''Masato Yoshii pitched well for us, but it wasn't the same feel of having Mike Hampton starting the game.''</p>
        <p>The Mets have never been more confident in Hampton than they were in his last start, on Monday in Game 5 of the N.L.C.S. His teammates sensed an even greater concentration than usual before Hampton pitched them to the pennant, allowing three hits.</p>
        <p>''That was a different sort of focus than I'd ever seen,'' the left-hander Bobby M. Jones said. ''He wasn't saying a whole lot. The TV was on, but he wasn't looking at it. It was like he was looking through the TV.''</p>
        <p>Wallace saw that determination, but he also saw a polished fastball, breaking ball and changeup in Hampton's pregame bullpen session.</p>
        <p>''It was evident warming up, 'Whoa, O.K., the stuff is there,' '' Wallace recalled. ''Now it was going to be a matter of catching breaks and making pitches. A lot of times, just because the stuff is there doesn't mean a guy's going to have a real good outing. The tendency is to think, 'Well, I've got my good stuff,' and you forget to pitch.''</p>
        <p>Hampton remembered how to pitch and won the most important game of his life. Even more important is the game that comes next. If Hampton learned something about himself from the last one, only he knows. Nobody but Hampton can write that entry in the diary.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
