<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knoblauch's Reply Is Loud and Clear</title>
    <meta content="21KNOB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/21/sports/21KNOB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240493"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knoblauch, Chuck</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0DE1E3EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1105" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knoblauch's Reply Is Loud and Clear</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles career of New York Yankees infielder Chuck Knoblauch; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The angry, haunting lyrics will spill out of the public address system at Yankee Stadium as soon as Chuck Knoblauch ambles from the on-deck circle to the plate in the first inning tonight. Knoblauch, the Yankees second baseman, feels misunderstood and mistreated, which is why his every step is accompanied by Eminem's vocals about being irritated with people who hound him and who think that they know him.</p>
        <p>''And I am whatever you say I am. If I wasn't, then why would I say I am? In the paper, the news, every day I am, radio won't even play my jam.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The angry, haunting lyrics will spill out of the public address system at Yankee Stadium as soon as Chuck Knoblauch ambles from the on-deck circle to the plate in the first inning tonight. Knoblauch, the Yankees second baseman, feels misunderstood and mistreated, which is why his every step is accompanied by Eminem's vocals about being irritated with people who hound him and who think that they know him.</p>
        <p>''And I am whatever you say I am. If I wasn't, then why would I say I am? In the paper, the news, every day I am, radio won't even play my jam.''</p>
        <p>Knoblauch's right foot kicks at the dirt in the back of the batter's box as Eminem continues to serenade him, motivate him. If Knoblauch takes a little extra time to tighten his batting gloves, ''The Way I Am'' continues kicking out of the speakers. Through Eminem's words, Knoblauch is anonymously kicking back at George Steinbrenner, the news media, fans, anyone who judges him.</p>
        <p>'' 'Cause I am whatever you say I am. If I wasn't, then why would I say I am? In the paper, the news, every day I am. I don't know, it's just the way I am.''</p>
        <p>The tune became Knoblauch's theme song last month, soon after Steinbrenner insinuated that he was recovering too slowly from tendinitis in his right elbow. Steinbrenner, the Yankees' principal owner, also inferred that the 32-year-old Knoblauch was afraid to return because of his throwing problems and essentially challenged him to get back onto the field. Now Eminem speaks for Knoblauch.</p>
        <p>''You get fed up with everything,'' Knoblauch said early Wednesday morning, after the Yankees clinched the American League Championship Series. ''It's not one particular thing. It's everything. The song speaks truth. You are who you are. If somebody likes it, great. If not, that's great, too. Life goes on. Everybody is who they are, they believe in what they believe in and they do what they need to do.''</p>
        <p>Eminem, the controversial rapper whose skills are often obscured by his vicious and venomous lyrics, is a complicated person. Knoblauch, the embattled second baseman and designated hitter, is complex, too. Knoblauch called this season very difficult, while Manager Joe Torre said it was turbulent and said Knoblauch was ''like the Nasdaq.'' Up and down. Knoblauch is up again now, leading off and starting at D.H. in Game 1 of the World Series and poised to play second with a still-tender elbow in the games at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>''No matter what I had gone through,'' Knoblauch explained, ''this is exactly where I want to be.''</p>
        <p>Torre sounded relieved that Knoblauch, who is batting .281 and has a .361 on-base percentage in the postseason, is up again and has a prominent role for the Yankees.</p>
        <p>''I think if you told both of us that six, seven weeks ago, we're not sure that would have taken place,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>That was back when Knoblauch was on the disabled list, the Yankees could not pinpoint what was wrong with his elbow and Steinbrenner was getting antsy. It seems likely that Steinbrenner's comments inspired Knoblauch's decision to turn Eminem loose.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch had to be creative to use the snippet of music. The song lasts 4 minutes 45 seconds, and the part that is played at Yankee Stadium is one of the only slivers where more than 40 seconds elapses without Eminem rapping expletives, meaning that most of the song is unplayable at the Stadium. ''And I am whatever you say I am'' could be Knoblauch's response to Steinbrenner's charges, charges that enraged him.</p>
        <p>When Knoblauch was asked what inspired him to use Eminem's song, he said, ''You need to ask me that?''</p>
        <p>When he was asked if it was directed toward Steinbrenner, Knoblauch said: ''Whatever, you know? So much garbage happened, it was, whatever.''</p>
        <p>So much stuff happened. The three-error night in June when Torre advised him to leave the Stadium and go home. The nagging injuries and his first-ever stint on the disabled list, Steinbrenner's criticisms and his retorts. The lingering throwing woes and the aftereffects, which continued on Wednesday when the announcer for the ''Late Show with David Letterman'' introduced Letterman as ''the head case with the throwing problems.''</p>
        <p>The postseason has also been chaotic for Knoblauch, who did not start in Games 2, 3 and 4 of the division series against Oakland and declined to field any pregame grounders. Knoblauch shagged fly balls in the outfield on two of those occasions and talked with a reporter and friends the other times.</p>
        <p>''Maybe I won't play again in the postseason,'' Knoblauch said then.</p>
        <p>But Knoblauch returned in Game 5, rapped two singles in the first inning and has been a stabilizing force in the lineup ever since. While Knoblauch was quoted in The Hartford Courant that same day as saying, ''Why don't they replace me on the roster? They don't have anything for me to do,'' he said that the comments were meant to be private.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch wants to return to the Yankees next season. But when a reporter mentioned that he had three years left on his contract because the Yankees had agreed to a two-year, $18 million extension that has never been publicized, he raised a finger and said, ''I've got one year left.'' He declined to discuss his contract status any further.</p>
        <p>Still, Knoblauch also spoke about loving New York because it had made him stronger. There is a part of Knoblauch that wonders why his experience has been so draining, beyond the scrutiny of his throwing jitters. But he is in his third year with the Yankees and is playing in his third World Series.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't change anything,'' he said. ''We've won two World Series. I've lived in New York. I feel like I'm a New Yorker. I ain't going nowhere.''</p>
        <p>Fifty-six thousand fans will hear Eminem's voice when Knoblauch saunters to bat tonight, and Knoblauch knows that only a few will have the slightest clue what the song signifies and why he selected it to express himself. Maybe it is Knoblauch's answer to everyone, his way of saying that no one knows who he is.</p>
        <p>''And I am whatever you say I am. If I wasn't, then why would I say I am?''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
