<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vick Finds Pressure On and Off the Field</title>
    <meta content="21VICK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/21/sports/21VICK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240536"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Virginia Polytechnic Institute &amp; State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vick, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E0DB1E3EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1158" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vick Finds Pressure On and Off the Field</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses pressures faced by Virginia Tech quarterback Michael Vick both on and off field; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are some things that 4.2 speed in the 40-yard dash and a left arm that can launch a football the length of a football field cannot help you with. Like fingers poking through your face mask at the bottom of the pile and punches banging against your kidneys when you are caught near the sideline.</p>
        <p>Like the 400 pieces of mail that pour into a small box in a college post office each week, and the professional autograph hounds that play bump-and-run on you all the way to the parking lot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are some things that 4.2 speed in the 40-yard dash and a left arm that can launch a football the length of a football field cannot help you with. Like fingers poking through your face mask at the bottom of the pile and punches banging against your kidneys when you are caught near the sideline.</p>
        <p>Like the 400 pieces of mail that pour into a small box in a college post office each week, and the professional autograph hounds that play bump-and-run on you all the way to the parking lot.</p>
        <p>From those things, Michael Vick needs protection. On the field, it comes from a vigilant line that takes its nickname, the Secret Service, seriously. Off the field, it comes from a no-nonsense athletic administrator named Sharon McCloskey. Of the two, Vick, the Virginia Tech quarterback, has had an easier time picking himself up off the ground and ignoring the bruises.</p>
        <p>His Hokies are No. 1 in the New York Times computer ranking and will enter tonight's game at Syracuse with a 6-0 record. Vick's Heisman Trophy candidacy has been buoyed by impressive statistics, as well as an ineffable flair.</p>
        <p>''It's just me being me'' is how he explained a dazzling 82-yard run touchdown against Boston College three weeks ago, but it can just as well be a catchall description for his growing highlight reel.</p>
        <p>Vick, 20, admits that it has been harder being college football's most wanted man away from the field. Beyond the Heisman talk, there are questions about whether he will turn professional after this, his sophomore season. There is also speculation that his poor grades will make it necessary for him to leave college early for the National Football League.</p>
        <p>''My grades are fine right now,'' said Vick, who said his grades were not shaky, as did Virginia Tech Coach Frank Beamer. ''I can't worry about things like that and what people are saying. I hear different things every day. I think I've done a good job with it all. Sometimes it gets in your mind and you wish they didn't ask about the Heisman, or about next year. Last year I was just going out there and playing football.''</p>
        <p>Vick has done plenty of that this season, but it has taken a toll on his body. There have been late hits, hard squeezes, pinches and pokes under the cover of the pile.</p>
        <p>''I got to keep my composure and not let it get to me,'' he said. ''At the same time, I can't let guys pound on me and do whatever they want to do with me.''</p>
        <p>Of late, the Virginia Tech line has extended its protection long after a play has been completed. The linemen trail Vick's runs in full sprint to make sure their quarterback quickly gets up with a minimum of contact after he is tackled.</p>
        <p>Anthony Lambo, a senior offensive tackle from Bloomfield, N.J., is Vick's shadow, and his duties go beyond body-guarding. He can calm the quarterback. ''He's so competitive that when he makes a mistake it stays with him,'' Lambo said. ''So you just tell him to let it go.''</p>
        <p>Lambo can scold Vick, as he did against Boston College when Vick took a hard shot to the knee and then took his time hobbling back to the huddle. Lambo thought the delay might halt the Hokies' momentum.</p>
        <p>''I told him to spit on it and let's get going,'' Lambo said. ''We play so much at his speed, I needed to remind him that he sometimes needs to play at ours.''</p>
        <p>The quarterback is also not coddled by the coaching staff. Last week, in the first half against West Virginia, after Vick fumbled on the goal line, he had a curt sideline exchange with the offensive coordinator, Rickey Bustle.</p>
        <p>''You're doing the same thing you did last week -- you're running the ball with the wrong hand,'' Vick said Bustle had told him. ''He was right, and I knew it.''</p>
        <p>In the second half of the West Virginia game, Vick led the Hokies to 41 points, including touchdown passes of 72 and 64 yards in a 48-20 victory. Vick, who appears to be aware of his limitations, indicated he would return next year. Beamer said he would talk with his quarterback after the season, but he seemed to believe Vick would be back in Blacksburg, Va.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to speak for Michael, but I think the decision is going to mean more than just pure dollars,'' Beamer said. ''I think, in our conversation, he understands that he needs to continue to improve as a quarterback before he's ready to use his talents at the next level.''</p>
        <p>Away from the field, Vick has decided to slow the rush to his predicted superstardom. He has entrusted McCloskey, an associate athletic director, to help him. Her duties range from setting up the $1 million insurance policy Vick took out against injury to sending out the 5x7 photographs with his autograph to the thousands of fans requesting it.</p>
        <p>McCloskey has told dozens of agents that their brochures would go in a file, and that they should stop contacting Vick's mother, Brenda Boddie.</p>
        <p>''To his credit, he anticipated this at the beginning of the year,'' McCloskey said. ''He wanted to concentrate on football and asked for help.''</p>
        <p>There are security details to be assigned, just so Vick can leave the locker room after practice. Most nettlesome of all, however, are the professional autograph seekers. If McCloskey is not on hand to separate the true fans from the speculators, Vick is instructed to hand people her business card. She will take care of it.</p>
        <p>She kids Vick often. ''I tell Michael all the time that I can't wait until he goes to the N.F.L., that this is getting exhausting,'' McCloskey said.</p>
        <p>But most of the time she admires his poise. ''The most amazing thing is the way he handles it,'' she said. ''Most kids his age would be caught up in all this. He's not at all.''</p>
        <p>Just as on the field, Vick does not like being hemmed in off it. He has not visited his home in Newport News, Va., since midsummer. He said that beyond a few late night video games with his teammates, he has little free time. ''It's film, football and school,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Is all this worth it?</p>
        <p>''Yeah, I'm enjoying myself, especially when we're winning,'' he said. ''We're winning. We, not me. That's what I'm most proud of.''</p>
        <p>Is he worth all this fuss?</p>
        <p>''I'm a good quarterback,'' he said. ''I'm not the best quarterback yet. I still got a lot to learn.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
