<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="21FSUM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DC1E3EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1126" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>Israeli Sees Halt in Talks As Violence Flares Anew  Prime Minister Ehud Barak said he was prepared to take an indefinite ''timeout'' from the Israeli-Palestinian peace effort. The announcement followed the deaths of 10 Palestinians in clashes at Israeli checkpoints in the West Bank. The violence, coming despite an internationally brokered truce agreement early in the week, occurred on the eve of a summit meeting of Arab leaders.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Secretary General Kofi Annan addressed the General Assembly before it adopted a nonbinding resolution condemning Israel for ''excessive use of force'' against Palestinians but also supporting both sides' returning to the negotiating table.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>Israeli Sees Halt in Talks As Violence Flares Anew  Prime Minister Ehud Barak said he was prepared to take an indefinite ''timeout'' from the Israeli-Palestinian peace effort. The announcement followed the deaths of 10 Palestinians in clashes at Israeli checkpoints in the West Bank. The violence, coming despite an internationally brokered truce agreement early in the week, occurred on the eve of a summit meeting of Arab leaders.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Secretary General Kofi Annan addressed the General Assembly before it adopted a nonbinding resolution condemning Israel for ''excessive use of force'' against Palestinians but also supporting both sides' returning to the negotiating table.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>The head of the Organization for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons, Jose M. Bustani, pleaded with Israelis, Egyptians, Palestinians and others in the Middle East to adhere to a treaty banning such weapons to reduce tensions in the region.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>New Details on Warship Blast  A significantly revised account of the deadly bombing of the destroyer Cole is emerging as one aspect of the investigation focuses on shipboard security, officials said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Deal Near for Russian Mogul  A dispute between the Russian media tycoon Vladimir V. Gusinsky and his company's biggest creditor, Gazprom, whose largest shareholder is the government, moved toward resolution. An agreement could ultimately keep Media-Most, the main independent media conglomerate, from government control.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>20 Die in Mexico Fire  A fire destroyed a big nightclub in Mexico City, killing at least 20 and injuring 39. The club had repeatedly been cited for safety violations, officials said, and the deaths set off an outcry against corruption that might have contributed to the deaths.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Dozens Die in Colombia Battles  At least 56 soldiers and police officers have been killed in battles with leftist rebels in a jungle in northern Colombia, the military said. The dead include 22 soldiers aboard a Black Hawk helicopter that crashed on Thursday after coming under fire in an isolated region.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A9-13, 16</p>
        <p>Bush Would Reshape NATO And Recast Nations' Roles  If elected president, George W. Bush plans to tell NATO that the United States should no longer participate in peacekeeping in the Balkans, signaling a major new division of labor in the Western alliance, according to his senior national security aide, Condoleezza Rice. Peacekeeping in Bosnia and Kosovo, and possibly elsewhere, would be a European responsibility. The United States would focus on deterring and fighting wars in the Persian Gulf, Asia and other distant trouble spots.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and Senator John McCain, fierce rivals in the primaries, campaigned together, with the senator declaring that the governor was ''fully prepared'' to lead.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Governor Bush and his wife, Laura, reported income of $1,610,400 last year and paid $449,827, or 27.9 percent, in federal income taxes.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Public Display of Affection  President Clinton, Vice President Al Gore and their wives exchanged a flurry of hearty handshakes and air kisses at a Missouri airport that aides said was meant to discredit reports of strained relations.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Breaking With Church Body  Former President Jimmy Carter reached ''a painful decision'' to sever ties to the Southern Baptist Convention, saying parts of its ''increasingly rigid'' doctrines violated the ''basic premises of my Christian faith.''</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Student Prayer Reinstated  A federal appeals court in Atlanta reinstated a ruling that permits student-led prayer in public-school assemblies and classrooms.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Gays Question School Donation  Gay rights advocates expressed concern at an $8.35 million gift from Stephen M. Case, the chairman of America Online, and his wife, Jean, to a Florida school that she attended and that is affiliated with a church that seeks to ''cure'' homosexuals.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-7</p>
        <p>In Plea, Ex-Sergeant Links Bin Laden to Embassy Blast  Ali A. Mohamed, a former United States Army sergeant, pleaded guilty to participating in a terrorist conspiracy against Americans and directly linked Osama bin Laden to the bombing of the American Embassy in Nairobi, Kenya, in 1998.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New Jersey Senate Debate  Jon S. Corzine, a Democrat, and Representative Bob Franks, a Republican, avoided the kind of dramatic confrontation that Mr. Franks, who is trailing, had been hoping for.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Beliefs</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-18</p>
        <p>Subway Series Begins Tonight  Mike Piazza will be the designated hitter and Todd Pratt will take his place behind the plate when the Mets take the field at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Golota Quits; Tyson Wins  Andrew Golota quit his heavyweight fight against Mike Tyson just before the third round was set to begin, handing Tyson a TKO victory.</p>
        <p>D15</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B9-20</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Drug Makers Assail F.D.A.  Pharmaceutical companies, facing possible restrictions on phenylpropanolamine, a major ingredient in popular over-the-counter products, said that their products were safe and that the F.D.A. had unwarranted faith in a questionable study.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Radiation in the Soil  The Energy Department has concluded that the amount of plutonium and other man-made radioactive elements released into soil or buried in flimsy containers during the first four decades of nuclear weapons manufacture was 10 times larger than it had estimated.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Honeywell Deal Falls Through  A counteroffer from G.E. broke up United Technologies' deal to buy Honeywell International, setting off a rush of activity as other suitors -- like Siemens and Tyco -- weighed bids for all or part of Honeywell.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>U.S. Admonishes Airlines  The Transportation Department warned airlines that they faced sanctions if they did not tell consumers who made reservations by telephone that cheaper fares might be available on the Internet.</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Positive Week for Stocks  The Nasdaq gained 64.54 points, or 1.9 percent, to 3,483.14; the Dow rose 83.61 points, to 10,226.59; and the S.&amp; P. 500 rose 8.17 points, to 1,396.93, giving the three major averages their first weekly gains in seven weeks.</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Japanese Insurance Bankruptcy  Kyoei Life Insurance, facing nearly $43 billion in liabilities, sought court protection from creditors in Japan's biggest bankruptcy since World War II. The move came after talks with Prudential about a possible joint venture ended without an agreement.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A14-15</p>
        <p>Editorials: Scholarly editions in jeopardy; America's bolshevik; the odysseys of two fans -- learning to like the Yankees, learning to love the Mets.</p>
        <p>Columns: Frank Rich, Anthony Lewis.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B17  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B20  Crossword</p>
        <p>B16  Weather</p>
        <p>D17  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A9</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
