<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Yankees, It's a Workout In Progress</title>
    <meta content="Y21TEX$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/21/sports/21TEXA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240459"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clemens, Roger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pettitte, Andy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E3D7113EF932A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Yankees, It's a Workout In Progress</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees pitchers Roger Clemens and Andy Pettitte discuss preparing for World Series against New York Mets; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Andy Pettitte would reach the seventh or eighth inning this year, and he would sense his fastball starting to lose its zip, fatigue gnawing at his body. At least that is what he thought.</p>
        <p>Pettitte would review the pitch charts after his games, and time and again, he would be surprised to see that radar clocked his fastball at 90 to 91 miles an hour in the late innings, excellent for a pitcher who had often topped out at 87 or 88 m.p.h. at the beginning of games in 1999. The difference, Pettitte is sure, is rooted in the training that he and Roger Clemens did together in the off-season in Texas, where the pitchers live about 30 minutes apart; they have continued that training throughout this season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Andy Pettitte would reach the seventh or eighth inning this year, and he would sense his fastball starting to lose its zip, fatigue gnawing at his body. At least that is what he thought.</p>
        <p>Pettitte would review the pitch charts after his games, and time and again, he would be surprised to see that radar clocked his fastball at 90 to 91 miles an hour in the late innings, excellent for a pitcher who had often topped out at 87 or 88 m.p.h. at the beginning of games in 1999. The difference, Pettitte is sure, is rooted in the training that he and Roger Clemens did together in the off-season in Texas, where the pitchers live about 30 minutes apart; they have continued that training throughout this season.</p>
        <p>''I think we've really pushed each other,'' said Pettitte, who will pitch Game 1 of the World Series tonight for the Yankees, with Clemens scheduled to pitch Game 2 tomorrow. ''Neither one of us wants to get too far behind the other, and the competition has helped both of us.''</p>
        <p>Pettitte is 6 feet 5 inches, 230 pounds, his shoulders broad and sturdy; he mentioned several times during the 1999 season that he felt good about his conditioning. Clemens called Pettitte last November and asked him to join his off-season workouts, which have been overseen by Brian McNamee, the Yankees' assistant strength and conditioning coach.</p>
        <p>Pettitte, a longtime unabashed fan of Clemens, was thrilled by the request and drove 30 minutes along Beltway 8, through Deer Park, to Clemens's home. After that first workout -- a day spent running through a training circuit and lifting weights, with abdominal exercises between each set -- Pettitte was overwhelmed. ''I think Andy had this predisposed notion that what he was doing was good enough,'' McNamee said, ''and he realized he wasn't in good shape. He realized that the workouts we were doing was a beginning to an end.''</p>
        <p>So two or three mornings a week, Pettitte would jump in his car and head over to the Clemens compound for workouts, sometimes twice a day. They pushed each other, the 38-year-old Clemens like an older brother to Pettitte, who is 10 years younger.</p>
        <p>''I could try to be cool about it and say it wasn't any big deal, but I'd be lying,'' Pettitte said. ''It's been fun for me. Growing up, Roger was obviously the guy I watched. When I came into the big leagues, I learned to hate him.</p>
        <p>''And we had that time where Roger hit Brosius,'' Pettitte added, referring to a 1998 incident with the Yankees' third baseman, Scott Brosius, ''but then all of a sudden he's over here with us, and I'm playing golf with him. Now he's taken me under his wing, and that's been special for me.''</p>
        <p>McNamee believes they have benefited from each other -- Pettitte learning from Clemens's work ethic, and Clemens gaining because he was pushed by a younger player.</p>
        <p>The biggest changes in Pettitte's workout regimen were in the abdominal and leg work. McNamee developed an exercise that the pitchers refer to as a power ab: while Pettitte or Clemens is doing a crunch, McNamee places added pressure on the movement to further isolate and develop abdominal strength.</p>
        <p>''That's a big part of why I firmly believe I can still throw the way that I do,'' Clemens said. ''It helps you keep your body in balance, and keeps the pressure away from your back. It keeps you strong, and it's all about longevity.''</p>
        <p>Clemens was about 30 when he started to change his off-season workouts, beginning them shortly after the end of the regular season.</p>
        <p>''I think Andy will find out that there's a point in his career where it becomes a year-round thing,'' Clemens said. ''When you're playing through October, there's a point where you shut your body down. But you can't wait all the way to January to start up again.</p>
        <p>''I saw a huge improvement with Andy's body, the shape. When you really started noticing it is in spring training, because it almost feels secondary at that point.''</p>
        <p>The two pitchers have adjusted their workouts throughout the year to account for the grueling toll the season takes. Clemens and Pettitte believe their workouts have helped them stay strong when their pitch counts mount deep in games and recover quickly the day after they pitch.</p>
        <p>Pettitte and Clemens have demonstrated consistency this year. Pettitte had a winning record in every month after losing his only decision in April, and he finished at 19-9.</p>
        <p>Clemens was the Yankees' most dominant pitcher after June. Opponents batted just .226 against him in his first 60 pitches of a game, and .240 from pitches 61 to 120, a negligible difference, and remarkable for a 38-year-old. In his last start, against Seattle in Game 4 of the American League Championship Series, Clemens was throwing fastballs clocked at 99 m.p.h., his highest reading of the year.</p>
        <p>Clemens said, ''I don't think there's any question that the success we've had goes back to the hard work you put in during the off-season.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
