<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Major Bidder For City Trash Agrees to Pay $252,000 Fine</title>
    <meta content="22TRAS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Allied Waste Industries</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Browning-Ferris Industries</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipton, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E3D81E3EF931A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="408" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Major Bidder For City Trash Agrees to Pay $252,000 Fine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Allied Waste Industries, Arizona company bidding on New York City contract to export most of city's residential trash, agrees to pay $252,000 fine after investigators determine that Browning-Ferris Industries, trash disposal company it acquired last year, had violated city rules and overbilled small number of its city clients (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Arizona company bidding on a New York City contract to export most of the city's residential trash has agreed to pay a $252,000 fine after investigators determined that a trash disposal company it acquired last year had violated city rules and overbilled a small number of its city clients.</p>
        <p>The fine has been paid by Allied Waste Industries, one of the nation's largest trash disposal outfits, which is bidding for the right to handle as much as 6,000 tons of city trash a day, about half the daily load of residential waste.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Arizona company bidding on a New York City contract to export most of the city's residential trash has agreed to pay a $252,000 fine after investigators determined that a trash disposal company it acquired last year had violated city rules and overbilled a small number of its city clients.</p>
        <p>The fine has been paid by Allied Waste Industries, one of the nation's largest trash disposal outfits, which is bidding for the right to handle as much as 6,000 tons of city trash a day, about half the daily load of residential waste.</p>
        <p>In July 1999, Allied Waste bought Browning-Ferris Industries, which is one of the nation's largest trash companies and which has a particularly large presence in New York City.</p>
        <p>City investigators at the Trade Waste Commission -- established in 1996 to reduce corruption and the influence of organized crime in the waste hauling industry in the city -- found that Browning-Ferris officials had misled the city by suggesting that the company had audited its trash collections to ensure it was charging its customers fairly, an official who participated in the settlement said.</p>
        <p>In fact, investigators learned, Browning-Ferris did not conduct a so-called waste stream survey in 1997 on 1,900 customers as required, resulting in a $201,000 fine, the official said. In early 1999, when the company requested permission for a rate increase for 103 commercial customers, it again was asked to audit its waste collections, but it did so for only 1 of the 103. That resulted in a $51,000 fine, the official said.</p>
        <p>Edward A. McDonald, a lawyer representing Allied Waste, did not dispute the charges, but he said last night that Allied executives should not be blamed for wrongdoing committed by Browning-Ferris. The Browning-Ferris officials involved in the matter no longer work for Allied, he said, but the company agreed to pay the fine because when it acquired Browning-Ferris's assets, it also agreed to accept its liabilities.</p>
        <p>''Simply put, it didn't happen on Allied's watch,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
