<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Digging Up The Perfect Potato, and Other Joys</title>
    <meta content="22LERM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lerman, Liz, Dance Exchange</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunning, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lerman, Liz</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E5DF1E3EF931A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Digging Up The Perfect Potato, and Other Joys</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
      <dateline>BECKET, Mass., Aug. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jennifer Dunning reviews performance by Liz Lerman Dance Exchange at Jacob's Pillow; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Liz Lerman has made a vibrant, provocative career out of fixing on a moment -- an idea, an emotion, an everyday event -- and making it come alive in simple, plain-spoken dance. God is in the details in her work.</p>
        <p>Her latest project is the three-year ''Hallelujah'' series, in which she and her Maryland-based company, Liz Lerman Dance Exchange, settle into areas around the nation to discover and make theater of the ''small hallelujahs'' of daily lives there. One such location is the Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival here in the Berkshire hills, where ''In Praise of Fertile Fields,'' the latest ''Hallelujah,'' was performed on Sunday night in the Doris Duke Studio Theater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Liz Lerman has made a vibrant, provocative career out of fixing on a moment -- an idea, an emotion, an everyday event -- and making it come alive in simple, plain-spoken dance. God is in the details in her work.</p>
        <p>Her latest project is the three-year ''Hallelujah'' series, in which she and her Maryland-based company, Liz Lerman Dance Exchange, settle into areas around the nation to discover and make theater of the ''small hallelujahs'' of daily lives there. One such location is the Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival here in the Berkshire hills, where ''In Praise of Fertile Fields,'' the latest ''Hallelujah,'' was performed on Sunday night in the Doris Duke Studio Theater.</p>
        <p>During a residency last year at the Pillow, which commissioned the piece, Ms. Lerman and her performers burrowed into the festival's rich 68-year history and into the lore of local gardeners. Ms. Lerman was also interested in the biblical connotation of the festival's name.</p>
        <p>The material surfaces throughout ''In Praise of Fertile Fields'' in telling and evocative ways. One of Ms. Lerman's major sources was a 1942 diary kept by Esther Miller, then the Pillow cook, which notes day-to-day activities in simple, eloquent detail. Martha Wittman plays Miller, who also planted the Pillow's kitchen garden, as an observant woman of quiet dignity. Her presence is a thread that almost connects the disparate elements of the piece.</p>
        <p>In one of the loveliest passages,  Ms. Wittman, simultaneously playing both Miller and a teacher at the Pillow, shapes a young dancer's plantlike body at the barre, admiring her strong roots and worrying that a small spot may be blight. But nothing else in the piece ties the material together so magically.</p>
        <p>In fact, there are so many ingredients in this pot that the stew has no discernible flavor. A strangely off-key jokiness doesn't help, either. The spoken litany of plant names is just right but marred by pointless touches like having a dancer mime a noose while saying, ''Croke us.''</p>
        <p>Potatoes figure prominently in the dance. Digging for potatoes, one gardener told the dancers, is like digging for gold. A dopey conversation between two potatoes held by dancers, one a sophisticated potato and the other a homebody, is inexplicable in the context of the piece.</p>
        <p>The creative work of Ted Shawn, the founder of the Pillow, is trivialized by a segment in which a Lerman dancer playing Shawn conducts a cutesy rehearsal with potatoes as performers. Just as strange is a segment in which bits of Shawn's choreography are woven into the piece as  Thomas Dwyer reads Shawn's notes as an increasingly impassioned sermon. The biblical overtones are there, but the piece as a whole is not.</p>
        <p>Robert Een composed the score for cello, percussion, accordion and voice; additional piano music is by Chopin. Naoko Nagata designed the costumes and Lewis Folden the set, with lighting by Michael Mazzolla.</p>
        <p>The resonant Lerman troupe, which was expanded with local performers, also includes Adrienne Clancy, Elizabeth Johnson, Maggie Kast, Pene McCourty, Kazu Nakamura, Vincent Thomas and Marvin Webb. Maura Keefe's genial pre-performance talk made sense of the work's complex creative process.</p>
        <p>The closer Ms. Lerman gets to pure anecdote, the better she is. ''In Praise of Animals and Their People'' is a wonder, particularly in the way Ms. Lerman weaves together and juxtaposes animal and human movement. A grand finale featuring three  Frisbee-catching pups from the All-American Fly Dogs was funny and dazzling. Another highlight was ''My Horse,'' a vignette for a glum Mr. Dwyer and Margot Greenlee as his horse, Ginger. Peter DiMuro stood out for his teasing performing, especially when playing a wild-haired Ms. Lerman.</p>
        <p>The evening opened with ''Gates of Praise,'' set to music by Andy Teirstein. The theme of this group piece, intended as a prologue for each ''Hallelujah'' program, is that light illuminates a gateway to celebration in even the darkest moments. All the reaching upward looked portentously murky before the theme was established by the other dances.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
