<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patients Are Discovering 'My Doctor, the Author'</title>
    <meta content="22WRIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health and Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verghese, Abraham (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markel, Howard (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E2DE123EF931A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patients Are Discovering 'My Doctor, the Author'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD MARKEL, M.D.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Markel, Howard (Dr)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>More and more doctors are sharing their wisdom and experience in books, articles and columns; photos; Dr Abraham Verghese, internist who wrote AIDS memoir, says he is struck by how much of what he learned in medical schools has helped him to be a writer, and vice versa (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Each year it seems that more and more physicians are putting aside their stethoscopes for word processors. Indeed, the most casual look at publishers' book lists or major magazines and newspapers demonstrates that an increasing cadre of doctors is writing best-selling works of nonfiction, novels, plays, motion pictures and essays.  Even professional conferences are being held to encourage physicians with literary aspirations.</p>
        <p>Doctors have been writing about their patients since at least the time of Hippocrates. But for most of this vast stretch of time, the writing was confined to an audience of other physicians, and the main goal was to inform them about the natural history of disease. But today's era is characterized by the presentation of medical narratives to large lay audiences.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Each year it seems that more and more physicians are putting aside their stethoscopes for word processors. Indeed, the most casual look at publishers' book lists or major magazines and newspapers demonstrates that an increasing cadre of doctors is writing best-selling works of nonfiction, novels, plays, motion pictures and essays.  Even professional conferences are being held to encourage physicians with literary aspirations.</p>
        <p>Doctors have been writing about their patients since at least the time of Hippocrates. But for most of this vast stretch of time, the writing was confined to an audience of other physicians, and the main goal was to inform them about the natural history of disease. But today's era is characterized by the presentation of medical narratives to large lay audiences.</p>
        <p>The mass appeal of this literary genre is hardly surprising. What could be more central to the understanding of the human condition than a reflection on the diseases to which we are all susceptible? Perhaps more to the point, doctor stories are dramatic with clear beginnings, middles and ends.</p>
        <p>To many observers, the practice of medicine and the writing of books seem disparate, despite exemplars like the playwright-physician Anton Chekhov and the poet-pediatrician William Carlos Williams. But those who practice these dual crafts fervently defend how complementary they are. Dr. Sherwin B. Nuland, the National Book Award-winning author of ''How We Die,'' explained:</p>
        <p>''I'm a surgeon who has been at this calling for a very long time, and even the least introspective of us cannot escape without having developed an entire steamer trunkful of experiences, impressions, philosophies and musings on the human condition, values and ethics. Writing brings everything forward. It enables us to recall things as they were experienced by us while they were happening; it enables us to find out what we think, often for the first time; it is a process that is totally honest if we are willing to allow ourselves to feel those emotions that are coming forth from preserved memories and then scribble the accompanying words down, uncensored.''</p>
        <p>Abraham Verghese, an internist who wrote the AIDS memoir ''My Own Country,'' said of the dual roles: ''To me, they're a seamless enterprise. I'm really struck by how much of what I learned in medical school has helped me to be a writer, and how much of what I learn as a writer helps my thinking as a physician. They are very parallel disciplines. When you take a patient's clinical history, what is that but a story?  What makes a good doctor is that he or she takes the story down well, sees the links and  makes the connections toward a diagnosis.  That's also what writing is about.''</p>
        <p>Doctor stories are not only confined to best sellers or lay publications. Several prominent medical journals regularly feature personal essays by physicians about their experiences. The best-known column, ''A Piece of My Mind,'' has run in The Journal of the American Medical Association each week for more than 20 years.</p>
        <p>Roxanne Young, who has edited this series since 1984, said she receives more than 400 submissions a year from doctors around the world, even though only about 10 percent make it into print. These stories have been  widely anthologized and taught in medical schools, and have inspired two books of collected essays.</p>
        <p>What compels busy physicians to reveal their thoughts and feelings to a readership of more than 400,000 clinical peers? Ms. Young believes that the simple act of writing is a catharsis, a part of the self-healing process that allows doctors to confront troubling issues -- fear, failure, guilt -- and to resolve them from within. It is also a means to honor a patient for helping them to come to grips not only with death but with life.</p>
        <p>As more physicians take to the pen, professional conferences have sprouted to bring them together for readings of their work, lectures and workshops on the rewards and pitfalls of being a doctor-writer.  The largest such symposium held so far was the Narrative Matters conference sponsored by the health policy journal Health Affairs and the W. K. Kellogg Foundation this past March.</p>
        <p>It brought together leading physician-writers in the United States with interested editors and policy makers. More than 70 participants discussed the parallels of creating literature and doctoring.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fitzhugh Mullan, a pediatrician who wrote ''Vital Signs,'' a memoir about overcoming cancer, organized the conference with specific goals in mind.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to give the genre a clearer and more prominent role,'' Dr. Mullan said, ''to stir the pot of the narrative essay as it relates to medical practice and health policy. I really believe that amidst the increasingly powerful quantitative science that exists today, human observation remains and should remain an important force in the forming of opinion in the national dialogue on health matters.''</p>
        <p>One of the most serious debates in the field has to do with confidentiality. Since antiquity, doctors have promised patients not to discuss their individual cases, except with other doctors, both as a means of protection and to encourage frank patient-doctor conversations.</p>
        <p>When writing about a particular patient, most doctor-writers will change the name and identifying details. But sometimes mistakes are made. In 1926, Dr. William Carlos Williams heard a remarkable story about a person while on his medical rounds. As was his habit, he wrote it down quickly as it was told to him without changing any of the details. Several months later, when he sent the story off to a magazine, he forgot to change the subject's name.</p>
        <p>As Dr. Williams recounted in ''The Autobiography of William Carlos Williams,'' the subject recognized himself immediately and promptly brought a lawsuit against the physician for what was then the princely sum of $15,000. Dr. Williams settled for $5,000, an amount that equaled his annual salary, and never made that mistake again.</p>
        <p>Some participants in the Narrative Matters conference argued for obtaining written permission or informed consent and even showing the article or essay to the patient before publishing it. But many others argued that such steps were not necessary, provided that the author changed the obvious identifying features and at least asked for oral consent.</p>
        <p>''My patients haven't been particularly aware of or worried about my writing about them,'' Dr. Mullan said, ''but many colleagues have expressed concern since I have written about my life in medicine. Not infrequently, I have had friends say in my presence, be nice to Fitz or you'll wind up in his next book. They are only half-kidding.''</p>
        <p>This points up the major problem that the art of writing is cannibalistic in nature and the telling of great stories often fails to meet the medical profession's ethical standards of studying patients.</p>
        <p>Dr. Nuland observes that there is no possibility of considerations of ethics, confidentiality or even loyalty to participants, only the reality of what the writer feels as the truth of what he is describing.</p>
        <p>''I change the names, and never consider the consequences of the text that results from the process,'' he said. ''Others have written that all writers ultimately betray those who are their subjects, but they would betray themselves if it were otherwise.  Writing is not an exercise in discretion, it is an exercise in truth. In this sense, the story belongs to the storyteller, because he is the truth seeker.''</p>
        <p>Given the national fascination with all things medical, it seems likely that both doctor stories and debates over privacy issues will continue to thrive. But among those in medicine who believe in the power of stories and the importance of communicating them to a wide audience, there seems to be wide agreement with Chekhov, who in 1888 wrote to his publisher: ''I have two professions and not one. Medicine is my lawful wife and literature is my mistress. When I get tired of one, I spend the night with the other. Though it's disorderly, it's not so dull and besides, neither loses anything through my infidelity.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
