<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>China's Migrants Find Europe's Open Back Door: The Balkans</title>
    <meta content="22YUGO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224500"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">China-International Relations-Serbia</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bosnia and Herzegovina</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Croatia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gall, Carlotta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EEDA1E3EF931A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>China's Migrants Find Europe's Open Back Door: The Balkans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARLOTTA GALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gall, Carlotta</byline>
      <dateline>ZAGREB, Croatia, Aug. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Balkans have become latest gateway to Western Europe for tens of thousands of immigrants from China, South Asia and Middle Eastern countries like Iran and Iraq; Yugoslavia in particular, which has cultivated strong ties with China, has opened gates to thousands of Chinese intent on reaching Western Europe; its consulates in China freely grant tourist visas to Chinese, and legal passage into Yugoslavia eases way for illegal entry to rest of Europe; Bosnia has its own flow of illegal immigrants from Iran and Iraq and other countries with which Muslim-led government in Sarajevo has maintained strong ties, and Croatia is experiencing staggering increase in human traffic; influx underscores growing alarm among Western diplomats and migration officials that sophisticated and far-reaching network of human traffickers from Asia has switched attention from US and is looking to Europe; traffickers have found troubled and unruly countries of former Yugoslavia, with porous borders and lack of immigration laws and agreements, are ideal gateway to West; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The chaotic lands of the Balkans have become the latest gateway to Western Europe for tens of thousands of illegal immigrants from China, South Asia and Middle Eastern countries like Iran and Iraq, according to Western diplomats, local officials and the increasing number of refugees who get caught.</p>
        <p>President Slobodan Milosevic of Yugoslavia, in particular, has opened the gates to thousands of Chinese intent on reaching Western Europe. Under Mr. Milosevic, Yugoslavia has cultivated strong ties with China, which was Belgrade's ally during the war over Kosovo last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The chaotic lands of the Balkans have become the latest gateway to Western Europe for tens of thousands of illegal immigrants from China, South Asia and Middle Eastern countries like Iran and Iraq, according to Western diplomats, local officials and the increasing number of refugees who get caught.</p>
        <p>President Slobodan Milosevic of Yugoslavia, in particular, has opened the gates to thousands of Chinese intent on reaching Western Europe. Under Mr. Milosevic, Yugoslavia has cultivated strong ties with China, which was Belgrade's ally during the war over Kosovo last year.</p>
        <p>Yugoslav consulates in China freely grant tourist visas to Chinese, and the legal passage to Yugoslavia eases the way for illegal entry to the rest of Europe. Typically, the Chinese arrive by plane in Belgrade, then travel to Bosnia and on to Croatia. Then they head for the Adriatic coast and hope to reach Italy.</p>
        <p>Bosnia has its own flow of illegal immigrants from Iran, Iraq and other countries with which the Muslim-led government in Sarajevo maintains strong ties out of gratitude for the support of Iran and Arab nations during the 1992-95 Bosnian war.</p>
        <p>But Croatia is experiencing a staggering increase in human traffic. Barely a week goes by without a new report of dozens of Chinese or other migrants being caught on the coast or inland.</p>
        <p>The authorities here have caught 10,000 illegal immigrants trying to cross into Croatia in the first half of this year, compared with 8,000 in all of 1999. On Aug. 12, for instance, 52 illegal immigrants were sent back to Bosnia, with which Croatia shares a 1,200-mile, largely mountainous and unpatrolled border. A few days later, 36 more migrants were caught in the town of Varazdin, close to the border with Hungary and Slovenia, said Miroslav Cindori, the head of a detention center outside Zagreb.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Cindori's center, a converted motel, young men in track suits and plastic sandals wander around and, using sign language, beg for cigarettes through the wire fence.</p>
        <p>Mostly Chinese, these men are illegal immigrants caught by the Croatian authorities, and they now await deportation. They represent a minuscule part of Europe's latest headache caused by Belgrade.</p>
        <p>The 85 men and 2 women detained here have mostly come through in groups, organized by a shadowy but extensive criminal network of human traffickers, who are suddenly using the Balkans for access to Europe, said Duc Tran of the International Organization for Migration, in Zagreb.</p>
        <p>None of the Chinese detainees wanted to talk or be photographed. ''No, no English, no, no,'' said one, smiling cheerfully but not stopping to talk. But other detainees, from Bangladesh, Tunisia and Iraq, were eager to talk and urgently asked for help. ''We took the wrong road,'' Shahabuddin, from Dhaka, Bangladesh, explained sheepishly. ''We wanted to go to Italy, and they stopped us and said, 'No, this is Croatia.' ''</p>
        <p>Their stories appear to confirm the growing alarm among Western diplomats and migration officials that a sophisticated and far-reaching network of human traffickers from Asia has switched its attention from the United States and is now looking to Europe. The traffickers have found that the troubled and unruly countries of the former Yugoslavia, with porous borders and a lack of immigration laws and agreements, are an ideal gateway to the West.</p>
        <p>Officials in Croatia recently signed an agreement with Bosnia in an effort to halt the human flow, but they lack the diplomatic contacts needed to reach a similar agreement with Mr. Milosevic's government in Belgrade.</p>
        <p>Chinese gangs have switched the focus of their activities toward Europe, Mr. Tran said. ''There has been a change in the final destination since the clampdown by the U.S. government, which has cut down illegal immigration to the United States,'' he said. ''Europe is now the specific destination of the Chinese.''</p>
        <p>In past years, Mr. Tran has dealt with waves of illegal immigrants from China who passed through Central America in an attempt to get to North America. It is estimated that as many as 500,000 Chinese tried to emigrate last year, he said.</p>
        <p>In recent years, China has generally not shown the same concern over barring its citizens from leaving as the old Soviet Union did. Furthermore, many emigrating Chinese are from southeast coastal areas where illicit traffic, in people as well as goods, is well-established.</p>
        <p>A large number of these people are now coming to Europe, taking advantage of the new Yugoslav route.</p>
        <p>''What triggered it was the granting of visas by Belgrade,'' Mr. Tran said. ''Two DC-10's come in a week to Belgrade. You pay $500 to $900 for a ticket, and you are in Belgrade.''</p>
        <p>The Serbian capital has a sizable Chinese community and an entire Chinese section in the vast open-air market that grew up in Belgrade over the last decade to circumvent sanctions and enable people in Belgrade to buy smuggled consumer goods. The groups of Chinese arriving by plane ''are not going to Serbia for business,'' Mr. Tran said. ''They may do some trade, but their final destination is Europe.''</p>
        <p>The lucky immigrants who make it through Bosnia and Croatia head for Italy by boat. Once there, they can travel freely within the block of European Union countries that are bound by the Schengen agreement and have abolished passport checks.</p>
        <p>Belgrade is almost certainly making money out of the scheme, said Dr. Thomas O'Rourke, acting chief of mission in Zagreb for the International Office of Migration. Besides the visa and ticket sales, there is talk that the Chinese can buy residency permits in Serbia for a few thousand dollars, Mr. Tran said.</p>
        <p>Diplomats and immigration officials add that Mr. Milosevic, already indicted on charges of war crimes and widely viewed as an international pariah, may enjoy causing another problem for his foes. ''He's irritating the West and making money at the same time,'' said a European diplomat in Zagreb.</p>
        <p>Yet the real concern is that the movement of illegal immigrants appears to be highly organized and run by international criminal rings who have realized that smuggling people for high fees is more profitable and less risky than trafficking in drugs, Mr. Tran said.</p>
        <p>The traffic in Chinese migrants in Western Europe came to light in June when the bodies of 58 Chinese were found in an airtight container on a truck in Dover, England.</p>
        <p>The Chinese travel in groups, and are often shipped to prearranged employers, who then recoup the cost from the immigrants' wages in sweatshops or restaurants or in the sex trade. Passage to the West can cost up to $60,000, Dr. O'Rourke said. In some cases, a whole village will join together to send the young men abroad so they can then support the village with their foreign earnings, said Mr. Cindori of the immigrant detention center.</p>
        <p>The latest group of 35 Chinese men in his center were arrested in the coastal port of Sibenik after they were returned from Italy. They had no passports and said very little when they arrived, Mr. Cindori said, but after a few days a phone call was made.</p>
        <p>Then, he said, their passports started arriving in the mail, some from Belgrade, some from Sarajevo and some from Zagreb. All the men are from the same place in China, the coastal province of Zhejiang. They received tourist visas at the Yugoslav Consulate in nearby Shanghai and flew into Belgrade, Mr. Cindori said.</p>
        <p>The Muslims who come through Bosnia arrive on flights from Istanbul and Tehran. A plane arrives from Iran every week and returns empty, Mr. Tran said. ''As soon as they get off the plane, there are buses waiting outside, and they are gone,'' he said.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Smuggling Plot Investigated</p>
        <p>BELGRADE, Serbia, Aug. 21 -- Reuters</p>
        <p>The Yugoslav Army is investigating whether two of its soldiers were involved in a plot to smuggle a group of Chinese illegal immigrants into Italy, Belgrade news media said today.</p>
        <p>The police in Montenegro, the smaller of two republics that constitute present day Yugoslavia, arrested the two soldiers -- Cpl. Zeljko Modosan and Capt. Aleksandar Todorovic -- on Saturday. Twenty-five Chinese people and another man discovered in a van at a checkpoint were detained, the newspaper Blic said.</p>
        <p>The other man with them, Dragoljub Vlaovic, was the organizer of the illegal transport scheme, it said.</p>
        <p>The report said the two soldiers were suspected of having forged travel documents and having put military license plates on the van transporting the migrants.</p>
        <p>Army units in Montenegro controlled by the Yugoslav president, Slobodan Milosevic, and police officers loyal to the pro-Western Montenegrin leader, Milo Djukanovic, have over the past few weeks been involved in a number of smuggling incidents.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
