<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ward Battles Brisby and Questions of His Size</title>
    <meta content="22JETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/22/sports/22JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224483"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ward, Dedric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E3DB1E3EF931A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ward Battles Brisby and Questions of His Size</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Aug. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New York Jets wide receiver Dedric Ward; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vincent Brisby had no sooner signed his contract with the Jets last week than the speculation began. Just how long would it take him, a 6-foot-3-inch veteran who learned much of the Jets' offensive system in New England under the former Jets assistant Charlie Weis, to bump the No. 2 receiver, Dedric Ward, for a starting job?</p>
        <p>It has been easy to overlook Ward throughout his career. He was the third wheel while Keyshawn Johnson and Wayne Chrebet played out their dysfunctional relationship in full view. But the days of anonymity ended when the Jets did not select a wide receiver who could replace Johnson in this year's draft and then did not acquire a big-name free-agent receiver, thrusting the starting job into Ward's lap.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vincent Brisby had no sooner signed his contract with the Jets last week than the speculation began. Just how long would it take him, a 6-foot-3-inch veteran who learned much of the Jets' offensive system in New England under the former Jets assistant Charlie Weis, to bump the No. 2 receiver, Dedric Ward, for a starting job?</p>
        <p>It has been easy to overlook Ward throughout his career. He was the third wheel while Keyshawn Johnson and Wayne Chrebet played out their dysfunctional relationship in full view. But the days of anonymity ended when the Jets did not select a wide receiver who could replace Johnson in this year's draft and then did not acquire a big-name free-agent receiver, thrusting the starting job into Ward's lap.</p>
        <p>Midway through training camp, Coach Al Groh declared that any competition for No. 2 receiver was over and that Ward had won, unless someone proved he could do the job better.</p>
        <p>Ward has been serviceable but unspectacular in the preseason, catching 9 passes for 160 yards, an average of 17.8 yards a catch, and no touchdowns. And he has been trailed throughout by questions about whether the Jets' offense can function with two pint-sized receivers and nobody to take the heat off the 5-10 Chrebet, who is sure to draw increased coverage now that he is the Jets' premier receiver.</p>
        <p>''That's what critics have been about all along,'' said Ward, who is 5-9. ''The aspect of what you can do versus what you can't do. Right now, we're going to focus on things we do well. We have a lot of flexibility. A bunch of guys who can get downfield. With the lack of height, you have to use speed and quickness to your advantage.''</p>
        <p>The Jets must hope so, because while their offense has performed well in the preseason -- quarterback Vinny Testaverde and Chrebet have repeatedly displayed their ability to connect on the field, and Curtis Martin had the best preseason of his career -- the receivers, Chrebet excepted, have been underwhelming.</p>
        <p>Fred Coleman has been cut and Yatil Green, signed just before training camp opened, is not likely to survive the next cutdown. The rookies Laveranues Coles (8 receptions for 135 yards) and Windrell Hayes (10 for 108 yards) have been inconsistent, and that has hindered their ability to develop a Chrebet-like chemistry with Testaverde.</p>
        <p>That leaves Ward to fend off the challenge from Brisby, who catapulted into the third-receiver job upon arrival, while adjusting to his new role.</p>
        <p>''I think I'll move around a lot more than I have in the past,'' Ward said. ''Myself and Wayne are the two most familiar guys at receiver. My flexibility will make me that much more versatile.''</p>
        <p>Ward laughed off recent suggestions by Johnson that he -- not Chrebet -- should be the Jets' No. 1 receiver. But as Brisby sets up base in the nearby locker once used by Johnson, the inevitable question lingers about whether Ward will even be No. 2 much longer.</p>
        <p>''Dedric has made a lot of big plays in the past,'' Testaverde said. ''Sometimes in the preseason, you don't have as many opportunities because you're splitting time with players, and we're trying to work in new guys. He's a guy quarterbacks can count on to go in and play consistently.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>The Jets cut the third-year tight end BLAKE SPENCE on Monday, paring their roster to 61 players. The Jets have to get to 53 by Sunday. Spence, a fifth-round draft choice in 1998, played in 16 games over the past two seasons, mostly on special teams and in third-down situations. His career highlight: he became the first player in team history to block a punt in a playoff game when he did so against Denver in the 1999 American Football Conference championship game.</p>
        <p>Quarterback VINNY TESTAVERDE said he had not given KEYSHAWN JOHNSON's ongoing commentary about the Jets and WAYNE CHREBET a second thought. ''I don't know if Keyshawn has a hang-up with Wayne,'' Testaverde said. ''Maybe he has some ill feelings toward the organization. I know Wayne tries not to pay attention to it. We can't be concerned with outside influences.'' . . . For the first time in weeks, the Jets had everyone at practice Monday, with Testaverde, AARON GLENN and BERNIE PARMALEE returning.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
