<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MetroStars Are Upset At Diallo</title>
    <meta content="22SOCCER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224578"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER: NOTEBOOK AND STANDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metrostars</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Mutiny</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diallo, Mamadou</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ammann, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EFDF1F3EF931A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MetroStars Are Upset At Diallo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>MetroStars are angry with Tampa Bay Mutiny's Mamadou Diallo, who kneed Mike Ammann in rib cage and stepped on his face during recent game; Ammann is out for season with injuries that forced him to stay in Tampa hospital until Aug 21 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The MetroStars are developing a great deal of animosity for Tampa Bay's Mamadou Diallo, who kneed Mike Ammann in the rib cage and stepped on his face during last Wednesday's game. Ammann is out for the season with injuries that forced him to stay in a Tampa, Fla., hospital until yesterday, when he was finally able to get on a plane home to New Jersey.</p>
        <p>In Sunday's 5-3 victory over Colorado at Giants Stadium, several MetroStars called Diallo a punk, but Mike Petke went a step further.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The MetroStars are developing a great deal of animosity for Tampa Bay's Mamadou Diallo, who kneed Mike Ammann in the rib cage and stepped on his face during last Wednesday's game. Ammann is out for the season with injuries that forced him to stay in a Tampa, Fla., hospital until yesterday, when he was finally able to get on a plane home to New Jersey.</p>
        <p>In Sunday's 5-3 victory over Colorado at Giants Stadium, several MetroStars called Diallo a punk, but Mike Petke went a step further.</p>
        <p>After he scored the last goal for the MetroStars, Petke pulled off his team jersey near the sideline in front of the team bench to reveal a T-shirt underneath that read Aug. 16: Crime of the Century in the front and ''Revenge is Coming'' on the back.</p>
        <p>After the game, Petke said in the heat of the moment, ''I was ticked off, and I wanted to show that shirt. I didn't say anything about anybody,'' he said, alluding to Diallo. ''I just made a statement.''</p>
        <p>While Diallo's action of inflicting three broken ribs, a punctured lung and a bruised right cheek on Ammann will go without punishment by Major League Soccer, Petke's action was under review by the league's disciplinary committee in Manhattan yesterday.</p>
        <p>Joe Machnik and Todd Durbin lead the league's disciplinary committee. Durbin said the committee would make a decision on Petke today, before the MetroStars' next game, which is tomorrow night against the visiting Kansas City Wizards. Petke was suspended for a game last year for kissing the ball and handing it to the referee.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars have no games left in the regular season against Tampa Bay and Diallo, the league's leading scorer with 22 goals. It is also unlikely the two teams will meet in the first round of the playoffs, which start Sept. 14. But there is a good chance they could meet in subsequent rounds, including, perhaps, the championship game, M.L.S. Cup 2000, Oct. 15 at Washington's Robert F. Kennedy Stadium.</p>
        <p>Each team won twice against each other in the regular season and the MetroStars eliminated the Mutiny in the third round of the United States Open Cup. Coincidentally, it was in that game the MetroStars also lost to injury for the season another key player, defender Daniel Hernandez, who has undergone reconstructive surgery in his right knee.</p>
        <p>MAJOR LEAGUE SOCCER</p>
        <p>Three-time champion D.C. United, the team that set the standard in the first four years of the league's existence, will not be in the playoffs this season. Not only that, the team is in serious danger of finishing last in the league with a record perhaps worse than the one the MetroStars had last year.</p>
        <p>United had a chance to escape last place but lost, 1-0, to the San Jose Earthquakes on Saturday in Washington. The victory ended a six-game losing streak for the Earthquakes (6-14-8, 26 points). United is now at 6-16-6, 24 points.</p>
        <p>Each team has four games left. New England (10-11-6, 36 points), which is fighting for a playoff spot, and the other two are against Miami (10-12-5, 35 points), which is also in a battle for a playoff spot.</p>
        <p>Both New England and Miami came away with victories over the weekend to revive their playoff chances. The Revolution defeated Tampa Bay by 2-1 and the Fusion edged Kansas City by the same score to stay 1 point behind the Revolution and Colorado (11-14-3, 36 points) for the eighth and last playoff spot in the 12-team league.</p>
        <p>At the other end of the spectrum, only 4 points separate the top five teams. The Chicago Fire narrowed the gap from Tampa Bay for the lead in the Central Division with a 2-1 triumph over the Los Angeles Galaxy. Sasha Victorine opened the scoring for the Galaxy, but Chicago got second-half goals from Hristo Stoichkov and Evan Whitfield for the victory.</p>
        <p>Chicago (13-9-5) and the Galaxy (12-8-8) have 44 points each. Kansas City (14-7-6) continues to be the top team with 48 points, followed by the MetroStars and Tampa Bay.</p>
        <p>UNITED STATES</p>
        <p>Chris Armas, who strained ligaments in his left knee in the 7-0 World Cup qualifying triumph over Barbados last Wednesday, will miss the qualifying game against Guatemala Sept. 3 in Washington. His place at defensive midfield will most likely be taken by John O'Brien, who plays in the Netherlands.</p>
        <p>Armas, who plays for the Chicago Fire in M.L.S., is one of the three over-age players selected for the Olympic team by Coach Clive Charles, who has to submit his roster for the Olympics by Sept. 5. If Armas is not making progress in his recovery, Charles will have to name someone else in his place.</p>
        <p>Sunil Gulati was elected executive vice president of the United States Soccer Federation in last week's annual meeting in Manhattan. He defeated the incumbent, John Motta, who won a close election over Gulati in 1998. The former deputy commissioner of M.L.S., Gulati currently serves as the managing director of the Kraft Soccer Properties, which operates the New England Revolution and the San Jose Earthquakes.</p>
        <p>The federation officially granted membership to the Women's United Soccer Association that plans to start operations in eight cities across the country next spring. All players from the World Cup and Olympic teams have committed to playing in the league, the country's top outfit for women.</p>
        <p>The women's Olympic team had difficulty scoring more than one goal in 1-1 ties with Canada and Russia in its last two games. This is after 9-1 and 4-0 victories over Canada and 7-0 over Russia earlier in the season.</p>
        <p>The Americans have a chance to get in sync offensively against Brazil Sept. 1 in San Jose, Calif., before they depart for Australia to defend their gold medal.</p>
        <p>ALEX YANNIS</p>
        <p>SOCCER: NOTEBOOK AND STANDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
