<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A CONVERSATION WITH: Nancy Padian; Battling AIDS in Africa by Empowering Women</title>
    <meta content="22CONV$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zimbabwe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Padian, Nancy (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dreifus, Claudia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Conversations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2D7113EF931A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1556" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A CONVERSATION WITH: Nancy Padian; Battling AIDS in Africa by Empowering Women</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA DREIFUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dreifus, Claudia</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Epidemiologist Dr Nancy Padian explains efforts to battle AIDS in Africa by empowering women; she describes struggle to help women in Zimbabwe; interview; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lounging in a high-floor room at the St. Francis Hotel, drinking coffee served in perfect porcelain cups, Dr. Nancy Padian was far from the sad, overcrowded streets of Harare, Zimbabwe, but they and their beleaguered people remained on her mind.</p>
        <p>Dr. Padian, 48, an epidemiologist who is director of research for the AIDS Research Institute of the University of California at San Francisco, is one the world's foremost experts on the heterosexual transmission of AIDS.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lounging in a high-floor room at the St. Francis Hotel, drinking coffee served in perfect porcelain cups, Dr. Nancy Padian was far from the sad, overcrowded streets of Harare, Zimbabwe, but they and their beleaguered people remained on her mind.</p>
        <p>Dr. Padian, 48, an epidemiologist who is director of research for the AIDS Research Institute of the University of California at San Francisco, is one the world's foremost experts on the heterosexual transmission of AIDS.</p>
        <p>For the past seven years, she has commuted between San Francisco and Harare -- some 10,000 miles -- to help Zimbabwean health workers gain some measure of control over the AIDS epidemic tearing through their nation in southern Africa. Their chief weapon against H.I.V. has been the barrier method of contraception, using devices like condoms.</p>
        <p>''There's this zeal to find this new magic bullet,'' Dr. Padian said. ''But there are all these existing methods with great potential and they are right under our noses and that haven't really been looked at. I'm hoping that what we do in Harare will help the women there and, frankly, here too.''</p>
        <p>Q.: You've racked up thousands of frequent flier miles between San Francisco and Zimbabwe. What exactly do you do there?  A.: I run a series of studies as part of a joint project between the University of Zimbabwe and the University of California, San Francisco. We examine the effect of contraception in preventing H.I.V. in Zimbabwean women. In Africa, AIDS is mainly heterosexually transmitted. So what we are looking at in a country where 25 to 30 percent of the population is infected with H.I.V. is whether different forms of contraception might increase or decrease the acquisition of H.I.V.</p>
        <p>We see a population of women who come to regular family planning clinics in Harare. About 30 to 40 percent are infected. The rate is much higher, of course, for women in the sex industry. In the one study, we try to help uninfected women to get their male partners to use condoms.  We've been able to persuade people to use condoms far more than we originally thought we could. In fact, we've been able to get more than half the women in this category to do this.</p>
        <p>For those women who aren't successful at that, we try to encourage them to use female methods of contraception: female condoms, spermicides, diaphragms. We are also looking at whether or not women who are using hormonal contraceptives are at increased or decreased risk of H.I.V. This study has just begun, so we don't have any answers yet.  Q.: The assumption has been that women in Africa and elsewhere cannot convince men to use condoms.  What are you doing differently?  A.: Some women can't. But for others, it's a question of teaching them negotiating strategies. We do role-playing. We present the women with obstacles and have them work out ways to overcome them. We encourage them to think it's O.K. to talk about sexual activity with their partners, that these discussions are part of a healthy lifestyle.  Q.: What makes women in southern Africa so much more vulnerable to AIDS than American women?  A.: There is a higher prevalence of other sexually transmitted diseases there -- as well as a lack of male circumcision, which turns out to be a factor in the susceptibility of the man to AIDS. And you know, the rates of infection from parasites, poor nutrition, all contribute to the problem. In general, if a woman's immune system is compromised because of other infections and nutritional factors, that too increases susceptibility to H.I.V. once she's exposed.</p>
        <p>There are some particular cultural factors, too. It is not uncommon also for African men to have multiple partners and still have their monogamous partner. The practice of ''dry sex,'' which occurs in certain countries in southern Africa, almost certainly increases the susceptibility of women to H.I.V., if their partner is infected. Dry sex is when a woman uses a chemical or physical substance that she puts into herself to dry up the cervical and vaginal secretions in advance of having sex. Women sometimes engage in this practice because there's a belief that men prefer it.  Q.: The Colombian writer Silvana Paternostro claimed that the biggest AIDS risk factor for a woman in many Latin American countries was to be married. Is that true in southern Africa, too?  A.: I think that's true in Zimbabwe, where the infection rate is from 25 to 30 percent, and where the likelihood that a husband is infected is quite high. It's not a question of the woman having multiple partners. Unless they are sex workers, the women are generally monogamous.  Q.: To what extent do you think the power imbalance between African men and women contributes to the spread of AIDS?  A.: I think the gender imbalance is huge there and accounts for some of the transmission. One of the things I see as helping in preventing AIDS, are microloan programs for women's economic development. These are small loans to women to help them start businesses of their own. In order for women to really negotiate sexual activity, it's important for them to be economically empowered.  Q.: The president of South Africa, Thabo Mbeki, has issued some rather ambiguous statements on AIDS.  He has raised doubts about whether  H.I.V. causes AIDS, declared a need for an African solution to the epidemic and suggested that researchers should look at poverty as a root cause. Considering that the South African AIDS rate has increased 50 percent since his election, what do you believe he's thinking?  A.: I don't understand why he said it. I wondered whether he was confusing two issues. I completely agree that we need indigenous solutions to indigenous problems. You definitely can't export American models of behavior changes and expect to implement them in southern Africa. But to suggest that H.I.V. doesn't cause AIDS when all the evidence points to the contrary verges on being irresponsible. It delegitimizes prevention programs. Most prevention programs, after all, are geared at preventing someone from being exposed to H.I.V. And if H.I.V. is not the issue, then what are we doing?  Q.: Is President Robert Mugabe of Zimbabwe in similar denial?  A.: Denial may be too strong a word here. Mugabe has certainly not dealt strongly with the epidemic. He's not strongly supporting the national AIDS control program in promoting condoms. Whether that's denial or avoidance, it's a shame. Because your best chance of success is if you can engage the local leaders. If the government isn't behind it, it's much more difficult to have widespread effective programs throughout the country.  Q.: How do you deal, emotionally, with the high death rate you are witnessing in Harare?  A.: I find it unbelievable, overwhelming. Among my colleagues at the university, someone I am working with is always off to a funeral. It's unbelievable. But I feel like I'm doing something. And that keeps me going. What makes me angry is when people say that it's all sealed and that it's too late and that you can't do anything more. Because I feel like even if I do a little bit, it will make a difference.  Q.: How did the epidemiology of H.I.V. in women become your specialty?  A.: I was in graduate school here at Berkeley in the early 1980's. I had originally wanted to be a psychologist, but fell in love with epidemiology because it seemed to be a good way to help a lot of people -- rather than one person at a time.</p>
        <p>My graduate adviser, Warren Winkelstein, had a grant to look at the natural history of AIDS. H.I.V. hadn't been discovered as the cause yet. So at that point, no graduate student was interested in working on this. I got the job as his assistant because there were no other takers. He suggested that I look into the female partners of bisexual infected men in the group he was studying. That's when I started getting involved in the heterosexual transmission of AIDS.</p>
        <p>Of course, what we found was, at that time, that male-to-female sexual transmission was a lot more frequent than female to male, that risk factors for transmission were primarily not using condoms, anal intercourse and S.T.D.'s in either partner.  Q.: You are about to go to India to start an AIDS study there. How bad is the problem on the subcontinent?  A.: The infection rate isn't that high, but the absolute numbers of people who are infected is huge. Huge! Given the numbers, one can only guess that the epidemic exists at an early stage. And, of course, all of the gender issues that we talked about in Zimbabwe are acute there as well. The women have little say. What I'm discovering as I travel the world, is that for women, power is an absolute dimension of physical health. The bottom line, universally is, If you cannot negotiate what you are doing with your body, you will not be able to lead a healthy and long life.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
