<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sale: Web Address, Unused, Not Cheap</title>
    <meta content="Y22DOM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/22/technology/22DOMA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224486"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Procter &amp; Gamble Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chartrand, Sabra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EEDB1E3EF931A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sale: Web Address, Unused, Not Cheap</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SABRA CHARTRAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chartrand, Sabra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Procter &amp; Gamble Co puts the Internet address www.flu.com up for sale at $1.4 million; address does not lead to World Wide Web site, and it never has; because virtually all catch Web addresses ending in '.com' have already been claimed, value of such unused names has risen sharply (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Internet address www.flu.com is for sale, and its sellers think it is worth $1.4 million.</p>
        <p>The address does not lead to a World Wide Web site, and it never has. Its estimated value seems to arise mostly because such an easy-to-remember destination is available for sale at all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Internet address www.flu.com is for sale, and its sellers think it is worth $1.4 million.</p>
        <p>The address does not lead to a World Wide Web site, and it never has. Its estimated value seems to arise mostly because such an easy-to-remember destination is available for sale at all.</p>
        <p>Because flu.com and virtually all of the other catchy Web addresses ending in ''.com'' have already been claimed, the value of such unused names has risen sharply. Into this speculative field have come a growing number of companies that have built businesses just by helping owners resell the names they no longer want or need.</p>
        <p>''The whole market is shifting; it's now all about the secondary market,'' said Jeff Tinsley, chief executive of GreatDomains.com, a Los Angeles company that is one of the largest resellers of names. ''All the best names are bought up.''</p>
        <p>Original domain name registrations once cost $35 a year. That lasted, for the most part, until this year, when Network Solutions Inc., which had a monopoly on registrations, lost its government contract. Now, more than 50 companies compete to register addresses, new and old, and the rivalry has driven prices as low as $8.</p>
        <p>But for the best generic and catchy domain names, prices are soaring. Early this year, several domain names sold for astronomical amounts -- www.business.com for $7.5 million, www.loan.com for $3 million and www.beauty.com for $1 million.</p>
        <p>The appraisers of flu.com evidently considered those sales when setting their asking price this summer. Since 1995, the address has belonged to Procter &amp; Gamble Inc., which registered hundreds of similar generic names like beautiful.com/ and scent.com/. After five years, the company has realized that it does not need so many generic domain names. So it decided to sell them, using GreatDomains.com to handle the transactions.</p>
        <p>''When we acquired these names, we acted to procure anything that was potentially useful for Procter &amp; Gamble,'' said Terri Carrick, a spokeswoman for the company, which is keeping domains for its brand-name products, like Crest  .com/ and Pringles.com/. Now, though, company officials realize that the unneeded names can be worth money.</p>
        <p>GreatDomains has more than a million domain names for resale on its site. The other leading reseller, Afternic.com, based in New York, has just more than 250,000. Most sales are for .com domain names, but .net and .org names are also available, and some companies are auctioning names with two-letter country codes, like .tv for the tiny nation of Tuvalu.</p>
        <p>Last month, Network Solutions, the onetime monopoly, started its own forum for reselling domain names. The company says it will not charge either buyers or sellers a handling fee or a commission. It hopes instead that the traffic the forum brings to the site will generate customers for its other services, like domain-name appraisals and Internet starter kits that include Web site design and e-mail.</p>
        <p>''Two years ago, registering a name was plenty,'' said Christopher Clough, a vice president for communications at Network Solutions. ''It was enough to fulfill demand. It was fresh, novel and important. But that was two years ago. Today, it is literally not enough, because there is a very interesting dynamic happening in the market.''</p>
        <p>That dynamic is the rise of resellers like GreatDomains.com and Afternic.com, which both charge a commission. At GreatDomains, where 25 domain names have asking prices of more than $1 million, that could mean substantial fees once the company takes 7 to 10 percent from sellers. Afternic charges 5 percent to buyers.</p>
        <p>GreatDomains says its average auction brings in $10,000; Afternic's is closer to $3,000.</p>
        <p>Like any other arena, the domain-name broker industry includes companies of varying size. Many smaller companies have auctioned domain names for years. YahooAuction, owned by Yahoo, and eBay have together listed 10,000 to 15,000 domain names. Other sites carry hundreds or a few thousand names, like domain4auction.com, hitdomain.com, listadomain.com, www.dngcom.com and www.domainmart.com, where www.peoplewhodontpaytheirbills.com was for sale recently.</p>
        <p>Register.com, a New York company, also plans to add auctions to its site.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tinsley of GreatDomains.com said his company had built enough of a reputation to withstand new competition.</p>
        <p>''We're in the fortunate position to be the clear leader in the secondary market,'' he said. ''We've figured out what it takes to get the names sold.''</p>
        <p>Procter &amp; Gamble, meanwhile, is in no hurry to sell flu.com. The company says it has had several inquiries, but predicted the auction could take three to six months.</p>
        <p>''We're waiting for the right customer,'' Ms. Carrick said, meaning one who could pay $1.4 million.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
