<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="22TRAN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="N.F.L."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EEDB1631F931A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BUFFALO BILLS--Released QB Phil Stambaugh, P Jason Van Dyke, K Jon Hilbert, DB Askari Adams, DB David Byrd, DB Quincy Coleman, FB Phillip Crosby, WR Scott Pingel, WR Corey Sullivan, TE John Jennings, C Spencer Riley, G Mike Tosaw, LB Keith Kelsey, and DT Nathaniel Williams.  CINCINNATI BENGALS--Waived PK Doug Pelfrey.  CLEVELAND BROWNS--Released WR Zola Davis, WR Dwaune Jones, RB Greg Robinette and OL Manuia Savea.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BUFFALO BILLS--Released QB Phil Stambaugh, P Jason Van Dyke, K Jon Hilbert, DB Askari Adams, DB David Byrd, DB Quincy Coleman, FB Phillip Crosby, WR Scott Pingel, WR Corey Sullivan, TE John Jennings, C Spencer Riley, G Mike Tosaw, LB Keith Kelsey, and DT Nathaniel Williams.  CINCINNATI BENGALS--Waived PK Doug Pelfrey.  CLEVELAND BROWNS--Released WR Zola Davis, WR Dwaune Jones, RB Greg Robinette and OL Manuia Savea.</p>
        <p>DALLAS COWBOYS--Released WR Darran Hall, WR Drew Cone, P Barry Cantrell, TE Lawrence Hart, TE J.J. Huggins, OL J.R. Conrad, OL Steve Scifres, OL Chad Slaughter, DL Kendrick Gholston, DL Keith Jackson and S Jason Kaiser. Placed LB Brandon Tolbert on waivers-injured reserve. Reached an injury settlement with OL Chris Brymer.  DENVER--Released FB Ryan Christopherson, DL Jerome Davis, DL Nathan Davis, G Allen DeGraffenreid and CB William Hampton. Placed WR Muneer Moore on injured reserve.  DETROIT LIONS--Placed QB Mike Tomczak on injured reserve. Released WR Henry Douglas, LB Scott Fields and S Ryan Stewart.  INDIANAPOLIS COLTS--Waived OL Joel Davis, LB Josh Gentry, TE Ibn Green, RB Mark Kacmarynski, LB Paul Lacoste, OT Craig Robeen, OT Paul Snellings, RB Tremayne Stephens, DB Scott Thomas and WR Brian Wofford.  KANSAS CITY CHIEFS--Waived WR Scott Cloman, LB Jonathan Jackson, G Eric King, S Percy King, FB Charles Kirby, WR Brock McGrew, T Josh Rawlings, DT Kevin Sluder and WR Germaine Stringer.  NEW ENGLAND PATRIOTS--Released TE Rob Tardio, G Brent Warren, S Rodney Rideau, OT Ryan Tujague and OLB Casey Tisdale.  NEW YORK JETS--Waived TE Blake Spence.  PHILADELPHIA EAGLES--Waived CB Tony Francis, WR Michael Lewis, K Rich Maston, WR Raki Nelson, FB Anthony Southern, LB Marc Stockbauer, C Ty Wise, T Robert Barr, S Lemar Marshall and TE Jed Weaver.  PITTSBURGH STEELERS--Waived OT Kris Farris, T Chris Conrad, OL Todd Burger, WR Shawn McWashington, TE Jason Gavadza, FB Joey Goodspeed, K Kyle Atteberry, CB Tim Strickland, LB Jonathan Foster and DE Johnny Mitchell. Placed WR Will Blackwell on the physically unable to perform list.  ST. LOUIS RAMS--Cut P Louie Aguiar. Released DE Vince Amey, OL Andrew Kline and WR Phil Savoy. Signed WR Chris Thomas.  SAN DIEGO CHARGERS--Released WR Pat Batteaux, DE Seneca Knight, DT Glenn Matthews, TE Terrance McCaskey, G Reggie Nelson, FB Durrell Price, WR Calvin Schexnayder, CB Eric Sloan, WR Kevin Swayne and S Fred White.  SAN FRANCISCO--Activated TE Greg Clark. Placed RB Paul Smith on injured reserve. Waived CB Mikki Allen, WR Jermaine Arrington, WR Eric Chew, DT Daniel Greer, DT Tony Plantin, DE Danny Scott and K James Tuthill.  WASHINGTON REDSKINS--Waived DT Doug Brown, S Quincy Sanders, K Clay Rush, K Peter Elezovic, LB Anthony Peterson, DL Lamont Bryant, WR Jammie Deese, WR Tommy Nash, QB Leon Murray, DL Eric Stevenson, DB Eric Whitfield and DB Clay Scanlon. Placed DL Derek G. Smith and RB Gerard Arnold on injured reserve.</p>
        <p>N.F.L.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
