<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Editorial Observer; In Chile, the Balance Tips Toward the Victims</title>
    <meta content="22TUE3$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224515"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chile</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Criminal Court</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenberg, Tina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pinochet Ugarte, Augusto (Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E3D81E3EF931A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Editorial Observer; In Chile, the Balance Tips Toward the Victims</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA ROSENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenberg, Tina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tina Rosenberg Editorial Observer says arrest and extradition of Gen Augusto Pinochet by Spain has tipped balance of power in Chile, unleashing desire for justice buried for a quarter-century, and could also lead to arrests of tyrranical leaders of other countries; says International Criminal Court offers hope of international justice for those too powerful to be tried at home (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until the last few weeks, testimony about the horrors committed by the Chilean military after Gen. Augusto Pinochet's coup in 1973 has virtually all come from one side, the victims'. The military refused to cooperate with Chile's truth commission, and provided very little information for the families of those who disappeared.</p>
        <p>The man who walked around Santiago's National Stadium with a television reporter recently represented something new for Chileans. Roberto Saldias was a soldier in 1973. He talked about the executions he witnessed in the stadium. He named one perpetrator and promised to identify others in court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until the last few weeks, testimony about the horrors committed by the Chilean military after Gen. Augusto Pinochet's coup in 1973 has virtually all come from one side, the victims'. The military refused to cooperate with Chile's truth commission, and provided very little information for the families of those who disappeared.</p>
        <p>The man who walked around Santiago's National Stadium with a television reporter recently represented something new for Chileans. Roberto Saldias was a soldier in 1973. He talked about the executions he witnessed in the stadium. He named one perpetrator and promised to identify others in court.</p>
        <p>The television appearance of Mr. Saldias is one more sign of Chile's transformation. After nearly a year of discussion between military leaders and human rights advocates, the armed forces pledged to help find the bodies of victims if those with information could remain anonymous. And earlier this month, the supreme court stripped General Pinochet of his legislative immunity, providing the first real chance that he could stand trial.</p>
        <p>The change in Chile is in part due to the passage of time, which has brought a new generation of judges into office. But the catalyst for their new assertiveness was the arrest of Mr. Pinochet in Britain on a Spanish warrant in 1998. That arrest caused reverberations elsewhere and led to the detention of Chad's former dictator in Senegal, although the courts later released him. Other arrests of tyrannical leaders could follow. But for now, Mr. Pinochet's capture has left a deeper footprint in Chile, where it has changed the balance of power.</p>
        <p>New democratic or reformist governments that lack power over the old guard can do little to reckon with the past. This was true of Chile until recently, and of most of Latin America's former military dictatorships. Typically, the generals retain their guns and can at any moment point them at civilian heads. It is also the case in most nations of the former Soviet Union, where top Communist officials retain positions of influence and can block any moves to bring the old regime's criminals to account.</p>
        <p>Very few countries have given victims acknowledgment of their suffering or families information about lost loved ones. Those that have done so possessed the power to threaten the collaborators or murderers with exposure or trials if they did not talk. Germany opened the files of the secret police, or Stasi, to its victims. It had not anticipated that as a result, many ex-informers would contact their victims to sit down and talk. Their motive is damage control -- they know they will be caught. But it has produced a healthy outpouring of discussion about why people collaborated and allowed many Stasi victims to hear personal confessions from their spies.</p>
        <p>Another country that has given some psychological healing to victims is South Africa. The unique feature of its truth commission -- those who confess to crimes can get amnesty from prosecution -- has broadened South Africa's reckoning with the past. Instead of trials in only a few high-profile cases, which is all the country could very likely afford, dozens of victims got to hear confessions and relatives of the murdered learned what happened to their loved ones.</p>
        <p>This could happen only because the government of Nelson Mandela could credibly threaten the old apartheid killers with real jail time if they did not talk. If Mr. Pinochet's successors in Chile had tried this, the military would simply have laughed.</p>
        <p>That changed with Mr. Pinochet's arrest. His detention tipped the balance of power in Chile and unleashed desires for justice that people had buried for a quarter-century. It also allowed Chile to press for testimony, offering the same deal as South Africa's truth commission. The military men who signed agreements in Chile to provide information on the 1,200 people still missing did so because for the first time, they run a real risk of prosecution for the forced disappearances. If Mr. Pinochet is tried in Chile, it will be under a new interpretation of a general amnesty he decreed in 1978 -- mainly benefiting his own forces. The courts now say that if the body in a case has not been found, the case is ongoing and can be prosecuted. If a body is found, the case becomes a murder -- and therefore covered by amnesty. So soldiers can escape trial for disappearances by producing the bodies.</p>
        <p>The world community could help achieve similar accountings in other countries if the International Criminal Court were up and running. Established two years ago in a treaty signed by 120 nations -- the United States not among them -- the court will try those accused of genocide and other heinous crimes. It offers the hope of international justice for those too powerful to be tried at home. But it will also provide an outside threat of justice that could strengthen a nation's own ability to try its criminals.  The International Criminal Court could help solve a central problem of dealing with the past -- that nations most in need of trials are least likely to be able to hold them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
