<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With One Foot Out the Door, Ewing Steps Back</title>
    <meta content="22KNIC$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/22/sports/22knic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Supersonics</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Detroit Pistons</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ewing, Patrick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Vin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rice, Glen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knight, Travis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Detroit Pistons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Seattle SuperSonics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E2DF1F3EF931A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1946" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With One Foot Out the Door, Ewing Steps Back</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anonymous NBA official says New York Knicks center Patrick Ewing was on brink of being traded to Seattle SuperSonics before 4-team, 13-player deal fell apart; says Detroit Pistons, who were set to acquire seven marginal players, called off trade; proposed trade would have had Knicks acquiring forward Vin Baker from SuperSonics and Glen Rice and Travis Knight from Los Angeles Lakers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Patrick Ewing, the stoic 7-foot center who for 15 years tried to be the player to bring a championship to the Knicks, was on the brink of being traded last night before a 4-team, 13-player deal hit a significant obstacle.</p>
        <p>Ewing, a 38-year-old veteran, was the centerpiece of the blockbuster deal that would have sent him to the Seattle SuperSonics, said a National Basketball Association official on the condition of anonymity. But the division within the Detroit Pistons, who were set to acquire seven marginal players, caused the team to call off the trade last night; four of the players had contracts that the team did not want to assume.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Patrick Ewing, the stoic 7-foot center who for 15 years tried to be the player to bring a championship to the Knicks, was on the brink of being traded last night before a 4-team, 13-player deal hit a significant obstacle.</p>
        <p>Ewing, a 38-year-old veteran, was the centerpiece of the blockbuster deal that would have sent him to the Seattle SuperSonics, said a National Basketball Association official on the condition of anonymity. But the division within the Detroit Pistons, who were set to acquire seven marginal players, caused the team to call off the trade last night; four of the players had contracts that the team did not want to assume.</p>
        <p>In addition to Ewing's going to Seattle, the proposed trade would have had the Knicks acquiring forward Vin Baker from the SuperSonics and forward Glen Rice and center Travis Knight from the Los Angeles Lakers.</p>
        <p>The Lakers would have received Chris Dudley from the Knicks and Christian Laettner from the Detroit Pistons. The Pistons would have added a number of role players from the three teams, including Vernon Maxwell, Lazaro Borrell, Greg Foster, Vladimir Stepania, John Celestand, Tyronn Lue and David Wingate.</p>
        <p>So the deal has been delayed for at least a day. But it seems unlikely that Ewing will return to the Knicks next season after the team seemed to have let him go yesterday, even preparing for a conference call to announce the trade. And Seattle remains interested in obtaining the 12-time All-Star.</p>
        <p>The Pistons executives, said one person with knowledge of the negotiations, were strongly debating whether to take on the seven players. One way to revive the deal may involve Detroit's asking the three other teams to sweeten the deal with higher-quality players and more money. The Pistons were willing to receive No. 1 draft picks from the Lakers and the Knicks in addition to an unspecified amount of money.</p>
        <p>As news of the trade broke yesterday afternoon, Pistons executives said the team's offices were besieged with negative calls, and they acknowledged that public opinion might have given them doubts.</p>
        <p>After losing the All-Star Grant Hill to Orlando earlier this month, Detroit was trying to find a creative way to make itself competitive over the next several years. The best way for the Pistons to achieve that goal is to acquire players with one year left on their contracts in order to free salary-cap room to bid for free agents like Chris Webber and Dikembe Mutombo next summer.</p>
        <p>In a summer of monster multiteam deals that involved some of the game's most prominent players, the proposed trade would have been the biggest in league history. Last week's four-team, nine-player swap, which involved Golden State, Utah, Dallas and Boston, marked the first time four teams agreed to trade players in one package. With salary complications, that deal took nearly a week to complete. Prolonging the process was that the three players first had to sign with their previous teams. One player originally included in the trade, Utah's Scott Padgett, was eventually taken out of the deal.</p>
        <p>So while Ewing was still a Knick last night, the prospects of his remaining in New York are over.</p>
        <p>''He wanted to win it here,'' Herb Williams, a former Knick, said last night at Madison Square Garden, where he was attending the Liberty's W.N.B.A. playoff game.</p>
        <p>One of the most dominating post players in the N.B.A.'s modern era, Ewing was taken by the Knicks with the No. 1 selection in the 1985 college draft. They won the pick that season by winning the N.B.A.'s first draft lottery; it was a day that sent long-suffering fans cheering into the streets of Manhattan with the knowledge that the Knicks would select the scowling, shot-blocking menace from Georgetown University.</p>
        <p>Ewing would lead the Knicks into the playoffs 13 straight years. With him, the Knicks advanced to the Eastern Conference finals three times. In 1994, they came within a game of winning the franchise's first title since 1973 before losing to the Houston Rockets in seven games.</p>
        <p>Holder of most major club records, Ewing ended last season as the 14th-leading scorer in league history. He is fourth in blocked shots and he played in his 1,000th game last season. Ewing is one of seven players in N.B.A. annals to spend 15 years with the same team.</p>
        <p>If his longevity was impressive, though, his durability was wearing thin. In the last three seasons, he missed 88 regular-season games because of injury. From a dislocated right wrist to a partial tear in his left Achilles' tendon, his production was severely limited by his health. He could not play in the 1999 championship series against the San Antonio Spurs, a series the Knicks lost in five games. He began last season on the injury list.</p>
        <p>Still, Ewing came back and silenced his critics for most of the regular season. He started 62 games, and he dutifully took on a reduced role in an offense suddenly powered by Allan Houston and Latrell Sprewell.</p>
        <p>But as the playoffs came, the old question began to re-emerge outside and inside the locker room: were the Knicks better off without their franchise center, the plodding, aging 7-footer whose post-up, halfcourt style came to be viewed as a blight to the Knicks' new high-octane outfit? He would miss two games in the playoffs because of his Achilles' problem.</p>
        <p>In complete games without Ewing against the Indiana Pacers in the past two postseasons, the Knicks went 5-1. Sprewell tried to play down the controversy during the Indiana series in June, saying, ''If we win the championship, Patrick has to be there.''</p>
        <p>But privately, he, Larry Johnson and others were convinced Ewing was slowing the offense down.</p>
        <p>Last night, John Starks, a former Knick, said: ''You never know what it took for him to go in the locker room night in and night out, to take the blame when he didn't win. He's been taking the blame his whole career. Now there's no more finger-pointing with Patrick Ewing gone.''</p>
        <p>When the Knicks, without the injured Ewing, won two straight playoff games against the Pacers this year, Coach Jeff Van Gundy bristled at questions that Ewing's return might tinker with his team's on-court chemistry.</p>
        <p>''Let the foolish remain foolish,'' Van Gundy said. ''I'm not even trying to educate them.''</p>
        <p>But even after sacrificing points and shots, Ewing could not escape the fickleness of the Garden crowd. When the Knicks were struggling and he was missing, he became the subject of derisive remarks and innumerable groans from the rafters.</p>
        <p>''It's over, Patrick!'' one particularly fed-up fan yelled after the Knicks were eliminated by the Pacers in Ewing's final game. ''Take the $18 million and retire.''</p>
        <p>Ewing is scheduled to make $14 million this season, the last installment of a four-year, $68 million contract signed in 1997. Even though his skills and stature as one of the game's elite centers declined, he spoke often of wanting to play beyond the coming season.</p>
        <p>The Knicks balked when it came to talk of a contract extension beyond this season, a development that forced Ewing and David Falk, his agent, to consider other options.</p>
        <p>After giving Scott Layden, the general manager, a list of eight teams he would not protest being traded to, Ewing waited for the Knicks to make their move.</p>
        <p>''To not win here, it probably hurts him even more because he gave so much to win a title, and unfortunately we didn't get it done,'' Starks said.</p>
        <p>Less than two months ago, the trade seemed highly unlikely.</p>
        <p>''In order for us to get back to the finals, Patrick has to be part of this team,'' Layden declared in June, the day after the Knicks were eliminated from the playoffs, when asked if Ewing would be moved.</p>
        <p>Dave Checketts, the Madison Square Garden president, often said he wanted Ewing to retire as a Knick.</p>
        <p>But Ewing's insistence on being compensated beyond this season -- coupled with his growing disenchantment with New York fans and news media -- made their decision to shop him more palatable.</p>
        <p>The end of the Ewing era would create even more questions for the franchise's future. Baker, a member of the United States Olympic team, who is coming off two subpar seasons, would fill the club's need at power forward. After four straight All-Star seasons, Baker has battled weight and confidence problems. He admitted last season to being counseled by the players union for depression, though no condition was ever diagnosed.</p>
        <p>But with no bona fide center to guard players like Alonzo Mourning of Miami and the Lakers' Shaquille O'Neal, the Knicks without Ewing would be at a distinct disadvantage in the middle. With the addition of Rice, a scoring small forward, the possibility of further moves would be likely. Sprewell, a natural shooting guard, was the team's starting small forward last season. If he were to move back to that position to accommodate Rice, then Houston would be the odd man out.</p>
        <p>Houston can opt out of his current deal next year. While Van Gundy is one of Houston's biggest supporters, the Knicks may think of moving him before he becomes a free agent in order to cure the imbalance in their lineup. In the meantime, the proposed trade would give the Knicks more offensive flexibility than ever before. The Sonics, meanwhile, would get out from under Baker's constraining contract, which has $77 million and seven years remaining.</p>
        <p>It is not clear whether the acquisition of Rice would be as part of a sign-and-trade deal with the Lakers, but Los Angeles, the defending N.B.A. champion, would rid itself of a player who had trouble coexisting in an offense dominated by O'Neal and Kobe Bryant.</p>
        <p>They would also acquire Laettner and Dudley to give O'Neal the post players he needs to help defend players like San Antonio's Tim Duncan and David Robinson, and Portland's Rasheed Wallace and probably Shawn Kemp.</p>
        <p>But few players and coaches in the N.B.A. were envisioning what their teams might look like next season. Most of the conversation around the league centered on the Knicks parting ways with their franchise center, the oft-maligned, aging veteran who never delivered the championship to New York he so desperately wanted -- and thus never earned the adoration of the fans he so desperately coveted. ''That's sad,'' O'Neal said when informed of the trade before it fell through. ''You always thought Patrick Ewing would retire in New York.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
