<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shakespeare, Still Hiding From the Biographers</title>
    <meta content="22KAKU$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shakespeare, William (1564-1616)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">William Shakespeare: The Man Behind the Genius (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D6113EF931A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1109" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shakespeare, Still Hiding From the Biographers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani reviews William Shakespeare: The Man Behind the Genius by Anthony Holden; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE  The Man Behind the Genius  By Anthony Holden  367 pages. Little, Brown &amp; Company. $29.95.</p>
        <p>''Shakespeare is in the singularly fortunate position,'' Auden once observed, ''of being, to all intents and purposes, anonymous.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE  The Man Behind the Genius  By Anthony Holden  367 pages. Little, Brown &amp; Company. $29.95.</p>
        <p>''Shakespeare is in the singularly fortunate position,'' Auden once observed, ''of being, to all intents and purposes, anonymous.''</p>
        <p>Though a documented record exists of his publishing history, his real-estate transactions and his involvement in assorted court cases, the man himself has successfully eluded the prying eyes of biographers and historians for four centuries. Almost nothing is known of the years between his childhood in Stratford and his appearance as a young man on the London theater scene, and his personality, vaguely sketched by contemporaries like Ben Jonson as being courteous, pragmatic and mild-mannered, remains enigmatic as well.</p>
        <p>Barrels of ink have been expended in debating the playwright's love life, his sexuality and the emotional arc his plays suggest he traveled -- from youthful exuberance into darkening melancholy and existential doubt, toward something approaching acceptance and reconciliation. And yet for all the Sturm und Drang, no biographer has shed any real light on how this small-town boy with no more than a grammar school education became the author of masterworks like ''Hamlet,'' ''Othello'' and ''King Lear,'' and in doing so permanently transformed the course of Western literature.</p>
        <p>The new biography, ''William Shakespeare: The Man Behind the Genius,'' by Anthony Holden -- the author of earlier books on Tchaikovsky and Laurence Olivier -- is no exception. Though breezily readable, the book offers no new facts about the playwright's life, adds nothing to our appreciation of the plays or poems and indulges in copious -- and often irresponsible -- speculation. Because so little is known about Shakespeare, all of his biographers have been forced to venture into the hazy realm of conjecture, but unlike, say, Samuel Schoenbaum and Park Honan, Mr. Holden does not tell the reader when he is extrapolating from the facts or offering a theory; instead, he cavalierly presents subjective opinion as recorded truth.</p>
        <p>He writes, for instance, that both Shakespeare's ''parents were illiterate,'' though this is a matter of some debate, and he similarly asserts, with little supporting evidence, that the playwright was secretly reared  as a Catholic, and that his ''Catholic indoctrination in childhood ran deep, whatever the subsequent falling-off in his beliefs.'' Like a number of previous biographers, he also suggests that the young Shakespeare worked as a tutor ''in a noble, wealthy and illicitly Catholic household in Lancashire.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Holden goes on to suggest that a teenage Shakespeare was strong-armed into marrying the older Anne Hathaway after she became pregnant, and that he became a lackadaisical husband and doting but absent father. He moved to London during his children's infancy and spent the next 25 years there leading an independent life. His return to Stratford in 1611, Mr. Holden implies, was not the happy homecoming many biographers have portrayed: the restless Shakespeare, he writes, bought a pied-a-terre in London and spent considerable periods of time there until ''failing health finally drove him back to his family for good.''</p>
        <p>As for other controversies in Shakespeare scholarship, Mr. Holden contends that the Sonnets ''should not be taken -- as they so often are -- to suggest that Shakespeare himself was homosexual.'' He looks at the usual suspects identified as the so-called ''Dark Lady'' of the Sonnets (including a married woman named Jeanette Davenant, who gave birth to a child, believed by some to be Shakespeare's illegitimate son), but concludes that it is perhaps best, in Anthony Burgess's words, to leave the Dark Lady ''anonymous, even composite,'' an icon of ''some of the commonest experiences known to men.''</p>
        <p>Early on in this biography, Mr. Holden wisely observes that ''we must remain ever vigilant against too readily reading the poet's own sentiments into those of his characters.'' But he then proceeds to do exactly that, uncovering autobiographical clues everywhere he looks. He describes ''The Merchant of Venice'' as a parable exploring Shakespeare's ''lifelong ambivalence about money, with especial reference to the usury which had so haunted his stricken father.'' He writes that the Sonnets, ''Othello'' and ''The Winter's Tale'' make it ''hard to resist the conclusion that the poet capable of evoking the 'green-eyed monster' in such violent language must have experienced its unique horrors himself,'' and he further suggests that an adulterous love affair might have spurred the playwright to the bravura writing in ''Antony and Cleopatra.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Holden adds that the playwright's grief over the death of his 11-year-old son, Hamnet, in 1596 ''becomes a recurring strain in his work, through 'Hamlet' to 'The Winter's Tale,' '' and that his ''preoccupation with his daughters'' -- ''sharpened by years of guilty absenteeism'' -- surfaces in the plays from ''Lear'' onward.</p>
        <p>These sorts of highly speculative observations linking Shakespeare's life and art are about the only form of original literary criticism Mr. Holden has to offer in this book. Clearly insecure about his own ability to render critical appraisals, Mr. Holden tends to confine himself to expressing bland platitudes (Shakespeare achieved ''a level of intelligence, honesty, wit and humanity unmatched in any other era'') or summarizing the opinions of others. When on the rare occasion he attempts to assess a play himself, the results verge on the laughable. Of ''Titus Andronicus'' he writes: '' 'Titus' has always been notoriously hard going for both cast and audiences; if not laughed off the stage, it requires extra paramedics to cope with the number of fainting spectators.''</p>
        <p>By far the strongest portions of this book have to do with Mr. Holden's depictions of the theatrical world in which Shakespeare came of age. He does a nimble job of sketching in the rivalries of the day, as well as the fashions in writing, which Shakespeare both exploited and transcended. He gives the reader a succinct overview of the historical backdrop to the playwright's life, while also providing insights into how political developments -- and changes in the theater -- might have affected Shakespeare's writing.</p>
        <p>None of this has the hard-earned specificity of serious scholarship, but instead feels fuzzily atmospheric and impressionistic. In fact ''Shakespeare: The Man Behind the Genius'' is perhaps best read not as a work of biography, but as a kind of historical novel starring a playwright as its conquering hero.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
