<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Korean Families Part Again As Bittersweet Reunions End</title>
    <meta content="Y19KOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North Korea-International Relations-South Korea</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pyongyang (North Korea)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kim Jong Il</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Len, Samuel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E2DF133EF93AA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Korean Families Part Again As Bittersweet Reunions End</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAMUEL LEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Len, Samuel</byline>
      <dateline>SEOUL, South Korea, Aug. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>One hundred North Koreans return home after family reunions in Seoul, and 100 South Koreans return home after family reunions in Pyongyang; South Koreans describe Pyongyang as drab but orderly; one 84-year-old man says he had to listen to more praise of Kim Jong Il from his two sons than he could stand; next reunion will take place in September (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Having begun to put back together the shattered fragments of their pasts, 200 North and South Koreans today separated from their families again.</p>
        <p>''Mother, try not to think about me, and take good care yourself,'' said Rim Jae Hyok, 69, bowing to his mother as she sat in a wheelchair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Having begun to put back together the shattered fragments of their pasts, 200 North and South Koreans today separated from their families again.</p>
        <p>''Mother, try not to think about me, and take good care yourself,'' said Rim Jae Hyok, 69, bowing to his mother as she sat in a wheelchair.</p>
        <p>Another North Korean, Kim Gyu Sol, 66, spoke to his South Korean brother over a cellular phone. ''Take good care of our parents, and you must fill in for the role that I cannot play,'' Mr. Kim said.</p>
        <p>The scenes took place outside the Sheraton Walker Hill Hotel in Seoul, where the 100 visitors from the North stayed during their four-day reunions. An equal number of South Koreans made a simultaneous trip north. Both groups returned to their homes today after celebratory, but bittersweet, visits.</p>
        <p>In Seoul, as eight buses of relatives  headed out of the parking lot and toward the airport, several North Koreans -- their hands on the windows -- could be seen trying to catch a last glimpse of family members.</p>
        <p>The 100 South Koreans, who were chosen through a lottery from among 76,000 applicants, returned to Seoul about 2 p.m. on a chartered Korean Air jet. Earlier in the day, the same plane carried the 100 North Koreans back home.</p>
        <p>The South Koreans described Pyongyang, the North Korean capital, as a drab yet orderly city, with tall buildings and crowded sidewalks.</p>
        <p>''The people of Pyongyang appeared to be a lot freer than I had thought, but their expressions seemed rigid,'' said Han Jae Il, 82, who went north to meet his wife, who is 75. ''But all of the bad feelings I had toward North Korea are all gone.''</p>
        <p>Television footage of Pyongyang showed a spacious and manicured city, with long rows of buildings decorated with red signs bearing revolutionary slogans like ''Self-Reliance, Powerful Nation.''</p>
        <p>In some cases, politics intruded on the family reunions. Lee Jong Sung, 84, while visiting two sons in the north, said he heard more praise of the North's leader, Kim Jong Il, than he could stand. ''I finally told them to get some common sense,'' Mr. Lee said, according to an Associated Press report. ''When they gave me that political nonsense, they didn't feel like my own sons.''</p>
        <p>The relatives are aged and the chances of them meeting again are slim. More exchanges are planned, but the visits will involve few of the families separated since the Korean War solidified the division of the nation into a Communist north and a capitalist south. Some 10 million people have been separated from their family members since 1950, according to South Korean estimates.</p>
        <p>After leading the South Koreans back to Seoul, Chang Choong Shik, the head of the South Korean Red Cross said the next reunion would take place in September.</p>
        <p>The reunions are part of an accord reached by Kim Jong Il and South Korea's president, Kim Dae Jung, during their historic meeting in June, when they agreed to start a process that could lead to the reunification.</p>
        <p>North Korea has already agreed to re-establish rail links, and last week it signed an agreement with one of South Korea's conglomerates to develop a permanent meeting place for separated families at Kaesong, just north of the border.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, the North Korean visitors were given a heavily guarded tour of a royal Korean palace built hundreds of years ago. But while the North Koreans seemed cheerful during an earlier tour of a giant shopping mall, at the palace they appeared somber and reluctant to speak, even to each other.</p>
        <p>At one point in the tour, a reporter asked a North Korean visitor if he had been to the palace before.</p>
        <p>''A long time ago,'' the North Korean man said. After a few more steps, he added, ''I think it was 60 years ago.''</p>
        <p>But the short conversation came to a halt when a North Korean cameraman swerved by, pointed to the old man and said: ''Look how red his face is. He's tired. Leave him alone.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the two Koreas continued their reconciliation efforts. Soon after the plane carrying the visitors left for Pyongyang, North Korea's State Symphony Orchestra arrived in Seoul to hold the first joint concert with the Korean Broadcasting System Philharmonic.</p>
        <p>The two Koreas have held joint performances of traditional arts and pop concerts but never before combined their symphony orchestras.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
