<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lawmakers Ask for Delay In Review of Nasdaq Rule</title>
    <meta content="Y19NASD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nasdaq Stock Market</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berenson, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E7DF133EF93AA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lawmakers Ask for Delay In Review of Nasdaq Rule</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX BERENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berenson, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Congressmen ask Securities and Exchange Commission to extend period for comment on plan intended to give investors more information about Nasdaq stocks and trades at best available prices (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Phil Gramm and Representative Thomas J. Bliley Jr. have asked the Securities and Exchange Commission to delay its review of a plan intended to give investors more information about Nasdaq stocks and trades at the best available prices.</p>
        <p>In a letter to the S.E.C. Thursday, Mr. Gramm, Republican of Texas, and Mr. Bliley, Republican of Virginia, who are chairmen of committees that oversee the S.E.C., asked the commission to add 30 days to a comment period now set to expire Aug. 30. At issue is a proposal to combine price quotes for stocks from different trading systems into one ''supermontage'' on the Nasdaq. Under S.E.C. rules, the commission can approve the proposal any time after the comment period expires.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator Phil Gramm and Representative Thomas J. Bliley Jr. have asked the Securities and Exchange Commission to delay its review of a plan intended to give investors more information about Nasdaq stocks and trades at the best available prices.</p>
        <p>In a letter to the S.E.C. Thursday, Mr. Gramm, Republican of Texas, and Mr. Bliley, Republican of Virginia, who are chairmen of committees that oversee the S.E.C., asked the commission to add 30 days to a comment period now set to expire Aug. 30. At issue is a proposal to combine price quotes for stocks from different trading systems into one ''supermontage'' on the Nasdaq. Under S.E.C. rules, the commission can approve the proposal any time after the comment period expires.</p>
        <p>The National Association of Securities Dealers, which runs Nasdaq, says the new system would enable investors to make sure they are getting the best price when they buy and sell stocks. But electronic communications networks, like Instinet, which directly match buyers and sellers of Nasdaq stocks, argue that the proposal will make Nasdaq both a regulator and a competitor of electronic networks.</p>
        <p>''The issues raised by this proposal are significant and must be considered and addressed only with the greatest of care,'' Mr. Gramm and Mr. Bliley wrote to Arthur Levitt, the commission's chairman. ''Market participants, investors, regulatory agencies and Congress must all have adequate time to review these proposals, consult and evaluate their implications.''</p>
        <p>The letter does not take a position on the merits of the supermontage proposal itself. A spokesman for Mr. Bliley said he had not yet decided whether to support or oppose the changes. Mr. Bliley is ''concerned that we not move in to implement too quickly such a new idea that will affect our markets,'' the spokesman said. ''There's certainly not consensus on this issue.''</p>
        <p>Under the supermontage proposal, electronic networks and market makers, which are brokerage firms that buy and sell shares from investors, would be encouraged to send their orders to buy and sell stocks to a central server maintained by Nasdaq. (Electronic networks make money by charging a small per-share fee to match investors directly; market makers profit on the difference between the bid and offer price on a trade.) Investors would be able to see the aggregate of all buy and sell orders at both the best bid and offer prices and two ''price levels'' above and below the best bid and offer.</p>
        <p>In other words, if market makers and electronic networks have collectively offered to buy 10,000 shares of Cisco at $65 and sell 12,000 shares at $65.05, investors would be able to see the entire pool of orders on the supermontage. Investors would also be able to see the orders at the next-lowest offer and next-highest bid, as well as the third-highest bid and third-lowest offer.</p>
        <p>In addition, the supermontage proposal would essentially end the difference between limit orders and quotes, which are treated differently under the current Nasdaq system. That means if an investor wanted to buy 15,000 shares of Cisco with a limit of $65.05, and 12,000 shares were available at that price, the investor would buy the available shares and have the new highest bid price, for 3,000 shares at $65.05.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq argues that the supermontage proposal will simplify and improve its current system, which is a hodgepodge of quotes, limit orders and prices that are sometimes out of date. The proposal will also give investors a better sense of the total buy and sell interest, or liquidity, available from all market participants, Nasdaq says.</p>
        <p>But electronic networks, which account for a rapidly growing share of the Nasdaq's volume, say that the proposal essentially turns Nasdaq into a competitor that is biased against them.</p>
        <p>''Although Nasdaq might be positioning this otherwise,'' said Douglas Atkins, chief executive of Instinet, the largest electronic network, ''this fundamentally changes Nasdaq's role in the marketplace, creates a competitor to the institutions that they regulate and creates concerns for investors.'' Instinet is a unit of Reuters Group P.L.C.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
