<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Ward Hopes To Step Past 'The Trade'</title>
    <meta content="19RHOD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhoden, William C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ward, Dedric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Keyshawn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EFDB133EF93AA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Ward Hopes To Step Past 'The Trade'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William C Rhoden Sports of The Times column on Dedric Ward, who will start for New York Jets at wide receiver in wake of trade of Keyshawn Johnson; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE was a day last week at Jets camp when Dedric Ward, the Jets' fourth-year wide receiver, was in a quiet, but upbeat, mood. Al Groh, the Jets' first-year head coach, had officially named Ward as the Jets' starting wide receiver alongside Wayne Chrebet.</p>
        <p>This was big news. Anything about the Jets' wide receivers is big news ever since the organization sent Keyshawn Johnson to Tampa Bay in the most controversial trade in franchise history.</p>
        <p>All sorts of names had been floated around as candidates to fill the void created by the Johnson trade. First, Carl Pickens was coming from Cincinnati, then Sean Dawkins from Seattle. Then talk turned to the armada of Jets rookie receivers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE was a day last week at Jets camp when Dedric Ward, the Jets' fourth-year wide receiver, was in a quiet, but upbeat, mood. Al Groh, the Jets' first-year head coach, had officially named Ward as the Jets' starting wide receiver alongside Wayne Chrebet.</p>
        <p>This was big news. Anything about the Jets' wide receivers is big news ever since the organization sent Keyshawn Johnson to Tampa Bay in the most controversial trade in franchise history.</p>
        <p>All sorts of names had been floated around as candidates to fill the void created by the Johnson trade. First, Carl Pickens was coming from Cincinnati, then Sean Dawkins from Seattle. Then talk turned to the armada of Jets rookie receivers.</p>
        <p>The Jets stuck with Ward.</p>
        <p>''Trading Keyshawn, then not bringing in another receiver, showed a lot of faith in me,'' Ward said.</p>
        <p>The Jets maintained that they were satisfied. Yes, the 5-foot-10-inch Chrebet and the 5-9 Ward were the shortest receiving tandem in the league. But height was just a number.</p>
        <p>''With receivers and running backs, they're not big or little; they're effective,'' Groh said.</p>
        <p>Then, lo and behold, with the season bearing down on them, the Jets acquired wide receiver Vincent Brisby after he was cut by New England. Brisby's key selling point was -- guess what? -- his size. While nobody mentioned the K-word, as in Keyshawn, Brisby, at 6-3, gave the Jets the big target they were looking for, at least on paper.</p>
        <p>With each practice, with each game, the Jets seem to be more fully realizing that trading Johnson may well be one of those moves that haunts the franchise for decades to come. It is Boston trading Babe Ruth,  the Nets trading Dr. J.</p>
        <p>But for one night, everything was all right for the Jets, who defeated the Giants, 27-24, in their final exhibition game. Chrebet caught three passes for 79 yards, scoring on a 52 yard flea-flicker. Ward had a quiet game, with four receptions for 49 yards, while Brisby caught two passes for 30 yards.</p>
        <p>But the most significant statistics belonged to quarterback Ray Lucas, who was 19-of-26 passing for 286 yards and 3 touchdowns.</p>
        <p>Ward could make everything right for himself and the Jets with a breakthrough season. If he does, the Jets' front office will take credit for having the foresight to let a soft-spoken third-round draft pick replace Johnson.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Ward got a vote of confidence from the man whose shoes the Jets are desperately trying to fill. ''In all honesty I've always liked Dedric Ward,'' Johnson said from Tampa. ''To me, I've always thought he was a much better player than the other guy,'' he added in a reference to Chrebet.</p>
        <p>''I've always thought he should have been the opposite receiver from me, for a lot of different reasons,'' Johnson said of Ward. ''He fits the role of a vertical guy.''</p>
        <p>Ward has been good, not great. When Chrebet broke a bone in his foot in the 1999 preseason, Ward became the No. 2 receiver for the first five games of the regular season. He ended up with 15 receptions for 143 yards and 2 touchdowns.</p>
        <p>For the season, Ward caught 22 passes for 325 yards. It wasn't Ward's best season; that came in 1998, when he averaged 19.1 yards a catch and established himself as a legitimate deep threat. Still, Ward said he viewed his five starts a year ago as a ''steppingstone for bigger and better things to come.''</p>
        <p>For Jets fans, for Bucs fans, this 2000 season has become an intriguing drama: eyes on Groh, eyes on Johnson, eyes on Chrebet, eyes on Ward. Perhaps, Chrebet in particular. Is he overrated, as Johnson suggests? Can he carry the Jets' offense the way Johnson did at times?</p>
        <p>The defining scene of last season was a tough, but catchable, pass bouncing off Chrebet's hands in the end zone against Indianapolis, a pass that would have tied the score in the final seconds of the game. This season, Chrebet will face the best corners week in and week out. At the same time, the 25-year-old Ward will be trying to break through to another level.</p>
        <p>''I think he'll do a good job,'' Johnson said of Ward. ''But the other guy -- I don't think he's good enough to take the heat off of Dedric. I took the heat off of him; I don't think he's good enough to take the heat off of Ward.''</p>
        <p>Who will catch those 9-to-14-yard passes in heavy traffic in clutch situations for the Jets?  Johnson, naturally, has his opinion: ''I don't know if they have a receiver who can do that.</p>
        <p>''Based on what we had last year, we really only had one guy who could do that,'' Johnson said. ''And he's in Tampa now.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
