<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Online Coverage Fell Short of the Hype</title>
    <meta content="Y19DOT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223572"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE INTERNET"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wayne, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E1D7123EF93AA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="790" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Online Coverage Fell Short of the Hype</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE WAYNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wayne, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Internet sites set up to cover presidential conventions fail to live up to expectations; technological problems cause many to crash or to abandon promised features; some sites find expenses so high and visitors so low at Republican convention that they drastically scale back operations at Democratic convention; even traffic to Web sites with brand names and long track records is disappointly low; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If any group was hoping for a ''bounce'' from the Democratic and Republican conventions, it was the scores of political Web sites that made their online debuts in Los Angeles and Philadelphia with lots of gizmos and hype.</p>
        <p>But while some said the coming of the Internet to the conventions would be as momentous as the advent of television 52 years ago, the reality has been somewhat less impressive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If any group was hoping for a ''bounce'' from the Democratic and Republican conventions, it was the scores of political Web sites that made their online debuts in Los Angeles and Philadelphia with lots of gizmos and hype.</p>
        <p>But while some said the coming of the Internet to the conventions would be as momentous as the advent of television 52 years ago, the reality has been somewhat less impressive.</p>
        <p>Technological problems have plagued many Web sites, causing them to crash or to abandon many promised features. Some Internet sites found expenses so high and visitors so low at the Republican convention two weeks ago in Philadelphia that they drastically scaled back operations at the Democratic convention in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Even traffic to political Web sites with brand names and long track records was disappointingly low for the Republicans' gathering, and some critics complained that the level of political discourse in online chat rooms was lower than expected, too. Detailed data on Web sites during the Democratic convention will not be available until next week.</p>
        <p>''The bridge hasn't yet been made between politics and the Internet,'' said James Carey, a spokesman for PC Data OnLine, which tracks Web use. ''There's not a lot of traffic to these sites. It just isn't working yet.''</p>
        <p>Visits to political Web sites -- ranging from such mainstream sites as MSNBC.com and CNN.com to more cutting-edge sites like Pseudo.com or SpeakOut.com -- actually fell during the Republican convention. MSNBC.com saw a 27 percent drop in its visitors to 2.4 million  during the week of the convention. And CNN.com saw an 18 percent drop to 1.9 million viewers, only to see viewership rebound by 13.6 percent following the convention week.</p>
        <p>Newer Web sites like Speak out.com and Voter.com failed to even pull more than 150,000 visitors during the Republican convention, according to Media Metrix Inc., a company that tracks this data. SpeakOut.com, which has an online poll that records instantaneous reactions to podium speeches, keeps a daily posting of how different speakers fared. The Gore speech received a favorable rating of 79 percent among Democrats, 50 percent among independents and swing voters and 26 percent among Republicans, with women rating Mr. Gore's speech higher than men.</p>
        <p>''The first online convention failed to live up to the hype that preceded it,'' Michael Cornfield, director of the Democracy Online Project at George Washington University, said about Philadelphia. ''This is not so surprising, because the convention was not an exciting news event.''</p>
        <p>Part of the reason for low traffic was the product: despite claims by many Web sites that they could jazz up convention coverage with offbeat stories, chat rooms and nifty camera shots, the online coverage proved to be no more exciting than that of  regular television, which itself was often greeted with yawns. Some of the promises -- streaming video, instantaneous polling and ''behind-the-scenes'' views -- failed to materialize, or did so in fuzzy and unattractive formats.</p>
        <p>''A lot of sites couldn't get their act together,'' said Marion Just, a researcher at the Joan Shorenstein Center on the Press, Politics and Public Policy at Harvard University. ''Many wanted to have the fanciest gadgets and gimmicks, and some sites crashed and burned.''</p>
        <p>Pseudo.com, which bought a sky box at both conventions, cut its convention staff in half after the Republican convention and did not bring its 360-degree camera to Los Angeles after the camera produced only small, grainy online pictures, in the opinion of some viewers, and those  came at high costs.</p>
        <p>The two political parties failed, as well, to live up to their promises of plugged-in conventions. The Dems.2000 Web site promised to have online chats with convention speakers immediately after their presentations. That did not happen.</p>
        <p>Instead of a live chat, anyone signing on with questions was given an automated response thanking them for participating in the ''online event,'' saying the party was ''doing its best'' to answer them and to continue participating in Democratic events online.</p>
        <p>And the Republicans' highly touted dot-com delegate Web site, which promised ''exclusive'' online access to top Republican officials, also failed to deliver. A promised live chat room never came about, information given to dot-com delegates was dated and generic, and online polls asked questions not related to the convention.</p>
        <p>''None of the features lived up to the hype,'' said Chris Hunter, an analyst with NetElection.Org. ''Chat rooms were vapid and off-topic. It was all very disappointing. I think lots of the dot-coms weren't there to promote democracy, but to get another round of venture capital.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE INTERNET</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
