<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Russian Admiral Acknowledges Explosion Inside Sub</title>
    <meta content="Y19RUS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223616"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Explosions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kursk (Submarine)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Barents Sea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tyler, Patrick E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myers, Steven Lee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Explosions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E0DD133EF93AA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Russian Admiral Acknowledges Explosion Inside Sub</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER with STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tyler, Patrick E; Myers, Steven Lee</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Aug. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Adm Vyacheslav Popov acknowledges that a terrible internal explosion devastated nuclear submarine Kursk before it sank; Russian Navy finally docks a rescue vehicle to the spine of the wrecked submarine after many unsuccessful attempts; rescuers find the deck area around a rear escape hatch so deformed that they are unable to make a watertight connection and enter the sub; photo; seismic wave analysis; drawing of hatch (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The commander of Russia's Northern Fleet acknowledged today that a terrible internal explosion devastated the nuclear submarine Kursk before it went down last Saturday, confirming Western intelligence reports of huge underwater explosions.</p>
        <p>The report by Adm. Vyacheslav Popov on Russian television came as the Russian Navy finally docked a rescue vehicle to the spine of the wrecked submarine after many unsuccessful attempts. But rescuers said they had found the deck area around a rear escape hatch so deformed that they were unable to make a watertight connection and enter the sub.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The commander of Russia's Northern Fleet acknowledged today that a terrible internal explosion devastated the nuclear submarine Kursk before it went down last Saturday, confirming Western intelligence reports of huge underwater explosions.</p>
        <p>The report by Adm. Vyacheslav Popov on Russian television came as the Russian Navy finally docked a rescue vehicle to the spine of the wrecked submarine after many unsuccessful attempts. But rescuers said they had found the deck area around a rear escape hatch so deformed that they were unable to make a watertight connection and enter the sub.</p>
        <p>One hundred eighteen men were on board the Kursk when it sank.  Navy officials said they would keep trying to reach them, and there remained the possibility that a British submersible, which is to arrive on Saturday night, might manage to enter the Kursk with a more flexible docking mechanism.</p>
        <p>Admiral Popov said the last sounds of crew noise from the submarine were monitored on Monday. Other naval officials have been saying survivors were tapping on the hull of the vessel through Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The admiral also said he was ''very worried that according to our calculations, the pressure in the submarine is higher than the normal atmosphere,'' indicating a dangerous threat to normal respiration. He said estimates of the time limit for the crew's survival ''have been based on the fact that the air pressure is normal,'' adding, ''The situation is very grave.''</p>
        <p>Most Russian officials have said the oxygen in the Kursk would be depleted by today.</p>
        <p>Though Admiral Popov confirmed internal explosions, he did not rule out earlier Russian claims that the Kursk sank after a collision with an unidentified object or vessel. He said the investigation into what set off the explosion centered on an outside impact, for instance a collision, or something inside. He did not elaborate.</p>
        <p>Some American officials in Washington said today it was conceivable that a collision had preceded the large explosion detected aboard the Kursk. Others said such a collision also would have been heard by Western intelligence sensors monitoring the Russian naval maneuvers in the Barents Sea last weekend.</p>
        <p>One theory circulating among American defense officials today was that the Kursk was in the process of firing an antisubmarine rocket from one of its forward weapons tubes when the rocket jammed in the tube. With the warhead outside the hull still attached to the rocket body and flaming engine, that would have set off a fire and an explosion, the first of two monitored by Western intelligence sensors.</p>
        <p>In the 2 minutes and 15 seconds between the explosions, the crew might have had the chance to try to free the missile and douse the fire, the American officials theorized.</p>
        <p>But after the two minutes, they say, the missile's warhead of high-yield conventional explosive could have detonated with the force of one to two tons of TNT, causing extensive damage to deck structures in the front and near the conning tower.</p>
        <p>The American experts estimated that a high-yield exploding warhead and a shock wave from the explosion could have destroyed an estimated 40 percent of the submarine, splitting and deforming parts of the hull. This may have given the appearance that the ship had been pummeled by the glancing blow of another ship and opened a gaping hole in the hull.</p>
        <p>Norman Polmar, an independent naval expert, said one torpedo carried by this type of submarine was designed to be fired underwater, shoot up through the air and then drop back into the water to home in on another submarine.</p>
        <p>American officials have said the Russians had been practicing missile and torpedo firings in a large naval exercise just before the explosions were heard. Mr. Polmar said that in the 2 minutes and 15 seconds before the torpedo's warhead exploded, it is possible that sailors in the back of the submarine would have shut watertight doors. He said those crew members could have survived as the sub plummeted to the bottom, while most men in the front of the sub would have perished quickly.</p>
        <p>Other experts said the sub's batteries lay below the front compartments. So they probably would have been knocked out, making it unlikely that survivors would have had any battery power and decreasing the odds that any could have survived more than three or four days.</p>
        <p>A Norwegian seismic institute joined with Western governments in saying today that it detected two underwater explosions in the area where the Kursk went down. The explosions were a little more than two minutes apart, the first one much smaller than the second.</p>
        <p>''The first explosion we recorded was probably the equivalent of less than 100 kilograms of TNT,'' said Frode Ringdal, scientific director of the institute, referring to about 220 pounds. But the second explosion, occurring at 7:30 a.m., Coordinated Universal Time, was the equivalent of one to two tons of TNT, he added. The explosion sent powerful shock waves through the water that could be detected by seismic equipment on Norway's northern coast, near where American intelligence sensors aboard submarines operating in the Arctic Sea area also detected the powerful explosions.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, President Vladimir V. Putin, facing biting criticism in the Russian media and among some leading political figures for vacationing at a Black Sea resort while any survivors on board the Kursk slowly asphyxiated 350 below the surface of the Barents Sea, flew back to Moscow after attending the opening in Yalta, Ukraine, of a meeting of leaders of former Soviet republics. There, he defended his five-day delay.</p>
        <p>''Of course, my first wish was to fly to the region, to the fleet base in order to study the situation on the spot,'' Mr. Putin told reporters before leaving Yalta. ''But I decided against that, and I think I made the correct decision,'' he said, explaining that ''the arrival in the disaster area of high-ranking officials who are not specialists'' does not ''help rescue either people or equipment.''</p>
        <p>Still, criticism was intense. The leader of Russia's liberal Union of Right Forces Party, Boris Y. Nemtsov, said in a statement today that Mr. Putin, ''as commander in chief'' has ''no right to vacation while his subordinates, Northern Fleet sailors, face this drama.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin defended his actions by saying the first assessment he received of the sea disaster from Marshal Igor D. Sergeyev, the defense minister, indicated that ''the chances the crew will survive are few, but they exist, and specialists will do their utmost.'' The Russian leader said he had also been assured that ''Russia has all the means for rescue work.'' When this proved not to be the case, Mr. Putin said active discussions were carried out with Western countries as soon as help was offered.</p>
        <p>Though there were reports in Murmansk that Mr. Putin would fly straight to the northern submarine base to console the families, Russian officials remained silent about whether Mr. Putin had reached Moscow.</p>
        <p>Tonight, the Russian government announced that each family of Kursk crew members would be allocated the equivalent of about $18,000 in immediate financial assistance to cover their needs.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the week, Adm. Vladimir Kuroyedov, the Russian Navy's  commander, said he would remain optimistic ''until Aug. 18.'' Other navy experts have suggested that any surviving crew members already have run out of oxygen and that most of the 86 officers, 31 enlisted men and one civilian perished in the first minutes after a catastrophic blow or explosion ruptured the hull and destroyed the watertight containment of the ship.</p>
        <p>The Murmansk edition of the Russian newspaper Komsomolskaya Pravda today published a full listing of the 118-member crew of the Kursk with an editorial note stating that after repeated attempts to obtain the list through officials navy channels, the newspaper finally resorted to bribery and paid 16,000 rubles for the list, the equivalent of about $650.</p>
        <p>Inflaming the mystery were many unconfirmed reports and theories spun out in the Russian press, several of them asserting that the Russian Navy suspected that one of the two American submarines said to have been operating in the area might have been involved in a collision with Kursk and then sought refuge at a Norwegian port.</p>
        <p>Those reports were further fanned by the arrival in Moscow of George J. Tenet, the United States director of central intelligence. Mr. Tenet's agenda was not clear, but Russian officials said Mr. Tenet's visit had been planned before the Kursk disaster.</p>
        <p>The United States has said that none of its submarines was involved in the disaster.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
