<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="TRA19" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223658"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EEDA133EF93AA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League  CHICAGO WHITE SOX--Signed RHP Ken Hill to a minor league contract.  National League  HOUSTON ASTROS--Activated OF Roger Cedeno from the 15-day disabled list. Waived OF Matt Mieske.  Northern League  SIOUX FALLS CANARIES--Sold the contract of INF Enohel Polanco to the Cleveland Indians.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League  CHICAGO WHITE SOX--Signed RHP Ken Hill to a minor league contract.  National League  HOUSTON ASTROS--Activated OF Roger Cedeno from the 15-day disabled list. Waived OF Matt Mieske.  Northern League  SIOUX FALLS CANARIES--Sold the contract of INF Enohel Polanco to the Cleveland Indians.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL  National Basketball Association  CHARLOTTE HORNETS--Agreed to terms with F Lee Nailon.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL  National Football League  CINCINNATI BENGALS--Waived S Greg Myers.  GREEN BAY PACKERS--Placed WR Anthony Lucas on the physically-unable-to-perform list and RB Rondell Mealey on injured reserve.  JACKSONVILLE JAGUARS--Placed S Carnell Lake and OL Joey Chustz on injured reserve.</p>
        <p>Xtreme Football League  CHICAGO--Named John Lanctot director of public relations.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY  National Hockey League  DETROIT RED WINGS--Agreed to terms with G Jason Elliott and F B.J. Young on two-year contracts and F Toivo Suursoo on a one-year contract.  PITTSBURGH PENGUINS--Signed C Toby Petersen.  East Coast Hockey League  JOHNSTOWN CHIEFS--Agreed to terms with D Brent Bilodeau and G Karol Kirzan.  United States Hockey League  SIOUX FALLS STAMPEDE--Announced F Rick Gorman has signed a contract with Syracuse of the AHL.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE  ALMA--Named Nathan Kronewetter men's assistant soccer coach.  ARMSTRONG STATE--Named Flori Willie women's assistant basketball coach and Andrea Bloodworth women's graduate assistant basketball coach.  DAYTON--Named Bill Comar men's assistant basketball coach and Josh Postorino coordinator of basketball operations.  ELON--Named Patti Raduenz softball coach.  MINNESOTA--Named Melissa Young-Kruse women's assistant basketball coach.  OHIO NORTHERN--Named Eric Westerfield assistant football coach and women's golf coach and Tim Hibbs assistant football coach.  OHIO WESLEYAN--Named Marge Redmond field hockey coach.  PACE--Named Tanya Yavarow women's assistant soccer coach.  UTAH--Named Beth Jerome women's assistant swimming coach.  UTICA--Named Tim Myslinski defensive coordinator, Frank Palmisano tight ends coach, Carvon Brazier running backs coach, Vin Sorce defensive assistant and William Berry defensive line coach.  VERMONT--Named Rick Gouse women's volleyball coach.  WENTWORTH--Named Tom Randolph baseball coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
