<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y19BRI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E6DB133EF93AA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1692" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Jeanne Moore</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>INDONESIA: BOOST FOR MILITARY  The country's top legislative body passed a decree allowing the military to keep its seats in the legislature until 2009, and banned retroactive prosecution of rights cases. The new laws contradict President Abdurrahman Wahid's campaign to remove the once-all-powerful military from politics and bring to justice members of the security forces accused of committing abuses in strife-torn regions like Aceh and East Timor.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>INDONESIA: BOOST FOR MILITARY  The country's top legislative body passed a decree allowing the military to keep its seats in the legislature until 2009, and banned retroactive prosecution of rights cases. The new laws contradict President Abdurrahman Wahid's campaign to remove the once-all-powerful military from politics and bring to justice members of the security forces accused of committing abuses in strife-torn regions like Aceh and East Timor.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>SRI LANKA: ELECTION CALLED  President Chandrika Kumaratunga dissolved Parliament six days before the end of its six-year term and called national elections for Oct. 10. Her constitutional plan for a quasi-federal system that would give greater autonomy to minority Tamils is dead for now, but she has said she will revive the proposal -- an effort to bring peace to a nation embroiled in a civil war with separatist Tamil militants -- after the elections.</p>
        <p>Celia W. Dugger (NYT)</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINES: HOSTAGE RELEASE EXPECTED  Muslim separatist rebels were expected to free the rest of their hostages today after releasing three Malaysians yesterday, said the chief government negotiator, Roberto Aventajado. The 25 remaining captives include nine Westerners abducted at a diving resort in Malaysia in April.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINES: ENVIRONMENTAL SUIT  More than 100 people filed suit against the United States and the Philippines, seeking $103 billion for deaths and illnesses they say were caused by hazardous waste at former American military bases. American officials have offered to help solve the Philippines' environmental problems, but insisted Washington has no legal obligation to clean up toxic wastes at the former bases.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>INDIA: BARGAINING OVER ACTOR  Veerappan, the South Indian outlaw who kidnapped a movie star, had demanded that five Tamil militants be released from jail, and the state of Tamil Nadu had agreed. But four of the militants refused to be released on bail, insisting that all charges against them be dropped before they are freed. Their refusal may further delay the release of the actor, Rajkumar.</p>
        <p>Celia W. Dugger (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFGHANISTAN: CALL FOR RECOGNITION  The Taliban government called for international recognition as it celebrated the country's 81st independence anniversary with a military parade featuring thousands of soldiers. Now, only Pakistan, Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates have diplomatic ties with the Islamic militia that has controlled most of the country since 1996.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>KOSOVO: TWO EXPLOSIONS  A grenade attack slightly wounded nine Serbian children in a Kosovo village, hours after an explosion in the province's capital, Pristina, wounded one woman and damaged several political offices, NATO said. The children were wounded when unidentified assailants threw two hand grenades onto a basketball court in Crkven Vodica. The explosion in Pristina was apparently caused by a bomb.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>SWITZERLAND: VOTE ON FOREIGNERS CRITICIZED  The Swiss government spoke out against a proposal to limit the country's foreign population, saying such a measure would damage Switzerland's economy and credibility. Swiss citizens will vote on Sept. 24 on the proposal to cap the proportion of foreigners at 18 percent of the population. As of last year, foreigners made up 19.2 percent of the country's residents.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>NICARAGUA: TAIWAN LEADER CULTIVATES TIES  The new president of Taiwan, Chen Shui-bian, concluded a visit to Nicaragua, one of the Latin American nations that has diplomatic relations with Taiwan, with a promise to promote investment in the Central American nation. He then flew to Costa Rica.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>COLOMBIA: DRUG SUSPECT EXTRADITED  Alberto Orlandez Gamboa, accused of leading one of Colombia's most powerful drug cartels, was sent to the United States to stand trial, days after drug dealers threatened violence if authorities carried out the extradition. He will face charges in United States District Court in Manhattan that he conspired to import and distribute thousands of pounds of cocaine from Colombia to New York and other American destinations. After a 10-year moratorium on extraditions, Mr. Gamboa is the third Colombian sent to the United States to face drug charges in the past nine months.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>ZIMBABWE: MORE FARM TAKEOVERS  The government said it would seize 229 more farms to resettle blacks, bringing to 3,270 the number of white-owned farms involved in its controversial land reform program. Last week the government began settling black families on 200 farms. The government plans to relocate peasants on about 100 farms in each of Zimbabwe's eight provinces before the onset of the rainy season in about two months' time.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>IVORY COAST: JUNTA LEADER TO RUN  The country's military ruler, Gen. Robert Guei, formally registered to contest a Sept. 17 presidential election he called to return Ivory Coast to civilian rule. General Guei came to power last December in Ivory Coast's first military coup, and expectations of a Guei candidacy have already prompted street protests.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>IRAQ: U.N. BODY URGES END TO SANCTIONS  The United Nations Subcommission on the Promotion and Protection of Human Rights called for the lifting of 10-year-old sanctions on Iraq, saying they had ''condemned an innocent people to hunger, disease, ignorance and even death.'' It said the United Nations' oil-for-food program, which since 1996 has allowed Iraq to sell oil to buy food and other essentials, was not meeting people's needs. Washington opposes easing sanctions, insisting that President Saddam Hussein is responsible for his people's suffering.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
