<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Piazza and Alfonzo Share Top Billing in Mets' Victory</title>
    <meta content="19METS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223650"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Dodgers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Florida Marlins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DA133EF93AA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1022" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Piazza and Alfonzo Share Top Billing in Mets' Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>piazzo</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sports Illustrated christened Mike Piazza as ''The Man'' on its cover this week, but the Mets catcher does not feel pressure to carry his team. He is thrilled with his supporting cast, and he needs it to produce if he is going to reach the World Series for the first time in his career. ''You're only as good as the guys around you,'' Piazza said.</p>
        <p>Piazza and the Mets began a three-game series tonight at Dodger Stadium, where Piazza began his career eight years ago and where he seemed destined to end it. But Piazza never led the Dodgers to a playoff victory, and they traded him to the the Florida Marlins in May 1998. Now Piazza looks poised to lead the Mets deep into the postseason. Games like tonight's make that seem possible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sports Illustrated christened Mike Piazza as ''The Man'' on its cover this week, but the Mets catcher does not feel pressure to carry his team. He is thrilled with his supporting cast, and he needs it to produce if he is going to reach the World Series for the first time in his career. ''You're only as good as the guys around you,'' Piazza said.</p>
        <p>Piazza and the Mets began a three-game series tonight at Dodger Stadium, where Piazza began his career eight years ago and where he seemed destined to end it. But Piazza never led the Dodgers to a playoff victory, and they traded him to the the Florida Marlins in May 1998. Now Piazza looks poised to lead the Mets deep into the postseason. Games like tonight's make that seem possible.</p>
        <p>Piazza slugged a two-run homer off Dodgers ace Kevin Brown in the third inning, but the Dodgers tied the score. It was Edgardo Alfonzo, Piazza's co-star, who drove in the winning run in a 5-3 Mets victory.</p>
        <p>After Joe McEwing singled and advanced to third on a wild pickoff throw by reliever Terry Adams, Alfonzo stroked his third single of the night to break a tie in the eighth inning. John Franco and Armando Benitez preserved the lead, ensuring the victory for Rick White, who worked one and two-thirds overpowering innings in relief of Al Leiter.</p>
        <p>Alfonzo added his fourth hit, a double, in the ninth inning, and Piazza singled him home for his 100th run batted in. This is the fifth season in a row that Piazza has reached that R.B.I. plateau.</p>
        <p>Leiter fell apart in a three-run Dodger sixth that erased the 3-0 lead the Mets built on Piazza's homer. Gary Sheffield, the best player of the five the Dodgers received from the Marlins in the Piazza trade, homered for the Dodgers' first run. Sheffield's popularity in Los Angeles will grow the more he produces, but he has said he does not feel embraced by the fans, many of whom still revere Piazza. Their statistics since the trade are similar, with Piazza holding an edge in batting average and runs batted in, Sheffield in on-base percentage and runs scored.</p>
        <p>The biggest difference is in the fortunes of the teams. The Mets are 65 games above .500 since they acquired Piazza from the Marlins. The Dodgers are only one game above .500 since they sent Piazza away.</p>
        <p>''The fans haven't gotten over it because of what Mike Piazza meant to the Dodgers, and I understand that,'' Dodgers Chairman Bob Daly said recently. ''That thing got messed up, and everyone knows about it.''</p>
        <p>Sheffield is the only player from the trade who is still with the Dodgers. Seven months after trading Piazza, they signed Brown to a seven-year, $105 million contract. Last winter, they signed outfielder Shawn Green to a six-year, $84 million deal. Both players have a higher average annual salary than the Dodgers offered Piazza.</p>
        <p>The Dodger Stadium crowd, so relaxed so often, has a strong reaction whenever Piazza comes to bat; he is booed and cheered with passion. He lined out in his first at-bat, then came up in the third with one out, after Edgardo Alfonzo lashed a single off the second baseman's glove.</p>
        <p>Brown's 1-1 fastball tailed inside on Piazza, but it did not sink. Piazza hit it squarely, and the ball carried into the left-center-field bleachers to give the Mets a 3-0 lead and Piazza his 32nd home run. He also drove in a run for the first time in a week. Piazza has not exactly slumped, but the two-run homer followed his only five-start stretch this year in which he did not drive in a run.</p>
        <p>The home run was an emphatic way to score off Brown, whose pitches, some hitters think, have more movement than any other pitcher's. Darren Dreifort, the right-hander who faces the Mets on Sunday, challenges Brown for that distinction.</p>
        <p>In the second, the Mets got their first run on two infield hits and an error by shortstop Kevin Elster, who could not glove Leiter's grounder. Piazza's homer brought in the only earned runs Brown allowed in an abbreviated outing. He was removed for a pinch-hitter in the sixth, an inning that started with a home run by Sheffield, his 38th.</p>
        <p>Eric Karros then singled and Shawn Green doubled to the warning track in center. A single by Adrian Beltre cut the Mets' lead to 3-2, and Green scored the game-tying run on a sacrifice fly, with Jay Payton's throw bouncing off his leg before it reached the plate. Leiter would get no more outs, walking the next two hitters -- including Jim Leyritz, batting for Brown -- and yielding to Rick White.</p>
        <p>White fanned F. P. Santangelo with a hard splitter, but Mark Grudzielanek grounded sharply down the right-field line. First baseman Todd Zeile, the other player the Dodgers traded when they dealt Piazza, dove to his left and speared it, flipping to White for the inning-ending out.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Mets left-hander MIKE HAMPTON, who left Thursday's start in the fourth inning because of a stress fracture in his right ribs, played catch on flat ground before Friday's game against the Dodgers, mainly to keep his shoulder in shape because his bullpen session has been pushed back. The Mets are not sure if Hampton will make his next scheduled start, on Tuesday in San Diego. But Hampton has pitched with the discomfort for weeks, and now that the condition has been diagnosed, Manager BOBBY VALENTINE said, ''They think there might be things that can be done to make it feel better before he pitches.'' . . . Left fielder BENNY AGBAYANI, who was hit on the left elbow on Thursday for the third time since the All-Star Game break, was given Friday off. . . . Shortstop MIKE BORDICK committed his fifth error in 20 games as a Met on a sharp, one-hop grounder by ERIC KARROS in the fourth. But the Dodgers did not score in the inning.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
