<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Erstad Steals One From the Yanks</title>
    <meta content="19YANK$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223651"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Anaheim Angels</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Angels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E1DA133EF93AA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1087" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Erstad Steals One From the Yanks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anaheim Angels defeat New York Yankees, 9-8; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You cannot see the whole field from the home bench at Yankee Stadium. There is a small rise that obscures the view of the left fielder, and the first base stands block the view of the right-field corner. From his corner seat in the dugout, Yankees Manager Joe Torre kept waiting for the fans to react and report on the doings of Anaheim left fielder Darin Erstad last night.</p>
        <p>After the Yankees blew a five-run lead in the ninth -- only the second time in Yankee Stadium history that has happened -- Erstad raced back and dove for Jorge Posada's long drive in the bottom of the 10th, and Torre heard silence; Erstad had completed a spectacular catch. And in the top of the 11th, Erstad lifted a high drive deep to right field.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You cannot see the whole field from the home bench at Yankee Stadium. There is a small rise that obscures the view of the left fielder, and the first base stands block the view of the right-field corner. From his corner seat in the dugout, Yankees Manager Joe Torre kept waiting for the fans to react and report on the doings of Anaheim left fielder Darin Erstad last night.</p>
        <p>After the Yankees blew a five-run lead in the ninth -- only the second time in Yankee Stadium history that has happened -- Erstad raced back and dove for Jorge Posada's long drive in the bottom of the 10th, and Torre heard silence; Erstad had completed a spectacular catch. And in the top of the 11th, Erstad lifted a high drive deep to right field.</p>
        <p>More silence. More bad news. Erstad's home run capped a stunning performance in Anaheim's wild 9-8 victory over the Yankees, a defeat that reduced the Yankees' lead over Boston in the American League East to three games. ''That one stung,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>It must have. The Yankees hadn't blown a five-run lead in the ninth inning since May 16, 1968, at Boston's Fenway Park. The only other time they blew a five-run, ninth-inning lead at Yankee Stadium was on Aug. 8, 1953, against the Senators.</p>
        <p>Roger Clemens probably had more reason to be exasperated by the defeat last night. He had walked off the mound to a standing ovation in the ninth inning, tipping his cap and raising a gloved hand, his 258th career victory all but assured. The Yankees led, 8-3. But later, when Clemens reviewed the game for reporters, a small smile crossed his face when he mentioned Erstad, and his catch -- ''one of the top three catches I've seen in my 17 years.'' It was a smile of admiration.</p>
        <p>''A lot happened in that game,'' said Clemens. ''Where do you begin?''</p>
        <p>Glenallen Hill had homered in the fourth and again in the fifth inning, his eighth and ninth homers in his first 43 at-bats for the Yankees, and with the Yankees holding a 7-3 lead over the Angels, who had played horribly in this series up to that moment, the fans were feeling very good and summoned Hill out for a curtain call.</p>
        <p>Clemens overcame some early control problems and dominated the Angels through the seventh and the eighth innings. He allowed back-to-back singles to start the ninth with the Yankees winning, 8-3; his pitch count was 122, and Torre called for Jeff Nelson. But after Nelson retired Adam Kennedy on a fly-out, he walked Kevin Stocker. Later, Torre would point to this, among all of the falling dominos on a disastrous evening: ''A tough pill to take,'' he called the walk issued by Nelson, who was not available for comment after the game.</p>
        <p>Torre replaced Nelson with Rivera, who had converted 10 of his last 11 save chances. But the air of invincibility has disappeared from Rivera this year. Erstad grounded to third and it appeared for an instant that Luis Sojo was going to execute a game-ending double play, stepping on third for the force and throwing to first. But Erstad beat Sojo's throw to the bag. Two outs.</p>
        <p>Orlando Palmeiro pulled a double inside first base and down the line, reducing the lead to three runs. Mo Vaughn was next, he and fouled Rivera's first pitch off the right toes of Posada.</p>
        <p>The catcher limped away from the plate and slumped to the ground, where he remained for a couple of minutes, waiting out the pain. Posada stood up, returned to his position, called for a fastball -- and Vaughn launched a high drive that landed in the right-field stands, tying the game, sucking all emotion other than disappointment out of Yankee Stadium. Tie score, on Rivera's fifth blown save of the year; he converted 45 of 49 last year. Rivera was not available for comment after the game.</p>
        <p>But it seemed the Yankees would win the game in the bottom of the 10th. They had a runner at third and two out, and the Angels elected to walk Derek Jeter intentionally to pitch to Posada.</p>
        <p>Shigetoshi Hasegawa got two strikes on Posada, and Erstad, playing left field, moved in and to his right, not wanting Posada to fight off a tough pitch and bloop a game-winning hit over the infield. ''If he was going to beat us, I wanted him to beat us over our heads,'' said Erstad.</p>
        <p>Posada smashed a line drive toward left-center, to Erstad's left and seemingly over his head. Erstad raced back, seeing the ball all the way, but unsure of whether he would reach it in time. Luis Polonia moved down the third base line; he would be the winning run if Posada's drive fell.</p>
        <p>Erstad, moving at a 45-degree angle, dove and reached for the ball. Torre waited to see the ball bounce, waited to hear the crowd roar. Mike Stanton, warming up in the bullpen, saw the ball and Erstad go out of sight.</p>
        <p>But there was nothing. Erstad felt the glove thump into the webbing of his glove, landed hard against the grass and slid. The Angels' players were shouting. The Yankees were in stunned silence.</p>
        <p>Stanton relieved for the Yankees in the top of the 11th, and Erstad was due to hit second. He went to the plate looking for a fastball. Stanton threw him a hanging curve. ''Right over the middle of the plate,'' Stanton recalled. And Erstad hit it imperfectly, high and to right field. Far enough. Anaheim held off the Yankees in the bottom of the 11th, leaving Torre to explain the loss.</p>
        <p>But Torre smiled, too, when Erstad's name was raised. ''This game belonged to him,'' said Torre. ''He was spectacular.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>CHUCK KNOBLAUCH seems to be making progress in his rehabilitation from a sore elbow. Knoblauch made 15 throws Thursday, and then yesterday he felt well enough to take ground balls and throw.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
