<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Defeated Mexico Party Faces Next Test in Chiapas</title>
    <meta content="Y19MEX$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000825T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EFD7123EF93AA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Defeated Mexico Party Faces Next Test in Chiapas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINGER THOMPSON</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, Aug. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although he calls himself a religious man, there is something mildly unholy about the way Pablo Salazar Mendiguchia delights in the prospect of killing the PRI.</p>
        <p>As he campaigns to be governor of Chiapas, the 45-year-old senator and father of three projects himself as a kind of political dragon-slayer, struggling against a government that has wreaked havoc on the lives of poor and defenseless Mexicans for more than seven decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although he calls himself a religious man, there is something mildly unholy about the way Pablo Salazar Mendiguchia delights in the prospect of killing the PRI.</p>
        <p>As he campaigns to be governor of Chiapas, the 45-year-old senator and father of three projects himself as a kind of political dragon-slayer, struggling against a government that has wreaked havoc on the lives of poor and defenseless Mexicans for more than seven decades.</p>
        <p>The fire-breather that he fights, the long-governing Institutional Revolutionary Party, known as the PRI, was severely wounded on July 2 when it lost the presidency for the first time since 1929. But, Mr. Salazar warns, the party still gasps with life.</p>
        <p>So with the help of his supporters at the polls, the candidate promises to deliver the coup de grace.</p>
        <p>''The PRI has entered intensive care,'' he called out to some 400 supporters in a rally outside the city of San Cristobal de las Casas. ''It is gasping for breath. And on Aug. 20 we are going to disconnect its oxygen tank and give a Christian burial to a party that no longer has a place in Chiapas.''</p>
        <p>In the dawning months of what may be a new era of democracy in Mexico, the people of Chiapas will be the first to test the depths of this country's political reforms when they go to the polls on Sunday to elect a new governor.</p>
        <p>The election -- in a state racked by generations of poverty, layers of social divisions and sporadic violence between the government and the Zapatista rebels -- will be the first major state contest since the fall of the PRI on July 2. It offers a look at how local politics have begun to evolve in Mexico, and for the PRI this election is widely seen as a test of the party's ability to survive among the scrappy forces of the opposition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salazar, a former member of the PRI who served as a mediator between the government and the Zapatistas, says a fair, transparent election will mean the difference between war and peace.</p>
        <p>As governor, he says, he would urge the president to drastically reduce the military presence in Chiapas, estimated at up to 50,000 troops. And he says he would create political openings that would allow leaders of the rebel Zapatista army to stop their fight and join the government in resolving the social crises in Chiapas.</p>
        <p>He offers his campaign as a testament to his ability to forge agreements. Eight opposition parties with otherwise divergent agendas -- including the conservative National Action Party of the president-elect and the leftist Democratic Revolutionary Party -- have united behind him.</p>
        <p>''The past governors have been obsessed with defeating the Zapatistas,'' Mr. Salazar said in an interview. ''That is not in my agenda. I am not a Zapatista, but I have learned to understand them, and I believe that we must try to get them involved in solutions.''</p>
        <p>Although the PRI carried about 45 percent of the vote in Chiapas during last month's presidential election, opinion polls and most political analysts predict that Mr. Salazar will win by a comfortable margin.</p>
        <p>His opponent, Sami David, 50, who is the PRI's candidate, has found more than the polls to be ominous. At the start of a campaign visit to his opponent's hometown, Soyalo, Mr. David was greeted by a belligerent mob that pelted his entourage with rocks and sticks, and he was forced to scramble for his safety.</p>
        <p>''It appears that I have not come at the best time to the party,'' said an exasperated Mr. David, referring to his run for governor.</p>
        <p>Farther east, among people in a village called Corazon de Maria, the people seem likely to cast their votes more as an act of protest against the PRI than a show of support for the opposition.</p>
        <p>Radishes in this village grow as big as apples, while the people languish from illiteracy and poverty. Although the village sits in the shadow of a brand new airport and less than 10 miles from one of Chiapas's largest cities, the people of Corazon de Maria still do not have paved roads or clean drinking water.</p>
        <p>On good days, farmers said, they sell their radishes at a local market for about $5 a crate. But most days are bad, and the farmers are stuck giving away their produce for pennies.</p>
        <p>''We have decided that we will not vote for the PRI,'' said Javier Gomez Diaz, 19, taking a break from bundling his radishes for market. ''Even if they come here and make promises, they will not deceive us anymore.''</p>
        <p>Although this discontent echoes across most of the state, some communities continue to support the PRI. But their support hardly sounds enthusiastic.</p>
        <p>In Amentenango del Valle, a community supported mostly by the work of women who mold clay pots, Petrona Gomez Hernandez, 34, described voting for the PRI more as a habit than an act of conviction.</p>
        <p>''It is our custom to vote for the PRI,'' she said. ''We have always given them our vote.''</p>
        <p>When asked if the PRI had improved the lives of people in her community, she shook her head. ''Our lives never change,'' she said. ''We are poor, and that is how we will continue: poor until we die.''</p>
        <p>At a rally there earlier in the afternoon, Mr. David presented his candidacy as a force for reform across Chiapas and within his own party. He told voters that he would increase government spending on social programs, that he would make the government more accessible to their pleas for assistance in selling their clay pots across the country, that he would work to build peace.</p>
        <p>''We must work so that there are more doves of peace than there are guns in Chiapas,'' he said, holding up the clay doves made by young girls in training to become pot makers. ''There must be more doves of peace than expressions of impunity, more doves of peace than injustice and insecurity.</p>
        <p>Election monitors said that they had received hundreds of reports about PRI campaign officials trying to coerce voters by telling them that their social benefits would be cut if the opposition won. But recent incidents among Zapatista supporters and right-wing paramilitary groups have raised concerns about the possibility of violence on election day.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, 90 people accused of supporting the rebels were burned out of their homes by a masked group of men carrying rifles and semiautomatic weapons. The group, calling itself Peace and Justice, refused to let the residents return to their land for several days until it was chased away by military troops.</p>
        <p>Such attacks, observers worry, may frighten voters from going to the polls on Sunday. In last month's election, more than 50 percent of voters in Chiapas did not cast ballots, the highest abstention rate in the nation.</p>
        <p>A high turnout is crucial to Pablo Salazar. But when he winds up his speeches -- often full of plans to increase higher education, reform the state justice system and improve health care -- he asks more of his supporters than just their votes. He enlists them for duty.</p>
        <p>The PRI is preparing more of the dirty election tricks that have kept it in power for 71 years, he says. And the only way to stop them, he adds, is by doing whatever it takes to defend people's votes. He asks supporters to stay at the polls all day to monitor the voting, and then to form caravans of cars to escort the ballot boxes to the tally stations.</p>
        <p>Then, with a sly smile spreading across his face, Mr. Salazar warns that there will be trouble for anyone who stands in their way.</p>
        <p>''Do you think the PRI would try to steal the ballots if they see a group as big as this one watching over the polls?'' he said to a crowd that filled the plaza in Jitotol. ''And if they do, we will beat them. If anyone dares, we will tie them up.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 25, 2000, Friday  An article on Saturday about the election for governor in the Mexican state of Chiapas, and a related map, misspelled the name of a town where one candidate held a campaign rally. It was Amatenango, not Amen tenango.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 25, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>An article on Saturday about the election for governor in the Mexican state of Chiapas, and a related map, misspelled the name of a town where one candidate held a campaign rally. It was Amatenango, not Amen tenango.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
