<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Northwest, Still Undecided</title>
    <meta content="19STA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223654"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE IMPRESSIONS -- WASHINGTON STATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nader, Ralph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verhovek, Sam Howe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Ralph Nader</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EFDA133EF93AA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Northwest, Still Undecided</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Verhovek, Sam Howe</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, Aug. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Group of friends watching Vice Pres Al Gore's acceptance speech at Democratic National Convention grumble that only Ralph Nader is bringing up the issues they consider central to this election: corporate power, the forces of globalization and widening divide between the rich and the poor, in US and around the world; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In one obvious sense, it would be hard to consider Martine Dedek or John Roderick ''swing voters'' in the coming presidential election. Young, unabashedly liberal, both proud participants in last fall's demonstrations here against the World Trade Organization, they both roll their eyes and offer a vigorous ''no way'' when asked if they would consider voting for the Republican candidate, George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>And yet, they will definitely go to the polls in November, they are still undecided, and they could be part of a hugely influential group in this election, especially in West Coast states where some polls suggest that as many as 10 percent of voters express a preference for Ralph Nader, the Green Party nominee. They are among the voters who are still making up their mind between Al Gore and Mr. Nader.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In one obvious sense, it would be hard to consider Martine Dedek or John Roderick ''swing voters'' in the coming presidential election. Young, unabashedly liberal, both proud participants in last fall's demonstrations here against the World Trade Organization, they both roll their eyes and offer a vigorous ''no way'' when asked if they would consider voting for the Republican candidate, George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>And yet, they will definitely go to the polls in November, they are still undecided, and they could be part of a hugely influential group in this election, especially in West Coast states where some polls suggest that as many as 10 percent of voters express a preference for Ralph Nader, the Green Party nominee. They are among the voters who are still making up their mind between Al Gore and Mr. Nader.</p>
        <p>So as they followed the Democratic convention this week, gathering at a friend's house Thursday night to watch Mr. Gore accept the party nomination, they were willing to listen intently to the vice president's speech. They came away ambivalent -- suggesting that while Mr. Gore failed to dazzle or even much impress them with his speech in Los Angeles, he may have drawn enough of a distinction between himself and Mr. Bush to get their vote if the election seems close in November.</p>
        <p>The Gore speech left all the friends grumbling that only Mr. Nader was still bringing up the issues they considered central in this election: corporate power, the forces of globalization, the widening divide between the rich and the poor, here in this country and around the world. They scoffed at many parts, and Ms. Dedek, 28, who has worked as an advocate for battered women and for welfare recipients, at one point pronounced the whole speech ''so orchestrated, so predictable, so scripted.''</p>
        <p>She nearly rose out of her chair at one point when Mr. Gore pledged to bring down the rising cost of prescription drugs. ''I mean, he's still not getting at any of the larger issues here,'' Ms. Dedek said. ''Why are prescription drugs so expensive?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Roderick, a singer-songwriter and the piano player in a Seattle rock band, nodded in agreement, and worried aloud that a Gore victory might bring four more years of complacency.</p>
        <p>''I'm not horrified about the idea of Bush winning this election,'' said Mr. Roderick, 31, who is about to graduate from the University of Washington with a degree in the comparative history of ideas. ''It could be the thing that reunites liberals around a common enemy, I guess, for lack of a better word. It could force liberals to see what their principles are.''</p>
        <p>Another friend, Phil Campbell, a reporter for The Stranger, an alternative weekly newspaper in Seattle, said Mr. Gore still left him feeling uncomfortable.</p>
        <p>''There's this obsession he has with his imperfections,'' said Mr. Campbell, 27, who covers criminal-justice issues, breaking into an imitation of Mr. Gore's voice as he watched the speech. ''I'm not popular; I'm not at ease with myself,' '' he intoned, as his friends laughed. ''It's weird. A little self-deprecation's fine, but this is ridiculous.''</p>
        <p>If the election looks like a rout for either candidate of the two main parties, there was general agreement that a vote for Mr. Nader would be in order. But if the election looks close, the friends said, it could be a very different matter -- and here, their words may offer some salve to the Gore campaign, which has always insisted that in the end, many people will not want to ''throw away'' their vote on Mr. Nader.</p>
        <p>''If it looks like Gore is clearly winning on Election Day, then you can send a vote for Nader, especially with the time difference'' on the West Coast, Mr. Campbell explained. ''If you know Gore's going to win, you can vote for Nader and contribute to that message being sent.'' But if it looks like a tight contest, he said, he will probably vote for Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dedek, who has a job in public relations, reluctantly agreed, explaining that on one core issue raised by Mr. Gore, she thought there was a critical difference between him and Mr. Bush -- abortion rights.</p>
        <p>''To me, knowing that Bush is so pro-life, that's just really scary,'' she said. ''Knowing that he could appoint all those Supreme Court justices. That is something that strikes me as a big difference'' between the two major-party candidates, she added.</p>
        <p>Ariella Robison, 26, a technical publisher for a software company, nodded in vigorous agreement. Mr. Bush, she said, gave her a ''serious case of the willies,'' with, among other things, his stated opposition to abortion. For that reason alone, she said, she was likely to wind up voting for Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roderick, like the others watching with him, said he would wait to learn more from the debates, and said he would be  outraged if Mr. Nader was excluded. ''I did come into this situation feeling the only responsible vote was a vote for Nader,'' he said. Still, he said, the acceptance speech by Mr. Gore had ''put my vote back in play,'' because the vice president touched on important themes. ''I'm susceptible to that kind of Democratic rhetoric -- talking about the poor, about schools, about paying teachers what they're worth. As much as I believe those are the first things that always go out the window, he was talking about them.''</p>
        <p>''And yet'' -- and here Mr. Roderick smiled at himself for trawling back and forth again with his thoughts -- ''everyone seems to want to reduce this whole thing to Bush against Gore. And that's a condensation I don't want to participate in.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE IMPRESSIONS -- WASHINGTON STATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
