<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Religion Journal; Amsterdam Conference Sets Goals for Evangelists</title>
    <meta content="Y19REL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223587"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Evangelical Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missionaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Africa</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">center for applied research in the apostolate</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Niebuhr, Gustav</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Billy (Rev)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Columns/Religion Journal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evangelical Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missionaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E7DF133EF93AA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Religion Journal; Amsterdam Conference Sets Goals for Evangelists</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUSTAV NIEBUHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Niebuhr, Gustav</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Conference of 10,000 evangelists in Amsterdam sponsored by Rev Billy Graham's organization issues document intended to be a broad statement of purpose for evangelists in proclaiming Christian gospel in 21st century; American Roman Catholic bishops' conference sends three bishops to Central and East Africa's Great Lakes region to learn about the problems facing refugees and displaced people, of whom there are more than three million in that region alone; Center for Applied Research in the Apostolate, a Catholic group, reports that 30 percent of recent immigrants to US identify themselves as something other than Protesant, Catholic or Jewish, that nearly 15 percent profess no religion and that 41 precent say they are Catholic (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Rev. Billy Graham's organization convened a conference of more than 10,000 evangelists from around the world in Amsterdam on July 29, the event was described as notable for its size and its extraordinary international composition, with people from more than 200 nations and territories represented.</p>
        <p>But despite the fact that the event, Amsterdam 2000, was intended primarily as a series of teaching and training sessions, its organizers also produced a document as the conference ended last week. It is intended to be a broad statement of purpose for evangelists in proclaiming the Christian gospel in the 21st century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Rev. Billy Graham's organization convened a conference of more than 10,000 evangelists from around the world in Amsterdam on July 29, the event was described as notable for its size and its extraordinary international composition, with people from more than 200 nations and territories represented.</p>
        <p>But despite the fact that the event, Amsterdam 2000, was intended primarily as a series of teaching and training sessions, its organizers also produced a document as the conference ended last week. It is intended to be a broad statement of purpose for evangelists in proclaiming the Christian gospel in the 21st century.</p>
        <p>The Amsterdam Declaration, as it is called, includes 14 points and runs to nine single-spaced pages. It may be particularly interesting on several counts, not least in saying that women and young people should be encouraged to be gospel teachers, in urging that evangelists be sensitive to the societies in which they work (not equating Christianity itself with any particular culture) and in its embrace of social responsibility, like fighting poverty and racism.</p>
        <p>The document is firm in rejecting the belief that there is no absolute truth and also in declaring that evangelists are obliged to present the Christian gospel as authoritative, even while treating people of other religions with respect.</p>
        <p>It also calls for evangelists to be prayerful and to be accountable for their lives, avoiding scandal. It cites ''money, sex, pride, power, neglect of family and lack of integrity,'' temptations that so spectacularly afflicted some prominent television preachers in the United States a decade ago.</p>
        <p>In addition, the document calls for all evangelists to ''stand in solidarity'' with Christians persecuted for their beliefs. In that sense, it reflects a concern emerging in the United States and elsewhere that some of the places in the world where Christianity is growing fastest are also among the most difficult for believers.</p>
        <p>Bishops' Mission to Africa</p>
        <p>An unusual event began yesterday, when three American bishops departed for Central and East Africa's Great Lakes region, on a two-week journey to learn about the problems facing refugees and displaced people, of whom there are more than three million in that region alone. Among the bishops' goals, the National Conference of Catholic Bishops says, is to discover what specific forms of assistance -- in terms of public policy and material aid -- the refugees need and, upon returning, to lobby for that help, from such sources as the United States government, the United Nations and Catholic church agencies.</p>
        <p>The visit comes as Catholic leaders, including Pope John Paul II, as well as other religious organizations and labor unions have become increasingly outspoken in urging governments and international banks to forgive the foreign debts of poor nations, especially in Africa, so that those nations can spend more on their own internal needs.</p>
        <p>The bishops' schedule calls for them to visit Burundi, Rwanda, Congo (the former Zaire) and the Congo Republic, all of which have been deeply affected by several years' of wars and civil turmoil that have disrupted their societies. The group will also go to Kenya, which has one of the largest refugee encampments in the region.</p>
        <p>The conference said the three prelates, Bishop Philip F. Straling of Reno, Nev., Auxiliary Bishop Thomas Wenski of Miami and Bishop Donald Pelotte of Gallup, N.M., will visit refugee camps and meet with officials of humanitarian aid agencies, local government officials and Catholic leaders. Bishop Wenski serves on the American bishops' Migration Committee, and Bishop Pelotte will represent Catholic Relief Services.</p>
        <p>David Early, a spokesman for the bishops' conference, said the Migration Committee, which also deals with issues affecting American immigrants, wanted to draw attention to the refugee camps and the needs of those in them.</p>
        <p>A New Wave of Immigrants</p>
        <p>On the subject of new American immigrants, a Roman Catholic church-related research organization in Washington recently noted some interesting statistics about that group's religious identities, indicating differences from the long-standing religious situation in the United States. The statistics, taken from a conference at Georgetown University, suggest how the new wave of immigrants may change the nation's religious makeup.</p>
        <p>The organization, the Center for Applied Research in the Apostolate, based at Georgetown, reported in its summer newsletter that nearly 30 percent of recent immigrants in a 1996 survey described themselves as something other than Protestant, Catholic or Jewish, which together have long formed the three dominant categories in American religious life.</p>
        <p>Nearly 15 percent of the new immigrants said they had no religion, more than 7 percent said they were Muslim, 4 percent described themselves as Buddhist and more than 3 percent said they were Hindu, the center said. (All these figures, by the way, far exceed survey results for these categories among the general American population.)</p>
        <p>The center also reported that more than 41 percent of the recent immigrants said they were Catholics (compared with about 25 percent of the overall American population); just 9 percent said they were Protestants (who make up about half the overall population, when one includes both mainline and evangelical Protestants in that category).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
