<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Powerhouse Teams Are Picking Up Where They Left Off Last Season</title>
    <meta content="16SKOO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/16/sports/16SKOO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230840"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HIGH SCHOOL FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glickson, Grant</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E5DB1138F935A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1084" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Powerhouse Teams Are Picking Up Where They Left Off Last Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRANT GLICKSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glickson, Grant</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses outlook for high school football season in NYC metropolitan area (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While the high school football season begins in earnest this weekend, powerhouse programs like St. Anthony's of South Huntington, N.Y., Monsignor Farrell of Staten Island, Poly Prep of Brooklyn and Hackensack in New Jersey appear to be in midseason form. They notched impressive victories in their openers last weekend.</p>
        <p>''I knew coming into the game that St. Anthony's had an outstanding offense,'' said Coach Tony Karcich of St. Joseph, a top program in Montvale, N.J. ''But what amazed me about them was their execution. They were operating on all cylinders.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While the high school football season begins in earnest this weekend, powerhouse programs like St. Anthony's of South Huntington, N.Y., Monsignor Farrell of Staten Island, Poly Prep of Brooklyn and Hackensack in New Jersey appear to be in midseason form. They notched impressive victories in their openers last weekend.</p>
        <p>''I knew coming into the game that St. Anthony's had an outstanding offense,'' said Coach Tony Karcich of St. Joseph, a top program in Montvale, N.J. ''But what amazed me about them was their execution. They were operating on all cylinders.''</p>
        <p>Last weekend St. Anthony's, the Catholic High School Football League finalist in 1999, disposed of St. Joseph, the top-ranked team in New Jersey last year, 35-16; Farrell, the C.H.S.F.L.'s two-time defending champion, defeated Canarsie, a Public Schools Athletic League contender, 24-6; Poly Prep, which has lost one game in four seasons, defeated Bethlehem, Pa., 34-20; and Hackensack routed Kennedy of Paterson, N.J., 45-0.</p>
        <p>Tonight, in a big Catholic school matchup, St. Anthony's, the fourth-ranked team in the New York State Coaches' poll, will try to avenge losses to Farrell in the title game last year and in a semifinal game in 1998.  For the Friars to return to glory, they will need John Fiske (241 yards on 5 rushes, 3 touchdowns) and Frank Lazio (138 yards on 12 carries) to continue to carry the offensive load. Farrell's bid to win a third straight league title will depend on the performances of Jason Sullivan, a 1,000-yard rusher in 1999; Giuseppe Aguanno, a 6-foot-2, 220-pound linebacker, who has committed to Duke; Brian Carstens, the senior defensive end; and the returning linemen Steve Bossic, Steve Broecker and Mike Margiotta.</p>
        <p>The other elite Catholic school teams are Chaminade (8-2 last year) and Christ the King (5-4). Chaminade -- led by quarterback Fred Edwards and linebacker Joe Ryan -- was humbled last Saturday by Xaverian of Massachusetts, 55-10.</p>
        <p>In the P.S.A.L., Staten Island teams have captured 9 titles in 15 years. New Dorp secured the 1985 title; Susan Wagner won in 1986, '88, '89, '92 and '95; Tottenville in 1997 and Curtis the past two seasons.</p>
        <p>Curtis will face an uphill battle to repeat without quarterback George Hassell and Mike Goodman, the featured runner. The Warriors will now count on the rushing of Steve Gregory and Warren Bright.</p>
        <p>For Susan Wagner, it was a long off-season as the players thought of last year's 26-22 championship loss to Curtis. The Falcons' hope of dethroning Curtis will depend on Ramel Myers and Gary Ham, who are both running backs and free safeties, and the first-year quarterback Ben Salmani.</p>
        <p>The team that may have the best chance for the P.S.A.L. title is Canarsie of Brooklyn, a semifinalist last year. Canarsie has  Earl Charles (1,300 yards rushing and 17 touchdowns in 1999), and a tenacious defense, led by the city's best linebacking duo: Leon Williams and Dennard Nimmons.</p>
        <p>''Leon is the best football player that I've ever coached,'' said Mike Camardese, a 30-year veteran, who has coached his share of college and pro players, including Lance Schulters, a Pro Bowl safety for the 49ers. ''He has the rare size, speed and tenacity that few players at any level possess.''</p>
        <p>Poly Prep should dominate with Marcus Wilson and 15 other starters returning.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>Hackensack, the state's preseason top-rated team, is loaded with Division I-AA prospects, among them Johnny Sylvain, a cornerback with 4.4-second speed in the 40-yard dash; running back Kaliym Hazel; linebacker Cedric Browne; Karon Singleton, a guard and defensive tackle; nose guard Marlin Townes; quarterback Bryson Rosser; and wide receiver Bryan Wilson.</p>
        <p>Wayne Hills -- led by the junior quarterback Chris Olsen, who passed for 12 touchdowns and more than 1,200 yards last season, and defensive end Ryan Neill -- may compete with Ramapo, which returns 8 of 11 starters on defense, in the Northern Bergen Interscholastic League.</p>
        <p>Bergen Catholic, the Parochial IV champion, will have to play stellar ball to defend its title against talent-rich programs like St. Joseph and Don Bosco Prep.</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND</p>
        <p>In Nassau County, Farmingdale, led by Tom Cinelli, a junior quarterback, is expected to beat out Massapequa and Lawrence, now coached by Lou Andre, formerly of Massapequa, for the Conference I title. Hewlett, considered the best team in the county, will need quarterback Jason Baron and the two-way tackle Adam McEntee to hold off Garden City for the Conference II title. In Conference III, Glen Cove, led by the running of Zhivargo Simmons, Jeff Rudloff and Dave Paskoff, will attempt to hold off Bethpage, whose coach, Howie Vogts, is in his 47th season and is 9 victories from tying Johnny Barnes (Canisius of Buffalo) for New York State's career victory mark. Roosevelt, the only Nassau team to defeat a Suffolk squad in the four title games, will rely on Randall James, a senior guard, to clear the way past Manhasset for the Conference IV title.</p>
        <p>In Suffolk County, Brentwood, the defending Division 1 champion, may have trouble holding off Lindenhurst, led by Erik Conroy, a senior quarterback; Central Islip, keyed by Steven Davis, a 1,250-yard rusher last season; and Patchogue Medford, which is guided by Mike Farrell, a senior quarterback. In Division 2, North Babylon, the defending champion, will attempt to hold off Bellport and West Islip. Running back Eugene Nottingham and Tristian Smith, a receiver and safety, give Amityville, the defending Class 3 champion, an edge over Huntington and Kings Park for the Division 3 title. Harborfields, propelled by Darwin Powell's running, is favored in Division 4.</p>
        <p>WESTCHESTER</p>
        <p>Edgemont, North Rockland, Clarkstown South, Nyack, Harrison and Tuckahoe figure to contend in their divisions. Players to watch are Edgemont's Matt Bernstein, a fullback and linebacker headed to Wisconsin; Tuckahoe's Audwin Davis, a senior linebacker and tailback; Horace Greeley's Reyn Garnett, a senior running back; Clarkstown South's Bill Henderson, a junior quarterback; and Iona Prep's Yohance Perry, a 6-5, 335-pound tackle.</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>New Canaan and West Haven are two of the top-rated schools. New Canaan returns five starters on both sides of the ball, including the senior tri-captains: defensive tackle Nick Campbell, offensive tackle Chris Balestrino and linebacker Dan Gross. West Haven relies on Dan Orlovski, the senior quarterback who signed with Connecticut; Brian Pratt, the featured back; and Derrick Lewis, a two-way lineman.</p>
        <p>HIGH SCHOOL FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
