<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mathis Ends Drought At an Opportune Time</title>
    <meta content="16STAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/16/sports/16STAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230938"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metrostars</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Burn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6DB1E38F935A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mathis Ends Drought At an Opportune Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Sept. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses MetroStars victory over Dallas Burn in first game of Major League Soccer playoff series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Clint Mathis was in front of the Dallas goal in the 34th minute tonight and the ball came to his left foot, he did not stop to think. If he had, he might have remembered how he had been in this sort of spot before, and how he had been unable to score.</p>
        <p>Mathis struck the ball as soon as Mike Petke directed a header to him, slipping it softly past Dallas goalkeeper Matt Jordan. As the ball crossed into the net, Mathis broke a scoring drought that had lasted four games and gave the MetroStars their first goal in a 2-1 overtime victory in a Major League Soccer playoff game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Clint Mathis was in front of the Dallas goal in the 34th minute tonight and the ball came to his left foot, he did not stop to think. If he had, he might have remembered how he had been in this sort of spot before, and how he had been unable to score.</p>
        <p>Mathis struck the ball as soon as Mike Petke directed a header to him, slipping it softly past Dallas goalkeeper Matt Jordan. As the ball crossed into the net, Mathis broke a scoring drought that had lasted four games and gave the MetroStars their first goal in a 2-1 overtime victory in a Major League Soccer playoff game.</p>
        <p>Mathis also played a crucial role in what proved to be the winning goal of Game 1 of this two-of-three-game quarterfinal series. In the 100th minute, he found Adolfo Valencia just inside the box. Valencia turned that pass into a goal.</p>
        <p>On Aug. 26, the last time that the MetroStars had faced Dallas, Mathis scored five goals so easily that even he could not explain just how it had happened.</p>
        <p>But since that day, his goal total stood at 16, good enough to lead the MetroStars this season, but a source of frustration for Mathis, who continued to see scoring opportunities slip away.</p>
        <p>''That takes off any pressure,'' Mathis said of the early goal. ''You try to block out those thoughts, but the greatest feeling to see that go in is that our team is up, 1-0, in a playoff situation. That's how you win games.</p>
        <p>''My play in the past few games, that was on my mind a little bit, and I think that was the cause of my problems,'' he added. ''I said, 'I need to let everything go and just play like I can play.' I wanted to keep everything out and stay focused on the task at hand. When it comes crunch time, if I'm able to go out there and stick one away and set up players like Adolfo, we don't care who scores.''</p>
        <p>Before his goal, tonight's game was going much the same as the last four for Mathis.</p>
        <p>He was shadowed by Burn defenders, and when he came close to the ball the defense reminded him that it was there.</p>
        <p>Ricardo Iribarren drew a yellow card in the 31st minute when he delivered a forearm, wrapped in a cast, to the back of Mathis's head.</p>
        <p>But Mathis got his revenge three minutes later. Peter Villegas sent a corner kick into the box, which Petke headed, while jumping over Iribarren, down to Mathis, who was seven yards out.</p>
        <p>In the second half, Iribarren took Mathis down hard again from behind, drawing no card, but raising the ire of the MetroStars as their leading scorer limped out of the scrum.</p>
        <p>The pain faded, as did the pressure that was mounting on Mathis to carry the offensive load once again.</p>
        <p>In the final minute of overtime, Mathis had a chance to end the game, firing a shot that sailed just wide of the left side of the net.</p>
        <p>But before Mathis could wonder how he misfired, he found himself with the ball again. This time he set up Valencia just inside the box and let his partner up front take over from there.</p>
        <p>''I'm just feeling better about the team play,'' Mathis said. ''That's the most important thing. If I can step my level up to help the team, that's what I need to do. The best thing out of this is that the team looked a lot better than we have in the last few games.</p>
        <p>'' We showed a lot of courage to stay with it. To be in the game that long, fight that hard to be up, 1-0, and not come away with a win would have been tough.</p>
        <p>''But anything can happen in soccer,'' he added. ''If you work hard the whole time through the 90 minutes, the overtime, something can come out of it.''</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
