<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Albright Sits Face to Face With Iranian</title>
    <meta content="Y16NAT$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/16/world/16NATI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230871"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iran-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Taliban (Afghan Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Annan, Kofi (Sec Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albright, Madeleine K (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kharrazi, Kamal (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wren, Christopher S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2D71138F935A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Albright Sits Face to Face With Iranian</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER S. WREN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wren, Christopher S</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Sept. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>State Sec Madeleine K Albright and Iranian Min Kamal Kharazi find selves in rare accord in meeting at United Nations with senior diplomats from six other nations to discuss what to do about Afghanistan and its ruling Taliban; meeting is first at small forum by top foreign officials of Iran and United States since 1979; Sec Gen Kofi Annan presides; participants call for cease-fire in civil war (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright and Iran's foreign minister, Kamal Kharazi, found themselves in rare agreement today when they sat down together with senior diplomats from six other countries to discuss what to do about Afghanistan and its ruling Taliban.</p>
        <p>It was the first time that the top foreign officials of Iran and the United States had attended so small a forum together since 1979, when diplomatic relations were broken after rioting students in Tehran occupied the American Embassy, holding its diplomats hostage for more than 14 months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright and Iran's foreign minister, Kamal Kharazi, found themselves in rare agreement today when they sat down together with senior diplomats from six other countries to discuss what to do about Afghanistan and its ruling Taliban.</p>
        <p>It was the first time that the top foreign officials of Iran and the United States had attended so small a forum together since 1979, when diplomatic relations were broken after rioting students in Tehran occupied the American Embassy, holding its diplomats hostage for more than 14 months.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright and Mr. Kharazi sat across from each other at the horseshoe-shaped table in a basement conference room. A diplomat at the closed meeting said they appeared to be comfortable with the encounter.</p>
        <p>When Dr. Albright attended an earlier meeting of the same group two years ago, Mr. Kharazi stayed away, sending a deputy minister.</p>
        <p>Today, Dr. Albright told reporters after the meeting, ''We were sitting on opposite sides of the table, so we didn't have a conversation, but I was very interested in the similarity of our views on Afghanistan.''</p>
        <p>As she spoke, Mr. Kharazi silently glided past behind her without talking to the news media.</p>
        <p>There is probably no other issue on which the American and Iranian government share such close views as the Taliban, a militant Islamic movement that has battled its way to power and imposed an austere brand of Islamic law.</p>
        <p>The high-level meeting, held under United Nations auspices, involved the Six Plus Two group of Afghanistan's six neighbors -- Iran, Pakistan, Tajikistan, Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan and China (whose territory barely touches Afghanistan) -- and two other concerned nations, Russia and the United States.</p>
        <p>Participants included the Russian foreign minister, Igor S. Ivanov; the Chinese foreign minister, Tang Jiaxuan; and the Pakistani foreign minister, Abdul Sattar.</p>
        <p>Secretary General Kofi Annan presided over the discussion. ''Our common goal,'' he said in a statement, ''is to see an end to the fighting and the establishment of a broadly representative, multiethnic government that would reflect the genuine aspirations of the Afghan people and be responsive to the legitimate concerns of the international community.''</p>
        <p>''Indeed, the conflict in Afghanistan has ceased to be, if it ever was, merely an internal Afghan problem,'' Mr. Annan said. ''Years of foreign intervention have not only failed to produce any significant benefits for those meddling in the country's affairs, but have also led to a situation where the Afghan conflict has become a growing threat to peace and stability in the region and beyond.''</p>
        <p>The group was formed two years ago to discuss prospects for ending the civil war in Afghanistan, more than 90 percent of which is now controlled by the Taliban.</p>
        <p>''I think when there are problems to be solved like this together, it is very encouraging,'' Dr. Albright said. She called the meeting ''useful,'' saying the participants talked about ''the bloodshed caused by the Taliban,'' and their record of condoning drug trafficking and terrorism.</p>
        <p>In a statement after the meeting, the group ''emphasized that there can be no military solution to the Afghan conflict and again called upon the warring parties to agree to a cease-fire and enter into negotiations aimed at bringing about a political solution to the conflict.'' The Taliban's military opposition has been driven back into a northern pocket.</p>
        <p>Other representatives of the eight countries met on Wednesday to discuss Afghanistan's emergence as the world's leading producer of opium, the raw ingredient of heroin, and the problems it has caused the region.</p>
        <p>The Security Council imposed financial and airline sanctions against the Taliban last year after they refused to expel Osama bin Laden, a Saudi-born terrorist suspected of organizing the bombing of American embassies in Kenya and Tanzania in 1998.</p>
        <p>Iran nearly went to war with the Taliban in 1998 after they killed 10 Iranian diplomats and a journalist in  Mazar-i-Sharif, in northern Afghanistan. Iran has also absorbed an estimated one million Afghan refugees, many of them Shiite Muslims fleeing persecution by the Taliban.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration has made several overtures to improve relations with Iran, like lifting a ban on the import of Iranian luxury goods into the United States.</p>
        <p>At a meeting of world leaders here last week, President Clinton attended a speech by the Iranian president, Mohammad Khatami. Dr. Albright attended another appearance by Mr. Khatami at a ''dialogue among civilizations'' earlier last week.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
