<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SHIFTING TACTICS, BUSH USES ISSUES TO CONFRONT GORE</title>
    <meta content="16BUSH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/16/politics/16BUSH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE STRATEGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E7DF1E38F935A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1572" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SHIFTING TACTICS, BUSH USES ISSUES TO CONFRONT GORE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush, in tactical switch, is confronting Vice Pres Al Gore head-on over issues, area long considered to be Gore's greatest strength; his campaign opens advertising campaign in swing states comparing candidates' programs; his advisers say he can no longer rely on attacks on Gore's character and credibility (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Faced with an opponent who has managed to deflect questions about his character and trustworthiness, Gov. George W. Bush has shifted tactics and begun confronting Vice President Al Gore head-on over the issues, an area long considered to be Mr. Gore's greatest strength.</p>
        <p>Day after day this week, from one coast to the other, Mr. Bush has sought to draw contrasts between his positions on Medicare, the environment, education and tax cuts and those of his rival. And to amplify the theme, his campaign began running a new advertisement in 18 swing states comparing the two candidates' programs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Faced with an opponent who has managed to deflect questions about his character and trustworthiness, Gov. George W. Bush has shifted tactics and begun confronting Vice President Al Gore head-on over the issues, an area long considered to be Mr. Gore's greatest strength.</p>
        <p>Day after day this week, from one coast to the other, Mr. Bush has sought to draw contrasts between his positions on Medicare, the environment, education and tax cuts and those of his rival. And to amplify the theme, his campaign began running a new advertisement in 18 swing states comparing the two candidates' programs.</p>
        <p>''Al Gore's prescription plan forces seniors into a government-run H.M.O.,'' says the commercial. ''Governor Bush gives seniors a choice. Gore says he's for school accountability, but requires no real testing. Governor Bush requires tests and holds schools accountable for results.''</p>
        <p>The commercial also says that ''Gore's targeted tax cut leaves out 50 million people -- half of all taxpayers.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Bush's running mate, former Defense Secretary Dick Cheney, has been using blunt language this week to criticize Mr. Gore's positions on the economy, health care and education. [Page A11.]</p>
        <p>The tack is a change in emphasis that Mr. Bush's advisers say is every bit as important as the Texas governor's recent decision to court voters in more unscripted settings. Just last week, Mr. Bush was hammering at Mr. Gore's personal credibility and character. All year, the emotional center of the Bush campaign has been a pledge to bring ''dignity and honor'' back to the White House after the Clinton years.</p>
        <p>But with some polls showing a slight Gore edge and others showing a statistical dead heat, Mr. Bush's advisers say that he can no longer count on questions of personality and character to carry him into the White House, and that he needs to go after Mr. Gore on the issues that voters put at the top of their list of concerns.</p>
        <p>''There was a thought we needed to go much more pointedly at issues and show these differences,'' one Bush aide said. ''Everybody agreed we needed to be much more pointed in drawing contrast.''</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign argues that it can change the way the public is thinking about the issues, in much the same way that Republicans and their allies dampened enthusiasm for President Clinton's plan for universal health care coverage by persuading the public that the proposal amounted to government intrusion in private lives. The plan died in 1994 and the Republicans went on to win control of Congress.</p>
        <p>''Just like President Clinton's failed health care effort in 1993, we believe that the more people look at the details of Al Gore's plans, the less they'll like,'' said Ari Fleischer, a spokesman for Mr. Bush. ''The more they look, the less they'll see.''</p>
        <p>The new Bush effort reflects a fundamental change in the dynamics of the presidential race.</p>
        <p>Throughout the spring and summer polls showed that Mr. Bush had a comfortable lead that was built in large part on personality and on public dismay with President Clinton's personal morality. Polls found that voters had judged Mr. Bush more likable than Mr. Gore and more of a leader.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Bush has consistently talked about the issues, holding policy speech after policy speech, he mostly set out his own plans without drawing sharp contrasts to Mr. Gore's proposals. Before the Republican convention, his aides had said the issue speeches were largely designed to bolster impressions of Mr. Bush as a strong leader. That the Republican dared to propose changes in Social Security or that he said he would consider changes in nuclear doctrine made him look like a bold leader willing to challenge the status quo, his aides said.</p>
        <p>Then came the Democratic National Convention.</p>
        <p>During that critical period, Republicans now acknowledge, Mr. Gore did everything that he needed to do. By choosing Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut as his running mate, he managed to separate himself from Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Polls now show that the vice president is as highly regarded as Mr. Bush when it comes to traits like leadership, character and personal popularity.</p>
        <p>If both men are viewed as personable and strong leaders, that shifts the focus of the race to the issues. Indeed, a survey of 2,000 voters, released this week by The Pew Research Center for the People and the Press, concluded that ''clearly, issues have fueled Gore's gains.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's advisers say they have not abandoned efforts to raise questions about Mr. Gore's credibility. Mr. Bush, for example, jumped on new reports that federal investigators are examining the Democrats' efforts in 1996 to raise money from a handful of Texas trial lawyers.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush's aides say he needs to talk about credibility in the context of issues. One strategist close to the Bush campaign said recent focus groups with voters had shown that while Mr. Gore had shaken off questions about his character, there were still doubts about him just below the surface. He said those doubts could be used to push people back into the undecided category.</p>
        <p>''The difference between now and seven or eight weeks ago,'' the strategist said, ''is that before you could go straight at credibility issues. You could say, 'Al Gore: how can you believe anything he says?' People would nod and say, 'That's right.' Now people want to hear the comparison on the issues. Then you can bring up credibility and it's more viable.''</p>
        <p>The Republican strategist said that the shift in perception was subtle but that ''it means we won't run away with this election.''</p>
        <p>''We will have to aggressively compete on the issues,'' the strategist said.</p>
        <p>Another Bush adviser said, ''Pointing out issue differences is a way of pointing out credibility differences.''</p>
        <p>The difficulty for Mr. Bush is that, unlike in the 1980's when issues like crime and taxes and the cold war favored the Republicans, this year's top voters' concerns -- health care and education -- are subjects on which Democrats have long had an edge. Still, Mr. Bush's advisers contend that their candidate has already narrowed the traditional Democratic advantage on education and Social Security. And they say that he can prevail on the issues if he reshapes the public debate.</p>
        <p>Ralph Reed, a Bush adviser, said the campaign would now focus on the details of Mr. Gore's plans.</p>
        <p>''We'll say he's got bad ideas,'' Mr. Reed said. ''Not just that his ideas are not as good as our ideas, but that they could harm people. People might not get the drugs they need because of price controls.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reed was referring to the accusation made by Mr. Bush and by the drug industry that Mr. Gore's proposal to create a new prescription drug benefit inside the traditional Medicare program would create such a government buying monopoly for drugs that it would amount to price controls.</p>
        <p>In another line of attack on Mr. Gore's Medicare plan, the Republican National Committee is also running a new advertisement. Speaking of Mr. Gore's prescription proposal, an announcer says, ''He says he wants to fight for the people against H.M.O.'s, but his prescription drug plan forces seniors into one H.M.O. selected by the government. Al Gore: federal H.M.O. George Bush: seniors choose.''</p>
        <p>The reference to H.M.O.'s echoes Mr. Gore's criticism of Mr. Bush's own Medicare plan, which would foster competition between Medicare and private insurers and encourage recipients to opt into government-subsidized private health plans with prescription drug coverage. The Gore campaign says the proposal would force more and more people out of Medicare's traditional fee-for-service program and into health maintenance organizations.</p>
        <p>''It's no surprise that they are trying to distort the issue because it's so plain that Bush's plan puts seniors off on the tender mercies of the H.M.O.'s,'' Douglas Hattaway, a spokesman for Mr. Gore, said in response to the Republican spots. ''He knows that's one of the main vulnerabilities of his plan, so he's trying desperately to turn it around.''</p>
        <p>One question for Mr. Bush is precisely how to frame the contrasts on the issues. He has spent the year presenting himself as a ''different kind of Republican'' who is less hostile to government than the Republicans who gained control of Congress  in 1994.</p>
        <p>But some of his appeals recently have been sharply ideological, skating close to the traditional right-left confrontation over the role of government.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's advisers say he wants to present himself as a conservative reformer who is more market oriented and innovative while painting Mr. Gore as favoring government-run command and control policies that deny individuals choices.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush says he is game for the fight. At a rally in California on Wednesday, he said: ''We've got a big debate on the issues during the campaign. And by the way, I love talking about the issues on the campaign, because we stand with the majority of the people when we talk about the issues.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE STRATEGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
