<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Teenager Drives Into Scaffold At Port Authority, Injuring 3</title>
    <meta content="16SCAF$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/16/nyregion/16SCAF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230865"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Port Authority of New York and New Jersey</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koh, Eun Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rivera, Marcus</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E3D81138F935A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="446" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Teenager Drives Into Scaffold At Port Authority, Injuring 3</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EUN LEE KOH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Koh, Eun Lee</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Car driven by unlicensed teenager Marcus Rivera crashes into scaffold in front of Port Authority bus terminal in midtown Manhattan, injuring three people, two critically; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A car driven by an unlicensed teenager crashed into a scaffold in front of the Port Authority Bus Terminal yesterday afternoon, injuring three people, including two who were left in critical condition.</p>
        <p>The accident occurred about 2 p.m. at 42nd Street and Eighth Avenue, near a taxi lane where at least two dozen people were standing or walking, the authorities said. The driver, Marcus Rivera, 17, of Bergen Street in Brooklyn, tried to run away but was chased down by a witness, the police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A car driven by an unlicensed teenager crashed into a scaffold in front of the Port Authority Bus Terminal yesterday afternoon, injuring three people, including two who were left in critical condition.</p>
        <p>The accident occurred about 2 p.m. at 42nd Street and Eighth Avenue, near a taxi lane where at least two dozen people were standing or walking, the authorities said. The driver, Marcus Rivera, 17, of Bergen Street in Brooklyn, tried to run away but was chased down by a witness, the police said.</p>
        <p>The car hit one person, and two others were injured by falling scaffolding.</p>
        <p>Two of the victims had head injuries and were in critical condition at Bellevue Hospital Center last night, said the police, who did not release the names of the injured. The third victim had less serious injuries and was in stable condition at St. Clare's Hospital. The police said the injuries were not life-threatening.</p>
        <p>''Hundreds of people travel this street corner,'' said Chief Joe Nardone of the Fire Department's Ninth Battalion. ''It's a miracle that only three people were struck.''</p>
        <p>The car, a maroon Chrysler Concorde, had been parked near the taxi lane with Mr. Rivera on the passenger's side and another person in the driver's seat, the police said.</p>
        <p>The other occupant of the car,  whom the police have not identified, went inside the bus terminal, and Mr. Rivera climbed into the driver's seat to move the car. He then lost control and hit the scaffolding, the police said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marcus will be charged with leaving the scene of an accident and driving without a license, the police said.</p>
        <p>Christos Bournias, who owns a hot-dog stand at 42nd Street and Eighth Avenue, was almost struck when the car came to a stop inches away from his push cart.</p>
        <p>''I am so sick now because I saw people get hit and then lie on the ground,'' said Mr. Bournias, who crouched on the sidewalk at 42nd Street and surveyed the mangled metal and wood. ''I just froze. Jesus saved my life today.''</p>
        <p>The accident caused a major traffic disruption in the area, one of the most congested in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
