<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>30,000-Gallon Fuel Spill Largely Washes Out to Sea</title>
    <meta content="16SPIL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/16/nyregion/16SPIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230926"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sandy Hook (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4DC1E38F935A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>30,000-Gallon Fuel Spill Largely Washes Out to Sea</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Coast Guard reports that most of 30,000 gallons of diesel fuel that spilled into Sandy Hook Bay in New Jersey was apparently blown east toward open water and away from land; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Jersey Shore caught a break.</p>
        <p>Most of the 30,000 gallons of diesel fuel that spilled into Sandy Hook Bay on Thursday afternoon -- one of the largest fuel spills in New York Harbor in a decade -- was apparently blown east yesterday toward open water and away from land, United States Coast Guard officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Jersey Shore caught a break.</p>
        <p>Most of the 30,000 gallons of diesel fuel that spilled into Sandy Hook Bay on Thursday afternoon -- one of the largest fuel spills in New York Harbor in a decade -- was apparently blown east yesterday toward open water and away from land, United States Coast Guard officials said.</p>
        <p>Much of what was left was being scooped up by oil-skimming vessels, and a lot of the rest was quickly evaporating, they said.</p>
        <p>State environmental protection officials in New York and New Jersey also said that the fuel, No. 2 diesel, had apparently not made landfall anywhere in the region and that no reports of damage to wildlife had been received.</p>
        <p>The spill occurred when a United States Navy supply ship taking fuel to the Earle Naval Weapons Station pier in Middletown Township, in Monmouth County, N.J., collided with a tugboat about 4:20 p.m. Thursday. More than three miles of booms were deployed by late evening to protect shore areas, and environmentalists and cleanup officials then braced for a storm front that was expected after midnight.</p>
        <p>A Coast Guard spokesman, Petty Officer Angelo Patti, said the storm was less violent than expected, however, and westerly winds picked up immediately afterward, pushing the fuel toward open water.</p>
        <p>The New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection suspended commercial shellfishing in Raritan Bay and Sandy Hook Bay and in the Navesink and Shrewsbury Rivers as a precaution, but a spokeswoman for the agency, Loretta O'Donnell, said that no beach closings were expected this weekend. She said people fishing or bathing in the area should use common sense if they see a sheen on the water.</p>
        <p>Diesel fuel, while poisonous to many forms of marine life, is one of the lightest petroleum distillates, so it tends to stay on or near the surface of the water and evaporates readily into the air in sunlight.</p>
        <p>The spill also occurred at a time of year when there are relatively few birds on the shore. The summer birds that nest on the beaches and feed in the shallows in the Sandy Hook area have largely gone south, and the birds that are more common in winter have yet to arrive, said Dery Bennett, executive director of the American Littoral Society, a coastal environmental organization based at Sandy Hook.</p>
        <p>Under slightly different conditions, environmental experts said, the impact of the spill could have been severe. It occurred under a full moon, when tides are at their highest and their lowest, so if it had washed toward land it would have been pushed farther inland by the high tide, into sensitive marsh areas, while the lower low tides would have deposited more of the spill into the mud flats, where many birds feed.</p>
        <p>Some emergency procedures that were put in place after a spate of huge spills in the early 1990's also apparently did not work perfectly.</p>
        <p>The baykeeper for New York Harbor and its tributaries, Andrew Willner, said that under the emergency response rules, his office was supposed to be notified immediately so that he could be the public's environmental representative on the scene, but that he was not called until about 10 p.m., more than five hours after the spill.</p>
        <p>Apparently, he said, an incorrect telephone number for him had been entered into the system.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
