<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="16TRAN$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230946"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2DB1E38F935A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="485" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS--Signed a two-year working agreement with Rancho Cucamonga of the California League.  TEXAS RANGERS--Promoted Tim Hallgren to director of amateur scouting.  National League  PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES--Announced a four-year working agreement with Lakewood of the South Atlantic League.  SAN DIEGO PADRES--Recalled RHP Buddy Carlyle from Las Vegas of the PCL.</p>
        <p>Eastern League  NEW BRITAIN ROCK CATS--Announced a two-year extension of their player development contract with the Minnesota Twins, through the 2002 season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS--Signed a two-year working agreement with Rancho Cucamonga of the California League.  TEXAS RANGERS--Promoted Tim Hallgren to director of amateur scouting.  National League  PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES--Announced a four-year working agreement with Lakewood of the South Atlantic League.  SAN DIEGO PADRES--Recalled RHP Buddy Carlyle from Las Vegas of the PCL.</p>
        <p>Eastern League  NEW BRITAIN ROCK CATS--Announced a two-year extension of their player development contract with the Minnesota Twins, through the 2002 season.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL  National Basketball Association  MIAMI HEAT--Re-signed C Duane Causwell. Agreed to terms with F Ron Hale.  PHOENIX SUNS--Agreed to terms with G Mario Elie.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL  National Football League  SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS--Waived G Dwayne Ledford.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY  National Hockey League  ANAHEIM MIGHTY DUCKS--Agreed to terms with D Oleg Tverdovsky on a three-year contract.  BOSTON BRUINS--Assigned to D Elias Abrahamsson, D Johnathan Aitken, D Vratislav Cech, D Shane Belter, D Keith McCambridge, D Eric Van Acker, D Denis Timofeev, G Seamus Kotyk, F Peter Ferraro, F Joel Trottier, F Jeremy Brown, F Eric Manlow, F Jeff Zehr, F Matt Zultek, F Shawn Mather, F Blaz Emersic, F Mattias Karlin, F Joe Talbot and F Michael Mader to Providence of the AHL. Sent F Sean Pronger on loan to Manitoba of the IHL. Returned G Donald Choukalos to Regina of the WHL and D Tuukka Makela to Montreal of the QMJHL. Released G Ryan Aschaber, F Colton Orr and F Chris Pittman.  COLUMBUS BLUE JACKETS--Released LW Robb Palahnuk, LW Ben Keup and RW Jeff Mitchell.  WASHINGTON CAPITALS--Signed C Jan Bulis to a three-year contract.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE  SMU--Named Beverly Bowes women's tennis coach.  URI--Named Deanna Tate assistant women's basketball coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
