<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Questions Raised About Ford Explorer's Margin of Safety</title>
    <meta content="16FORD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/16/business/16FORD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230880"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Motoring</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1D61138F935A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Questions Raised About Ford Explorer's Margin of Safety</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Sept. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Focus of attention passes from tires to vehicle as regulators and investigators search for causes of death of nearly 100 Americans riding in Ford Explorers with Bridgestone/Firestone tires; article explores safety aspects of Explorer's engineering and its use by customers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the wide-open highways of the South and West, drivers often push their Ford Explorers toward the vehicle's maximum speed -- 99 miles an hour -- for hours at a time. Yet the Firestone tires on millions of Explorers are certified to last only 10 minutes at a slightly higher speed -- 106 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>When those Explorers are filled with children, luggage and the many accessories of family life, the rear suspensions of sport utility vehicles are sometimes forced to carry loads that exceed the recommended weight limits, putting extra strain on the fairly small, low-pressure rear tires.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the wide-open highways of the South and West, drivers often push their Ford Explorers toward the vehicle's maximum speed -- 99 miles an hour -- for hours at a time. Yet the Firestone tires on millions of Explorers are certified to last only 10 minutes at a slightly higher speed -- 106 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>When those Explorers are filled with children, luggage and the many accessories of family life, the rear suspensions of sport utility vehicles are sometimes forced to carry loads that exceed the recommended weight limits, putting extra strain on the fairly small, low-pressure rear tires.</p>
        <p>As Bridgestone/Firestone Inc., the Ford Motor Company, federal regulators and Congressional investigators try to sort out why close to 100 Americans have died in crashes involving Firestone tires on sport utility vehicles, particularly Ford Explorers, attention has focused on how Firestone designed and manufactured the tires being recalled. Indeed, Firestone admitted for the first time on Tuesday that it had made ''bad tires'' and said it was investigating the manufacture of a steel belt in the steel-belted radial tires.</p>
        <p>But what has also emerged from Congressional testimony and recently released internal company documents is a picture of a tire, made according to Ford's design and marketing demands, that has often been run to its very limits. Indeed, in choosing those tires, Ford permitted a narrower margin of safety than in many other vehicles.</p>
        <p>Not only does the combination of vehicle and tire push the limits on weight and speed. The Explorer itself, like many other sport utility vehicles with high centers of gravity, is prone to roll over despite what company documents show was an extensive but not entirely successful effort by Ford in 1989 to make the vehicle more stable. Taken together with the tire manufacturing problems and a variety of human factors -- in essence, people tend to drive too fast and pay too little attention to the age or air pressure of their tires -- the Explorer and the Firestone tires have proved a deadly pairing.</p>
        <p>The demands that Ford placed on the tires reflect the difficult trade-offs the company faced in trying to turn the Explorer, essentially an off-road truck, into a more fashionable, refined vehicle that would feel like a car during high-speed driving. To give the Explorer a more comfortable ride and make it less likely to roll over in everyday driving, Ford chose a fairly low inflation pressure of 26 pounds a square inch. But at low pressures, tires cannot support as much weight and are more susceptible to coming apart at high speeds.</p>
        <p>Jacques A. Nasser, Ford's chief executive, has denied that Ford bears any responsibility for what has happened, and he did so again in testimony before the Senate Commerce Committee on Tuesday. ''We know that this is a Firestone tire issue, not a vehicle issue,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ford officials have two arguments to buttress their position. Goodyear tires installed on nearly half the Ford Explorers produced from 1995 to 1997 have had few problems, despite having the same recommended pressure. And even with the tire-related deaths, which have mostly occurred in rollovers, occupants of Ford Explorers still have lower overall death rates, and fewer deaths in rollovers, than occupants of other midsize sport utility vehicles.</p>
        <p>It is possible, although hard to confirm, that in choosing a low pressure, Ford might have actually saved more lives than have been taken in tire-related crashes. Low-pressure tires reduce the risk of rollovers during sharp maneuvers. Even with the tire-related rollovers, the death rate in rollovers for Explorers is 42 percent lower than for its main rival, the Chevrolet Blazer, which uses a much higher-pressure tire but is also marketed to a younger audience that may take more risks while driving.</p>
        <p>Ford officials say that the safety margin was adequate and that Ford maximized the vehicle's overall stability and handling.</p>
        <p>That Ford had to look at tire pressure at all in conjunction with rollovers is another sign of the problems that automakers face in trying to make sport utilities as stable as cars.</p>
        <p>The Firestone tires being recalled had what the tire industry calls an ''S'' rating for speed, meaning that they could go 112 miles an hour for at least 10 minutes if inflated to 35 pounds a square inch. By choosing 26 pounds, Ford lowered the tires' top speed to 106 miles an hour, according to tire industry guidelines, and trimmed the safety margin to 7 miles an hour above the vehicle's top speed. That is a few miles an hour less than on other Ford models or other manufacturers' models.</p>
        <p>General Motors uses S-rated tires for midsize and full-sizesport utility vehicles but recommends 35 pounds of tire pressure except for the Cadillac Escalade and GMC Denali, which have a recommended pressure of 30 pounds but use extra-large tires. G.M. specifies a tire safety margin of 14 miles an hour above the vehicle's computer-limited top speed except for models with extra-large tires, which provide a different kind of safety margin, said Brook Lindbert, G.M.'s tire and wheel director.</p>
        <p>Then there is the question of weight. The Explorer's tires have less overall capacity to carry weight, in addition to the vehicle's own weight, than do the tires on most sport utilities. The Chevrolet Blazer uses the same size tires as the Explorer, for example, but because they are inflated to 35 pounds a square inch, they can carry 1,100 pounds more than the Explorer's tires. A Blazer typically weighs 100 to 200 pounds less than an Explorer, too.</p>
        <p>A Firestone technical document, presented at a conference in 1998, shows that when the vehicle is carrying even a modest load, more of the weight is on the left rear tire than on any other tire -- about 60 pounds more than on the right rear tire and 300 pounds more than the front tires.</p>
        <p>Tom Baughman, Ford's engineering director for light trucks, said in an interview that the left rear tire was the most likely to fail, but added that weight did not appear to be the main reason for this. Ford has nonetheless decided in the last several weeks that the recommended pressure for tires on the company's completely redesigned 2002 Ford Explorer, scheduled to go on sale next January, will be at least 30 pounds for the front tires and 32 to 35 pounds for the rear tires, he said. A month ago, Ford officials had said that the pressure would be 30 pounds in the front and in the rear for the new Explorer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baughman said the choice of a fairly high pressure for the rear tires had been made to improve the ability to carry weight in the rear. Extra tire capacity to carry weight is needed because Ford will start offering a third row of seats in the Explorer, he added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baughman said that Ford had analyzed Firestone's database of property damage and physical injury claims and found that the claims were more likely to involve the left rear tire than any other tire. But Ford found in the Firestone database for the tires being recalled that this was true for sport utilities made by Toyota, Nissan and DaimlerChrysler, too, although tires on these companies' models were subject to far fewer claims over all, he said.</p>
        <p>While the Explorer's gas tank is near the left rear tire and is heavy when full, Ford does not believe that the concentration of problems on the left rear tire reflects the weight distribution, Mr. Baughman said. Ford suspects that rear-wheel-drive vehicles put more strain left rear tires because these tires get energy from the engine during acceleration slightly more directly than the right rear tire.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baughman said that Ford also suspected that the center of a road radiates more heat on a hot day than the edges. Ford has been using infrared devices to measure this while driving Ford Explorers around a test track in Dearborn, Mich., in recent weeks, Mr. Baughman said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lindbert of G.M. was skeptical of the rear-wheel-drive hypothesis and had not heard of road heat being a problem. G.M. has tested the strain on rear tires during acceleration and found no meaningful difference between the left and right, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lindbert expressed surprise that many Ford Explorers were encountering problems with the left rear tire, explaining that it is more common for right rear tires to fail on other vehicles than left rear tires. Road debris, like nails, tends to end up by the side of the road -- roads are built highest in the middle so that rain can drain off. Vehicles' front right tires briefly tip the points of the debris up into the air and then the rear right tires hit the debris at the wrong angle, are punctured and begin losing air, Mr. Lindbert said.</p>
        <p>The high frequency of rollovers in Explorers that have lost tires has focused the tire industry's attention on how automakers have shifted from building cars to building sport utility vehicles. John Lampe, Firestone's executive vice president, admitted in testimony last Tuesday that the tire company had not understood until now that sport utilities were especially vulnerable to tire problems. But he also pointed out that federal regulators had not recognized the problem either, in leaving tire standards less stringent for sport utility tires than for car tires.</p>
        <p>The regulations, ''do not address this vehicle population, a population which has exploded in the past 10 years,'' he said. ''These issues have been difficult for us. We are not vehicle experts. And these issues may have made it harder for us to see the problems we had and that we now recognize in our tires.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
