<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Women Grab Gold and Bronze for Switzerland</title>
    <meta content="16TRIA$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/16/olympics/16TRIA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230942"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: TRIATHLON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Triathlon</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Switzerland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarey, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McMahon, Brigitte</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Messmer, Magali</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Michellie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Triathlon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Triathlon</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E4DB1E38F935A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Women Grab Gold and Bronze for Switzerland</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Saturday, Sept. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brigitte McMahon (Switzerland) wins gold medal in women's triathlon at Sydney Olympics; Michellie Jones (Australia) wins silver medal and Magali Messmer (Switzerland) wins bronze medal; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michellie Jones sprinted down Macquarie Street: past the boxing kangaroo flags, past thousands of her fellow Australians who were packed four rows deep to watch the first Olympic triathlon in history.</p>
        <p>The finish line, the same one she had crossed in first place in April, was now in sight along with the Harbor Bridge, and the Opera House with its massive, shimmering shells. It would have been a perfect view if not for the fact that Brigitte McMahon was running so quickly and so comfortably just in front of her.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Michellie Jones sprinted down Macquarie Street: past the boxing kangaroo flags, past thousands of her fellow Australians who were packed four rows deep to watch the first Olympic triathlon in history.</p>
        <p>The finish line, the same one she had crossed in first place in April, was now in sight along with the Harbor Bridge, and the Opera House with its massive, shimmering shells. It would have been a perfect view if not for the fact that Brigitte McMahon was running so quickly and so comfortably just in front of her.</p>
        <p>''One final surge,'' Jones told herself, reassured herself, and off she loped, her long legs and crooked elbows working desperately in unison. Down to the bottom of the final hill. Round the final roundabout, and then came the realization that her legs were starting to feel too heavy; that she was losing ground not gaining it; that her ideal day on the harbor that she and all Sydneysiders know so well was about to lose a great deal of its luster.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to relive that last 100 meters for the rest of my life,'' Jones said later, after McMahon and Switzerland had become the big winners of the most important triathlon ever run.</p>
        <p>''I'm in heaven,'' said McMahon, a 33-year-old high school teacher from Baar, Switzerland, who later shared the medal podium with her 3-year-old son, Dominic, and her American husband, Michael.</p>
        <p>It was certainly an ethereal morning for her sport, which was finally in the Summer Games after 26 years of sweat and growth and had the chance to make its debut in one of the most picturesque venues imaginable.</p>
        <p>The fans began lining up shortly after dawn: the cockatoos squawking as they swooped over Macquarie Street and the heads of people pouring through triumphant newspaper coverage of the previous night's opening ceremony.</p>
        <p>''I've never been prouder to be Australian,'' said Debora Gowley, who lives in Penrith, the site of the Olympic rowing competitions, and drove into the city with her family. ''We got up at 4 to be here by 6:30. We came to see our girls get a gold.''</p>
        <p>There had even been talk here of a sweep by the Australian women, traditionally the strongest contingent in this grueling, individual sport. But as it turned out after a 1.5 kilometer swim in the harbor, a 40-kilometer bike ride and a 10-kilometer run, the only nation that came close to a sweep was Switzerland.</p>
        <p>McMahon would get gold in 2 hours 40.52 seconds, 2.03 seconds ahead of Jones. Teammate Magali Messmer would get the bronze. And though the Australian fans looked stunned, it should not have come as a surprise considering that McMahon and Messmer finished second and third to Jones at the World Cup meet on this same course in April.</p>
        <p>''It got tough with three kilometers to go,'' said Jones. ''I'm really disappointed, but when I think about it, a silver medal ain't bad.''</p>
        <p>But a gold would certainly have been better, and now it is McMahon who will always be the first woman to win an Olympic triathlon. ''It's overwhelming,'' she said. ''The Australians had a lot more pressure than we did. I was not under pressure.''</p>
        <p>McMahon met her husband in 1992 in Hawaii, where he was training as a triathlete. They now live in Switzerland and are coach and wife as well as husband and wife. ''The biggest change came when Mike took over my training 18 months ago,'' she said. ''That was the first time I had personal coaching. Before I had training plans mailed to me.''</p>
        <p>Though the triathlon is an American creation -- and was first contested in San Diego in 1974 -- Mike McMahon was the only American who made it on the podium today. Joanna Zeiger, an excellent runner who stayed with the medalists until the final two kilometers, came very close, finishing fourth, and Sheila Taormina was sixth.</p>
        <p>The 49 women who competed here began by diving into Farm Cove, the inlet just east of the Opera House, off a temporary pontoon with a long line of photographers snapping away from a pontoon that looked considerably less stable.</p>
        <p>From the start, the swim leg belonged to Taormina, which was not surprising considering that Taormina was the only woman in the field who had won an Olympic gold medal in swimming. But by the end of the first of six bike laps through the harbor area, she was barely in front. And when the front pack left the final transition area with their running shoes on, Jones had a slight lead as the Australian fans chanted what they chant whether they are watching rugby, tennis, cricket or triathlon: ''Oi, oi, oi!''</p>
        <p>McMahon did not join the leaders until near the end of the first 5-kilometer loop, but she had rarely felt more comfortable in the final stages of a race, and that proved crucial. And in the end, while only three women walked away from the Opera House with medals around their necks, the losers did not necessarily walk away disappointed.</p>
        <p>''We are part of the Olympics; we are special; we are blessed,'' Taormina said. ''When we are 80 years old, we will be able to look back and say we were all part of the first Olympic triathlon.''</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: TRIATHLON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
