<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Counterfeit Parking Placards Lead to Arrest</title>
    <meta content="16FRAU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/16/nyregion/16FRAU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230874"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Counterfeit Merchandise</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garcia, Miguel (Police Officer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiser, Benjamin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Counterfeit Merchandise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7D61138F935A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="432" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Counterfeit Parking Placards Lead to Arrest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN WEISER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weiser, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Department of Defense Police Officer Miguel Garcia is charged with possession of counterfeit parking placards from law enforcement agencies (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A police officer from the Department of Defense was charged this week with possession of counterfeit parking placards from law enforcement agencies. The placards are displayed in car windshields to gain official parking privileges at government buildings.</p>
        <p>The officer, Miguel Garcia, 48, was also charged with selling two United States Marshals Service badges, for $500 for both, and then lying about the sale to federal investigators.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A police officer from the Department of Defense was charged this week with possession of counterfeit parking placards from law enforcement agencies. The placards are displayed in car windshields to gain official parking privileges at government buildings.</p>
        <p>The officer, Miguel Garcia, 48, was also charged with selling two United States Marshals Service badges, for $500 for both, and then lying about the sale to federal investigators.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia, of Manhattan, was charged Thursday and pleaded not guilty later that day in Federal District Court. A magistrate judge, Ronald L. Ellis, released him on $50,000 personal recognizance bond.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia, who is stationed at the United States Army base at Fort Monmouth, N.J., was under investigation for at least several months in 1999, according to a federal complaint filed in the case. His phone calls were monitored from February to August 1999. In a tape that was recorded on April 20, 1999, Mr. Garcia told a  government informer that he could ''do the badges,'' and that it would be ''a lot cheaper to buy a lot'' of them, according to the complaint.</p>
        <p>The document, filed by the office of United States Attorney Mary Jo White, also says that federal officials raided Mr. Garcia's apartment at 400 West 43rd Street in August 1999. The officials recovered more than 135 parking placards bearing the seals of agencies like the United States Park Police and the Department of Defense Police, the complaint said. The placards included language like ''This Vehicle Is on Official Police Business,''  creating the possibility of security breaches at public or government buildings.</p>
        <p>Michael B. Ronemus, a lawyer for Mr. Garcia, declined to make him available for an interview yesterday, but said that his client denied any wrongdoing. He said  Mr. Garcia had numerous letters from his superiors in the government and other authorities ''permitting him to obtain and distribute police identification cards to fellow officers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ronemus said his client has been a police officer for about 10 years, and had never been arrested before. ''He clearly feels everything he was doing was legal and above board,'' Mr. Ronemus said.</p>
        <p>He noted that Mr. Garcia was a collector of police memorabilia, including badges from around the country.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
