<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bottled-Water Complaints Multiply</title>
    <meta content="16WATE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/16/nyregion/16WATE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bottled Water</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kifner, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gootman, Elissa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEFDC1E38F935A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bottled-Water Complaints Multiply</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN KIFNER and ELISSA GOOTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gootman, Elissa; Kifner, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Complaints of possibly tainted bottled water mount in NYC metropolitan region even as law enforcement authorities say that thus far they have not discerned any link or pattern to reports (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Complaints of possibly tainted bottled water mounted in the metropolitan region yesterday, even as law enforcement officials said that thus far they had not discerned any link or pattern to the reports.</p>
        <p>Although local and federal authorities have yet to find any evidence of bottle tampering, they have not ruled out the possibility of foul play. All of the bottles of suspect water are being turned over to the Federal Bureau of Investigation for testing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Complaints of possibly tainted bottled water mounted in the metropolitan region yesterday, even as law enforcement officials said that thus far they had not discerned any link or pattern to the reports.</p>
        <p>Although local and federal authorities have yet to find any evidence of bottle tampering, they have not ruled out the possibility of foul play. All of the bottles of suspect water are being turned over to the Federal Bureau of Investigation for testing.</p>
        <p>''The critical question as to whether or not any of these instances are linked has not yet been answered,'' said Joseph Valiquette, the F.B.I. spokesman in the New York office. ''Nor do we have the answer to the question as to whether a crime has been committed.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Valiquette would not say how many reports were being investigated, saying, ''We're not going to get into a numbers game.''</p>
        <p>The city police and state health officials have reported at least 12 incidents involving complaints of potentially contaminated bottled water: 9 in the city and 1 each in Westchester, Suffolk and Rockland Counties.</p>
        <p>''I think that obviously it's serious,'' said Claire Pospisil, a spokeswoman for the State Health Department. ''I don't think we really know the answer to how widespread it is.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani announced at a news conference on Wednesday that there had been three incidents of people becoming sick after drinking bottled water between Aug. 3 and Sept. 6. Although no one was seriously ill, the incidents have unnerved many people and led to concerns among the authorities that the contamination could have been deliberate.</p>
        <p>City officials said that at first these three reports seemed to be isolated incidents, so there was no public announcement. Only recently did the City Health Department determine that the contaminants in the three reported cases were similar, said Deputy Commissioner Sandra Mullin.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mullin described two of the contaminants, found in separate bottles, as ammonia and sodium hydroxide. Health officials still have not identified the third contaminant, she said, although it had a similar alkalinity to the others.</p>
        <p>One early theory was that a contaminant might have been inserted into plastic water bottles with a hypodermic syringe, said an official familiar with the investigation. But, he added, ''the preliminary indication is that is not the case.''</p>
        <p>Investigators are looking into each report individually, since the circumstances vary. So far, the incidents have involved Perrier, Poland Spring and Aquafina water.</p>
        <p>In the first and most serious incident, and the only one involving a glass bottle, a diner at Benihana, a Japanese steakhouse on West 56th Street, felt a burning sensation and began bleeding from her mouth after drinking some Perrier. She was hospitalized for several days, with a diagnosis of chemical burns to her mouth and esophagus. Trace elements of lye were found in the remaining water, the police said. The original bottle was not recovered, but the water had been poured into a glass, raising the possibility that it was the glass, not the water, that had been contaminated.</p>
        <p>The police were looking into a complaint made on Thursday by a Bronx man who said that he had suffered a burning sensation in his mouth after drinking from a bottle of Aquafina water he had bought from a gas station vending machine. The man, Jose Pena, was taken to Jacobi Medical Center, where he was treated and released with no apparent injuries, the police said. The bottled water was found to contain chlorine bleach. The police said a bottle of chlorine bleach was found on a counter at a nearby florist shop where Mr. Pena had gone to drink his water. They did not say how bleach had gotten into his water.</p>
        <p>''There were no injuries that were diagnosed,'' said a senior investigator working on the case.</p>
        <p>The police seem to be taking each report seriously. They took measures, for example, when a Bronx woman reported around 9 p.m. Thursday that she had a burning sensation in her mouth after drinking from a bottle of Aquafina water, the police said. She had not sought medical treatment at the time, the authorities said, but thought she should report the incident after seeing a story about the bottled water scare on the evening news.</p>
        <p>About 11:30 that night, a detective contacted the store where the woman had bought the water,  Rosa Frasca Groceries, at 1028 Morris Park Avenue, said Antonio Frasca, one of the store's owners. The detective asked that the store take all its Aquafina water off the shelf, he said. The same detective called around 9:30 yesterday morning with questions about the source of the water and the delivery driver and made another request not to sell the water, Mr. Frasca said.</p>
        <p>''The police told me to pull it off the shelf and not to sell it,'' he said. ''When the police ask you to do something like that, you do it.</p>
        <p>''I wish I knew something more specific,'' Mr. Frasca said. ''I have to take my water off the shelf. Meanwhile everyone else is selling it. There's no recall. No one tells us anything specific. I see other people sell it. So I want to know -- is it something serious?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
