<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y16BRI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/16/world/16BRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230864"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D81138F935A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: KURSK THEORIES -- The official inquiry into the sinking of the submarine Kursk has discarded 11 theories, leaving only the possibilities of an onboard accident and collisions with a World War II mine or another vessel, Deputy Prime Minister Ilya Klebanov told Parliament. Mr. Klebanov said that a Russian minisub would arrive at the wreck site on Sept. 23 or 24, and that the cause of the disaster might be known even before efforts begin to raise the sub or remove the remains of its 118 crewmen.</p>
        <p>Michael Wines (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: KURSK THEORIES -- The official inquiry into the sinking of the submarine Kursk has discarded 11 theories, leaving only the possibilities of an onboard accident and collisions with a World War II mine or another vessel, Deputy Prime Minister Ilya Klebanov told Parliament. Mr. Klebanov said that a Russian minisub would arrive at the wreck site on Sept. 23 or 24, and that the cause of the disaster might be known even before efforts begin to raise the sub or remove the remains of its 118 crewmen.</p>
        <p>Michael Wines (NYT)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: TURNABOUT ON GRAFT -- Switzerland's top prosecutor said Russia ''has taken on concrete commitments'' to pursue charges of money-laundering, a turnabout from past complaints of foot-dragging in politically sensitive inquiries. The prosecutor, Valentine Roschacher, met with the Russian prosecutor general, Vladimir Ustinov, and an official told the Interfax news service that investigations of the Aeroflot airline and the Kremlin's hugely expensive renovation were on their agenda.</p>
        <p>Michael Wines (NYT)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: FLIGHTS TO IRAQ PROPOSED -- Aeroflot and Vnukovo airlines repeated their intent to seek Russian approval to open commercial air service to Baghdad despite complaints by the United States and other Western nations that it would flout the United Nations' economic sanctions against Iraq. Vnukovo's general director said the airline would fly a charter to Baghdad on Sept. 23 carrying relief aid and a delegation promoting Russian-Iraqi friendship.</p>
        <p>Michael Wines (NYT)</p>
        <p>YUGOSLAVIA: MILOSEVIC'S WIFE BARRED -- Kosovo's NATO-led peacekeeping force warned Mira Markovic, the wife of President Slobodan Milosevic, that she would be barred from entering the province if she tried to visit in connection with the Sept. 24 elections because she had not given the required four days' notice. But the news agency Beta said the ban might be the result of a misunderstanding, since another Mira Markovic, also an official in the Yugoslav Left Party, planned to visit Kosovo.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>SPAIN: FRENCH HOLD TOP BASQUE SUSPECT -- The French police arrested the reputed head of the Basque separatist group E.T.A., Ignacio Gracia Arregui, in a joint operation with the Spanish Civil Guard, the Spanish Interior Ministry said. Mr. Gracia Arregui, 45, is wanted in Spain on charges that he ordered a failed assassination attempt on King Juan Carlos in 1995. His detention follows the arrests this week of 20 members of an E.T.A. planning and support group in Spain.</p>
        <p>Benjamin Jones (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: QUEEN DEPLORES DIANA BOOK -- In a joint statement, Queen Elizabeth II and Prince Charles said they ''deeply deplore'' a new book by Patrick Jephson, private secretary to Diana, Princess of Wales, during the years in which her marriage collapsed. They said while they felt that Mr. Jephson was violating a signed confidentiality agreement, the royal family had ruled out legal action.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>MYANMAR: ACTIVIST DEFIANT -- The pro-democracy leader Daw Aung San Suu Kyi emerged from two weeks of virtual house arrest and promised to keep challenging the military rulers, who have barred her from pursuing political activities outside the capital. ''Stop us if you dare!'' she told the government at a news conference. ''I shall be traveling outside Rangoon within the next 10 days for party organizational work,'' she said.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NORTH KOREA: G.I. REMAINS RETURNED -- Remains believed to be those of nine American soldiers missing in action in the Korean War were returned to the United States military. A United Nations honor guard removed them from a plane that flew them to Tokyo from Pyongyang, North Korea. The recovery operation, the third this year, was the 15th in North Korea since the program began in 1996.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CHINA: TWO U.S. WARPLANES FOUND IN TIBET -- China has found two American planes that crashed in Tibet in World War II, according to Robert Jones, deputy assistant secretary of defense for P.O.W. and missing personnel affairs.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>KYRGYZSTAN: MORE CLASHES WITH ISLAMIC REBELS -- Islamic insurgents used grenade-launchers to fire on government troops as clashes erupted for a third night on Kyrgyzstan's southern frontier, the Defense Ministry said. Kyrgyz border troops waged a three-hour battle with about 10 armed rebels who attacked the Dzhyly-Suu border post late Thursday, according to the chief military spokesman, Bolot Imanaliyev.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>NIGERIA: SHELL FACES TRIAL -- A lawsuit against the Shell oil company over its operations in Nigeria will be heard in federal court in New York. The United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit decided on Thursday that officials of Royal Dutch/Shell could be tried on charges of colluding with the authorities in Lagos in the torture and murder of Nigerian activists, including the author and opposition leader Ken Saro-Wiwa. Mr. Saro-Wiwa was hanged with eight others in 1995.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>CONGO: 51 CIVILIANS SLAIN -- Congolese rebels discovered the bodies of 51 civilians who appeared to have been shot at close range by government troops retreating from the northwest town of Dongo, a rebel leader said. Jean-Pierre Bemba, leader of the Ugandan-backed Congolese Liberation Movement, which is fighting to oust President Laurent Kabila, said that the 47 men and 4 women had been killed Sept. 8 and were found the next day, when the rebels took over the town.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>IRAN: LEADING THE GROUP OF 77 -- Iran was elected by acclamation to the chairmanship of the influential Group of 77, which now numbers 133 developing countries. The election was held at the annual meeting of the group's foreign ministers in New York. Iran will succeed Nigeria in January.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
