<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush's Tune Is the Same Even as the Pitch Varies</title>
    <meta content="Y16NOT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/16/politics/16NOTE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230857"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: REPORTER'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E3D91138F935A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush's Tune Is the Same Even as the Pitch Varies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>ALBUQUERQUE, Sept. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reporter's Notebook comments on George W Bush's reinvention of himself and his campaign slogans, on his long campaign days that are tallied by aides miffed at unfavorable comparisons with Al Gore's taxing schedule, on speculation that Bush's frequent malapropisms are caused by dyslexia (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For much of the presidential campaign, Vice President Al Gore has been cast as the desperate master of morphing and derided for earth-toned makeovers and alpha-male aspirations.</p>
        <p>But lately, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas has been more than holding his own in the reinvention sweepstakes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For much of the presidential campaign, Vice President Al Gore has been cast as the desperate master of morphing and derided for earth-toned makeovers and alpha-male aspirations.</p>
        <p>But lately, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas has been more than holding his own in the reinvention sweepstakes.</p>
        <p>He was once ''a reformer with results,'' the primary-season catch phrase of choice for a campaign with a yen for alliteration and a determination to appropriate Senator John McCain's mantle. Now Mr. Bush has ''real plans for real people,'' the similar consonants spawning semantic confusion.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to carry Florida, and the reason why is that I've got real plans for real people,'' he told reporters during an airport stop near St. Petersburg, Fla., on Monday. Minutes later, he said he would win Florida because he was bent on getting ''real results for real people,'' presumably through reform.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush prides himself on his constancy, and while his staff and proposed policies have not changed much in 15 months, his packaging has, and not only recently.</p>
        <p>For a long time, he was offering ''a fresh start,'' which his advisers believed to be the perfect pitch for voters with Clinton fatigue. He angled for ''prosperity with a purpose,'' the ripe fruit of ''compassionate conservatism.''</p>
        <p>After the Republican National Convention, his aides printed banners and literature with a promise to ''change the tone.'' But that was hard pressed to survive the sometimes acidic oratory and advertising that he and other Republicans trained on Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Bush is trying something old, something new and something borrowed.</p>
        <p>Just before Mr. Bush started campaigning on Monday, his aides informed reporters that he would be showing up as ''a different kind of Republican,'' which is what he was in the spring as well.</p>
        <p>But this kind of Republican would now be reaching those ''real people,'' an obvious answer to Mr. Gore's references to ''working people'' and ''working families.''</p>
        <p>At an event in Clearwater, Fla., that immediately followed his appearance at the airport, Mr. Bush explained his Medicare and prescription drug proposals by saying, ''Our prosperity must have a purpose.''</p>
        <p>And a candidate must have an epigram -- or four or five of them.</p>
        <p>A Candidate in Motion</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Mr. Bush's campaign day spanned about 17 hours, three states and four time zones, undeniable evidence that he has picked up his pace. But who is counting?</p>
        <p>His aides, for one, and they are not being particularly subtle.</p>
        <p>''If you feel tired at the end of this week, I noticed that we're covering 7,756 miles,'' Karen P. Hughes, the campaign's director of communications, told reporters. She made it sound as if she had accidentally tripped across the information.</p>
        <p>''We're visiting nine cities in five different states, I think for a total of 106 electoral votes,'' Ms. Hughes added, again striving for a casual, just-occurred-to-me delivery. But there was nothing nonchalant about it.</p>
        <p>Long miffed by news articles that Mr. Bush's schedule was less taxing than Vice President Al Gore's, Bush aides have begun offering reporters regularly updated statistics about the campaign's ambitious reach.</p>
        <p>At one point, they even compared the relative velocities of a train that Mr. Bush used for a campaign trip and a riverboat that transported Mr. Gore. Mr. Bush's vehicle was about seven times faster, his aides noted, which allowed the governor to cover more ground.</p>
        <p>They know in their hearts that Mr. Gore is the real slacker, and they will not be fooled by any of the vice president's 24-hour, round-the-clock preening.</p>
        <p>''Despite Vice President Gore's much-ballyhooed Labor Day workathon last week,'' Ms. Hughes told reporters, ''we visited more cities in more states by week's end than he had.''</p>
        <p>A Slip Caused by Fatigue</p>
        <p>The problem with all that hustle and bustle is that Mr. Bush often wears his fatigue on his tongue. And never has it twisted in such an exquisite fashion as it did during a visit on Thursday to a drugstore in Orange, Calif.</p>
        <p>A woman there asked Mr. Bush about an article in Vanity Fair magazine that postulates a cause for his frequent malapropisms and lapses of grammar: dyslexia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has laughed off that theory and did so on this occasion by pointing out how little contact he had had with the writer of the Vanity Fair article, Gail Sheehy.</p>
        <p>''The woman who knew that I had dyslexia -- I never interviewed her,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>He did not appear to be making what would have been an incredibly clever joke.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: REPORTER'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
