<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Revival Of 'Capeman'?</title>
    <meta content="20BROA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/arts/20BROA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240203"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON STAGE AND OFF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jewish Repertory Theater</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Actors Theater</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Theater Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simon, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Laurents, Arthur</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albee, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meara, Anne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wallach, Eli</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Anne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wallach, Roberta</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stiller, Amy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schell, Maximilian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grizzard, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hatcher, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Capeman (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Big Potato (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Play About the Baby, the (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Judgment at Nuremberg (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Compleat Female Stage Beauty (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/On Stage and Off</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Edward Albee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E3DD133EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1070" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Revival Of 'Capeman'?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jesse McKinley</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Stage and Off column; new version of Paul Simon's musical Capeman, $11 million flop in 1998, may be in works; Arthur Laurents says he does not like Jewish Repertory Theater's production of his play Big Potato, and wishes it will not open at all; The Play About the Baby by Edward Albee may book into Lucille Lortel Theater; Anne Meara's play Down the Garden Paths is in rehearsal; photo of Meara with actors Eli Wallach and Anne Jackson and their daughter Roberta Wallach, and Meara's daughter, Amy Stiller; Maximilian Schell and George Grizzard look set for National Actors Theater production of Judgment at Nuremberg; Jeffrey Hatcher's play Compleat Female Stage Beauty to open at Philadelphia Theater Company</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was one of the most expensive and contentious flops in Broadway history, an $11 million disaster that seemed to inspire record levels of nastily expressed joy in a business famed for super-strength schadenfreude. The show, Paul Simon's ''Capeman,'' closed in March 1998 after 68 performances and countless swipes at its pop-icon composer.</p>
        <p>Now there are signs that a new version of the musical may be in the works. A member of the original production said this week that Mr. Simon had recently met with Emily Mann, the artistic director of the McCarter Theater in Princeton, N.J., about a possible revision and remounting of the show. Few details were available, but tentative plans would call for new writers to collaborate on the book, by the Nobel Prize-winning poet Derek Walcott, which many critics said was a principal problem with the show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was one of the most expensive and contentious flops in Broadway history, an $11 million disaster that seemed to inspire record levels of nastily expressed joy in a business famed for super-strength schadenfreude. The show, Paul Simon's ''Capeman,'' closed in March 1998 after 68 performances and countless swipes at its pop-icon composer.</p>
        <p>Now there are signs that a new version of the musical may be in the works. A member of the original production said this week that Mr. Simon had recently met with Emily Mann, the artistic director of the McCarter Theater in Princeton, N.J., about a possible revision and remounting of the show. Few details were available, but tentative plans would call for new writers to collaborate on the book, by the Nobel Prize-winning poet Derek Walcott, which many critics said was a principal problem with the show.</p>
        <p>''What it would require and they are talking about is rewriting the book,'' said the former production member. ''But they are in the very early stages.'' A McCarter spokesman confirmed that the theater was in ''very preliminary'' discussions with Mr. Simon.</p>
        <p>''The Capeman'' is about a notorious 1959 murder case in which a Puerto Rican gang member, Salvador Agron, was convicted of murdering two white teenagers in Hell's Kitchen. Because he wore a cape during the crime, the tabloids nicknamed him ''The Capeman.''</p>
        <p>The buzz on the musical was critical almost from its outset, in part because Mr. Simon resisted industry suggestions that he hire a proven Broadway director or turn over some creative control to experienced producers. The troubles worsened after producers were forced to bring in several show doctors; Mr. Walcott reportedly resisted changes in his writing, further hampering efforts to save the show. It is unclear whether Mr. Walcott would now assent to  changes.</p>
        <p>Despite the show's travails, Mr. Simon's score and some individual performances received praise. Many reviews spoke of opportunity lost. Vincent Canby said in The New York Times that ''the failure of 'The Capeman' should not be a cause for derision but for lamentation.'' Perhaps it is that sense of missed chances that Mr. Simon hopes to remedy.</p>
        <p>A Dejected Laurents</p>
        <p>The producers of ''Big Potato,'' a new comedy by Arthur Laurents, said yesterday that they intended to open the show as planned on Sunday. That's apparently bad news for the playwright, who said yesterday he would prefer that the production just go away. ''I don't want it to open at all,'' said Mr. Laurents, sounding dejected. ''I believe in the play, but this production just isn't good. And I don't need the critics to tell me that it isn't any good. I know it.'' Richard Sabellico, the director, said he agreed with Mr. Laurents.</p>
        <p>The play, a dark comedy about a beautician who captures a Nazi in her salon, is being produced by the Jewish Repertory Theater. Ran Avni, the artistic director, said he believed it was a solid production. ''I think it's a terrific show,'' he said. ''I think it should be seen by as many people as possible.''</p>
        <p>Albee's 'Baby'</p>
        <p>''The Play About the Baby'' has apparently found its crib. The newest work from Edward Albee, starring Marian Seldes and Brian Murray, has been awaiting a theater booking since last spring. This week its producer, Elizabeth Ireland McCann, said she was close to booking a 299-seat house and was likely to complete the deal on Monday. The play is about two couples -- one young, one older -- in a cosmic tug of war over a child who may or may not exist. It is  one of several high-profile Albee offerings this year, including a New York revival of ''Tiny Alice.''</p>
        <p>Ms. McCann would not identify the theater for ''Baby,'' but insiders say the Lucille Lortel is a possibility. Ms. McCann said rehearsals would begin in mid-December for a Jan. 15 opening. David Esbjornson will direct.</p>
        <p>A Reunion, Sort Of</p>
        <p>It's a rainy Wednesday afternoon in Shubert Alley and under the Shubert Theater's marquee, some cast members of Anne Meara's new play, ''Down the Garden Paths,'' have assembled for a photo shoot.</p>
        <p>Eli Wallach is standing in front of a ''Lion King'' poster, clowning with an umbrella. (''Look, I'm the Lion King. And I couldn't even get a ticket.'') A stage door away, Ms. Meara and Anne Jackson are hugging and  joking. (Ms. Meara: ''Are you taking your clothes off for this?'') In the middle stands Ms. Meara's daughter, Amy, who smiles and offers this summary: ''It's always like this when they get together. Chaos.''</p>
        <p>That said, chaos isn't exactly surprising in a production rife with family connections. ''Down the Garden Paths'' stars Mr. Wallach and Ms. Jackson, one of Broadway's legendary couples, and their daughter, Roberta Wallach. Also in the cast are several members of Ms. Meara's extended family, including her husband, Jerry Stiller -- who makes a video appearance in the play -- and  Amy. The cast, which also includes John Shea, started rehearsal yesterday for a Nov. 20 opening at the Minetta Lane Theater.</p>
        <p>''It's like a reunion,'' Ms. Meara said. ''Anything else I would say would sound pretentious. I'm just so glad we're together.''</p>
        <p>Along the Way</p>
        <p>* Maximilian Schell and George Grizzard look set for the National Actors Theater production of ''Judgment at Nuremberg,'' due to open in March at a Shubert house. The script should be familiar enough to Mr. Schell; he appeared in the 1959 teleplay on which this version is based, as well as the 1961 film.</p>
        <p>* Expect attention to be paid to Wednesday night's opening -- and Thursday's reviews -- of ''Compleat Female Stage Beauty,'' a new play by Jeffrey Hatcher about Edward Kynaston, a 17th-century actor famed for his female impersonations. Several Broadway veterans, including the director, Walter Bobbie, are involved in the play, to be staged at the Philadelphia Theater Company. Fran Weissler, a New York producer, is considering a transfer.</p>
        <p>ON STAGE AND OFF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
