<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.F.L. Matchups Week 8</title>
    <meta content="MAT20" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240370"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E6DB103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1982" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.F.L. Matchups Week 8</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Preview of this weekend's NFL matchups; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUNDAY 1 p.m.  DENVER (4-3) AT CINCINNATI (0-6)  It is getting rough for Bengals players. They are insulted at local supermarkets by their fans. They grimace when they watch TV highlights of so many other players around the league having fun while they toil in futility. With each Bengals loss, the pressure mounts and the disappointment grows. Their offense is a mess. Their confidence is shot. There is little relief in sight.Broncos, 26-20</p>
        <p>NEW ENGLAND (2-5) AT INDIANAPOLIS (4-2)  New England dumped Indianapolis two weeks ago and looked ready for a revival until the Jets crushed those hopes last Sunday. Now the Patriots travel to Indianapolis and attempt to duplicate the first meeting, in part by using back Kevin Faulk as a frequent pass receiver. But Indianapolis will be ready. Colts kicker Mike Vanderjagt (10 consecutive field goals made, 38 of his last 39 converted and 12 of 13 this season) is simply the start of New England's worries. Colts, 27-17</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUNDAY 1 p.m.  DENVER (4-3) AT CINCINNATI (0-6)  It is getting rough for Bengals players. They are insulted at local supermarkets by their fans. They grimace when they watch TV highlights of so many other players around the league having fun while they toil in futility. With each Bengals loss, the pressure mounts and the disappointment grows. Their offense is a mess. Their confidence is shot. There is little relief in sight.Broncos, 26-20</p>
        <p>NEW ENGLAND (2-5) AT INDIANAPOLIS (4-2)  New England dumped Indianapolis two weeks ago and looked ready for a revival until the Jets crushed those hopes last Sunday. Now the Patriots travel to Indianapolis and attempt to duplicate the first meeting, in part by using back Kevin Faulk as a frequent pass receiver. But Indianapolis will be ready. Colts kicker Mike Vanderjagt (10 consecutive field goals made, 38 of his last 39 converted and 12 of 13 this season) is simply the start of New England's worries. Colts, 27-17</p>
        <p>SAN FRANCISCO (2-5) AT CAROLINA (2-4)  Jeff Garcia has more touchdown passes than Kurt Warner's 17. In fact, Garcia has more than any other quarterback. Quite an accomplishment for a player who entered this season considered only a temporary fill-in, with little shot as the sole answer for the future. Garcia is changing that thinking. Well, why haven't the 49ers won more with that kind of production? Easy -- no defense.  Panthers, 27-24</p>
        <p>ARIZONA (2-4) AT DALLAS (2-4)  After being trounced last week at home by 33-14 by Philadelphia, some of the Cardinals described themselves as ''garbage.'' That is severe analysis coming from inside the locker room, no matter how true. Certainly, Arizona has been lifeless in Dallas during the regular season, where it has lost its last 10 games. Wonder if anyone in the Dallas locker room, though, thinks of his current crew as garbage? Cowboys, 23-9</p>
        <p>CHICAGO (1-6) AT PHILADELPHIA (4-3)  Brian Urlacher, Chicago's rookie middle linebacker, earned a starting job in preseason, lost it and then won it again. He leads his team not only in tackles but also in sacks. His total of six sacks is more than Mike Singletary, the Hall of Fame Bears middle linebacker, gained in his first seven games as a rookie. Urlacher, though, needs more help, especially against the meshing Eagles. Eagles, 17-14</p>
        <p>NEW ORLEANS (3-3) AT ATLANTA (2-5)  New Orleans has shown promise while the Falcons are sinking. The Saints are riding four consecutive 100-yard rushing games by Ricky Williams and a defense that ranks first leaguewide in total and pass defense. Those are smart and impressive numbers for Jim Haslett, the Saints' rookie coach. A victory here would help make the Saints' legitimate playoff contenders. They get it.  Saints, 19-17</p>
        <p>SUNDAY 4 p.m.</p>
        <p>SEATTLE (2-5) AT OAKLAND (5-1)  It has all fallen apart for the Seahawks. Seattle is giving the ball away too frequently. Its defense is not gaining enough turnovers, with no Seahawk having more than one interception after the team led the league in picks last year. There has already been a quarterback change. But the Raiders just won at Kansas City (an early Christmas for them) and are primed to win the A.F.C. West. This is another big step. Raiders, 28-23</p>
        <p>CLEVELAND (2-5) AT PITTSBURGH (3-3)  Pittsburgh was a team buried with a quarterback controversy, a running game that was limping, young receivers who looked spooked and, over all, a club that lacked confidence. There has been a major turnaround in each of those areas because Pittsburgh can win its fourth consecutive game for the first time since the 1997 season. It will. Doug Pederson starts for Tim Couch, out six weeks with a broken thumb.  Steelers, 24-10</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON (5-2) AT JACKSONVILLE (2-5)  Jaguars' Mark Brunell has more interceptions (8) than touchdown passes (7). Those statistics say plenty about the Jaguars. Washington is playing impressive football, having won four straight games against teams (Giants, Buccaneers, Eagles and Ravens) who have a combined 17-10 record. Washington has never played at ALLTEL Stadium but will enjoy the amenities -- a Jaguars team that too frequently self-destructs. Redskins, 21-17</p>
        <p>SUNDAY 1 p.m.</p>
        <p>ST. LOUIS (6-0) AT KANSAS CITY (3-3)  Both teams reside in Missouri, so this is an intrastate blood battle. There are several reasons to pick the Chiefs in a stunning upset. First, Kansas City has won its last 10 games at home versus N.F.C. teams. The Chiefs' offense is best in the A.F.C. in red-zone touchdown percentage (68.4). Quarterback Elvis Grbac is 3-0 against the Rams and has thrown at least one touchdown pass in his last 12 games. How can anyone, however, pick against the fleet Rams, champions and unbeaten until proven otherwise? Here goes. Chiefs, 30-28</p>
        <p>BUFFALO (3-3) AT MINNESOTA (6-0)  It has been 21 years since Buffalo played at Minnesota. That game was a 10-3 Minnesota victory during which quarterback Tommy Kramer threw a winning 19-yard scoring pass to receiver Ahmad Rashad. Now the Vikings' signature passing connection is the rookie Duante Culpepper to receiver Randy Moss. The Bills will wish for Kramer and Rashad. Buffalo's Doug Flutie is back at quarterback, which makes the game more fun but only in spurts. Vikings, 28-17</p>
        <p>TENNESSEE (5-1) AT BALTIMORE (5-2)  This will be a fast and furious game, with the defenses dominating. These teams will see each other again in the regular season and likely again in the playoffs. Tennessee enters confidently with a five-game winning streak. The Ravens are struggling to score points but know they must have this game to stay on track for the divisional championship. Ravens quarterback Tony Banks gets it together. Ravens, 16-14</p>
        <p>GAME OF THE WEEK</p>
        <p>MIAMI (5-1) AT NEW YORK JETS (5-1)  Two first-place teams in the A.F.C. East battle in a ''Monday Night Football'' game. The pace of the game should be fast, and the play should be clean because both teams run the ball efficiently and rely on persistent defense. Miami's defense has gained the early glamour this season, but will the Jets' unit respond and steal the show? There is every indication that it can and will, especially considering that it has a return touchdown in each of its past three games against Miami. That streak gives the Jets' defense the confidence it needs to excel. Comparisons with the Miami defense will provide extra incentive. Jets, 13-10</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
