<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Prosecutors Willing To Review DNA Evidence</title>
    <meta content="Y20DNA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/national/20DNA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001023T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240253"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deoxyribonucleic Acid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">False Arrests, Convictions and Imprisonments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Travis (Tex)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milloy, Ross E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lavernia, Carlos</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E6D6133EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="949" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Prosecutors Willing To Review DNA Evidence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROSS E. MILLOY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Milloy, Ross E</byline>
      <dateline>AUSTIN, Tex. Oct. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Travis County, Tex, district attorney's office has started re-examining more than 400 criminal convictions in wake of ruling based on DNA evidence that found Carlos Lavernia not guilty of 1983 rape, for which he had served 16 years in prison; similar reviews are being taken in other jurisdictions throughout the nation as DNA testing improves and becomes more widespread (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For nearly 16 years, Carlos Lavernia, a Cuban refugee, has languished in a Texas prison since being found guilty of a 1983 rape that he swore he did not commit.</p>
        <p>Last week, a state judge ruled that Mr. Lavernia was not guilty of the crime, based on DNA evidence, and the Travis County district attorney has started re-examining more than 400 convictions to see if other miscarriages of justice could be corrected through DNA testing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For nearly 16 years, Carlos Lavernia, a Cuban refugee, has languished in a Texas prison since being found guilty of a 1983 rape that he swore he did not commit.</p>
        <p>Last week, a state judge ruled that Mr. Lavernia was not guilty of the crime, based on DNA evidence, and the Travis County district attorney has started re-examining more than 400 convictions to see if other miscarriages of justice could be corrected through DNA testing.</p>
        <p>''This is a great tragedy for Mr. Lavernia, but also for this community,'' said Ronnie Earle, the district attorney who supervised Mr. Lavernia's conviction and exoneration. ''Austin has always prided itself on its values, and there is no higher value than justice.''</p>
        <p>Similar reviews have been announced in San Diego and Riverside, Calif., and as DNA testing improves and becomes more widespread, other jurisdictions will be reviewing  convictions in which the technology could establish guilt or innocence, said Barry C. Scheck, co-director of the Innocence Project at the Benjamin N. Cardozo School of Law in New York.</p>
        <p>The review panel in Travis County is significant because of the scope of the inquiry and the attitude of prosecutors, Mr. Scheck said, adding that Texas law does not require postconviction access to DNA testing.</p>
        <p>''This shows that there are prosecutors who are willing to seek the truth and correct injustices, no matter how embarrassing it might be,'' he said. ''That's an important principle.''</p>
        <p>There have been at least 82 post-conviction exonerations through DNA in North America -- 76 in the United States and 6 in Canada, said Mr. Scheck, who has been involved in dozens of DNA cases and who has written, with Jim Dwyer, a book on the topic, ''Actual Innocence: Five Days to Execution and Other Dispatches From the Wrongfully Convicted'' (Doubleday, 2000).</p>
        <p>''Eight of those exonerations were of people on death row, which is important in itself,'' Mr. Scheck said. ''But in 16 of these 82 postconviction exonerations, DNA testing has not only remedied a terrible miscarriage of justice but led to the identification of the real perpetrator.''</p>
        <p>''Remember,'' he said, ''every time the wrong person is in jail, the real perpetrator is out there committing more crimes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Scheck, who discussed the structure and methods of the review panel with Mr. Earle, said that five states -- New York, Arizona, California, Illinois and Oklahoma -- had  laws that guaranteed access to DNA testing and that legislation had been proposed in both houses of Congress.</p>
        <p>In Texas, State Senators Rodney Ellis and David Sibley, a Democrat and a Republican, have prepared similar legislation for consideration by the next session of the Legislature, which begins in January.</p>
        <p>California's law guaranteeing access to DNA testing will go into effect in January, and prosecutors in San Diego County have already set up a program to comply with it.</p>
        <p>Lisa Weinreb, a deputy district attorney who heads the San Diego review panel, said 560 potentially problematic convictions had been identified. So far, Ms. Weinreb said, 200 have been reviewed, and only one case has emerged in which DNA testing might exonerate the defendant.</p>
        <p>''We're looking at everything where biological evidence might have played a role prior to 1992, because that's when we started using DNA testing as part of our conviction process,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Among the nine members of the Austin review panel are police representatives, defense and appeals lawyers, victims' services personnel and a DNA specialist.</p>
        <p>''We have no way of knowing if there are any more cases where DNA testing would exonerate a person,'' Mr. Earle said. ''We do know that there are roughly 400 cases we're going to examine that meet our initial criteria for a second look.''</p>
        <p>The cases involve convictions before 1994, when DNA testing technology became available here, and include any in which there is a continuing claim of innocence, where the identity of the suspect was at issue and where DNA evidence could have influenced the outcome of a trial had it been available, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lavernia, 50, was convicted of rape in 1985, based primarily on the  testimony of the victim.</p>
        <p>''We did not have DNA technology at the time this case was investigated,'' Mr. Earle said. ''If we had, Carlos Lavernia would never have been charged.''</p>
        <p>William P. Allison, Mr. Lavernia's lawyer, applauded the formation of a panel, saying: ''I think it's incredibly courageous of Earle to be so aggressive on this. It's also kind of scary. We've got 162,000 prisoners in Texas. How many more are innocent?''</p>
        <p>But even if a state appeals court concurs with last week's ruling that Mr. Lavernia is innocent, his troubles are not over.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lavernia, who entered the United States in the Mariel boatlift from Cuba in 1980, was on probation for a 1982 conviction of indecency with a child when he was charged with the rape in 1983.</p>
        <p>Immigration officials have said  they will hold him for possible deportation on the 1982 charge, but because the United States has no diplomatic relations with Cuba, his detention will be indefinite.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Lavernia did not commit the rape for which he was convicted, he cannot receive a pardon, which makes him ineligible for compensation under Texas law for the 16 years he has spent in prison.</p>
        <p>''If he had committed the crime, he would have been eligible to receive up to $50,000,'' Mr. Allison said.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 23, 2000, Monday  An article on Friday about a Texas prosecutor's re-examination of more than 400 convictions to see whether DNA testing could find anyone who had been wrongly convicted referred incompletely to the authorship of the book ''Actual Innocence: Five Days to Execution and Other Dispatches From the Wrongfully Convicted'' (Doubleday, 2000). Besides Barry Scheck and Jim Dwyer, the authors included Peter Neufeld.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 23, 2000, Monday</p>
        <p>An article on Friday about a Texas prosecutor's re-examination of more than 400 convictions to see whether DNA testing could find anyone who had been wrongly convicted referred incompletely to the authorship of the book ''Actual Innocence: Five Days to Execution and Other Dispatches From the Wrongfully Convicted'' (Doubleday, 2000). Besides Barry Scheck and Jim Dwyer, the authors included Peter Neufeld.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
