<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Unlikely Hero Of '55 Series. Well, Sort Of.</title>
    <meta content="20BERK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/sports/20BERK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240274"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Dodgers (Defunct Team)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berkow, Ira</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, Don</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Ira Berkow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E1DF103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="824" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Unlikely Hero Of '55 Series. Well, Sort Of.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berkow, Ira</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ira Berkow, in Sports of The Times, recalls Don Zimmer's role in 1955 World Series when he was second-baseman for Brooklyn Dodgers, who played New York Yankees in Series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAYBE you heard about how Popeye -- he was simply called Don Zimmer in those days -- was single-handedly responsible for the one and only time the Brooklyn Dodgers won the World Series, in 1955, in the first of back-to-back Subway Series with the Yankees. And he wasn't even playing. A lot of people aren't aware of how it happened, even fans in all the boroughs who have followed baseball right up to this weekend, when a Subway Series in these populous woods resumes after a parched 44-year interruption.</p>
        <p>This time, of course, it's the Yankees against the Mets, inheritors of the hearts of many fans of the long-gone Dodgers and New York Giants. And Popeye will be the only man on either bench who was in uniform during the last two Subway Series. Zimmer, the bench coach to Yankee Manager Joe Torre, was a 24-year-old second baseman for the Dodgers in 1955.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAYBE you heard about how Popeye -- he was simply called Don Zimmer in those days -- was single-handedly responsible for the one and only time the Brooklyn Dodgers won the World Series, in 1955, in the first of back-to-back Subway Series with the Yankees. And he wasn't even playing. A lot of people aren't aware of how it happened, even fans in all the boroughs who have followed baseball right up to this weekend, when a Subway Series in these populous woods resumes after a parched 44-year interruption.</p>
        <p>This time, of course, it's the Yankees against the Mets, inheritors of the hearts of many fans of the long-gone Dodgers and New York Giants. And Popeye will be the only man on either bench who was in uniform during the last two Subway Series. Zimmer, the bench coach to Yankee Manager Joe Torre, was a 24-year-old second baseman for the Dodgers in 1955.</p>
        <p>He is called Popeye today at age 69 because he is puffy-cheeked, like the cartoon character. When you look at old photographs of Zimmer, say, turning the double play with Pee Wee Reese, he looks svelte -- not quite Olive Oyl, but in the ballpark.</p>
        <p>Since baseball thrives on history, as well as contemporary sound and fury, it is intriguing to learn how Popeye saw himself saving that long-ago day in '55. It was a sunlit October afternoon in Yankee Stadium. Fans in the stands generally dressed more formally, with men in suits and fedoras and women in furs. Trolleys still ran in Brooklyn, and Eisenhower was planning to run for a second term.</p>
        <p>The series was tied at three victories each when, in the top of the sixth, with the Dodgers ahead, 2-0, Brooklyn Manager Walter Alston, with lefty-righty switches, sent in George Shuba to pinch-hit for Zimmer against Bob Grim, who had been brought in to pitch that inning by Yankee Manager Casey Stengel. Shuba grounded out. Now Junior Gilliam, the left fielder, moved to second base for Brooklyn, and Sandy Amoros went in to play left field.</p>
        <p>In the bottom of the sixth, Billy Martin walked, Gil McDougald beat out a bunt, and Yogi Berra drove a certain extra-base hit to the left-field corner. But Amoros made a sensational catch and threw to Reese, who threw to Gil Hodges to double McDougald off first. Johnny Podres shut out the Yankees the rest of the way. ''Remember,'' recalled Zimmer, sitting in the Yankee dugout before a team workout yesterday, ''Amoros was left-handed and wore his glove on his right hand. A right-handed fielder cannot make that play in that corner. If I don't go out, Gilliam is still in the game. And we're in trouble with Yogi's hit. So, you see, with me on the bench, we won the game!''</p>
        <p>He continued: ''There was a team celebration in the Bossert Hotel in Brooklyn that night, and I'll never forget how happy the veterans especially were. Like Campy and Jackie and Erskine and Gil and Furillo and Newk. For years in the several other Subway Series, they could never beat the Yankees. The monkey was finally off their backs.''</p>
        <p>The next season, the Yankees and the Dodgers met again in a seven-game World Series, and the Yankees won. Zimmer sat on the bench, having suffered a fractured cheekbone after being hit by a pitch in June.</p>
        <p>In 1958, the Dodgers and the Giants moved to California. Four years later the Mets surfaced. And who was the starting third baseman for this New York expansion team? Popeye. ''The Mets lost 120 games that season,'' he said, ''but you can only blame me for the first 20 or so. I was traded to Cincinnati 30 days into the season.''</p>
        <p>Eventually, Popeye managed the Red Sox. ''The difference between those days and now?'' he said. ''I don't think there's the hatred between fans as there used to be, and not the hatred between the players either. The reason is that with free agency so many players move so much, it's hard to build up personal antagonisms. Like the Red Sox and Yankees of '76 and '77 -- there was Nettles against Lee, Fisk against Munson, Yaz and Piniella. And the old Dodgers and Yankees had the same players year after year. They weren't too thrilled with each other either.''</p>
        <p>Despite the lack of animosity -- a Clemens-versus-Piazza clash being relatively aberrant -- he said: ''This Subway Series is going to be unbelievable. It's been so long since there's been one, and these are two very good teams. Could go seven games. New York fans were waiting for this for the last two, three years and it was close. I know the players are excited. The fever of the Subway Series is catching.</p>
        <p>''Now,'' said Popeye, with his nearly half-century perspective, ''now it's finally here, again.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
