<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plan to Seal Some Criminal Records Debated</title>
    <meta content="20RECO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/nyregion/20RECO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lueck, Thomas J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koch, Edward I</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerik, Bernard B (Comr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3DE103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="479" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plan to Seal Some Criminal Records Debated</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lueck, Thomas J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Proposal to seal lower-level convictions of some nonviolent criminals draws appearances at City Hall of former mayor Edward I Koch, who argues merits of measure, and Police Comr Bernard Kerik, who staunchly opposes it; proposal, already passed by State Assembly, would assist people who have served state prison terms for misdemeanors or nonviolent felony convictions, mainly in drug cases; it would make New York the only state to permit criminal records to be sealed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A proposal to seal lower-level convictions of some nonviolent criminals drew the appearances at City Hall yesterday of former mayor Edward I. Koch, who argued the merits of the measure, and Police Commissioner Bernard Kerik, who staunchly opposed it.</p>
        <p>The proposal, already passed by the State Assembly, would assist people who have served state prison terms for misdemeanors or nonviolent felony convictions, mainly in drug cases. Termed a ''second chance program,'' it would make New York the only state to permit criminal records to be sealed -- and employers denied knowledge of an applicant's criminal past -- five years after a convict's sentence is completed. The Republican-controlled state Senate did not vote on the bill before adjourning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A proposal to seal lower-level convictions of some nonviolent criminals drew the appearances at City Hall yesterday of former mayor Edward I. Koch, who argued the merits of the measure, and Police Commissioner Bernard Kerik, who staunchly opposed it.</p>
        <p>The proposal, already passed by the State Assembly, would assist people who have served state prison terms for misdemeanors or nonviolent felony convictions, mainly in drug cases. Termed a ''second chance program,'' it would make New York the only state to permit criminal records to be sealed -- and employers denied knowledge of an applicant's criminal past -- five years after a convict's sentence is completed. The Republican-controlled state Senate did not vote on the bill before adjourning.</p>
        <p>Under the proposal, in the five-year period before records could be sealed, applicants would be required to perform community service, undergo drug and alcohol testing and get high school equivalency degrees.</p>
        <p>Anyone with a sealed record who was then re-arrested would lose the confidentiality, and their conviction records would be made available for police investigations, prosecution and court sentencing.</p>
        <p>''This is not soft on crime,'' said Mr. Koch in testimony before the City Council Committee on Fire and Criminal Justice Services. ''People would have an opportunity not to become recidivists, but to contribute to society.''</p>
        <p>In a surprise appearance, Commissioner Kerik argued strenuously against support for the bill. He called it ''a travesty of justice and an insult to law enforcement.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, asked about Mr. Koch's proposal at a press conference, said he might support a different version that only applied to people convicted of misdemeanors.  ''I think records should be open,'' he said. ''People hiring someone for a job should have the maximum amount of information about them.''</p>
        <p>Commissioner Kerik, who appeared before the council committee with Steven M. Fishner, the mayor's criminal justice coordinator, said the proposal ''would give drug traffickers the opportunity to make their convictions disappear.''</p>
        <p>''I state unequivocally and emphatically that if enacted, this bill will seriously impede my ability to fulfill the duties I owe to the citizens of New York City,'' he said. Although the bill provides police with access to sealed criminal records in investigations, he said its language was ambiguous and might prevent the broad access that the police depend on in undercover narcotics work, and incases involving gangs where a former felon with a sealed record may pose a threat even though he is not the main focus of suspicion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koch argued that the measure would help ease employment circumstances for the large numbers of Hispanic and black men who had been incarcerated, and might help counter what he termed the unfairness of the state's drug laws.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
