<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.D.A. BAN SOUGHT ON CHEMICAL USED FOR COLD REMEDIES</title>
    <meta content="20FDA.$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001021T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240338"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stroke</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Influenza</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Phenylpropanolamine (Ppa)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Food and Drug Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Influenza</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Stroke</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Influenza</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stroke</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E1DC103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.D.A. BAN SOUGHT ON CHEMICAL USED FOR COLD REMEDIES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL GAY STOLBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</byline>
      <dateline>GAITHERSBURG, Md., Oct. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Panel of scientific experts recommends that common ingredient in decongestants and appetite suppressants be removed from over-the-counter products, citing new evidence that phenylpropanolamine may increase risk of stroke in young women; consumers are warned to carefully read labels of popular cold and flu medications and diet pills; listing of products containing drug; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A panel of scientific experts recommended today that a common ingredient in decongestants and appetite suppressants be removed from over-the-counter products, citing new evidence that the chemical may increase the risk of stroke in young women.</p>
        <p>The panel's recommendation to the Food and Drug Administration is not binding, although the agency usually follows the recommendations of its outside experts. Agency officials must now decide whether to issue a rule that would permit the ingredient, phenylpropanolamine, to remain over the counter, or restrict it to prescription drugs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A panel of scientific experts recommended today that a common ingredient in decongestants and appetite suppressants be removed from over-the-counter products, citing new evidence that the chemical may increase the risk of stroke in young women.</p>
        <p>The panel's recommendation to the Food and Drug Administration is not binding, although the agency usually follows the recommendations of its outside experts. Agency officials must now decide whether to issue a rule that would permit the ingredient, phenylpropanolamine, to remain over the counter, or restrict it to prescription drugs.</p>
        <p>Phenylpropanolamine, or PPA, has been used for more than 50 years, primarily in nonprescription cold and cough remedies as well as in appetite suppressants and some prescription decongestants. Dozens of medicines contain PPA, including certain Alka-Selter, Dimetapp, Robitussin and Triaminic products as well as some intended for children. The agency said six billion doses were sold last year alone.</p>
        <p>In a series of votes, an overwhelming majority of the 14-member panel concluded that while the risk of stroke among women ages 18 to 49 taking phenylpropanolamine was small, it was significant. So the panel decided the ingredient could no longer be ''generally recognized as safe,'' which is the food and drug agency's requirement for drugs that can be bought without a doctor's prescription.</p>
        <p>''It did not meet the burden of proof for safety,'' said Dr. Eric Brass, chairman of the panel of independent experts.</p>
        <p>After listening to researchers at Yale University present the results of a new, five-year study on phenylpropanolamine and stroke, Dr. Brass said he and the other agency advisers had ''serious safety concerns.'' The Yale study found an increased risk of a certain type of stroke, hemorrhagic stroke, among women who had taken appetite suppressants containing phenylpropanolamine, and among women who were first-time users of the drug.</p>
        <p>''The message for women should be that PPA does appear to be associated with an increased risk of hemorrhagic stroke, but it's not a huge risk,'' said Dr. Walter Kernan, an associate professor of medicine at Yale who led the study.</p>
        <p>But scientists who spoke on behalf of the nonprescription drug industry today insisted that the $5 million Yale study, which was paid for by their own trade group, was flawed.</p>
        <p>''Our members stand behind PPA as safe and effective products when used according to label directions,'' said Dr. R. William Soller, senior vice president of the trade group, the Consumer Healthcare Products Association.</p>
        <p>Staff scientists at the Food and Drug Administration, however, were not convinced by the Yale study. The agency's staff has estimated that phenylpropanolamine is responsible for 200 to 500 strokes each year in people ages 18 to 49, primarily women and first-time users of the drug.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert DeLap of the Food and Drug Administration's Center for Drug Evaluation and Research, could not say when a decision on phenylpropanolamine would be made. And if a rule is issued, it would be open to public comment and would likely be challenged by drug makers.</p>
        <p>Phenylpropanolamine is the active ingredient in 35 brand-name medicines as well as some generic cold remedies and appetite suppressants under the Dexatrim and Acutrim names. Should the agency decide to ban the ingredient in nonprescription drugs, it is possible that manufacturers could reformulate their products or seek approval for them as prescription medications.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Dr. DeLap urged consumers to ''carefully read the label on the packages of these products.'' Dr. Brass, who is also chairman of the department of medicine at Harbor-U.C.L.A. Medical Center in Torrance, Calif., went one step further, saying, ''If asked by one of my patients, I would recommend that they try alternative products rather than phenylpropanolamine.''</p>
        <p>While there are alternative cold and cough remedies, including products that use pseudoephedrine as the active ingredient, every appetite suppressant sold over the counter contains phenylpropanolamine.</p>
        <p>The F.D.A. has been receiving reports for decades that some patients taking phenylpropanolamine suffered hemorrhagic stroke, a relatively uncommon type of stroke caused by bleeding in the brain, as opposed to ischemic stroke, caused by a cutoff of blood to the brain. Since 1969, the year it began keeping track, the agency has received 44 such reports.</p>
        <p>''The figure of 44 is literally the very tip of the iceberg,'' Dr. Lois La Grenade, the food and drug agency official who analyzed the reports, told the committee.</p>
        <p>The typical stroke victim in these cases, Dr. La Grenade told the committee, was an otherwise healthy young person, most often a woman or a first-time user of phenylpropanolamine. Within a few days, with no warning, the patient would suffer a hemorrhagic stroke, leading to either permanent disability or death.</p>
        <p>Scientists do not know why the ingredient might cause a stroke, although they said its effect on blood pressure might play a role.</p>
        <p>Despite these reports, the agency has allowed the ingredient to remain on the market, saying research about its risks was inconclusive.</p>
        <p>The Yale epidemiologic study, which took five years to complete, did not prove cause and effect, but rather examined the link between phenylpropanolamine and hemorrhagic stroke. It compared 702 patients, ages 18 to 49, who suffered hemorrhagic stroke to 1376 people in a control group. Although the study included men, there were too few who both used phenylpropanolamine and suffered strokes to draw any conclusions about the risks in men.</p>
        <p>But among women, the study found the risk of hemorrhagic stroke was as much as 15 times higher for those who had taken appetite suppressants in the three days before the stroke. Among women using any phenylpropanolamine product for the first time, the risk of hemorrhagic stroke was three times higher than for other women.</p>
        <p>Hemorrhagic stroke is relatively rare among young people -- the food and drug agency says 8 out of 100,000 people ages 18 to 49 suffer these strokes each year -- and so the absolute number of phenylpropanolamine-related strokes among women in the Yale study was small.</p>
        <p>A panel of prominent scientists, hired by the Consumer Healthcare Products Association to review the  study, challenged its findings. The study has not yet been published in an academic journal and so has not gone through the rigorous scientific examination known as peer review.</p>
        <p>''This is a failed study,'' declared a member of the trade group's panel, Dr. Lewis Kuller, an epidemiologist at the University of Pittsburgh. He and the other members argued that the study contained too few patients to be statistically significant and that the strokes in people taking phenylpropanolamine could have been caused by factors like drug abuse and excessive caffeine consumption.</p>
        <p>But Dr. La Grenade said the agency had conducted its own analysis of the raw data submitted by Yale, and agreed with the Yale conclusions. Several members of the expert panel said today that while the Yale study might be imperfect, any flaws were due to the inherent difficulties of conducting such research.</p>
        <p>List of Over-the-Counter Products With PPA</p>
        <p>The Consumer Healthcare Products Association said yesterday that these products contained phenylpropanolamine, or PPA, the chemical that an F.D.A. advisory panel said could increase the risk of stroke among young women. The chemical is also in similar products marketed by many drug store and supermarket chains as house brands.</p>
        <p>AcuTrim Diet Gum Appetite Suppressant Plus Dietary Supplements; Acutrim Maximum Strength Appetite Control.</p>
        <p>Alka-Seltzer Plus Children's Cold Medicine Effervescent; Alka-Seltzer Plus Cold Medicine (Cherry or orange flavor); Alka-Seltzer Plus Cold Medicine Original; Alka-Seltzer Plus Cold &amp; Cough Medicine Effervescent; Alka-Seltzer Plus Cold &amp; Flu Medicine Effervescent; Alka-Seltzer Plus Cold &amp; Sinus Effervescent; Alka-Seltzer Plus Night-Time Cold Medicine Effervescent;</p>
        <p>BC Allergy Sinus Cold Powder; BC Sinus Cold Powder;</p>
        <p>Comtrex Deep Chest Cold &amp; Congestion Relief; Comtrex Flu Therapy &amp; Fever Relief Day &amp; Night;</p>
        <p>Contac 12 Hour Cold Capsules; Contac 12 Hour Cold Caplets;</p>
        <p>Coricidin 'D' Cold, Flu &amp; Sinus;</p>
        <p>Dexatrim Caffeine Free; Dexatrim Extended Duration; Dextrim Gelcaps; Dexatrim Vitamin C/Caffeine Free  Dimetapp Cold &amp; Allergy Chewable Tablets;</p>
        <p>Dimetapp Cold &amp; Cough Liqui-Gels; Dimetapp DM Cold &amp; Cough Elixir; Dimetapp Elixir; Dimetapp 4-Hour Liqui-Gels; Dimetapp 4-Hour Tablets; Dimetapp 12-Hour Extentabs Tablets;</p>
        <p>Naldecon DX Pediatric Drops;</p>
        <p>Permathene Mega-16;</p>
        <p>Robitussin CF;</p>
        <p>Tavist-D 12 Hour Relief of Sinus &amp; Nasal Congrestion;</p>
        <p>Triaminic DM Cough Relief; Triaminic Expectorant Chest &amp; Head Congestion; Triaminic Syrup Cold &amp; Allergy, and Triaminic Triaminicol Cold &amp; Cough.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 21, 2000, Saturday  Because of an editing error, a front-page article yesterday about a Yale University study linking risk of stroke to an ingredient in some decongestants and appetite suppressants referred incorrectly at one point to the position of staff scientists at the Food and Drug Administration. While scientists speaking for the nonprescription drug industry disputed the study, F.D.A. scientists indeed found the study convincing, in part because of their own estimates that the ingredient was responsible for 200 to 500 strokes a year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 21, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a front-page article yesterday about a Yale University study linking risk of stroke to an ingredient in some decongestants and appetite suppressants referred incorrectly at one point to the position of staff scientists at the Food and Drug Administration. While scientists speaking for the nonprescription drug industry disputed the study, F.D.A. scientists indeed found the study convincing, in part because of their own estimates that the ingredient was responsible for 200 to 500 strokes a year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
