<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Buffett Shows Gillette's Chief the Door</title>
    <meta content="Y20RAZO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/business/20RAZO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gillette Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonhardt, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buffett, Warren E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hawley, Michael C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Degraan, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E7D7133EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="926" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Buffett Shows Gillette's Chief the Door</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leonhardt, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Warren E. Buffett, a board member, personally asks for--and receives--resignation of Gillette Co's chief executive, Michael C Hawley, on the day that company announces yet another disappointing quarter of earnings; Gillette's stock, which has fallen more than 50 percent in last two year, rises 15 percent; company's president, Edward F DeGraan, is named acting chief executive; company says it earned $350 million on $2.32 billion in sales in third quarter, drop of 1 percent in sales and profits; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Warren E. Buffett, the world's most famous long-term investor, finally lost patience with Gillette yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buffett, a board member, personally asked for -- and received -- the resignation of Gillette's chief executive, Michael C. Hawley, on the day that the company announced yet another disappointing quarter of earnings. With Gillette troubled by currency problems in Europe and mediocre results from its Duracell battery division, its stock has fallen more than 50 percent in the last two years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Warren E. Buffett, the world's most famous long-term investor, finally lost patience with Gillette yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buffett, a board member, personally asked for -- and received -- the resignation of Gillette's chief executive, Michael C. Hawley, on the day that the company announced yet another disappointing quarter of earnings. With Gillette troubled by currency problems in Europe and mediocre results from its Duracell battery division, its stock has fallen more than 50 percent in the last two years.</p>
        <p>Edward F. DeGraan, the company's president and a 32-year employee who has overseen all of Gillette's businesses since July, became acting chief executive, the board announced. The company said that it would hire a search firm to evaluate both external and internal candidates, including Mr. DeGraan, to replace Mr. Hawley, 62, who joined Gillette in 1961 and took over the top job in April 1999.</p>
        <p>''We thought there was someone better to do the job,'' said Mr. Buffett, who owns a large stake in the company, during a conference call yesterday. He declined to criticize any of Mr. Hawley's decisions and said the stock decline was not a factor in the board's decision. Instead, Mr. Buffett compared Mr. Hawley to a ''very, very good'' hitter in baseball with a .320 batting average and said the board would now look for someone who could hit .360 or .370.</p>
        <p>Investors were less charitable. Within minutes of the company's 1:30 p.m. announcement of Mr. Hawley's resignation, the stock began climbing sharply and finished the day at $32.63, up $4.31, or 15 percent. In effect, the company gained more than $4 billion in market capitalization because of Mr. Hawley's dismissal, analysts said.</p>
        <p>The company, which is based in Boston and employs 40,000 people worldwide, also reported that sales and profits both fell about 1 percent in the third quarter. Gillette earned $350 million on $2.32 billion in sales. The earnings were in line with analysts' expectations, but only because the company had warned analysts last month to lower their forecasts.</p>
        <p>Gillette becomes the third giant consumer products company recently to replace a chief executive with less than two years on the job. In June, Durk I. Jager, the head of Procter &amp; Gamble, stepped down, and M. Douglas Ivester, Coca-Cola's chief, resigned abruptly in December. Mr. Buffett also serves on the board of Coke.</p>
        <p>All three companies were favorites of the stock market for much of the 1990's, thanks largely to brands with global recognition that few rivals can approach. Gillette -- quarter after quarter, for nearly a decade -- reported earnings per share that were at least 10 percent higher than the previous year's.</p>
        <p>Lately, however, the consumer companies have suffered from a weak euro, which has caused profits from European operations to suffer after being converted into American dollars. About two-thirds of Gillette's revenue comes from abroad.</p>
        <p>The companies have also found themselves largely unable to raise prices in the United States because of competition from imports and the bargaining power of retailers, which have consolidated in recent years.</p>
        <p>Gillette tried to find a new source of profits in 1996 by buying Duracell, the battery company, for $7 billion. Executives planned to use their marketing expertise to come up with high-priced products, just as they persuaded millions of men to buy new, more expensive razors that caused fewer cuts, according to the company's advertisements.</p>
        <p>In 1998, for instance, Gillette introduced the Mach 3 razor, which is widely considered a success.</p>
        <p>The company seemed to repeat the formula with batteries, creating a product called the Ultra and advertising it as lasting longer than other brands. Over the last year, the Ultra's sales have almost doubled, according to Information Resources Inc., a market research firm in Chicago.</p>
        <p>At the same time, however, the nation's second- and third-largest battery companies -- Energizer and Rayovac -- responded by cutting prices on their basic brands, causing many customers to switch from Duracell's copper-and-gold brand.</p>
        <p>''Duracell has been a real disappointment,'' said Lewis Piantedosi, a vice president at Eaton Vance Management, a Boston investment firm that owns Gillette shares. ''The core copper-and-black has lost more market share than the Ultra has gained.''</p>
        <p>Daniel Peris, an analyst at Argus Research, added that most people saw no difference between the basic brands of the three companies. Consumers, he said, are less loyal to  products they put in their electronic gadgets than to ones they drag across their faces or legs.</p>
        <p>For the first nine months of the year, Duracell's profits declined 26 percent, the company said. Gillette also sells Oral-B dental products and Braun shaving products. Under Mr. Hawley, the company sold its pen and shampoo divisions.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeGraan, who is 57, took over the battery business when Gillette bought it in 1996. The company added razors to his portfolio in 1999 and promoted him to president in July of this year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
