<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Republican Poverty Victim; Years of Political Work Get Little for Senate Candidate</title>
    <meta content="20FRAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/politics/20FRAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240259"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barry, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franks, Bob (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E1D6133EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Republican Poverty Victim; Years of Political Work Get Little for Senate Candidate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barry, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>SOUTH ORANGE, N.J., Oct. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Repr Bob Franks, Republican candidate for US Senate in New Jersey, remains little known despite 30 years of work in state politics; his wealthy Democratic opponent, Jon Corzine, is known by more than 90% of voters; Corzine has spent more than $50 million, while Franks has raised roughly $4.3 million; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a high school student during the psychedelic Sixties, he earnestly asked classmates to focus long enough to become Young Republicans. As a seven-term assemblyman and state party chairman, he played a role in so many Republican campaigns that ''trusted lieutenant'' became his honorific. As a congressman, he signed the Contract with America and voted for the impeachment of President Clinton.</p>
        <p>For more than 30 years, Bob Franks has been working the room known as New Jersey, preaching the Republican world view, exuding empathy and eating enough pigs-in-a-blanket to give a gastroenterologist pause -- all for this moment: The Next Step. Few would argue against the notion that Mr. Franks has earned his shot at the United States Senate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As a high school student during the psychedelic Sixties, he earnestly asked classmates to focus long enough to become Young Republicans. As a seven-term assemblyman and state party chairman, he played a role in so many Republican campaigns that ''trusted lieutenant'' became his honorific. As a congressman, he signed the Contract with America and voted for the impeachment of President Clinton.</p>
        <p>For more than 30 years, Bob Franks has been working the room known as New Jersey, preaching the Republican world view, exuding empathy and eating enough pigs-in-a-blanket to give a gastroenterologist pause -- all for this moment: The Next Step. Few would argue against the notion that Mr. Franks has earned his shot at the United States Senate.</p>
        <p>And wouldn't you know it? Just as Mr. Franks begins calling in decades of political chits, a man he knows only in passing -- some bond trader who attends the very same church in Summit -- decides that he, too, wants to run for the Senate. And that bond trader, a Democrat named Jon S. Corzine, is wealthy enough to use C-notes for Kleenex; he has already spent more than $50 million on the race, the largest amount ever spent on a statewide campaign.</p>
        <p>That we are all equal in the eyes of the Lord may not bring much comfort to Mr. Franks these days. Thanks to his opponent's liberal spending, more than 90 percent of the state knows the Corzine name, and voters cannot avoid him if they want to: his smiling face is on their televisions, on their commuter buses, in their mailboxes and probably in their dreams.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Franks has raised roughly $4.3 million. There have been no statewide mailings, no bus placards, and no radio. This week, with less than three weeks left until Election Day, the Franks campaign ran its first television ad in the New York City media market -- for a candidate whose name is vague to many of the state's voters and who trails his opponent by at least 10 points in several recent polls.</p>
        <p>What is the reaction of Mr. Franks to all this? The same as that of a battered bantamweight peering through swollen eyes at his preening opponent: I got him right where I want him.</p>
        <p>Working yet another spare crowd at yet another small-time fund-raiser Tuesday night, this one at a supporter's home here in South Orange, Mr. Franks shook the ice in an otherwise empty plastic cup and favorably interpreted what others might consider distressing polling results.</p>
        <p>After all that exposure and all that money spent, polls suggest that Mr. Corzine still has not earned the support of half the electorate, Mr. Franks said with feigned disbelief. ''He's probably achieved as much favorable impact with his money as possible and he's stuck in the mid-40's.''</p>
        <p>That means that when the Franks campaign essentially introduces Bob Franks to the electorate through last-minute television advertising, he said emphatically, ''We will defeat Jon Corzine.''</p>
        <p>Gerald M. Pomper, a political science professor at the Eagleton Institute of Politics at Rutgers University -- whose polls conducted with The Star-Ledger of Newark show Mr. Franks trailing by 12 points among registered voters -- said that he understood Mr. Franks's self-preserving point of view.</p>
        <p>''You're spending 12 to 16 hours a day in a very overwrought situation, you're spending your own money for sure, you're eating terribly and you're surrounded by people who say they love you,'' he said. ''It's hard to believe that the rest of the state doesn't love you.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pomper emphasized that he was not ruling out a Franks victory entirely, since there is always the chance for the lucky punch of politics. But that punch is usually delivered with either a single galvanizing issue or the underdog candidate's sheer charisma -- dynamics that he said are lacking in New Jersey at the moment.</p>
        <p>In addition, the outrage that Mr. Franks frequently expresses over the amount of money that Mr. Corzine has spent is not shared by most New Jersey voters, Mr. Pomper said, a point supported by a New York Times poll released this week. Besides, Mr. Franks ''is basically a moderate kind of Republican, a decent kind of guy, not charismatic, not magnetic,'' he said. ''You have to have something exciting when you're running against $50 million.''</p>
        <p>The many years that Mr. Franks, 49, spent as the dutiful Republican soldier, the kudos he received for leading his party to victory in the early 1990's, the sage advice he gave to Thomas H. Kean and other New Jersey Republican stalwarts -- all of it is a distant memory in 2000, a year when the strange political moons over New Jersey seem not to be aligning in his favor.</p>
        <p>His race comes in a presidential election year, and Vice President Al Gore is expected to carry New Jersey easily, which can only help his fellow Democrat, Mr. Corzine. In addition, the out-of-state contributions that Mr. Franks might have received are being sent to Representative Rick A. Lazio, a Republican in neighboring New York who is fighting Hillary Rodham Clinton, the favored motivational tool for Republican fund-raisers everywhere.</p>
        <p>And the problems of Mr. Franks go beyond money. New Jersey is becoming an increasingly Democratic state and has not elected a Republican senator since Clifford P. Case won a fourth term in 1972.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks is also campaigning for the Senate in a state where the two political parties are more interested in the race for governor, which is not until next year. A senator sits in an office many miles from the southernmost rest stop on the Garden State Parkway and has only a few jobs to hand out, while the governor has hundreds of jobs and appointments to dispense. Some would-be donors might reason a wiser investment would be in that annual ball thrown by the State Senate president, Donald T. DiFrancesco -- a likely gubernatorial candidate -- than in cheese cubes and boxed wine at some Franks event.</p>
        <p>''There's no patronage mill'' in the Senate, explained Mr. Franks, with a rueful smile earned from having spent more than a decade in Trenton. ''People are gearing up for a very competitive gubernatorial race.''</p>
        <p>Finally, there is Mr. Corzine, whose personal wealth financed an early advertising blitz that not only portrayed the Democrat as a well-intentioned liberal on the side of seniors and the middle class but painted Mr. Franks as a craven Newt Gingrich acolyte.</p>
        <p>''Corzine beat him to the punch with criticisms,'' explained David P. Rebovich, a political science professor at Rider University. ''Many people are getting to know Bob Franks not by his own positive ads, but by the critical ads from Corzine's campaign.''</p>
        <p>''The Corzine campaign will spend whatever it takes to close out the race,'' Mr. Rebovich said. ''With $50 million already sunk into the election, what's another $15 million?''</p>
        <p>The failure of Mr. Franks to raise anywhere near the $7 million that political analysts say is needed to run an effective campaign is particularly troubling, they say, given that New Jersey is among the richest states in the union.</p>
        <p>''It is astounding to me that a Republican candidate who was a leader in the Assembly, a state chairman and a congressman for four terms has not been able to raise more money in a state which is moneybags for candidates all over the country,'' said Stephen A. Salmore, a Republican consultant and retired political science professor.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Franks refuses to complain. ''Once you enter a race, you want to prevail,'' he said. ''I've watched the last five, six, seven Republicans running for the Senate lose. I believe we're getting it right despite the unique characteristics of Mr. Corzine's campaign.'' (Read: head-spinning spending.)</p>
        <p>He said he is proud of his ''no-frills'' campaign, one in which lawn signs used during the Republican primary in June were reclaimed for use in the fall. So what if he has been able to afford only two helicopter rides to traverse the state, while Mr. Corzine has an airplane at his disposal? So what if he has to spend much of the campaign's final weeks attending small fund-raisers, while his opponent can concentrate on better ways to spread his message?</p>
        <p>Actually, that last point is a sore one. On Tuesday, for example, he had to drive to Greenwich, Conn., for a quick fund-raiser. ''I need to go to Greenwich to raise the money to pay for the ads to reach more people,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He says he sees himself squarely in the race, and constantly reminds people that many New Jersey voters traditionally make up their minds in the last days of a campaign. In fact, he takes comfort in the large number of undecided voters who don't know much about him or his policies.</p>
        <p>''We are yet to begin our New York ad campaign,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In a twist on political stereotypes, he holds himself out as a grass-roots campaigner, even though he represents the Republican establishment down to the lapel buttons in his sober-blue shirts. At the same time, he tries to portray Mr. Corzine as the corporate behemoth, even though the Democrat espouses exceptionally liberal social policies.</p>
        <p>''It's sort of a confusing image: Republican as victim,'' Mr. Rebovich said. ''At the same time, he brags about his 20 years in politics, his great political resume, his influence in Washington. You can't have it both ways.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Rebovich and other consultants said they would understand if Mr. Franks privately harbored resentment these days. After all, they said, Mr. Corzine spent his money to secure the support of county committees, win the Democratic primary and dominate the Senate race, while Mr. Franks adhered to the rules and caste systems of party politics.</p>
        <p>''Twenty years of hard work, shaking hands, kissing babies,'' Mr. Rebovich said. ''For what?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
