<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="CRAP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240372"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E5DB103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="579" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS--Announced the resignation of John McNamara, major league roving catcher instructor.  SEATTLE MARINERS--Called up RHP Ryan Franklin from Tacoma of the PCL. Sent INF Carlos Hernandez and RHP Ken Cloude to Tacoma. Signed RHP Kenny Rayborn and OF Chad Alexander to minor league contracts.  National League  ATLANTA BRAVES--Named Scott Nethery special assistant to the general manager.  ARIZONA DIAMONDBACKS--Announced Mel Didier, senior assistant to the general manager, has resigned effective at the end of the year.  ST. LOUIS CARDINALS--Signed RHP Darryl Kile to a three-year contract extension, through 2003.  LOS ANGELES DODGERS--Re-signed INF Dave Hansen to a one-year contract.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS--Announced the resignation of John McNamara, major league roving catcher instructor.  SEATTLE MARINERS--Called up RHP Ryan Franklin from Tacoma of the PCL. Sent INF Carlos Hernandez and RHP Ken Cloude to Tacoma. Signed RHP Kenny Rayborn and OF Chad Alexander to minor league contracts.  National League  ATLANTA BRAVES--Named Scott Nethery special assistant to the general manager.  ARIZONA DIAMONDBACKS--Announced Mel Didier, senior assistant to the general manager, has resigned effective at the end of the year.  ST. LOUIS CARDINALS--Signed RHP Darryl Kile to a three-year contract extension, through 2003.  LOS ANGELES DODGERS--Re-signed INF Dave Hansen to a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL  National Basketball Association  CHICAGO BULLS--Signed C Jake Voskuhl.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL  Arena Football League  AFL--Announced the relocation of the Albany Firebirds to Indianapolis. The team will be named the Indiana Firebirds and will begin competing in April, 2001.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY  National Hockey League  NHL--Suspended Washington Capitals LW Richard Zednik for four games and fined him $1,000 for a cross-checking incident in a game against the Colorado Avalanche on Oct. 17.  BUFFALO SABRES--Assigned G Mika Noronen to Rochester of the AHL. Recalled G Peter Skudra from Rochester.  CAROLINA HURRICANES--Recalled D Mike Rucinski and D Greg Kuznik from Cincinnati of the IHL. Placed D Niclas Wallin and D Marek Malik on the injured reserve list.  NEW YORK RANGERS--Announced D Jason Doig cleared waivers and sent him to Hartford of the AHL. Reassigned D David Wilkie to Houston of the IHL and G Jason LaBarbera to Hartford.  VANCOUVER CANUCKS-- Placed D Mattias Ohlund on injured reserve. Recalled D Bryan Helmer from Kansas City of the IHL. Reassigned D Brent Sopel to Kansas City.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE  CENTRAL IOWA--Announced the retirement of Gary Boeyink, women's basketball coach, at the end of this season.  SACRED HEART--Named Michael Barrett women's ice hockey coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
