<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 MANUFACTURERS ARE SET TO MERGE IN $40 BILLION DEAL</title>
    <meta content="20MERG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/business/20MERG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Honeywell International</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Technologies Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Otis Elevator Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pratt &amp; Whitney</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sikorsky Aircraft Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deutsch, Claudia H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">David, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E4DF103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1334" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 MANUFACTURERS ARE SET TO MERGE IN $40 BILLION DEAL</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN and CLAUDIA H. DEUTSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Deutsch, Claudia H; Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Technologies Corp, one of the last old-style conglomerates, is expected to buy Honeywell International Inc for about $40.3 billion in stock; acquisition would create industrial behemoth, bringing together United Technologies' Otis Elevators, Pratt &amp; Whitney aircraft engines, Sikorsky helicopters and Carrier air-conditioners with Honeywell's aerospace systems, power and transportation products, specialty chemicals and home security systems; George David, chief executive of United Technologies, is expected to head combined company; his photo; charts profile two companies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United Technologies Corporation, one of the last old-style conglomerates that makes everything from jet engines to elevators, is expected to buy Honeywell International Inc. for about $40.3 billion in stock, according to executives close to the talks.</p>
        <p>Both boards are planning to meet today, the executives said. The companies acknowledged late yesterday that they were in talks, but declined to comment further. The executives said the companies hoped to announce the deal as early as today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United Technologies Corporation, one of the last old-style conglomerates that makes everything from jet engines to elevators, is expected to buy Honeywell International Inc. for about $40.3 billion in stock, according to executives close to the talks.</p>
        <p>Both boards are planning to meet today, the executives said. The companies acknowledged late yesterday that they were in talks, but declined to comment further. The executives said the companies hoped to announce the deal as early as today.</p>
        <p>The acquisition would create an industrial behemoth, bringing together United Technologies' Otis Elevators, Pratt &amp; Whitney aircraft engines, Sikorsky helicopters and Carrier air-conditioners, with Honeywell's aerospace systems, power and transportation products, specialty chemicals and home security systems.</p>
        <p>Last year, Honeywell merged with Allied Signal.</p>
        <p>The combined concern, which merges two Dow Jones industrial companies, is expected to take the Honeywell name and have its headquarters in New York, New Jersey or Connecticut, the executives said, though it remains unclear where it will be based. The executives suggested that the headquarters would not be in Hartford, where United Technologies is based, or in Morristown, N.J., where Honeywell is based.</p>
        <p>According to the executives, United Technologies has offered about 0.74 of a share, or $50.32, for each of the about 801 million outstanding shares of Honeywell, making the total purchase price $40.3 billion. That is a 39 percent premium above Honeywell's close yesterday of $36.13, up $2.44. Shares of United Technologies closed down 38 cents at $68.</p>
        <p>George David, the chairman and chief executive of United Technologies, would be chief executive of the combined company, while Honeywell's chairman and chief executive, Michael Bonsignore, would become chairman, the executives said.</p>
        <p>The companies hope to save about $1 billion annually by combining, the executives said, and add as much as 25 cents a share to earnings the first year after the merger.</p>
        <p>Although analysts had not predicted the deal, few were surprised by it. Wall Street had for some time been expecting United Technologies to announce an acquisition, and Honeywell's name has often made it onto the short list of possibilities. Honeywell has had a rough year both in terms of stock price and earnings, and several analysts have said it was vulnerable to takeover.</p>
        <p>The two companies have many overlapping businesses. United Technologies makes Carrier heating and air-conditioning systems; Honeywell makes thermostats and other climate control devices. United is in the process of forming a distributed power business; Honeywell already makes microturbines. United Technologies owns Otis elevators and escalators; Honeywell is big in building control systems. United Technologies makes Sikorsky helicopters; Honeywell is a big supplier of avionics and helicopter engines.</p>
        <p>''They are both major players in the same industries, and while there's lots of overlap in customers, there is surprisingly little overlap in their products,'' said one analyst who covers both companies.</p>
        <p>Honeywell and United Technologies' Pratt &amp; Whitney both make aircraft engines, of course, but while United Technologies is strong in the commercial airline market, Honeywell's strength is business jets. And, because replacement parts -- a very lucrative business -- are not interchangeable, they do not compete there. In fact, the two companies recently formed a joint Web site, Myaircraft.com, that enables their customers to buy technical information, use inventory control software and buy parts.</p>
        <p>''There are enormous operating and marketing synergies across a host of product lines, from small aircraft engines to air-conditioning controls,'' said Howard A. Rubel, an analyst with Goldman, Sachs.</p>
        <p>The expected merger comes less than 17 months after Honeywell was formed, the product of a merger between Honeywell Inc., a Minneapolis-based maker of electronic controls, and the Allied Signal Corporation, a diversified manufacturer in Morristown. Although Allied was by far the larger partner, the merged company kept the Honeywell name and named Mr. Bonsignore, Honeywell's chief, as its chief executive.</p>
        <p>But Honeywell has traveled a rocky path since then. The weak euro has pummeled its earnings, while the softening economy has put pressure on sales. Moreover, Honeywell has a large chemicals operation that has been badly hit by rising oil prices.</p>
        <p>It has also had trouble merging the disparate cultures of the two companies. Allied had for years been run by Lawrence Bossidy, a strong-willed executive who was groomed by John F. Welch at General Electric and had much of Mr. Welch's take-no-prisoners style. Honeywell people were used to a more relaxed, Midwestern and courtly management style.</p>
        <p>Analysts say Mr. Bonsignore has not been able to create a seamless whole out of such disparate parts. In fact, Wall Street has been speculating that Honeywell's board was looking to replace Mr. Bonsignore. One name that kept arising was that of Robert L. Nardelli, one of the contenders to succeed Mr. Welch as chairman of G. E.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bonsignore inherited some of the company's problems. Before the merger, Allied had invested heavily in pharmaceutical and chip-packaging businesses, both of which have been bottom-line disasters.</p>
        <p>But the merged company has also had disappointing growth in industrial controls and fire security systems, two businesses that the old Honeywell brought to the party. And it has not been able to offset tripling oil prices with price and volume increases in its chemicals businesses.</p>
        <p>Several analysts say the merged company has been marred by infighting, as each side tries to blame the other for this year's worsening numbers. In many ways, they say, that chaos may make the current merger with United Technologies more workable.</p>
        <p>''No new Honeywell identity has emerged as yet, so it won't be a melding of two strong cultures,'' one analyst said. ''George may just come in there and say, 'All right, kids, enough now, stop fighting,' '' referring to Mr. David, the United Technologies chief.</p>
        <p>He is widely regarded, both on Wall Street and among many management experts, as up there with Mr. Welch and Mr. Bossidy as among America's best chief executives. But unlike those men, both of whom are known for their brusque styles, Mr. David is someone who can win over customers and employees alike with a combination of charm and knowledge.</p>
        <p>He is also credited with turning United Technologies into a lean, cost- effective company that has enjoyed six continuous years of double-digit earnings growth.</p>
        <p>''George is a C.E.O. out of central casting,'' Mr. Rubel of Goldman, Sachs said. ''He's articulate; he understands customer problem;, he's aggressive; he's forward thinking; and he earns the respect of his competitors.''</p>
        <p>Actually, both companies have been promising double-digit sales and earnings growth for this year and next. Investors just seem to believe United Technologies, though -- its stock has held firm, even inched up steadily, despite the recent market turbulence, while Honeywell's has taken a beating in the last few months.</p>
        <p>Still, according to Charles L. Hill, research director at First Call/ Thomson Financial, analysts have strong buy recommendations on both stocks. He does note, however, that while analysts keep strengthening their recommendations on United Technologies, they have added caveats to their recommendations in light of Honeywell's lackluster earnings this year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
