<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="20MBRF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/nyregion/20MBRF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001102T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E6DD103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1014" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: JUDGE TO REHEAR INTERNET CASE -- Oliver Jovanovic, who won a retrial on charges of kidnapping and assaulting a woman he met on the Internet, must go before the same judge who improperly excluded evidence in the first trial, an appeals court ruled yesterday.  In December an appeals court overturned the conviction, criticizing the trial judge, William A. Wetzel, for preventing the jury from seeing e-mail messages in which the woman expressed interest in sadomasochism. She later accused Mr. Jovanovic of having tortured her for 20 hours. The decision yesterday did not explain why Mr. Jovanovic could not have another trial judge.</p>
        <p>Laura Mansnerus (NYT)</p>
        <p>SCHENECTADY: NEW LOTTERY MACHINES -- New York lottery fans, brace yourselves. As of tomorrow, new machines will be used for mixing and picking some of the winning numbers. The new machines will work the same way as the old ones. The difference is seven machines will be replaced by two: One with three chambers for Numbers, the three-number lottery, and one with four chambers for Win 4. A third machine, which has been used to pick Take 5, Lotto and Pick 10, will not change.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: SUIT AGAINST YANKEES DISMISSED -- A federal judge yesterday dismissed a racial discrimination lawsuit against the New York Yankees. V. Whitney Joseph had alleged in her lawsuit that the Stadium Club, a restaurant in Yankee Stadium, had discriminated against her because she is black. On July 20, 1998, she said, she was barred from the club because she was wearing a tank top, a violation of the club's posted dress code. When she changed into a T-shirt, she was admitted, but said she then saw white women there wearing tank tops. Judge Sidney H. Stein ruled that Ms. Joseph had failed to allege ''a likelihood of future harm,'' a necessary condition for the suit to go forward.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>MINEOLA: MONEY FOR SUPERFUND URGED -- Environmental groups called on elected officials yesterday to refinance the New York State Superfund, a toxic-site cleanup program that has run out of money. The state program, which was created in 1982 to clean up toxic dumps and spills not covered by the federal Superfund program, is run by the Department of Environmental Conservation. Jennifer Post, a spokeswoman for the department, confirmed yesterday that 790 toxic sites in the state lack the money to be cleaned up. Todd Stebbins, Long Island regional director for New York Public Interest Research Group, said 124 of these sites are on Long Island, where drinking water is threatened.</p>
        <p>Tara Bahrampour (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: TRASH CUSTOMERS DROPPED -- Waste Management has won permission from the city to follow through on its plan to eliminate unprofitable routes by dropping about 3,000 customers, about 10 percent of its  customer base. The Trade Waste Commission had ordered the company to halt its move after some of its approximately 3,300 affected customers complained that Waste Management was disregarding written contracts. The company has agreed to honor about 315  contracts, with the service for the remaining 3,000 to be  cut off Nov. 1, city officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Eric Lipton (NYT)</p>
        <p>QUEENS: LIBRARIANS SEEK RAISES -- Librarians demanding a pay increase demonstrated yesterday outside a trustees meeting of the Queens Central Library. The librarians, members of the Queensboro Library Guild, part of District Council 37, said the library should use the $2.6 million that the City Council restored to the library's budget to increase salaries. The union said about one-fourth of Queens librarians quit last year to take higher-paying jobs.</p>
        <p>Steven Greenhouse (NYT)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>FAIRFIELD: MOLD CLOSES SCHOOL -- McKinley Elementary School has been closed indefinitely while health officials investigate air quality problems believed responsible for making students sick. The decision to shut the school was made Wednesday night. McKinley will not be reopened until doctors from the University of Connecticut  Medical Center and a Maine company that specializes in building science, figure out how to rid the school of high mold spore levels. Dr. Eileen Storey of the university  said McKinley has ''mold that is beyond what we want to see.'' She said it was still unclear how dangerous the mold was but added the school had to be closed and cleaned.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>TRENTON: PRE-TEENAGE DRUG USE -- Fewer middle school students around the state are smoking marijuana and drinking alcohol, a survey found. The survey also found that students who talk regularly to their parents are less likely to drink or use drugs. The survey, conducted among seventh and eighth graders without teachers present, found that 9 percent of students reported having smoked marijuana within the past year, down from 11 percent in 1998, and 13 percent from 1995, the first year the Partnership for a Drug Free New Jersey did the survey. Alcohol use was down to 41 percent from 49 in 1995.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>SPRINGFIELD: AUTO DEALERS SETTLE CHARGES -- A group of five auto dealerships has agreed to pay more than $200,000 in prosecution costs and restitution to customers to settle complaints of unfair practices, the state attorney general's office announced yesterday. The 73 complaints against Toresco Auto Group, which includes the sprawling Autoland dealership on Route 22 in Springfield, involved allegations that dealers failed to refund deposits and used bait-and-switch tactics, said Jennifer Doktorski, a spokeswoman for the attorney general. Toresco did not admit any wrongdoing. Toresco's lawyer, Theodore Schiller, said the number of complaints,  dating from 1993 to 1999, was negligible compared with the 149,000 sales and thousands of repairs by the dealers during that time.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>CALENDAR</p>
        <p>Monday</p>
        <p>HEARING ON SIGHTSEEING BUSES -- The City Council plans to take testimony from city officials and private companies on a proposed change in city law requiring sightseeing companies to ensure that their buses comply with emissions standards. Council Chambers, City Hall, Manhattan, 10 am. Information: (212) 788-7210.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: JUDGE TO REHEAR INTERNET CASE -- Oliver Jovanovic, who won a retrial on charges of kidnapping and assaulting a woman he met on the Internet, must go before the same judge who improperly excluded evidence in the first trial, an appeals court ruled yesterday.  In December an appeals court overturned the conviction, criticizing the trial judge, William A. Wetzel, for preventing the jury from seeing e-mail messages in which the woman expressed interest in sadomasochism. She later accused Mr. Jovanovic of having tortured her for 20 hours. The decision yesterday did not explain why Mr. Jovanovic could not have another trial judge.</p>
        <p>Laura Mansnerus (NYT)</p>
        <p>SCHENECTADY: NEW LOTTERY MACHINES -- New York lottery fans, brace yourselves. As of tomorrow, new machines will be used for mixing and picking some of the winning numbers. The new machines will work the same way as the old ones. The difference is seven machines will be replaced by two: One with three chambers for Numbers, the three-number lottery, and one with four chambers for Win 4. A third machine, which has been used to pick Take 5, Lotto and Pick 10, will not change.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: SUIT AGAINST YANKEES DISMISSED -- A federal judge yesterday dismissed a racial discrimination lawsuit against the New York Yankees. V. Whitney Joseph had alleged in her lawsuit that the Stadium Club, a restaurant in Yankee Stadium, had discriminated against her because she is black. On July 20, 1998, she said, she was barred from the club because she was wearing a tank top, a violation of the club's posted dress code. When she changed into a T-shirt, she was admitted, but said she then saw white women there wearing tank tops. Judge Sidney H. Stein ruled that Ms. Joseph had failed to allege ''a likelihood of future harm,'' a necessary condition for the suit to go forward.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>MINEOLA: MONEY FOR SUPERFUND URGED -- Environmental groups called on elected officials yesterday to refinance the New York State Superfund, a toxic-site cleanup program that has run out of money. The state program, which was created in 1982 to clean up toxic dumps and spills not covered by the federal Superfund program, is run by the Department of Environmental Conservation. Jennifer Post, a spokeswoman for the department, confirmed yesterday that 790 toxic sites in the state lack the money to be cleaned up. Todd Stebbins, Long Island regional director for New York Public Interest Research Group, said 124 of these sites are on Long Island, where drinking water is threatened.</p>
        <p>Tara Bahrampour (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: TRASH CUSTOMERS DROPPED -- Waste Management has won permission from the city to follow through on its plan to eliminate unprofitable routes by dropping about 3,000 customers, about 10 percent of its  customer base. The Trade Waste Commission had ordered the company to halt its move after some of its approximately 3,300 affected customers complained that Waste Management was disregarding written contracts. The company has agreed to honor about 315  contracts, with the service for the remaining 3,000 to be  cut off Nov. 1, city officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Eric Lipton (NYT)</p>
        <p>QUEENS: LIBRARIANS SEEK RAISES -- Librarians demanding a pay increase demonstrated yesterday outside a trustees meeting of the Queens Central Library. The librarians, members of the Queensboro Library Guild, part of District Council 37, said the library should use the $2.6 million that the City Council restored to the library's budget to increase salaries. The union said about one-fourth of Queens librarians quit last year to take higher-paying jobs.</p>
        <p>Steven Greenhouse (NYT)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>FAIRFIELD: MOLD CLOSES SCHOOL -- McKinley Elementary School has been closed indefinitely while health officials investigate air quality problems believed responsible for making students sick. The decision to shut the school was made Wednesday night. McKinley will not be reopened until doctors from the University of Connecticut  Medical Center and a Maine company that specializes in building science, figure out how to rid the school of high mold spore levels. Dr. Eileen Storey of the university  said McKinley has ''mold that is beyond what we want to see.'' She said it was still unclear how dangerous the mold was but added the school had to be closed and cleaned.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>TRENTON: PRE-TEENAGE DRUG USE -- Fewer middle school students around the state are smoking marijuana and drinking alcohol, a survey found. The survey also found that students who talk regularly to their parents are less likely to drink or use drugs. The survey, conducted among seventh and eighth graders without teachers present, found that 9 percent of students reported having smoked marijuana within the past year, down from 11 percent in 1998, and 13 percent from 1995, the first year the Partnership for a Drug Free New Jersey did the survey. Alcohol use was down to 41 percent from 49 in 1995.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>SPRINGFIELD: AUTO DEALERS SETTLE CHARGES -- A group of five auto dealerships has agreed to pay more than $200,000 in prosecution costs and restitution to customers to settle complaints of unfair practices, the state attorney general's office announced yesterday. The 73 complaints against Toresco Auto Group, which includes the sprawling Autoland dealership on Route 22 in Springfield, involved allegations that dealers failed to refund deposits and used bait-and-switch tactics, said Jennifer Doktorski, a spokeswoman for the attorney general. Toresco did not admit any wrongdoing. Toresco's lawyer, Theodore Schiller, said the number of complaints,  dating from 1993 to 1999, was negligible compared with the 149,000 sales and thousands of repairs by the dealers during that time.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>CALENDAR</p>
        <p>Monday</p>
        <p>HEARING ON SIGHTSEEING BUSES -- The City Council plans to take testimony from city officials and private companies on a proposed change in city law requiring sightseeing companies to ensure that their buses comply with emissions standards. Council Chambers, City Hall, Manhattan, 10 am. Information: (212) 788-7210.</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 2, 2000, Thursday  A report in the Metro Briefing column on Oct. 20 misstated a federal judge's action in the case of a black woman who sued the New York Yankees, contending that she was barred from entering the Stadium Club attired in a tank top while white women similarly dressed were admitted. The judge did not dismiss the lawsuit, by V. Whitney Joseph; it is to be heard later this month. He refused the Yankees' request to dismiss the case summarily, and refused Ms. Joseph's request for injunctive relief, saying she had not claimed ''a likelihood of future harm.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 2, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>A report in the Metro Briefing column on Oct. 20 misstated a federal judge's action in the case of a black woman who sued the New York Yankees, contending that she was barred from entering the Stadium Club attired in a tank top while white women similarly dressed were admitted. The judge did not dismiss the lawsuit, by V. Whitney Joseph; it is to be heard later this month. He refused the Yankees' request to dismiss the case summarily, and refused Ms. Joseph's request for injunctive relief, saying she had not claimed ''a likelihood of future harm.''</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
