<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Ego Sashays In Style</title>
    <meta content="20MUSC$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/arts/20MUSC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DESIGN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Guggenheim Museum (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armani, Giorgio</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muschamp, Herbert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Fashion Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E1DD133EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2716" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Ego Sashays In Style</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERBERT MUSCHAMP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Muschamp, Herbert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Herbert Muschamp reviews Guggenheim Museum retrospective of fashion designer Giorgio Armani; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Guggenheim Museum has served up another plateau of urban history: a retrospective of the Milanese fashion designer Giorgio Armani. This show may lack the depth of the Guggenheim's other urban excavations, like ''The Great Utopia,'' ''The Italian Metamorphosis: 1943-1968'' and the recent ''1900: Art at the Crossroads.'' But what it lacks in depth it makes up for with sparkle. Organized by Germano Celant and Harold Koda, ''Giorgio Armani'' polishes up a familiar facet of urban life: the grand promenade through flattering reflections of ourselves (superimposed on fantasies of how much better we would look if we could afford nice clothes) that we take through the great shopping streets of Paris, Milan and New York. The show's pretext may be Mr. Armani, but its real subject is autoerotica, and the perverse generosity of which extreme narcissists are capable. And the show does it without mirrors.</p>
        <p>Frank Lloyd Wright, the Guggenheim's architect, would have loved this show. Wright cared a lot about clothes. He even designed some -- for himself, naturally (those dashing tweed capes!), but also for some of the women who inhabited his Prairie houses. Picture it: Arts and Crafts furniture, a matinee musicale and a hostess in a Wright-designed tea gown to complete the cultivated composition. The last Mrs. Wright, the tigerish Olgivanna, was a vision in white and Cherokee red.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Guggenheim Museum has served up another plateau of urban history: a retrospective of the Milanese fashion designer Giorgio Armani. This show may lack the depth of the Guggenheim's other urban excavations, like ''The Great Utopia,'' ''The Italian Metamorphosis: 1943-1968'' and the recent ''1900: Art at the Crossroads.'' But what it lacks in depth it makes up for with sparkle. Organized by Germano Celant and Harold Koda, ''Giorgio Armani'' polishes up a familiar facet of urban life: the grand promenade through flattering reflections of ourselves (superimposed on fantasies of how much better we would look if we could afford nice clothes) that we take through the great shopping streets of Paris, Milan and New York. The show's pretext may be Mr. Armani, but its real subject is autoerotica, and the perverse generosity of which extreme narcissists are capable. And the show does it without mirrors.</p>
        <p>Frank Lloyd Wright, the Guggenheim's architect, would have loved this show. Wright cared a lot about clothes. He even designed some -- for himself, naturally (those dashing tweed capes!), but also for some of the women who inhabited his Prairie houses. Picture it: Arts and Crafts furniture, a matinee musicale and a hostess in a Wright-designed tea gown to complete the cultivated composition. The last Mrs. Wright, the tigerish Olgivanna, was a vision in white and Cherokee red.</p>
        <p>The commercial aspect of the Armani show wouldn't trouble Wright much, either. Visitors to the Mercedes-Benz (originally Jaguar) showroom on Park Avenue, or the jewelery boutique shop off Union Square in San Francisco, can see that the spiral was entirely compatible with fashion and cash. This year, Mr. Armani pledged a major chunk of dough (perhaps as much as $15 million)  to the Guggenheim as part of a global partner sponsorship (gifts that can go to Guggenheim projects anywhere in the world). And it has been speculated that this show was contingent on the designer's financial support, which the museum has denied. (In Style magazine, a Time Warner enterprise, is the show's official sponsor.) The arrangement raises serious questions of institutional ethics, which I'll get to further on. But what a bore it is to think about such matters when you're looking at pretty things.</p>
        <p>The major affinity between Wright and Mr. Armani is that the Guggenheim's spiral and fashion are both signs of life. I can recall no other Guggenheim exhibition devoted entirely to the human form, or at least its mannequin simulacrum. ''Armani,'' in fact, presents an inverted version of a life class. Instead of the undraped body, the show offers just the drapes. The mannequins have been pared down to the edges of the costumes, creating the special effect of Invisible Women. These cluster in groups, arrayed in the building's structural bays, spatial modules with the proportions of shop windows. The presentation recalls the close relationship between fashion and Surrealism that flourished in New York in the 1940's.</p>
        <p>So, to a degree, does Robert Wilson's installation, at least when you consider that Isamu Noguchi was partly inspired by Surrealism's preoccupation with Freud. Architectural transformations of the Guggenheim rotunda have been a hallmark of the museum under the direction of Thomas Krens. Mr. Wilson's may be the best yet. On entering, you find yourself within a hugely magnified version of a Noguchi paper lantern turned inside out. A ribbon of white theatrical scrim winds almost continuously from the lowest coil of the spiral nearly to the top. Lighting, designed by A. J. Weissbard, glows from within. The dome's skylight has been dimmed; Wright's built-in ramp lighting is blocked by temporary walls.</p>
        <p>The walls are painted a dark taupe, the color of volcanic mud. Floors have been fitted with gray carpet except on the top level, which is carpeted in black. The monotony is relieved by the clothes, of course, and also by visual vignettes that occur along the ramp: cracks in the mud, illuminated from behind; stands of fiberoptic reeds; light panels in the floor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilson's aesthetic is a Zen version of Midwestern blandness: slow, flat, dull. Here, he gives us a regional department store in the state of satori, le Salon de Paris with one hand clapping. The carpeted floors account for much of the calm. A collage of religious and exotic sounds, created by Michael Galasso, amplifies the Eastern mood. Chanter?</p>
        <p>Sashay. Don't bother with that walk-down-from-the-top routine. ''Armani'' is designed for ascension, and it's good for the calf muscles besides. In the High Gallery, the double-height space near the bottom of the ramp, Mr. Wilson has installed a yin-yang, topsy-turvy runway. Visitors walk down the center of the space, on illuminated panels of white glass, while evening costumes are mounted on bleachers that rise on either side. How cruel to subject us poor slobs to the inspection of these peerless (and headless) women of style!</p>
        <p>But the tableaux are awesome, the outfits all black and white. En masse, they display a power of invention not seen since Cecil Beaton's famous Ascot scene in ''My Fair Lady.'' Plaids, stripes, florals, herringbones, chevrons and other patterns, rendered in sequins, tweed, silk, linen, beads and feathers, these dresses introduce the motif of unity and multiplicity that runs the entire length of the ramp.</p>
        <p>If, like me, you don't follow fashion closely, you may well have a stereotypical image of Armani fashion. The image is androgynous, monochrome, uniform and fluid. Isn't this the guy who, in the 1980's, put men and women into the power suit? I came here half expecting to see an ''Arrangement in Slate and Mushroom,'' with museumgoers providing the only variety in sight.</p>
        <p>The fluid part we got right. Otherwise, this show, which includes more than 400 costumes, explodes that preconception into as many smithereens. Along stretches of the ramp, we pass through monochromatic interludes, but these only heighten the designer's fecund talent for formal differentiation. And Mr. Armani uses color, particularly in floral fabrics, with the exuberance of an English gardener.</p>
        <p>The show is organized by themes, not chronology, which makes it tempting to use the word timeless, as if fashion, of all things, could stand outside time. The stuck-clock effect, I would say, derives from the poise Mr. Armani maintains between theme and variation. The theme is Mr. Armani's concept of ideal body proportions. The concept is Vitruvian as updated by Leonardo. This body image is fixed, eternal and universal, like the Hitchcock character Miss Torso. Once it is accepted, there is no reason to give the theme another thought. The designer is free to play with variations: palette, pattern, fabric, texture, collage, degree of transparency or opacity, brilliance or subtlety of ornamental detail.</p>
        <p>The thematic approach allows the curators to display Mr. Armani's own sense of historical awareness. Thus we come to a set of black dress variations, elaborate gowns said to be inspired by the mourning dress of the late Victorians. All this bombazine, just because the beloved Albert died? Get over it, Queenie.</p>
        <p>The German philosopher Walter Benjamin wrote that the architecture of the city is experienced through peripheral vision and should be analyzed and discussed as a fleeting, mercurial art. You could say as much about fashion, particularly as it is encountered on the runway or the street. When I heard about Mr. Wilson's plan for the scrims, I was afraid he would sacrifice one of the Guggenheim's glories: the opportunity to experience art on the periphery, across the atrium space, on several levels at once.</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Wilson's design enhances this wonderful effect. You can't see the costumes in any detail, of course, but you can discern their colors and shapes, and these glimpses are as tantalizing as a model's runway turn, or a stranger admiring her reflection in a window. And when you arrive at the shapes, peripheral vision may not be enough. I am thinking, for example, of a group of costumes on the third level, with beaded floral and arabesque motifs on see-through netting. Plan to be there when Mr. Galasso's soundtrack segues into sitar music. You do not need spiritual austerities to enter into a contemplative state: here every possible organic and geometric shape seems to rise up from a cosmic soup, then dissolve back into it.</p>
        <p>Another rhythm plays counterpoint to the shift between close-up and periphery: a continuous alteration between art and commodity. Some of Mr. Armani's fabrics made me want to burst into tears, like Daisy Buchanan. They have an emotional power similar to art. The next minute I'd be thinking, ''But I could own one of these pieces!'' They're within human range. So it goes; admire, covet, admire, covet, round and round the room.</p>
        <p>The men's sportswear, a quilted leather jacket in particular, brought back memories of when I first became aware of fashion and would fantasize over pictures in l'Uomo Vogue. Now, at 52, I could dress in mourning for a fantasy that I never pursued. I've lived my whole life the wrong way!</p>
        <p>On the androgyny question; I am not young. And I did live in London in the days of Ossie Clark and the Chelsea Cobbler. But I must say that no one at my end of the world ever made much fuss over gender differences in dressing. For those of us who buy dress shirts from Brooks Brothers, jeans from Levi Strauss, and T-shirts from wherever, gender  is a nonstarter. So the surprise, for me, is that Mr. Armani's clothes are remarkably gender-specific. Can anyone living recall a time when suits for women looked weird? And the guy clothes are for guys: leathers, rich wools, the suits we once called Continental.</p>
        <p>Gender differentiation takes its toll on the visitor's concentration. Toward the top of the spiral, the men thin out and disappear. One misses them: the contrast between girls and guys below helps to keep one's attention focused. And a guy doesn't feel quite welcome at this gathering of ball-gowned sorority sisters unless he's carrying a corsage.</p>
        <p>Into the two side galleries. One gallery on celebrity. Strangely dowdy after the rotunda's grand promenade. Half the Oscar nominees look as if they want to play Amanda Wingfield. All of them could get a lift from a commentary by Joan Rivers. The gallery's shoebox proportions  are unsympathetic to Mr. Armani's Vitruvian ideal. It's weird to see a Ricky Martin outfit without the navel showing, like a temple sculpture without the ruby in its third eye.</p>
        <p>Second side gallery: the spring-summer 2000 collection. It is best left to fashion critics. The atmosphere here is too much like a boutique for my comfort. The great thing about fashion shows in museums is that you get to examine the merchandise without salespeople making you feel like dirt. In this gallery, the museum guards come off as maximum-strength floor walkers.</p>
        <p>Now I get to have my Savanarola moment. I'm not going to beat up on the Guggenheim for doing what all museums have been doing since the dawn of time. There never has been a fixed border between cultural institutions and private enterprise. The boundary has always been fluid. For more than a decade, it has been under intense renegotiation, in part to compensate for diminished public financing for the arts. Narcissism should be part of this discussion, too.</p>
        <p>As I hope I've made clear, I respect fashion, I respect Mr. Armani's artistry and I think the show looks great. I think it's grand to display fashion in an art museum. But showing fashion in a museum is one thing.  Importing fashion-world values into a museum's decision-making process is something else. The transferral of those trade values is not grand at all.</p>
        <p>Historical amnesia, intellectual pretension, cronyism, promotion, delusion, sycophancy, bribery, betrayal, all wrapped up in press releases passed off as journalism: these are some of the lubricants that make the wheels of fashion turn. If you enjoy the fashion spectacle, you wouldn't want to miss one treacherous moment. In the Eastern spirit of the Armani show, you could even say that such ugliness makes the beauty possible. In any case, it's not against the law.</p>
        <p>Museums, however, are not commercial institutions, even if they sometimes behave otherwise. Museums may, of course, be swayed by intellectual fashions. This is not in itself objectionable, or even avoidable. The British Museum has reconsidered its display of the Elgin Marbles several times over the years, and the evolution of taste illustrated by these alterations is itself of cultural interest. Intellectual fashion may be healthy for a living cultural institution. The values of commercial fashion, however, are not. Commercial fashion, like any business, depends on smoothness: on greasing the wheels of designers, their investors, the fashion press, celebrity clients and retail advertisers. The credibility of museums depends on traction: on their ability to resist the smoothness of the market system.</p>
        <p>Museums don't need that traction to get publicity, attract crowds and even put on worthwhile shows. Without it, however, there's nothing particularly special about them apart from the cachet of their names. I could live without the cachet. If traction isn't available, I'll settle for candor. I would prefer it if the Guggenheim came out and said: ''We need the money! We want to fix up the Dogana in Venice and we need $15 million! You got a problem with that?'' This would at least be an ethical stance, if not a noble one.</p>
        <p>This is where the Armani show's theme of self-absorption becomes a metaphor for the predicament of many cultural institutions today.  Those who want to import fashion values into the art world don't get up in the morning and ask themselves, ''What can I do today to sabotage civilization?'' In the overlapping worlds of fashion and contemporary art, there is no shortage of pret-a-porter rationalizations for conflicts of interest. Many of them are rooted in the Romantic myth that formal training and conventional morality are the enemies of creativity and truth. We're free! Down with the old walls! We're breaking through!  (Never mind that today's free spirits are aching to get into the institutions that the Romantics were trying to get out of.)</p>
        <p>Then there's the Specialness factor. What some may see as intellectual corruption is in fact to be seen as enlightened obedience to a higher calling of profound cultural value, which critics, benighted fools, are unable to discern. Don't worry. Trust us. In the future, the truth will be revealed. Postmodern thinking is very Special in this sense. It is a fancy way of applying commercial values to art.</p>
        <p>The truth is that we'll never know whether, without his eight-figure pledge, the Guggenheim would have mounted a retrospective on the work of Giorgio Armani. Just as we'll never know whether the Metropolitan Museum would have presented a show of Cartier jewels without financial support from the House of Cartier. Or whether the Museum of Modern Art would have devoted a show to a Ferrari without support from Ferrari. Or whether the Brooklyn Museum of Art would have presented ''Sensation'' without a check from Charles Saatchi.</p>
        <p>The artists will never know, either, and neither will the institutions, for that matter. That's the way narcissism works. I doubt this will ruin Mr. Armani's day. Unlike Mr. Wilson's mannequins, the designer appears to have a head on his shoulders. Narcissism is his business. Enlightenment is a cultural institution's stock in trade. The light fades where delusion rules.</p>
        <p>''Giorgio Armani'' is at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, through Jan. 17. It will travel to the Guggenheim Museum Bilbao in Spain (March to August).</p>
        <p>DESIGN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
