<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES: FOR CHILDREN</title>
    <meta content="20KIDS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240162"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5D6143EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES: FOR CHILDREN</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>''THE ADVENTURES OF MAYA THE BEE,'' told through rod and shadow puppets and a jazz score, is about a little bee who rejects toiling in the hive and flies off to pursue tastes more exotic than honey. Saturdays at 11 a.m. at the Salon Theater, 45 Bleecker Street, Greenwich Village. Tickets: $15; $7 for children. Reservations: (212) 539-6644.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>''THE ADVENTURES OF MAYA THE BEE,'' told through rod and shadow puppets and a jazz score, is about a little bee who rejects toiling in the hive and flies off to pursue tastes more exotic than honey. Saturdays at 11 a.m. at the Salon Theater, 45 Bleecker Street, Greenwich Village. Tickets: $15; $7 for children. Reservations: (212) 539-6644.</p>
        <p>''ARABIAN NIGHTS.'' Youngsters won't have to jump aboard a magic carpet and ride to an exotic desert kingdom to hear these stories, presented by the Young Vic Theater Company on an enchanted circle of sand. New Victory Theater, 209 West 42nd Street, Manhattan. Tonight at 7; tomorrow at 1 and 7 p.m.; Sunday at noon and 5 p.m. Tickets: $10, $20 and $25. Reservations: (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>''A LADY NAMED JO,'' a musical adaptation of Louisa May Alcott's ''Little Women,'' running just over two hours, is for children over 8 who will enjoy the drawing-room dramas and lovely melodies. Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Exit 9E off the Grand Central Parkway. Tomorrow at 3 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m. Information: (718) 760-0064.</p>
        <p>''SCHMOOZY TOGETHERNESS,'' an hourlong musical from Manhattan Theater Source (''Kingdom of the Sun'') in which the heroine, Schmoozy, ventures into a magical meta-forest. Although theatergoers under 10 may not understand the puns in Sam Forman's book and lyrics, they will enjoy seeing grown-ups act silly. Sunday at 1 p.m. at Manhattan Theater Source, 177 Macdougal Street, Greenwich Village. Tickets: $7. Reservations: (212) 501-4751.</p>
        <p>''THE SWINEHERD,'' the Hans Christian Andersen fairy tale about a selfish, materialistic princess who learns the value of love, adapted by Morna Murphy Martell. Vital Children's Theater, third floor, 432 West 42nd Street, Clinton. Saturdays through Nov. 4 at 10:30 a.m. and 12:30 p.m. Tickets: $10. Reservations: (212) 592-4508.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>ANNUAL PUMPKIN PATCH, Sunday from 1 to 4 p.m. at the Queens Botanical Garden, 43-50 Main Street, Flushing, featuring pumpkin-painting, storytelling and crafts. The garden will turn the courtyard of its plant shop into a pumpkin patch where children can select and buy pumpkins. Afterward they can take their choices to a free pumpkin-painting workshop where garden staff members will offer instructions and advice. Pumpkins are $3. Prizes will go to the scariest and silliest jack-o'-lantern faces. Information: (718) 886-3800.</p>
        <p>''ART AND POETRY,'' a family workshop with Hal Wirowitz, author of ''Mother Said,'' who will use his humorous poetry to inspire children to write their own missives and create ''Poetry in Motion'' posters like the ones in the subways. Sunday at 1:30 p.m. at the New York Transit Museum, Boerum Place and Schermerhorn Street, downtown Brooklyn. Reservations required. Fee: $5, which includes museum admission; free for members. Information: (718) 243-8601.</p>
        <p>BIG APPLE CIRCUS. New York's one-ring circus returns to Damrosch Park at Lincoln Center through Jan. 7. No seat is more than 50 feet from the action. The year's theme is ''The City Mouse and the Country Mouse,'' or more like the city clown and the country clown, who go on adventures around the city. There will also be aerialists, acrobats, a Hula-Hoop dancer, dogs, equestrians and jugglers. Tickets range from $12 to $62. Call for the schedule. Tickets: (212) 721-6500 or (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN CHILDREN'S MUSEUM, 145 Brooklyn Avenue, at St. Marks Place, Crown Heights. ''Early Learner Workshops,'' the first of a series of programs for children ages 2 to 5, is meant to be educational, fun and inexpensive. Tomorrow and Sunday from 10:30 a.m. to noon at ''Great Pumpkin,'' parents and their children can learn how plants grow. $5 materials fee. Registration: (718) 735-4402. At a Sukkot celebration today from 2 to 5 p.m. youngsters will build and decorate a sukkah, make tea bags, weave baskets and listen to stories. Free with suggested admission: $4. Information: (718) 735-4400.</p>
        <p>GREENWICH PUMPKIN FIELD AND HUNT. The Jefferson Market Garden on Greenwich Avenue, between West 9th and 10th Streets, will be transformed into a pumpkin patch where children can hunt for pumpkins, tomorrow from noon to 1 p.m. They can create their own jack-o'-lanterns with paints available across the street, at the Ruth Wittenburg Triangle, Avenue of the Americas and Greenwich Avenue, from 1 to 3 p.m. Free while supplies last. Information: (212) 777-2173.</p>
        <p>''HALLOWEEN CLOWNS AND CARNIVAL MAGIC.'' The Little Orchestra Society, conducted by Dino Anagnost, begins its season of Happy Concerts for Young People ages 6 to 12 tomorrow at 11 a.m. and 1 p.m. at Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center. The stage becomes the big top, with the clown troupe the New York Goofs and a carnival filled with jugglers, magicians and mimes. The music will be by Shostakovich, Bizet, Kabalevsky and Dukas. Single tickets, $10 to $50; subscription series of all three programs, $24 to $90. Reservations: (212) 971-9500, weekdays from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>HAUNTED HALLOWEEN WEEKEND IN CENTRAL PARK. Shakespeare's ghost will confront his scariest creations, including the witches from ''Macbeth,'' the ghost from ''Hamlet'' and Caliban from ''The Tempest,'' in ''Shakespeare's Haunted House,'' an interactive theater production presented by Faux-Real Theater Company. The 45-minute sessions are appropriate for children 5 and older. The Central Park Halloween Parade and Pumpkin Sail at the Harlem Meer, which includes storytelling, refreshments and characters from children's tales, is for children of all ages. Revelers should come in costume with a carved pumpkin (not heavier than 10 pounds), which they will later cast upon the waters of the Harlem Meer. Shakespeare's Haunted Castle, 1 to 5 p.m. tomorrow and Sunday at Belvedere Castle, midpark at 79th Street, (212) 772-0210. Halloween Parade and Pumpkin Sail, Sunday from 3:30 to 6:30 p.m., at the Charles A. Dana Discovery Center, at 110th Street, near Fifth Avenue, (212) 860-1370. Free; registration is required, especially for the Pumpkin Sail. For all ages. Free.</p>
        <p>''KIDS 'N' COMEDY'' WORKSHOP/AUDITION, for budding comedians 8 to 15 who would like to participate in the ''Kids 'n' Comedy'' series. The workshop, on Sunday from 2 to 4 p.m. at the Gotham Comedy Club, 34 West 22nd Street, will also act as an audition. Each child will take a turn at the mike and learn while performing. Registration is required, and participants should prepare a three-minute routine appropriate for children 7 and older and their families, who will be the audience. Space is limited. Fee: $40, which must be prepaid. The workshop will be videotaped, with a copy given to each child who attends. Information: (212) 877-6115.</p>
        <p>POETRY AND PERFORMANCE WORKSHOP for teenagers interested in performing their words, with vocal and physical warm-ups and exercises in writing, movement and music, tomorrow from 1 to 3 p.m. (also Nov. 11 and Dec. 2), at the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea. Free. Information: (212) 255-5793, extension 15.</p>
        <p>''RUDDIGORE,'' part of Amato Opera's ''Opera-in-Brief for the Family Series,'' is a fully costumed 90-minute version of the Gilbert and Sullivan operetta, adapted for children 6 and older, tomorrow at 11:30 a.m. at 319 Bowery, at Second Street, Lower East Side. Tickets: $15. Information: (212) 228-8200.</p>
        <p>''SONIC BOOM FOR KIDS (AGES 7-97),'' an introduction to contemporary music for youngsters, Sunday at 2 p.m. at the Great Hall at the Cooper Union, Third Avenue at Seventh Street, featuring Paul Schoenfield's ''Boogie,'' Igor Stravinsky's ''Owl and the Pussycat'' and Aaron Copland's ''Cat and the Mouse.'' Tickets: $12; $6 for students and the elderly. Reservations: (212) 279-4200, daily from noon to 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>''WHAT'S A WORM?'' Youngsters will learn the difference between flatworms, roundworms and segmented worms, while learning about their anatomy and survival needs, tomorrow from 10 a.m. to noon at the Staten Island Institute of Arts and Sciences, 75 Stuyvesant Place. For children 8 to 13 years old. Fee: $10; $8 for members. Registration required. Information: (718) 727-1135, Ext. 29.</p>
        <p>Exhibitions</p>
        <p>''GOOD GRIEF!'' Charlie Brown and his creator, Charles M. Schulz, are the stars of this exhibition, in which families are invited to inhabit a life-size version of the ''Peanuts'' comic strip, which always offered lessons as well as laughs. Activities include video games, a psychotherapy session at Lucy's booth (cost: a nickel) and a crawl through the Great Pumpkin Patch. Children's Museum of Manhattan, Tisch Building, 212 West 83rd Street. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free with museum admission: $6; $3 for the elderly; infants, free. Information: (212) 721-1234. In conjunction with the exhibition, the Film Society of Lincoln Center's Movies for Kids presents a movie series, ''Good Grief! It's Charlie Brown in the Movies.'' Tomorrow and Sunday at 2 p.m., ''Bon Voyage, Charlie Brown (And Don't Come Back)'' (1980). Walter Reade Theater, Lincoln Center, 165 West 65th Street. Tickets: $3. Information: (212) 875-5600.</p>
        <p>''WILLIAM WEGMAN: CANES ECCLESIORUM'' (that's Latin for church dogs) is an exhibition of the photographer's famous pooches doing amazing humanlike things, created especially for the Cathedral of St. John the Divine, 1047 Amsterdam Avenue, at 112th Street, Morningside Heights, through Sunday. Free. Information: (212) 316-7540.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
