<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Jews and Muslims Uneasily Shared Morocco</title>
    <meta content="20COTT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/arts/20COTT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Morocco</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jewish Museum (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotter, Holland</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Morocco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E5D6123EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1376" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Jews and Muslims Uneasily Shared Morocco</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOLLAND COTTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotter, Holland</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Holland Cotter reviews Jewish Museum exhibit on culture and art of Jews in Morocco, where they lived from Roman times, long before arrival of Arab Muslims; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The drive west from the interior of Morocco to the Atlantic port city of Essaouira in summer is a desert trip. The heat is blistering; the terrain stays the same for hours, brown earth and platinum light. Suddenly there's a change. As if someone had thrown a switch, the temperature drops, a moist breeze stirs, green appears. The sea is miles away and invisible, but you feel its presence like a balm.</p>
        <p>That's Morocco: grueling and inviting. Probably it was that way for the Berbers who arrived millenniums ago, and certainly for the immigrants who came after them, most recently Arab Muslims in the seventh or eighth century. Their presence is the dominant one now, in language, music, food and art and in the minarets that ornament the urban horizons and anchor the oasis towns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The drive west from the interior of Morocco to the Atlantic port city of Essaouira in summer is a desert trip. The heat is blistering; the terrain stays the same for hours, brown earth and platinum light. Suddenly there's a change. As if someone had thrown a switch, the temperature drops, a moist breeze stirs, green appears. The sea is miles away and invisible, but you feel its presence like a balm.</p>
        <p>That's Morocco: grueling and inviting. Probably it was that way for the Berbers who arrived millenniums ago, and certainly for the immigrants who came after them, most recently Arab Muslims in the seventh or eighth century. Their presence is the dominant one now, in language, music, food and art and in the minarets that ornament the urban horizons and anchor the oasis towns.</p>
        <p>Another highly mobile people, less often noted in the history books, preceded the Muslims. These were Jews, who have lived in Morocco since at least Roman times and who flooded in when they were expelled from Spain and Portugal in the 15th century.</p>
        <p>Overall, the relationship between the ruling Muslims and the Jews was cooperative but uneasy. Under Islamic law, Jews, as ''people of the book,'' were a protected minority. They were also second-class citizens, confined to separate neighborhoods, made to pay extra taxes and handed jobs like moneylending and jewelry-making, which Muslims disdained.</p>
        <p>Even so, Jews gained wealth and power. With an ancient tradition of rabbinical scholarship, they were vital players in great university centers like Fez, where Maimonides of Cordoba lived for a while. And because they were plugged into international economic networks, they found careers in diplomacy and trade. For nearly two centuries Essaouira was the primary node of commercial exchange between Morocco and Europe. And although it was officially a Muslim town, Jews made up 30 to 40 percent of its population.</p>
        <p>''Morocco: Jews and Art in a Muslim Land'' at the Jewish Museum tells the story of the tense mutual dependence of two cultures and tells it perhaps as well as it can be told in an exhibition format. Scant Moroccan Jewish material survives from before the 18th century. For firsthand depictions of Jewish life, we have to rely on 19th-century Orientalist painters from Europe -- an iffy source -- and some early photographs.</p>
        <p>Vivian B. Mann, the show's organizer and the museum's curator of Judaica, makes the most of what is available by offering a little bit of many things: jewelry, textiles, folk amulets, paintings, political posters. She and the exhibition designer, Stuart Silver, have obviously thought hard about how to put such things across while avoiding a rummage-sale effect, and they have done a good job in a carefully paced and atmospheric installation.</p>
        <p>Much of that atmosphere, it should be said, is generated by two short films commissioned for the occasion. Made by the Iranian-born director Hamid Fardjad, who has worked with the video artist Shirin Neshat, the films are not optional audio-visual supplements set off to one side. You have to walk past them to enter and leave the show.</p>
        <p>The introductory one is especially absorbing. Only six minutes long, it is a poetic, double-screen evocation both of life in Morocco and of the show itself, with the camera sweeping across bare landscapes and into lamplit synagogues, then traveling in close-up over the iridiscent, gold-shot surfaces of textiles on view in the galleries beyond.</p>
        <p>The history of the Jewish presence in Morocco is phrased in more concrete terms in the show, beginning with a pair of objects that establish a chronological span. One is a fragment of a third-century tombstone, found at a Roman site and engraved with a woman's name: ''Matrona, daughter of Rabbi Judah Noah.'' The other is a painting from 1875 titled ''A Jewish Marriage in Tangier'' by the Spanish artist Francisco Lameyer y Berenguer.</p>
        <p>Lameyer's vision of a festive courtyard gathering is standard Orientalist fare: exotic display with an ethnological gloss. But to his credit, he seems more interested in recording than dramatizing his subject, and he pays close attention to details that reveal a range of cultural ingredients, from Islamic-style architecture to the design of the bride's dress, which includes Jewish symbols but has sources in medieval Spain.</p>
        <p>An identical dress, with an arc of gold embroidery surging up from the hem, appears in an 1832 watercolor by Eugene Delacroix. Another is worn by a cushiony, sloe-eyed, come-hither beauty in Charles-Emile Vernet-Lecomte's 1868 painting ''Jewish Woman of Tangier.'' And finally, a ''live'' example can be found in a gallery devoted to ''material culture,'' which delivers a shot of pure luxe at the center of the show.</p>
        <p>Some of the textiles seen in the film are here: shimmery silk belts woven in Fez. And anyone heavy into jewelry, especially heavy jewelry, will want to linger over the gem-encrusted headdress and silver ankle bracelets, which have a primeval heft even though they are from the 19th and 20th centuries.</p>
        <p>The cultural blend of Moroccan art, though, is most pronounced in religious objects. Some, like an openwork Hanukkah lamp from Meknes, are generic in design, while a pair of elaborate silver Torah finials take the form of Spanish turrets pierced by Moorish windows.</p>
        <p>With a group of amulets made for the protection of infants, the show enters truly hybrid ground. Each includes an open hand, an emblem brought to Morocco by Phoenician sailors in the ninth century B.C. and adopted by both Jews and Muslims. It is ubiquitous in the Moroccan Jewish context, whether cast in metal, drawn on paper or, in one spectacular instance, imbedded within a filigree pattern of trees, flowers, menorahs and swans cut from paper and colored foil.</p>
        <p>No shared tradition is more striking, though, than the Moroccan devotion to the cult of saints, which Jews borrowed from Islam. Most of the saints were rabbis revered in life but  credited with miraculous powers after death. Some were local personalities. Others were near-mythical figures, like Rabbi Simeon bar Yohai, thought by some to be the author of the mystical five-volume Zohar. Many saints are worshiped by Jews and Muslims alike and their tombs are magnets for ardent, sometimes arduous pilgrimage.</p>
        <p>The show ends with a reference to a journey, though not a pilgrimage exactly. A small installation recreates the type of classroom found in Jewish schools set up throughout Morocco by the French philanthropic organization Alliance Israelite Universelle. Secular and francophile, the schools were meant to prepare Jewish children in ''backward'' countries for life in the wider modern world, and the wider world is where many of the graduates ended up.</p>
        <p>Throughout the 19th and early 20th centuries Jews left Morocco for Europe, the Americas and elsewhere. Then in the 1950's and 1960's virtually the entire Jewish population -- some 280,000 people -- emigrated, spurred in part by the founding of Israel but mostly by fear for the status of Jews once Morocco gained independence from the Europeans.</p>
        <p>This diaspora is a star-crossed tale of illusions and betrayals, one far too complex for mere objects to explain, which makes the exhibition catalog a crucial component of the show. It includes solid historical essays and a reminiscence by the Muslim writer Oumama Aouad Lahrech about her confused reactions as a young girl to seeing her Jewish friends leaving their homeland.</p>
        <p>Most evocative, though, is an account by the novelist Ami Bouganim about his Jewish childhood in Essaouira, a city ''on the fringes of history, banished from the heavens, at the windswept crossroads.'' Many images from the exhibition find mention here: amulets and Torahs, Jewish quarter streets and imminent departures. The result is a short, intense trip through the Moroccan past as dreamlike as Mr. Fardjad's film, as sad and sardonic as a Kafka tale, and as full of contradictions as the country that produced it.</p>
        <p>''Morocco: Jews and Art in a Muslim Land'' is at the Jewish Museum, 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, (212) 423-3200, through Feb. 11.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
