<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fewer Catches Not a Concern For Chrebet</title>
    <meta content="20JETS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/sports/20JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240333"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chrebet, Wayne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E3DC103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fewer Catches Not a Concern For Chrebet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Oct. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jet player Wayne Chrebet says he does not mind his diminished role in Jets' offense; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jets receiver Wayne Chrebet is not upset that he is averaging fewer than four catches a game, that the running backs Richie Anderson and Curtis Martin are the team's leading receivers. He is not upset that at this rate, he would catch only 56 passes this season, fewer than he has caught in any of his professional seasons, except last year, when he missed five games and caught 48 passes.</p>
        <p>Chrebet is not complaining about his diminished production in the Jets' offense. But he is less blithe about the accounts he has read of his actions in the Jets' loss to Pittsburgh, when Chrebet threw his hands in the air after one of Ray Lucas's passes had sailed over his head. Chrebet, who leaves the locker room early after home games to meet numerous family members and friends, had not spoken to reporters since the Pittsburgh game. It had been suggested that Chrebet's actions could be interpreted as showing up Lucas; today, Chrebet vented his frustration -- not with Lucas, but with the speculation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jets receiver Wayne Chrebet is not upset that he is averaging fewer than four catches a game, that the running backs Richie Anderson and Curtis Martin are the team's leading receivers. He is not upset that at this rate, he would catch only 56 passes this season, fewer than he has caught in any of his professional seasons, except last year, when he missed five games and caught 48 passes.</p>
        <p>Chrebet is not complaining about his diminished production in the Jets' offense. But he is less blithe about the accounts he has read of his actions in the Jets' loss to Pittsburgh, when Chrebet threw his hands in the air after one of Ray Lucas's passes had sailed over his head. Chrebet, who leaves the locker room early after home games to meet numerous family members and friends, had not spoken to reporters since the Pittsburgh game. It had been suggested that Chrebet's actions could be interpreted as showing up Lucas; today, Chrebet vented his frustration -- not with Lucas, but with the speculation.</p>
        <p>''You're talking about this thing in the Pittsburgh game, which was no big deal,'' Chrebet said. ''So I didn't choose to discuss it. Ray didn't care. I went on WFAN and apologized, just in case. All people see is the headlines, 'Chrebet points fingers,' 'Chrebet frustrated,' Chrebet this, Chrebet that. I don't want to be selfish, to take away from what this team is doing.</p>
        <p>''I made a gesture?'' Chrebet asked rhetorically. ''My whole career, I've been pumping fists, I've been doing that. I'm an emotional player; that's the bottom line. I've never been much for words. I hate talking about myself, whether I did the best thing in the world or the worst thing in the world.''</p>
        <p>Chrebet, who has a black right eye courtesy of an errant finger by the Patriots' Ty Law last weekend, began his interview by saying: ''I'm not going to talk about negative or irrelevant things. I just want to talk about positive things.''</p>
        <p>If Chrebet is perturbed by what he has read, he is remaining positive about what he has caught. The highlight reel is filled with Chrebet. He caught both touchdown passes in the Jets' dramatic fourth-quarter comeback against New England in the second week of the season, and was on the receiving end of Martin's stunning halfback option pass to beat Tampa Bay.</p>
        <p>But his overall production -- he has caught only eight passes in the past three games -- has mirrored that of the other receivers, declining while the fortunes of the running backs have improved. The Jets' offense looked its best against New England last weekend. A conservative game plan resulted in Martin running for 143 yards and Vinny Testaverde completing 15 of his 23 passes for 139 yards, with a long pass of only 17 yards. Chrebet caught two of those passes, for 22 yards.</p>
        <p>Anderson is the Jets' leading receiver, with 24 receptions for 230 yards. Martin has 23 catches for 142 yards and two touchdowns. Chrebet has 21 catches for 240 yards. Dedric Ward, the starting receiver opposite Chrebet, has 16 receptions for 289 yards, only three in the last two games.</p>
        <p>Vincent Brisby, the 6-foot-3 receiver who was signed during training camp and was thought to have a chance to unseat the smaller Ward for the second spot, has only four receptions for 60 yards. He has been inactive for the last three games. Brisby has lost his No. 3 job to the rookie Laveranues Coles, who has nine receptions for 105 yards and who possesses blistering speed that makes him a deep threat.</p>
        <p>Coach Al Groh said Chrebet is seeing more double coverage as the team's No. 1 receiver; that is smothering his production but opening the field for the others.</p>
        <p>''Some of the plays have me take more defenders out of there to open them up,'' Chrebet said. ''That's fine. We're the kind of offense that takes what they give us. We're a running offense. We have, in my eyes, the best running back in the league. You just want to get the ball in his hands as much as you can. I like to contribute the best I can. Maybe it's only a couple of catches, but hopefully they're important and something that helps us score.</p>
        <p>''Understanding my role is the important thing. If that gives opportunities to other players, that's completely fine with me. I'll do that all the way to the playoffs.''</p>
        <p>Testaverde said he is content with how the offense looks, even though he conceded that quarterbacks often prefer big receivers like Brisby. He is encouraged by Coles's development as another offensive option, especially a deep one.</p>
        <p>''I think we're getting better as the season continues to move forward,'' Testaverde said. ''Last week was an indication of us having a more solid, more consistent outing. That's the direction I'd like to head. What we're trying to do here isn't about Wayne or me. It's not about any individual. It's about the team. That's why we've been successful to this point, because we're playing as a team. We don't have a bunch of individuals who are unhappy with how things are going.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>The rookie linebacker JOHN ABRAHAM, who had two sacks and forced a fumble against New England before staggering to the sideline in the fourth quarter, will not play in Monday night's game against the Dolphins because of a pulled stomach muscle. Coach AL GROH would not speculate about how long Abraham might be sidelined. ''How much would you guys think we'd miss Abraham?'' Groh said. ''He's changed the team.'' . . . Groh would not say it, but linebacker MO LEWIS, who played in the nickel package last week to great results, will almost certainly do it again. . . . Center KEVIN MAWAE (foot) is still listed as doubtful, although he believes he will play and he practiced. Tight end ANTHONY BECHT (knee) and running back BERNIE PARMALEE (hamstring) are still questionable but both practiced. . . . SCOTT FROST and KEVIN WILLIAMS will share time at free safety this week.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
