<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Camby Sending Out Encouraging Signs for Knicks</title>
    <meta content="20KNIC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/sports/20KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Camby, Marcus</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E1DD103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Camby Sending Out Encouraging Signs for Knicks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knicks' player Marcus Camby is showing improved play in exhibition games (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>His opponents have not been of the household-name variety, but it is worth noting that Marcus Camby has played exceptionally well in the Knicks' last three games. He has rebounded tenaciously, attacked the rim with aggressiveness and even banged his slender 6-foot-11-inch, 225-pound frame against the competition.</p>
        <p>What does it all mean?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>His opponents have not been of the household-name variety, but it is worth noting that Marcus Camby has played exceptionally well in the Knicks' last three games. He has rebounded tenaciously, attacked the rim with aggressiveness and even banged his slender 6-foot-11-inch, 225-pound frame against the competition.</p>
        <p>What does it all mean?</p>
        <p>That is hard to tell. After all, this is the preseason, one in which Camby's not-so-stellar cast of opposing starters has included Michael Ruffin of the Chicago Bulls, Jahidi White of the Washington Wizards and Joel Pryzbilla of the Milwaukee Bucks. But at the very least, Camby's performance may be a sign that he is capable of not only filling the Knicks' void primarily inside, but also of doing so dynamically.</p>
        <p>''I like the way Marcus has been playing,'' Don Chaney, the Knicks' assistant coach, said. ''To me, he's playing with more enthusiasm and he's playing tougher. I really feel that he's making a valid effort and trying to be aggressive and trying to bang some of the bigger guys.''</p>
        <p>After a poor debut in which he managed only 3 points and two rebounds against the Bulls, Camby has averaged 15.6 points and 10.3 rebounds on 64.3 percent shooting over the last three games. Though it was the least impressive of his three games statistically, Camby's finest outing came against the Philadelphia 76ers and its reputable center, Theo Ratliff.</p>
        <p>Ratliff, who averaged three blocks a game last season, is one of the toughest defensive players in the league, but Camby outplayed him, notching 13 points, 10 rebounds and 2 blocked shots.</p>
        <p>In recording double-doubles in his last three games, Camby has shown a nice touch on a new and improved 15-foot baseline jumper and has averaged four offensive rebounds a game.</p>
        <p>''He's one of the only guys in this league who's a natural offensive rebounder,'' Coach Jeff Van Gundy said. ''I really believe that if he can stay healthy and stay out of foul trouble, the guy could lead the league in offensive rebounds per minute.''</p>
        <p>Camby attributes his improved play and more forceful approach to his health. Though he still experiences some swelling and soreness in the right knee, which hindered him for much of last season, Camby no longer wears a brace during games and said his knee was not hampering him.</p>
        <p>''When I get the ball inside, I'm trying to go up and dunk and get fouled or get to the free-throw line,'' Camby said. ''That's my mind-set going into every game. Last year, that was my mindset, but I just couldn't do it physically. Now that my knees are feeling a little better, I'm able to go out there and get some explosiveness.''</p>
        <p>Van Gundy, whose undefeated Knicks (4-0) are host to the Utah Jazz tonight at the Pepsi Arena in Albany, is not surprised by Camby's play and expects it to continue into the regular season.</p>
        <p>''We expect him to have a great year,'' Van Gundy said. ''I think you can expect him to play that well regardless of what his statistics are.''</p>
        <p>The biggest keys for Camby are remaining healthy and staying out of foul trouble. Except for the game against the Bulls, fouling has not been a problem, but staying foul free will be one of his biggest challenges as the competition becomes more imposing.</p>
        <p>When talking to Camby, one gets the feeling that his success inside has come almost grudgingly. He hates being called a center and dislikes battling the league's biggest men on the blocks so much that he said he would rather come off the bench at power forward.</p>
        <p>''I've been coming off the bench, providing the spark that we need,'' Camby said. ''But I don't mind starting either. I'm no center. I just have to play that because that's the position that needs to be filled.''</p>
        <p>So far he is filling it quite well.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>GLEN RICE, who strained his left knee Monday against the Wizards, missed his second practice because of the injury yesterday and is expected to miss his second game tonight in Albany. Rice and the Knicks have said the injury is not serious and that he does not need to undergo a magnetic resonance imaging test.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
