<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Intensifies Attack on Bush Tax Plan</title>
    <meta content="Y20GOR$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7DC103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1402" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Intensifies Attack on Bush Tax Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore, campaigning in New York, makes blistering attack on Gov George W Bush's economic policies; says Bush's tax proposals would give 'too much to too few at the expense of too many;' photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore said yesterday that Gov. George W. Bush's tax cut proposal would drain Social Security, jack up interest rates and undermine economic growth by giving ''too much to too few at the expense of too many.''</p>
        <p>On a whirlwind day in New York, where the vice president courted national television personalities, campaigned with Hillary Rodham Clinton and appeared on a dinner dais with Mr. Bush, Mr. Gore delivered a blistering condemnation of Mr. Bush's economic proposals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore said yesterday that Gov. George W. Bush's tax cut proposal would drain Social Security, jack up interest rates and undermine economic growth by giving ''too much to too few at the expense of too many.''</p>
        <p>On a whirlwind day in New York, where the vice president courted national television personalities, campaigned with Hillary Rodham Clinton and appeared on a dinner dais with Mr. Bush, Mr. Gore delivered a blistering condemnation of Mr. Bush's economic proposals.</p>
        <p>''The economic policies my opponent has put forward in this election are not just unfair, they're unsound, and they would hurt our economy,'' Mr. Gore declared at a noon speech in the soaring rotunda of Columbia University's Low Library.</p>
        <p>''Governor Bush's plan gambles with our prosperity by bringing back deficits, draining Social Security, delaying debt reduction and fueling higher interest rates,'' he said, adding that the governor's tax cut proposal would ''lavish more on those who need it least.''</p>
        <p>In his speeches to date, Mr. Gore has generally portrayed himself as the more responsible steward of the nation's economy, and he did so again yesterday. But in increasing signs that the economy will be the central issue in the election, both candidates have been escalating their predictions of how the other would ruin the prosperity, and Mr. Gore took his oratory to new heights.</p>
        <p>''My opponent's plan really does pose a threat,'' the vice president said. ''These are not personal differences. I'm not questioning Governor Bush's heart, I'm questioning his priorities.''</p>
        <p>And in a refrain that is emerging as the core of his message, he declared, ''Prosperity itself is on the ballot.''</p>
        <p>These dire warnings came on an otherwise breezy day spent mostly on glossy television sets, where the vice president taped three national television programs -- with Regis Philbin, Rosie O'Donnell and a pre-election skit for ''Saturday Night Live.'' In the latter, he sat stiffly in a formal chair in a White House-like setting and punctuated his scripted remarks with several deep sighs.</p>
        <p>Perhaps most remarkably, he plowed through a day in the media capital of the world in advance of a World Series with two New York teams and managed to avoid saying which team he favored.</p>
        <p>Flying into New York late Wednesday night, reporters asked Mr. Gore if he was rooting for the Yankees or the Mets.</p>
        <p>''Uh-huh,'' he replied.</p>
        <p>By today, he had worked out a more elaborate answer. ''I'm for New York City!'' he said.</p>
        <p>He might have had a hard time convincing some people of that fact as his motorcade tied up traffic across town. Streets were blocked and pedestrians barricaded throughout the day, and some made unwelcoming gestures at his caravan.</p>
        <p>But all was cheerful on the television sets. Ms. O'Donnell, an unabashed Gore promoter, captured the tone by announcing, ''This is going to be a very pro-Gore day.''</p>
        <p>Early this evening, Mr. Gore attended a raucous rally with Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, his running mate, and Mrs. Clinton, the Democratic candidate for the Senate in New York. Thousands of people jammed a midtown hotel for the rally, sponsored by the Service Employees International Union. Mrs. Clinton appealed to the crowd to get out the vote for the ''Gore/Lieberman/Clinton ticket.''</p>
        <p>The message of the day was twofold: To convey his sense of fiscal discipline, in the speech at Columbia, and to show his human side on popular daytime television programs intended chiefly for women.</p>
        <p>At Columbia, Mr. Gore was introduced by Robert E. Rubin, the former treasury secretary. Mr. Rubin told the audience of a few hundred people that Mr. Gore was ''at the center'' of the difficult economic choices made by the Clinton administration. He said Mr. Bush's proposals would take the nation on the ''wrong path.''</p>
        <p>In his speech, Mr. Gore pledged to ''underspend'' the surplus, balance the budget and eliminate the national debt. He also insisted that he would not, as Mr. Bush has charged, expand the size of government.</p>
        <p>''You'd better believe that the era of big government is over,'' he said. He pledged that in a Gore administration, he would take government spending to ''the smallest share of national income in 50 years.''</p>
        <p>On ABC's ''Live With Regis,'' Mr. Gore demonstrated how as a teenager he hypnotized chickens, using Mr. Philbin as the stooge. The vice president, standing behind Mr. Philbin, circled his finger around the talk-show host's head, declared him under and intoned this message: ''Regis, between now and Nov. 7, you will say good things about the Gore/ Lieberman ticket.''</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Donnell asked about Mr. Clinton, giving Mr. Gore a chance to debunk any negative association with Mr. Clinton's sex scandal that might linger among her primarily female audience.</p>
        <p>''Why has it tarnished you when it has nothing to do with you?'' she asked.</p>
        <p>''I hope it hasn't, because I am who I am,'' Mr. Gore said. ''I condemned his personal mistake. I do so again. He's my friend. We've worked together, we've been able to do some good things for the American people. I'm not trying to make this race about the past. It really is about the future.''</p>
        <p>He went on to note that he has been married 30 years.</p>
        <p>After appearing on the ''Rosie'' set, he stepped across the hallway at the NBC studios at Rockefeller Center to tape a segment for a ''Saturday Night Live'' election special to be shown on Nov. 5.</p>
        <p>As the cameras rolled, he began reading a script off the teleprompter, but stopped himself. ''I thought we edited that,'' he said, calling for his speechwriter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is also to appear in the skit as himself. The script has Mr. Bush saying that he is offended by some of the material on the show, and Mr. Gore then says: ''I was one the very first to be offended by material on 'Saturday Night Live' and I'm glad to see the governor has joined with me in condemning it.''</p>
        <p>He then sighs deeply.</p>
        <p>In His Own Words  AL GORE  Speaking yesterday at Columbia University:</p>
        <p>''Governor Bush has very different priorities. Instead of underspending the surplus, he overspends it. He starts with a $1.6 trillion tax cut that gives too much to too few at the expense of too many. Then he adds about a half a trillion dollars in new spending. Then he privatizes Social Security, which would cost another trillion dollars.</p>
        <p>The choice couldn't be clearer. Under my plan, zero deficits and a zero national debt within 12 years. Or a Bush plan that would leave us with a $1.1 trillion deficit in our non-Social Security accounts over the next 10 years, would raise interest rates and could undermine economic growth. . . . Sound fiscal policy sends a signal of reassurance to our markets, and my budget surplus reserve fund is a hedge against the possibility that even today's best projections of economic growth might turn out to be overly optimistic. . . .</p>
        <p>Let's cut to the heart of the matter. Both sides in this election have proposed targeted tax cuts. The difference is, my plan targets the middle class; the Bush plan targets the wealthy. In fact, the other night in our debate, Governor Bush was asked directly by the moderator whether what I was saying about his plan was correct and whether his plan 'benefits the top 1 percent of wealthiest Americans.' His answer? 'Of course it does.' . . .</p>
        <p>And just yesterday, we learned that there's some confusion in the Bush campaign about how soon Social Security will be in deficit under their plan. . . . In this week's debate, I asked the governor to address this confusion. But when he tried to explain his proposal, his own chief economist said, 'I don't know why he said what he said.' . . .</p>
        <p>If his chief economist has no idea what he's talking about, how are the rest of us supposed to figure it out?''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
