<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jacques Henri Lartigue</title>
    <meta content="RV013004" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lartigue, Jacques-Henri (1894-1986)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Ken</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EFDC103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="575" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jacques Henri Lartigue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Ken</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ken Johnson reviews exhibit of photographs of Jacques Henri Lartigue, at Edwynn Houk Gallery; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'Imprints of Joy'  Edwynn Houk Gallery  745 Fifth Avenue, at 58th Street  Through Nov. 4</p>
        <p>Jacques Henri Lartigue (1894-1986) was one of the few child prodigies in the history of art: before he reached adolescence he created works that stand today as masterpieces in the history of photography. The nature of his genius -- if that is what it was -- was not merely technical, though the formal sophistication of his early work is amazing; it had to do, rather, with his ability to animate his mechanical medium with a spirit of play and wonder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'Imprints of Joy'  Edwynn Houk Gallery  745 Fifth Avenue, at 58th Street  Through Nov. 4</p>
        <p>Jacques Henri Lartigue (1894-1986) was one of the few child prodigies in the history of art: before he reached adolescence he created works that stand today as masterpieces in the history of photography. The nature of his genius -- if that is what it was -- was not merely technical, though the formal sophistication of his early work is amazing; it had to do, rather, with his ability to animate his mechanical medium with a spirit of play and wonder.</p>
        <p>''Imprints of Joy,'' the title of this exhibition of more than 60 vintage prints from the private collection of Lartigue's widow, who died in May,  gets it just right. The secret of Lartigue's charmed art and life was his capacity to be delighted by the world. (It probably didn't hurt that he was born into a wealthy and warmly supportive family.)</p>
        <p>This collection of prints, most of which were made before World War I and are postcard-size or smaller, does not include some of Lartigue's most famous images, like the self-portrait in which the young photographer's head seems to float like a balloon on the still surface of his bathwater. But it is alive with his boyish vision -- his enthusiasm for childhood games, his fascination with flying, racing cars and fashionable women and his excitement about the miracle of photography itself. Born a half-century later, he might have been a young Steven Spielberg.</p>
        <p>Among the earliest works are images of people leaping to simulate flight for the camera and its new fast-action technology. In a tiny print from 1910, the fluttering silhouette of a young man in a suit hangs in midair over a grassy hillside, an image of levitation that is at once drolly mundane and magical. Elsewhere, young friends and relatives career wildly in homemade cars and the artist's brother, Zissou, try to take off in a homemade glider. In one especially amusing picture, Zissou floats in an aquatic vessel of his own invention -- an inflated tire tube with waders attached. Sitting upright, he wears a suit, a hat, spectacles and an expression of studied seriousness.</p>
        <p>Later come pictures of women on parade wearing the latest styles; the teenage photographer seems to regard them as mysteriously exotic creatures. One of the exhibition's largest prints shows a frieze of three monumental women at the race track, in chic gowns and hats, all in profile looking in the same direction; it could be a scene from ''My Fair Lady.'' Finally, a series of portraits of a darkly beautiful young woman named Renee Perle, dating from 1930-31, exudes a Vermeer-like erotic delicacy.</p>
        <p>Almost always Lartigue's work is fresh and effortlessly composed -- nothing in this show has the usual stiffness of old photographs. He was, after all, a natural.</p>
        <p>KEN JOHNSON</p>
        <p>ART IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
