<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Companies Talk, Who Gets to Listen?; Corporate News Will Soon Flow Simultaneously To Everyone</title>
    <meta content="Y20FAI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/business/20FAIR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Investor Relations Institute</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levitt, Arthur Jr (Chmn)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Louis M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E5D9133EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1828" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Companies Talk, Who Gets to Listen?; Corporate News Will Soon Flow Simultaneously To Everyone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>SEC rule taking effect Oct 23 will require American corporations to divulge important information about their performance to everyone at same time, taking away an advantage now enjoyed by analysts, their customers and big institutional investors; chairman, Arthur Levitt Jr, who has crusaded against selective disclosure, says issue is one of fairness and respect; critics worry that companies, unwilling to risk violating rule, will release less information; National Investor Relations Institute president, Louis M Thompson, says that in the short term there will be less information handed out by companies and higher stock volatility, but that in time analysts will have to do more fundamental work, which is positive; graphs; charts; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ever wondered what you were missing from corporate America? No longer will you have to wait for disclosures that could affect your stock portfolio to be filtered through Wall Street. The days of being shut out of conference calls between executives and analysts are coming to an end.</p>
        <p>Starting on Monday, American corporations will be required to divulge important information about their performance to everyone at the same time. Wall Street, which traditionally heard the news first -- and had the trading advantage -- will have to make room for Main Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ever wondered what you were missing from corporate America? No longer will you have to wait for disclosures that could affect your stock portfolio to be filtered through Wall Street. The days of being shut out of conference calls between executives and analysts are coming to an end.</p>
        <p>Starting on Monday, American corporations will be required to divulge important information about their performance to everyone at the same time. Wall Street, which traditionally heard the news first -- and had the trading advantage -- will have to make room for Main Street.</p>
        <p>While there may be secrets that still end up being leaked, the new rule will bring abrupt changes to the stock market. Regulators expect the market to be less volatile; critics are not so sure.</p>
        <p>The new rule, approved by the Securities and Exchange Commission in August, prohibits the selective disclosure of important information like earnings and revenue projections, announcement of new products or discoveries and other facts crucial to making an investment decision.</p>
        <p>If such information is given to anyone, it must simultaneously be released publicly. If there is an unintentional release of this information, the company must follow up with a formal release within 24 hours or before the beginning of the next trading day.</p>
        <p>Arthur Levitt, the S.E.C. chairman who has crusaded against selective disclosure, said the issue was one of fairness and respect. ''The kind of volatility, uncertainty and even insider trading created by a system which depends on winks, nods and whispers is far more dangerous to our markets than a system which respects the intelligence of investors who do not need intermediaries to interpret financial information for them,'' he said last week.</p>
        <p>Critics worry that companies, unwilling to risk violating the rule, will just release less information. That, they argue, will lead to more surprises -- bad and good -- and make stocks more volatile.</p>
        <p>Consider Intel, which the S.E.C. cites as one company already meeting requirements of the new regulation. Its stock fell 22 percent in a day last month after the company said third-quarter revenue would grow less than expected. In the past, a company that big might have been able to nudge down investor expectations by spoon-feeding private signals to analysts before the earnings announcement. While the stock probably would have fallen anyway, the decline might not have been as sudden, or as fast.</p>
        <p>But Intel has not been a nudger, and therefore is an example of how the fair-disclosure world could work. While abrupt, such stock moves at least affect all investors equally. And the current practice of selective disclosure increases stock volatility in its own way. With many investors counting on earnings forecasts to be well managed by some companies, a miss of a mere penny or so can send a stock tumbling.</p>
        <p>The new regulation is already affecting behavior, and making some companies cautious beyond cautious.</p>
        <p>When DuPont sent the group vice president and general manager of DuPont iTechnologies to address a chemical industry conference at Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette, for example, DuPont issued a release saying that the talk ''will not contain significant new announcements.'' In addition, the executive, John C. Hodgson, was briefed on how to answer questions without inadvertently disclosing significant new information, said Ann K. M. Gualtieri, DuPont's vice president for investor relations.</p>
        <p>''We are likely to bend over backwards to avoid the appearance of preferential treatment,'' she said.</p>
        <p>At Gillette, Eric Kraus, the vice president for corporate communications, said, ''there will be a significant increase in the number of press releases we issue'' to ensure that any important company information that might be mentioned to an analyst or money manager is also made public at the same time.</p>
        <p>Broadcasting of Wall Street analysts' meetings on the Internet, what is known as Webcasting, is already becoming standard procedure and will grow, as will public access to conference calls that companies use to brief analysts. The National Investor Relations Institute said 86 percent of its member companies that hold earnings conference calls allowed individual investors to listen in, up from 29 percent two years ago. About 74 percent let the news media listen in, up from 14 percent. Companies are also lobbying investment banks to let them Webcast their executives' presentations at these traditionally closed sessions.</p>
        <p>(The New York Times Company will begin Webcasting its earnings conference call when fourth-quarter results are released, probably in February, according to Catherine Mathis, a Times spokeswoman. Until now, the company limited its conference calls to analysts and shareholders, and excluded the news media.)</p>
        <p>In the short term, Louis M. Thompson Jr., president of the National Investor Relations Institute, said there would be less information handed out by companies and higher stock volatility. But in time, he said ''analysts will have to do more fundamental work and that is positive.''</p>
        <p>The new regulation will take away the advantage of early knowledge of vital company information -- conveyed directly or indirectly -- that has been enjoyed by analysts, their customers and big institutional buyers over the general public, which often does not hear good or bad news until the stock has already moved.</p>
        <p>An example of this kind of selective disclosure came in June when a Merrill Lynch analyst, Stephen McClellan, lowered his second-quarter revenue estimate for Electronic Data Systems after meeting with company executives. The stock fell 8.5 percent on June 8, though E.D.S. did not confirm the new estimate all day. In the evening, the company did call other analysts to say the revenue number would move from middle single digits to lower single digits. Not until the morning of June 9, before the market opened, did E.D.S. make a public announcement of the changed forecast. That day, the stock fell another 24 percent.</p>
        <p>The change that Oracle put in place with its quarterly earnings announcement last month makes clear how ''guidance'' was given to analysts privately in the past and how that practice will change.</p>
        <p>Stephanie Aas, senior director for investor relations, said that Oracle used to not make any forecast of revenue or earnings when it announced quarterly results. Instead, it would meet with Wall Street analysts privately, or speak with them on the telephone. In those conversations, Oracle would not make any forecasts either. But she said the company official and the analyst could discuss the analyst's earnings forecast. ''And if they were out of range we would build a case on why they were out of range,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Now Oracle will make specific revenue and earnings forecasts at the quarterly conference calls, which are already being broadcast on the Internet.</p>
        <p>But some lawyers who are offering advice on the new rule suggest that it is possible that some companies will still try to guide individual analysts in an effort to manage market expectations for their earnings.</p>
        <p>''My sense,'' one lawyer said, ''is a lot of companies will say: 'On the one hand, if I do selective disclosure I will get my wrist slapped, but if I let the earnings forecasts of some analysts remain way out of line, then my stock will get creamed in the market.' ''</p>
        <p>Stephen M. Cutler, the deputy enforcement director at the S.E.C., warned companies not to consider such ploys. If there is a pattern of intentional selective disclosure, he said, the new regulation will be enforced vigorously.</p>
        <p>There is also the possibility, some critics say, that companies, to avoid the risk of violating the rule, will reduce the amount of information they impart to analysts -- and through them, to the public. That could lead to more earnings surprises, increasing the chances for an abrupt move in the stock.</p>
        <p>''The concern is that the new regulation will produce a chilling effect, causing companies to reduce significantly communications to analysts, and to release more limited, watered-down information directly to the public,'' Daniel J. Kramer, a partner at the New York law firm of Schulte Roth &amp; Zabel, said in a written analysis of the new regulation.</p>
        <p>In explaining how the future will be different, Mr. Kraus of Gillette said: ''Say you have a conversation with an analyst and he asks if you will still meet the First Call estimates for this quarter's earnings. We will say to the analyst that Fair Disclosure says we cannot comment on that. So we will be providing less exclusive information.''</p>
        <p>This means, he said, that Gillette would even decline to confirm current forecasts on earnings. Otherwise, he said, the company will have to put out a news release. Gillette has more than 20 one-on-one meetings with analysts a year and about two to three telephone calls a day, on average, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cutler said that the S.E.C is ''mindful of the chilling aspect'' of the new regulation and will not be looking for ''marginal violations.'' And, he added, companies have been making decisions about what is material information for years, so this is not a brand-new exercise.</p>
        <p>It is clear, however, that the new rule will change the way that Wall Street analysts work. Until now, a lot of the game has been to stay cozy with a company so that officials there will give the guidance needed to make accurate earnings estimates or to be early with a change in the outlook.</p>
        <p>Now if that information is impossible to get -- or released to the public at the same time -- the job is going to be different. ''It will put a greater premium on analysts doing fundamental work; on understanding what is going on with customers,'' said Christopher T. Stix, a Morgan Stanley Dean Witter analyst.</p>
        <p>It is possible that some smaller companies that are now studied by Wall Street analysts will be dropped because the extra work needed to follow them will not be worth it.</p>
        <p>One brokerage firm executive summed up the uncertainty, ''We are still finding our way here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
