<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ailment Might Sideline Cook</title>
    <meta content="20SHEA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/sports/20SHEA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240257"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES -- METS NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cook, Dennis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Agbayani, Benny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E2D6133EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ailment Might Sideline Cook</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets' reliever Dennis Cook has kidney stone and may not be available when World Series begins; photo of Benny Agbayani (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even though he announced his starting pitching rotation yesterday, Bobby Valentine has promised not to disclose the Mets' final roster for the World Series until the last possible moment, and now he has good reason to wait. That is because Dennis Cook has a kidney stone, and Valentine is not sure if the reliever will be available when the series begins tomorrow night.</p>
        <p>Cook learned of the kidney stone on Wednesday when he met with doctors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even though he announced his starting pitching rotation yesterday, Bobby Valentine has promised not to disclose the Mets' final roster for the World Series until the last possible moment, and now he has good reason to wait. That is because Dennis Cook has a kidney stone, and Valentine is not sure if the reliever will be available when the series begins tomorrow night.</p>
        <p>Cook learned of the kidney stone on Wednesday when he met with doctors.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the left-handed setup man threw in the outfield with John Franco and then worked out, just like any other day. But afterward, he was to consult with more doctors, searching for a solution to the ailment.  ''Dennis Cook has a situation that we're going to wait on,'' Valentine said. ''He has a kidney stone, and we're trying to get him taken care of. It's causing a lot of discomfort. Today, he feels like it's O.K., but that's a very precarious situation. It could lodge somewhere where it's not O.K. Hell's bells, it could be in the fifth inning.''</p>
        <p>While Cook was more confident that he would be able to pitch, his condition is an important factor in this series. He pitched in three games in the postseason without allowing a run and has gone 16 postseason games, spanning 16 innings, without ever allowing a run. As a member of the 1997 champion Florida Marlins, Cook pitched in three of the seven games in the World Series, striking out five and allowing just one hit in three and two-thirds innings.</p>
        <p>But Cook did have trouble with the Yankees this season, allowing five runs and eight hits in one and two-thirds innings of work in two games.  ''There is a little bit of discomfort, but I don't think it's anything that's going to stop me from pitching,'' said Cook, who underwent a CAT scan on Wednesday. ''I'm going to see another doctor and we're going to determine the best follow-up on it so I'll be able to go 100 percent when the Series gets here.''</p>
        <p>If Cook can not pitch, the Mets will have to decide on a replacement. It could be the right-handed reliever Pat Mahomes, who has yet to be on a postseason roster, or it could be Bobby M. Jones, a left-hander who spent much of the season in the minors but pitched well for the Mets in September. If Cook is placed on the disabled list, then the Mets could add any pitcher from the organization.</p>
        <p>Making the Rounds</p>
        <p>While players like Mike Piazza or Al Leiter normally find the spotlight, Benny Agbayani was very visible yesterday morning before the Mets workout.</p>
        <p>He appeared on the Howard Stern radio show, not answering most of the risque questions but giving in to requests for a prediction, opting to choose the Mets in five games. He then continued on to the ''Live With Regis'' show on ABC, appearing ahead of Senator Joseph Lieberman, the Democratic vice-presidential candidate; and Victoria Beckham, better known as Posh Spice of the Spice Girls.</p>
        <p>Regis Philbin, who noted he was a Yankee fan, asked Agbayani if the Mets had a ''shot against the Yankees.'' Agbayani replied: ''If we play the way we've been playing, we have a good shot.''</p>
        <p>''So what's your prediction?'' Philbin later asked.</p>
        <p>''Mets in five,'' Agbayani replied. ''Talk about confidence,'' Philbin shouted as the audience laughed and applauded.</p>
        <p>Afterward at Shea, Agbayani said: ''I'm not one of the superstars on this team. I didn't figure I'd be a person that people would want to go on a show and talk. It was fun and it was exciting. It was my first experience doing that kind of thing.''</p>
        <p>Of his exchange with Stern, Agbayani said: ''It could have been worse. . . . For me, I think he was at an even keel.''</p>
        <p>As for the Yankee reaction to Agbayani's prediction, Derek Jeter chuckled in the Yankee clubhouse and said: ''I'm not going to make any predictions. Because if you're wrong and the other team happens to win, you're going to be in a lot of trouble.</p>
        <p>''There's no need to talk about it. You go out on the field and you play. You get in trouble when you say some things and then you do something wrong, so I don't think anyone in here is going to make any predictions.''</p>
        <p>Asked why he was laughing, Jeter said, ''It takes a lot of courage to make a prediction like that. Hopefully, he's wrong.''</p>
        <p>Knee Troubles</p>
        <p>Armando Benitez has been bothered by an arthritic right knee, but the Mets believe that it will not hinder him in the World Series. The hard-throwing closer had surgery immediately following last season. And although the knee still troubles him, he did play catch on Wednesday and said he would have been available if needed in Game 5 of the National League Championship Series.</p>
        <p>A Rat's Chance</p>
        <p>The appearance of a black cat on the field at Shea Stadium in September 1969, scampering past the Chicago Cubs' dugout, made some belief the Mets had a bit of black magic on their side in the race for the National League Eastern Division crown. But make what you will of the sighting yesterday.</p>
        <p>While a few players spoke with  reporters in the Mets clubhouse, John Franco spotted a small mouse running through the crowd. Franco tried in vain to catch the mouse and save it from the shoes clomping around it. But the mouse eluded Franco and made its way into the office of the equipment manager, Charlie Samuels, disappearing from sight.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES -- METS NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
