<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Images of Still Water That Always Run Deep</title>
    <meta content="20BOXE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/arts/20BOXE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Whitney Museum of American Art</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horn, Roni</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boxer, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DB153EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1082" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Images of Still Water That Always Run Deep</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH BOXER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Boxer, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sarah Boxer reviews Roni Horn's photographs of water, printed as lithographs, at Whitney Museum; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''The minimum you can say about life is that it's wet.''</p>
        <p>How true. But who says things like that? On the opening night of the exhibition ''Roni Horn: Still Water (The River Thames, for Example)'' at the Whitney Museum of American Art, Ms. Horn stood in a darkened auditorium and recited -- in a smooth, measured, dry voice -- some of her wandering thoughts about water. Projected on a screen behind her were pictures she had taken of the Thames in May 1999. The people in the audience stared at the screen in front of them like little children lulled on the raft of Ms. Horn's free associations. It was a night to remember.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''The minimum you can say about life is that it's wet.''</p>
        <p>How true. But who says things like that? On the opening night of the exhibition ''Roni Horn: Still Water (The River Thames, for Example)'' at the Whitney Museum of American Art, Ms. Horn stood in a darkened auditorium and recited -- in a smooth, measured, dry voice -- some of her wandering thoughts about water. Projected on a screen behind her were pictures she had taken of the Thames in May 1999. The people in the audience stared at the screen in front of them like little children lulled on the raft of Ms. Horn's free associations. It was a night to remember.</p>
        <p>If you ever have the chance to hear Ms. Horn read, especially about water, you should quickly row there. But for now, you will have to settle for absorbing her thoughts in another way -- either in book form, ''Another Water'' (Scalo, 2000), or in the small exhibition of 15 photographs at the Whitney.</p>
        <p>Ms. Horn's pictures, printed as lithographs, are of water only. No shores, no boats, no bridges; only bubbles, roils, undulations and occasional flat patches. Her pictures are shades of gray, black, yellow, brown, blue and white. Some look shiny in places and others are almost uniformly murky. Some are abstract and others are clearly what they are, water. All are absorbing in one way or another. All were taken in medias Thames, but you can't tell exactly where, because there are no reference points.</p>
        <p>Or at least not visual reference points. The notable thing about these photographic images is that they are littered with tiny numbers, each of which refers to a footnote at the bottom of the print. The footnotes, cross-referenced to other footnotes, are Ms. Horn's private thoughts about water. (Her past projects have involved weather and geometry.) Some are about color, blackness and wetness. Others are song lyrics that float up from the river to Ms. Horn's mind. Many are accounts of suicides, people who have come specifically to the Thames to end it all. Happy thoughts!</p>
        <p>There is one yellowish photograph of the Thames, for example. It shows a little white froth at the lower right corner, some patches of baby blue and a few wisps of brown. It looks a little like a desert. Many of the footnotes run along a brownish crevice in the water.</p>
        <p>They go like this: ''28 Is this khaki or beige? 29 Is this beige or ochre? 30 Is this ochre or yellow? 31 Is this yellow or tan? 32 Is this tan or brown? 33 Is this brown or black? 34 Is this black. . . . 36 What does water look like? 37 See Sand (Especially sand dunes.) 38 See deserts, for example the Gobi or the Sahara. 39 There's a story (it's true) about a man traveling by Tube to Westminster Bridge handcuffed to a chair. He threw himself in the river with the chair. He was found some days later downstream attached to a stick of wood and a section of naugahyde (almond-colored).''</p>
        <p>The color exercise is fun. At every point, you can look at the picture of the yellowish river and think, ''Is this beige or ochre?'' and ''Is this ochre or yellow?'' It is strangely absorbing. It is nice to be carried away by someone else's thoughts while looking at water, to see whether your thoughts match hers.</p>
        <p>For example, there is a flat blob in the middle of one very black picture. You would think Ms. Horn might be wondering what caused it. But her thoughts are elsewhere. She writes, ''A Rat surrendered here,'' and in the next footnote she writes, ''See poem No. 1340 by Emily Dickinson.'' I see the poem. It is about a rat in a trap and the dangers of temptation.</p>
        <p>The pictures put you in the mood for vagueness. But the footnotes put you in the mood for exactitude. You want assurance that the numbers in the water are closely related to their notes. That is, you want her to think about black water in the black passages of the river. But it doesn't always work out that way. The more carefully you look at the footnotes, comparing them to the passages in the river, the less matched they seem.</p>
        <p>Yet if you follow Ms. Horn's thoughts in any direction, you will notice a great consistency there. She is interested in the transparency of water -- why water, when taken in small quantities, is transparent -- and she is interested in its filth. She insists numerous times that ''black water isn't sexy.'' And sometimes she is confiding: ''Doesn't this picture look familiar? Are you thinking Claude Monet, too?''</p>
        <p>She likes circular references. She writes about ''this notation'' and the ''brownish color of the ink deployed to image the water.'' She notes, ''My gaze alights on the water -- on some spot (this spot) on the river.'' She is obsessed with certain words: dismemberment, darkness, disappearance. And with certain popular songs: ''Blah, blah, blah, your hair,/ Blah, blah, blah, your eyes;/Blah, blah, blah, blah, care,/ Blah, blah, blah, blah, skies.'' Certain people figure prominently in her thoughts: Blake, Heidegger, Dickinson, Conrad, Ira Gershwin and Aretha Franklin.</p>
        <p>But most memorably she is fascinated by river suicides. (Could Peter Greenaway's movie ''Drowning by Numbers'' have inspired her?) She notes that water is ''a soft entrance to not being here,'' a ''solvent for identity.'' She says people go to die in the Thames, but not the Hudson. She observes how many bodies found in the Thames are found dismembered. ''Where is the torso?'' She likes to describe what the people were wearing and the notes and jewelry they left behind.</p>
        <p>And she manages to be funny, in a deadpan kind of way. ''I doubt you've had this experience,'' she confides, ''but last night when I was watching the water 'I Say a Little Prayer' wafted up from the river. (It came along in a faster tempo than the version I remembered.)''</p>
        <p>''Roni Horn: Still Water (The River Thames, for Example)'' is at the Whitney Museum of American Art, 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3600, through Jan. 14.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
