<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Roman Rarities to Mickey Mouse, a Global Bazaar</title>
    <meta content="20GLUE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="47" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/arts/20GLUE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240200"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Fine Art and Antique Dealers Show</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glueck, Grace</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DD133EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1615" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Roman Rarities to Mickey Mouse, a Global Bazaar</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRACE GLUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glueck, Grace</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Grace Glueck reviews some of works at International Fine Art and Antique Dealers Show in New York; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Emerging triumphant from acres of shipping containers and oceans of bubble wrap, the International Fine Art and Antique Dealers Show has ensconced itself in the Seventh Regiment Armory for its 12th annual appearance in New York.</p>
        <p>On hand through Thursday are 72 dealers from the United States, Canada and Europe, offering furniture, paintings, silver, ceramics, rugs, textiles, antiquities, jewelry, wallpaper, books, manuscripts and other treasures in a glamorous one-stop shopping mall that adds pizazz to the city's status as a mecca for art and antiques buying.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Emerging triumphant from acres of shipping containers and oceans of bubble wrap, the International Fine Art and Antique Dealers Show has ensconced itself in the Seventh Regiment Armory for its 12th annual appearance in New York.</p>
        <p>On hand through Thursday are 72 dealers from the United States, Canada and Europe, offering furniture, paintings, silver, ceramics, rugs, textiles, antiquities, jewelry, wallpaper, books, manuscripts and other treasures in a glamorous one-stop shopping mall that adds pizazz to the city's status as a mecca for art and antiques buying.</p>
        <p>''Even though we're based in New York, we like to exhibit at the fair because it provides a broader context for the objects and creates excitement and competitiveness among collectors,'' said Michael Ward of Ward &amp; Company, which specializes in antiquities and medieval art. ''It's a kind of dealers' answer to the auction houses.''</p>
        <p>The usual dealers' haunts of New York, Boston, Paris and London are well represented here, but exhibitors have also come from places like Norfolk, Conn.; San Francisco; Amsterdam; Bremen, Germany; Brussels and Antwerp, Belgium; Ontario, Canada; and, in England, Shipston-on-Stour. The show's offerings date from the third millennium B.C. to the present, and among the wide range of rarities for sale are an ingeniously carved Mayan vase of white marble (about 900 A.D.) from Honduras, at Lin and Emile Deletaille; a pair of Scottish belt pistols with brass fishtail stocks, dated 1622, at Peter Finer; a George III English library table of mahogany with a ladder that folds up inside of it, at Jeremy Ltd.; and several Mickey Mouse pop-up books issued by Disney in the 1930's, tucked among the shelves of sober leather bindings at Ursus Books.</p>
        <p>The upmarket fair, whose contents are checked for authenticity and proper dating by specialists in each field before the official opening, was started in 1989 by Anna and Brian Haughton, London dealers in 18th- and 19th-century English and Continental ceramics. It draws about 22,500 visitors each year, Ms. Haughton said, with more than 58 percent from outside New York City.</p>
        <p>Although this fair is more attuned to furniture and objects than to fine art -- the Haughtons also run the International Fine Art Fair here each May -- some standout paintings are on view, including three from Paris dealers. De Jonckheere shows ''The Wedding Dance in an Interior'' (1622), a lively scene with some naughty goings-on by the 17th-century Flemish artist Pieter Brueghel the Younger.</p>
        <p>''The Harvesting of Apples,'' a blazingly colored allegorical triptych by Paul Serusier (1863-1927), a founder of the Gauguin-influenced Nabi group in France, is on view at the Galerie Hopkins-Thomas-Custot. And a spare, sketchy but wonderfully fluent Monet oil of 1880, ''Sunset on the Seine at Vetheuil,'' makes its first American bow at Philippe Cazeau-Jacques de la Beraudiere.</p>
        <p>Among noteworthy works of sculpture are a piece of found wood fashioned by Picasso into a head (1943) at the Belgian dealer Axel Vervoordt; a small prancing bronze horse (no date) by Degas at Browse &amp; Darby of London; and a grisly portrayal in marble (1680) by Agostino Cornacchini of two lions in a death struggle at Antoine Cheneviere Fine Arts of London.</p>
        <p>In furniture, dealers in 20th-century works, whose presence at the fair seems to be growing, make a strong stand. Philippe Denys of Brussels offers a knockout Italian side cabinet, circa 1940, entirely covered in white parchment. With its organically sculptured body and heavy but gracefully tapered legs of fluted walnut, it could have emerged from a Surrealist painting.</p>
        <p>At Ciancimino Ltd. of London, two sets of funnel-shaped hanging lights circa 1935, Art Deco style in white painted metal and chrome by the French designer Jacques Adnet, share honors with a whole roomful of vintage Adnet furniture, including two elegant boudoir pieces covered in white shagreen, the hard, rough skin of a shark.</p>
        <p>Among the stellar attractions at Vallois of Paris are an African-influenced head of a woman, carved in wood (1920) by the English designer Eileen Gray, and a lustrous, mirror-smooth screen of black lacquer on one side, red on the other (1930), by the Swiss-born designer Jean Dunand, a master lacquer craftsman.</p>
        <p>Dealers in older furniture have flushed out some significant trophies, too. At Mallett of London, one show-stopper is a small English roll-top desk of satinwood and mahogany, graceful in shape and magnificently inlaid with marquetry. Once owned by the Earl of Rosebery, it is thought to have been turned out around 1785 by Mayhew &amp; Ince, a fashionable cabinetmaker of the period,</p>
        <p>Another stunner, shown by Maroun H. Salloum of Paris, is a massive sideboard of mahogany with marquetry inlay designed by George Jack for the English firm Morris &amp; Company around 1887. Designed for the display of silver or china, with built-in candlestands at either end, the sideboard has shelves that have protective flaps of embossed leather at their bottoms.</p>
        <p>American furniture also has its innings, with Hirschl &amp; Adler of New York displaying an ensemble of neo-Classical period pieces from New York, Boston and Philadelphia. At Carswell Rush Berlin, also of New York, one showpiece is a sideboard unusually open in structure. Of matched flame mahogany, with brass mounts, this Duncan Phyfe-style piece was made in New York around 1810. Its upper case is supported only by columns and an undershelf.</p>
        <p>Antiquities and medieval and Renaissance works are by no means scanted here. At Ward &amp; Company of New York, a wistful Roman marble portrait bust of a noblewoman, circa 130 A.D., steals the show. Among many treasures at the Blumka Gallery, also of New York, a 14th-century bronze aquamanile, or vessel, from northern Germany in the form of a slim warrior on a fat horse, arrests the eye.</p>
        <p>One of the oldest works here is at the Galerie Blondeel Deroyan of Paris: a wonderful silver vase, with a modern-looking sculptural motif of ibexes walking, from Bactria, that dates to the third millennium B.C. And at Doris Wiener of New York, a Chola Dynasty bronze from southern India, from the 12th century A.D., depicts a marvelously detailed, animated version of the goddess Parvati, whose erotic body seems ready to begin a dance.</p>
        <p>As usual at this fair, there is a lot of Chinese-influenced work. The French firm of Ariane Dandois shows a pair of striking painted and gilded Italian doors from the mid-19th century. Carved in high relief and polychromed, they have Chinese figures as their central motifs, surrounded by bamboo strapwork, bells and Chinese characters.</p>
        <p>The Chinese flavor is also seen in tapestries, most notably in a stunning ensemble of four early-18th-century works from Brussels at the Paris-based Galerie Chevalier. Woven in wool, silk, silver and gold, they have black grounds adorned with delicately drawn Chinese fantasy scenes, presumably inspired by Asian lacquerwork and by the 17th-century series ''The Story of the Emperor of China,'' woven at the Beauvais tapestry works in France.</p>
        <p>Needlework is the only presentation at Cora Ginsburg of New York, which is showing a sumptuous example of late-16th-century embroidery in the form of three bed valances devoted to the Biblical story of Queen Esther and King Ahasuerus. The tale of Esther's heroism is laid out in a series of domestic scenes, with richly worked decorations of architectural elements and formal gardens, to make a remarkable ensemble.</p>
        <p>Strong narrative works can also be seen at Carolle Thibaut-Pomerantz of New York, probably the only dealer anywhere to specialize in French period wallpaper from the 18th century through the Art Deco period. The most spectacular on view is two panels from a scenic paper of 1812, in grisaille, or gray and white tones, depicting in Neo-classical style the Greek Olympic games. A campy extravaganza, it is a pastoral view replete with gods, goddesses, spectators, palm trees and classical ruins.</p>
        <p>Two dealers in works from tribal cultures make a robust showing. One prize at the Galerie Meyer-Oceanic Art of Paris is a finely carved Maori lintel, stained in red pigment, from a food storage or meeting house. Its grotesque central figure represents a deified ancestor. At the Donald Ellis Gallery of Ontario, a life-size wooden portrait mask of a man (circa 1840-1860), from northern British Columbia, impresses with an austere stylization that nevertheless makes a wonderfully expressive visage.</p>
        <p>But many other irresistible objects command the viewer's attention: a pair of Faberge match holders in the form of egg-shaped birds at Wartski of London; a huge Queen Anne wine cistern of solid silver that may be one of the largest pieces of its kind, at Koopman Ltd. &amp; Rare Art of London; a miniature but regal statue of Sevres porcelain, all in white, depicting the French King Henri IV on horseback, at Brian Haughton Antiques of London.</p>
        <p>A special loan exhibition of 16 early-20th-century ''Mystery Clocks'' from Cartier, so called because their works are ingeniously hidden, is also part of the show, but was not available for viewing on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Some advice: more than one visit is needed to take in the riches of this extraordinary bazaar. Take walking shoes.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
