<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Goes Around Comes Around? Doing Good Deeds in a Bad World</title>
    <meta content="20PAY.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/arts/20PAY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leder, Mimi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A O</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pay It Forward (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By A. O. Scott</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EED6123EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Goes Around Comes Around? Doing Good Deeds in a Bad World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A O</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A O Scott reviews movie Pay It Forward, directed by Mimi Leder; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The title of ''Pay It Forward'' refers to an idea dreamed up by a seventh grader named Trevor McKinney who lives with his mother, a waitress struggling to stay on the wagon, in a modest ranch-style house on the edge of Las Vegas. Trevor's social studies teacher, Mr. Simonet, a sarcastic fellow with a badly scarred face and an impressive vocabulary, has given his class a yearlong extra-credit assignment: to think of something that will change the world and to put it into action.</p>
        <p>Trevor (Haley Joel Osment) concocts a system of expanding generosity that he graphs in his spiral notebook and on the classroom blackboard. He will do a good turn for three people, each of whom will in turn do good to three more, and so on. Mr. Simonet (Kevin Spacey) mocks him gently, suggesting that the project may be a bit utopian. (''Look it up,'' he instructs his puzzled pupils). ''What's wrong with that?'' young Trevor replies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The title of ''Pay It Forward'' refers to an idea dreamed up by a seventh grader named Trevor McKinney who lives with his mother, a waitress struggling to stay on the wagon, in a modest ranch-style house on the edge of Las Vegas. Trevor's social studies teacher, Mr. Simonet, a sarcastic fellow with a badly scarred face and an impressive vocabulary, has given his class a yearlong extra-credit assignment: to think of something that will change the world and to put it into action.</p>
        <p>Trevor (Haley Joel Osment) concocts a system of expanding generosity that he graphs in his spiral notebook and on the classroom blackboard. He will do a good turn for three people, each of whom will in turn do good to three more, and so on. Mr. Simonet (Kevin Spacey) mocks him gently, suggesting that the project may be a bit utopian. (''Look it up,'' he instructs his puzzled pupils). ''What's wrong with that?'' young Trevor replies.</p>
        <p>The concept has a beguiling simplicity, and the movie's thesis is that the rippling out of what a popular bumper sticker calls ''random, senseless acts of kindness'' might tip the world's moral balance and make it a better place. (A real foundation has been set up to foster the spirit of Trevor's project, which in the film spawns a movement.)</p>
        <p>One narrative thread follows the efforts of a cynical journalist (Jay Mohr) to understand why, on a rainy night in Los Angeles, a complete stranger has given him a shiny new Jaguar. His investigation leads him to a swaggering felon, then to an alcoholic who lives in her car and  finally to Trevor. The boy, meanwhile, has been trying to apply his theory, bringing home a homeless drug addict for a feast of cereal and snack cakes and trying to engineer a romance between his harried mother and the tense, guarded Mr. Simonet.</p>
        <p>It's hardly an accident that ''Pay  It Forward'' takes place in a city whose utopian impulse is expressed in the promise of the big score and the dream of a foolproof system for beating the odds. The logic of Trevor's project, after all, is that of a classic pyramid scheme, in which participants recoup their investments by recruiting new suckers, but with benevolence rather than money as the currency. This makes less of a difference than you might think. A fraud is still a fraud.</p>
        <p>A more benign (and legal) version of the pyramid con, ubiquitous on the Internet, is the chain letter. It is a game whose essentially coercive nature -- you're typically threatened with bad luck or at least bad karma if you break it -- is camouflaged in the mystical language of community. ''Pay It Forward'' perpetrates a similar kind of manipulation. It's so enamored of its own upbeat view of human nature that it expects you to overlook its stick-figure characters, its creaky plot machinery and its remorseless assault on your tear ducts.</p>
        <p>That it succeeds at all -- that the film elicits moments of genuine feeling, rather than the derisive laughter it deserves -- is largely thanks to the three principal actors. Helen Hunt, who plays Trevor's mother, Arlene, expands her range with every movie. A tired, unhappy working-class woman trying to overcome a lifetime of addiction and abuse, this character is something of a stretch for her, but Ms. Hunt has managed to expunge all traces of the privileged perkiness that made her character in ''Mad About You'' so annoyingly lovable.</p>
        <p>Her performance is vulnerable, direct and without vanity. When Arlene walks into the kitchen one morning, hung over and dispirited, she looks truly awful -- not like a movie star who has been carefully mussed, but like an almost middle-aged woman who has worked two shifts, drunk too much and fallen asleep without removing her makeup.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spacey and young Mr. Osment, who between them carried the two most improbably successful movies of 1999, take fewer risks. ''Do I strike you as someone who's falsely nice?'' Mr. Simonet asks Trevor at one point. ''You're not even really nice,'' the boy replies, and the exchange neatly summarizes Mr. Spacey's career to date.</p>
        <p>But, of course, there's never any doubt about the essential goodness that lurks inside the teacher's prickly carapace. There's goodness in everyone, except for a gang of schoolyard bullies and Arlene's abusive husband (Jon Bon Jovi), who shows up to spike the film's melodramatic volume. Once again, Mr. Osment, with his cupid's-bow scowl and his watchful blue eyes, is gifted with second sight. He sees nice people.</p>
        <p>Mimi Leder, one of the creative forces behind ''E.R.'' and the director of the hugely successful ''Deep Impact,'' gives her actors no room for modulation. The scenes between Arlene and Mr. Simonet have a rushed, lurching rhythm, and the picture drowns its quieter moments in teary pathos and lump-in-the-throat sitcom humor, all leading up to a final tableau of a thousand candles and a soundtrack hemorrhaging with a song about angels.</p>
        <p>Plausibility and character are sacrificed in what the movie congratulates itself is a good cause. And it would be a tolerably hokey bit of uplift -- a special two-hour episode of ''Touched by an Angel,'' perhaps -- if not for its ending, which the people at Warner Brothers have asked reviewers to refrain from divulging, I'd like to think because they were ashamed of themselves for stooping to gratuitous spiritual pornography.</p>
        <p>In the spirit of the movie, I'll do them the kindness of keeping the secret. In exchange, maybe the studio will approve three honest movies that respect the audience's intelligence and good sense. Is that too utopian?</p>
        <p>''Pay It Forward'' is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has some mild profanity and a number of upsetting scenes.</p>
        <p>PAY IT FORWARD  Directed by Mimi Leder; written by Leslie Dixon, based on the novel by Catherine Ryan Hyde; director of photography, Oliver Stapleton; edited by David Rosenbloom; music by Thomas Newman; production designer, Leslie Dilley; produced by Peter Abrams, Robert Levy and Steven Reuther; released by Warner Brothers Pictures. Running time: 155 minutes. This film is rated PG-13.</p>
        <p>WITH: Kevin Spacey (Eugene Simonet), Helen Hunt (Arlene McKinney), Haley Joel Osment (Trevor McKinney), Jay Mohr (Chris Chandler), James Caviezel (Jerry), Jon Bon Jovi (Ricki) and Angie Dickinson (Grace).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
