<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Plan to Offer High Schoolers Better Choices</title>
    <meta content="20HIGH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/nyregion/20HIGH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240286"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE4DE103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1300" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Plan to Offer High Schoolers Better Choices</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy has proposed a far-reaching plan to change the way most students are assigned to New York City high schools, with an emphasis on creating more appealing choices for students in their own neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>The plan, whose initial details were given to the Board of Education on Wednesday, would also designate neighborhood high schools that would be run by the city's 32 community school districts; create at least one kindergarten-through-12th-grade school in each borough; and overhaul vocational high schools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy has proposed a far-reaching plan to change the way most students are assigned to New York City high schools, with an emphasis on creating more appealing choices for students in their own neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>The plan, whose initial details were given to the Board of Education on Wednesday, would also designate neighborhood high schools that would be run by the city's 32 community school districts; create at least one kindergarten-through-12th-grade school in each borough; and overhaul vocational high schools.</p>
        <p>Except for prestigious schools like the Bronx High School of Science and Stuyvesant High, the city's nearly 200 public high schools have long been seen as troubled, with many plagued by weak academic programs, widespread discipline problems, poor attendance and high dropout rates. Many parents in middle-class neighborhoods -- even those who send their children to public elementary and middle schools -- believe that the city's high schools are not sufficiently rigorous or safe. In recent years, those parents have clamored for a return to the traditional neighborhood high school, which would restrict enrollment to students from the immediate neighborhood or school district.</p>
        <p>Judith Rizzo, the deputy chancellor for instruction and author of the plan, said yesterday that Mr. Levy was not looking to scale back the existing system of school choice, in which students can apply to high schools throughout the city instead of attending one in their neighborhood. But she said that too many neighborhood high schools have become choices of last resort and have suffered from neglect, and that the new plan would result in better and more appealing high schools.</p>
        <p>Only 35 percent of the city's high school students attend their neighborhood schools, her aides said.</p>
        <p>For those who want to leave their neighborhood, Dr. Rizzo said, the process of applying to high schools is too confusing for parents and students, and too often, students do not get admitted to any of the schools on their list of choices. Roughly 45 percent of students who apply to schools outside their neighborhood are not admitted to any. Many of them leave the New York public school system.</p>
        <p>''We want kids to have viable options to stay in their district and their borough if that's what they prefer,'' Dr. Rizzo said yesterday. ''But the overall goal is to guarantee that whichever high school they choose, a top-quality instructional program will be waiting for them.''</p>
        <p>In the past, most New York City high schools were reserved for students who lived in the immediate neighborhood. But in the late 1960's, many of the school attendance zones were redrawn to promote racial integration, and the schools lost their distinct neighborhood character. The ties weakened more over the last 15 years, as the city moved to a system of choice and many schools were broken up into smaller schools with themes like technology or the arts.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rizzo made it clear that she would like to create more appealing and academically rigorous programs within neighborhood high schools. But she also wants to overhaul the system for choosing high schools anywhere in the city, she said. Details of a new assignment system remain to be worked out, and would require board approval.</p>
        <p>She said the current choice system was problematic because of a complicated selection process, which does not guarantee students admission to any of the choices they list in the high school applications they fill out during eighth grade.</p>
        <p>Any change to the high school assignment system would not affect the handful of highly selective schools, like Stuyvesant and Bronx Science, that require applicants to take an admissions test. Instead, the changes would affect dozens of traditional high schools -- including many that have been broken up into magnet, or alternative, schools.</p>
        <p>Under the current assignment system, half of the students at those schools are chosen by the school administrators, supposedly based on grades and test scores. The other half are randomly selected by computer. Using both methods, 16 percent of those selected are supposed to be students who perform below grade level, and 16 percent are supposed to be students who perform above grade level. The remainder are supposed to be average students.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Rizzo said schools in affluent neighborhoods tend to admit more high-achieving students than they are supposed to, while schools in poor neighborhoods get a disproportional number of struggling students.</p>
        <p>While changes to the citywide assignment system are an important part of Mr. Levy's overall plan, he is placing the heaviest emphasis on improving neighborhood high schools. For one thing, he is proposing that each community school district create its own high school, which would draw the majority of its students from the immediate neighborhood or school district. Several such schools are already in the works, including one in District 23 in Brownsville, Brooklyn, and another in District 1 in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy also wants each of the city's five boroughs to have at least one school encompassing kindergarten through 12th grade, which would allow teachers to better know and help students throughout their academic careers.</p>
        <p>In both kinds of high schools, the academic programs would be tailored to match those that the students had in the elementary and middle grades, fostering a smoother academic flow from grade to grade.</p>
        <p>''It's important that the high school curriculum be tied to the preparation kids get in the earlier grades,'' Mr. Levy said. ''That can be done best if there is careful coordination.''</p>
        <p>Both new kinds of high schools would not be built from the ground up in most cases. Rather, the Board of Education would redesign existing schools and put them under the control of the community schools superintendent. One example is John Jay High School in Park Slope, Brooklyn. Under a plan pushed by local parents and supported by the district, John Jay would become a sixth- to 12th-grade school and eventually reduce the number of students coming from outside the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rizzo said she also wanted to overhaul vocational high schools, so that their curriculums were more aligned with the state's rigorous new academic standards. And she wants to replicate popular themed schools, like Fiorello H. La Guardia High School for Music and Art and Performing Arts in Manhattan, so that each borough has one.</p>
        <p>One question about the plan is whether revamped neighborhood high schools would redraw their attendance zones in ways that would be perceived as elitist or racist. In predominantly white neighborhoods like Park Slope and the Upper East Side, where middle-class parents are already demanding a return to neighborhood high schools, a rezoning would almost certainly decrease the number of minority students.</p>
        <p>Another challenge is ensuring that poor neighborhoods get redesigned schools that are just as rigorous as those in affluent neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Levy said it made sense to re-examine the attendance zones for many neighborhood high schools, because they were drawn up decades ago to promote racial integration. Many of those neighborhoods no longer have substantially white populations, he said, so the integration issue is moot.</p>
        <p>''Right now the high schools are zoned to serve purposes that are essentially historic and no longer valid,'' he said. ''Saying that we want to rethink how zoning works is simply recognizing that communities have changed.''</p>
        <p>Two Board of Education members, Terri Thomson of Queens and Jerry Cammarata of Staten Island, said yesterday that it was too early to comment on the rezoning issue. But they said they strongly supported the idea of overhauling the high school assignment process.</p>
        <p>''We need to beef up these neighborhood schools so they are viable choices,'' Ms. Thomson said. ''I'm really delighted it's now on the front burner.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
