<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Connecticut Approves Plan For Takeover By Con Ed</title>
    <meta content="20CONE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/nyregion/20CONE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001030T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240268"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northeastern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Hampshire</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consolidated Edison Co of New York Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Northeast Utilities</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zielbauer, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Richard (Atty Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DF103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Connecticut Approves Plan For Takeover By Con Ed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL ZIELBAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zielbauer, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Connecticut Dept of Public Utility Control, over objections of state's atty gen, Richard Blumenthal, gives its final approval to Consolidated Edison's proposed $3.8 billion acquisition of Northeast Utilities; if deal is approved by New Hampshire and two federal agencies, it will create largest gas and electric utility in Northeast, with 6.5 million customers in eight states (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the objections of Connecticut's attorney general, the state's regulatory authority gave its final approval yesterday to Consolidated Edison's proposed $3.8 billion acquisition of Northeast Utilities.</p>
        <p>If the deal is approved by New Hampshire and two federal agencies, it will create the largest gas and electric utility in the Northeast, with 6.5 million customers in eight states.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the objections of Connecticut's attorney general, the state's regulatory authority gave its final approval yesterday to Consolidated Edison's proposed $3.8 billion acquisition of Northeast Utilities.</p>
        <p>If the deal is approved by New Hampshire and two federal agencies, it will create the largest gas and electric utility in the Northeast, with 6.5 million customers in eight states.</p>
        <p>The acquisition would be the latest in a string of East Coast utility mergers, prompted by competition in a market where electricity generation is no longer regulated, though its distribution is.</p>
        <p>There is some doubt, however, whether the two companies will agree to the terms of the merger set today by the State Department of Public Utility Control.</p>
        <p>The agency's five commissioners voted 4 to 1 to accept a modified version of a 146-page draft document that set the conditions the companies will need to fulfill. But yesterday the department issued only a three-page news release, not its detailed final approval document. Beryl Lyons, a spokeswoman for the authority, said the details of the state's approval would be released this morning.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for both companies declined to comment on the state's approval until they reviewed the details.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Con Ed's chairman, Eugene R. McGrath, criticized the Sept. 22 draft document approving the merger, saying that its conditions were too harsh and that the deal did not benefit company shareholders.</p>
        <p>Richard Blumenthal, the state attorney general, said yesterday that he was so opposed to the merger that he was considering challenging the state's ruling in court, and he called Con Ed ''the worst possible partner'' for Northeast Utilities, which also owns Yankee Gas and is based in Berlin, Conn.</p>
        <p>''The rate reductions are trivial and totally inadequate,'' Mr. Blumenthal said referring to the state's conditions. ''The threat to the environment is real and immediate,'' and the conditions set by the state utility control board, he added, ''are weaker than they were in the draft.''</p>
        <p>He, along with many Connecticut residents, also expressed concern over Con Ed's reputation for unreliability and poor customer service in light of blackouts and brownouts that New York City customers have endured in recent years.</p>
        <p>Connecticut is the sixth state to approve the merger conditionally, following in the regulatory footsteps of Maine, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Vermont and New York, whose Public Service Commission approved the deal early last month. The deal also appears to be on track in Massachusetts, where there is no formal approval process, only a requirement that the two companies submit a letter describing their plans.</p>
        <p>Each state's assent follows different guidelines, and Connecticut's approval of the deal includes many requirements that could deter the companies.</p>
        <p>For instance, Connecticut requires Con Ed to pay an ''acquisition premium'' of $1.5 billion, which is included in the $3.8 billion takeover price. Within two months of the merger, Connecticut would also require one of Northeast Utilities' subsidiaries, Connecticut Light &amp; Power, to take measures that would reduce residential nonheating prices by about 1 percent, saving consumers $45 million over three years.</p>
        <p>The state would also impose a two-year ban on Con Ed's ability to impose involuntary layoffs of Connecticut workers and would forbid the utility to recover costs incurred from the merger by raising consumer prices. In addition, the state would add hundreds of acres of utility-owned land that the merged companies, to be known as New Consolidated Edison, would have to offer to sell to Connecticut municipalities before selling them elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lyons, the state agency's spokeswoman, said the merger, as arranged by the authority, would be good for the companies and for Connecticut consumers.</p>
        <p>The utility companies said banding together was the only way to survive in an increasingly competitive market for gas and electric power.</p>
        <p>If the two companies agree to Connecticut's merger conditions, there will be three other regulatory hurdles to clear. The first is New Hampshire, which recently completed its review and is expected to issue a decision within weeks.</p>
        <p>After that, final assent will have to come from the United States Department of Justice and the Securities and Exchange Commission, officials said.</p>
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission approved the merger on Aug. 22, said Mr. Poirot, and the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission approved it on June 1.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 30, 2000, Monday  An article on Oct. 20 about Connecticut regulators' approval of the proposed acquisition of Northeast Utilities by Consolidated Edison included an erroneous name, supplied by the regulators, for the company that would result. (The error was repeated in an article on Wednesday.) It would be Consolidated Edison, not New Consolidated Edison.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 30, 2000, Monday</p>
        <p>An article on Oct. 20 about Connecticut regulators' approval of the proposed acquisition of Northeast Utilities by Consolidated Edison included an erroneous name, supplied by the regulators, for the company that would result. (The error was repeated in an article on Wednesday.) It would be Consolidated Edison, not New Consolidated Edison.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
