<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boy Is Stabbed in Brooklyn After School-Cafeteria Fight</title>
    <meta content="20STAB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/nyregion/20STAB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240303"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gootman, Elissa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haynes, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gregoire, Rickley</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hall, Eduardo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E4DD103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boy Is Stabbed in Brooklyn After School-Cafeteria Fight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISSA GOOTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gootman, Elissa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fight that begins in Canarsie High School, Brooklyn, cafeteria ends in fatal stabbing of a 12-year-old immigrant from Guyana, Anthony Haynes, outside of school; two 16-year-olds, Rickley Gregoire and Eduardo Hall, are arrested; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A fight that began in a high school cafeteria ended in the fatal stabbing of a 12-year-old immigrant from Guyana yesterday, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>Two 16-year-olds were arrested in the stabbing, which appeared to stem from a dispute involving four boys that began about 11 a.m. in the cafeteria at Canarsie High School, and resumed hours later near the school, the police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A fight that began in a high school cafeteria ended in the fatal stabbing of a 12-year-old immigrant from Guyana yesterday, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>Two 16-year-olds were arrested in the stabbing, which appeared to stem from a dispute involving four boys that began about 11 a.m. in the cafeteria at Canarsie High School, and resumed hours later near the school, the police said.</p>
        <p>The suspects, Rickley Gregoire and Eduardo Hall, both of Brooklyn, were apparently fighting with the victim, Anthony Haynes, and a 15-year-old boy. Three of the boys are students at the high school, but it was not clear why Anthony, a student at Intermediate School 211, was in the cafeteria yesterday morning. His parents said he had been suspended from that school.</p>
        <p>Just before the stabbing, the boy who had been with Anthony in the cafeteria was arrested when a police officer spotted him allegedly carrying a .44 Magnum in his waistband several blocks from the school. That youth, whose name was not released because of his age, is being charged with weapons possession, said Sgt. Elias Nikas, a police spokesman.</p>
        <p>About 15 minutes later, Anthony was stabbed once in the chest in front of 1536 Rockaway Parkway, less than a block from the school, the police said. The suspects were arrested after the police canvassed the area and a knife was found on the ground nearby, Sergeant Nikas said. Last night, the police were questioning both boys, the sergeant said.</p>
        <p>The victim was taken to Brookdale University Hospital and Medical Center, where he died in the operating room at 4:07 p.m. from a stab wound to the heart, said Malcolm E. Kafka, a hospital spokesman.</p>
        <p>While the police said last night that they were still investigating whether the stabbing might have been gang-related, several friends of the victim said that he was a member of what members called a Crips gang and that he had been taunting the suspects, who they said belonged to a  Bloods gang.</p>
        <p>Last night, Anthony's parents stood, shocked, in the hallway of the two-story brick building where the family moved after coming from Guyana in 1997.</p>
        <p>''People told me that the children here are bad, that they have guns, that they have drugs,'' said the victim's father, Vincent Haynes, 55. In recent years, Mr. Haynes said, he has felt his son ''drifting away.''</p>
        <p>One girl, who identified herself only as a member of the Crips, said she saw Anthony taunt the suspects just before he was stabbed, saying, ''Crips, Crips.''</p>
        <p>Last night, two of Anthony's cousins sat on a stoop outside the two-story Rockaway Parkway building where, they said, Anthony had lived with his parents since the family came to the United States. They said his father worked as a grocery wholesaler and his mother worked in a department store.</p>
        <p>The cousins, who declined to give their names for fear of retribution, said that Anthony was not involved in a gang and did not use drugs.</p>
        <p>''We migrated from a third-world country to come here for a better life, and now we come here to have this happen to a child,'' said one cousin, who is 26 and lives in East Flatbush.''It's just devastating to see what can happen when a child gets caught up in the wrong crowd.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
