<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'The Tavern'</title>
    <meta content="RV001133" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/arts/20ROUN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foote, Walter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Tavern, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2DC103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'The Tavern'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawrence Van Gelder reviews The Tavern, movie written and directed by Walter Foote; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Directed by Walter Foote  Not rated; 88 minutes</p>
        <p>Sometime, somewhere, some professor at a school of business will program a double feature of ''Two Family House'' and ''The Tavern.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Directed by Walter Foote  Not rated; 88 minutes</p>
        <p>Sometime, somewhere, some professor at a school of business will program a double feature of ''Two Family House'' and ''The Tavern.''</p>
        <p>They are cautionary tales of the pitfalls of small-business ownership, in particular the ownership of a bar.</p>
        <p>But where ''Two Family House,'' which opened two weeks ago, is bathed in warm sentiment, ''The Tavern,'' opening today at the Village East (Second Avenue at 12th Street, East Village), is more like a plunge into chill waters. Astringent and unsentimental, it is a case study of losing, its clear eye focused unwaveringly on the realities of commerce and kinship, its ear and heart closed to the temptation of a happy ending it knows to be a lie.</p>
        <p>Written, directed and produced by Walter Foote, a son of the playwright Horton Foote, ''The Tavern'' is surehanded, sober-eyed and bracing. Focused on Cameron Dye as Ronnie, a bartender on the far downside of unfocused youth, the film tells of a dream that goes up in smoke.</p>
        <p>Ronnie's dream is to own a bar. And when the opportunity arises to buy out Kevin (Greg Zittel), a tavern owner who says he is moving to Florida, Ronnie sees his big chance. The problem is that he doesn't have enough money. Turned down by his father, who reminds Ronnie that there is a difference between being a bartender and running a bar, he borrows some money from his boss, Jerry (Steven Marcus), who has a bad habit of betting with bookmakers. And Ronnie borrows some more from his widowed sister-in-law, Gina (Nancy Ticotin), pledging in return that he will provide work for her rebellious teenage son, Tommy (Carlo Alban), who isn't doing well in school and is hanging around late at night with the wrong crowd.</p>
        <p>The rest of the money comes from Ronnie's buddy and partner, Dave (Kevin Geer), an assistant manager at a megastore, whose wife, Carol (Margaret Cho), has serious misgivings about the friends' venture.</p>
        <p>For a while things seem to be going well, but from a business standpoint, Ronnie and Dave's Tavern on Main is underfinanced and unprepared for cutthroat competition. To begin with, Kevin has lied. Having sold his old place to Ronnie, he promptly opens a new one close enough to pull business from the Tavern on Main. When Ronnie retaliates by stealing Kevin's gifted chef, Miguel (Gary Perez), Kevin uses the Immigration and Naturalization Service to steal him back. When Ronnie tries to attract business by offering music and dancing, he discovers he lacks a permit for dancing.</p>
        <p>So in that first year when the casualty rate for such establishments is some 90 percent, the Tavern on Main has its ups and downs. One of the ups is Ronnie's romance with the stylish Sharon (Kym Austin), who catches his eye in a boutique and who favors French films. Another is young Tommy's interest in cooking.</p>
        <p>But when Dave runs afoul of an ill-tempered customer and loses his job at the megastore and when Jerry runs afoul of his bookmakers and turns over stock that is Ronnie's collateral for a loan, Ronnie has reached a point of no return.</p>
        <p>Well cast, well acted, well written and spiced with music by the Saw Doctors, an Irish band, ''Tavern'' is as much a worthwhile lesson in filmmaking as it is in business.</p>
        <p>LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</p>
        <p>FILM IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
