<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Master Who Can Perceive Unorthodoxy in the Ordinary</title>
    <meta content="20LOKE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="42" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/arts/20LOKE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240167"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PHOTOGRAPHY REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frank, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Loke, Margarett</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE4DB153EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1143" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Master Who Can Perceive Unorthodoxy in the Ordinary</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGARETT LOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Loke, Margarett</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Margarett Loke reviews photographs by Robert Frank, at Scalo Gallery; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among photography's masters, few have shunned the limelight as resolutely as Robert Frank or been as disinclined as he to revisit the past by making prints of earlier work, which includes, in his case, the iconic images from his 1959 book ''The Americans.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Frank continues to scorn the trappings of fame, but of late he seems not to mind a steady return to the past. Since 1997, Scalo Publishers, which has headquarters in Zurich and has worked with the Swiss-born Mr. Frank for more than a decade, has re-released a number of his out-of-print books. These include ''The Americans,'' ''The Lines of My Hands'' (1972) and ''Black White and Things'' (1952).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Among photography's masters, few have shunned the limelight as resolutely as Robert Frank or been as disinclined as he to revisit the past by making prints of earlier work, which includes, in his case, the iconic images from his 1959 book ''The Americans.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Frank continues to scorn the trappings of fame, but of late he seems not to mind a steady return to the past. Since 1997, Scalo Publishers, which has headquarters in Zurich and has worked with the Swiss-born Mr. Frank for more than a decade, has re-released a number of his out-of-print books. These include ''The Americans,'' ''The Lines of My Hands'' (1972) and ''Black White and Things'' (1952).</p>
        <p>In June, Mr. Frank gave access to his archive to Theres Abbt, Scalo's associate publisher, and Walter Keller, its publisher.  Together they selected the images for ''Robert Frank: Photographs and Books, 1950's to 1990's,'' an exhibition at the Scalo Gallery in SoHo that is unburdened by a preponderance of the famously familiar (''The Americans'') or the hermetically unfamiliar (his work from the 1970's on).</p>
        <p>This is not to say that the show avoids ''The Americans'' or the later work. They are represented but put in proper context.</p>
        <p>Mirroring Mr. Frank's penchant for achieving a powerful personal vision with an abstract expressionist's passion for rigorous minimalism, the Scalo show has only 54 images. And they do a fine job of connecting the dots.</p>
        <p>''The Americans'' and the later work may look drastically dissimilar but they are connected. Although Mr. Frank persists in producing unsettling work, he has a mind and an eye that have a way of being unusually prescient and perceptive about his life and  times.</p>
        <p>Before he drew his trailblazing portrait of a starkly asymmetrical and lonely America in ''The Americans,'' Mr. Frank had been honing his styleless style for about 10 years: in Switzerland, Peru and the streets of Paris, London and New York. In his early 20's in Switzerland, for instance, he made an image out of 25 small prints, five per row, that was a harbinger of his startlingly innovative work of the next decades. A seemingly random assemblage of vignettes of city and country life, it shows skiers here, a cow there, roiling waves, snow-laden trees, a flea market and so on. But even then, in the mid-1940's, the photographer was inviting the viewer to look closely at the unorthodox in the ordinary.</p>
        <p>Among the images in this show that have not been exhibited or published before are a group of photographs he took in Peru in 1948, a year after he moved to the United States. It was a time when Alexey Brodovitch, the art director of Harper's Bazaar, was trying to turn Mr. Frank into a fashion photographer.</p>
        <p>Preferring the uncertainties of pursuing his own kind of photography, Mr. Frank appears to be in his element photographing the Peruvian Indians.</p>
        <p>A work simply titled ''Peru'' consists of two sets of four pictures. In one, a man harvests, bundles and carries his cut sugar cane; in the other, children and women in their signature bowler hats are patient passengers in a boat. The close-ups of the Peruvians are casually made; some are out of focus. But they are, refreshingly so for that time, neither picturesque nor patronizing. Mr. Frank shows the Indians clearly as individuals, and in a separate study of two Indian women, the face of an elderly woman seems to be as intensely private as the photographer's.</p>
        <p>In the early 50's, while traveling in Europe, he was perfecting a style characterized by harsh tones, emphatic shapes, blur and tilted angles. The work of this period shows the influence of Henri Cartier-Bresson, Bill Brandt and Andre Kertesz.</p>
        <p>Beguiled by the romance of Paris, Mr. Frank shows in the charming ''New Year, Paris'' (1951) two men in dark winter coats passing each other, the younger man holding a tulip behind him, the older man reaching into a tobacco pouch to refill his pipe. ''Woman, Paris'' (1952), a lusty portrait of the back of a woman in a tight sheath, foreshadow's Garry Winogrand's 1960's  takes on comely women who crossed his path.</p>
        <p>But a loneliness also began to set in, as seen in ''Andraitx, Mallorca'' (1950), a moodily Pictorialist rendering of a solitary table and chair in a vast, dark space, some indistinct lights glowing in the distance. In London in 1952, Mr. Frank took a picture of a girl running down a gray and misty street, away from the open door of a hearse. The quintessential decisive moment, this image is mesmerizingly menacing.</p>
        <p>A Guggenheim fellowship allowed Mr. Frank to crisscross the United States in 1955-56. Among the images from ''The Americans'' shown here is the lyrical ''Teardrops, New Jersey,'' in which the solid shape of a tabletop jukebox is juxtaposed with the misty form of a snow-covered automobile outside.</p>
        <p>Yet even before ''The Americans'' was published, Mr. Frank's mind was turning to a personal form of filmmaking that is a cinematic extension of his still photography. With films, though, as he once put it, ''I have to talk to the people who move across my viewfinder.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Frank picked up still photography again in the early 70's, it seemed logical that it would bear the raw imprint of his experimental films.</p>
        <p>Over these largely Polaroid works -- sometimes composed of a single image, sometimes of multiple images seemingly stripped to the bone -- the photographer often scrawled a few words, like notes to himself.</p>
        <p>After his daughter, Andrea, was killed in a plane crash, and his son, Pablo, committed suicide, the words became anguished cries.</p>
        <p>In this exhibition, a selection of this later work is shown in a separate room with never-before-exhibited pictures that Mr. Frank took in Beirut in late 1991, after the end of a 16-year civil war.</p>
        <p>That year, a French publisher, Cypres Press, asked Mr. Frank and five other photographers to document the destruction of a city that was once a Middle Eastern financial and cultural center. The Beirut pictures are brilliantly all of a piece with the later work. The Beirut images show the outward wreckage; the later work the interior one.</p>
        <p>''Robert Frank: Photographs and Books, 1950's to 1990's'' is at the Scalo Gallery, 560 Broadway, at Prince Street, SoHo, (212) 334-9393, through Nov. 4.</p>
        <p>PHOTOGRAPHY REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
