<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>7-Hour Gun Battle in West Bank Strains the Cease-Fire</title>
    <meta content="20MIDE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/world/20MIDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240347"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nablus (West Bank)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0DC103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1275" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>7-Hour Gun Battle in West Bank Strains the Cease-Fire</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Oct. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seven-hour gun battle between Israeli settlers and Palestinians in hills above Nablus, in the West Bank, leaves one Israeli and one Palestinian dead; shootout raises doubts about whether newly-brokered truce will hold; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An army-escorted hike by three dozen Jewish settlers in the hills above Nablus, in the West Bank, touched off a long firefight today that weakened expectations that the two-day-old cease-fire agreement would take hold.</p>
        <p>Midway through a relatively quiet day elsewhere in the West Bank and Gaza, the hikers descended a slope toward a Palestinian town, trying to see the holy site known as Joseph's Tomb, which was burned by Palestinians two weeks ago. The Israelis say Palestinians below fired on them; Palestinians say the Israelis shot first after youths stoned them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An army-escorted hike by three dozen Jewish settlers in the hills above Nablus, in the West Bank, touched off a long firefight today that weakened expectations that the two-day-old cease-fire agreement would take hold.</p>
        <p>Midway through a relatively quiet day elsewhere in the West Bank and Gaza, the hikers descended a slope toward a Palestinian town, trying to see the holy site known as Joseph's Tomb, which was burned by Palestinians two weeks ago. The Israelis say Palestinians below fired on them; Palestinians say the Israelis shot first after youths stoned them.</p>
        <p>Either way, a gun battle that raged for seven hours left two men dead, one Israeli, one Palestinian. They were the first deaths since the Israeli and Palestinian leaders agreed in Egypt this week to halt the violence.</p>
        <p>Each side accused the other of approaching the agreement in bad faith. The Palestinians put out a statement charging that the Israelis were ''continuing their aggression in all areas.'' The Israelis said the Palestinians were making a mockery of the understandings reached at Sharm el Sheik, Egypt.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak declared the Nablus situation ''a gross violation by the Palestinian Authority.'' Nabil Aburdeineh, a senior aide to Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, called it ''a great violation of the Sharm agreement by the Israelis.''</p>
        <p>With Israeli combat helicopters over Nablus, American officials worked the phones, urging restraint and invoking the security cooperation agreement reached in Egypt.</p>
        <p>George J. Tenet, director of central intelligence, called Mr. Arafat, who agreed to send in security officers to clear the way for Israeli troops to evacuate the wounded settlers who were hiding behind rocks in the craggy hills.</p>
        <p>But the Israelis said Palestinian officers had done nothing to ease the situation. After the last wounded were evacuated, the Palestinians did offer ambulances, an army spokesman said, but the Israelis declined.</p>
        <p>''Whatever they did or didn't do to help at the end, this is another incident, a severe one,'' said Nahman Shai, an Israeli government spokesman. ''It's one more proof that Arafat's not serious, and we're very upset at the way he handled the Sharm el Sheik understandings. I'm very pessimistic.''</p>
        <p>Later, P. J. Crowley, a White House spokesman, said: ''The president has called both Chairman Arafat and Prime Minister Barak this evening, expressing his concern about today's incidents of violence and encouraging both to continue to take steps to implement the agreement at Sharm el Sheik and to do all they can to restore calm to the region.''</p>
        <p>Broadcast on Israeli and Palestinian television, the Nablus scenes tended to confirm each people's belief that the truce would not stick.</p>
        <p>Israeli combat helicopters fired machine guns as Palestinian gunmen shot back. Heavily armed Israeli soldiers escorted crying children off the hill.</p>
        <p>A Palestinian policeman ran carrying a bleeding, uniformed colleague. The screams of villagers, most of whom ended up fleeing, blended with the crackling fire.</p>
        <p>Israeli opposition parties said today that they would ''not dismiss'' the idea of joining an emergency government -- if the truce did not work and Mr. Barak made no move to restart the peace talks based on the understandings reached at the Camp David meeting in July.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak ''still hopes against hope'' that the peace effort will be saved, a Western diplomat said today, adding: ''In his mind, he was elected to make peace. And that's what he wants to do. He doesn't see himself as a politician. He doesn't see his historic role as leading a national unity government. So it's still there but as a vain hope.''</p>
        <p>The day started on a somewhat positive note. Israel partly eased closings and other restrictions imposed during the last few weeks of violence. For the first time since Oct. 8, planes began flying again out of the Gaza International Airport, a symbol of Palestinian sovereignty that is nonetheless controlled behind the scenes by the Israelis.</p>
        <p>The Rafah border between Gaza and Egypt reopened. And trucks began moving through the Karni commercial crossing between Gaza and Israel. Israel continued to prevent Palestinian day laborers from traveling to their Israeli jobs, however, citing concerns about terrorism. And it announced that it would again limit access to Al Aksa Mosque in Jerusalem on Friday to prevent clashes.</p>
        <p>After unconfirmed reports on Wednesday, an Israeli general confirmed today that Israel had captured several Palestinians suspected of taking part in the mob killings of two Israeli soldiers last week. Asked about who was in custody, Maj. Gen. Yitzhak Eitan said, ''I won't go into detail about who is or who isn't.'' He added that the hunt for other suspects ''won't stop until everyone involved is brought to justice.''</p>
        <p>A Palestinian official said Israel must have caught the men in Israeli-controlled parts of the West Bank, insisting that they had not been abducted from Palestinian territory. He sought to quash rumors that the Palestinians had aided their arrests.</p>
        <p>''It's not true that the occupation army kidnapped a group of youths in an area under Palestinian control,'' Tawfiq Tirawi, head of Palestinian intelligence in the West Bank, said in the newspaper Al Ayyam.</p>
        <p>Tensions are still high everywhere.</p>
        <p>This morning, in the Old City, there was an Israeli housewarming party in the Muslim quarter. The guests danced, ate and gave welcoming speeches as they celebrated the newest Jewish real estate acquisition in an overwhelmingly Palestinian area. Jerusalem's mayor, Ehud Olmert, joined in, as did Noach Dear, a New York City Council member. The cordon of Israeli officers protecting the festivities bothered no one inside. But the Palestinians outside fumed at what they called the gross insensitivity of holding such an event at a volatile time.</p>
        <p>But Aryeh King, spokesman for a group that promotes Jewish building in predominantly Palestinian areas, said, ''Let me tell you a secret: There isn't a time when a housewarming party like this isn't perceived as a provocation.''</p>
        <p>In the early afternoon, a powerful explosion shook the headquarters of an elite Palestinian security force in Bethlehem. With nerves taut, Palestinians there felt certain that they were under Israeli rocket attack.</p>
        <p>William Salibi, who lived nearby, took his mother to the basement, he said. The first reports on local television even cited an official of Mr. Arafat's Fatah party as saying he had seen the rocket land.</p>
        <p>From the outside, the building, an old British fort that previously housed the Israeli military headquarters, looked mostly intact. Windows appeared to have been blown out, and a grocer nearby said glass fragments had flown across the street. From an adjacent rooftop, the damage was more apparent.</p>
        <p>But shortly afterward, the Voice of Palestine began announcing that cooking gas canisters had exploded.</p>
        <p>This calmed the scene, and prevented clashes from developing at the Israeli checkpoint. But many Palestinians continued to believe that the blast was the work of Israelis. ''After Sharm el Sheik, the Israelis can't attack Bethlehem, so they sent someone with a bomb inside,'' John Elias said. ''If they say it's an Israeli bomb, people will go out into the streets and throw stones.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
