<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Giants' McDaniel, Pain Isn't in Game Plan</title>
    <meta content="20GIAN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/sports/20GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240332"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eskenazi, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcdaniel, Emmanuel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E3DC103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="800" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Giants' McDaniel, Pain Isn't in Game Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eskenazi, Gerald</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Oct. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giant Emmanuel McDaniel sustains eye injury (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two Giants trainers hovered over the defensive back after he was accidentally poked in the eye, no big deal for a little guy who had already played with a painful hip pointer and a torn shoulder muscle. After all, Emmanuel McDaniel vowed after a kidney injury in high school that pain alone would never stop him again.</p>
        <p>Coach Jim Fassel placed a fatherly arm around McDaniel in practice today after the cornerback sustained the eye injury.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two Giants trainers hovered over the defensive back after he was accidentally poked in the eye, no big deal for a little guy who had already played with a painful hip pointer and a torn shoulder muscle. After all, Emmanuel McDaniel vowed after a kidney injury in high school that pain alone would never stop him again.</p>
        <p>Coach Jim Fassel placed a fatherly arm around McDaniel in practice today after the cornerback sustained the eye injury.</p>
        <p>This was a scary prospect for the team as well as for McDaniel. He had just been designated as the replacement at right cornerback for Jason Sehorn, the Giants' leading tackler, who may miss as many as three games with a broken rib.</p>
        <p>The trainers ministered to McDaniel, one testing his vision by holding up a forefinger, then moving the finger left and right, up and down. Suddenly, Fassel sprinted back to the field. McDaniel then said he was fine, put on his helmet and returned to the field, too.</p>
        <p>It was the final practice of the Giants' bye week. The players will be off until Monday. Even Fassel is going to relax in a cabin in Lake Placid, N.Y.</p>
        <p>''They were good today,'' Fassel said of his 5-2 team, still flush with a victory over the Dallas Cowboys and preparing for a meeting with the Philadelphia Eagles in 10 days.</p>
        <p>But this will be a different Eagles team from the one the Giants faced in a Game 2 victory. That team featured running back Duce Staley. Staley's season ended after he had surgery on his right foot last week, and so now quarterback Donovan McNabb is throwing more. McNabb is certain to be looking in the direction of the inexperienced McDaniel.</p>
        <p>There is another thing about McDaniel. He is 5 feet 9 inches tall and weighs 175 pounds ''on a wet day,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But the things that have impressed Fassel and McDaniel's teammates most are his energy, toughness and resiliency. The Giants picked him up as a free agent before last season, but soon placed him on the practice squad. Fassel recalls how McDaniel asked to see him then. McDaniel came into the coach's office frustrated and angry.</p>
        <p>''I had a long talk with him before I waived him,'' Fassel said. ''I told him to stick with it, and he did.''</p>
        <p>McDaniel was activated for Game 10 last season, saw action as a nickel back and even got to start two games late in the season. Both Sehorn and Philippi Sparks, the starting cornerbacks, were out. But McDaniel sustained a shoulder injury.</p>
        <p>Wide receiver Ike Hilliard remembered the situation.</p>
        <p>''His shoulder was torn up, but they wrapped it up and he played,'' Hilliard said. ''We all play with nicks and bruises, but to see him go out with the injury he had, that was big for us.''</p>
        <p>McDaniel had surgery on his shoulder after the season. Then this year, he sustained a hip pointer in a game against the Atlanta Falcons on Oct. 8.</p>
        <p>''It's probably the most painful injury you can have,'' Fassel said.</p>
        <p>Still, McDaniel played. He has also continued to play despite being burned as a nickel back three games ago against the Tennessee Titans. He was even removed from that game.</p>
        <p>''Even the best corners have their bad games,'' he said.</p>
        <p>McDaniel was playing at Jonesboro High in Georgia when he sustained the kidney injury.</p>
        <p>''I had to sit out,'' he said, ''and since then I feel as long as I can move all four of my limbs, I will play.''</p>
        <p>McDaniel has adopted a positive attitude, he said, because ''I've always been the smallest on every team I've been on.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''I'm the kid no one wanted.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Trying to improve an anemic performance on third-down situations -- the Giants are 6 for 36 in converting third downs in their last three games -- JIM FASSEL stressed those situations with his receivers in practice this week. In fact, he cut short some of the drills and repeatedly sent out players for mock third-down situations. The team also worked on shoring up the scoring in the red zone. The Giants have scored an average of barely 4 points a possession inside the opponents' 20-yard line. . . . Fassel had a talk Thursday morning with receiver AMANI TOOMER, who was taken out of last Sunday's game against Dallas and benched. Toomer complained during interviews Wednesday that he has not seen as many passes this season as last season. Fassel said he told Toomer that he actually has had more balls thrown to him than any other receiver. Toomer described the talk as encouraging.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
