<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commuter Survey Finds Improvement in Service on L.I.R.R.</title>
    <meta content="20RAIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/nyregion/20RAIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240273"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Rail Road Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Rail Road Commuters Council</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, Tina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E1DF103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commuter Survey Finds Improvement in Service on L.I.R.R.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina</byline>
      <dateline>MINEOLA, N.Y., Oct. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Rail Road Commuters Council, riders' group, finds that oft-maligned railroad showed improvement in 38 of 46 areas that commuters were asked to grade; while railroad's grades go up in 38 areas, they fall in none, in contrast with last year, when 24 grades fell; survey findings reviewed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They've been working on the railroad, and the passengers have noticed. The oft-maligned Long Island Rail Road got good grades today from a riders' group that found improvement in 38 of 46 areas that commuters were asked to grade.</p>
        <p>Michael T. Doyle, the associate director of the Long Island Rail Road Commuters Council, said this was probably the best report card the railroad had received in 14 years of such monitoring by the state-chartered advocacy group.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They've been working on the railroad, and the passengers have noticed. The oft-maligned Long Island Rail Road got good grades today from a riders' group that found improvement in 38 of 46 areas that commuters were asked to grade.</p>
        <p>Michael T. Doyle, the associate director of the Long Island Rail Road Commuters Council, said this was probably the best report card the railroad had received in 14 years of such monitoring by the state-chartered advocacy group.</p>
        <p>While the railroad's grades went up in 38 areas, they fell in none, in contrast with last year, when 24 grades fell. The overall grade rose from a C to a C+. The most significant improvements seen were in air-conditioning, heating, morning on-time performance and morning seating availability.</p>
        <p>''I think the report card is good news for riders,'' said Larry Silverman, chairman of the council and the Democratic candidate for the State Senate from District 5 on Long Island.</p>
        <p>''This is the result of the railroad finally making an investment in its rolling stock, overhauls, and air-conditioning,'' he said. ''It shows what happens if they make an adequate investment in the infrastructure.''</p>
        <p>The survey of more than 2,000 commuters, conducted in May, asked riders to grade the railroad in categories like announcements, cleanliness, security and train crews. More than half the passengers on the Oyster Bay, Montauk and Port Jefferson lines, where new diesel trains have recently begun running, said train service had improved.</p>
        <p>Still, much work has to be done, the survey found. It faulted the railroad for late trains, a failure to provide adequate seating and insufficient parking at outlying stations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silverman noted that most passengers were pleased with the service they received from train crews, although he expressed concern that scheduling changes that had been planned for this year would probably not be instituted until 2002, as more electric trains start running. He also questioned the railroad's policy on borrowing. He said increased debt meant increased interest payments and that a fare increase could be a result.</p>
        <p>''We're encouraged to see that customers are responding to the improvements we are making,'' said Brian Dolan, a spokesman for the railroad. ''Great effort was placed into improving air-conditioning performance this summer, and the results were positive, as well as on-time performance.''</p>
        <p>In the year ending last month, he said, 92.8 percent of the trains were on time, up from 91.2 percent the year before. The railroad considers a train on time if it arrives at its destination within six minutes of its scheduled arrival time.</p>
        <p>He said ridership was up 4.4 percent from last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dolan said the railroad's capital program, approved late last year, would bring 472 new electric cars. An additional 226 had already been ordered and are to arrive in the spring of 2002. ''We will move from having one of the oldest fleets in the region, to the newest,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In response to customer concerns about dirty trains, a campaign will begin later this month to keep trains cleaner, Mr. Dolan said. The trains will be thoroughly cleaned every 45 days, instead of every 60 days.</p>
        <p>Recently acquired diesel trains -- 134 double-decker coaches and 46 locomotives, half operating on electricity and diesel, the other half operating solely on diesel -- represent a $500 million investment from the railroad's 1995-1999 capital plan, Mr. Dolan said.</p>
        <p>After many complaints about the loud or rude use of cell phones on the trains, the council asked passengers in the survey what should be done about them. A little over 80 percent of those surveyed favored an education program to encourage courtesy by phone users, and 87 percent opposed a prohibition on their use.</p>
        <p>When passengers were asked for their comments on service, they presented a variety of concerns. ''Please give me a chance to make the opening bell at the stock exchange,'' one Huntington passenger begged, while a rider from Long Beach asked for some compensation when trains are not on time: ''Rebates if more than 10 minutes late.'' A Bellmore passenger asked for one easy, common-sense change -- ''Conductors should announce destinations before, not after train departs.''</p>
        <p>And several commuters offered clipped lines suggestive of haiku:</p>
        <p>''I see roaches on the trains.</p>
        <p>''Pigeons at the Huntington station.''</p>
        <p>''Be as good as Metro-North.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
