<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BUSINESS: German Giants to Clash in Britain; Volkswagen and BMW to Vie for Sales to the Very Wealthy</title>
    <meta content="20ROLL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="W" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/business/20ROLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240201"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Volkswagen Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rolls-Royce Motor Cars Ltd</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bentley Motor Cars</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bayerische Motorenwerke Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mercedes-Benz Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimlerchrysler Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bugatti Motors</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E5DD133EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1271" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BUSINESS: German Giants to Clash in Britain; Volkswagen and BMW to Vie for Sales to the Very Wealthy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>CREWE, England</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Volkswagen AG, which owns Rolls-Royce and Bentley Motor Cars of Britain, and BMW plan to vie for sales to wealthy in Britain; Volkswagen is working on prototype of so-called mid-range Bentley that will reach market just when Volkswagen and BMW divide Britain's most prestigious car brands between them at end of 2002; it will be first divorce of Rolls-Royce and Bentley since they fused in 1931; BMW is set to build Rolls-Royces at new plant in southern England, competing with full-size Bentley model built by Volkswagen for attention of superrich who are able to pay up to $360,000; smaller Bentley model will challenge DaimlerChrysler's top-of-the-range Mercedes S500 and S600 sedans just as Mercedes introduces premium luxury car, the Maybach; Volkswagen plans to revive Italian Bugatti brand with car that would retail at rumored $700,000 to $800,000; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The red-brick car assembly plant in the unassuming suburbs of this town in northwest England seems an unlikely front line in a looming clash of titans in the German auto industry.</p>
        <p>But since Volkswagen bought Rolls-Royce and Bentley Motor Cars of Britain two years ago, the Rolls-Royce factory here, built in the 1930's, has been propelled to the center of a scramble among German carmakers for the wallets of the newly very rich.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The red-brick car assembly plant in the unassuming suburbs of this town in northwest England seems an unlikely front line in a looming clash of titans in the German auto industry.</p>
        <p>But since Volkswagen bought Rolls-Royce and Bentley Motor Cars of Britain two years ago, the Rolls-Royce factory here, built in the 1930's, has been propelled to the center of a scramble among German carmakers for the wallets of the newly very rich.</p>
        <p>The calculation is that, stock market gyrations notwithstanding, unparalleled Western prosperity has produced more folks with cash to spend on high-ticket autos than ever before -- a market built on what one Bentley executive called ''the polarization of wealth, the abundance of people with extremely high net worth.''</p>
        <p>Here, behind the closed doors of a new design center, the German-owned British company is working on the prototype of a so-called mid-range Bentley that will reach the market just when Volkswagen and BMW divide Britain's most prestigious car brands between them at the end of 2002. It will be the first divorce of Rolls-Royce and Bentley since they fused in 1931.</p>
        <p>BMW is set to build Rolls-Royces at a new plant in southern England, competing with the full-size Bentley model built by Volkswagen for the attentions of the superrich who are able to pay up to $360,000 for the carriage of choice among royalty and rock stars.</p>
        <p>The smaller Bentley model, moreover, will challenge DaimlerChrysler's top-of-the-range Mercedes S500 and S600 sedans just as Mercedes introduces its own premium luxury car, the Maybach. And Volkswagen is planning to leapfrog all the others by reviving the Italian Bugatti brand with a car for the very, very rich that would retail at a rumored $700,000 to $800,000.</p>
        <p>''The feeling is that there's scope somewhere to tap further into the superrich and more than one level where you can try that,'' said John Lawson, an auto industry analyst at Schroeder Salomon Smith Barney in London.</p>
        <p>This three-cornered fight for the hearts and minds, or at least the egos and checkbooks, of the very rich has its roots, in part, in the sale of Rolls-Royce in 1998. Volkswagen paid the British industrial company Vickers P.L.C. $790 million for the Crewe plant, only to discover that BMW had struck a separate deal to secure the legendary Rolls-Royce trademark. That led BMW and Volkswagen to split up Bentley and Rolls-Royce.</p>
        <p>Coming just a few years after BMW's disastrous takeover of Rover cars of Britain, the sale of Rolls-Royce and Bentley -- as much emblems of Britishness as the Union Jack or the Beatles -- struck horror into the hearts of nationalist Britons who were clinging to the last automotive vestige of independence and empire. When BMW finally sold Rover earlier this year, the question was revived: How could a German producer of mass-volume cars be expected to nurture its British acquisition?</p>
        <p>The answer is a surprising bullishness among Bentley managers about their future -- and a robust conviction that the Britishness of Bentley will not be diluted when the new, midrange models enter production at far higher volumes than at present, pushing production from less than 2,000 to around 9,000 cars a year. That will be the first major fruit of a five-year, $750 million investment program.</p>
        <p>''This is not like BMW and Rover,'' said Mr. Lawson, the auto industry analyst. ''That was a slow transition. Volkswagen is actually rebuilding the entire company. What Volkswagen will do with this new product will be to move in one fell swoop.''</p>
        <p>With that in mind, Volkswagen has installed its own German engineering and finance directors here. The marketing director, Adrian Hallmark, is a Briton recruited from the British division of Porsche of Germany.</p>
        <p>Tony Gott, a 17-year Rolls-Royce veteran who is now chief executive, says he travels once a week to Volkswagen's headquarters in northern Germany. And Ferdinand Piech, the Volkswagen boss, visits here once a month to check on his investment, Mr. Hallmark said. There have even been press reports -- denied here -- that Volkswagen may move production of the new car from Crewe to Dresden in eastern Germany.</p>
        <p>This year, the Rolls-Royce and Bentley factory here has expanded its staff by 400, to 2,500, working around an assembly line that produces both brands in a variety of models. One of Volkswagen's first moves was to resurrect Rolls- Royce's own 6.75-liter V-8 engine, modifying it to meet European emission-control standards. That heartened nationalistic enthusiasts and decreased dependence on other engines supplied by BMW.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gott asserted in an interview that, while many long-timers mourned the imminent end of Rolls-Royce production in Crewe, the company had drawn far more benefit from its ownership by Volkswagen -- major investment, huge technical expertise and a guarantee that, for all their German technology, the new cars will be built here on a Bentley platform and will maintain a spirit of leather-and-walnut British opulence.</p>
        <p>The looming loss of the Rolls- Royce label, though, offers a particular challenge to the company's branding. Mr. Gott said Rolls- Royce had an ''iconic'' status, even though Bentleys have provided the bulk of the sales for a company that is only now producing an operating profit after years of losses.</p>
        <p>According to the company's figures, worldwide sales -- including Rolls-Royce's main market, the United States -- fell 15.7 percent between 1997 and 1998, to 1,619 cars. From 1998 to 1999, reflecting uncertainties surrounding Volkswagen's takeover, they dropped a further 10.6 percent, to 1,447.</p>
        <p>But this year, in what Mr. Gott depicted as a turnaround, sales have rebounded. By the end of August, the company had sold 1,169, a 22 percent increase from the period in 1999. Almost half of the cars were sold in the United States and around two-thirds of the total were Bentleys.</p>
        <p>For many years, Rolls-Royce and Bentley were essentially the same cars with different badges and radiator grilles. Then, the company sought to project Bentley's sporty, owner-driver mystique alongside the staid, chauffeur-driven aura of the Rolls.</p>
        <p>''The risk with Rolls-Royce is that you can revere it too much so that it doesn't work in a modern world,'' Mr. Hallmark said. Bentley's new model, he said, ''would draw on luxury, the Bentley look, but more performance-inclined.'' And it would aim for drivers a little younger than the early 50's set who generally buy the big cars.</p>
        <p>The new model will sell, Mr. Gott said, for around $:100,000, or roughly $144,000 -- slightly more than Mercedes' top-of-the-range S-class, but far less than the current price range in the United States, between $209,000 for a Bentley Arnage Red Label and $359,990 for a Rolls- Royce Corniche convertible.</p>
        <p>The competition with other luxury brands will happen not only in the showroom. Mr. Gott said Bentley also hoped to re-enter auto racing for the first time since 1930, when one of its cars won the Le Mans 24-hour endurance race for the fifth time. In corporate mythology, the memory of that particular race is molded by a moment that resonates with today's competition for dominance. In 1930, they like to recall here, a Bentley thundered down the track at 130 miles an hour, overtaking -- guess what? A Mercedes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
