<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Japanese Government Raises Forecast of Growth to 1.5%</title>
    <meta content="20JAPA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="W" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/business/20JAPA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240197"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WORLD BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gross Domestic Product</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strom, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gross Domestic Product</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EEDE133EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Japanese Government Raises Forecast of Growth to 1.5%</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, Oct. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Japan's Economic Planning Agency says gross domestic product will rise 1.5 percent in current fiscal year, which ends March 31; it had previously anticipated growth of 1 percent; government cuts estimates for nominal growth, or growth that takes into account inflation or deflation; it expects nominal growth of 0.4 percent, compared with its previous projection for 0.8 percent, suggesting there are strong deflationary forces in economy, which threatens to choke business spending (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Japanese government raised its economic growth forecast today, saying its previous estimate was too cautious in light of robust corporate spending and an expected increase in consumer spending.</p>
        <p>The Economic Planning Agency said it now expected the gross domestic product to rise 1.5 percent in the current fiscal year, which ends March 31. It had previously anticipated growth of 1 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Japanese government raised its economic growth forecast today, saying its previous estimate was too cautious in light of robust corporate spending and an expected increase in consumer spending.</p>
        <p>The Economic Planning Agency said it now expected the gross domestic product to rise 1.5 percent in the current fiscal year, which ends March 31. It had previously anticipated growth of 1 percent.</p>
        <p>The agency's revised projections still fall short of the expectations of private economists, most of whom say the economy will grow by roughly 2 percent.</p>
        <p>But the government would have difficulty reconciling such a sharp positive change in the economic outlook with its latest economic stimulus package, which it formally announced today. The broad outlines of that package, which will pump another 3.9 trillion yen, or about $36 billion, into the economy, have been known for a while, and include investment in infrastructure, assistance to small and midsize businesses, and money for housing and jobs.</p>
        <p>The government also plans to spend an additional 1 trillion yen, or about $926 million, on information technology, but that will come out of previous budgets or in the form of tax breaks and loan guarantees.</p>
        <p>Officials have promised this spending package will be the last. The government has spent about 130 trillion yen over eight years to invigorate the economy, and its expectations for more robust growth suggest the spending is finally paying off.</p>
        <p>But the optimistic picture painted today contained some ominous elements. While the government increased projections for economic growth, it cut estimates for nominal growth, or growth that takes into account inflation or deflation.</p>
        <p>The agency said it now expected nominal growth of 0.4 percent, compared with its previous projection for 0.8 percent. That suggests there are strong deflationary forces at work in the economy, which threaten to choke business spending.</p>
        <p>Deflation means businesses are under pressure to reduce their prices, and indeed, the agency said today that the consumer price index would fall this fiscal year rather than rise by 0.3 percent as it had originally projected.</p>
        <p>''The key point is the strong between-the-lines message that the E.P.A. is sending, which is that out in the business world, where the only real number is nominal sales, things are tougher in Japan than it thought earlier,'' said Jesper Koll, an economist at Merrill Lynch in Tokyo.</p>
        <p>Economists were also worried that the government now expected its own spending to fall this fiscal year rather than rise as it had previously anticipated. A sharp drop in public investment could tilt the economy back into a slump if deflation does curtail business spending.</p>
        <p>The spending package announced today did not impress the Japanese financial markets, and the benchmark Nikkei stock average fell 0.4 percent, to 14,811.08, the latest in a series of 19-month lows. Japanese officials, however, dismissed the market's behavior.</p>
        <p>''The stock fall is not having a critical impact on the economy,'' Taichi Sakaiya, the country's chief economics minister, told reporters.</p>
        <p>WORLD BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
