<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Little Shop Of Learning</title>
    <meta content="20FLIC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/arts/20FLIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240174"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AT THE MOVIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Winstar Communications Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kehr, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corman, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramsey, Lynne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fassbinder, Rainer Werner (1936-82)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ratcatcher (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns/At the Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns/At the Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/DVD and Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E0D7123EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1198" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Little Shop Of Learning</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dave Kehr</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kehr, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>At the Movies column interviews Julie Corman, new chairwoman of NYU's graduate film and television program; photo; director Lynne Ramsey explains Scottish movie Ratcatcher, set in poor Glasgow neighborhood during sanitation strike; Winstar Communications, video company, acquires 18 features and two documentaries from estate of Rainer Werner Fassbinder (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During the 1970's the Los Angeles independent studio New World Pictures was famous for turning out exploitation films with a little something extra, movies with titles like ''Night Call Nurses'' and ''Humanoids from the Deep.'' Founded by the legendary drive-in auteur Roger Corman (''Little Shop of Horrors'') and his wife, Julie, the company became known for its willingness to give creative freedom to promising young directors, provided that they stayed within tight budgets and respected certain rules (like having the leading lady remove her shirt at least once every couple of reels).</p>
        <p>Among the many well-known filmmakers who got their start with the Cormans were Martin Scorsese (''Boxcar Bertha,'' 1972), Jonathan Demme (''Caged Heat,'' 1974) and Ron Howard (''Grand Theft Auto,'' 1977). With alumni like that it was clear that the Cormans were, knowingly or not, running one of the finest film schools in the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During the 1970's the Los Angeles independent studio New World Pictures was famous for turning out exploitation films with a little something extra, movies with titles like ''Night Call Nurses'' and ''Humanoids from the Deep.'' Founded by the legendary drive-in auteur Roger Corman (''Little Shop of Horrors'') and his wife, Julie, the company became known for its willingness to give creative freedom to promising young directors, provided that they stayed within tight budgets and respected certain rules (like having the leading lady remove her shirt at least once every couple of reels).</p>
        <p>Among the many well-known filmmakers who got their start with the Cormans were Martin Scorsese (''Boxcar Bertha,'' 1972), Jonathan Demme (''Caged Heat,'' 1974) and Ron Howard (''Grand Theft Auto,'' 1977). With alumni like that it was clear that the Cormans were, knowingly or not, running one of the finest film schools in the country.</p>
        <p>Now it's official. Since September Ms. Corman has been the chairwoman of the graduate film and television program at New York University's Tisch School of the Arts. So far, she said in her sunny corner office, the experience has been harrowingly close to that of the in-the-trenches producer: a question of immediate problem-solving rather than pondering lofty principles.</p>
        <p>''The first day I walked in the office, there were boxes everywhere, and they were painting,'' she said. ''A foreign student came to see me and said, 'I promise not to cry,' which is when she burst into tears and said: 'I've raised all the money to finance my education here. But between the time I was accepted here and now, the New Zealand dollar has been devalued by 50 percent.' ''</p>
        <p>''I found a solution,'' said Ms. Corman, ''I found that they have a fund earmarked for an extraordinary problem for a first-year student in the graduate film department. So she's still here, and now she's smiling. In production the question is always, 'Why aren't we shooting?' And the problem is usually either functional -- like a strike -- or something more personal, like an actor who doesn't feel comfortable shooting a scene unless he has a cotton shirt. So one thing I bring to N.Y.U., I think, is my way of dealing with those areas.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Corman may have left Los Angeles -- she and her husband are now living in the university's faculty housing -- but she has not left the business. She said she planned to continue producing, both for Concorde-New Horizons, the company she and her husband founded after they sold New World, and for other studios.</p>
        <p>''I was just talking to a potential director for a film I am doing at New Line,'' Ms. Corman said. ''He lives in Australia. The New Line executives are in L.A. I'm here, and we're talking about shooting in the Virgin Islands. But we've always been very international. Of the last two films I produced, one was in Peru and one was in Egypt.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Corman's internationalism comes in handy at N.Y.U., where the film students come from 42 countries. ''I think that one of the great benefits they have here, beyond learning to make films, is the cross-fertilization between so many countries, so many ways of life.''</p>
        <p>The Dustbin School</p>
        <p>The Scottish film ''Ratcatcher'' is set in a poor neighborhood of Glasgow where a sanitation strike has left mounds of garbage in the streets. ''Look,'' remarks one of the film's pre-teenage protagonists, ''someone's thrown out a perfectly good dog.''</p>
        <p>It isn't an idyllic Spielbergian idea of childhood, but that's not what Lynne Ramsay, the director of ''Ratcatcher,'' had in mind. ''We start off with a boy who is killed, who is actually much cuter than our main protagonist. I believe I did that consciously. I was thinking at the time, this is the kind of sweet-looking kid who should be in one of those conventional coming-of-age films. And then we pass the baton on to this boy who's a bit weird-looking and kind of suspicious.''</p>
        <p>The critically acclaimed ''Ratcatcher,'' now playing in Manhattan, is the story of James (William Eadie), an anxious 12-year-old who believes himself responsible for the accidental death of his best friend, who drowned in a refuse-choked canal. This moody, allusive film creates an image of a world suspended between beauty and horror, building up tiny details of texture and color.</p>
        <p>''It was a funny time politically,'' Ms. Ramsay said of the film's 1970's setting. ''There were a lot of strikes, a sense of chaos was in the air, and punk was about to happen. The dustbin strike in particular felt like the end of the world. I liked it as a backdrop to this story of the end of childhood, as a parallel to James's psychological state.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ramsay plans to start her next film, ''Mordern Celler,'' in February, with Samantha Morton as a rock-loving drifter. ''She's so much like this character, it's uncanny,'' Ms. Ramsay said of her actress. ''She's even got a scar where the character's got a scar. I think she's just a ball of energy, Sam, so I'm really looking forward to working with her.''</p>
        <p>Keeper of the Flame</p>
        <p>Winstar Communications, the video company that recently re-released much of the Francois Truffaut film library, has announced a new acquisition: 18 features and two documentaries from the estate of Rainer Werner Fassbinder, the revolutionary realist of the German cinema, who died in 1982 at 37. Library building is very much part of the company's strategy, said Krysanne Katsoolis, Winstar's senior vice president for acquisitions.</p>
        <p>''Even when we buy a new film now,'' she said, ''we try to go back and acquire as many of the older films of the filmmaker as we can. We want people to see a film in its context, to have a background for watching it. I don't know if it's a new policy, but it's definitely one we're pursuing aggressively.''</p>
        <p>Juliane Lorenz, who was Fassbinder's wife and edited 14 of his films, said, ''There were long talks and long negotiations, but finally Winstar made it.'' The films in the package, which will be released to theaters and then on DVD next year, include ''The Marriage of Maria Braun,'' ''The Bitter Tears of Petra von Kant'' and ''Love Is Colder than Death,'' Fassbinder's first feature, which has never been seen in the United States.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lorenz directs the Fassbinder Foundation in Berlin, which administers his estate and seeks to support young filmmakers.</p>
        <p>The features owned by the foundation are less than half of Fassbinder's output (45 features and shorts), but Ms. Lorenz is exploring ways of buying back and preserving the other works.</p>
        <p>''I was living as well as working with Mr. Fassbinder,'' she said. ''These films are our children. I have to care for them.''</p>
        <p>AT THE MOVIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
