<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With New Goals, Leaving the Nest for College</title>
    <meta content="20COLL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223906"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MILESTONES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Middlebury College</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herring, Katherine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ames, Lynne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DF143EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="948" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With New Goals, Leaving the Nest for College</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNE AMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ames, Lynne</byline>
      <dateline>KATONAH</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Katherine Herring, 18, of Katonah, NY, who, having been accepted at Middlebury College in Vermont, only school to which she applied, is first child in her family to leave nest; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>KATHERINE HERRING cried when she got the answer to the most pressing question of her life so far: had she been accepted to the college of her choice?</p>
        <p>Middlebury College, in Vermont, was the only school to which she had applied, the only school where she could envision herself, the only school that seemed as if it had been designed with her desires in mind: small, liberal arts, beautiful campus, intellectually challenging, in the Northeast.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>KATHERINE HERRING cried when she got the answer to the most pressing question of her life so far: had she been accepted to the college of her choice?</p>
        <p>Middlebury College, in Vermont, was the only school to which she had applied, the only school where she could envision herself, the only school that seemed as if it had been designed with her desires in mind: small, liberal arts, beautiful campus, intellectually challenging, in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>And so when she got the word, by e-mail at her home here, she let out a shriek and a sob that scared her parents. ''I was crying hysterically,'' she recalled. ''They thought I'd been rejected. But I was actually crying from happiness.''</p>
        <p>Early admission to the college of one's choice is a landmark event in the life of a young person and her family, especially in Westchester County.</p>
        <p>Education-conscious -- make that education-obsessed -- parents sweat it out with their sons and daughters, coaching them on essays that extol their virtues as scholars, community activists and creative souls, nudging their test grades with special preparatory courses.</p>
        <p>The applicants cram into their lives not only round-the-clock studying but also extracurricular activities ranging from French horn to football, chess tournaments to volunteer charity work.</p>
        <p>And then, after all the preparation, comes the actual departure for school.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Herring, 18, this will be in two weeks. In the meantime, she and her family are packing, preparing and reminiscing.</p>
        <p>Ms. Herring is the first child in the Herring household to leave the nest (her brother, Andrew, is 12); they are both excited and  wistful. In that household, things intellectual have long held sway.</p>
        <p>Howard Herring is executive director of Caramoor.</p>
        <p>His wife, Laura Calzolari, is executive director of the Music Conservatory of Westchester.</p>
        <p>''Katherine is a sensitive, intelligent, wonderful person,'' Mr. Herring said. ''I don't think she even realizes fully how the college experience will cause her to be a more independent thinker. I think she has a lot of opinions rolling around in her head that she hasn't even expressed yet.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Calzolari added, ''She will explore all of her intellectual possibilities.'' A laugh. ''This, after all, is what we're paying for.''</p>
        <p>As for Ms. Herring, the changes have her thinking of everything from the concrete to the abstract.</p>
        <p>On the level of creature comforts, she said she will miss her room at home: pink walls, dozens of stuffed animals on the bed, scores of delicate little perfume bottles on the bureau.</p>
        <p>The oblong glass aquarium with four iridescent tropical fish, however, is going with her.</p>
        <p>''Even though they have a no pets policy in the dorm,'' she said, ''I don't think they'll mind Harvey, Princess, Tiger and Vladimir.''</p>
        <p>On a more esoteric level, she spoke of goals and philosophies.</p>
        <p>A graduate of John Jay High School here, she took courses that included advanced placement English, advanced French, third-year Latin, calculus and philosophy. She has also studied violin since she was 4. In the college essay asking her to describe the most influential person in her life, she chose one of her teachers at the Music Conservatory of Westchester, Dr. Anna Pelekh.</p>
        <p>''She has never let one out-of-tune note slip her by,'' Ms. Herring wrote. ''I have learned the value of discipline and more importantly, the concept of working toward an ideal. I accept challenges in areas beyond music, perhaps more readily than others do, because I have learned to strive for musical perfection.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Herring has also served on the Student Council at John Jay, been the class treasurer, built homecoming parade floats and played in the school orchestra, and she dances, plays tennis and skis.</p>
        <p>Those who would look for a flaw in this seemingly perfect picture might find it in the pressure she puts on herself: when her first set of S.A.T. scores were not up to what she had expected, she cried hysterically and called her mother at work for solace. When she began having difficulty in an advanced chemistry class, she toughed it out rather than switch to an intermediate one. ''They say colleges look at classes of higher levels, so I stayed with the advanced chemistry.''</p>
        <p>Considering the immediate future, she figures that she will miss her boyfriend (who is attending the University of Vermont in Burlington), her two closest girlfriends and her parents, although ''it'll be really exciting to be bombarded with so many things, ideas and experiences.''</p>
        <p>To keep in touch, there is always the telephone and e-mail. ''I'm a real daddy's girl emotionally,'' she said. ''And I'll really miss him, although I'll miss my mom too. She's actually the first one I usually go to for advice.''</p>
        <p>For the longer term, she envisions all sorts of psychological changes.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to predict just what I will become,'' she said. ''I'm going to be surrounded by the unfamiliar. Although at Middlebury I have reached -- well, we've all reached a certain academic level, so we have that in common. College is a preparation for the real world -- for work. But it still is not quite the pressure of what I think the real work world will be. For the next four years, I'm still protected.''</p>
        <p>MILESTONES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
