<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sometimes, Smaller Is Better</title>
    <meta content="ALACRU$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223770"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alaska</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cruise West</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenthal, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E6D6103FF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1892" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sometimes, Smaller Is Better</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenthal, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Rosenthal travel article describes advantages of small-ship cruise to Alaska aboard Cruise West Spirit of Discovery; photos; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S hard not to be smug when you're on a small-ship cruise of Alaska.</p>
        <p>Whenever my wife, Lisa, and I were not congratulating ourselves for having chosen our little 84-passenger ship  for a journey through Alaska's Inside Passage last August, somebody else was doing it for us: the crew, our fellow passengers, even local residents at the ports of call.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S hard not to be smug when you're on a small-ship cruise of Alaska.</p>
        <p>Whenever my wife, Lisa, and I were not congratulating ourselves for having chosen our little 84-passenger ship  for a journey through Alaska's Inside Passage last August, somebody else was doing it for us: the crew, our fellow passengers, even local residents at the ports of call.</p>
        <p>Our boat, the Cruise West Spirit of Discovery, was smaller and nimbler than the big ships, able to get in and out of narrow inlets, and at liberty to slow down any time somebody saw a grizzly bear on shore, or speed up to catch a pod of breaching humpback whales. It could maneuver through ice floes without disturbing the seals sleeping on them, and linger at thousand-year-old glaciers. And unlike some boats, ours had no rigid schedule dictated by the need to get back into international waters to resume gambling; in fact, there was no gambling at all.</p>
        <p>Never having taken a cruise before, I was concerned that a small ship would be less stable in choppy waters. I worried that the tiny cabins and lack of on-board entertainment would drive us stir-crazy after a few days. The pessimist in me envisioned nine days of sightseeing punctuated by bouts of vomiting and thumb-twiddling.</p>
        <p>I needn't have worried. Our cabin was indeed small, but cozy. The simply prepared food -- everything from fresh Alaskan halibut to barbecued chicken and ribs -- was plentiful. And the public spaces, including a cafeteria-like dining room and a comfortable lounge with a bar and a shelf of books, were crowded only when rain (or a brimming platter of snacks) forced everybody indoors. We never needed our seasickness pills, barely cracked the thick paperbacks we brought from home, and rarely tore ourselves from the majesty outside our window.</p>
        <p>Alaska's natural beauty is a never-ending spectacle, and our small ship gave us front-row seats.</p>
        <p>We knew we had made the right choice on our arrival in Ketchikan, where we boarded. At the dock, we were treated to a side-by-side comparison. To our left stood the 166-foot-long Spirit of Discovery, no bigger than a Circle Line boat. To our right was a 2,000-passenger megalopolis of the seas. The ship's anchor was nearly the size of our entire boat. Only after the gargantuan cruise ship pulled out of port did I realize that its 12 stories had been blocking out the sun. And the four-foot swells created by the leviathan's wake would be the roughest waters we encountered during the entire trip.</p>
        <p>For the next few days, we nearly forgot about the existence of the bigger boats as we cruised through inlets too narrow for them to negotiate.</p>
        <p>Our first full day of sightseeing brought us early in the morning to Misty Fjords National Monument, which was indeed misty. But by 8 a.m., the fog began to dissipate, unveiling a world of vibrant evergreens. The steep, forested cliffs on either side of the fjords presented a landscape like none we had ever seen.</p>
        <p>The next day we cruised through the Wrangell Narrows on our way to the LeConte Glacier. Lisa and I had tried to see a glacier once before, in Patagonia, but bad weather had forced us to turn back. So we were excited the minute we saw the Windex-blue ice floes mining LeConte Bay. The crackling of the glacial chunks made us feel as if we were cruising through a bowl of Rice Krispies. The floes got bigger and bluer as we traveled closer, until we finally stopped, 400 yards away from the glacier itself, the biggest and bluest berg of all.</p>
        <p>At that distance, you see things happen before you hear them. By the time we heard the thundering explosion of a huge piece of ice calving, the event was over. So we scanned the horizon diligently, hoping to rest our eyes on the exact spot where the next bus-sized chunk would break off the glacier and plunge into the water below.</p>
        <p>In the ship's central corridor, Margie McGregor, the cruise's coordinator and staff naturalist, posted a list of wildlife seen during the cruise. For the first few days, it remained fairly short: a group of orcas as we moved toward LeConte Glacier, a few bald eagles, and a mountain goat that was hard to see even with binoculars. But by Day 5, as we cruised through Glacier Bay, additions came fast and furious.</p>
        <p>Humpback whales were a major reason to brave the cold on deck. At first they were identifiable only by their plumes of mist in the water, but as we got closer, we could make out heads, fins, tails. None of the whales did a Shamu-worthy leap out of the water, but dozens breached within gasping distance of the boat.</p>
        <p>Glacier Bay was where we also got our first grizzly bear sighting. A mother and her two cubs frolicked on a hill above the shoreline, oblivious to our presence 200 feet away. Seals and sea lions were plentiful, often napping atop ice floes. Sea otters swam, dived, chased each other through kelp, or simply lay on their backs while eating shellfish off their chests. A family of puffins floated silently off the starboard side.</p>
        <p>Each time an animal was sighted, a crowd jumped up to see, yet the person who seemed the most excited was Margie, who presumably had seen all these critters many times before. Only Big Al Carter, who delivered the freshly baked chocolate chip cookies to the lounge each afternoon, was more popular.</p>
        <p>That morning in Glacier Bay had started out foggy, but by late afternoon it was sunny and I was in shorts and a T-shirt on the top deck, working on my tan. The gloriously sunny 75-degree weather followed us for the last three days of the trip.</p>
        <p>The next morning in Skagway, Lisa and I went ashore and biked to the ghost town of Dyea, 10 miles away. During the Klondike Gold Rush of 1898, this boomtown was the last place where prospectors could stock up before setting off on the Chilkoot Trail. But two years later, when the White Pass and Yukon Railroad chose Skagway for its depot, Dyea literally disappeared. Even the boards used for the houses and stores were carted up and moved to Skagway. Today, the Alaska Highway dead-ends in Dyea, so there's little automobile traffic. All that remains is a cemetery and some historical markers showing where things used to be.</p>
        <p>We pedaled up one finger of the Taiya Inlet and down another, looping back and forth several times until we reached Dyea. Along the way, vistas proliferated, each more picturesque than the last, where the snow-capped purple mountains perfectly framed the landscape of teal waters and evergreen forest.</p>
        <p>When we returned to Skagway, we saw that the quaint, sleepy town (population 816) had been overrun by thousands of shoppers from the two cruise ships that dwarfed our little boat in port. People packed stores selling T-shirts, fudge and overpriced gold trinkets.</p>
        <p>In Haines, late that afternoon, our timing was more auspicious. The bigger boats go to Haines too, but they didn't show up that day until after we left. When our little boat arrived, the port was empty except for three extremely warm-blooded (some might say foolhardy) souls bobbing in the 45-degree water around the pier. Lisa and I chose a rafting excursion through the Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve.</p>
        <p>This was no death-defying trip through whitewater canyons. The shallow river's current moved slowly and steadily, while Sarah, our strong-armed 20-year-old guide, did all the rowing for our eight-passenger raft, leaving us free to watch for wildlife. Bald eagles were plentiful as advertised -- we saw more than a dozen -- but the heat of the day scared off wolves, moose and grizzlies.</p>
        <p>When we disembarked the last day in Juneau, we joined the crowds of other cruise ship tourists in the stores and restaurants buying postcards and smoked salmon. But we wanted one more uncrowded Alaskan experience before we returned home. So we abandoned the shopping streets in favor of a web of hiking trails, where the city's water supply cascaded through mossy glens.</p>
        <p>After a six-mile hike, I looked at a map of Alaska. Over the entire nine-day cruise, we had gone fewer than 500 miles. We hadn't even set foot on mainland Alaska. At our rate of travel, it would take us more than a thousand weeks to see the entire state. But we returned home wishing not that we had seen more places, but that we had had more time to explore the ones we did.</p>
        <p>Seal's-eye view</p>
        <p>Cruise West has three different tours of the Inside Passage, leaving from Juneau, Ketchikan, or Seattle. Some tours may be combined with air, rail and bus transportation through mainland Alaska (including Anchorage, Fairbanks and Denali National Park), or with a three- or four-night cruise of Prince William Sound.</p>
        <p>The Alaska ships carry 78 to 102 passengers, the Prince William Sound ships 52 to 108. All tours are sold out for this year. Prices depend on size of cabin, size of ship, length of trip and time of year. For a typical nine-day cruise of the Inside Passage next year, the costs will range from just under $3,000 a person for the smallest double occupancy cabin to $4,895 a person for a deluxe cabin in July. At least one shore excursion (a walk with guides or sightseeing by bus) is included in each port of call. Call (800) 888-9378 for a video, schedule and rate information, or visit www.cruisewest.com.</p>
        <p>Alaska's Glacier Bay Tours and Cruises offers tours similar to those provided by Cruise West, but the company also has two itineraries for people who want to be out in the wilderness at all times. These ships stop not in cities along the way, but in places where you can drop a kayak off the top deck and paddle near a glacier, or hike through national forest areas where eagles are known to nest.</p>
        <p>Glacier Bay ships carry 34 to 88 passengers (the smaller boats are for wilderness cruises). Tours are booked for this year. Rates for 2001 range from $1,680 a person, double occupancy, for the most rugged six-night wilderness cruise, to $3,780 for a seven-night port-to-port trip, shore  excursions included. Call (800) 451-5952 for a brochure and video, or go to www  .glacierbaytours.com</p>
        <p>JOHN ROSENTHAL writes frequently about travel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">JOHN ROSENTHAL writes frequently about travel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
