<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High Rate of Asthma For Hartford Children</title>
    <meta content="20ASTH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223847"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asthma</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hartford (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tuhus, Melinda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Asthma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/Hartford</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asthma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E4DD163EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="931" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High Rate of Asthma For Hartford Children</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA TUHUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tuhus, Melinda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>City Council in Hartford, Conn, prompted by results of screening of local children, declares asthma emergency, fortifying effort at city, state and federal levels to find cause of problem, conduct preventive education and provide treatment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A screening of Hartford children for asthma shows that 41 percent have the illness, which city officials and environmental activists believe is the highest rate in the country. Among the city's Latino youngsters, the rate is 48 percent.</p>
        <p>Those numbers persuaded Hartford's City Council to declare an asthma emergency last Monday. The vote fortifies an effort at the city, state and federal levels to find the cause of the widespread problem, conduct education for prevention and provide treatment to the thousands of city residents who need it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A screening of Hartford children for asthma shows that 41 percent have the illness, which city officials and environmental activists believe is the highest rate in the country. Among the city's Latino youngsters, the rate is 48 percent.</p>
        <p>Those numbers persuaded Hartford's City Council to declare an asthma emergency last Monday. The vote fortifies an effort at the city, state and federal levels to find the cause of the widespread problem, conduct education for prevention and provide treatment to the thousands of city residents who need it.</p>
        <p>The Connecticut Children's Medical Center, with a grant from the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation, is screening all Hartford children for asthma under its Easy Breathing project; so far, more than 6,600 have been tested -- 20 percent of the city's population under 15. A 1997 study of adults by the Hartford Health Department identified 17 percent of adults with asthma. Nationally, the asthma rate for all ages is 7 percent.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Kertanis, an epidemiologist with the state Department of Public Health, urged caution about the medical center's numbers for Hartford children. ''This sampling of children may not be representative of all of Hartford's kids,'' she said. ''We don't know if every child in Hartford has the opportunity to participate in the survey.''</p>
        <p>What is causing Hartford's asthma rate to rise? No one knows what causes the illness, which is the most common medical reason for children to miss school, according to the federal Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, with each asthmatic child missing an average of 50 days per school year. But health experts do know that several factors can trigger attacks in people who have asthma: cigarette smoke, mold, pollen, animal dander and cockroaches. Experts say family and socioeconomic variables are involved as well, with higher rates for poor children and black and Latino children.</p>
        <p>Asthma is not a reportable illness under public health guidelines, so data is not available from all cities and states. But of the places that have gathered statistics, Hartford ranks No. 1. (New Haven's childhood asthma rate of 25 percent, from a study conducted by Connecticut Voices for Children, seems high except in comparison with Hartford's.)</p>
        <p>The Hartford City Council resolution, sponsored by Deputy Mayor Frances Sanchez and Councilwoman Elizabeth Horton Sheff, calls for a multimedia, multilingual asthma education and outreach campaign, especially targeting those most at risk. It also requests the state health department and the Centers for Disease Control to conduct an epidemiological study to determine why Hartford's asthma rate is so high and how the illness can be prevented.</p>
        <p>The resolution also requests monitoring of asthma rates; increasing screening; encouraging accurate diagnosis, treatment and self-management of asthma; promoting full enforcement of environmental laws and regulations to protect lung health; and increasing public education of how recycling reduces trash incineration and reduces air pollution.</p>
        <p>That last policy goal was included at the urging of the Hartford Environmental Justice Network, a coalition of 25 neighborhood, parent, religious, labor and environmental groups that believes trash incineration produces air pollution and toxins that trigger asthma attacks.</p>
        <p>Connecticut burns more of its garbage than any other state, the federal Environmental Protection Agency says, and Hartford is the incineration capital, with 66 Connecticut towns -- as well as towns in New York, Massachusetts and Vermont -- taking their garbage to the city, according to the Connecticut Department of Environmental Protection's solid waste management plan for 1999. A flier from the Environmental Justice Network says Hartford is home to eight regional waste facilities -- more than any other city in the state -- and four power plants.</p>
        <p>''Hartford is the dumping ground for the entire region,'' said Cynthia R. Jennings, a lawyer and chairman of the Connecticut Coalition for Environmental Justice, parent of the Hartford group. ''If it's dirty, it's in Hartford and we have to breathe it every day.''</p>
        <p>The group believes that sources of environmental pollution are concentrated in poor, mostly minority neighborhoods, resulting in disproportionate health problems for those communities.</p>
        <p>Katherine McCormack, the Hartford health director, said that her department had already taken steps to raise awareness about asthma, but that much more needed to be done. She expects the city council resolution will jump-start more resources for the effort. The city has already allocated one additional position to her department for an asthma outreach worker.</p>
        <p>Ms. McCormack said that one major objective was to decrease hospitalization for asthma among children and that providing information about smoking-cessation programs would help.</p>
        <p>The city is already working with the state health department, the Connecticut Children's Medical Center and the American Lung Association of Connecticut, among others. The lung association runs a program called Open Airways for Schools in which 8- to 11-year-olds in more than 25 Hartford schools learn to recognize early warning signs of asthma, like dry cough, wheezing, tightness in the chest and itchy, watery eyes.</p>
        <p>''They learn what triggers their own asthma attacks and they become more able to manage their condition to live as normal a life as possible,'' said Angela Testa, program coordinator. She said that in the program's two years, children had missed fewer days of school and spent fewer days in the hospital.</p>
        <p>''Asthma kills people,'' Ms. Jennings said. ''It's like putting a pillow over your face and holding it there. But if you don't see a child in the midst of an asthma attack, you don't see how they are suffering. If 41 percent of people woke up blind one day, then they would know what a problem it is.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
