<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>She Knows What You Did Last Summer</title>
    <meta content="20JAMSCT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223712"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jamison, Laura</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blake, Sarah</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Grange House (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3D6163FF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>She Knows What You Did Last Summer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Laura Jamison</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jamison, Laura</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Laura Jamison reviews novel Grange House by Sarah Blake (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GRANGE HOUSE</p>
        <p>By Sarah Blake.</p>
        <p>375 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Picador USA. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GRANGE HOUSE</p>
        <p>By Sarah Blake.</p>
        <p>375 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Picador USA. $24.</p>
        <p>WHEN Sarah Blake's pleasing, intricate first novel, ''Grange House,'' opens, the year is 1896, and young Maisie Thomas has returned to the seaside hotel in Maine where she and her parents stay every summer. Now on the eve of womanhood, 17-year-old Maisie is ''eager to know the world,'' a desire that is entirely at odds with what others have in mind for her -- a walk down the aisle. ''I'd like,'' Maisie complains to Miss Grange, a spinster ''authoress'' who has spent her life in this mansion-turned-resort, a story ''in which the heroine is not directed straight into marriage.''</p>
        <p>Maisie soon has her wish. After a pair of young lovers drown, the mysterious Miss Grange moans, ''The old story of Grange House has repeated once again,'' and instructs Maisie to try to stop this process, leading her to a tiny grave hidden in the woods and declaring that it harbors ''the last story, the unwritten story. . . . This one I never could write. . . . I pass it on. . . . To you. To write it.'' Happily for our heroine, she has entered a story in which she is not at all ''directed straight into marriage''; rather, she has been appointed the story's director.</p>
        <p>Blake, who has a doctorate in Victorian literature, has plundered all the best elements of her favored genre: ghostly apparitions, shameful secrets glinting in the moonlight, an intelligent heroine who resists the plot threatening to be imposed on her life -- that is, the marriage plot. And while it's hard not to wrinkle your nose at the first seemingly stagy whiffs of Victoriana, Blake draws nicely on her familiarity with the era, respectably adopting its language and vividly evoking its manners.</p>
        <p>She also deftly layers calamities and intrigue. Before Maisie can fully comprehend her assignment from Miss Grange, a terrible misfortune befalls the young woman's family and she must return home to Brooklyn. But the spinster begins sending her bits of old letters and diaries, which serve both to partly uncover the mysteries of Grange House and further obscure them. The papers also reveal a painful truth about Maisie's relatives. And just as Maisie is about to master Miss Grange's story, a suitor makes his move to annex her into one of his own, a story of romance.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, a nagging problem afflicts this generally delightful book. Maisie admirably wishes to control the course of her life; to use an appropriate metaphor, she wants to be the author of her life's narrative. But here the metaphor is made literal: writing a story is imagined as a way of creating -- and therefore controlling -- reality. Miss Grange, for instance, insists that writing the story of the grave will have a manifest effect on the lives of those at Grange House. (Though why she maddeningly parcels out half-truths to her chosen ghostwriter makes little sense; it seems intended more for novelistic suspense than for Maisie's edification.) Furthermore, images of reading and writing appear with tiresome frequency; at one point, we read about a woman who is reading the diaries of another woman who is writing about a discussion on writing. Certainly the best Victorian heroines strive to be the authors of their life stories, but perhaps this theme is better explored in less literal terms than Blake does here.</p>
        <p>Yet if she errs on that count, Blake wins on most others. The secret that is revealed at the novel's close is a humdinger and does much to compensate for our earlier exasperation. ''Grange House'' also finds its own distinctive way of resolving Maisie's battle with the marriage plot. In the final pages, she learns that ''a woman's story is not single, never a lone tramp toward the end. . . . Because there are the voices of her house. The lit rooms, peopled and cushioned, that she carries. And though she may travel. . . . Aye, that is the horror of it -- she may never travel from the house that made her.''</p>
        <p>Laura Jamison is a freelance writer living in New York.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Laura Jamison is a freelance writer living in New York.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
