<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.Y.I.</title>
    <meta content="20FYI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pigeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Printing and Allied Trades</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, Daniel B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFD8153EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.Y.I.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schneider, Daniel B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>FYI column answers questions on upholstered tree stumps on West 42nd Street, why certain lampposts seem to attract more pigeons and pigeon droppings than others, and about a Midtown church that used to celebrate Printer's Mass in the middle of the night; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bark Is So Passe</p>
        <p>Q.: Someone has upholstered three tree stumps on the north side of West 42nd Street, between Eighth and 10th Avenues. Why?</p>
        <p>A.: ''I'm trying to take care of something that's been dismembered, been neglected,'' said Madelon Galland, a sculptor, who has been upholstering tree stumps around Manhattan since October 1999, mostly on West 42nd Street and in the East Village.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bark Is So Passe</p>
        <p>Q.: Someone has upholstered three tree stumps on the north side of West 42nd Street, between Eighth and 10th Avenues. Why?</p>
        <p>A.: ''I'm trying to take care of something that's been dismembered, been neglected,'' said Madelon Galland, a sculptor, who has been upholstering tree stumps around Manhattan since October 1999, mostly on West 42nd Street and in the East Village.</p>
        <p>The Stump Project, as it is called, eventually became the thesis project for Ms. Galland's Hunter College master's degree in fine arts. Of the 15 stumps she has upholstered to date, all but 7 have been removed by the Parks Department and replaced by new trees, an action Ms. Galland describes as ''the ideal outcome.''</p>
        <p>Working in broad daylight, and without the city's permission, Ms. Galland uses the tools and techniques of conventional upholsterers -- staple gun, hammer, pliers, tacks -- to stretch a piece of vinyl or Naugahyde over the top of the stump, trim it and finish it like a piece of furniture. Some stumps are high and wide enough to function as padded stools, while others are as small as three inches in diameter, or almost flat upon the ground. The process can take 20 minutes to two hours, Ms. Galland said, and is sometimes recorded on videotape.</p>
        <p>Neat, professional-looking and quietly absurd, the upholstered stumps do not immediately identify themselves as artworks. ''They are almost invisible,'' said Ms. Galland, who grew up in the redwood country of Northern California. ''But by upholstering them I bring attention to the stumps, and hopefully, help resuscitate them.'' Upholstered tree stumps, of course, lend themselves to multiple readings. ''One guy thought I was protecting people from stubbing their toes,'' Ms. Galland said.</p>
        <p>Life Is Like That</p>
        <p>Q.: Why is it that certain lampposts seem to attract far more pigeons -- and far more pigeon droppings -- than others?</p>
        <p>A.: It's probably breadcrumbs, not lampposts, that are attracting the pigeons, says Veronique Connolly, a Cornell ornithologist associated with the university's Project Pigeon Watch. ''Most of the time, if they're choosing one lamppost over another, it's going to be about the availability of food,'' she said. ''If there's a source of food nearby, the pigeons will stay there.''</p>
        <p>The food source may not be evident, especially since pigeons in the city tend to eat just about anything that falls on the ground, but Ms. Connolly said they are intelligent enough to remember where -- and when -- a regular feeding occurs, and to wait. ''Pigeons usually feed early in the morning and late in the afternoon, but birds that rely on human feeding will adjust to a human schedule,'' she said. ''If one person has been feeding the pigeons, they will learn to recognize them.''</p>
        <p>Pigeons are genetically programmed to perch on lampposts, which resemble the cliffs and rocky ledges of their primordial habitat, Ms. Connolly said. The composition of the flock is not static, however, so on a given lamppost, about half the group will be regulars, and half might be visitors from other flocks. ''We don't know everything about pigeons,'' Ms. Connolly said.</p>
        <p>Away, Printer's Devil!</p>
        <p>Q.: Which Midtown church used to celebrate the ''Printer's Mass'' in the middle of the night?</p>
        <p>A.: The Rev. Francis P. Duffy inaugurated the ''Printer's Mass'' at the Church of the Holy Cross at 329 West 42nd Street in 1932. The Roman Catholic Mass was offered at 2:20 a.m. on Sunday morning to serve late-shift workers at The New York Herald Tribune, The Daily News, The Daily Mirror and The New York Times, all of which had offices nearby.</p>
        <p>DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</p>
        <p>E-mail: daschn@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: daschn@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
