<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="20GUID$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EED9163EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1349" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Barbara Delatiner</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>Almost by stealth, the summer is disappearing, signaling the arrival of fall festivals. This week offers a taste of things to come.</p>
        <p>For example, today's Street Fair and Polka Dance Festival in Polonaise Park in Riverhead. From 10 a.m. to 6 p.m., the fair's the thing, with ethnic foods, arts and crafts, music and the re-enactment of such customs as an authentic Polish wedding. Then, from 4 to 10 p.m., the Freddie K. Band and Lenny Gomulka and Chicago Push turn everyone's attention to the polka (631) 369-1616.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>Almost by stealth, the summer is disappearing, signaling the arrival of fall festivals. This week offers a taste of things to come.</p>
        <p>For example, today's Street Fair and Polka Dance Festival in Polonaise Park in Riverhead. From 10 a.m. to 6 p.m., the fair's the thing, with ethnic foods, arts and crafts, music and the re-enactment of such customs as an authentic Polish wedding. Then, from 4 to 10 p.m., the Freddie K. Band and Lenny Gomulka and Chicago Push turn everyone's attention to the polka (631) 369-1616.</p>
        <p>Ethnicity also figures in one of two events on Saturday: the 40th Annual Scottish Games at Old Westbury Gardens. Besides traditional foods like fish and chips and scones, and Scottish and Gaelic crafts, the day, from 8 a.m. to 5 p.m., will include Scottish bagpipe music and Highland dancing and demonstrations and competitions in caber-tossing, sheepdog trials and putting the stone (516) 333-0048.</p>
        <p>There's nothing as exotic at the annual Seafood Festival from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Saturday and next Sunday at the Long Island Maritime Museum on West Avenue in West Sayville. Just fish and fishing, with Long Island seafood and entertainment featuring seafaring stuff like sea chanteys, an exhibition of antique boats and accompanying crafts demonstrations and sales. The museum will be open to visitors (631) 854-4974.</p>
        <p>East End Talk</p>
        <p>When Hamptons celebrities in various fields get together, chances are the conversation will be about art or theater. This week the talk about both subjects will be in public, giving those not necessarily in the loop an opportunity to eavesdrop. Today it's ''Art Criticism: Whose Truth?,'' a round table discussion at 5 p.m. at the LongHouse Reserve on Hands Creek Road in East Hampton. Those chatting with Rose Slivka, the moderator, include the art critics Grace Glueck and Peter Schjeldahl; the writer David Lehman; Klaus Kertess, curator of the current ''Willem de Kooning: In Process'' exhibition at Guild Hall; the painter Connie Fox, and the ceramics artist Diane Mayo (631) 329-3568.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow at 8 p.m., the question at the Bay Street Theater in Sag Hrabor will be ''American Musical Theater -- Quo Vadis?,'' with Peter Stone moderating a panel consisting of such practitioners as Betty Comden, Adolph Green, Cy Coleman and Sheldon Harnick (631) 725-9500.</p>
        <p>Doubling Up</p>
        <p>The fact that performers make the best of their road trips by playing as often as possible in a given area is not news. But this week that non-news makes headlines when fans of two artists have multiple chances to catch their acts. Today in a free concert at 8:30 p.m. at Heckscher Park in Huntington, Clarence (Gatemouth) Brown, that veteran master of American roots music, performs in the finale of the Huntington Arts Council's Summer Arts Festival (631) 271-8423. On Saturday, Mr. Brown takes his blues and jazz -- and his fiddle and harmonica -- to Amagansett and the Stephen Talkhouse on Main Street for an 8 p.m. performance (631) 267-3117.</p>
        <p>Then there's Dr. John, the three-time Grammy-winning funk rock legend. He appears today at 7 p.m. at Jones Beach State Park in Wantagh in ''Destination: New Orleans,'' sharing the stage with John Fogerty and Aaron Neville (516) 221-1000. Come Friday and he travels east to the Westhampton Beach Performing Arts Center on Main Street, 8:30 p.m. (631) 288-1500.</p>
        <p>'Male Intellect'</p>
        <p>Robert Dubac, an actor and playwright, has a performing personality that splits six ways. And all of them figure in his one-man show ''The Male Intellect: An Oxymoron?,'' which pulls into the Westhampton Beach Performing Arts Center on Saturday for a two-night run. In this comic examination of male-female relationships, Mr. Dubac, in his ''Bobby'' mode as a young man dumped by the girl of his dreams, queries five male mentors to find the answer to the question, ''What do women want?'' These alter-egos range from the Colonel, whose forte is honesty, to Old Mr. Linger, a 123-year-old bachelor still searching for his perfect woman, a mermaid, to Fast Eddie, who is ''all sex and no relationship.'' The show can be seen at 8:30 p.m. Saturday and 7 p.m. Sunday (631) 288-1500.</p>
        <p>Fading Summer</p>
        <p>Quick, before the summer disappears entirely, there's still time to make the rounds of parks for free outdoor concerts.</p>
        <p>Today Mark Morganelli headlines an ''All-Star Jazz Tribute'' at 8 p.m. at Morgan Park in Glen Cove (516) 759-6970, while in Southold, Dave Raphelson, a guitarist who specializes in Victorian music, plays a concert of 19th-century tunes, at 1 p.m. at the Oysterpond Historical Society Village House, on Village Lane in Orient (631) 323-2480. In Stony Brook, on the Village Green at 8 p.m., Black Tie Affair recreates the big band sound (631) 751-2244.</p>
        <p>The various beats go on throughout the week: T'Bazco Road's country music at 8 p.m. Tuesday at New York Beach in Long Beach (516) 432-3890; the Lone Sharks rockabilly at 6:45 p.m. Wednesday at Agawam Park in Southampton (631) 287-4377; the Greenport Band at 8 p.m. Wednesday on the Town Green in Southold (631) 765-3598; the Merrymakers Steel Band at 7:30 p.m. Thursday on the Village Green in Westhampton Beach (631) 288-0780; the Band of Long Island at 8:15 p.m. Friday at the Sousa Band Shell in Port Washington (516) 739-2345; and on Saturday, the Long Island Philharmonic with works by Bernstein, Gould and Tchaikovsky -- and fireworks by Grucci -- at 8 p.m. at the Brookhaven Amphitheater in Farmingville (631) 732-4011; or Randy and the Rainbows at 6 p.m. at Overlook Beach in Babylon (631) 893-2119.</p>
        <p>Firefighters</p>
        <p>More than 25 fire departments from all over the Island will be in Riverhead on Saturday to compete in the Riverhead Fire Department's 13th Annual Invitational Motorized Drill. The volunteers, including the West Sayville Flying Dutchmen, who were the New York State Champions in 1999, will vie for honors in such evolutions as the three-person ladder, motorized ladders and hoses, motor pumps and a bucket brigade.  The drill starts at 10 a.m. at the department's training grounds on Route 58 (631) 727-2751.</p>
        <p>Afternoon Music</p>
        <p>If you're in downtown Bay Shore or perhaps shopping at the malls in Garden City and Westbury, you can take a pleasant midday break with a musical interlude. In Bay Shore, at the Gazebo on Main Street, the Scirocco Wind Quintet does the honors at 12:30 p.m. on Tuesday (631) 224-5420. In a shady area between Parking Fields 6 and 6A in Eisenhower Park, in East Meadow, the Sound on Sound Band closes out the Noontime Concert Series at noon Wednesday (516) 572-0223.</p>
        <p>Puente Tribute</p>
        <p>Tito Puente may be gone, but his particular brand of music is not forgotten. His orchestra and special guest stars appear in ''A Tribute to Tito Puente'' on Saturday at 8 p.m. at the Friends of the Arts Long Island Summer Festival in Planting Fields in Oyster Bay. The evening features the Tito Puente Latin Jazz Ensemble and such colleagues of the late ''Mambo King'' as Bobby Sanabria and his group Ascension (516) 922-0061.</p>
        <p>Free Choices</p>
        <p>TODAY -- Edward Kalendar leads a klezmer quintet at 2:30 p.m. in the Astarita Garden on the grounds of the Merrick Library on Merrick Avenue (516) 379-3476.</p>
        <p>TOMORROW -- Parents are the heroes in two talks: Using stories from from his mother's life, Mario Macaluso has fashioned ''My Mother: Memoir of a Sicilian Women,'' which he presents at 1:30 p.m. at the Levittown Library on Bluegrass Lane (516) 731-5728, while Steven E. Danish, who wrote ''One Soldier's Memories: World War II,'' offers ''Walk the War in My Father's Boots'' at 7 p.m. at the Lindenhurst Library on Lee Avenue (631) 957-7755.</p>
        <p>Compiled by Barbara Delatiner</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
