<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Casbah for Clothes Is Bustling in California.</title>
    <meta content="20ROOT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223937"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GRASS-ROOTS BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Santee Alley</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kotkin, Joel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE2DB143EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1498" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Casbah for Clothes Is Bustling in California.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL KOTKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kotkin, Joel</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joel Kotkin column on retail apparel corridor in Los Angeles, Santee Alley; 80-block jumble of pre-war commercial buildings houses 5,000 companies employing 50,000 people and taking in $8 billion annually in retail and wholesale business; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is just a short walk from the Staples Center, where the Democrats, the news media and assorted demonstrators spent the week playing out the politics of the information age. But the thriving Los Angeles fashion district has more in common with 12th-century Baghdad than the California of the new millennium.</p>
        <p>The 80-block jumble of prewar commercial buildings, hastily constructed low-rise arcades commingled with a few modern towers, is home to 5,000 companies employing 50,000 people and taking in $8 billion a year in wholesale and retail sales. And it epitomizes raw capitalism in both its glory and its shame.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is just a short walk from the Staples Center, where the Democrats, the news media and assorted demonstrators spent the week playing out the politics of the information age. But the thriving Los Angeles fashion district has more in common with 12th-century Baghdad than the California of the new millennium.</p>
        <p>The 80-block jumble of prewar commercial buildings, hastily constructed low-rise arcades commingled with a few modern towers, is home to 5,000 companies employing 50,000 people and taking in $8 billion a year in wholesale and retail sales. And it epitomizes raw capitalism in both its glory and its shame.</p>
        <p>The district has a reputation for paying its lowest rung of workers brutally low wages -- which drew the ire of demonstrators last week -- and for having too little respect for trademark laws and tax codes. But for many of those who work here, including some who have made fortunes, the district also reflects the essence of the American dream. It is a place where recent immigrants can build successful businesses and new lives in an environment not dissimilar to those found in many developing countries.</p>
        <p>''What we have here is a souk,'' said Uri Harkham, one of the major property owners in the district. ''It's open to everyone, and it's the kind of place you can go to buy something for $3 or $300.''</p>
        <p>MR. HARKHAM, who was born in Iraq and is chief executive of Jonathan Martin, one of the area's leading garment manufacturers with more than $100 million in annual sales, is reluctant to talk specifically about the extent of his holdings in the district. But they are big and growing. One new building that he is constructing with his Moroccan-born partner, Moshe Aflalo, has space for 13 retail stores and more than 60 companies clamoring to fill them.</p>
        <p>The district, just southeast of the center of downtown Los Angeles, was widely perceived as dirty and dangerous five years ago, but it has since blossomed. Property values have more than doubled and vacancies, particularly for ground-floor properties, are almost impossible to find in much of the area, said Ed Zoraster, a vice president at CB Richard Ellis, a real estate broker. The city has issued more than 650 building permits for renovations or new construction in the district since 1995.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zoraster gives some credit for the revival to a business improvement district, organized that year, that has improved the neighborhood's appearance and security. But the most important factor, he said, has been the drive of immigrants like Mr. Harkham, 52, who came to Los Angeles in 1975 after living in Israel and Australia.</p>
        <p>Like many of his peers, Mr. Harkham brought with him the bazaar culture of his native land, with its love of bargaining, jostling and quick, seat-of-the-pants decision-making. ''At the end of the day, the Middle Easterners are all traders at heart -- Arab, Jew and Persian, Christian, Muslim, it doesn't matter,'' he said. ''We have the ambition and the drive others don't. The fashion business is so fast you have to be willing to be a gambler, and live on the edge.''</p>
        <p>Jerry Sullivan, the editor of California Apparel News, a trade paper, said newcomers from the Middle East and North Africa had largely replaced the American-born Jewish entrepreneurs, many transplanted from New York, who helped establish Los Angeles as a leading center for sportswear and women's garment manufacturing in the 1950's. Though Middle Easterners own only 7 percent of the district's apparel manufacturers and account for a negligible part of the factory work force, they own most of the area's premier brands, including Guess, Hot Kiss, Bissou Bissou and BCBG, and control much of the region's textile trade.</p>
        <p>''These guys are better at developing brands and styles than anyone else who has been here,'' Mr. Sullivan said. ''They are more aggressive than the native-born. They know what sexy is. They are willing to strike their own path and offer no apologies.''</p>
        <p>The restaurant scene in the district has come to reflect the new ethnic order. Many Israeli, Persian and North African establishments have opened, and many get the bulk of their sales from meals they deliver to their perpetually harried customers. Korean eateries are also popping up, reflecting Korean immigrants' emergence as the second powerful ethnic influence in the increasingly polyglot district.</p>
        <p>UNLIKE those from the Middle East, who dominate the local industry's high-fashion end, the Korean entrepreneurs tend to make their presence felt in the lower price ranges and in manufacturing. Victor C. Kim, owner of Cherish International, a consulting firm in the district, said people of Korean background own at least 600 wholesale and retail operations, as many as 1,000 contractors -- the companies who actually do the sewing under contract from marketers and design houses -- and hundreds of knitting and other manufacturing operations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim said many business people of Korean descent in the district felt unfairly tarred with negative stereotypes -- that Koreans rely on knockoffs of styles developed by others; that the worst wages and most abusive labor practices are found in their factories; that they dodge paying taxes. In fact, he said, Koreans are more likely than other groups to be victims of unfair business practices, like landlords' demands for astronomical rents and ''key money,'' an upfront payment to obtain a lease that can run as high as $200,000. Protests by Korean groups against this practice have been laced with talk about ''Merchant of Venice'' figures, a none-too-subtle stereotyping of the landlords, many of whom are Jewish, Mr. Sullivan said.</p>
        <p>The tensions may ease as the Korean segment of the district becomes more self-sufficient, Mr. Kim said, with Korean-owned banks and real estate companies coming to the fore and with Korean-owned garment companies like Koo's Manufacturing, Bubblegum USA and Impression developing their own fashion sensibility, often by hiring recent Korean-American graduates of the nearby Fashion Institute of Design and Merchandising and other local design schools.</p>
        <p>Latinos constitute the third major ethnic element in the district, accounting for the majority of the work force, including 85 percent of factory workers; most retail shoppers in the district are Hispanic as well. Spanish-speaking immigrants have only begun to be a business force in the district, through the rise of locally trained designers of Latin background and through ownership of sewing shops.</p>
        <p>Sewing is proving to be the part of the industry most vulnerable to overseas competition, said Joe Rodriguez, the executive director of the Garment Contractors Association of Southern California. The number of production jobs has fallen by 10,000 since the peak in 1997, and low unemployment has made the remaining jobs harder to fill with legal workers.</p>
        <p>Ordinarily, Mr. Rodriguez said, such conditions might lead to higher wages. But most shops cannot afford to go much above the $7-an-hour average paid by most contractors, because of intense price pressures from retail customers and the ease with which production can be moved outside the country, especially to Mexico.</p>
        <p>THOSE pressures have also hampered union organizers, who, after decades of trying, have yet to penetrate virtually any of the district's small factories, most employing 50 or fewer workers. Goetz Wolff, research director for the County Federation of Labor, cited overseas competition, fragmentation and the ready supply of illegal workers available to less scrupulous operators.</p>
        <p>''There are still lots of illegal shops,'' said Mr. Wolff, an economist who has studied the garment industry for years. ''Everyone says they don't know about it, or someone else is doing it. But somebody is buying the product.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Wolff and other economists predict that the district will continue to thrive, partly because of the fashion world's rapid pace of change and the resulting need for quick turnaround by manufacturers. They also point to the growing influence of Los Angeles as a design center and to the region's huge and highly diverse consumer base.</p>
        <p>''This kind of thing can't be stopped,'' said Mr. Harkham at his real estate office in the heart of the district. ''It's a very unique place, and it serves the region's melting pot. There's a comfort level to being here. You have the good, bad and the ugly, but it works.''</p>
        <p>GRASS-ROOTS BUSINESS Joel Kotkin is a senior fellow at the Davenport Institute for Public Policy at Pepperdine University. His column on the Main Street economy appears the third Sunday of each month. E-mail may be sent to  grassrts@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Joel Kotkin is a senior fellow at the Davenport Institute for Public Policy at Pepperdine University. His column on the Main Street economy appears the third Sunday of each month. E-mail may be sent to
&lt;br&gt;grassrts@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
