<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paint Me a Dinner</title>
    <meta content="20DINE$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223910"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Foy's (Point Pleasant Beach, Nj, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Catherine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E7DE143EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1173" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paint Me a Dinner</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHERINE JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Catherine</byline>
      <dateline>POINT PLEASANT BEACH</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Catherine Jones reviews Foy's restaurnat in Point Pleasant Beach, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DENNIS FOY, a highly respected New Jersey chef, is also a painter. He has kept a studio in Point Pleasant Beach since 1982, finding rare minutes to paint while spearheading restaurants in Chatham, Summit and  Manhattan. However, the white walls are left bare at Foy's, his month-old restaurant here.</p>
        <p>''My paintings are so personal, I wouldn't enjoy hearing the criticism,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DENNIS FOY, a highly respected New Jersey chef, is also a painter. He has kept a studio in Point Pleasant Beach since 1982, finding rare minutes to paint while spearheading restaurants in Chatham, Summit and  Manhattan. However, the white walls are left bare at Foy's, his month-old restaurant here.</p>
        <p>''My paintings are so personal, I wouldn't enjoy hearing the criticism,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One bite of the tuna tartare and I realized there was no need for any other form of art.</p>
        <p>''This dish is both balanced and convoluted in its composition,'' Mr. Foy explained. ''The cinnamon, apples and cucumber add a variety of flavors; the dash of truffle oil, a surprise.'' It was a curious dish in its blending of land and sea, but utterly addictive, and so simple in its execution. But still, he said, the tuna is ''convoluted like my paintings,'' which he described as representational landscapes created with a modern palette and 17th-century glazes. Fresh color layered with old techniques, a dead-on description of hot entrees of the moment -- simply substitute seared wahoo for color and turn glazing into some sort of reduction.</p>
        <p>There is certainly a kinship between painting and cooking. Both require technical craftsmanship and each has limitations that drive the artist to further excel.</p>
        <p>''I've always had an eye,'' Mr. Foy said with a smile. ''And cooking, being more immediately satisfying, has been where I've devoted the most time.''</p>
        <p>And for that, New Jersey is fortunate. Mr. Foy's culinary combinations clearly express just what he's made of, and that is a mixture of zeal and talent.</p>
        <p>The cucumber soup, for example, is composed of onions sweated in butter, pureed and then thinned with cucumber juice diluted with distilled water. It is summer in a bowl.  Shaved baby fennel is lightly splashed with a green dressing made from lemon juice, olive oil, balsamic vinegar and parsley. Haricots verts and asparagus (slightly chewy) were as loosely arranged as a vase overflowing with sunflowers.</p>
        <p>But three appetizers will make you pause for breath. One of them, a warm Montrachet goat cheese tart, does not have a pastry base, nor does it need one. A foundation of confited thyme-infused Jersey beefsteak tomatoes (cooked slowly overnight in  olive oil) supported the warm disc of cheese. Toasted bread crumbs added crunch and a welcome garlic flavor. The tuna tartare mentioned above was brightened not only with cinnamon, apples, cucumber and truffle oil but was also softened with rice wine vinegar, balsamic vinegar, chive oil and fresh thyme. And Mr. Foy's signature dish, the tian of crab,  unabashedly unadorned, expertly sauteed and made with top-quality jumbo lump crab meat, provided pure joy.</p>
        <p>The entrees are primarily fish-driven, as Mr. Foy buys from the dayboats along the shore before scripting his menu at 5:30 p.m. The dishes are mostly protein, with a small, lovely vegetable accent. Seared wahoo, much like yellowtail in texture, was set atop a row of sliced golden beets beside a mound of smoked, thinly sliced squid in a spicy chili glaze. This dish was colorful, texturally stimulating and flavorfully aggressive. Sushi-grade tuna, sauteed only slightly, was paired with a Mediterranean stew studded with artichokes, roasted peppers, garlic, confit tomatoes and zucchini.</p>
        <p>The soft-shelled crabs took a little getting used to, as they veered from traditional deep-frying or sauteeing preparations and also still sported their gills -- thoroughly cleaned, but left because ''they brim with salt water and add so much'' Mr. Foy said. He removed the crunchy posterior, roasted the crabs gently and quickly in butter, and then served them with Silver Queen corn, confited tomatoes and roasted carrots and potatoes, as if his guest were at a clambake. The dish was visually and texturally unusual, but it too tasted like summer and was honest Foy cuisine.</p>
        <p>Roasted diver scallops with cauliflower puree and sauteed chanterelles were a sensual textural experience. The mushrooms, imported from France, transported me deep into the woods, but then the silken vegetable puree, rounded out with creme fraiche, got me thinking of getting back indoors to lie down on a luxurious chaise. Mr. Foy said the mushrooms reminded him of the sensual curve of an earlobe (he's an artist, after all), and he thought it fitting to add a seductive finishing drizzle of decadent scallop butter.</p>
        <p>The poeled halibut reached the ethereal. Poeled means cooking by quickly immersing in hot liquid. In this case the fish was cooked in grape seed oil until just barely done. Once drained, the tender fish finished cooking on the plate, and the result was a mound of almost translucent, highly flavorful, smooth meat that may have been the best halibut preparation I've ever tasted. The wonderful roast shallot puree and the sweated dandelion greens added color and a pleasing touch of both bitter and sweet.</p>
        <p>Desserts at Foys are small in portion but, not surprisingly, big on quality. Bubbling lemon sabayon filled a pine-nut-flavored pate sucre, and despite the pleasure this afforded, the accompanying dollop of honey mascarpone did not go unnoticed. Decadent chocolate royale over a crispy praline disc was a bit rich for me;  not so the creme brulee, plain, simple and satisfying.</p>
        <p>This new gem of a spot could easily be given a rating of excellent -- the steep prices certainly raise expectations. But there's time for that. Mr. Foy, supported by his sous chef, Laurie Samules, and his children, the skilled Natasha, and the sunny Dennis Jr., has all of the ingredients at his fingertips. But something about the spartan decor, the harsh lighting and the distracting storefront nature of the space calls out for change.</p>
        <p>Given all that and the casual approach of the service, maybe Mr. Foy is content to do without the big impact of his earlier restaurants.  Perhaps he's created something else altogether. With offerings like the purist tian or the simple brulee, the ''convoluted'' tuna tartare or the sexy scallops, Foy's is an art gallery in its own right, a place where you can purchase, and consume, a work of art from the hands of a master.</p>
        <p>Foy's  816 Arnold Avenue, Point Pleasant Beach  (732) 295-0466</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- So stark that it appears not yet finished.  SERVICE -- Surrounded by family, and a gracious one at that.  SMOKING -- Not allowed.  WINE LIST -- B.Y.O.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Cucumber soup; fennel salad; goat cheese tart; tian of crab; tuna tartare; soft-shelled crabs; pole halibut; Diver scallops; wahoo; lemon sabayon; chocolate royale; creme brulee.  PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers; $7.25 to $13.75; Entrees: $25 to $39; Desserts: $8.50.  CREDIT CARDS -- All major.  HOURS -- Daily from 6 to 11 p.m. in summer; Thursday to Sunday nights in off-season.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: All on street level.</p>
        <p>RATINGS Poor, Fair, Satisfactory, Good, Very Good, Excellent,  Extraordinary.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambiance and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
