<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Soaring to the Heights, on a Rubber Band</title>
    <meta content="20JOUR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Models and Replicas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cradle of Aviation Museum (Garden City, NY)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Squash! The Improv Troupe</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bender, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mayo, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFD61F3FF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Soaring to the Heights, on a Rubber Band</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Journal column: Bob Bender, 75, retired New York City police officer from Mineola, builds and flies ultra-light model planes made of balsa and tissue paper and powered by rubber bands in nearly empty hangar at Cradle of Aviation Museum at Mitchel Field; college students, many of them Deborah Mayo's former Pumpkin Patch Players members, are performing this summer as members of Squash! The Improv Troupe at the Red Barn in Brookhaven Hamlet; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HIS eyes sparkling like a little boy playing with a favorite toy, Bob Bender cranked the gear intently, winding the rubber band running through the fuselage of his homemade airplane tighter and tighter.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Bender, 75, walked to the center of the nearly empty hangar at the Cradle of Aviation Museum at Mitchel Field, delicately placed the tissue paper and balsa wood aircraft with a 13-inch windspan on the floor and released the propeller. Driven by the rubber-band motor, the tiny copy of a 1932 De Havilland Puss Moth with a red fuselage and white wings raced forward and lifted into the air, climbing higher and higher in a looping arc. Standing on the side, a group of volunteers who spend Wednesdays restoring old aircraft for the museum watched, counting the seconds of its flight, their mouths agape as it descended to a perfect landing on the cement floor 47 seconds later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HIS eyes sparkling like a little boy playing with a favorite toy, Bob Bender cranked the gear intently, winding the rubber band running through the fuselage of his homemade airplane tighter and tighter.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Bender, 75, walked to the center of the nearly empty hangar at the Cradle of Aviation Museum at Mitchel Field, delicately placed the tissue paper and balsa wood aircraft with a 13-inch windspan on the floor and released the propeller. Driven by the rubber-band motor, the tiny copy of a 1932 De Havilland Puss Moth with a red fuselage and white wings raced forward and lifted into the air, climbing higher and higher in a looping arc. Standing on the side, a group of volunteers who spend Wednesdays restoring old aircraft for the museum watched, counting the seconds of its flight, their mouths agape as it descended to a perfect landing on the cement floor 47 seconds later.</p>
        <p>''None of my planes are going to fly for a minute,'' Mr. Bender hedged, worried that having switched to new rubber bands the previous evening would affect how his Lilliputian fleet was going to perform. For each minute each craft remained aloft on a recent morning, the spectators agreed to a dollar donation, a grass-roots fund-raiser for the museum, which is scheduled to open next spring.</p>
        <p>''The meister,'' declared Bob Schwartz, 65, of Hicksville, a retired elevator constructor and one of the volunteers. ''Nothing to it,'' Mr. Schwartz said. ''Ten cents worth of balsa wood. Five cents worth of tissue paper, three cents worth of glue and 50 years of experience and he'll help any kid who wants to learn. I wish I could build airplanes the way he does. To see something like this fly is fantastic.''</p>
        <p>But the planes follow a strictly indoor trajectory. To keep Mr. Bender's gossamer winged, rubber-band powered, aeronautical models from tumbling to the ground, the air needs to be perfectly still.</p>
        <p>''The least little breeze affects these planes because they are so light,'' Mr. Bender said. ''The lighter the craft, the longer they can fly.''</p>
        <p>Five of his planes together would weigh no more than a penny. Under perfect conditions, the lightest aircraft can fly for over an hour -- the rubber band provides the thrust to overcome the drag; the curvature of the wings creates lift to overcome gravity and the rudder is offset to keep the plane flying in circles in a confined space.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bender, a retired New York City police officer from Mineola, was a radio operator on a B-24 during his service in the Air Corps during World War II in the Phillipines. He never earned a real pilot's license. He has found clear skies inside the cradle's hangar for more than 15 years, frequently giving model flying demonstrations.</p>
        <p>But this fall, as 64 aircraft begin to be rolled into the museum for a chronological display of aviation history from the Hempstead Plains to the Golden Age of Aviation, the jet age and the space age, Mr. Bender's hobby may be short a runway. So far, only a newly restored 1909 Bleriot, the fourth oldest airplane in the United States, and several missiles are in the hangar.</p>
        <p>''It's not the best place to fly, but it's almost the only place to fly,'' said Mr. Bender, though he also flies monthly during the academic year at East Memorial Public School in Farmingdale. Tom Gwynn, senior planning coordinator for the cradle, said the museum would try to help Mr. Bender secure a new location.</p>
        <p>Inspired by Lindbergh's first flight, Mr. Bender started building model airplanes at age 7, beginning with stationary models. By the time he was 12, he had shifted focus to the matchstick wings that could soar. As an adult, his passion for rubber-band aviation never wavered. He has constructed about 75 flying machines. One creation is crafted for endurance. Another does aerobatics. And one will take off from a standing stop on a concrete floor, sail to within inches of the ceiling and then land by itself with neither computer chips or remote-control toggle to direct it.</p>
        <p>''If I had to be at work at 5 o'clock, I would get up at 4 o'clock and go down the cellar even if I only put one stick on that board,'' Mr. Bender recalled while preparing a hang glider-like Rogollo-wing plane for a quick takeoff.</p>
        <p>Next, to keep the fuselage from rattling, Mr. Bender wound a braided rubber band inside his 20-inch-long Manhattan, designed with a fish-type body and a 20-inch wingspan. That didn't stop it from flying smack into the skywalk, then getting lodged in the crossbeams. He poked the airplane with a long pole and it resumed its glide.</p>
        <p>Though most paper-plane enthusiasts move on to gas-powered or electric-powered models, Mr. Bender said he was a purist, sticking with his own rubber-band designs and those taken from blueprints in model airplane magazines. He belongs to a rubber-band fliers club with about 15 members on Long Island.</p>
        <p>Using a jeweler's loupe for the precision work, Mr. Bender builds his aircraft from scratch in his basement. To test the planes, he glides them down the cellar stairs. Those that don't fly right away are added to his static model collection, including the world's first seaplane from 1910 and a Korean War MASH helicopter model made with a plastic pantyhose cover for a canopy.</p>
        <p>No matter how often he launches his fleet, the thrill never diminishes.  ''When I fly this I get goose pimples,'' he said, fiddling with a 1954 Navy Fan jet '' My hands tremble. They are so fragile. I feel very proud watching my planes. I know it makes people happy to watch. I just come here to fly and have my fun and go home.''</p>
        <p>Acting Out</p>
        <p>For the final act, Justin Flagg, 17, of Bellport, stuck his head in a bucket of water while Matt Gelfer, 17, of Brookhaven, and Natalie Thompson, 18, of East Patchogue, improvised a scene about smoking in a school bathroom.</p>
        <p>As Justin ran out of breath, he waved his hand furiously to get the other actors' attention. Water dripping down his face, he joined Ms. Thompson on the makeshift stage, switching the scenario to a leaky sink. And then it was Matt's turn to dunk his head in the pail.</p>
        <p>It was show time at the Red Barn, 83-year-old Betty Puleston's playhouse on a field by the community organic garden in Brookhaven Hamlet. Spectators stood in the open doorway and sat on a motley assortment of chairs watching the 10 young adult actors improvising on stage.</p>
        <p>Most of the cast had spent a decade of childhood summers under Deborah Mayo's tutelage in the Pumpkin Patch Players, her neighborhood theater troupe, performing classics like ''Antigone,'' and ''Oedipus Rex.'' Now they were taking their dramatic talents to another level.</p>
        <p>''I teach theater arts,'' said Ms. Mayo, 52, who enticed the students back on stage this summer as  ''Squash! The Improv Troupe.'' ''But it's not so much with a view to making them professional actors. I'm not doing theater training for careers. I do theater for living.''</p>
        <p>Using minimal props and maximum imagination, she said, the theater provides a safe, comfortable venue for youngsters to be creative, play, develop confidence and a sense of ensemble. And for returning college students, a place to hang out.</p>
        <p>''Nobody is a star in my company,'' Ms. Mayo said. ''Nobody is and everybody is. Working together, they support one another.''</p>
        <p>And keep a steadily growing audience chuckling. With neither prompting nor rehearsal, the troupe acts out a series of improvisational, party-style games. On a recent evening, Katie Becht, 19, of Patchogue narrated as the actors pretended to be an ice cream machine. In a mock version of  ''The Dating Game,'' Meghan Mullaney, 19, of Bellport quizzed Brian Dolber, 18, of Medford playing a manic/depressive; Sean Pilger, 20, portraying a dot-com billionaire; and Dan Sack, 19, impersonating a biker dude, about what they'd bring her on their first date. Mr. Sack chose a helmet. Mr. Pilger and Mr. Sack are  Brookhaven Hamlet residents.</p>
        <p>''You can only sit so long before you want to get up and try it,'' Ms. Mayo said. The troupe's last performance is on Wednesday at 8 p.m. at the Red Barn on Beaver Dam Road.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mayo, an actress in regional theater and drama teacher at SUNY-Stony Brook, had just moved to the hamlet 10 years ago when her new neighbor, Ms. Puleston, knocked on her door. Seeing her rehearse an African folk tale, Ms. Puleston made an offer.</p>
        <p>''I've got a place for you,'' Ms. Puleston said. Sitting in a pumpkin patch, her father's old barn was just perfect for Ms. Mayo's drama school, Acting Up. It had a potbelly stove, space for weaving and pottery classes and a makeshift stage where Ms. Puleston often gave puppet shows. Its walls were covered with oversize French posters. The closets were soon stuffed with costumes.</p>
        <p>''She's made this place what I've always wanted it to be,'' Ms. Puleston said. ''It belongs to the community. I just live here, I think it's something every community needs. If they are lucky and they get something like this, they're home free.''</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
