<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Life and Times Of a Pool in Scarsdale; Once the Scene of Parties, Now It Serves a Solitary Swimmer</title>
    <meta content="20POOL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223869"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Swimming Pools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Scarsdale (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Arnold</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Seena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E0DA163EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3486" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Life and Times Of a Pool in Scarsdale; Once the Scene of Parties, Now It Serves a Solitary Swimmer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON</byline>
      <dateline>SCARSDALE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article traces history of pool at home of Arnold and Seena Davis of Scarsdale, NY, which is now used only by Arnold, 76, for daily laps; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERY morning from May to September Arnold Davis, 76, steps out his back door onto the smooth concrete pool deck and, after testing the water, plunges in.</p>
        <p>He swims the 40-foot length of the pool in a slow, smooth Australian crawl, gripping the edge after each lap, pausing, and then pushing off to begin another.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERY morning from May to September Arnold Davis, 76, steps out his back door onto the smooth concrete pool deck and, after testing the water, plunges in.</p>
        <p>He swims the 40-foot length of the pool in a slow, smooth Australian crawl, gripping the edge after each lap, pausing, and then pushing off to begin another.</p>
        <p>There are few distractions -- he has the pool to himself these days -- and staring at the bleached white bottom, he focuses on his rhythmic breathing and counting his laps. Occasionally, though, his thoughts wander back to earlier days when the pool echoed with the voices of friends and family.</p>
        <p>When they first moved into their home here in 1959, Arnold and Seena Davis were excited about the pool. They described it to friends as Olympic size.</p>
        <p>This wasn't exactly true. The pool was only about half the length of a true Olympic-size pool. But it was so well suited for lap swimming, especially for a backyard pool, and, well, it sounded good.</p>
        <p>But if the Davises' description of the pool was a bit exaggerated, their expectations for it were perhaps more so. Sure, there were good times -- dinner parties on the deck, teaching the children to swim -- but the pool never really became the draw for family and friends that the Davises hoped it would.</p>
        <p>Back in the 50's, when the girls were still small, the Davises would leave the city and spend summers in Yorktown Heights in a house that shared a pool with six others.</p>
        <p>The owner built the houses for himself and his five children so they could all spend summers together around the pool, even as the children  grew up, got married and had their own families. As it happened, the close quarters wound up causing quarrels, but the idea of keeping the children around stuck with the Davises, especially when they began house hunting in Scarsdale a few years later.</p>
        <p>They first saw the tan Tudor in the summer of '59. It was on a quiet block near the Bronx River Parkway, close enough to the city for Mr. Davis to commute. It had a slate roof, charming leaded glass windows and a sloping front lawn.</p>
        <p>And best of all, it had a pool, a rectangular one with a nice deck that took up most of the backyard.</p>
        <p>Few people had homes with pools in those days, and the Davises' city friends advised against getting involved with a pool. Too much work, they said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Davis's family had a real estate business that Mr. Davis helped manage after working as a record producer and head librarian of the music libraries for the Juilliard School of Music. The company owned and maintained apartment buildings in the city, and everyone in the family lived in apartments and wondered why anyone would want to take care of a whole house, much less a pool.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Davis's mother saw it, she said, ''The first thing you do is fill in the pool and plant a nice rose garden.'' Even the girls -- Wendy was 11 then and Gail was 13 -- weren't all that crazy about the pool.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Davis was an avid swimmer and loved the idea. Now they wouldn't need Yorktown Heights. And a pool would keep the family together. Plus, an elderly man lived in the house behind it. The Davises recalled the family in Yorktown Heights and figured that when the neighbor died, they could grab the house.</p>
        <p>''We thought that, as we grew older,'' Mr. Davis said, ''it would be a good idea to have a house for the girls to come back to on the weekend when they had their own families, sort of a family compound.''</p>
        <p>So that fall, they moved in and opened the pool the next spring.</p>
        <p>At first there were many parties, ''swinging affairs,'' Mrs. Davis called them, with friends and family from the city. They would turn on the underwater lights and float candles on the smooth iridescent water. Sometimes, guitarists were hired to stroll the deck as guests sipped cocktails and admired the shimmering blue centerpiece.</p>
        <p>The oak bar on wheels was rolled out from the sun room to the deck. And out came the food, catered and on a spiffy stainless steel hospital cart, which Mr. Davis had converted by attaching a clear plastic cover.</p>
        <p>The parties began at 4 p.m., Mrs. Davis said, ''because that's when drinking time started,'' and would last until late. Most guests came dressed up and rarely swam, since the unheated pool got chilly in the evening.</p>
        <p>But sometimes the parties really got going and people did swim -- voluntarily or not. People were thrown in, sometimes deck chair and all. Some parties were so lively so late that it took a knock on the door from the police to wind them down.</p>
        <p>Then there were Mrs. Davis's ''ladies' days.'' Once a week, she'd invite a few women, different combinations of acquaintances new and old, for lunch around the pool. She would serve soft drinks and put out salads, finger food and bowls of nuts.</p>
        <p>But it wasn't all deck parties and backyard barbecues. The pool saw a lot of swimming by children and then the grandchildren. It's an unofficial measure, but Mrs. Davis likes to say: ''I must have gone through hundreds of towels a summer.''</p>
        <p>She had strict rules for the pool deck. Plastic cups only. No running. No dunking or rough stuff, and no wearing suntan oil into the pool. Girls had to wear bathing caps. Long hair clogs drains, she said.</p>
        <p>There was a diving board early on, a long wooden one. But Mrs. Davis had it removed because the pool was only about five or six feet deep throughout.</p>
        <p>The maintenance kept the family busy. Mr. Davis cleaned the pool and tended the filter and added chemicals daily. Each May, everyone, including the girls and their friends, would put on Mr. Davis's old shirts and paint the pool walls and bottom.</p>
        <p>But these days, the backyard is quiet. There are no more shouts and splashes and cannonballs. Now the only thing disturbing the calm blue shimmer is Mr. Davis's morning swim.</p>
        <p>''All of our wild friends are gone,'' said Mrs. Davis. ''No one really swims here anymore.''</p>
        <p>The Davises are both in their 70's, though you'd hardly think so to look at them. Most of their friends have either died or moved away.</p>
        <p>Their daughters and grandchildren don't come around much either. Someone else bought the old neighbor's house, so that didn't work out. Anyway, the girls wanted to get away from Scarsdale after high school.</p>
        <p>Only in recent years has Wendy, 51, moved back, and now her two teenagers would rather swim with their friends at the town pool. Mr. and Mrs. Davis rarely speak to their older daughter, Gail, 53, a lawyer who lives in Manhattan, and her 28-year-old daughter is an actress and always traveling.</p>
        <p>''When we bought the house, we thought we'd always have a lot of guests,'' Mrs. Davis said. ''We thought it would keep the family together and the kids coming back, but it didn't.''</p>
        <p>On the pool deck, there are two chaise longues set up. The rest of the patio furniture remains stacked off to the side. The only young girl on the deck now is a stone statue of a young maiden lifting her skirts to dip her toes in the 76-degree water.</p>
        <p>The thick wall of green around the pool is mostly evergreens. They keep the yard secluded all year round and do not drop leaves into the pool.</p>
        <p>At one end of the pool, there's an elegant stone bench flanked by tall iron stanchions holding geraniums and Swedish ivy. A 25-year- old rose bush grows along the house, and wild blueberry and mulberry bushes grow along the rear fence where the ivy advances toward the pool so quickly that it has to be cut back every week.</p>
        <p>The wooden shed in the corner of the yard was the pool equipment room. There are still bags of rubber balls, straw hats and old floats in the musty shed. The floats, once bright with zany animal faces, are now dusty, faded and crumpled.</p>
        <p>''Bits and pieces,'' said Mrs. Davis, looking over it all. ''That's all that's left. The kids used to fight over them. We didn't even take them out last year.''</p>
        <p>Years ago, she set up a dressing room in the basement. It has hardly been touched in decades and is more like a time capsule.</p>
        <p>There are rope mats on the floor, an ashtray on the white dressing table. There are two white pith helmets and old green canvas hammocks, like something out of an old Rye Playland photograph. On a wire rack, there is a stack of about 10 neatly folded towels. Every spring, Mrs. Davis laundered loads of towels to prepare for summer, she said. Also there is the wooden dresser, still full of odd bathing suits kept around for the guests who forgot theirs.</p>
        <p>Everything is still there, except for the excited shouts of children in dripping bathing suits.</p>
        <p>In their later years, the Davises have taken up other hobbies, quite remarkable ones, actually. They collect art, and their walls are covered with paintings from 17th- century Europe and earlier. There is a 10-foot-tall portrait of Louis XIV in the living room, for example.</p>
        <p>The Davises look for bargains at auctions, antique shows, flea markets and church sales. They love stumbling onto a painting, buying it for a song and then learning through research and consultations with art experts that it has a distinguished pedigree.</p>
        <p>Their rooms are furnished with period furniture, including many Second Empire couches and armchairs.</p>
        <p>Also, Mr. Davis is an English lord, of a small area near Norwich called Barnham Broom, and Mrs. Davis is the lady. They bought the titles some years back after traveling often to England on vacation and to search for art.</p>
        <p>They are members of the Manorial Society of Britain and attend its annual September banquet in Oxford. The title gets them a coat of arms, a fancy scroll and a complimentary bottle of champagne on British Airways flights. But aside from the occasional greetings of ''M'lord'' around the countryside, it's mainly a bit of fun and an impressive bit of conversation.</p>
        <p>The pool was built of poured concrete several years before the Davises moved in by the Wagner Pool Company, still a pool builder in Westchester.</p>
        <p>In 1971, the Davises considered installing a heater but decided not to spend the $2,200.</p>
        <p>In time, concrete pools crack, and Mr. Davis first had the pool renovated in 1980. It was renovated again in 1995 by Shoreline Pools. They reinforced the pool with steel, sprayed the walls with Gunite, replaced the filter system and changed the steel pipes to plastic. It cost $47,500, more than the Davises paid for the entire house in 1959.</p>
        <p>The Davises have spent more than $100,000 maintaining and renovating the pool over the years. But it is more than just a deck and 36,000 gallons of water. Over the 45 years since it was built, it has seen generations of a family grow up in and around it.</p>
        <p>Each of its three incarnations seems to correspond to a different era in the family: First the children, then the grandchildren. And now it is something of a reflecting pool, a collective memory of the life of a Westchester family.</p>
        <p>That is, of course, except for Mr. Davis's morning swims. He does 85 laps every morning, starting around 10 a.m., when the sun clears the row of trees bordering the backyard fence.</p>
        <p>He breathes to his right and has a steady even stroke. It takes him about 45 minutes, and you can always tell when he's been in. Water has splashed over the deck leaving a ring of darkened pavement around the pool.</p>
        <p>He has lost 35 pounds in the past year and looks more like the Arnold Jack Davis of old. Years ago, the neighbors called him Johnny Weismuller. And he's still tan and solidly built, with broad shoulders, a barrel chest and a hard stomach that he challenges his wife to punch.</p>
        <p>In the city, he taught children to swim at the Lenox Hill Neighborhood House on the Upper East Side. ''I still have friends who say, 'He taught me to swim,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>There is something about a private pool, he said, and he prefers it to the larger pools at their co-ops in Palm Beach and St. Croix. He calls the water in his pool drinkable.</p>
        <p>''You get a good, clean feeling in it compared to public pools,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He can almost tell the days of the week by the pool bottom. More leaves and debris accumulate on it until Tuesday, when it is vacuumed by Paul Moloney, the service man for the last eight years.</p>
        <p>Before that, Mr. Davis used to sweep the deck and skim the pool each day himself. He would walk around the perimeter in the evening, adding chlorine and algicide, following the former owner's typewritten instructions.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Moloney tends the pool. He puts in time-release chlorine tablets, which dissolve gradually during the week. There are fewer insects to skim, because the trees are sprayed. The deck is cleaned by gardeners.</p>
        <p>So instead of tending the pool, Mr. Davis talks art with Mr. Moloney once a week. Mr. Moloney is a pool man now, but he was a fine arts major in college and likes Mr. Davis. He invited him to his bachelor party five years ago.</p>
        <p>The pool is the oldest Mr. Moloney tends. Its filter is in an underground room under the deck called the filter pit.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Davis calls the pool a liability. She likes it as background while she reads in the backyard or in the airy sun room or the porch, which both overlook the pool.</p>
        <p>The doctor has told her she can't sit much in the sun, and she would just as well ''fill it in and make a planter out of it.''</p>
        <p>They had the kitchen window enlarged so Mrs. Davis could keep an eye on her husband swimming his laps. The foam life ring and the sheperd's crook nearby are not just for show, she said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Davis studied art and tried to interest her daughters and then her grandchildren, playing treasure hunts with paintings, like ''How many Cupids can you find in this picture?'' She tends to blame herself for the girls not staying closer.</p>
        <p>''When you have two children, one is always neglected,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Davises try to take the grandchildren on a vacation every winter, introducing them to museums like the Prado in Madrid. But as teenagers, their interest is waning. They would rather stay home with their friends.</p>
        <p>They used to love being picked up by Mr. Davis in his green 1959 Bentley, begging him to circle their school again so their friends could see them in the car.</p>
        <p>The Davises' younger daughter, Wendy Schwam, remembers swimming with college friends and playing all kinds of sports, like water polo and pool basketball.</p>
        <p>She said that when her parents discussed buying the old man's house, they suggested putting a gate in between the two houses and building a tennis court.</p>
        <p>''Then I thought, 'They'll hear me yelling at my kids,' '' she recalled. ''It was a little too close for comfort. I wanted to be close, but not that close.</p>
        <p>''As far as having parties there,'' she added, ''I keep saying I'm going to, but I never get around to it.''</p>
        <p>Once in high school, she came home one afternoon to find two young boys, strangers, playing in the pool. The gate was still locked, so she went in and asked the maid, ''Are they your kids?'' The maid answered, ''What kids?''</p>
        <p>She went out back, and one boy hopped the fence and escaped. Wendy grabbed the other and held him till her parents got home.</p>
        <p>Now, the Davises have mixed feelings about the pool. Mrs. Davis said she would rather bulldoze it and start a garden. In fact, she would just as soon move back to the city.</p>
        <p>But there are times she could easily draft the old wooden bar right into action again. The silver martini shaker still stands on it, next to a lineup of liqueur bottles.</p>
        <p>''All you need is ice, and we could have a party tomorrow,'' she said with a laugh.</p>
        <p>A Booming Business In What's Cool and Pricey</p>
        <p>WITH the economy as brisk as it has been, demand for backyard swimming pools is at an all-time high.</p>
        <p>Pool builders say that things have never been busier, from construction of the most inexpensive pools with vinyl liners, which start at $12,000, to high-end pools that carry price tags of $300,000 and up.</p>
        <p>''Business is booming in all phases of the industry, from service to construction to renovation,'' said Chris Lightenberg, a board member of the metropolitan chapter of the National Spa and Pool Institute. ''We haven't seen this kind of boom since the mid-  to late-80's.</p>
        <p>''Especially in Westchester, there is tremendous growth in the building of very high-end pools,'' he added. ''It goes with the whole cocooning aspect of society. People are insulating themselves in their own backyards and want all the luxuries.''</p>
        <p>Builders have so many requests for jobs that homeowners often have to arrange pool plans in the fall to have them finished by the next summer. ''People don't just want pools anymore, the classic rectangular ones,'' he said. ''Now they want waterfalls and natural looking ponds with boulders. They're requesting new exotic decking materials.''</p>
        <p>One downside of the pool boom, Mr. Lightenberg said, is the shortage of labor. ''A lot of guys used to hire high school and college kids, but now young people think they can make more money in other jobs.''</p>
        <p>Donald J. Bashak, president of Estate Pools, a Connecticut-based company that does most of its work in Westchester, called it a record year for building pools.</p>
        <p>''I'm booked through next Fourth of July,'' said Mr. Bashak, 44, a former stockbroker who got into the business in 1989. ''Some companies are pounding out 70 pools a year.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bashak's company does not keep that pace. They call their creations ''swimming pool environments,'' which are compounds where the pool is only one feature of a veritable water park.</p>
        <p>One such complex, built in 1998 in Westport, cost $850,000. Typical features include hot tubs, heated caves with large TV's, wood-burning fireplaces, electric bonfires and extravagant barbecues with special lobster-roasting sections.</p>
        <p>The most luxurious pools are being built in Scarsdale, Bronxville, Ossining and Salem, said Mr. Bashak, who is currently planning a three-tiered pool for a home in Scarsdale.</p>
        <p>Steve Mundree, whose company, H2 0 Pools in Irvington, has serviced pools in central Westchester for 20 years, said that the builders he knows have more clients than they can handle. Some are charging customers as much as $25,000 more than their ordinary price for a pool, he said, ''and they're getting it.''</p>
        <p>''The high-end has gotten higher than ever,'' he said. ''People are spending ridiculous money.''</p>
        <p>He continued: ''People used to keep their pools running with spit and glue. Now even cement doesn't cut it anymore. People are choosing blue stone and granite. Anything to make it look more tropical. They go to Hawaii on vacation and come back saying, 'I saw this, can you build it?' Hey, If they're willing to pay for it, we'll get it done.''</p>
        <p>COREY KILGANNON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
