<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Spacious, Leafy New Setting For Ambitious Shakespeareans</title>
    <meta content="20FANG$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theaters (Buildings)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lenox (Mass)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Shakespeare &amp; Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Packer, Tina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fanger, Iris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE6D61E3FF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Spacious, Leafy New Setting For Ambitious Shakespeareans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRIS FANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fanger, Iris</byline>
      <dateline>LENOX, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iris Fanger interviews Tina Packer, artistic director of Shakespeare &amp; Company, on company's new home in Lenox, Mass, and plans to build replica of London's Rose Theater; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN ''Henry V,'' Shakespeare asked the groundlings standing in the Globe's pit and the patrons crammed onto the hard benches to use their imaginations and ''Suppose within the girdle of these walls/ Are now confin'd two mighty monarchies.''</p>
        <p>Tina Packer, the ebullient artistic director of the performing troupe Shakespeare &amp; Company, is making an equally audacious request of her audiences here in Western Massachusetts: to envision an exact replica of an Elizabethan playhouse nestled among the rolling Berkshire hills at the company's new home. But where Shakespeare relied on his verse to conjure up the illusion, Ms. Packer has a real building in mind.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN ''Henry V,'' Shakespeare asked the groundlings standing in the Globe's pit and the patrons crammed onto the hard benches to use their imaginations and ''Suppose within the girdle of these walls/ Are now confin'd two mighty monarchies.''</p>
        <p>Tina Packer, the ebullient artistic director of the performing troupe Shakespeare &amp; Company, is making an equally audacious request of her audiences here in Western Massachusetts: to envision an exact replica of an Elizabethan playhouse nestled among the rolling Berkshire hills at the company's new home. But where Shakespeare relied on his verse to conjure up the illusion, Ms. Packer has a real building in mind.</p>
        <p>Soon, and perhaps none too soon -- after its wrangles over use of the Mount, the nearby Edith Wharton estate -- Shakespeare &amp; Company will be ensconced on 63 acres in Lenox, near Tanglewood. The troupe, which has presented a large repertory of Shakespeare plays in the summer and fall at the Wharton estate since 1978 and which also runs an extensive school education program, bought the new property in April for $4.1 million.</p>
        <p>There are 22 buildings on the site in various conditions of repair, including an estate house, Springlawn, built in 1904, the same era as Edith Wharton's home a mile away. A boys' school and a religious organization were among the owners of the property at 70 Kemble Street, which was ultimately sold by the National Music Foundation, a nonprofit organization for the promotion of American music. The foundation's own plans for a performing arts complex, which it had shelved before the sale, did not include a copy of a 16th-century English theater.</p>
        <p>But given Ms. Packer's drive and the plans already in motion, a replica of the Rose Theater, which once stood in London in Shakespeare's time, is likely to be the core of what Ms. Packer hopes will be a major center for Shakespearean performance, teaching and scholarship in this country.</p>
        <p>In a recent conversation at the new property, the director said she had always wanted an Elizabethan theater. ''If you make Shakespeare the backbone of what you do, it's a good idea to have the physical space and condition that the scripts were written for,'' she said. ''What we love about the Elizabethan playhouse is the actor-audience relationship. The first half I wanted was the aesthetic. The other half was that this would put us on the map. It's a contribution to scholarship and a real contribution to tourism.''</p>
        <p>If a casting director were to choose a Shakespearean role for Ms. Packer, who is 61, it might be that of the vigorous Mistress Quickly in ''Henry IV, Parts 1 and 2'' or the nurturing, resourceful Nurse in ''Romeo and Juliet.'' Short and sturdy, with strands of gray in her red hair, Ms. Packer has a wide smile, a laugh that breaks out often and an English accent that is hard to miss.</p>
        <p>Typically, she seems undaunted by the task facing her nonprofit organization, with its budget of $2.8 million this year and its staff of 100 artists, teachers and directors. The company has estimated that the cost of the move to the new property over the next five years, along with the purchase price, will come to nearly $17 million, not including the expense of the Rose. Construction of that building could run anywhere from $10 million to $30 million, according to Michael A. Miller, the chairman of the company's board of trustees. ''We don't really know,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Challenges are nothing new for Ms. Packer, whose energy and determination tend to attract followers. Several of the company's founders are still with her in the troupe's 23rd season, including Dennis Krausnick, the director of training (and her husband); Kevin G. Coleman, the director of education; John Hadden, a director, and Mitchell Berenson, a trustee.</p>
        <p>Born near Birmingham, in northern England, Ms. Packer studied acting at the Royal Academy of Dramatic Art in London, then joined the Royal Shakespeare Company and performed often on BBC-TV. By the time she was in her mid-30's, she had determined to start a Shakespeare theater of her own, where she could train English and American actors to understand and express the feelings behind Shakespeare's language.The idea would combine the British approach to the spoken word with the American freedom of physical action, enlivened by Ms. Packer's probing of the language for emotional truth. She based her studies in part on the acting techniques developed by the well-known voice teacher Kristin Linklater, who would later become one of the founders of Shakespeare &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>After several visits to the United States in the 1970's and the failure of her first attempt to start a theater in England, Ms. Packer came upon the boarded-up Wharton estate while on an exploratory trip through the Berkshires in 1978. With her co-founders, she raised the money to buy it and created two separate entities: the performing troupe Shakespeare &amp; Company and, eventually, Edith Wharton Restoration Inc., which was set up to restore and maintain the historic house. The chronicle of those early years is told in ''The Companies She Keeps'' (1985), a book by Helen Epstein.</p>
        <p>Two decades of critical praise and increasing audiences followed as Ms. Packer directed Shakespeare's plays on the outdoor mainstage behind the Wharton house, developed an indoor stage at the former stables and presented adaptations of Wharton's works in the Salon Theater -- the author's parlor -- with tea and cookies served during intermission. In the Shakespeare productions especially, readily accessible language continued to be the goal.</p>
        <p>In a 1994 review of Shakespeare's ''Comedy of Errors'' by the company at the estate, Ben Brantley wrote in The New York Times that ''the spoken lines get more laughs than the sight gags.'' Mr. Brantley went on to say that ''the director, John Hadden, has also provided the verbal and aural equivalents of funny costumes and pratfalls: silly accents, divertingly varied rhythms of speech and vocally highlighted phrases that force us to listen.'' The result, Mr. Brantley wrote, was that ''you can understand every word'' because language ''is the unyielding cornerstone for theatrical interpretation here.''</p>
        <p>During its years at the Mount, the company also developed year-round education and training programs about Shakespeare in public and private schools mainly in New England. These involve touring to schools, colleges and community centers; residencies at schools; and training workshops for teachers and professional actors. The faculty is drawn from the troupe's artists and teachers.</p>
        <p>Yet despite the success of its productions and programs, the company -- and Ms. Packer -- became embroiled in a dispute over control of the Wharton estate with the group that had been set up to restore it. The bitter struggle mirrored the rivalries depicted in many of Shakespeare's plays. After repeated clashes about the use of the Mount, it had become obvious by 1998 that Shakespeare &amp; Company would have to find a new home. ''I never would have left the Mount if I hadn't been pushed,'' Ms. Packer said.</p>
        <p>''I had always known,'' she continued, ''even if we had stayed at the Mount, that we would have had to buy 50 acres next door to connect our training and education programs and relate them to the performances. But the fact that we now have this beautiful new property means we can put all our energy into it -- and we have a lot of energy. I think it's a great lesson. Out of adversity come all sorts of good things.''</p>
        <p>The Kemble Street campus is a mixture of verdant meadow and lush woodland, recalling Shakespeare's settings for ''As You Like It.'' The company began the move to the property in April, shifting its administrative offices to a 1950's library building and its rehearsals to Springlawn, and housing actors and students in dormitories for the summer residential training programs.</p>
        <p>With the construction of two theaters -- the Salon Theater in Springlawn and the larger Founders' Theater in a former gym -- the company will have year-round producing capabilities for the first time. Currently, the Lenox performances at the Mount are presented from May to October.</p>
        <p>Among the productions now running in repertory at the Wharton estate are ''Romeo and Juliet'' on the outdoor mainstage and ''Coriolanus,'' directed by Ms. Packer, alternating with ''Jack and Jill,'' a contemporary play by Jane Martin.</p>
        <p>The move to the new property has been supported in tangible ways by private individuals as well as by the Commonwealth of Massachusetts, which has recently distributed additional money to support the arts in the western part of the state through a variety of agencies. A tax-exempt revenue bond was issued by Mass Development, a state-chartered finance agency, which allowed Shakespeare &amp; Company to secure a low-interest mortgage; the state Department of Environmental Management gave $500,000 to the company in exchange for a preservation restriction on Springlawn and 15 surrounding acres; and $4.4 million has been received from private donations, out of the $5.5 million needed. ''We'll have the rest in hand by the end of the summer,'' Mr. Miller predicted.</p>
        <p>Ms. Packer has also found an ally in the British theater consultant Iain Mackintosh, who will design the Founders' Theater (with the American architect George E. Marsh Jr.) and plan the Rose.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mackintosh, whose optimism seems to match Ms. Packer's, designed the Cottesloe space at the Royal National Theater in London and the Glyndebourne Opera House, also helping save the remains of the Rose when they were discovered in 1989 during excavations for a London office building.</p>
        <p>The Founders' Theater will be modeled after Mr. Mackintosh's design for the Tricycle Theater in Kilburn in northwest London, described by Ms. Packer as ''a tough theater, made out of scaffolds and canvas, a courtyard theater that can be used in two or three ways.'' In addition, an open-air theater behind Springlawn is planned to replace the outdoor mainstage space at the Mount.</p>
        <p>''When Tina said, 'I want to build the Globe,' '' Mr. Mackintosh recalled, ''I said, 'No, you want to build the Rose. We already have a Globe.' '' He was referring to the American actor Sam Wanamaker's replica of the Elizabethan Globe theater that opened in London in 1997 and that is larger than the Rose.</p>
        <p>''It's better to build the Rose because we know more about it,'' Mr. Mackintosh said. ''Finding the foundations gave us the footprint of the building, its size, dimensions and the way it was sited. The Lenox Rose will hold 800 people, a good size for Shakespeare &amp; Company. But also good for the actors.''</p>
        <p>The original Rose was built by Philip Henslowe in 1587 and flourished as the home of the first productions of plays by Christopher Marlowe, Thomas Kyd and Shakespeare, whose ''Henry VI, Part 1'' and ''Titus Andronicus'' were staged there.</p>
        <p>This week, Mr. Mackintosh will lead a team of British theater scholars and builders to Lenox for a five-day seminar to advise Shakespeare &amp; Company about the Rose. Among the participants will be Julian Bowsher, the archeologist who headed the team that excavated the Rose; Patrick Spottiswoode, director of the Globe education programs; Peter McCurdy, master carpenter for the Globe, and Andrew Gurr, a scholar who advised Wanamaker on the Globe's design.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Epstein, one of Shakespeare &amp; Company's veteran actors, sees some changes ahead. ''Right now,'' he said, ''we have two ways of acting: working on one of the largest stages in the world, outdoors at the Mount, where we need a kind of ballistic style, and working on one of the smallest, in the Salon, where you need a style where delicacy is significant. These things won't be the same in the new theaters.''</p>
        <p>Within a decade, Ms. Packer envisions the Rose and the other theaters operating at Kemble Street, along with a performance space in the woods for dance, a media center containing a sound stage for film, a library for scholarly conferences, and year-round residential education and training programs on the site.</p>
        <p>''The scope of the place feeds my imagination,'' the director said with a broad grin. ''We'll have enough room to do all our programming. You know, we're a very ambitious theater company.''</p>
        <p>Training in the Art of Word and Deed</p>
        <p>NOT surprisingly, Shakespeare's works form the basis of Shakespeare &amp; Company's education programs. ''While his poems can be read and reflected upon, his plays are meant to be performed,'' said the company's artistic director, Tina Packer. The training draws from text analysis, voice, movement, staged fights, clowning, the Alexander Technique and the relationship between the actor and the audience. Voice work is based on theories and exercises developed by the master teacher Kristin Linklater.</p>
        <p>''During the spring, a company of six actors performs in about 100 schools,'' said Kevin G. Coleman, the head of the troupe's arts in education program, which reaches more than 40,000 students and teachers each year. ''This year, the play was 'Hamlet,' '' Mr. Coleman said.</p>
        <p>After a general introduction to Shakespeare, the students watch a performance and then participate in a class in which they perform brief excerpts from one of the plays. Every fall, 10 teams, consisting of two directors, technical crews and costumers, work with from 30 to 100 students for eight weeks in each of 10 high schools, then bring them together to present their plays.</p>
        <p>Two summer education programs take place in Lenox: ''Riotous Youth,'' for children 8 to 15, and ''Shakespeare &amp; Young Company'' for older teen-agers. There are also two actor training workshops for adults in the summer.</p>
        <p>Separate monthlong workshops for actors are held in January and June, as well as a series of weekend intensives. Among the workshop graduates are Karen Allen, Anna Deavere Smith, Keanu Reeves, Alicia Silverstone, Sigourney Weaver and Raquel Welch.</p>
        <p>''The possibilities for the new property are fabulous,'' Mr. Coleman said. ''We'll be able to offer summer housing to students from across the country. Now we just accept local kids. It will also let us provide housing for teacher workshops and bring in scholars to talk with the teachers.''</p>
        <p>Speaking of the potential influence he believes the expanded program might have, Mr. Coleman said, ''It could change the teaching of Shakespeare in this country.''</p>
        <p>IRIS FANGER</p>
        <p>THEATER Iris Fanger, who directed the Harvard Summer Dance Center from 1977 to 1995, writes frequently about theater and dance for The Christian Science Monitor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Iris Fanger, who directed the Harvard Summer Dance Center from 1977 to 1995, writes frequently about theater and dance for The Christian Science Monitor.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
