<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Carriacou, Parrotfish And Pastel Cottages</title>
    <meta content="20FRUG$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223772"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FRUGAL TRAVELER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">St Vincent and the Grenadines</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mclane, Daisann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Frugal Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/St. Vincent and the Grenadines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/St. Vincent and the Grenadines/St. Vincent</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0D6103FF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2968" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Carriacou, Parrotfish And Pastel Cottages</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAISANN McLANE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mclane, Daisann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daisann McLane Frugal Traveler column describes laid-back stay at Bayaleau Point Cottages on Grenadine island of Carriacou; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE market was the talk of downtown Hillsborough, Carriacou. The old building, with its rusty corrugated-iron roof sheltering a handful of hard-bargaining fruit and vegetable hawkers, had stood at the foot of the town dock for as long as anyone could remember. Now the city council wanted to tear it down and relocate the market about 100 yards down the street.</p>
        <p>''What foolishness!'' exclaimed one of regulars at Bill Patterson's place, when I broached the controversial topic over an orange juice one morning. Patterson's is a general store cum bar-lunch counter across the street from the proposed new market site. The other day, said the fellow, they'd watched from the bar as a protest march passed outside. ''Such a commotion!'' he exclaimed. Nearly 10 people had come.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE market was the talk of downtown Hillsborough, Carriacou. The old building, with its rusty corrugated-iron roof sheltering a handful of hard-bargaining fruit and vegetable hawkers, had stood at the foot of the town dock for as long as anyone could remember. Now the city council wanted to tear it down and relocate the market about 100 yards down the street.</p>
        <p>''What foolishness!'' exclaimed one of regulars at Bill Patterson's place, when I broached the controversial topic over an orange juice one morning. Patterson's is a general store cum bar-lunch counter across the street from the proposed new market site. The other day, said the fellow, they'd watched from the bar as a protest march passed outside. ''Such a commotion!'' he exclaimed. Nearly 10 people had come.</p>
        <p>Ah, life on a small island. I sank into my chair on Patterson's back porch, which sticks out into the sleepy Hillsborough harbor, sipped my juice and waited, along with the town's 600 residents, for the day's other big event, the arrival of the morning ferry from St. George's, Grenada.</p>
        <p>When I long for the Caribbean, my thoughts don't turn to snazzy resorts but to local gossip, goats, chickens, marketplaces,  empty beaches and pots of home-cooked fish stew, fragrant with pepper. Thirty years ago just about any place in the Caribbean would have fit that bill. But nowadays, to get to the slow-motion islands you need to plan, especially if you don't have endless time, bottomless resources or a close personal friendship with Jimmy Buffett.</p>
        <p>The Grenadine islands, which stretch in a loose 75-mile north-south arc in the aqua marine seas between St. Vincent and Grenada, are one of the last Caribbean outposts of Small and Slow. Beloved by the yachting set, the Grenadines are a challenging destination for a budget traveler. Some of the most beautiful islands in the chain, like Petit St. Vincent and Palm Island, consist of privately held resorts with stratospheric prices. Transportation to and from and between the islands can be sporadic, slow and unreliable, unless you've got your own boat or can charter a plane.</p>
        <p>I looked at the map and came up with a plan that I thought might land me in an affordable space in the millionaire's parking lot. I'd head for tiny Carriacou, a seven-mile speck at the southern end of the Grenadines, just 23 miles north of Grenada. Carriacou and nearby Petit Martinique are geographically part of the Grenadines but politically and economically incorporated with Grenada (unlike the others, which are administered by St. Vincent). An industrious sailing family on Petit Martinique launched a fast, cheap catamaran ferry service between the three islands in 1998. The Osprey Lines ferry to Carriacou leaves from the main dock at St. George's daily, costs $15 and takes only 90 minutes.</p>
        <p>I hopped on the sleek, modern boat one cloudy morning in July. The ride was rougher than I'd counted on. A crewman roamed the aisle handing out seasickness bags, and many of my fellow passengers took advantage of the offer. But after about an hour, the worst seemed to be over. The sky cleared and turned intensely blue, and I could see the low, white-sand-fringed shore of Carriacou in the distance.</p>
        <p>Carriacou has no big hotels, only a couple of small guest houses, a few properties comprising little cottages on the beach and an agency that rents out houses. Since it was off season, I was pretty sure I'd have no trouble getting a place to stay on the island at the last minute, and I didn't. From Grenada I called the Bayaleau Point Cottages, and Ulla Goldhill, the friendly owner, said, sure, she had a small cottage I could rent for $55 a night.</p>
        <p>Over the telephone, Ulla, who is Danish and runs Bayaleau with her American husband, Dave, gave me some excellent advice.</p>
        <p>First off, she told me where I could get a nice lunch in Hillsborough when I got off the boat (Bill Patterson's, where a hot plate of chicken, vegetables and rice is $5.50). She also explained that my cottage had a kitchen, and that I might want to stock up on groceries in Hillsborough, where the markets were better supplied than in Windward, the closest village.</p>
        <p>Lunch at Patterson's cleared my head after the wobbly boat ride. I store-hopped from one end of Hillsborough to the other; the town's main drag hugs the waterfront, and it takes about five minutes to walk from end to end. On the way I picked up some basic supplies (milk, tomatoes, cereal, fruit, pasta, oil, bottled water). As long as I had a kitchen I wanted to use it. A taxi driver in a red minivan spotted me, introduced himself as Thomas and offered to drive me to Bayaleau for $10.</p>
        <p>The cottages are only about four miles from town, but the way is slow, along narrow, concrete-paved roads that twist carefully through little villages. As poky as Hillsborough seemed, it is a metropolis compared with the rest of the island. We drove for about 20 minutes, stopping for cows and goats and the occasional yappy dog. I was surprised at how many Carriacouans had rejected the bland concrete-box Caribbean house template in favor of pretty pastel A-frame wooden houses with gingerbread trim. Finally, Thomas turned left down a narrow lane that ended in a white picket gate -- Bayaleau Point Cottages.</p>
        <p>My cottage, the Little Yellow Cottage, was open and ready for me. I unloaded my bags on the porch, stepped inside to inspect, and broke into a smile because in the riot of pastel green beams and walls I could sense the hand of an inspired, whimsical carpenter. The place had something that is a rare commodity in Caribbean budget lodging: style. An adult's tropical take on a summer camp in the Adirondacks, circa 1945, the cottage had a peaked roof, wood-slatted windows (no screens) on all sides, and eaves open to the breeze. A built-in queen-sized platform bed dominated the space, but there was room along one wall for a full kitchen with stove and fridge and a breakfast bar with stools. Toward the back, two swinging wooden saloon-style doors opened, one to a cold-water shower  and the other to a toilet.</p>
        <p>At night, in total darkness and serenaded by a cacophony of frogs and birds and loud green crickets, I felt even more as if I were in a camp, albeit a luxury one. Because the cottage was open (there was a fan, no air-conditioning), I definitely needed the mosquito net -- summer is when mosquitoes take over in the Caribbean. The only drawback to the cottage, I found, was having to slather repellent on my legs and feet before stepping out from under the net in the morning. But the same open slats that let in mosquitoes also admitted the breeze -- and the little bananaquit birds that occasionally fluttered in by accident, then zoomed out in a feathery, black and yellow blur.</p>
        <p>On my first evening I had dinner with my hosts (this was available by arrangement for about $12 a person).  There were two other guests, a Grenadian journalist and his Irish wife, and the five of us ate on a communal deck with a view of the sea below (Bayaleau has a little gray-sand beach, with nice swimming). Over rum punches I learned that Dave was a transplanted New Yorker who had moved to the islands 23 years ago. He met Ulla, they married and remained on Carriacou to build their house and the cottages and raise children (they have three), in a happier real-life version of ''The Mosquito Coast.''</p>
        <p>I also learned that Dave had recently built a fiberglass boat, and took guests on excursions up the Grenadines. In fact, he was taking a group to the Tobago Cays the next day -- did I want to come?</p>
        <p>I could hardly believe my luck. The Tobago Cays, a tiny collection of uninhabited islets, is a nature preserve that has some of the best snorkeling in the Caribbean. But to get there you must go in your own boat, so I didn't think I would make it. Now, for $60 (Dave's daylong excursion included a big lunch, beer and drinks), I would.</p>
        <p>For the next two days -- I ended up taking two excursions with the Goldhills, one full day and one half-day -- I nearly forgot about Carriacou. ''Out here is my backyard,'' laughed Dave, as we zoomed in his 28-foot boat, the Mostly Harmless, over delicious warm seas, surrounded by the hilly silhouettes of nearby islands: Union Island off to the west, Petit Martinique to the east, and flat, sandy Petit St. Vincent dead ahead.</p>
        <p>While the distances between the little Grenadines had seemed long on my map, in the motorboat we hopped from one to another easily, with an hour between stops, sometimes less. On the first excursion (which included me and a group of eight Swedes) I swam in the horseshoe reef of the Tobago Cays with a school of iridescent parrotfish. Then, while the Swedes sat and drank rum punch on the crescent-shaped bay of Mayreau, I climbed a muddy path to the top of that island's highest hill.</p>
        <p>The next day, along with a couple from Cambridge, England, we stopped for lunch (stewed fish, rice and salad) at a little family beachfront restaurant on Petit Martinique called the Palm Beach. Afterward, I strolled along the beach to take a look at the large wooden boats being built by Petit Martinican craftsmen along the shore. Boats built on this island have been famous for their design and seaworthiness since the 1700's.</p>
        <p>Petit St. Vincent, the island  that contains but one luxury resort (rooms cost more than $800 a night in high season for two with meals), is a five-minute ride across the bay from the Palm Beach restaurant. While the island's lodging is exclusive, many small dinghies and yachts anchor off the beach for swimming and picnicking. And so I enjoyed the unexpected pleasure of spreading my towel on pricey sands.</p>
        <p>ON the third day, Dave was heading out on yet another island trip, but I passed. Part of the reason was that, in spite of regular applications of SPF 48, I was looking at my back in the mirror and seeing red. But the other reason was that I felt a stranger to the very island I was sleeping on. So I made two decisions the next morning. One was to stay for a whole week at Bayaleau (if I did, the rate dropped  to $35 a night). The other was to put on my sneakers and hat and walk around the road that follows the northern perimeter of the island.</p>
        <p>It was a walk that led me along the sea through the village of Windward, which was founded by Scottish shipbuilders in the 1700's, and is now a settlement of Afro-Scots. Wooden boat skeletons lined the waterfront and gingerbread pastel cottages delighted at every turn. Passers-by  said good morning; goats snorted. The cottages thinned, and the road, now unpaved, twisted up and over a hill, then into cool green forest. A crooked trail off the main road led down to the most gorgeous white-sand beach on the island, I'd been told. But the paths were numerous, and the markings poor. I chose one that looked likely, and after thrashing through bramble for 15 minutes, came out to a rocky horseshoe bay, with huge heaps of pink conch shells piled here and there. Was this the famous Anse La Roche beach? I later found it wasn't, but it was, indeed, beautiful. I sat on the rocks and enjoyed it for a while, collected a perfect pink shell, then tracked back. Hot midday sun forced me to abandon my plans to walk all the way into Hillsborough. Instead, I jumped on one of the local red vans that run a regular loop around the island, and rode the last mile or so.</p>
        <p>At Bill Patterson's, lunch was on the stove, almost ready. I sat down to chat with Mr. Patterson while I waited with a cool drink, hoping for more dish on the market controversy. Instead, the conversation turned to the stranger in town -- so, where was I from?</p>
        <p>Brooklyn, N.Y., I said, knowing that Brooklyn, with its big West Indian community, is a landmark in the Caribbean.</p>
        <p>Bill Patterson brightened. ''I lived for years in Brooklyn. Do you know Clarkson Avenue?''</p>
        <p>Clarkson Avenue had been my address for 14 years.</p>
        <p>''No charge for the drink, neighbor,'' he insisted. I raised my glass and made a toast, to a small island, and a small world.</p>
        <p>The bottom line in the balmy Grenadines</p>
        <p>I spent eight days and nights on the island of Carriacou, and my expenses for lodging, food, local transportation and boat excursions averaged $67.75 a day. Prices are calculated at $2.67 E.C. (Eastern Caribbean) to the U.S. dollar.</p>
        <p>Getting There</p>
        <p>A catamaran ferry, run by Osprey Lines, (473) 440-8126, takes passengers from the Carenage, in St. George's, Grenada, to Hillsborough in Carriacou. The trip takes about 90 minutes and costs about $15.</p>
        <p>Since my crossing was quite rough, I decided to return from Carriacou by plane -- SVG Air, (473) 444-0328, operates a little nine-seat propeller plane between the two islands. On a clear day, the air views of the Grenadines are magnificent, and worth far more than the price of the one-way fare of $34.50.</p>
        <p>Lodging</p>
        <p>Bayaleau Point Cottages, in Windward, Carriacou, telephone and fax (473) 443-7984, has four pastel wooden cabins with porches on the property, a communal dining porch and a little beach that's good for swimming and snorkeling. Each cottage is slightly different (they can be seen at www.carriacoucottages.com), but all are charming, rustic and beautifully designed. My Little Yellow Cottage had a kitchen with a camp stove, fridge and toaster oven. There was a flush toilet, a shower stall with cold water and a standing electric fan. The cottage wasn't screened -- during the summer, mosquito season, this can be annoying. But there are mosquito nets. The Little Yellow was the smallest and cheapest cottage at $55 a night, off season; $35 a night for stays of a week or more.</p>
        <p>The Round House, (473) 443-7841, in Bogles offers a similar situation to Bayaleau Point Cottages, although the three cottages on this property are plain and functional and lack the Bayaleau's whimsy and design flair. One plus: the cottages have screens. Low-season rates: $45, $55 and $65.</p>
        <p>The Cassada Bay Resort, (473) 443-7494, at the southern end of Carriacou, used to be a summer nature camp for Canadian children. It's been through several managements , and is a bit on the ramshackle side -- I noticed that the plumbing in the rustic wooden cabin that I inspected, one of nine currently available, didn't work. What the place has going for it is an incredible setting -- on a hill atop a blue-green bay, with a view of White Island, a deserted sandbar just offshore that's good for snorkeling. If you call ahead, someone on the staff can take you out for around $10, and pick you up later. Cottages are $60 a night, negotiable.</p>
        <p>Dining</p>
        <p>Since I had a kitchen, I prepared a lot of my meals in the cottage. Breakfast isn't served at Bayaleau. I spent about $40 on groceries.</p>
        <p>Ulla Goldhill, at Bayaleau Point Cottages, is a terrific cook who blends local spices and produce with European cuisine, and the results are delicious. Dinner, typically a fish creole with salad and fresh-baked bread and a good key lime pie, costs $12 to $15, depending on the entree; it is served casually, family style on the open-air deck; wine and beer are available. There is no menu.</p>
        <p>The chef at the Round House (see above) is a transplanted New Yorker who used to work in a Park Avenue Italian restaurant. Dinner in the darkened, candlelit dining room is a more formal affair than at Bayaleau. There is no menu here either -- you decide if you want fish, chicken or pasta, and the chef does the rest. My meal included a pumpkin-coconut-milk soup, goat cheese salad, fish brushed with a balsamic vinegar sauce, and a standout shortcake topped with tropical fruits. The bill, including an aperitif and a glass of wine, came to $25.</p>
        <p>Both the Round House and Bayaleau serve dinner by prearrangement only -- you need to call them by around lunchtime.</p>
        <p>Bill Patterson's (also known as D'Anchor Bar) is on the waterfront in Hillsborough, with no sign visible from the street. Ask any resident to point it out. It serves tasty island-style lunches on the back porch overlooking the harbor. My stewed chicken, rice and peas and salad cost $5.50.</p>
        <p>The Palm Beach restaurant, (473) 443-9103, on Petit Martinique serves similar creole-style lunches right on the beach at picnic tables. Lunch is around $7 with a drink.</p>
        <p>Activities</p>
        <p>At Bayaleau Point Cottages Dave Goldhill takes groups out on the 28-foot fiberglass boat seating 12 that he built himself. The excursions include lunch and drinks; the fee varies with the length of the trip and the distance covered -- my daylong excursion to the Tobago Cays and Mayreau cost $60.</p>
        <p>Local Transportation</p>
        <p>A private taxi from the ferry dock to Bayaleau Cottages costs $7.50; from the airport $9.40. The rates are fixed. Private shared vans ply two loops around the main roads of the island; a ride costs around $1.</p>
        <p>DAISANN McLANE</p>
        <p>FRUGAL TRAVELER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
