<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hoping to Make the Net Inviting for Older Users</title>
    <meta content="20COMP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEW JERSEY &amp; CO."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ican (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suhay, Lisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E2DF163EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1117" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hoping to Make the Net Inviting for Older Users</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA SUHAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Suhay, Lisa</byline>
      <dateline>LITTLE SILVER</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on iCan, mature-market-friendly Web-based service which will begin offering variety of services to older computer users for about $4 to $8 a month on October 1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Computers may seem to be as common as telephones these days, connecting users with information and with one another. But they are less common among the elderly, who often find computers daunting.</p>
        <p>Starting Oct. 1, a ''mature-market-friendly'' Web-based service called iCan will start up, hoping to bring the older population into the world of computer access. The service will provide standard features like e-mail, tailored financial data, news sources, library access and shopping portals -- all tailored to be as unintimidating as possible. Subscribers are expected to pay somewhere in the range of $4 to $8 a month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Computers may seem to be as common as telephones these days, connecting users with information and with one another. But they are less common among the elderly, who often find computers daunting.</p>
        <p>Starting Oct. 1, a ''mature-market-friendly'' Web-based service called iCan will start up, hoping to bring the older population into the world of computer access. The service will provide standard features like e-mail, tailored financial data, news sources, library access and shopping portals -- all tailored to be as unintimidating as possible. Subscribers are expected to pay somewhere in the range of $4 to $8 a month.</p>
        <p>Those who join will be given the option of becoming part of an existing organization of older people in their region and being given local daily calendars of a variety of events such as exercise classes and seminars. A dozen such groups around New Jersey including Greenbriar in Toms River, Ocean County and SCAN (Senior Citizens Activities Network) in Eatontown, Monmouth  County, have already set up partnerships with iCan. The company is soliciting such groups around the United States and the world to link to the service.</p>
        <p>In addition there will be a 24-hour medical service feature that will allow caregivers and loved ones, with the written permission of the subscriber, access to monitor whether  Mom, Dad or grandparents are taking their  medications and making it to doctor visits on schedule.</p>
        <p>The system includes medication reminders, advice and the ability to easily notify local medical services, relatives and others of medical emergencies. It will have full access to a patient's medical records and can phone or e-mail friends and family in the event of a medical emergency.</p>
        <p>Pioneer Medical Systems of Boston, which already has its own 24-hour telephone service that links a subscriber with an electronic medallion to an emergency service, came aboard last month as a financial backer and participant in the service.</p>
        <p>iCan2 Services, Inc. is not a server like America Online, but rather is a service that  subscribers connect to once they are on the Net. It was created by Ezra Hedaya, a 47-year-old entrepreneur who lives in Deal, along with Allon Biberman, a 61-year-old commodities trader from Long Branch,</p>
        <p>''I had spent time in consumer electronics and then was in the family business for years, importing handbags from South Korea,'' said Mr. Hedaya. ''What I began to see was that all of the salesmen were older and they were scared to death to touch a computer. It drove me crazy. So I began simplifying the systems to make it less intimidating.'' He set up screen menus to include 6 choices instead of 20 and to consolidate other choices.</p>
        <p>Looking at various Internet service providers, he reached this conclusion: ''It all looked like some guy from I.B.M. created it for another guy from I.B.M. to use. What was needed was something that looked like it came from a real person.''</p>
        <p>''Then I started looking into it and found the 50-plus market was ignored on the Net because everybody knew there was this phobia,'' Mr. Hedaya said. The iCan2.net  project began in December 1998.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hedaya has put about $250,000 of his own money into the startup effort. He declined to disclose the amount his partners have added.</p>
        <p>Since he was having trouble finding partners in the youth-oriented world of computing, Mr. Hedaya turned to his longtime friend Mr. Biberman. They met while Mr.  Biberman was importing textiles and trading commodities in India and South Korea in the early 1980's when Mr. Hedaya was importing handbags from the same countries.</p>
        <p>''I like this whole concept,'' Mr. Biberman said as he waved a hand around the second-floor offices of iCan in Little Silver. The walls were covered with printouts and site plans that are thumb-tacked in place, and piles of handbooks and files lined the walls. In an adjacent room a team of computer technicians sipped from soda cans and ordered take-out lunches while they feverishly  planned the start-up.</p>
        <p>Hoon Lee of South Korea, age 24, now of Matawan, is a graduate of the Chubb Institute in Woodbridge and the application developer working nearly around the clock to bend the existing tenets of Web site creation to fit the needs of iCan.</p>
        <p>''I needed to try new things to create this environment,'' Mr. Lee said. ''We are integrating with the Microsoft Internet Explorer browser. It's innovating and pioneering, and that is what I find do exciting about this project.''</p>
        <p>The company hopes to get subscribers excited about the start-up by exhibiting their service at Caesars Palace in Atlantic City, Oct. 10 and 11 during the Spirit+Expo, aimed at the older set, and at the 50 Plus Lifestyle Expo at the Huntington House, in Huntington, Long Island, on Oct. 19.</p>
        <p>Ultimately Mr. Hedaya and Mr. Biberman hope the service will evolve into something long envisioned by everyone from cartoonists to technology types: the Internet appliance, the computing and Internet equivalent of a toaster. It will use high-speed Internet connections that would be left running permanently, like a bedside clock.</p>
        <p>''You never sign off your Internet connection,'' Mr. Biberman said.</p>
        <p>''What's the most friendly appliance in your home?'' he asked. ''The telephone,'' he answered, pointing to a sleek black creation sitting on a desk. It looked like one of those combination telephone-answering machine devices but with a small, flat laptop-like screen built on. A thin keyboard pulled out  like a drawer. ''There it isn't,'' he said. ''It's a prototype like many being developed, but not yet perfected.''</p>
        <p>That is where iCan is going with the innovation of the online medical services provision and the monitoring service run by Pioneer Medical Systems.</p>
        <p>''We seniors are a tough market where computers are concerned,'' Mr. Biberman said. ''I've been talking to a lot of seniors in our test groups and I can tell you, getting them there is tough. But, once they're online there is no stopping them, and the Internet appliance is the tool to get them there.''</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY &amp; CO.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
