<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boomerang Lives</title>
    <meta content="20WOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223724"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wood, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malouf, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dream Stuff: Stories (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E7DF173FF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1356" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boomerang Lives</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michael Wood</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wood, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Wood reviews book Dream Stuff: Stories by David Malouf; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DREAM STUFF</p>
        <p>Stories.</p>
        <p>By David Malouf.</p>
        <p>185 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Pantheon Books. $22.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DREAM STUFF</p>
        <p>Stories.</p>
        <p>By David Malouf.</p>
        <p>185 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Pantheon Books. $22.</p>
        <p>DAVID MALOUF'S Australia, as it figures in his poems, novels and stories, is a place of surprises and shifting possibilities. It is a youthful, sparsely settled country, but it is also very old, and Malouf is interested in the question of its age, in its populated and unpopulated history. In his novel ''Remembering Babylon,'' a strange creature appears from the past, and everywhere there are landscapes and perspectives that put the very idea of pastness in question. At the end of ''Dream Stuff,'' his new collection of short fiction, light strikes beaches ''all round the continent, round the vast outline of it,'' but these nine haunting stories show us that the continent is full of darkness too.</p>
        <p>''Nothing was lost,'' we read in the first story. The context here is miniature and domestic, ''the broken continuities'' of holiday arrangements at the beach at Scarborough as experienced by a fatherless boy before and during World War II. ''You let things drop out of sight, then you picked them up again further on.'' When the notion recurs, in the last story in the book, the context is vast and cosmic. ''Nothing is lost. Nothing ever gets lost.'' The speaker is a man who has forfeited his ability to talk, as well as much of his mind, in an accident, and has then recovered to some still uncertain degree: ''Out there -- out there in space, I mean -- there's a kind of receiver. . . . What it picks up, it's made that way, is heartbeats, just that. Every heartbeat on the planet, it doesn't miss a single one, not one is missed. . . . Only it takes such a long time for the sound to travel across all that space that the receiver doesn't even know as yet that we've arrived -- us whites, I mean. Our heartbeats haven't even got there yet. But that doesn't matter. . . . Others were here, now they're gone. But their heartbeats are still traveling out. Even though they stopped ages ago, they're still traveling. . . . Nothing is lost.''</p>
        <p>Of course, these assertions are partial and hopeful, made up of ''dream stuff,'' to borrow Malouf's title. They are protests against recurring and unmistakable loss. The boy in the first story has lost his father; the man in the last story doesn't know how much of his mind or memory is gone forever. But the assertions are not deluded: one of Malouf's most important claims is that return is always possible, even if not everyone and everything returns, even if such returns are not always desirable.</p>
        <p>In this collection of stories, the central metaphor for this claim is a stretch of wilderness by a river in a modern city, now ''won for progress,'' as the narrator ironically says, about to be turned into a shopping mall with tennis courts, a skateboard ramp and a Heritage Walk. The place is called Jacko's Reach, the name apparently a corruption of Jago. (''How, and at what point, by what slip of the tongue or consonantal drift, did the name lurch backwards into an earlier, not-quite-forgotten history, so that the white man's name became a black one and the place reverted, if only in speech, to its original owners?'') The Reach is four and a half acres of scrubland: an ''eyesore,'' according to the city council; an ''area of disorder and difference,'' according to the narrator. Things and people get lost there; children play there; men are found hanged or with their skulls smashed in. But it's also a space of freedom from modernity, a place of chaotic but enduring memories. The idealizing narrator even finds there ''the last luminous grains of a freer and more democratic spirit.'' More ambiguously, he says that it's a place a whole generation turns to in its dreams: ''You walked out there in your sleep and found it crowded.'' It's crowded not because it's appealing or romantic but because it represents ''an area of experience'' that is indispensable, a version of darkness that will resist all forms of light. ''If they take it away we will preserve it in our head. If there is no such place we will invent it. That's the way we are.'' In other words, ''it will be gone and it won't be. Like everything else.''</p>
        <p>Nothing is lost, Malouf is suggesting, but nothing is untouched by loss. ''That's the way we are.'' But who is ''we''? In ''Jacko's Reach,'' they are white Australians of a certain age, whose childhood is inseparable from the encounter with this bit of wilderness. In other stories, they are other Australians or anyone driven by the anxious thought that memory is both too much and not enough. In ''Closer,'' the banished, grown-up son of a deeply pious Pentecostal family regularly drives out from Sydney to his parents' farm but is never allowed to enter the property. When he stops coming, his memory is kept vividly alive in the mind of his 9-year-old niece, who thinks of him all the time and narrates the story.</p>
        <p>In the title story, a writer who now lives in England visits his hometown, Brisbane, and finds there a proliferating vegetation (''unkillably, uncontrollably green'') and ''an aboriginal misery'' that is not necessarily the misery of the aborigines. He also, in the person of an unloved, betrayed man who mistakes the writer for the person who has stolen his woman, meets a violence that is more familiar than he would like to think. ''Far from having put it too far behind him,'' he thinks of the city and his past, ''he felt entangled, caught.'' The dream stuff of the title is marijuana, supposedly grown in fields outside the city, to which trucks take randomly selected pickers, blindfolded, at night. Is this story true? ''It did not have to be,'' Malouf's narrator says. ''It was convincing at some deeper level than fact.''</p>
        <p>The dream-pickers of the dream stuff are, like Jacko's Reach, the image of a secret lawlessness that in some stories must not be denied and in others just won't go away. In ''Lone Pine,'' a middle-aged couple taking a trip through the wilderness (''the first real trip they had ever taken'') is held up and killed by a ''a good-looking young fellow of maybe 20.'' In ''Blacksoil Country,'' an angry racist kills a black man who is bringing him a gift, unleashing a chain of violence in a place where a precarious peace had held for some time.</p>
        <p>And in the ambitious concluding story, ''Great Day,'' which recounts the birthday festivities of a distinguished retired civil servant (''his signature had appeared on the nation's banknotes''), an arsonist sets fire to a local museum, seeming to wipe out the very past that is being celebrated, since many of the family's memorabilia were in this place. And yet Audley, the civil servant, feels ''against all sense or reason, exhilarated, released.'' Not quite against all sense or reason, since he offers himself the following explanation, which brings together conceptually, in slightly overripe Victorian tones, what Malouf has been saying throughout the volume by means of images and events: ''There is ancient and irreconcilable argument in us between settlement and the spirit of the nomad, between the makers of order and our need to give ourselves over at moments to the imps and demons, to the dervish dance of what is in the last resort dust.'' What's exhilarating, in this story and all the others, is the endless liveliness of the dust, the clear conviction that the last resort is both ancient history and just a beginning.</p>
        <p>Michael Wood teaches English at Princeton. His most recent book is ''Children of Silence: On Contemporary Fiction.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michael Wood teaches English at Princeton. His most recent book is ''Children of Silence: On Contemporary Fiction.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
