<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Age 40 Doesn't Mean the End of Everything</title>
    <meta content="20GREE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223807"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Harris</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Can't Stop Now (Tv Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E6DB1E3FF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Age 40 Doesn't Mean the End of Everything</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARRIS GREEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Green, Harris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harris Green article on current interest in dancers over 40 in light of 1998 Canadian documentary Can't Stop Now, which will air on Great Performances; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN recent years, Americans have become more accepting of older dancers. Whether this attitude is a result of aging baby-boomers or has been imposed by political correctness, it is expanding the concept of dancing. The United States now has several organizations that present performances by older dancers, Dancers Over 40 -- the traditional retirement age -- and the 40Up Project among them, or mingle the generations onstage, as does Liz Lerman's Dance Exchange.</p>
        <p>The 1998 Canadian documentary ''Can't Stop Now,'' which Channel 13 will broadcast on ''Great Performances'' on Wednesday night at 8:30, reports on how the Netherlands Dance Theater has extended the careers of dancers by creating NDT3, a company that commissions works specifically for those over 40. No other troupe offers such opportunities. Of course, classical dancers gifted in mime have continued onstage for decades as Drosselmeyer or Dr. Coppelius or Giselle's mother, but most companies have not sought new roles for them to perform.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN recent years, Americans have become more accepting of older dancers. Whether this attitude is a result of aging baby-boomers or has been imposed by political correctness, it is expanding the concept of dancing. The United States now has several organizations that present performances by older dancers, Dancers Over 40 -- the traditional retirement age -- and the 40Up Project among them, or mingle the generations onstage, as does Liz Lerman's Dance Exchange.</p>
        <p>The 1998 Canadian documentary ''Can't Stop Now,'' which Channel 13 will broadcast on ''Great Performances'' on Wednesday night at 8:30, reports on how the Netherlands Dance Theater has extended the careers of dancers by creating NDT3, a company that commissions works specifically for those over 40. No other troupe offers such opportunities. Of course, classical dancers gifted in mime have continued onstage for decades as Drosselmeyer or Dr. Coppelius or Giselle's mother, but most companies have not sought new roles for them to perform.</p>
        <p>NDT3 was spun off in 1991 by the main company's artistic director, Jiri Kylian (now its principal choreographer), at the urging of his wife, the dancer Sabine Kupferberg, and the veteran NDT member Gerard Lemaitre, the oldest of the troupe at 62. (NDT2 is an experimental company for dancers from 17 to 22.) Despite its size -- it has never consisted of more than a handful of dancers -- and considerable turnover, NDT3 has drawn worldwide attention.</p>
        <p>The writer and director Eileen Thalenberg has built ''Can't Stop Now'' around the arrival in The Hague of Karen Kain, a former principal of the National Ballet of Canada, to replace Martine van Hamel, a ballerina from American Ballet Theater who had moved on to NDT3. The sequence in which Ms. Kain learns Mr. Kylian's snaky pas de deux ''No Sleep Till Dawn of Day,'' set to a Solomon Islands lullaby, is a triumph for all concerned, including the film editor, Michele Hozer. (The cameraman, Neville Ottey, however, sometimes cuts off feet later in the film.)</p>
        <p>Although she dwells on Ms. Kain's unease about this transition, Ms. Thalenberg avoids any chauvinistic, local-girl-makes-good approach by giving equal time to Ms. van Hamel's thoughts about turning 50. ''Dancing with NDT3 has given me lightness in a way,'' Ms. van Hamel says. ''I can't, still can't, imagine really having a life without dancing.'' Such expressions of loss by NDT3 members are a constant throughout this moving film.</p>
        <p>What also comes across is how often the choreographers fall back on gimmickry, hyperactivity and calculated cuteness, and how they talk better dances than they deliver. Patrick Delcroix, for example, deplores the practice of giving older dancers something ''dramatic'' just so they can move slowly; he wants ''to do something happy and have some fun.'' Mr. Delcroix may have had a ball creating ''Grain de Folie,'' but for anyone familiar with the heady high jinks of Jerome Robbins (''The Concert,'' say, or the percussion section of ''Fanfare'') or the balletic romps of Charlie Chaplin, the mugging, flailing and shimmying he foists on his dancers seem rather desperate.</p>
        <p>In this film, Mr. Kylian is particularly articulate, but his works for NDT3 can be disconcerting. Last summer, when all three Netherlands Dance Theater companies appeared in the Lincoln Center Festival, his eclectic recent works suggested that his artistic goal had changed; instead of matching movement to rarely used composers like Janacek and Haydn, he was trying to match his fellow European choreographers in the exploitation of oversize props, disco-style seizures, cacophonous amplification or intermittent chaos. It was not surprising that in ''A Way a Lone,'' one of the first works he made for NDT3, he fell back on the familiar distraction of having dancers compete with projected images, in this case of themselves viewed from above. He had no idea, he tells Ms. Thalenberg, how different a dancer would look from that angle.</p>
        <p>Given that sensibility, it shouldn't come as a surprise when we see the men as well as the women in one section of Mr. Kylian's ''Arcimboldo'' don misshapen black tutus that look like wind-sprung umbrellas and slip in and out of these encumbrances to selections from Bach's noble suites for unaccompanied cello, waggling their tongues on the trills. NDT3 costumes are generally striking -- watch for the dancing jellyfish -- but some viewers may sense that using such outre garb indicates an attempt to bolster a performance the dancers can't quite give.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kylian puts Bach to better use when the ''Goldberg Variations'' accompany Ms. Kupferberg, Mr. Lemaitre and the ever-striking Gary Chryst as they employ sign language to ''speak'' their own haikulike eulogies of departed friends -- effective and touching, but also reminiscent of the way in which some choreographers, notably Bill T. Jones, rely on something beyond mere movement (like, say, death) for extra impact. The idea to use sign language was Mr. Kylian's, but he can't claim the result, for neither the words nor the gestures are his creation. What this documentary reports most forcefully is that gifted older dancers with presence and command of gesture can have extended careers once choreographers meet them on an equally high level of dedication.</p>
        <p>DANCE Harris Green, a former editor at Dance Magazine, writes about the performing arts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Harris Green, a former editor at Dance Magazine, writes about the performing arts.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
