<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Site for Restaurant Patrons</title>
    <meta content="20ROW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223864"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Restaurantrow.Com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gurfein, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markowitz, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E7DA163EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="972" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Site for Restaurant Patrons</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN MARKOWITZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Markowitz, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>RYE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Jim Gurfein, lead of Internet company RestaurantRow.com, which consists of database of about 110,000 restaurants in about 50 cities; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Jim Gurfein started his Internet company, Restaurant Row.com, here in 1994, his premise was simple.</p>
        <p>''Everybody eats,'' Mr. Gurfein, 53, said. ''We're looking at an enormous business market of $355 billion a year spent in restaurants. People are passionate about food.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Jim Gurfein started his Internet company, Restaurant Row.com, here in 1994, his premise was simple.</p>
        <p>''Everybody eats,'' Mr. Gurfein, 53, said. ''We're looking at an enormous business market of $355 billion a year spent in restaurants. People are passionate about food.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gurfein certainly is.</p>
        <p>After 25 years in the diamond and jewelry-manufacturing business, which he said he hated, Mr. Gurfein decided to start anew by combining two of his favorite avocations, food and working on computers.</p>
        <p>''In my travels around the world,'' Mr. Gurfein, a Harrison resident, said, ''listening to other people's restaurant recommendations, I thought it'd be great to devise a system where, literally, people can visit a restaurant without actually stepping through the door.''</p>
        <p>Visitors to the RestaurantRow .com Web site can view photographs of restaurants, read menus and search for a particular restaurant by cuisine, proximity, ambience and special features. They can also read reviews by people who have dined there. Reviews by critics are coming soon.</p>
        <p>In six years, Mr. Gurfein and his staff of 25 employees -- with the help of 6,000 recruiters worldwide who sign up online ''for love of God, country and food,'' Mr. Gurfein said, jokingly -- have built a database of 110,000 restaurants in about 50 cities.</p>
        <p>According to Avantgo, a company that allows users to download from the Internet onto hand-held devices, RestaurantRow .com is the second-most accessed site, next to weather services, on wireless and hand-held devices. Mr. Gurfein said four million pages a month are viewed.</p>
        <p>''If there's anything to do with a restaurant, we're the place to go,'' he said. ''You can find it, make a reservation, buy a gift certificate and order food.''</p>
        <p>The offices are on the ground floor of a Colonial-style house in a residential neighborhood here.</p>
        <p>The chief operating officer, Dick Bayles, held the same post at Fairchild Publications, and the vice chairman, William Corbin, is a former executive producer at CBS.</p>
        <p>Daniel Rosenblatt, director of content, is the judge for the James Beard Foundation Awards and former head of dining content for CitySearch.com and Microsoft Sidewalk.</p>
        <p>Many RestaurantRow.com employees make a reverse commute from the city, but not Mr. Gurfein.</p>
        <p>''Living up here,'' he said, ''I recognized quickly that you can have an Internet company anywhere. After spending 25 years commuting in and out of the city, it's been great to live and work in the same community.''</p>
        <p>The company has yet to turn a profit, but after obtaining additional financing from outside private investors, it is beginning to expand its services.</p>
        <p>In the next year, Mr. Gurfein said the company expects to deliver more than 10,000 wireless devices to restaurants on its site. Consumers can then send their reservations into the restaurant, which in turn will contact RestaurantRow.com with their confirmation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gurfein said, RestaurantRow .com alreay makes more reservations in a week than its chief competitors, Open Table and Food Line, do in a month. Open Table and Food Line, however, have real-time reservations while RestaurantRow.com operates on a small delay.</p>
        <p>Zagat.com is its most formidable competitor on the information side.</p>
        <p>Visitors to the RestaurantRow.com Web site will also soon be able to order take-out food for delivery or pick-up.</p>
        <p>''We know that the consuming family of today does very little cooking at home,'' Mr. Gurfein said. ''Our research shows that our clientele eats out anywhere from two to five times a week.</p>
        <p>''In 1999, $110 billion was spent on take-out food. There's room for us to make an impact. Even a small piece of these transactions makes for a big business.''</p>
        <p>American Express and MasterCard Platinum card holders already have most of their restaurant reservations handled by RestaurantRow.com. As of this month, RestaurantRow.com is the dining guide on CNBC's Lifestyle and Entertainment Section. Mr. Gurfein has also just signed a deal with Saber.com, the No. 1 reservation service for travel agencies, for their agents to include restaurant reservations in clients' travel plans.</p>
        <p>''As an outgrowth of being self-funded, one has to scramble,'' Mr. Gurfein said. ''Over time we've built a complete network of distributed sites that work with us.''</p>
        <p>Revenue is derived through these partnerships and what Mr. Gurfein called the ''extraction of a small fee'' from restaurants that use the service. The restaurants pay the company in gift certificates, which are then resold to customers or partnering companies.</p>
        <p>''The only time we get paid by a restaurant is when we send people through its door,'' Mr. Gurfein said. ''We've always been free to the consumer.''</p>
        <p>RestaurantRow.com has had its difficult requests. A week before last New Year's Eve, a woman in New Jersey asked the company to find her a caterer.</p>
        <p>A family traveling throughout Europe asked for dining reservations for their complete trip. In both cases, Mr. Gurfein reported, RestaurantRow.com came through.</p>
        <p>''We expand a diner's horizons to move on from the staid and known when making a decision as to where to enjoy their next meal,'' Mr. Gurfein said. ''To me, that's a marvelous thing.''</p>
        <p>Personal Favorites, From Seafood to Pizza</p>
        <p>The following is a list of Jim Gurfein's favorite restaurants in Westchester and Greenwich.</p>
        <p>Best restaurant: La Panetiere in Rye.</p>
        <p>Italian: Hostaria Mazzei in Port Chester.</p>
        <p>Chinese: K. Fung in Hartsdale.</p>
        <p>Japanese: Abis in Mamaroneck and Greenwich.</p>
        <p>Indian: Bengal Tiger in White Plains.</p>
        <p>Seafood: Elm Street Oyster in Greenwich.</p>
        <p>Continental: Rye Bar and Grill and Cafe Livorno in Rye.</p>
        <p>Pizza: Sunrise in Rye.</p>
        <p>IN BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
