<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Good News: 'Big' Is Back</title>
    <meta content="20BIG.$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223876"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gateway Playhouse (Bellport, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shire, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maltby, Richard Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robillard, Nancy</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Big: The Musical (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E6D9163EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Good News: 'Big' Is Back</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <dateline>PATCHOGUE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alvin Klein reviews Gateway Playhouse revival of David Shire-Richard Maltby Jr play Big: The Musical, directed by Nancy Robillard, at Patchogue Theater for the Performing Arts; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JOSH is 12 years, 11 months and 2 weeks old, going on thirtysomething. He threw a quarter into a make-a-wish machine at a carnival and his wish, to grow up fast, was granted. Josh is living proof that you should be careful of what you wish for. As soon as Josh gets his wish, he wants to get rid of it.</p>
        <p>Moviegoers can tell the rest of the tale. Besides bestowing a breakthrough role on Tom Hanks, the 1988 movie ''Big'' is a lovable comedy fantasy. In 1996, four big-time Broadway producers were wishing that ''Big: The Musical'' would make as indelible an impression with theatergoers as the film did with moviegoers. That wish was not granted, and the musical went down as one of Broadway's costliest money-losers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JOSH is 12 years, 11 months and 2 weeks old, going on thirtysomething. He threw a quarter into a make-a-wish machine at a carnival and his wish, to grow up fast, was granted. Josh is living proof that you should be careful of what you wish for. As soon as Josh gets his wish, he wants to get rid of it.</p>
        <p>Moviegoers can tell the rest of the tale. Besides bestowing a breakthrough role on Tom Hanks, the 1988 movie ''Big'' is a lovable comedy fantasy. In 1996, four big-time Broadway producers were wishing that ''Big: The Musical'' would make as indelible an impression with theatergoers as the film did with moviegoers. That wish was not granted, and the musical went down as one of Broadway's costliest money-losers.</p>
        <p>By bringing back ''Big: The Musical,'' the producers at Gateway Playhouse in Bellport are adding a valuable footnote to recent musical theater history and offering an important second look at an undervalued show.</p>
        <p>Gateway is doing what it must be doing. That means not just reviving safe oldies year after year, but taking a chance on a show that didn't make it, well, big. And Gateway is going all the way. Instead of opening in Bellport, the Island's oldest established home for professionally produced summer musicals, this one is playing in Gateway's newly renovated showplace here, a much bigger theater -- bigger by more than 700 seats.</p>
        <p>''Big'' cannot be cavalierly dismissed as a failed musical that was no match for a blockbuster movie. It is satisfyingly good -- and it was shortchanged. The music of David Shire, the lyrics of Richard Maltby Jr., the book by Jerome Weidman and the choreography by Susan Stroman extol all the values of the grand tradition of musicals. The characters are very dear and complex. It is hard to sit still when the dances take over. You can sing the songs. The words explore the interior child -- his own and the man's.</p>
        <p>''The movie doesn't have a single introspective sentence in it,'' Mr. Maltby said, ''and lyrics are introspective moments.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weidman's adaptation illuminates the contradictions and evokes the mythology of being a child, daring to transport us to the realm of an impossible love between a boy who looks like a man and a woman who doesn't know he is just a boy. By the time he works up the nerve to tell her (''I'm just a kid who looks like a grown-up''), he is all of 13.</p>
        <p>The dances do take over, but are not conceived to be show-stealing. Now that Ms. Stroman (''Crazy for You,'' ''Contact'' and ''The Music Man'') is the incontestable top of musical theater choreographers, it is joyous to rediscover her work of four years ago. As dreamy as they are infused with the tension of break-dancing, the dance patterns are so theatrical and character-driven, it is safe to say they will never go out of style. All of it is faithfully preserved in Gateway's staging by Ginger Thatcher, the original production's assistant choreographer.</p>
        <p>Even though Nancy Robillard was assistant director of Broadway's ''Big,'' she has overdirected this production, going for obvious effects, almost as if she didn't trust the story's inherent tenderness. She seems surer of the characters' conflicts than of their connections. In a cast that tries to make up in eagerness and bounce what they lack in nuance, Eileen Kaden is a standout as Susan, the tough, savvy toy executive who dissolves when Josh says, ''I can show you stars.''</p>
        <p>For all its imperfections, Gateway's ''Big'' is a reminder of the musical theater's irreplaceable pleasures when irrational commercial necessities do not diminish a once flourishing art to an overpriced product for conspicuous consumers. Grab it.</p>
        <p>''Big: The Musical,'' produced by Gateway Playhouse at the Patchogue Theater for the Performing Arts. Box-office: (631) 286 - 1133. Performances through Saturday.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
