<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Performers Behind the Costumes</title>
    <meta content="20FAIR$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6DE143EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1248" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Performers Behind the Costumes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. KYLE MINOR</byline>
      <dateline>TUXEDO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT the New York Renaissance Faire here, there is the Fair Maid Marian joining in a hand-to-hand brawl between the forces of Robin Hood and the Sheriff of Nottingham. A few steps farther into Sterling Forest, the first Queen Elizabeth and her courtiers greet her majesty's 21st-century subjects. Not far off two slightly crazed creatures, Thomas of Bedlam and the Faerie Trapper, show visitors the unpredictable nature of humors in disharmony.</p>
        <p>Who are these performers who usher patrons into a 16th-century hamlet of escapism? Why are they willing, for unprincely pay, to dress in hot and heavy costumes, improvising under the blistering sun or pouring rain, from 10:30 a.m. to 7 p.m.?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT the New York Renaissance Faire here, there is the Fair Maid Marian joining in a hand-to-hand brawl between the forces of Robin Hood and the Sheriff of Nottingham. A few steps farther into Sterling Forest, the first Queen Elizabeth and her courtiers greet her majesty's 21st-century subjects. Not far off two slightly crazed creatures, Thomas of Bedlam and the Faerie Trapper, show visitors the unpredictable nature of humors in disharmony.</p>
        <p>Who are these performers who usher patrons into a 16th-century hamlet of escapism? Why are they willing, for unprincely pay, to dress in hot and heavy costumes, improvising under the blistering sun or pouring rain, from 10:30 a.m. to 7 p.m.?</p>
        <p>''As a performer it's the greatest challenge imaginable,'' said Ann Alford of Brooklyn, who plays Queen Elizabeth. ''Being onstage with a written script is a cakewalk in comparison.''</p>
        <p>Kelly Kilcoyne of Hawthorne, who plays Maid Marian, agreed, saying that the fair, which opened Aug. 5, was an opportunity to grow as a performer. (Her husband is Tom of Bedlam, otherwise known as Don Kilcoyne.) ''You also learn period language, dialects, have the opportunity to learn stage combat, traditional songs, period dance'' said Ms. Kilcoyne, who grew up in New Milford. ''Yes, the costumes are often heavy and hot, but it is the ultimate game of dress-up.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Alford and the Kilcoynes are trained actors with experience ranging from community to professional theater. Ms. Alford, in fact, earned a master of fine arts degree from the University of Virginia in Charlottesville and studied in London before moving to New York to pursue her acting career. For nine years the Renaissance Faire has provided her with steady employment without forcing her to give up her day job at a private investment company in Greenwich, where she supervises payroll and pensions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kilcoyne, a 10-year veteran at Sterling Forest and a member of Actors Equity Association, works as a creative director for a Manhattan marketing concern, while Ms. Kilcoyne, a five-year veteran, works in a Hawthorne bookstore.</p>
        <p>The fair also offers performers a close-knit second family. After a long Saturday of being in character, the actors camp out in Sterling Forest, where they may drink a beer, grill a bite to eat and generally hobnob.</p>
        <p>''Ren Faire people, present and past, are definitely my closest friends,'' Ms. Alford said. ''I initially auditioned back in 1992 because the stage manager that year was the best man at my wedding.''</p>
        <p>The Kilcoynes said that in the last three years they have attended seven weddings of people they met at the fair. The Kilcoynes themselves were married there five years ago. Mr. Kilcoyne, who was playing a pirate that summer, kidnapped Ms. Kilcoyne and absconded with her to the Kissing Bridge, where he proposed -- in verse. Ms. Kilcoyne consented through her tears.</p>
        <p>''I didn't realize that the stage manager heard me instruct the other pirates about the plan,'' Mr. Kilcoyne said. ''So when I was proposing, she told everybody on the headset. When we returned from the Kissing Bridge, everybody was cheering us.''</p>
        <p>Christine Well of Danbury first went to Sterling Forest 10 years ago. She enjoyed herself so much that this year she has joined the ensemble as Heather Willow, a Cockney Faerie trapper.</p>
        <p>''When I became an avid reader of Shakespeare, my mother suggested I try out for it,'' said Ms. Wells, who will be a senior at Danbury High School in a few weeks. ''I get to set my inner lunatic free.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Wells, who has had no previous experience, took up improvisation during the rigorous rehearsal period that starts in June in Manhattan. The actors attend workshops structured toward ''building a character with a history and a reason for being at this fair on this particular day,'' Ms. Alford said. ''The language workshops, some of which I teach, aim to get people used to speaking in a 16th-century way so that it becomes second nature and doesn't get in the way of improvising.''</p>
        <p>In July, the rehearsals intensified, Mr. Kilcoyne said. ''Kelly, as Marian, has had a heavy fighting rehearsal schedule, including work with the joust horses, because Maid Marian will be seeing a lot of combat this year. She's also got a lot of scene work, and rehearsals with the Singing Wenches.</p>
        <p>''I had a lot more improvisational work, since my role will mostly entail theater sports-style improvisational comedy,'' he said. ''I'm also rehearsing for the role of Petruchio in 'The Taming of the Shrew,' '' an hourlong production that is part of the fair.</p>
        <p>Now that the show has opened, Ms. Wells said, her routine, at least on weekends, hasn't relented.</p>
        <p>''On Saturday I'm up at 6:30 a.m., on the road by 7:30 a.m.,'' she said, adding that her father drives her since she's just learning to drive herself. ''Then I scramble into my costume to be ready for the 9:45 company meeting, after which we all head out to assigned areas on the grounds to wait for the first patrons that pour in. I have three shows a day with Luna Bloom, the Faerie Godmother, called Faerie Lore, where we tell a fairy tale and talk about the nature of fairies. I take a half-hour break for lunch. I dance the maypole once or twice a day and cheer at the royal joust and then try to meet as many people as I can before they leave the shire.''</p>
        <p>Hard work notwithstanding, there is relatively little turnover in the cast, Ms. Alford said. Nonetheless, she continued, ''There's always attrition,'' adding, ''We lose actors for many reasons including injuries, other job offers, or sometimes, I believe, panic.''</p>
        <p>Of the four actors, Mr. Kilcoyne is the only one to miss a performance thus far. He missed one day during his first year to attend his father's funeral.</p>
        <p>''Of course, it never occurred to me to go back to work the next day, until my mom woke me up early in the morning and said, 'You've got to get to the fair,' ''he said. '' 'Mom,' I said, 'we just buried Dad yesterday.' 'Yes,' she said, 'and that's why you have to go. Today's the only day he'll be able to see you perform.' ''</p>
        <p>Each of the actors plans to return next year and, perhaps, the year after. They show no signs of wearying of returning to the 21st century for any foreseeable weekends.</p>
        <p>''Every once in a while we think 'beach house,' '' Mr. Kilcoyne said. ''We could be sitting in a beach house right now. But the audience is still here, and the shore will be there for a long time. It'll wait for us.''</p>
        <p>The New York Renaissance Faire runs Saturdays and Sundays from 10:30 a.m. to 7 p.m. through Sept. 20. Sterling Forest is in Tuxedo on Route 17A, just off Route 17 (11 miles south of Woodbury Common Factory Outlets). Admission is $15.75, $6 for children 3 to 12 and free for children under 3. Parking costs $5, and a shuttle service is available.</p>
        <p>The number to call for information is (914) 351-5174, and the Web site is found at www.renfair.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
