<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Assessment Cometh</title>
    <meta content="20TAX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223920"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOVERNMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strunsky, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E1DD143EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1287" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Assessment Cometh</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE STRUNSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strunsky, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on homeowners' reaction to upcoming property revaluations in Newark, NJ, which many fear may force them to sell; city last revaluated properties in 1972; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A lot has changed in the 26 years since Jean and Ralph Shomer moved from Bergen County to the gracious Forrest Hill neighborhood here along Branch Brook Park so Mr. Shomer, now 82, could be closer to the coat factory he still owns.</p>
        <p>The neighborhood is noisier, with more children and loud music playing, said Mrs. Shomer, 66, a retired court clerk. The couple's property tax bill has also changed, from $1,800 a year to $4,800. Likewise, the market value of their house, a center-hall colonial on a corner lot, has risen significantly above the $58,000 they paid for it in 1974, when the Shomers bucked a trend by moving to Newark during the decade following the city's riots of 1967, when many families were moving out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A lot has changed in the 26 years since Jean and Ralph Shomer moved from Bergen County to the gracious Forrest Hill neighborhood here along Branch Brook Park so Mr. Shomer, now 82, could be closer to the coat factory he still owns.</p>
        <p>The neighborhood is noisier, with more children and loud music playing, said Mrs. Shomer, 66, a retired court clerk. The couple's property tax bill has also changed, from $1,800 a year to $4,800. Likewise, the market value of their house, a center-hall colonial on a corner lot, has risen significantly above the $58,000 they paid for it in 1974, when the Shomers bucked a trend by moving to Newark during the decade following the city's riots of 1967, when many families were moving out.</p>
        <p>But one thing has remained constant for the Shomers: their property tax assessment.</p>
        <p>Now that, too, is about to change, and the Shomers and many other homeowners in Newark are worried that a revaluation will drive their property taxes so high that they will be driven out of town.</p>
        <p>''The writing's on the wall, and they want to make sure they can sell their homes,'' Mrs. Shomer said.</p>
        <p>It has been 39 years since the last time Newark adjusted the assessed value of every taxable property to match its estimated true market value, that is, the price it would likely fetch if it were put up for sale.</p>
        <p>It is not unusual for cities and towns to go several years without a revaluation. In Newark's case, however, it has been so long that fundamental shifts have occurred in the value of properties relative to one another, and major inequities have evolved in the amount of taxes that property owners pay in relation to the real value of their property.</p>
        <p>Newark has probably been overdue for a revaluation at least since 1972, when Essex County officials pressed the state to impose one because the city's antiquated assessments were causing inequities in what other municipalities were contributing to the county tax levy, said Robert Thompson, director of the State Division of Taxation.</p>
        <p>City officials fought off that attempt, and, with the aid of sympathetic state legislators, deferred revaluation for three decades. The historical rationale has been that, in the wake of the riots, the potential spike in property taxes for many homeowners after a revaluation would accelerate the exodus of the city's middle class.</p>
        <p>But last October, after Essex County again asked the state Attorney General to sue Newark to conduct a revaluation, Judge Harry A. Margolis of State Superior Court in Newark ordered that the State Division of Taxation should arrange for the process itself, and deduct its cost from Newark's annual state aid allocation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson said that a $6.2 million contract would be signed this week with a Randolph-based appraisal company, Certified Valuations, which won the bidding on the project. The project, for which the company will employ 50 assessors whose work will be checked by the city assessor's 16 staff members, is to be completed in time for 2003 tax bills.</p>
        <p>Indicating just how far Newark's assessments have fallen behind real values, a study completed last September by the Center for Government Services at Rutgers University's Richard J. Bloustein School of Planning and Public Policy estimated that the true market value of Newark's taxable property was about $5 billion. By contrast, the total assessed value of the city's 38,648 residential, commercial, industrial and vacant taxable properties was just $792,855,400 -- or about one-sixth of the market value -- in 1999, according to figures provided by the city tax assessor, Evelyn Loaccitiello.</p>
        <p>As a result of the low assessments, the city's tax rate is an absurdly high $24.53 per $100 of assessed value.</p>
        <p>The Rutgers study, led by the center's director, Prof. Henry Coleman, also reveals disparities in Newark's current assessments and its property tax levy, and draws several conclusions about the impact of the revaluation. For one thing, the study concludes that because residential properties have appreciated at a higher rate than commercial properties since the last revaluation, homeowners will end up shouldering a larger share of the total property tax burden -- nearly 50 percent, up from 35.7 percent in 1998.</p>
        <p>''On average, commercial, industrial and apartment properties will likely experience a favorable impact from revaluation,'' the study said.</p>
        <p>Within the residential property category, the study found that revaluation will result in a shift of the property tax burden away from the city's poorer neighborhoods toward its more affluent ones.</p>
        <p>Currently, the study concluded, the East and North wards, which include the relatively prosperous Ironbound and Forrest Hill sections respectively, have the greatest disparity between their assessed and market values. Assessments equaled less than 10 percent of market value in the East Ward, and just above 10 percent in the north, the study found.</p>
        <p>One result of a revaluation, said Mr. Thompson, the state tax man, will be a more fair and just distribution of the tax burden, at least when speaking strictly in terms of what homeowners contribute.</p>
        <p>But fairness can be a relative concept. To homeowners in Forrest Hill and the Ironbound, where the revaluation is expected to increase tax bills by 50 to 100 percent, the revaluation is unfair because they will be the hardest hit.</p>
        <p>For example, even with its antiquated $19,600 assessment, the Shomers's house is still officially valued at nearly twice the city-wide average, and the couple pays nearly double the average tax bill for a single-family home. Mrs. Shomer, who is president of the Forrest Hill Action Group, a neighborhood association, said the quality of life had slipped in her neighborhood, and city services, especially the state-controlled school system, were just not worth the higher taxes.</p>
        <p>Jack DaSilva, a real estate broker in the East Ward who is also president of the Ironbound Community Corporation, a civic group, said the Portuguese and Brazilian community will essentially be punished by the revaluation for working hard to transform the Ironbound from a run down neighborhood into a prosperous one.</p>
        <p>''I know that it's been many years since the revaluation was done,'' Mr. DaSilva said. ''Unfortunately it's not the fault of the present population who's living here, and it's unfair to put the burden on the present population.''</p>
        <p>City Councilman Donald Tucker, who is also a state assemblyman, successfully proposed state legislation allowing Newark to soften revaluation's blow by phasing in tax increases over a five-year period. But while Mrs. Shomer applauded the law, Mr. DaSilva said it merely gives homeowners' five years' notice to sell their property.</p>
        <p>The council president, Donald Bradley, who represents the South Ward, did not respond to a request for comment on the revaluation.</p>
        <p>Pam Goldstein, a spokeswoman for Mayor Sharpe James, said the mayor simply had no control over the court-ordered, state-implemented revaluation. She did say that he supports the phase-in plan.</p>
        <p>In the end, Mr. Thompson insisted, revaluation will be a good thing for the entire city. Even the break that revaluation appears to offer commercial properties will lead to enhanced business and employment opportunities for residents.</p>
        <p>''Certainly, when burdens shift, everybody has a position that they would use to defend their situation which is going help them avoid paying more,'' Mr. Thompson said. ''I think history will show that once you go through the admittedly agonizing process of revaluation in an urban community the size of Newark, then Newark, I believe, and everybody in Newark will be better off once it's done.''</p>
        <p>GOVERNMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
