<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Land So Wild, It's Getting Crowded</title>
    <meta content="ISSUES$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/20/travel/ISSUES.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000903T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223759"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alaska</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Timothy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E5D9103FF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2136" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Land So Wild, It's Getting Crowded</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY EGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Egan, Timothy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Timothy Egan travel article on $1 billion tourism industry that threatens Alaska with overcrowding and is raising environmenal concerns; photos; maps (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was not so long ago that most of Alaska was cloaked in anonymity, and the idea that more than half a million people a year would pay money to visit a waterlogged fishing village or come within smelling distance of a grizzly bear was laughable. Towns that had seen their last mines sealed, their timber mills shuttered and their fishing docks empty huddled against the elements, the people wondering whether one last boom would come their way.</p>
        <p>In the minds of many outsiders, Alaska was too cold, too wild, too remote. But those very words have become the selling points of a $1 billion tourism industry that has exceeded even the wildest projections. Visits have tripled since 1980, and tourism has caught up with fishing to become the state's second largest industry, behind oil and gas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was not so long ago that most of Alaska was cloaked in anonymity, and the idea that more than half a million people a year would pay money to visit a waterlogged fishing village or come within smelling distance of a grizzly bear was laughable. Towns that had seen their last mines sealed, their timber mills shuttered and their fishing docks empty huddled against the elements, the people wondering whether one last boom would come their way.</p>
        <p>In the minds of many outsiders, Alaska was too cold, too wild, too remote. But those very words have become the selling points of a $1 billion tourism industry that has exceeded even the wildest projections. Visits have tripled since 1980, and tourism has caught up with fishing to become the state's second largest industry, behind oil and gas.</p>
        <p>But even as cash registers clank and whirr from Deadhorse, in the far north, to Sitka, in the southeastern rain forest, an effort to rein in explosive growth has taken hold and appears to be gaining momentum. Some of the people who live in the coastal towns that have had their economies transformed by the cruise ship industry are trying to limit visits. In the national parks, which used to be some of the loneliest places on the planet, the number of visitors has doubled in 10 years, and officials say the crowds at some sites are threatening the very thing that is their draw -- the sense of wildness. Backpackers, kayakers and sports fishers are complaining about excessive helicopter flights, Jet Skis and group fishing tours.</p>
        <p>Tourism itself is not under fire. There is nary an Alaskan village, from the Bering Sea to the roadless interior, that does not welcome visitors. What bothers many Alaskans is the onslaught of ''industrial tourism,'' a term coined by the environmental writer Edward Abbey to describe mass tourism and its effects -- in Moab, Utah, for example, the crush of visitors has damaged the fragile desert and forced federal officials to limit visitation to some areas. People also fear that the singular character of the state is changing as Alaskans conform to the expectations of large tour companies.</p>
        <p>''My concern is that the people coming to see Alaska ultimately won't see it,'' said Kelley Weaverling, a former mayor of the fishing village of Cordova, on Prince William Sound, who runs a bookstore in the town. ''When I first came here, this place was almost prehistoric. Now, it's in danger of becoming very Disneyfied.''</p>
        <p>Cordova is the kind of town where dogs fall asleep in the middle of the road and relentless rain wraps the town in a towel of moisture nine months a year. It is known for the fleet that brings in the first wild salmon of the year, from the nearby Copper River. But its quirky charms have been discovered by some of the biggest tourism operators in the world -- to mixed reception.</p>
        <p>When Princess Cruises and Tours recently announced that it would be building a $10 million, 100-room lodge on 200 acres of the Copper River, a wild expanse of glacial runoff that feeds one of biggest wetlands in the Western Hemisphere, it was hailed by the company as a new frontier in Alaska tourism. The lodge would border the Wrangell-St. Elias National Park and Preserve -- at 13 million acres, the largest unit in the National Park system. Princess officials described the lodge plan as a way for visitors to experience ''one of the state's best-kept secrets,'' and said it would not harm the marine ecosystem.</p>
        <p>But while new lodges are welcomed for the construction and service jobs they bring, small tour operators and wilderness advocates fear that much of the state's tourism is being ceded to foreign-owned interests. Princess, a subsidiary of the London-based shipping company P &amp; O, runs four big lodges in Alaska, 10 private rail cars between Fairbanks and Anchorage, numerous buses, and a fleet of ships carrying more than 200,000 people a year to the state.</p>
        <p>''Cruise ships are kind of like colonists,'' said Mr. Weaverling, referring to the companies that run the lines. ''They come in their own large ships. They put people on their own tour buses. They build their own lodges. Until, finally the cruise ship visitor never sees an actual Alaskan unless it's somebody who made their bed.''</p>
        <p>Dean Brown, an executive vice president at Princess, scoffs at such characterizations. Alaska cruise ship passengers, he said, defy the stereotype of sedentary seniors tied to the cocoon of the cruise ship.</p>
        <p>''When people used to come to Juneau or Sitka, they wanted to ride a tour bus,'' said Mr. Brown. ''Now they want to kayak, or ice-climb or canoe or hike to a glacier -- and we don't own any of those attractions or the services built around them.''</p>
        <p>As for fears of Alaska's being loved to death, the solution, according to state tourism officials and some cruise line executives, is to spread out the visitors. ''People forget that Alaska is a huge land mass, and we have a million visitors a year -- just a fraction of what Hawaii gets,'' said Ginny Fay, director of tourism for the state. ''We just need to disperse our visitors more.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown pointed to the plan to build a lodge on the Copper River as an example of how the major tour operators were trying to move visitors out of crowded areas.</p>
        <p>The most vocal and organized opposition to the growth of the cruise ship industry is in Juneau, the state capital, where more than 630,000 passengers are expected this year, in a town of 30,000 -- a nearly 50 percent increase over the last five years. The biggest of the 540 ships that will tie up in Juneau this summer is the 10-story Sea Princess, which is taller than the highest building in Juneau.</p>
        <p>Juneau residents complain about excessive noise, air and water pollution, and crowds from the cruise ships, which usually dock in the morning and leave in the evening of the same day. Helicopter and small-plane sightseeing tours, working with the cruise ships, have made the skies around Juneau a zone of noise and air clutter in the summer.</p>
        <p>''It's like 'Apocalypse Now,' '' said Kimberly Metcalfe-Helmar, a Juneau resident who has helped to promote two ballot initiatives to limit tourism related to cruise ships. ''You just can't get away from the noise. If you're on your favorite hiking trail, there may be six helicopters overhead. People are fed up.''</p>
        <p>Reflecting the outrage, voters in Juneau last year bucked the cruise ship industry and Alaska's political leaders. Seventy percent of voters agreed to put a $5 a person tax on every arriving cruise ship passenger. The money is used for hospitals, parks, roads and other parts of the city that are burdened by heavy visitation.</p>
        <p>This year, Juneau residents are likely to vote on the so-called Peace and Quiet Initiative, which would restrict helicopter flights in the area. It is being promoted by some bed-and-breakfast owners, who stress that they are not against tourism but are unhappy at the growth of mass tourism. A Web site run by Crondahls' Bed &amp; Breakfast in Juneau (www.juneaucrondahls.com) has links to the campaign, with pictures of ships belching smoke into the sky above the clear harbor.</p>
        <p>North of Juneau, the town of Haines voted last year to limit the number of cruise ships that can dock. But in nearby Skagway, a former ghost town that had its glory years during the Gold Rush, the ships are welcome, as they bring more than 8,000 passengers a week to a village of 800 people.</p>
        <p>The cruise industry responded to the campaigns in Haines and Juneau by cutting donations to the arts and canceling some visits. Princess pulled out of Haines, and Holland America reduced its charitable donations. And while this cutback has prompted many in Alaska to label the industry arrogant, it has spurred merchants to fight future efforts at restricting tourism.</p>
        <p>Cruise ship passengers spend more than $160 million a year in southeast Alaska, according to Alaskan tourism officials and studies sponsored by the industry. To towns like Ketchikan and Sitka, which saw their big timber-processing mills close in recent years, the cruise ships are the key to prosperity. Cruise industry officials say they oppose head taxes, because they already pay in excess of $10 million a year in local sales tax and fees.</p>
        <p>But it would be wrong for the industry to ignore or dismiss complaints from the towns most affected by heavy growth, said Ms. Fay, the Alaska tourism director.</p>
        <p>''If you think of these residents as the canaries in the coal mine, the fact that they are complaining is a good indication that visitors may soon start complaining,'' she said. ''The message from Juneau was: 'I'm trying to tell you something.' And I'm not sure the response of the industry was as constructive as it could have been because it has not calmed down.''</p>
        <p>Another concern is that the growth of large-scale tourism will come at the expense of not just individual communities but also of Alaska's largely pristine environment, and the many small outfits who cater to the growing eco-tourism market.</p>
        <p>These critics point to the dumping of toxic waste water by Royal Caribbean Cruise Lines during the mid-1990's, and recent citations of other lines for violating air pollution levels. Royal Caribbean agreed to pay $6.5 million in criminal fines -- a record for a cruise ship operator in American waters -- for the discharges at sea.</p>
        <p>The industry promotes itself as environmentally clean, and says it processes solid waste on board and then disposes of it ashore. The water used in showers, dishwashing and laundry is still dumped at sea, but cruise ship operators say it is harmless and in compliance with Federal regulations.</p>
        <p>Steve Torok, the Environmental Protection Agency's senior representative in Juneau, and Capt. Ed Page, chief of marine safety for the Coast Guard in Alaska, said the only regulations for this so-called gray water is that it comprise solely waste water from showers, food preparation and laundry. Yet there have been violations over the years, they added, because hazardous materials were mixed with the waste water and dumped. As a result, Captain Page said, spot-testing of such water began this year.</p>
        <p>Beyond pollution concerns, some critics say Alaska's wild lands and formerly empty fjords and inlets have simply become too crowded. Twenty years ago, President Jimmy Carter more than doubled the size of the national park and wildlife refuge systems in the state. The move outraged members of Alaska's Congressional delegation, who said the new parks and refuges would not attract sufficient visitors.</p>
        <p>Not only have people flocked to these federally protected lands, but Alaska's powerful representatives in Congress have become the biggest promoters of the expanded tourism industry that has resulted. In the mid-90's, the delegation pushed through a change in the law allowing cruise ship traffic to nearly double -- to 184 -- in June, July and August in Glacier Bay National Park and Preserve, the nation's largest protected marine ecosystem. A compromise eventually set the limit at 139.</p>
        <p>The Congressmen have also promoted plans to build a 90-mile road through the wilderness of Denali National Park, and have quashed efforts to limit visitors around the falls where brown bears gather to eat salmon in Katmai National Park. Senators Frank H. Murkowski and Ted Stevens, Republicans of Alaska, say Denali needs more development and Katmai can accommodate more visitors without affecting the behavior of the big bears.</p>
        <p>Others, like Chip Dennerlein, director of the Alaska office of the National Parks Conservation Association, which is opposed to many of the new development plans in or near Alaska's parks, disagree.</p>
        <p>''If you come all the way to Alaska to experience the wild,'' he said, ''and what you see is a free-for-all to watch bears, or you go to pristine camp site and there are 35 helicopter flights over your head, that's going to give you second thoughts.''</p>
        <p>TIMOTHY EGAN is a reporter for The Times, based in Seattle.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 3, 2000, Sunday  An article on Aug. 20 about cruising the Inside Passage of Alaska on a small ship misstated the range of the author's trip. The ship did indeed stop on the mainland, at the ports of Skagway and Haines. It did not stop only at island ports.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 3, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on Aug. 20 about cruising the Inside Passage of Alaska on a small ship misstated the range of the author's trip. The ship did indeed stop on the mainland, at the ports of Skagway and Haines. It did not stop only at island ports.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">TIMOTHY EGAN is a reporter for The Times, based in Seattle.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
