<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Risky Business</title>
    <meta content="20KAUFMAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223713"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ashbrook, Tom</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Leap, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E3D6163FF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Risky Business</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Leslie Kaufman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leslie Kaufman reviews book The Leap: A Memoir of Love and Madness in the Internet Gold Rush by Tom Ashbrook (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE LEAP</p>
        <p>A Memoir of Love and Madness</p>
        <p>in the Internet Gold Rush.</p>
        <p>By Tom Ashbrook.</p>
        <p>295 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE LEAP</p>
        <p>A Memoir of Love and Madness</p>
        <p>in the Internet Gold Rush.</p>
        <p>By Tom Ashbrook.</p>
        <p>295 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. $25.</p>
        <p>Who among us has not at least daydreamed about chucking that ho-hum desk job and heading off to join an Internet start-up? It all sounds so adventuresome, so new frontier, so, well, so tantalizingly lucrative.</p>
        <p>Few of us, of course, have the nerve to make the jump. But for those who want to experience vicariously the vicissitudes of starting an e-business, there is Tom Ashbrook's alternately informative and overwrought chronicle of his own exploits in the new economy.</p>
        <p>The story opens as Ashbrook, a former foreign correspondent who seems to relish danger, is being tempted from his secure but unchallenging job as an editor with The Boston Globe. The bait: a chance to join an old Yale pal in developing a home-design CD-ROM that eventually becomes a Web-site business called HomePortfolio.com.</p>
        <p>Almost half the book is taken up by Ashbrook's tortured soul-searching over whether to join the start-up, forcing the reader to plow through the same soliloquy more than once. From Chapter 1: ''I had played out the better part of a first career and found some of its limits -- and some of my own. It was time to make the leap.'' Then three chapters later: ''It was time to wade in, I thought. I needed to wade in all the way over my head and come out fresh, come out new.'' And, again, 60 pages down the road: ''So I had a choice. I could stay where I was, hoping the old world would see me through. Or I could jump. I could make the leap to the new world, a new economy.'' For God's sake, man, just do it already!</p>
        <p>When Ashbrook finally commits to his new venture, the book picks up. At its best, it guides us step by step along the rocky path from brainstorming on the back porch to creating a real, live business. Time after time, our novice entrepreneurs are forced to amend and simplify their vision to make it workable. They travel endlessly to persuade skeptical manufacturers to come on board. And they seek help -- advice, solace, cash -- from just about everyone they encounter, from next-door neighbors to Harvard Business School professors.</p>
        <p>It is the search for capital to keep the enterprise afloat that forms the leitmotif of the book. Indeed, the hunt for money is all-absorbing -- and often humiliating. Just to meet their meager payroll, our dreamers must prostrate themselves repeatedly before those with fat bank accounts. At one point they call on a former college friend, a television news anchor, who tells them he is eager to help. He never calls back. And so it goes.</p>
        <p>The pressure to raise money also takes a personal toll. Ashbrook runs up his credit cards to the maximum and pushes his family's finances to near ruin. His wife -- who makes this adventure possible by providing a regular income, caring for their three children and making ends meet out of dwindling savings -- tolerates his 18-hour days, but she, too, falls prey to anxiety. Once she sends him an e-mail message to explain that the stress has become so overwhelming that she vomited at work. Our hero, who seems to believe that his own selfishness is somehow negated by his candor in acknowledging it, feels her pain -- and then barrels ahead anyway.</p>
        <p>Yet despite the ups and downs of the money hunt and the other insights Ashbrook offers into how single-minded one must be to succeed as an entrepreneur, there is still not enough material in ''The Leap'' to sustain a 300-page book.</p>
        <p>Ashbrook seems aware of this, which may explain why he frequently resorts to melodrama. There can be little doubt, for example, that Ashbrook's business dealings were tough on his family. But do we really need to know how, after a fight, his wife tore up the little paper hearts with which she had covered the bathroom mirror for Valentine's Day?</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most disappointing thing about ''The Leap'' is that it is not really about the Internet, as its subtitle suggests. All the difficulties Ashbrook tackles would be familiar to anyone who built a business before the new technology. His narrative ends abruptly just at the moment we might learn about the peculiar problems of running an e-business -- when the money arrives.</p>
        <p>In an epilogue, Ashbrook informs us that the company was blessed with $25 million in capital and quickly took on nearly 100 employees. So the Web site will live! But to find out how such a business overcomes obstacles like establishing a customer base, designing an attractive, workable Web site and responding to a flood of new competitors, we will have to wait for someone else's memoir.</p>
        <p>Leslie Kaufman is a business reporter for The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Leslie Kaufman is a business reporter for The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
