<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Son of Hartford With No Need to Leave</title>
    <meta content="20CHET$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hartford (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kempczynski, Chet</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Minor, E Kyle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/Hartford</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E3DE163EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1147" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Son of Hartford With No Need to Leave</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. KYLE MINOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Minor, E Kyle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on artist Chet Kempczynski of Hartford, Conn; he comments on his decision to remain in downtown Hartford rather than join New York City art scene; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MANY artists move to New York City in hopes of making a splash in the art world. They figure to be near the prestigious galleries as well as the potential customers who will buy their work.</p>
        <p>Chet Kempczynski, on the other hand, has established a distinctive reputation and a comfortable living while remaining in Hartford for almost all his 51 years. He has shown at nearly all the galleries in the Hartford area and has several clients throughout the country who frequently buy his paintings for thousands of dollars apiece.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MANY artists move to New York City in hopes of making a splash in the art world. They figure to be near the prestigious galleries as well as the potential customers who will buy their work.</p>
        <p>Chet Kempczynski, on the other hand, has established a distinctive reputation and a comfortable living while remaining in Hartford for almost all his 51 years. He has shown at nearly all the galleries in the Hartford area and has several clients throughout the country who frequently buy his paintings for thousands of dollars apiece.</p>
        <p>He recently completed his second one-person exhibition at Westwood Gallery in Soho, and he is currently represented by a cow (''Ceci n'est pas une vache,'' ''This is not a cow'') pastured in front of the News Corporation building at 1211 Sixth Avenue as part of the New York City ''Cow Parade.'' And Mr. Kempczynski has accomplished all of this without ever buying an E-ZPass. ''A lot of artists do go to New York,'' he said. ''I never felt the need to move. I mean, have you seen my place?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kempczynski was referring to the third-floor apartment-cum-studio in downtown Hartford that he shares with his wife, Genevieve Rela, and their daughters Eva, 9 and Margot, 7. It is a magnificent spread of more than 12 rooms; Mr. Kempczynski uses about 5 for his work.</p>
        <p>The apartment includes a rooftop garden, a studio with a cathedral ceiling, nearly a dozen closets, and a larger studio awash in sunlight that overlooks the heart of downtown. ''If I could find a studio like this in New York, I could never, ever afford it,'' the artist said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kempczynski needs plenty of elbow room to work on his 7 feet by 7 feet canvases and on his nearly-as-large monotypes. The latter is an art form in which the artist paints his subject in reverse on glass, then presses a one-of-a-kind print on Stonehenge-heavy paper. It requires Mr. Kempczynski to work quickly and without interruption, lest the paint start drying on the glass before the pressing.</p>
        <p>James Cavello, president of the Westwood Gallery in Soho, which recently presented its second show of Mr. Kempczynski's oils and monotypes, said that the monotype is an art form all its own and that Mr. Kempczynski is one of the gallery's truly unusual artists. ''I get excited about Chet's work,'' he said. ''His landscapes and florals are so colorful and alive, they are not like other works.''</p>
        <p>Margarite Almeida, director of the Westwood Gallery, said that Mr. Kempczynski's style is ''representational and slightly abstract.''</p>
        <p>''Most artists are aware of other styles and Chet is in touch with what others are doing around him,'' Ms. Almeida said, ''but he's not afraid to follow his own path.''</p>
        <p>The fact that Mr. Kempczynski lives two hours from Manhattan is part of his unusualness, Mr. Cavello said. ''Chet is very influenced by his environment, in a spiritual sort of way,'' Mr. Cavello said. ''If he were pounding the pavement in New York, he might be influenced by what he sees other people are doing. He doesn't need to live in New York for his art.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kempczynski, who studied at the Paier School of Art in New Haven from 1967 to 1970 and the Hartford Art School of the University of Hartford in 1975, has certainly paid his dues. He has worked at various unglamorous survival jobs, such as cabby and lab technician for the Red Cross. (In September he will start a new job, teaching at the Loomis-Chaffee School in Windsor.) Mr. Kempczynski also entered many local juried art shows that he learned about through the handful of artists' guilds and associations to which he belonged. He showed in more than 20 exhibitions during the 70's and twice that during the 80's. He walked off with nearly a dozen awards for oils and watercolors.</p>
        <p>In the winter of 1980-81, Mr. Kempczynski created his first monotype while house-sitting in Spain. ''I bought a brayer, some rice paper, some paint and started experimenting,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kempczynski painted his subject -- backward -- directly on the glass. Next he placed the paper on the freshly painted glass and impressed the image to the paper with his brayer. It is a technique similar to silk screening.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Kempczynski returned to Hartford, he met his soon-to-be wife, Genevieve Rela, an educator born and raised in France. The couple started their tradition of summering in the south of France, where Ms. Rela's family still lives.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kempczynski finally landed his first show in New York, at Westwood Gallery. He had met Mr. Cavello and Ms. Almeida through a mutual friend who liked Mr. Kemp czynski's work enough to show him in early 1998.</p>
        <p>But when Mr. Kempczynski arose at 4 a.m. on Dec. 27, 1997, to finish up some pieces slated for the show, he smelled smoke in his studio. He quickly awakened his family and helped take them to safety on the sidewalk below. By the time he returned to the building, the fire, which started with a faulty light fixture in the second-floor law office, had consumed the entire main studio above. And by the time the firefighters left the scene, Mr. Kempczynski had lost 121 works, including three seven-foot-square oils-on-canvas headed for the Westwood Gallery. Mr. Kempczynski was devastated.</p>
        <p>''I didn't feel like painting anymore,'' said Mr. Kempczynski, who had no homeowner's insurance at the time. ''I figured, what's the use?''</p>
        <p>With the help of his family, Mr. Cavello and Ms. Almeida, Mr. Kemp czynski rebounded in time for his exhibition. The gallery borrowed five monotypes from corporate clients who had purchased their works from Mr. Kempczynski. He salvaged six others from the ruins to enter into the show.</p>
        <p>In the four months following the fire, Mr. Kempczynski created more than 60 new pieces. Much of his inspiration came from ''the way everybody in the community supported me,'' Mr. Kempczynski said. ''I think I've grown as an artist since the fire.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Almeida agreed: ''Now that Chet is in midcareer, we feel he has a great sense of his work and where he wants to go. We feel that he has a long career still ahead of him.''</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
