<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Hands of a Master, Eventful Photographs</title>
    <meta content="20ART.$22" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Parrish Art Museum (Southampton, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Braff, Phyllis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leipzig, Arthur</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloom, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7D8163EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Hands of a Master, Eventful Photographs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phyllis Braff</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Braff, Phyllis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Phyllis Braff reviews retrospective of works by photojournalist Arthur Leipzig at Beacon Gallery, Bellport, Long Island, group art exhibition at Graphic Eye Gallery in Port Washington and works by Barbara Bloom at Parrish Art Museum in Southampton; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Arthur Leipzig  Beacon Gallery, 112 South Country Road, Bellport. To Oct. 1. (631) 286-6363.</p>
        <p>Selections from Mr. Leipzig's 1943 photo essay, ''Children's Games,'' are among the highlights of this overview of a six-decade career in photojournalism. These, and a number of other works, represent the photographer's frequently insightful interpretations of New York City, although the show also includes work based on world travels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Arthur Leipzig  Beacon Gallery, 112 South Country Road, Bellport. To Oct. 1. (631) 286-6363.</p>
        <p>Selections from Mr. Leipzig's 1943 photo essay, ''Children's Games,'' are among the highlights of this overview of a six-decade career in photojournalism. These, and a number of other works, represent the photographer's frequently insightful interpretations of New York City, although the show also includes work based on world travels.</p>
        <p>Many of the images, like ''Opening Night at the Opera'' and ''Brooklyn Bridge,'' have been widely circulated through books and periodicals, but a separate section of the gallery features first-time prints from favorite negatives that Mr. Leipzig has just turned to in his retirement years.</p>
        <p>Much of Mr. Leipzig's success comes from the way he often blends engaging personality captured off-guard, a story worth remembering and a dynamic composition. There is tremendous energy in ''V. E. Day, Times Square, 1945,'' but there is an equal amount of intensity in the tightly knit pile of student faces in ''Hebrew Class, Benker, Ethiopia, 1979.''</p>
        <p>The effective combination of dramatic pictorial design and content makes a particularly memorable impact in ''Chalk Games,'' a view from above of youngsters circling over their white linear markings placed in the center of a city road flanked by parked cars. Dating from the pre-television era, the image also documents once-typical childhood activities.</p>
        <p>Photographs that seem to celebrate soft technical effects within the context of their story provide another dimension and suggest that Mr. Leipzig has enjoyed the challenge of creating the nuances in light and tone required by illumination contrasts inside a theater, hazy rain covering the city, mist produced by New Jersey smokestacks and a blurring sandstorm in the Sudan.</p>
        <p>'Go Fish...'  Graphic Eye Gallery, 301 Main Street, Port Washington. To Sept. 3. (516) 883-9668.</p>
        <p>This group exhibition takes a fairly loose attitude toward its theme. Most of the participating artists have woven some reference to fish or water into their paintings, prints or drawings, while others, perhaps with tongue-in-cheek, seem to be suggesting that visitors fish for alternative content.</p>
        <p>Ann Pellaton's bold red, white and blue fish bursts beyond its borders with energy and has an iconic quality, somewhat in the tradition of potent fish symbols used in mythology or religion or as a marker for environmental issues.</p>
        <p>In contrast, it is the subtlety of Mary Anne Decarlo's three-part etching filled with undulating floating fragments that makes it a convincing metaphor for constant changes within the natural world.</p>
        <p>A multilayered, compressed abstraction by Barbara Fishman picks up this spirit, too, extending it with vibrant color.</p>
        <p>Marion Klein's ''Framed Catch of the Day'' is another high-impact, successful piece, although its recall of Marsden Hartley's style lessens its originality to some extent.</p>
        <p>All the possibilities conjured by imaginary, strange organic life on the ocean floor seem present in Toby Sullivan's lively, somewhat surreal watercolor, ''No Fish to Fry.''</p>
        <p>A very different kind of imagination contributes to Ellen Brous's fascinating mixed-media work, which uses collaged toe prints to invent clustered anthropomorphic black forms silhouetted against a cloud-filled backdrop.</p>
        <p>The odd configurations appear marvelously monumental in this context.</p>
        <p>A measure of technical experimentation runs throughout the gallery. Angela Milner's ''Fish Eye View,'' based on emulsion transfer photography, is a notable example.</p>
        <p>Barbara Bloom: 'The Gaze'  Parrish Art Museum, 25 Job's Lane, Southampton. To Sept. 17. (631) 283-2118.</p>
        <p>During the past two decades, Ms. Bloom's tense installation pieces have earned attention and respect internationally. They are usually notable for the sharpness and wit they bring to broad social questions. How people perceive things has been a principal concern, and ''The Gaze,'' now occupying a portion of the Parrish Art Museum, is widely regarded as a particularly accessible and effective example of this interest. Shown first at the Stedelijk Museum, Amsterdam, in 1986, it is on loan from the collection of the Art Gallery of Ontario.</p>
        <p>Demonstrating how the act of looking can be extremely complex, ''The Gaze'' sets up its theme by requiring the viewer to pull aside floor-to-ceiling gauzelike curtains in order to view each of the artist's 20 conventionally framed large photographs. Many subjects deal with famous images of nudity and intimacy.</p>
        <p>In both her content and approach, Ms. Bloom taps into aspects of contemporary mentality like voyeurism and game playing. She also reflects a current interest in exploring viewer participation and in re-examining things that were made at another time and for another purpose. Like a number of other artists, she sees rich possibilities in analyzing the museum visitation experience.</p>
        <p>''The Gaze'' interweaves themes concerning real and photographed behavior and themes concerning the uses of curtains, ranging from fabric tied back, revealing a seductive figure painted by Ingres, to the light protective covering over an Old Master drawing being raised by a visitor.</p>
        <p>The analysis of peeping builds surprising intensity, especially in a second section where Ms. Bloom's photographs recreate acts of chance sightings. These are generally through windows, sometimes in trains or cabins, which increases the sense of uneasy stealth.</p>
        <p>The characteristics of peeping are dramatized, too, by dark, mysterious periphery areas, plus black matting and framing.</p>
        <p>A lasting, deliberately unsettling question raised by both sections deals with the potential of a work to change according to the context in which it is placed by those who gaze.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
