<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GOING OUT</title>
    <meta content="20CALE$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE7DE143EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GOING OUT</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An opinionated guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Westchester and Putnam Counties this week. Items may be submitted by mail, at least three weeks in advance, to Westchester Cultural Calendar, North Salem, N.Y. 10560.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>ELMSFORD -- ''Sound of Music.'' Matinee and evening performances Wednesdays through Sundays. Through September. Tickets: $46 to $66, including dinner. Discounts available for students, people 62 and older and children at selected performances. Westchester Broadway Theater. (914) 592-2222.</p>
        <p>GARRISON -- Hudson Valley Shakespeare Festival presents ''The Taming of the Shrew.'' Today at 6 p.m., Wednesday and Thursday at 7 p.m., next Friday and Saturday at 8 p.m. and next Sunday at 6 p.m. Tickets: $19 to $30, with discounts available for students, people 65 and older and children, except Saturday evening. Picnicking encouraged before show. Picnic dinners available by reservation. Cost: $16 and $18. Boscobel Restoration, 1601 Route 9D. (845) 265-9575.</p>
        <p>GARRISON -- One-act festival features ''White Inferno'' by Catherine Gonick, ''Thirty Odd Years'' by Ric Siler and ''Monkey See, Monkey Voodoo'' by Bruce Pearl. Today at 5 p.m., Thursday through next Saturday at 8 p.m. and next Sunday at 5 p.m. Philipstown Depot Theater. (845) 265-2797.</p>
        <p>HARTSDALE -- ''Secret Life of Walter Mitty,'' musical performed by Hartsdale Players. Today at 4 p.m. Tickets: $15; students, people 62 and older and children, $12. St. Paul's Methodist Church, 130 North Central Avenue.  (914) 961-2055.</p>
        <p>MONTROSE -- Workshop performance of five short original plays by local playwrights: ''Go to Sleep'' by Jeremy Feig, ''To Be Announced'' by Harlan Baker, ''A City Fairy Tale'' by Jim Whelan, ''Last Confession'' by Bonnie Pompili and ''The Yak Yak Club'' by Kathryn Cloonan. Presented by Hand to Mouth Players. Next Friday and Saturday at 8 p.m. and next Sunday at 2 p.m. Tickets: $10; people 62 and older and children, $8. Theater of Building 2, Veterans Affairs Hospital, Route 9A. (914) 734-8486.</p>
        <p>Music and Dance</p>
        <p>BRONXVILLE -- Bob Thoesan Big Band. Presented by Eastchester Arts Council. Thursday at 7 p.m. Free. Morange Memorial Park.</p>
        <p>CROTON-ON-HUDSON -- Bayou music festival with Little Feat, Shannon Curfman, Original P with founding members of Parliament Funkadelic, Tab Benoit, Lil' Brian and the Zydeco Travelers, Popa Chubby, Ray Schinnery, Toots and the Shades and Ron Levy's Wild Kingdom. Today from noon to sundown. Tickets: $35. Croton Point Park. (914) 699-5038.</p>
        <p>ELMSFORD -- The Duprees in concert with guest comedian Teddy Bergeron. Tuesday at 8 p.m., with dinner at 6. Tickets: $55. Westchester Broadway Theater. (914) 592-2222.</p>
        <p>FORDHAM -- ''Viva Italia!'' Bronx Arts Ensemble and Joseph Addeo, tenor, perform Neapolitan songs and Italian opera favorites.  Today at 4 p.m. Free. McGinley Center, Fordham University at Bronx Rose Hill Campus.  (718) 601-7399.</p>
        <p>GOLDENS BRIDGE -- Folk dancing led by Betsy Glass. Friday at 8:30 p.m. Admission: $6. Goldens Bridge Community Center Barn, Hall Avenue. (914) 232-1862.</p>
        <p>KATONAH -- Felix Swing Band. Wednesday at 6:30 p.m. Picnicking encouraged. Free. Rain or shine. Garden of Katonah Museum of Art, Route 22 at Jay Street. (914) 232-9555.</p>
        <p>MOUNT VERNON -- Contemporary jazz flutist, Sherry Winston, and her quartet. Presented by Jazz Forum Arts and Mount Vernon Recreation Department. Tuesday at 7:30 to 9 p.m.  Free. Hartley Park, Gramatan and East Lincoln Avenues. (Rain location, Allen Memorial Church, 132 Crary Avenue.) (914) 631-1000.</p>
        <p>PAWLING -- Diane Ponzio, with guest artist, Dave's True Story. Tonight at 8. Tickets: $15; members, $12.50. Gandalf Murphy and the Slambovian Circus of Dreams and Jack Hardy. Friday at 9 p.m. Tickets: $17.50; members, $15. Holmes Brothers. Next Saturday at 9 p.m. Tickets: $20; members, $17.50. Towne Crier Cafe, 130 Route 22. (845) 855-1300.</p>
        <p>RIVERDALE -- ''Viva Italia!'' Bronx Arts Ensemble and Joseph Addeo, tenor, perform Neapolitan songs and Italian opera favorites.  Today at 2 p.m. Free. Rockwood Drive Circle, Van Cortlandt Park. (718) 601-7399.</p>
        <p>RIVERDALE -- Take part in a dance workshop, learn about summer bulbs, hear the sitar music of Bina Khan or relax in the gardens. Wednesday from 6 to 7:30 p.m. Free with grounds admission: $4; students and people 60 and older, $2; children 5 and younger, free. Wave Hill, West 249th Street and Independence Avenue. (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>SCARSDALE -- Summer sing of Brahms's ''German Requiem'' with Theora Cultice, pianist; Daniel Paget, conductor. Presented by Westchester Chorale. Tuesday at 8 p.m. Admission: $8, including score and refreshments. Scarsdale Public Library. (914) 693-0990.</p>
        <p>SCARSDALE -- Auditions to join New Choral Society of Central Westchester; John T. King, conductor. Rehearsals on Monday evenings.  This season's program includes portions of Handel's ''Messiah,'' Gounod's ''St. Cecilia Mass'' and American choral music. Wednesday through Sept. 6, by appointment. Hitchcock Presbyterian Church, 6 Greenacres Avenue. (914) 725-1678.</p>
        <p>SLEEPY HOLLOW -- Tenor saxophonist, Houston Person, and vocalist, Etta Jones, and their quintet perform jazz, swing and rhythm and blues. Thursday from 6:30 to 8 p.m. Free. Kingsland Point Park. (914) 631-1000.</p>
        <p>SOMERS -- Acoustic folk concert by Gene Tullio, guitarist and singer, with guest harmonicist, Marty Stole. Friday from 8 to 9:30 p.m.  Free. Coffee 'n, Heritage Hills Shopping Center, Route 202. (914) 276-2233.</p>
        <p>TARRYTOWN -- ''Tap Kids,'' performance showcasing outstanding young tap dancers.  Presented by New York Stage Originals. Next Sunday at 2 p.m. Tickets: $15. (With master class led by Gil Stroming, former member of Tap Dogs. Next Saturday at 2 p.m. Cost: $10.)  Music Hall, 13 Main Street. (914) 332-5757.</p>
        <p>TARRYTOWN -- Sunnyside jazz festival, featuring 20 hours of jazz. Next Saturday and Sunday, beginning at 11 a.m. with jazz history workshop led by trumpeter, Bob Arthurs, and the Music Conservatory of Westchester Jazz Ensemble. Both days close with a jam session with trumpeter and flugelhornist, Mark Morganelli, and others from 6 to 7:30 p.m. Presented by Jazz Forum Arts and Historic Hudson Valley. Next Saturday: alto saxophonist, Sonny Fortune, at noon and 3 p.m., Kenny Barron and his Brazilian jazz group at 1 and 4 p.m., contemporary jazz guitarist, Gil Parris, at 2 and 5 p.m. Next Sunday: drummer, Chico Hamilton, and Euphoria at noon and 3 p.m., tenor saxophonist, Jimmy Heath, and his quartet at 1 and 4 p.m. and Hugh Masekela and his eight-piece group at 2 and 5 p.m. Tickets: $20 each day, including tour of Washington Irving's cottage; children 6 through 17, $10; younger children, free. Both days: $35; children 6 through 17, $15. Reservations. Sunnyside, off Route 9. (914) 631-1000.</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>ELMSFORD -- ''Nature Around Us,'' oil, gouache and pencil drawings by Magda E. Nemlich. Through August. Greenburgh Town Hall, Tarrytown Road and Hartsdale Avenue. (914) 422-1038.</p>
        <p>HARRISON -- Art by Lawrence Flanagan.  Through Friday. Monoprints by Cary Thorp Brown. Opens next Saturday. Through Sept. 23. Harrison Public Library, Bruce Avenue. (914) 835-0324.</p>
        <p>MOUNT KISCO -- ''Inhouse and Outhouse,'' pastels, watercolors, oils, acrylics and works in other media by faculty members. Through Sept. 23. Northern Westchester Center for the Arts, 272 North Bedford Road. (914) 241-6922.</p>
        <p>NORTH SALEM -- Photographic portraits of renowned artists by Carl Van Vechten and John Gruen. Through Sept. 15. ''Modern Prints -- Ancient Fans,'' 100 international printmakers' prints from woodcuts, lithographs and etchings, assembled into traditional folding fans in Japan. Through October.  Museum's hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays from noon to 4 p.m. Admission: $4; people 62 and older, $3; children, free. (Lunch available by reservation. (914) 669-6777.) Hammond Museum and Japanese Stroll Garden, top of Deveau Road, off June Road. (914) 669-5033.</p>
        <p>PURCHASE -- PepsiCo sculpture garden featuring works by Alexander Calder, David Wynne, Joan Miro, Art Price and other sculptors, set among fountains, manicured lawns, flowers and wooded areas. Daily from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free. PepsiCo World Headquarters, Anderson Hill Road. (914) 253-2000.</p>
        <p>SHRUB OAK -- ''Scenes of Summer,'' photography by Charles Francis Vigliotti. Through August. John C. Hart Memorial Library, 1130 Main Street. (914) 245-5262.</p>
        <p>SPRING VALLEY -- Barbara Yaeger photos. Through August. Finkelstein Memorial Library, 24 Chestnut Street. (845) 352-5700.</p>
        <p>VALHALLA -- ''Summer Pallette,'' art works by Stephanie Brauer, Betty Barnthouse Chateauvert, Christine Shannon Aaron, Mary LaGreca, Stanley Gluck and others. Through Sept. 1. Gallery of Macy Pavilion, Westchester Medical Center. (914) 493-8397.</p>
        <p>WHITE PLAINS -- ''Westchester in the Movies,'' exhibition of photographs and posters about the films of D. W. Griffith and more recent films with Westchester locations, like ''Goodbye Columbus,'' ''Age of Innocence'' and ''Ragtime.'' Through Labor Day. Museum gallery of White Plains Public Library, 100 Martine Avenue. (914) 422-1480.</p>
        <p>YONKERS -- ''Open Air Sketching: 19th-Century American Landscape Drawings in the Albany Institute of History and Art.'' Closes today. ''Fun City: Celebrating the Life of Ralph Fasanella.'' Through Sept. 10. Continuing: ''Boats on the Hudson: Navigating Through History'' and viewing of the renovated Glenview Mansion. Admission: $4; people 62 and older and children, $3. ''Ralph Fasanella's America,'' Paul Dambrosia of the Fenimore Museum discusses the folk artist's life and leads a tour of the artist's paintings of American politics and culture on exhibit. Program especially for people 62 and older. Wednesday at 1:30 p.m. Cost: $1.50 with museum admission. Hudson River Museum, 511 Warburton Avenue. (914) 963-4550.</p>
        <p>YONKERS -- ''A Midsummer Night's Dream,'' two exhibitions presented by Yonkers Public Library and Art on Main Street.  Art works by Sheila Benedis, Eleanor Goldstein and Catherine L. Wells at Will Library, 1500 Central Park Avenue. Works by Vivian Bergenthal, Gregory Paul Henne, Cheryl Jelonek Kawalerski and Terry Kessler Schwarz at Getty Square Branch, 7 Main Street. Both through August. (914) 337-1500.</p>
        <p>Lectures</p>
        <p>MOUNT VERNON -- Story of the founding of the village of Mount Vernon in the 1850's as one of the first railroad suburbs in America.  Thursday at 11 a.m. Free. St. Paul's Church National Historic Site, 897 South Columbus Avenue. (914) 667-4116.</p>
        <p>Films</p>
        <p>PEEKSKILL -- ''Beau Travail,'' French film with subtitles. Thursday through next Saturday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $9. Paramount Center, 1008 Brown Street. (914) 739-2333.</p>
        <p>Children</p>
        <p>FORDHAM -- Bronx Zoo. Open daily from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. 365 days a year. Admission: $9; people 65 and older and children 2 through 12, $5. Free on Wednesdays. Parking: $6. Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road. (718) 367-1010.</p>
        <p>KATONAH -- Drop-in activities for children 4 and older with accompanying adult: story hour. Saturdays at 10:30 a.m. Free with museum admission: $3; members and children, free. See and do art activities. Saturdays at 1 p.m. and Sundays at 1:30 p.m. Cost: $1 and museum admission. Katonah Museum of Art, Route 22 at Jay Street. (914) 232-9555.</p>
        <p>MOUNT VERNON -- Demonstration of caring for the wounded during the Civil War. Program with special children's activities.  Wednesday from 12:15 to 1 p.m. Church bell tower tour. Friday at 3 p.m. Free. St. Paul's Church National Historic Site, 897 South Columbus Avenue. (914) 667-4116.</p>
        <p>NEW ROCHELLE -- Children's film ''Stuart Little.'' Tomorrow at 10:30 a.m. and 2:30 and 7 p.m. Free tickets available to New Rochelle residents in children's room of library. Bokandeye African-American Dance Theater. Show for children 6 and older and adults. Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. Free. New Rochelle Public Library, Library Plaza. (914) 632-7878.</p>
        <p>PLEASANTVILLE -- Auditions for boys 6 through 14 to join the Boys' Choir of Westchester; David Graf, music director. Weekly rehearsals of secular and sacred music. For further information, call (914) 666-5719.</p>
        <p>RIVERDALE -- ''Walk on the Wild Side,'' family members walk in the meadows and woods and sketch wildflowers, then extend these notes into colorful paintings. Next Saturday and Sunday from 1 to 4 p.m. Free with grounds admission: $4; students and people 60 and older, $2; children 5 and younger, free.  (Free admission Saturdays from 9 a.m. to noon.) Wave Hill, West 249th Street and Independence Avenue. (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>RYE -- Fireworks. Wednesdays and Fridays at 9:15 p.m. Through Sept. 1. Parking: $4.  Playland Park. (914) 925-2700.</p>
        <p>SCARSDALE -- ''Meet Your Favorite Reptile,'' program featuring live turtles, snakes and other reptiles by Bruce Lowder. Presented by Sierra Club, Lower Hudson Group. Tomorrow at 8 p.m. Free. Scarsdale Library, Olmsted Road. (914) 234-7533.</p>
        <p>SOMERS -- ''Vegetable Medley,'' an afternoon of vegetable cooking and other activities. Today from noon to 3 p.m. Free. Muscoot Farm, Route 35. (914) 232-9555.</p>
        <p>YONKERS -- Campfire singing, river stories and watching the sunset. Tonight at 7. Free.  Bring instruments. Beczak Environmental Education Center's beach, 21 Alexander Street. (914) 376-0859.</p>
        <p>YONKERS -- Children's films. Tomorrow at 2 p.m. Free. Getty Square Branch of Yonkers Public Library, 7 Main Street. (914) 337-1500.</p>
        <p>YONKERS -- Pajama time stories and songs, for children in pajamas carrying Teddy bears. Wednesdays at 6:30 p.m. Through August. Will Library, 1500 Central Park Avenue. (914) 337-1500.</p>
        <p>YONKERS -- Christopher Letts and Tom Lake present their catch of the day, blue crabs from the Hudson River. Today at 1:30 p.m. Cost: $1 and museum admission, additional $4; people 62 and older and children, $3. Sky shows: ''Sky Tonight.'' Saturdays and Sundays at 1:30 p.m. ''Rusty Rocket's Last Blast.'' Saturdays and Sundays at 2:30 p.m. ''Daughter of the Stars.''  Today at 3:30 p.m. ''Start of It All.'' Next Saturday and Sunday at 3 p.m. Admission: $4 each; people 62 and older and children, $3. Admission to galleries and one sky show: $7; people 62 and older and children, $5. ''Sky Tonight,'' planetarium show for children 8 and older and adults. Fridays at 7 p.m. Free tickets at front desk, beginning at 6:30. Hudson River Museum, 511 Warburton Avenue. (914) 963-4550, 24-hour recorded planetarium message (914) 963-2139.</p>
        <p>Potpourri</p>
        <p>COLD SPRING -- Exhibition illustrating the story of the West Point Foundry, with John Ferguson Weir's painting ''The Gun Foundry'' and articles produced at the foundry. Also Hudson River School paintings, regional 19th-century furnishings and museum store. Tuesdays and Wednesdays from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m., Thursdays from 1 to 4 p.m. and Saturdays and Sundays from 2 to 5 p.m. 63 Chestnut Street.  (845) 265-4010.</p>
        <p>GARRISON -- Outdoor fine arts and crafts fair, with craft demonstrations and refreshments.  Today from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Rain or shine.  Tented lawn of Garrison Arts Center, short walk from train station. (845) 424-3960.</p>
        <p>GARRISON -- Book sale. Today from noon to 3, next Saturday from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. and next Sunday from noon to 3 p.m. Desmond Fish Library, Routes 9D and 403. (845) 424-3020.</p>
        <p>GARRISON -- Guided tours of Boscobel Restoration, the 19th-century Federal-style home of States Morris Dyckman, a Loyalist during the American Revolution. Original Dyckman possessions, including silver, glassware and Wedgwood dishes bought in London. Daily, except Tuesdays from 9:30 a.m. to 5 p.m., with last tour beginning at 4:15 p.m. Admission: $8, people 60 and older, $7; children 6 through 14, $5; younger children, free. Grounds only pass: $5; children 6 through 14, $3. 1601 Route 9D. (845) 265-3638.</p>
        <p>GARRISON -- Self-guided hikes of Manitoga, featuring two and a half miles of trails designed for clambering among boulders, resting by Lost Pond or dangling one's feet in cool creeks. Weekdays from 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. and Saturdays and Sundays from 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.  Donation: $4; children, $2. Route 9D, two miles south of Route 403. (845) 424-3812.</p>
        <p>GREENBURGH -- Tour the herb garden and learn of the different kinds of culinary and medicinal herbs that can be grown locally.  Followed by participants helping to prepare pizza, salad and iced tea flavored with mint.  Today at 2 p.m. Cost: $4; members, $2. Greenburgh Nature Center, Dromore Road.  (914) 723-3470.</p>
        <p>MOUNT VERNON -- Tour and talk about the lives of some of the more than 50 Union Army veterans buried at St. Paul's. Tuesday from 10:30 to 11:15 a.m. Free. St. Paul's Church National Historic Site, 897 South Columbus Avenue. (914) 667-4116.</p>
        <p>NEW CITY -- ''Leaving Her Mark: Contributions of Rockland's Women,'' exhibition highlighting the contributions of diversely talented Rockland women from the 18th through 21st centuries; from suffrage to medicine, law and politics. Tuesdays through Sundays from 1 to 5 p.m. (Closed next Sunday through Sept. 4.)  Through Sept. 13. Donation: $4, including guided tours of Jacob Blauvelt House on Sundays; children, $3. Historical Society of Rockland County, 20 Zukor Road. (845) 634-9645.</p>
        <p>NEW ROCHELLE -- Screenings for glaucoma, cataracts and other eye disorders by Dr. Bradley Scharf. Wednesday from 10 a.m. to noon. Free. New Rochelle Public Library, Library Plaza. (914) 632-7878.</p>
        <p>SOMERS -- Art and crafts fair. Next Saturday and Sunday from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $4. Lasdon Park, Route 35. (914) 242-7275.</p>
        <p>VALHALLA -- Hispanic heritage celebration.  Today from 1 to 8 p.m. Free admission. Kensico Dam Plaza, north end of Bronx River Parkway. (914) 242-7275.</p>
        <p>WHITE PLAINS -- Amish quilt and craft sale, featuring 250 quilts (for twin, full, queen and king beds), 500 smaller quilts for wall hangings; pillows, dolls, toys, furniture, rugs, books and more. Next Saturday from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free admission. County Center, Bronx River Parkway and Central Avenue.  (914) 285-4050.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An opinionated guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Westchester and Putnam Counties this week. Items may be submitted by mail, at least three weeks in advance, to Westchester Cultural Calendar, North Salem, N.Y. 10560.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>ELMSFORD -- ''Sound of Music.'' Matinee and evening performances Wednesdays through Sundays. Through September. Tickets: $46 to $66, including dinner. Discounts available for students, people 62 and older and children at selected performances. Westchester Broadway Theater. (914) 592-2222.</p>
        <p>GARRISON -- Hudson Valley Shakespeare Festival presents ''The Taming of the Shrew.'' Today at 6 p.m., Wednesday and Thursday at 7 p.m., next Friday and Saturday at 8 p.m. and next Sunday at 6 p.m. Tickets: $19 to $30, with discounts available for students, people 65 and older and children, except Saturday evening. Picnicking encouraged before show. Picnic dinners available by reservation. Cost: $16 and $18. Boscobel Restoration, 1601 Route 9D. (845) 265-9575.</p>
        <p>GARRISON -- One-act festival features ''White Inferno'' by Catherine Gonick, ''Thirty Odd Years'' by Ric Siler and ''Monkey See, Monkey Voodoo'' by Bruce Pearl. Today at 5 p.m., Thursday through next Saturday at 8 p.m. and next Sunday at 5 p.m. Philipstown Depot Theater. (845) 265-2797.</p>
        <p>HARTSDALE -- ''Secret Life of Walter Mitty,'' musical performed by Hartsdale Players. Today at 4 p.m. Tickets: $15; students, people 62 and older and children, $12. St. Paul's Methodist Church, 130 North Central Avenue.  (914) 961-2055.</p>
        <p>MONTROSE -- Workshop performance of five short original plays by local playwrights: ''Go to Sleep'' by Jeremy Feig, ''To Be Announced'' by Harlan Baker, ''A City Fairy Tale'' by Jim Whelan, ''Last Confession'' by Bonnie Pompili and ''The Yak Yak Club'' by Kathryn Cloonan. Presented by Hand to Mouth Players. Next Friday and Saturday at 8 p.m. and next Sunday at 2 p.m. Tickets: $10; people 62 and older and children, $8. Theater of Building 2, Veterans Affairs Hospital, Route 9A. (914) 734-8486.</p>
        <p>Music and Dance</p>
        <p>BRONXVILLE -- Bob Thoesan Big Band. Presented by Eastchester Arts Council. Thursday at 7 p.m. Free. Morange Memorial Park.</p>
        <p>CROTON-ON-HUDSON -- Bayou music festival with Little Feat, Shannon Curfman, Original P with founding members of Parliament Funkadelic, Tab Benoit, Lil' Brian and the Zydeco Travelers, Popa Chubby, Ray Schinnery, Toots and the Shades and Ron Levy's Wild Kingdom. Today from noon to sundown. Tickets: $35. Croton Point Park. (914) 699-5038.</p>
        <p>ELMSFORD -- The Duprees in concert with guest comedian Teddy Bergeron. Tuesday at 8 p.m., with dinner at 6. Tickets: $55. Westchester Broadway Theater. (914) 592-2222.</p>
        <p>FORDHAM -- ''Viva Italia!'' Bronx Arts Ensemble and Joseph Addeo, tenor, perform Neapolitan songs and Italian opera favorites.  Today at 4 p.m. Free. McGinley Center, Fordham University at Bronx Rose Hill Campus.  (718) 601-7399.</p>
        <p>GOLDENS BRIDGE -- Folk dancing led by Betsy Glass. Friday at 8:30 p.m. Admission: $6. Goldens Bridge Community Center Barn, Hall Avenue. (914) 232-1862.</p>
        <p>KATONAH -- Felix Swing Band. Wednesday at 6:30 p.m. Picnicking encouraged. Free. Rain or shine. Garden of Katonah Museum of Art, Route 22 at Jay Street. (914) 232-9555.</p>
        <p>MOUNT VERNON -- Contemporary jazz flutist, Sherry Winston, and her quartet. Presented by Jazz Forum Arts and Mount Vernon Recreation Department. Tuesday at 7:30 to 9 p.m.  Free. Hartley Park, Gramatan and East Lincoln Avenues. (Rain location, Allen Memorial Church, 132 Crary Avenue.) (914) 631-1000.</p>
        <p>PAWLING -- Diane Ponzio, with guest artist, Dave's True Story. Tonight at 8. Tickets: $15; members, $12.50. Gandalf Murphy and the Slambovian Circus of Dreams and Jack Hardy. Friday at 9 p.m. Tickets: $17.50; members, $15. Holmes Brothers. Next Saturday at 9 p.m. Tickets: $20; members, $17.50. Towne Crier Cafe, 130 Route 22. (845) 855-1300.</p>
        <p>RIVERDALE -- ''Viva Italia!'' Bronx Arts Ensemble and Joseph Addeo, tenor, perform Neapolitan songs and Italian opera favorites.  Today at 2 p.m. Free. Rockwood Drive Circle, Van Cortlandt Park. (718) 601-7399.</p>
        <p>RIVERDALE -- Take part in a dance workshop, learn about summer bulbs, hear the sitar music of Bina Khan or relax in the gardens. Wednesday from 6 to 7:30 p.m. Free with grounds admission: $4; students and people 60 and older, $2; children 5 and younger, free. Wave Hill, West 249th Street and Independence Avenue. (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>SCARSDALE -- Summer sing of Brahms's ''German Requiem'' with Theora Cultice, pianist; Daniel Paget, conductor. Presented by Westchester Chorale. Tuesday at 8 p.m. Admission: $8, including score and refreshments. Scarsdale Public Library. (914) 693-0990.</p>
        <p>SCARSDALE -- Auditions to join New Choral Society of Central Westchester; John T. King, conductor. Rehearsals on Monday evenings.  This season's program includes portions of Handel's ''Messiah,'' Gounod's ''St. Cecilia Mass'' and American choral music. Wednesday through Sept. 6, by appointment. Hitchcock Presbyterian Church, 6 Greenacres Avenue. (914) 725-1678.</p>
        <p>SLEEPY HOLLOW -- Tenor saxophonist, Houston Person, and vocalist, Etta Jones, and their quintet perform jazz, swing and rhythm and blues. Thursday from 6:30 to 8 p.m. Free. Kingsland Point Park. (914) 631-1000.</p>
        <p>SOMERS -- Acoustic folk concert by Gene Tullio, guitarist and singer, with guest harmonicist, Marty Stole. Friday from 8 to 9:30 p.m.  Free. Coffee 'n, Heritage Hills Shopping Center, Route 202. (914) 276-2233.</p>
        <p>TARRYTOWN -- ''Tap Kids,'' performance showcasing outstanding young tap dancers.  Presented by New York Stage Originals. Next Sunday at 2 p.m. Tickets: $15. (With master class led by Gil Stroming, former member of Tap Dogs. Next Saturday at 2 p.m. Cost: $10.)  Music Hall, 13 Main Street. (914) 332-5757.</p>
        <p>TARRYTOWN -- Sunnyside jazz festival, featuring 20 hours of jazz. Next Saturday and Sunday, beginning at 11 a.m. with jazz history workshop led by trumpeter, Bob Arthurs, and the Music Conservatory of Westchester Jazz Ensemble. Both days close with a jam session with trumpeter and flugelhornist, Mark Morganelli, and others from 6 to 7:30 p.m. Presented by Jazz Forum Arts and Historic Hudson Valley. Next Saturday: alto saxophonist, Sonny Fortune, at noon and 3 p.m., Kenny Barron and his Brazilian jazz group at 1 and 4 p.m., contemporary jazz guitarist, Gil Parris, at 2 and 5 p.m. Next Sunday: drummer, Chico Hamilton, and Euphoria at noon and 3 p.m., tenor saxophonist, Jimmy Heath, and his quartet at 1 and 4 p.m. and Hugh Masekela and his eight-piece group at 2 and 5 p.m. Tickets: $20 each day, including tour of Washington Irving's cottage; children 6 through 17, $10; younger children, free. Both days: $35; children 6 through 17, $15. Reservations. Sunnyside, off Route 9. (914) 631-1000.</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>ELMSFORD -- ''Nature Around Us,'' oil, gouache and pencil drawings by Magda E. Nemlich. Through August. Greenburgh Town Hall, Tarrytown Road and Hartsdale Avenue. (914) 422-1038.</p>
        <p>HARRISON -- Art by Lawrence Flanagan.  Through Friday. Monoprints by Cary Thorp Brown. Opens next Saturday. Through Sept. 23. Harrison Public Library, Bruce Avenue. (914) 835-0324.</p>
        <p>MOUNT KISCO -- ''Inhouse and Outhouse,'' pastels, watercolors, oils, acrylics and works in other media by faculty members. Through Sept. 23. Northern Westchester Center for the Arts, 272 North Bedford Road. (914) 241-6922.</p>
        <p>NORTH SALEM -- Photographic portraits of renowned artists by Carl Van Vechten and John Gruen. Through Sept. 15. ''Modern Prints -- Ancient Fans,'' 100 international printmakers' prints from woodcuts, lithographs and etchings, assembled into traditional folding fans in Japan. Through October.  Museum's hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays from noon to 4 p.m. Admission: $4; people 62 and older, $3; children, free. (Lunch available by reservation. (914) 669-6777.) Hammond Museum and Japanese Stroll Garden, top of Deveau Road, off June Road. (914) 669-5033.</p>
        <p>PURCHASE -- PepsiCo sculpture garden featuring works by Alexander Calder, David Wynne, Joan Miro, Art Price and other sculptors, set among fountains, manicured lawns, flowers and wooded areas. Daily from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free. PepsiCo World Headquarters, Anderson Hill Road. (914) 253-2000.</p>
        <p>SHRUB OAK -- ''Scenes of Summer,'' photography by Charles Francis Vigliotti. Through August. John C. Hart Memorial Library, 1130 Main Street. (914) 245-5262.</p>
        <p>SPRING VALLEY -- Barbara Yaeger photos. Through August. Finkelstein Memorial Library, 24 Chestnut Street. (845) 352-5700.</p>
        <p>VALHALLA -- ''Summer Pallette,'' art works by Stephanie Brauer, Betty Barnthouse Chateauvert, Christine Shannon Aaron, Mary LaGreca, Stanley Gluck and others. Through Sept. 1. Gallery of Macy Pavilion, Westchester Medical Center. (914) 493-8397.</p>
        <p>WHITE PLAINS -- ''Westchester in the Movies,'' exhibition of photographs and posters about the films of D. W. Griffith and more recent films with Westchester locations, like ''Goodbye Columbus,'' ''Age of Innocence'' and ''Ragtime.'' Through Labor Day. Museum gallery of White Plains Public Library, 100 Martine Avenue. (914) 422-1480.</p>
        <p>YONKERS -- ''Open Air Sketching: 19th-Century American Landscape Drawings in the Albany Institute of History and Art.'' Closes today. ''Fun City: Celebrating the Life of Ralph Fasanella.'' Through Sept. 10. Continuing: ''Boats on the Hudson: Navigating Through History'' and viewing of the renovated Glenview Mansion. Admission: $4; people 62 and older and children, $3. ''Ralph Fasanella's America,'' Paul Dambrosia of the Fenimore Museum discusses the folk artist's life and leads a tour of the artist's paintings of American politics and culture on exhibit. Program especially for people 62 and older. Wednesday at 1:30 p.m. Cost: $1.50 with museum admission. Hudson River Museum, 511 Warburton Avenue. (914) 963-4550.</p>
        <p>YONKERS -- ''A Midsummer Night's Dream,'' two exhibitions presented by Yonkers Public Library and Art on Main Street.  Art works by Sheila Benedis, Eleanor Goldstein and Catherine L. Wells at Will Library, 1500 Central Park Avenue. Works by Vivian Bergenthal, Gregory Paul Henne, Cheryl Jelonek Kawalerski and Terry Kessler Schwarz at Getty Square Branch, 7 Main Street. Both through August. (914) 337-1500.</p>
        <p>Lectures</p>
        <p>MOUNT VERNON -- Story of the founding of the village of Mount Vernon in the 1850's as one of the first railroad suburbs in America.  Thursday at 11 a.m. Free. St. Paul's Church National Historic Site, 897 South Columbus Avenue. (914) 667-4116.</p>
        <p>Films</p>
        <p>PEEKSKILL -- ''Beau Travail,'' French film with subtitles. Thursday through next Saturday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $9. Paramount Center, 1008 Brown Street. (914) 739-2333.</p>
        <p>Children</p>
        <p>FORDHAM -- Bronx Zoo. Open daily from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. 365 days a year. Admission: $9; people 65 and older and children 2 through 12, $5. Free on Wednesdays. Parking: $6. Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road. (718) 367-1010.</p>
        <p>KATONAH -- Drop-in activities for children 4 and older with accompanying adult: story hour. Saturdays at 10:30 a.m. Free with museum admission: $3; members and children, free. See and do art activities. Saturdays at 1 p.m. and Sundays at 1:30 p.m. Cost: $1 and museum admission. Katonah Museum of Art, Route 22 at Jay Street. (914) 232-9555.</p>
        <p>MOUNT VERNON -- Demonstration of caring for the wounded during the Civil War. Program with special children's activities.  Wednesday from 12:15 to 1 p.m. Church bell tower tour. Friday at 3 p.m. Free. St. Paul's Church National Historic Site, 897 South Columbus Avenue. (914) 667-4116.</p>
        <p>NEW ROCHELLE -- Children's film ''Stuart Little.'' Tomorrow at 10:30 a.m. and 2:30 and 7 p.m. Free tickets available to New Rochelle residents in children's room of library. Bokandeye African-American Dance Theater. Show for children 6 and older and adults. Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. Free. New Rochelle Public Library, Library Plaza. (914) 632-7878.</p>
        <p>PLEASANTVILLE -- Auditions for boys 6 through 14 to join the Boys' Choir of Westchester; David Graf, music director. Weekly rehearsals of secular and sacred music. For further information, call (914) 666-5719.</p>
        <p>RIVERDALE -- ''Walk on the Wild Side,'' family members walk in the meadows and woods and sketch wildflowers, then extend these notes into colorful paintings. Next Saturday and Sunday from 1 to 4 p.m. Free with grounds admission: $4; students and people 60 and older, $2; children 5 and younger, free.  (Free admission Saturdays from 9 a.m. to noon.) Wave Hill, West 249th Street and Independence Avenue. (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>RYE -- Fireworks. Wednesdays and Fridays at 9:15 p.m. Through Sept. 1. Parking: $4.  Playland Park. (914) 925-2700.</p>
        <p>SCARSDALE -- ''Meet Your Favorite Reptile,'' program featuring live turtles, snakes and other reptiles by Bruce Lowder. Presented by Sierra Club, Lower Hudson Group. Tomorrow at 8 p.m. Free. Scarsdale Library, Olmsted Road. (914) 234-7533.</p>
        <p>SOMERS -- ''Vegetable Medley,'' an afternoon of vegetable cooking and other activities. Today from noon to 3 p.m. Free. Muscoot Farm, Route 35. (914) 232-9555.</p>
        <p>YONKERS -- Campfire singing, river stories and watching the sunset. Tonight at 7. Free.  Bring instruments. Beczak Environmental Education Center's beach, 21 Alexander Street. (914) 376-0859.</p>
        <p>YONKERS -- Children's films. Tomorrow at 2 p.m. Free. Getty Square Branch of Yonkers Public Library, 7 Main Street. (914) 337-1500.</p>
        <p>YONKERS -- Pajama time stories and songs, for children in pajamas carrying Teddy bears. Wednesdays at 6:30 p.m. Through August. Will Library, 1500 Central Park Avenue. (914) 337-1500.</p>
        <p>YONKERS -- Christopher Letts and Tom Lake present their catch of the day, blue crabs from the Hudson River. Today at 1:30 p.m. Cost: $1 and museum admission, additional $4; people 62 and older and children, $3. Sky shows: ''Sky Tonight.'' Saturdays and Sundays at 1:30 p.m. ''Rusty Rocket's Last Blast.'' Saturdays and Sundays at 2:30 p.m. ''Daughter of the Stars.''  Today at 3:30 p.m. ''Start of It All.'' Next Saturday and Sunday at 3 p.m. Admission: $4 each; people 62 and older and children, $3. Admission to galleries and one sky show: $7; people 62 and older and children, $5. ''Sky Tonight,'' planetarium show for children 8 and older and adults. Fridays at 7 p.m. Free tickets at front desk, beginning at 6:30. Hudson River Museum, 511 Warburton Avenue. (914) 963-4550, 24-hour recorded planetarium message (914) 963-2139.</p>
        <p>Potpourri</p>
        <p>COLD SPRING -- Exhibition illustrating the story of the West Point Foundry, with John Ferguson Weir's painting ''The Gun Foundry'' and articles produced at the foundry. Also Hudson River School paintings, regional 19th-century furnishings and museum store. Tuesdays and Wednesdays from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m., Thursdays from 1 to 4 p.m. and Saturdays and Sundays from 2 to 5 p.m. 63 Chestnut Street.  (845) 265-4010.</p>
        <p>GARRISON -- Outdoor fine arts and crafts fair, with craft demonstrations and refreshments.  Today from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Rain or shine.  Tented lawn of Garrison Arts Center, short walk from train station. (845) 424-3960.</p>
        <p>GARRISON -- Book sale. Today from noon to 3, next Saturday from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. and next Sunday from noon to 3 p.m. Desmond Fish Library, Routes 9D and 403. (845) 424-3020.</p>
        <p>GARRISON -- Guided tours of Boscobel Restoration, the 19th-century Federal-style home of States Morris Dyckman, a Loyalist during the American Revolution. Original Dyckman possessions, including silver, glassware and Wedgwood dishes bought in London. Daily, except Tuesdays from 9:30 a.m. to 5 p.m., with last tour beginning at 4:15 p.m. Admission: $8, people 60 and older, $7; children 6 through 14, $5; younger children, free. Grounds only pass: $5; children 6 through 14, $3. 1601 Route 9D. (845) 265-3638.</p>
        <p>GARRISON -- Self-guided hikes of Manitoga, featuring two and a half miles of trails designed for clambering among boulders, resting by Lost Pond or dangling one's feet in cool creeks. Weekdays from 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. and Saturdays and Sundays from 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.  Donation: $4; children, $2. Route 9D, two miles south of Route 403. (845) 424-3812.</p>
        <p>GREENBURGH -- Tour the herb garden and learn of the different kinds of culinary and medicinal herbs that can be grown locally.  Followed by participants helping to prepare pizza, salad and iced tea flavored with mint.  Today at 2 p.m. Cost: $4; members, $2. Greenburgh Nature Center, Dromore Road.  (914) 723-3470.</p>
        <p>MOUNT VERNON -- Tour and talk about the lives of some of the more than 50 Union Army veterans buried at St. Paul's. Tuesday from 10:30 to 11:15 a.m. Free. St. Paul's Church National Historic Site, 897 South Columbus Avenue. (914) 667-4116.</p>
        <p>NEW CITY -- ''Leaving Her Mark: Contributions of Rockland's Women,'' exhibition highlighting the contributions of diversely talented Rockland women from the 18th through 21st centuries; from suffrage to medicine, law and politics. Tuesdays through Sundays from 1 to 5 p.m. (Closed next Sunday through Sept. 4.)  Through Sept. 13. Donation: $4, including guided tours of Jacob Blauvelt House on Sundays; children, $3. Historical Society of Rockland County, 20 Zukor Road. (845) 634-9645.</p>
        <p>NEW ROCHELLE -- Screenings for glaucoma, cataracts and other eye disorders by Dr. Bradley Scharf. Wednesday from 10 a.m. to noon. Free. New Rochelle Public Library, Library Plaza. (914) 632-7878.</p>
        <p>SOMERS -- Art and crafts fair. Next Saturday and Sunday from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $4. Lasdon Park, Route 35. (914) 242-7275.</p>
        <p>VALHALLA -- Hispanic heritage celebration.  Today from 1 to 8 p.m. Free admission. Kensico Dam Plaza, north end of Bronx River Parkway. (914) 242-7275.</p>
        <p>WHITE PLAINS -- Amish quilt and craft sale, featuring 250 quilts (for twin, full, queen and king beds), 500 smaller quilts for wall hangings; pillows, dolls, toys, furniture, rugs, books and more. Next Saturday from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free admission. County Center, Bronx River Parkway and Central Avenue.  (914) 285-4050.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
