<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lyme Sufferers Are Hoping A New Treatment Is Answer</title>
    <meta content="20LYME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223878"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lyme Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tweksbury, Lynn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotsalas, Valerie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Lyme Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lyme Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E2D9163EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lyme Sufferers Are Hoping A New Treatment Is Answer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE COTSALAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotsalas, Valerie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on four-year study, which began in January, to test controversial long-term antibiotic treatment for people who suffer debilitating effects of chronic Lyme disease; Lynn Tweksbury, Long Island's first volunter to meet study's requirements, and others with disease comment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A SMALL tube dangles from Lynn Tewksbury's arm, then disappears under the skin and snakes through a vein straight to her heart. Each night she hooks up the tube to a plastic pouch filled with antibiotics or a placebo -- she knows not which -- and sits down to watch television in her Islip Terrace home.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tewksbury will do this every night for 10 weeks as part of a new study that she and others hope will give patients and doctors some guidance in treating a chronic form of Lyme disease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A SMALL tube dangles from Lynn Tewksbury's arm, then disappears under the skin and snakes through a vein straight to her heart. Each night she hooks up the tube to a plastic pouch filled with antibiotics or a placebo -- she knows not which -- and sits down to watch television in her Islip Terrace home.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tewksbury will do this every night for 10 weeks as part of a new study that she and others hope will give patients and doctors some guidance in treating a chronic form of Lyme disease.</p>
        <p>After more than a decade of trying to find effective treatment for symptoms that she says range from painful stiffness and extreme fatigue to seizures and a heaviness in her legs that makes her feel like she's wearing cement boots, Ms. Tewksbury, 43, believes that it is her duty to take part in the study.</p>
        <p>''I really think that if you can meet the criteria and it's not too inconvenient, you should almost be obligated to do it if you can because there are so many people that are suffering,'' said Ms. Tewksbury, the first Long Island volunteer to meet the requirements to take part in the study. ''We're all small specks, but maybe they'll get some answers.''</p>
        <p>The study is the first to test a hotly debated treatment for people who suffer the debilitating effects of chronic Lyme disease, an infection that is spread by deer ticks found in nearly any woodsy area on Long Island, Connecticut and New Jersey. (New York tops the list of Lyme disease nationwide, with 39,370 cases reported between 1989 and 1998. Next is Connecticut with 17,728, followed by Pennsylvania with 14,870 and New Jersey with 13,428).</p>
        <p>The study, which began in January and is scheduled to last four years, with a budget of $4.7 million from the National Institutes of Health, is testing the hypotheses that chronic Lyme disease affects the brain and that a long-term course of intravenous antibiotics will make the symptoms go away. More information is available from the Web site www.columbia-lyme.org.</p>
        <p>Spatial and geographical disorientation is common in chronic sufferers, according to Dr. Brian Fallon, a professor of clinical psychiatry at Columbia University and director of the Lyme disease research program at the New York State Psychiatric Institute in Manhattan. People who have had the disease for years can't remember conversations they had an hour earlier, he said, or they walk into a room and forget why.</p>
        <p>''Everyone does that a little bit,'' Dr. Fallon said. ''But these people do it a lot. They can't attend to conversations and follow the conversations normally because the brain is working so much slower than others. They experience the world as if they're in a fog.</p>
        <p>''The Lyme bacterium is a spirochete, just like syphilis,'' he said. ''And like syphilis, it affects the brain if it is not treated early.''</p>
        <p>Trish Monsen woke up with a rash 10 years ago and went to her doctor, who gave her some medication to take for 10 days. Two months later, the Kings Park resident could barely walk from the acute pain in her spine.</p>
        <p>It was four years before Ms. Monsen, 37, was diagnosed with Lyme disease. At that point, she said, she was always tired and went to work each day feeling ''washed out.'' She couldn't organize her thoughts or her work. One afternoon during a lunch break, she drove across the parking lot and got lost.</p>
        <p>''It was like I just appeared there and I had no idea where I was,'' Ms. Monsen said. ''It lasted for about 30 seconds and then I knew where I was again.''</p>
        <p>Many of the symptoms that she complains of were echoed at a recent support group, a meeting of 15 sufferers at St. Charles Hospital in Port Jefferson. In addition to the arthritic swelling of joints associated with Lyme disease, many of those who have had the disease for more than a decade described blurred vision, sensitivity to light, forgetfulness, disorientation and depression.</p>
        <p>For 55-year-old Linda Simeone, who wore dark sunglasses to the meeting and walked with a cane, losing her ability to write and her peripheral vision and having cataract surgery are only one part of the suffering she has experienced over the last nine years.</p>
        <p>''I think it's the loneliest disease because you're so unsupported,'' Ms. Simeone said, as others sitting beside her nodded in agreement. ''We've all gone through hell -- medical hell, physical hell and emotional hell. After a while, you become old news. You don't even want to share it with anybody.''</p>
        <p>The medical textbooks, Dr. Fallon said, advise four weeks of antibiotics to treat Lyme disease. Prescribing more than four weeks, he said, is considered an unapproved treatment. The risk of a long-term course of antibiotics is damage to organs like the kidneys and liver, and an increase in the chance of developing bacteria resistant to antibiotics.</p>
        <p>Some New York doctors use this aggressive treatment anyway, and are subject to discipline by the state Office of Professional Medical Conduct.</p>
        <p>''There's no scientific data to support that type of therapy,'' said Dr. Raymond Dattwyler, director of the Lyme disease center at the State University of New York at Stony Brook. He added that the antibiotics can alleviate the symptoms of diseases other than Lyme, possibly masking the real cause of the problem.</p>
        <p>''Ultimately, you have to do really rigorous study to help sort things out like that,'' he said. ''Until that's done, it has to be considered experimental.''</p>
        <p>Chronic Lyme disease is a condition that is itself a subject of debate within the medical community. Most sufferers respond to antibiotic treatment, and some researchers believe the chronic form of Lyme is very rare and that many of those who complain of the condition are actually suffering from another condition that Lyme symptoms are known to mimic, like chronic fatigue syndrome, lupus or multiple sclerosis.</p>
        <p>''No one has a definition of what chronic Lyme disease means, so it's hard to define it as an entity,'' Dr. Dattwyler said.</p>
        <p>The study will require participants to meet strict criteria that Dr. Fallon, who is also an expert on hypochondria, has defined for the program. But his basic definition of the ailment is this: ''We're calling it chronic Lyme disease because we believe the person's current symptoms are related to the initial Lyme disease infection.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Fallon has been studying the effects of Lyme disease on the brain since 1990, when he and his wife, also a psychiatrist, paid a visit to Lyme, Conn., where the disease was first identified 25 years ago. There, Dr. Fallon said, he interviewed victims complaining of depression, anxiety and panic attacks.</p>
        <p>''Compared to people with arthritis, lupus and other diseases like this, Lyme victims had three times more common complaints of depression than others,'' Dr. Fallon found in a subsequent survey. ''Seventy-five percent reported, at some point during their illness, depression or marked irritability.''</p>
        <p>Trish Monsen has been taking antibiotics regularly for more than five years under the care of an East Hampton doctor, Joseph Burrascano. She is aware of the risks of long-term antibiotics, she says, but chooses that risk over the daily battle with painful symptoms of Lyme disease. By the time she found Dr. Burrascano, she said, she had all but given up.</p>
        <p>''He saved my life, he really did,'' Ms. Monsen said. ''If it wasn't for him, I can't imagine what would have happened to me. And there are so many people like me.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Burrascano, who has published a protocol for treating long-term Lyme disease and is considered a leader in this therapy, is currently under investigation by the Office of Professional Medical Conduct, which has examined his patient records.</p>
        <p>Citing this investigation, Dr. Burrascano declined to comment, but directed inquiries to Monica Miller, a spokeswoman for the Foundation for the Advancement of Innovative Medicine.</p>
        <p>''The state is taking enforcement measures based on no science,'' Ms. Miller said of the investigation of Dr. Burrascano. ''It goes in the opposite direction of good science and it is an enforcement measure based on bias.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Fallon's study is a step in the right direction, Ms. Miller added, but she said that since the state is threatening to take away medical licenses from doctors prescribing unapproved treatments for chronic Lyme disease, the results of the study may come too late. ''At that point,'' she said, ''they will have put doctors out of business.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Monsen and others believe that long-term antibiotics are the only way to deal with their disease. She said she would be ''totally devastated'' if Dr. Burrascano could no longer treat her.</p>
        <p>''Through this whole thing, the only thing more scary than being sick was having nobody to treat me,'' Ms. Monsen said. ''As soon as I found him, it was like the big load was lifted. Somebody was going to take care of me.''</p>
        <p>For now, Dr. Fallon is looking for people who fit the criteria for the study that could help clear up the confusion over Lyme disease treatment.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tewksbury was a perfect candidate because she still tests positive for the Lyme antibody even after years of antibiotic treatment. Out of 100 people with chronic Lyme symptoms, Dr. Fallon guesses that maybe 10 will test positive. He hopes to find 15 new patients each year from New York, Connecticut and New Jersey. He added that patients who receive the placebo will be offered free antibiotic treatment later.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tewksbury monitors her own health, being careful to notice when she gets very tired for a long time or when she feels like she can't lift her legs anymore to walk. If it gets bad, she'll let Dr. Fallon know.</p>
        <p>''That's one thing about this study: patient involvement is 100 percent,'' she said, sitting beside a rattan tray loaded with the antibiotic pouch and saline syringes. ''They're not going to stick you with this stuff and leave you hanging.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
