<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Pines' Ashes, a Different Landscape</title>
    <meta content="20PINE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pine Barrens (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marcazzo, Regina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0D9163EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1522" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Pines' Ashes, a Different Landscape</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By REGINA MARCAZZO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marcazzo, Regina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article assesses renewal of section of Long Island's pine barrens, ravaged by fire five years ago; scientists say 225 acres of globally rare dwarf pitch forest are regrowing as scrub oak shrubland; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHARRED treetops still loom in the sparse-looking areas where Long Island's worst wildfires in decades raged five years ago this week. For the driver along Sunrise Highway and the other thoroughfares where the flames met the road, the sight is a constant reminder of a time when smoke and fear filled Westhampton, Westhampton Beach, Remsenburg, Speonk, Eastport and Rocky Point.</p>
        <p>The burned areas are regrowing, to be sure. But not as before. Scientists say the landscape has been altered for decades or longer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHARRED treetops still loom in the sparse-looking areas where Long Island's worst wildfires in decades raged five years ago this week. For the driver along Sunrise Highway and the other thoroughfares where the flames met the road, the sight is a constant reminder of a time when smoke and fear filled Westhampton, Westhampton Beach, Remsenburg, Speonk, Eastport and Rocky Point.</p>
        <p>The burned areas are regrowing, to be sure. But not as before. Scientists say the landscape has been altered for decades or longer.</p>
        <p>It was on Aug. 21, 1995, during an especially hot and dry summer, that a fire began in the state conservation area south of Rocky Point. Three days later, a fire started on the grounds of Suffolk County Community College's eastern campus in Riverhead and roared out of control, jumping Sunrise Highway.</p>
        <p>Before the flames were declared out on Sept. 10, the fire consumed 1,800 acres of pitch pine-scrub oak-heath woodland and pine-oak forest in Rocky Point and 3,000 acres from Westhampton to Eastport. More than 2,000 volunteer firefighters from all over Long Island and beyond battled the flames, which reached 200 feet high in some places.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of residents from Eastport to Westhampton Beach were evacuated from their homes; one evacuation center, the Eastport High School, also had to be evacuated. Some residents were not permitted back to their homes for up to three days. In terms of area burned, it was one of the worst weeks of fires on Long Island since the 1860's, when a mammoth blaze burned from Smithtown to Riverhead.</p>
        <p>But there was no loss of life in the 1995 fires, and property damage was relatively slight. Two houses were ruined in the Sunrise fire and 12 other structures damaged, including homes, businesses and the Westhampton station of the Long Island Rail Road.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully we won't quickly forget,'' said Ray Corwin, executive director of the Central Pine Barrens Commission. It was created in 1993 by the Long Island Pine Barrens Protection Act to manage the 55,000-acre core preservation area and the 47,500-acre ''compatible growth area'' surrounding the core.</p>
        <p>The worst damage, at least from an environmental perspective, was the destruction of 225 acres of globally rare dwarf pitch forest, which exists on Long Island and New Jersey and nowhere else.</p>
        <p>Scientists at first voiced expectations that the dwarf pitch pine forest would regenerate, mostly from seeds left by the destroyed trees. Now, after five years of careful monitoring of patterns of regrowth in the stricken areas, some of those scientists say the hardest-hit areas are decades away from being restored to the forest primeval. Large tracts that had been dwarf pitch pines are now regrowing as scrub oak shrubland, a lower, denser cover that bears little resemblance to the lost thickets of dwarf pine.</p>
        <p>''It was so hot and so big that the cones completely became destroyed,'' said Jessica Gurevitch, an ecology professor at the State University of New York at Stony Brook, explaining the absence of pitch pine seeds in the most badly burned areas.</p>
        <p>Most pitch pines burned in the fire were too old to resprout and up to 98 percent died. But scrub oaks re sprouted 10 days after the fire and have continued to come back vigorously. A report written in February by Marilyn Jordan, an ecologist at The Nature Conservancy, states that the Sunrise fire ''converted 2,000 acres of woodland and forest back into scrub oak shrubland that may persist for decades.''</p>
        <p>''It's not a disaster,'' said Dr. Jordan, noting that only 15 percent of the dwarf pines burned. She described the burned pine barrens as ''a shifting mosaic'' and said the scrub oak is a key pine barrens plant, providing food and habitat for a variety of local species like birds, squirrels and the rare buck moth. ''We're seing a huge amount of buck moth caterpillars this year,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Although no precise cause of the Sunrise fire was determined, its birth on the Suffolk Community College campus suggests human agency. Even so, Dr. Jordan described the fire as ''part of the normal cycle of things.'' She estimated it would take 10 to 30 years for pines to re-establish themselves, regaining ground a few yards per year as seeds from pines that survived the fire fall into devastated areas.</p>
        <p>''It's not all lost, it's a little bit smaller,'' Dr. Gurevitch said. ''If we continue to let it get smaller and smaller, then it will be lost. I think it's gotten a lot of people to pay more attention.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the burned areas have become an outdoor research facility. Plant measurements were taken one and two years after the fire and are being taken again this summer.</p>
        <p>Philip Rutkowski, a Hofstra University student, has been spending the summer measuring the regrowth for The Nature Conservancy. His days in the field are spent laying a 100-meter tape measure along 14 preselected spots and measuring all the live plants growing above or below the line of the tape.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gurevitch said that research since the fire had called into question whether the dwarf pitch pines are genetically distinct from regular pitch pines or are simply stunted by local environmental conditions.</p>
        <p>''It's not just that the plants are different,'' she said. ''The question is are they genetically different or is there something more than that. It's the place that's so special. I suspect that at least one big thing is soil.''</p>
        <p>John Black, a retired Suffolk Community College professor of environmental science, has been contending that the dwarf pines are not genetically different but contorted because of changing direction in their search for light.</p>
        <p>The summer of 1995 was one of extreme drought, and there is little chance the disaster can be repeated this soggy summer. But preparedness has also been increased. Three months after the fires, local fire departments put together a wildfire task force, which devised a plan to coordinate the response to future fires. The group meets four times a year.</p>
        <p>Fire weather stations, a fire hazard monitoring system and new water buckets for helicopters that are housed at the Air National Guard in Westhampton Beach are among the initiatives that stem directly from the wildfires.</p>
        <p>The New York State Fire Academy, on the grounds Brookhaven National Laboratory, is another. Since 1998 it has been offering courses on fighting wildfires. Last year there were 215 students from 15 states. Capt. Robert Conklin, the chief of forest rangers for the state Department of Environmental Conservation, said that three local Fire Academy graduates, volunteers from St. James, Stony Brook and Dix Hills, were out West now, fighting this summer's huge crop of forest fires.</p>
        <p>The 1995 wildfires have increased pressure to set preventive fires, controlled burns intended to clear out deadwood and undergrowth and thereby reduce the ''fuel load'' available to feed a wildfire.</p>
        <p>Thirteen such prescribed burns have been carried out this year, and the Pine Barrens Commission is working on a prescribed fire management plan. But the issue is sensitive, with concern about a mistake like the controlled burn that ran out of control in May, destroying much of Los Alamos, N.M.</p>
        <p>''We're in favor of using controlled, prescribed fire as a maintenance tool in the pine barrens,'' said Shelley Green, a pine barrens project director at The Nature Conservancy's Long Island chapter office in Cold Spring Harbor.</p>
        <p>Not everyone agrees that prescribed fire is the way to maintain the Long Island pine barrens.</p>
        <p>''I don't agree that you have to have a fire once every 10 years in the dwarf pines,'' said Mr. Black, citing a study that he conducted with a grant from the Defense Department. ''I don't think it's a fire-dependent ecosystem.'' Some varieties of pine require fire to burst open their cones, releasing their seeds.</p>
        <p>Since the wildfires, risk ratings have been issued daily based on data collected at fire weather stations in Shirley and Westhampton. If a fire department gets a call on a day rated extreme risk, it could immediately call for the help of a neighboring department without having to assess the situation in the field. ''It lets the fire company know what he can expect so he can make the decision,'' said Robert Parris, a United States Fish and Wildlife employee who makes the daily risk evaluation.</p>
        <p>The rating system was the basis for the closure of several state and county parks in Suffolk last summer, when drought prevailed.</p>
        <p>''We are really in a short fire interval system, that's why it's important for us to address these issues, Dr. Parris said. ''We live in a fire habitat here and it's important to recognize that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
