<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All Aboard for a Museum That Rolls On and On</title>
    <meta content="20MAND$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223822"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Artrain Usa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mandell, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6DF1F3FF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All Aboard for a Museum That Rolls On and On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN MANDELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mandell, Jonathan</byline>
      <dateline>ATHENS, Ga.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jonathan Mandell article on Artrain USA, which began bringing traveling art exhibits to more than 600 towns and cities in 44 states 29 years ago; staffers comment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JEFF JEWELL, from Watertown, Tenn., (population 2,000), had never attended an art exhibition, and he had boarded a train only once before in his life, when Artrain rolled into town. When it left after a week, he left with it.</p>
        <p>Now, two months and three towns later, he was helping to set up here, along with the other members of Artrain's staff, who also got hooked in their hometowns. Kim Kapalka, the tour manager, had hopped aboard in Lawrence, Kan., leaving her job at a library.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JEFF JEWELL, from Watertown, Tenn., (population 2,000), had never attended an art exhibition, and he had boarded a train only once before in his life, when Artrain rolled into town. When it left after a week, he left with it.</p>
        <p>Now, two months and three towns later, he was helping to set up here, along with the other members of Artrain's staff, who also got hooked in their hometowns. Kim Kapalka, the tour manager, had hopped aboard in Lawrence, Kan., leaving her job at a library.</p>
        <p>Since it began 29 years ago, Artrain USA, one of the oldest of an increasing number of museums on wheels, has brought original artworks by Picasso and Warhol, Calder and O'Keeffe, Norman Rockwell and Robert Rauschenberg, to more than 600 towns and cities in 44 states. It has gone to big cities like Baltimore, Detroit, Pittsburgh and Washington, but more often its destination isn't even a whistle stop anymore -- places like Zeeland, Mich.; Plant City, Fla., and Parkers Prairie, Minn.</p>
        <p>''All a community needs is railroad tracks,'' Ms. Kapalka said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jewell's official title is facility technician, which means he does the heavy lifting. His folks back home kid him that he's a modern-day carny. ''It is like the circus,'' he admitted. ''Just move along, set something up, then get going again.''</p>
        <p>Becky Schutt doesn't see it that way. ''I prefer the rock tour analogy,'' she said. Ms. Schutt, from New Jersey, signed up for Artrain while she was attending the University of Michigan and it was resting in Ann Arbor, its home base. ''I tell my friends, 'I'm on tour,' '' she said, ''so it sounds like I'm a rock star.''</p>
        <p>She is in the right town at the moment for such a fantasy; Athens is best known as the college town that gave birth to the rock bands R.E.M. and the B-52's, a place where young people go to become rock stars.</p>
        <p>''Athens has always been very, very supportive of people creating stuff,'' said Michael Stipe, an actual rock star (with R.E.M.) and a former art student. He was standing with friends outside the Flicker Bar, which was having an art opening -- some half-dozen photographs on a wall. ''In the mid-90's, people began coming out as much for the art as for the music,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Artrain was on railroad tracks near the University of Georgia's Lamar Dodd School of Art, which has 60 full-time faculty and is named after a painter, educator and long-time resident of Athens who had two works in the Artrain exhibition. This was a major reason the people of Athens, especially C. L. Morehead, a collector who owns hundreds of Lamar Dodds, sponsored an Artrain stop here.</p>
        <p>Athens is not typical of the places Artrain visits; in most towns, its exhibition is often the Big Cultural Event. But no town is really typical, staff members say. ''It might all be small-town America, but each town is different,'' said Sheila Debrunner. Another staff member, Kelly Raymond, added,  ''We're often in towns much smaller than this.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Raymond and Ms. Debrunner were in the first of the train's five cars, where Ms. Debrunner was reading a light meter in front of ''Earth Crust,'' a lithograph by Robert Rauschenberg as Ms. Raymond made notations on a clipboard. They moved to Andy Warhol's silkscreen ''Moon Walk (1),'' then to an oil painting by Peter Max, some watercolors by James Wyeth and finally to another car, this one full of works on paper. They were making sure that the paintings and drawings were not exposed to too much light; the rocking of the train can sometimes rattle the carefully calibrated track lighting, knocking it off kilter. The works of art themselves were all bolted into the walls and fronted by Plexiglass at the beginning of the tour more than a year ago.</p>
        <p>This helps protect them not only from possible damage but also from vandalism and theft. Indeed, Artrain's adherence to standard museum practice in climate control (to keep a steady temperature and humidity), the handling of art and security has enabled it to attract some high quality art, much the same as that lent to any museum; Artrain has no collection of its own.</p>
        <p>A few cars down, Ms. Kapalka, the tour manager, had unpacked gift items and shelved them in the gift shop, which also serves as an art studio. There, local artists demonstrated their skills, whether painting or pottery making. Ms. Kapalka soon moved to the office, at the end of the fourth car, and phoned ahead to make arrangements in Woodward, Okla., a stop more than a month in the future.</p>
        <p>Outside, Mr. Jewell and Emily Hewitt were setting up a canopy in the parking lot next to the train and raising flags on the sides of the railroad cars. Ms. Hewitt's official title is facility manager; she is the only one of the seven staff members who actually rides on the train as it travels from town to town. She also lives in the little red caboose for as long as three weeks at a stretch. The others drive vans and stay in hotels.</p>
        <p>This is not fun time. ''I'm not a railroad buff,'' Ms. Hewitt said. Having no locomotive itself, Artrain must rely on the kindness of railroad companies to move it along their tracks. Only rarely does a railroad connect two small towns directly, so Artrain must often travel a painfully circuitous route with many delays. It is completely normal for a 14-mile trip to take 6 hours.</p>
        <p>Hearing about their life on the road -- traveling 11 months out of 12, eating on the go, rarely knowing where they will be from week to week, having no permanent place to live -- one begins to think of the Artrain workers as a group of art-history hobos.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jewell, a 22-year-old computer science major working on Artrain for the summer, was also one of the few on the staff without a background in art history. And even he can't help being influenced.</p>
        <p>''A few nights ago in my hotel room,'' he said, ''I got a little bored, and I started doodling. I wouldn't have done that before. I would have just watched TV.''</p>
        <p>Artrain USA bills itself as the only art museum on a train, but there are an increasing number of such museums in vans, buses, recreational vehicles and tractor-trailers.</p>
        <p>''Right now, everyone seems to want one,'' said Lee Skolnick, an architect who designed two Movable Museums for the American Museum of Natural History in New York and is working on four more such mobile museums. One is for a new collection of antiquities in Las Vegas, Nev., another for a children's museum in Chicago; the others will be based in Indiana and Beirut, Lebanon.</p>
        <p>In Arlington, Va., last year, the Newseum, a museum about the news media, introduced NewsCapade, a rolling exhibition of such artifacts as a fragment of the Berlin Wall and Bill Gates's autographed keyboard. The show is lugged by custom-designed trucks to locations in all 50 states.</p>
        <p>Most mobile museums travel within a limited region, often a single state. The Museum of New Mexico sends out some of its collection to rural areas in the state in a bus it calls the Van of Enchantment. The Susquehanna Art Museum in Harrisburg travels the state of Pennsylvania with a mobile museum it calls VanGo.</p>
        <p>The Natural History Museum of Los Angeles operates both an Earthmobile, which looks at a coastal Native American culture, and a Seamobile, about the marine sciences.</p>
        <p>The American Museum of Natural History's two mobile museums travel within the city limits. ''We've been in Winnebagos since 1992,'' said Jenny Lando as she drove one of them to a community festival in Two Coves Park playground in Astoria, Queens. The vehicle, almost as long as a city bus, held an exhibition about dinosaurs. ''But the museum has had movable museums for a long time,'' Ms. Lando said. ''They started with a suitcase. They were on motorcycles in the 1920's. In the 1930's and 1940's, they used converted ambulances.''</p>
        <p>Artrain itself began small, as a temporary program of the Michigan Council for the Arts with the aim of reaching rural areas of that state. But demand, and a grant from the National Endowment for the Arts, turned it into a nationwide nonprofit arts organization.</p>
        <p>The trend toward mobile museums is partly a result of modern technological advances. Vehicles can now come with better climate control and security and portable interactive computers. It also coincides with the renewed popularity of museums. ''People are going to museums for more things than ever before, not just to see objects; they've become in some ways akin to malls,'' Mr. Skolnick said. ''So it's not so surprising that these institutions are looking for new ways to reach their public.''</p>
        <p>BUT for all that is new about the phenomenon, there is also something old-fashioned about what is going on, especially on Artrain. ''Some of the draw is just the excitement of boarding a train, the nostalgia of that,'' said Jean Steppe, a staff member. ''About a quarter of our visitors are railroad buffs who get an education in art sort of accidentally.''</p>
        <p>At Artrain's opening reception in Athens, the first of four days here, staff members have changed from their work clothes to evening wear and welcome the local V.I.P.'s to the exhibition, the organization's 14th, entitled ''Artistry of Space.'' Scheduled to tour for two more years, the show offers a selection of 78 artworks on space travel from the hundreds that the National Aeronautics and Space Administration has commissioned over the last four decades as part of NASA's art program.</p>
        <p>''NASA had hundreds of cameras photographing every nut and bolt, but there was something missing,'' said James Dean, a retired federal official who flew down from Washington. ''You had all the facts, but you didn't have any of the emotion.'' Mr. Dean started the agency's art program 38 years ago and is now himself a painter with works in the show.</p>
        <p>''Artistry in Space'' harks back to a time when the space program offered a new and exciting landscape for Americans to explore, in the way that the trains offered Americans a fresh landscape in the 19th century. Though the art in the exhibition is varied -- one car is devoted entirely to abstract work -- paintings like Attilla Hejja's ''Light Ship,'' which depicts the launching of the Space Shuttle Challenger, recall the kind of detailed, theatrical landscapes captured by 19th-century American artists like Frederick Church. The fiery vapor, smoke and cloud bursting from the booster rockets even bear some resemblance to the billowing steam and smoke in 19th-century art featuring early locomotives.</p>
        <p>Walking through Artrain, the students from Ben Bridgers' intermediate drawing class at Lamar Dodd  are impressed. ''People don't even ride trains anymore,'' Mr. Bridgers said, ''much less expect an art exhibition on one.''</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE Jonathan Mandell, a former art critic, is managing editor of www.GothamGazette.com, a Web site about New York City politics and policy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jonathan Mandell, a former art critic, is managing editor of www.GothamGazette.com, a Web site about New York City politics and policy.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
