<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The State's New Watchdog Gets Down to Business</title>
    <meta content="20INSP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOVERNMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neafsey, Edward M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1DD143EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1049" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The State's New Watchdog Gets Down to Business</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Edward M Neafsey, 49, New Jersey's first inspector general, who was also state's first insurance fraud prosecutor; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After being sworn in by a superior court judge who also happened to be his wife, Edward M. Neafsey began his duties last week as the state's first inspector general -- a watchdog assigned to make sure the state bureaucracy operates efficiently and free of corruption.</p>
        <p>The 49-year old Mr. Neafsey, (pronounced NEEF-see), who was also the state's first insurance fraud prosecutor, began the week setting up a system to monitor the new $13 billion school construction program and is expected to submit the proposal to his boss, Attorney General John J. Farmer, Jr., by week's end.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After being sworn in by a superior court judge who also happened to be his wife, Edward M. Neafsey began his duties last week as the state's first inspector general -- a watchdog assigned to make sure the state bureaucracy operates efficiently and free of corruption.</p>
        <p>The 49-year old Mr. Neafsey, (pronounced NEEF-see), who was also the state's first insurance fraud prosecutor, began the week setting up a system to monitor the new $13 billion school construction program and is expected to submit the proposal to his boss, Attorney General John J. Farmer, Jr., by week's end.</p>
        <p>''It's the biggest expenditure of public money New Jersey has ever undertaken,'' said Mr. Neafsey.</p>
        <p>''Our role will be to monitor those expenditures, but also how the contracts are let to ensure that there is no corruption in the system,'' Mr. Neafsey added in a telephone interview last week from his temporary office in Lawrenceville. ''We'll review the bids themselves and the contractors who are qualified to bid on these contracts, and we will accept referrals from citizens, school officials and anyone else if they uncover anything that seems untoward.''</p>
        <p>The Attorney General created the office of the inspector general in May amid controversies involving allegations of racial profiling by State Police and a malfunctioning auto emissions testing system. He said those problems showed that a permanent investigative agency was needed to prevent waste and malfeasance in government and, when necessary, to prosecute.</p>
        <p>Although not critical of Mr. Neafsey himself, some Democrats have questioned the independence of the new watchdog unit because the attorney general to whom the inspector general reports is appointed by the governor. The Senate Minority Leader, Richard Codey, Democrat from Essex County, for instance, has referred to the new position as ''inspector corporal.''</p>
        <p>Critics also note that the Whitman Administration had stripped power from two independent watchdog agencies. The strong investigative role of the public advocate was eliminated six years ago under the governor's plan to streamline state government. And the State Commission of Investigation was directed to report criminal findings to the attorney general.</p>
        <p>Attorney General Farmer, however, says Mr. Neafsey's independence is assured because he, like the attorney general himself can be removed from office only for cause.</p>
        <p>And because of his affiliation with the attorney general's office, the inspector general has even more far-reaching power, Mr. Farmer said. He will be able not only to file civil lawsuits but also to convene grand juries to seek criminal indictments. The inspector general will also issue reports on weaknesses he finds in state agencies and recommend policy changes.</p>
        <p>The federal government has long had inspectors general in various departments with good results, said Ingrid Reed, director of the New Jersey Project of the Eagleton Institute of Politics at Rutgers University.</p>
        <p>''You'll see that they have had significant power and have been respected,'' Ms. Reed said. But, she added, the effectiveness of the office in New Jersey will depend on the character, independence, experience and reputation of the person who fills the position.</p>
        <p>''It will be hard for the position to be powerful if the person in it isn't powerful,'' Ms. Reed said.</p>
        <p>John Tiene, executive director of the Insurance Council of New Jersey, said, ''Ed Neafsey has served various governors and there is nothing that we've seen, while he was insurance fraud prosecutor, that would indicate anything other than an allegiance to the law rather than to any elected officials.''</p>
        <p>''He organized the office of insurance fraud prosecutor in a short time and then established a record of indictments and convictions in 18 months that rivals similar entities that have been in office for decades,'' Mr. Tiene said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Neafsey, who set up the first insurance fraud prosecutor's office in October 1998, sent 26 insurance cheats to prison for a total of 77 years.</p>
        <p>In a legal career that has spanned 23 years, Mr. Neafsey has been chief enforcement officer for the State Department of Environmental Protection and chief of the environmental crimes bureau in the attorney general's office.</p>
        <p>The inspector general's office, which will be in a building in Trenton separate from the attorney general's building, has a $3 million budget and will eventually have a staff of 30, including lawyers, investigative supervisors, investigator-accountants and management-improvement specialists.</p>
        <p>Mr. Neafsey's second major assignment is to review purchases under the open space preservation program, which has an annual allocation of $98 million. The goal is ''to determine all the checks and balances there are existing in the system,'' Mr. Neafsey said, ''how the money gets spent and determine if there is a need for additional checks and balances.''</p>
        <p>He will also review whether appropriate rules exist governing ethics and conflicts of interest in the open space program.</p>
        <p>Mr. Neafsey holds a bachelor's degree from Assumption College in Worcester, Mass., and a law degree from Southwestern Univerity of Law in Los Angeles. Of Irish descent, he is active in groups promoting peace in Northern Ireland and in 1997 took a seven-week sabbatical in Dublin to get a certificate in peace studies from the Irish School of Ecumenics, which is affiliated with Trinity College in Dublin.</p>
        <p>An avid cyclist, he once spent a week's vacation riding his bike from Sandy Hook to Cape May. His wife, and the woman who swore him in along with five aides is Judge Jane Grall of Mercer County Superior Court. He and his wife share a two-family house in Avon with his father, Edward Sr. a retired court clerk, and mother, Agnes, a retired schoolteacher.</p>
        <p>Asked why he has pursued the role of prosecutor so vigorously, he replied, ''One of government's more important missions is to protect the people. In these various roles that I have had, that's how I went about my business.'' He added, ''At the same time, you want to make sure you do it in a fair and just manner.''</p>
        <p>GOVERNMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
