<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Officials Questioned Over Tribal Recognition</title>
    <meta content="20TRIB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223846"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Eastern Pequot indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pequot Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paucatuck Eastern Pequot Indians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bureau of Indian Affairs</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Richard (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Libby, Sam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E4DD163EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="428" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Officials Questioned Over Tribal Recognition</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM LIBBY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Libby, Sam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Bureau of Indian Affairs researchers, questioned during meetings called by Connecticut Attorney General Richard Blumenthal regarding agency's decision to grant preliminary federal recognition to Eastern Pequots and Paucatuck Eastern Pequots, say state itself has provided important evidence defending action (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR two days state and municipal lawyers questioned researchers for the United States Bureau of Indian Affairs regarding the agency's decision to grant preliminary federal recognition to the Eastern Pequots and the Paucatuck Eastern Pequots.</p>
        <p>''We're going to make a record that may well be before a court some day,'' said Attorney General Richard Blumenthal, describing his agenda for the meeting in Washington Aug. 8 and 9. Attorney General Blumenthal said he was fighting the federal recognition of all petitioning Connecticut Indian tribes because of the added burdens of traffic and law enforcement that Indian casinos put on neighboring towns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR two days state and municipal lawyers questioned researchers for the United States Bureau of Indian Affairs regarding the agency's decision to grant preliminary federal recognition to the Eastern Pequots and the Paucatuck Eastern Pequots.</p>
        <p>''We're going to make a record that may well be before a court some day,'' said Attorney General Richard Blumenthal, describing his agenda for the meeting in Washington Aug. 8 and 9. Attorney General Blumenthal said he was fighting the federal recognition of all petitioning Connecticut Indian tribes because of the added burdens of traffic and law enforcement that Indian casinos put on neighboring towns.</p>
        <p>But at the meetings, the researchers said that the state itself had provided their most important evidence in defending a decision for  federal recognition of the Eastern Pequots in court.</p>
        <p>''You may not like hearing this,'' said Virginia DeMarce, one of the researchers. ''But the best evidence supporting the Eastern Pequots' federal recognition comes from the state's own record, comes from the fact that the state has maintained and documented a continuous government to government relationship.''</p>
        <p>Ms. DeMarce said fewer hurdles had to be overcome for the federal recognition of the Eastern Pequot, the Golden Hill Paugussett and the Schaghticoke Indian tribes than had to be overcome by the Mohegan Indian tribe. The Mohegans were federally recognized in 1994 even though the tribe had voluntarily dissolved its Uncasville reservation in 1861 and then had voluntarily dissolved its tribal government. The remaining state-recognized tribes that are seeking federal recognition have continuously maintained their reservations and their government to government relationship with the state of Connecticut, Ms. DeMarce noted.</p>
        <p>Researchers say there is ample documentation that the colony and then the state of Connecticut maintained a continuous government to government relationship with the Eastern Pequots, but researchers said they found no evidence that the Paucatuck Eastern Pequot tribe existed before 1973.</p>
        <p>Kevin Gover, assistant secretary of the Interior Department and director of the Bureau of Indian Affairs, has recommended that the Paucatuck Eastern Pequot tribe merge with the Eastern Pequots. Paucatuck Eastern Pequot tribal leaders have rejected this suggestion and say they will produce conclusive evidence that they have existed as a separate tribe since 1890.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
