<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scenes From a Hellish Marriage</title>
    <meta content="20WINEAPT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223720"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wineapple, Brenda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Monica</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strindberg, Frida Uhl (1872-1943)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E2D6163FF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1230" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scenes From a Hellish Marriage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Brenda Wineapple</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wineapple, Brenda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brenda Wineapple reviews book Cruel Banquet: The Life and Loves of Frida Strindberg by Monica Strauss; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CRUEL BANQUET</p>
        <p>The Life and Loves of Frida Strindberg.</p>
        <p>By Monica Strauss.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 264 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Harcourt. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CRUEL BANQUET</p>
        <p>The Life and Loves of Frida Strindberg.</p>
        <p>By Monica Strauss.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 264 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Harcourt. $25.</p>
        <p>VIRGINIA WOOLF remembered the so-called geniuses of her father's generation as a special breed -- always men, of course, but the temperamental sort who wore their hair long, wrapped themselves in brooding capes and needed (demanded) protection from the trials of everyday life by unbegrudging wives or sisters. These men were the subjects of serious books. Then, with the publication of Nancy Milford's biography of Zelda Fitzgerald in 1970, the wives of the geniuses stepped out of the back room and into biographies of their own: Alma Mahler, Nora Joyce, Jane Carlyle, Frida Kahlo, Vera Nabokov.</p>
        <p>Monica Strauss, an independent scholar, now tries to liberate Frida Uhl Strindberg (1872-1943), who suffered the double jeopardy of being the wife of a genius, August Strindberg, and the daughter of a well-known newspaperman. Friedrich Uhl was editor in chief of the Wiener Zeitung, Austria's official government daily, and a theater critic of decided discernment. ''I came into the world with ink in my veins,'' Frida recalled wistfully.</p>
        <p>As Uhl's daughter, Frida was admitted to the theatrical salons of Berlin and Munich, where she hung about, a would-be journalist, and tried her hand at a play or two before meeting Strindberg early in 1893. She was then 20; he was more than twice her age, recently separated from his wife and children, and a misogynist literary star with 26 plays as well as several novels, autobiographies, stories, poems and essays under his belt. ''His nerves are badly strained,'' Frida wrote of the moody playwright to her father, ''but it is an inspired madness.''</p>
        <p>So saying, she set the terms of the relationship. Frida would devote herself to Strindberg's career in an attempt to please both father and lover. (''I can only love a man who is my superior,'' she informed Strindberg.) Despite a rocky engagement, Frida married her genius and immediately began making herself useful, trying to finagle the production of his work in England and to arrange its translation, while staving off creditors and managing his business affairs. Strindberg resented his wife's meddling. He also resented her translating the work of other men. After the birth of their daughter, an increasingly jealous Strindberg accused Frida of conduct unbefitting a wife and mother. ''Go your dirty way to the life you seek in the gutter,'' he thundered. Desperate, Frida turned to her father for emotional and financial support and in 1895, with his blessing, arranged for a divorce.</p>
        <p>Strauss chronicles Frida's subsequent affairs with men who would wallow in the coming sexual revolution but pay no price for it, as women did. ''Without the protection of a permanent partner and often with the burden of an illegitimate child,'' Strauss observes, ''a sexually emancipated woman had to fend for herself financially and was easily exploited.'' The playwright Frank Wedekind, the father of Frida's second child, ended their affair without marrying her, leaving Frida a divorced woman and unwed mother drifting on the margins of respectability. She dispatched her children to her family's care, earned her living as the German agent for the English publisher William Heinemann and in 1900 helped to begin the first German cabaret, where her latest paramour, the poet Hanns Heinz Ewers, caused a ruckus by using a colloquial term for derriere onstage.</p>
        <p>''Women were pawns for the men's aspirations,'' Strauss writes about the limited opportunities available to smart, sexy women at the turn of the century. When Friedrich Uhl offered his daughter ''the vision of what it meant to be a man,'' he dislodged Frida from the fixed conventions of the middle class, and though Frida ''opted for the male role,'' she was ''not adequately prepared for the life she sought, nor was she encouraged.'' What's a girl to do? Frida ''clasped her cultural heroes to her bosom.''</p>
        <p>A salonniere sans salon, Frida traveled on the fringe of the Jung Wien, writers of the Viennese avant-garde. She urged the acerbic journalist Karl Kraus (who detested intellectual women) to sponsor a reading of Wedekind's ''Pandora's Box'' (Wedekind played Jack the Ripper). She advised the essayist Richard Schaukal, organized a subscription to support the poet Peter Altenberg, and translated ''Salome'' and ''The House of Pomegranates'' for the first complete German edition of Oscar Wilde's work.</p>
        <p>Yet the clenched tone of ''Cruel Banquet'' suggests its author grew weary of Frida's self-destructive peccadilloes, her self-delusions and her callous neglect of her children. Though her career as ''cultural impresario'' flourished, her behavior grew inexplicably erratic. Strauss gently mentions ''too many tranquilizing drugs,'' but Frida clearly hated the men she idealized. In 1905, she sued her most recent lover, the writer Werner von Oesteren, for harassing the detective she hired to tail him. During the seamy trial, the public learned that Frida had already threatened von Oesteren twice with a revolver. Three years later, after a spate of suicide notes, she fired a pistol in the Hotel Bristol on New Year's Day, and no one was sure whether she meant the shot for an Austrian aristocrat or herself.</p>
        <p>Frida bolted to London, where she somehow managed to set herself up as an art dealer. Before long, she was toting her gun again, stalking the painter Augustus John. At the same time, she opened a German-style cabaret theater, the Cave of the Golden Calf, decorated by Wyndham Lewis, Spencer Gore and Charles Ginner. Ezra Pound dropped by and complimented the enterprising Mrs. Strindberg: ''More brains than Gertie or Amy put together.''</p>
        <p>There was something irrepressible about Frida Strindberg, something angry and something ultimately diminished, both by circumstance and by herself. She sabotaged the cabaret venture, feuding with customers and siphoning off funds, and by 1914, with England and Austria at war, she took off for the United States, where she planned to promote the recently deceased Strindberg's work in a series of lectures. With her gift for survival, she was soon hired by Fox Film to develop Swedish and other European properties, hawking both the work of the Russian writer Mikhail Artzybashev and her own screenplays. But she shrugged off her accomplishments as well as the rise of Hitler, her son's political vulnerability, the Anschluss -- anything that interfered with her dream of reflected glory. Her real home was the New York Public Library. ''My husband is there, complete now in 58 volumes,'' she explained. ''My father, Friedrich Uhl, novelist, critic, connoisseur and editor, is also there.''</p>
        <p>Frida Strindberg published a memoir of her husband, translated as ''Marriage With Genius'' in 1937. It transformed her, Strauss says. ''She was no longer the woman behind the scene -- whether as lover, translator, agent, screenwriter, publicist or patron -- of the writers and artists she admired. She was out front as Strindberg's representative.'' Alas, poor Frida. This dubious distinction sends her straight back to the time when women measured themselves -- and were measured -- by the stature of the men they served.</p>
        <p>Brenda Wineapple is the Washington Irving professor of modern literary and historical studies at Union College. She is writing a biography of Nathaniel Hawthorne.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Brenda Wineapple is the Washington Irving professor of modern literary and historical studies at Union College. She is writing a biography of Nathaniel Hawthorne.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
