<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>They Laughed, They Cried, Maybe They Even Meant It</title>
    <meta content="20POL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E4DB143EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>They Laughed, They Cried, Maybe They Even Meant It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David M. Halbfinger</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Halbfinger On Politics column on New Jersey delegation's teary-eyed addresses, real or not, at parties and events during Democratic National Convention (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The question of the week at the Democratic national convention may have been whether the hopelessly impassive Al Gore could show television viewers a looser, emotional inner self -- that he feels even his own pain, to put it one way.</p>
        <p>But New Jersey's delegates -- still reeling from the late-summer psychodrama of Senator Robert G. Torricelli's failed attempt to boot James E. McGreevey from the governor's race -- had no such trouble. From morning to night, at pep rallies, fund-raisers and parties, it seemed as if someone was always on the verge of tears, or at least claiming to be.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The question of the week at the Democratic national convention may have been whether the hopelessly impassive Al Gore could show television viewers a looser, emotional inner self -- that he feels even his own pain, to put it one way.</p>
        <p>But New Jersey's delegates -- still reeling from the late-summer psychodrama of Senator Robert G. Torricelli's failed attempt to boot James E. McGreevey from the governor's race -- had no such trouble. From morning to night, at pep rallies, fund-raisers and parties, it seemed as if someone was always on the verge of tears, or at least claiming to be.</p>
        <p>Mr. Torricelli said as much after he addressed the Jersey crowd on Monday and received a standing ovation just for showing up. Though he neither apologized to nor endorsed Mr. McGreevey, the mayor of Woodbridge, the senator did rule out a future run for governor himself.</p>
        <p>The next morning, Senator Frank R. Lautenberg, who hates being upstaged by Senator Torricelli, easily out-emoted him. In what was billed as his ''farewell address,'' Mr. Lautenberg spoke in a halting voice, choked back tears, and even recalled his father's death. Before he spoke, a videotaped tribute, of sorts, was shown: Mr. Lautenberg's campaign commercials from 1982, 1988 and 1994.</p>
        <p>Jon S. Corzine, who is running for Mr. Lautenberg's Senate seat, watched from the back of the room, transfixed, as Mr. Lautenberg's ads eviscerated Millicent Fenwick, Pete Dawkins and Chuck Haytaian, respectively. ''And you think my ads are tough?'' Mr. Corzine said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lautenberg has delivered several farewells this year, and he is clearly improving with practice.</p>
        <p>''And so, my friends,'' he said, letting each word linger, ''this part of this career is done, never to be forgotten, hoping that some of the things I did will be things that some kid, perhaps a grandchild of mine, may be able to look in a book when they study American history, and say, 'he made a contribution. Frank Lautenberg worked hard to do the right thing.' ''</p>
        <p>There were no crocodile tears, but there was much feigned love in the air when George E. Norcross and Raymond J. Lesniak ran into one another at a party for Mr. McGreevey on Tuesday. Mr. Norcross is the Camden County power broker who had tried to deliver a united South Jersey for Mr. Torricelli. Mr. Lesniak is the state senator from Union County who, along with Senator John Lynch of neighboring Middlesex, is one of Mr. McGreevey's biggest supporters. The two have been locked in a long battle for influence in the New Jersey Democratic party.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lesniak, appropriately, is feeling triumphant lately, and when he saw Mr. Norcross, he flexed a bicep and smiled devilishly at his rival. Mr. Norcross smiled back and complimented Mr. Lesniak's lean physique. ''Ray, you've changed since the last time I've seen you,'' he said. ''You look like John Lynch.''</p>
        <p>''I'm Mary Poppins, compared to John Lynch,'' Mr. Lesniak responded. Seeing a photographer and several reporters, however, Mr. Lesniak reached for Mr. Norcross's hand, and pulled him into an uneasy embrace. Mr. Lesniak even planted a kiss on Mr. Norcross's cheek. Somehow there was no earthquake.</p>
        <p>Mr. McGreevey's party in downtown Los Angeles was held at the same time as a dinner in Mr. Torricelli's honor at Spago, the Beverly Hills glitzeria. But Mr. McGreevey had little trouble getting a crowd. One speaker was Edward G. Rendell, the former mayor of Philadelphia and chairman of the Democratic National Committee. He said he was barred from endorsing in primaries, then promptly broke the rule: ''If they give a half a vote to those of us who have summer homes in New Jersey,'' he said, ''Jim McGreevey would start a half a vote up.''</p>
        <p>The party, which cost about $30,000, was paid for by the Democratic State Committee, said Gary Taffet, a McGreevey adviser. The state committee was the beneficiary of a $2.8 million fund-raiser that Mr. McGreevey held in June. During Mr. Torricelli's brief candidacy for governor, Mr. McGreevey was unable to direct how that money was spent. But that problem appears to have been resolved. Mr. Taffet said that more than $300,000 more was being doled out to county Democratic committees to help them in November, something local officials are likely to remember with gratitude during the governor's race next year.</p>
        <p>Joe Lieberman was not the only politician trying out Borscht Belt lines. Mr. Lautenberg also was doing quite a bit of shtick. Backhandedly complimenting Representative Rush Holt, the rocket scientist from Princeton who is running for a second term in Congress, Mr. Lautenberg said: ''He's new at it, but he's gaining speed very rapidly, and he's bright as can be. No one knows what he says when he makes a speech, but it sounds good.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lautenberg saved his best lines for Mr. Corzine. If there is any truth in humor, it seems Mr. Lautenberg is increasingly reluctant to relinquish his seat. ''I have mixed emotions,'' he said on Sunday at a luncheon for Mr. Corzine. ''But Jon has spent too much to step aside now.''</p>
        <p>At the Tuesday breakfast, Mr. Lautenberg tried another riff on the  theme. ''We don't hold his success against him,'' he said from the dais. ''I tested it. I just leaned over to him, and I said, 'Jon, you worked hard, I know you'd like this job. I don't want to declare -- I'll buy it back from you at 20 cents on the dollar.' ''</p>
        <p>''I write it myself,'' Mr. Lautenberg said after the laughter died down. ''That's the problem.''</p>
        <p>ON POLITICS David Halbfinger is Trenton bureau chief for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Halbfinger is Trenton bureau chief for The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
