<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From a Bland Hayfield to a Burst of Color</title>
    <meta content="CNGARDEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223968"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E2D9153EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From a Bland Hayfield to a Burst of Color</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH GINSBURG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE are parts of Long Island that have gotten lots of publicity lately because of the gigantic waves of cold hard cash that have been pounding the shoreline. The problem is not so much the waves as the enormous stone, wood and brick configurations that they leave behind. Fortunately there are still a few places where you can catch glimpses of the area's rural past.</p>
        <p>One of those places is Ann Badagliacca's farm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE are parts of Long Island that have gotten lots of publicity lately because of the gigantic waves of cold hard cash that have been pounding the shoreline. The problem is not so much the waves as the enormous stone, wood and brick configurations that they leave behind. Fortunately there are still a few places where you can catch glimpses of the area's rural past.</p>
        <p>One of those places is Ann Badagliacca's farm.</p>
        <p>Eleven years ago, Ann and Ralph Badagliacca went to Mattituck to buy a retirement home and found Mrs. Badagliacca's personal field of dreams disguised as a hayfield. As soon as the couple moved into the adjacent farmhouse, she began making a garden. Now her dream has been realized in raised beds full of flowers and vegetables, blossoming shrubs and an array of fruit trees and berry bushes.</p>
        <p>The Badagliaccas created their garden by themselves, digging out hundreds of rocks and making raised beds out of mostly salvaged materials. The ongoing project was fueled by her inexhaustible supply of energy. ''I am just always having ideas,'' she said.</p>
        <p>A tour of the Badagliacca garden begins on the deck that the couple added to the back of their 1934 farmhouse. Spikes of blue veronica rise out of pots, a small conifer flanks the steps and honeysuckle twines around the wooden railing. In the spring a large weeping cherry in front of the deck smothers itself in pink blossoms while the new shoots of hostas emerge underneath.</p>
        <p>A row of blue spruce trees divides the garden into two large sections. The front portion, which is closer to the house, is dominated by the skeleton of an old water tower, its lower half covered by the abundant foliage and brilliant orange flowers of trumpet vine. Bright red corn poppies have self-seeded throughout the beds, and their blooms appear like a profusion of vivid exclamation points. Spires of white false dragonhead (Physostegia) provide cool contrast to the hotter colors.</p>
        <p>The farm came complete with a chicken coop, barn and other outbuildings. Tall hybrid tea roses grow in front of the barn, with a climbing rose on one end. If all goes according to plan, the old coop will one day become a playhouse for the Badagliaccas' nine grandchildren.</p>
        <p>A dozen or so azalea bushes flourish in the shelter provided by the blue spruce trees, a prelude to the back half of the garden, which is home to beds of fruits and vegetables, accented by small trees and shrubs. Tall ferny stalks have sprouted from the asparagus bed, now that the season is over, and the rhubarb leaves are almost as big as car tires. Various types of tomatoes, including plum, Big Boy and Big Girl grow plump. As with all vegetable beds, there are successes and failures. ''The crows ate all the butternut squash,'' Mr. Badagliacca said.</p>
        <p>A healthy stand of lavender covers the gangly legs of several pale peachleaf bellflowers. Blazing star (Liatris spicata) pops up here and there like a leitmotif, as do rose, pink and white cosmos. In one bed, there are clumps of an unusual pale lavender variety of yarrow; in another, cleome towers over everything. Yellow archangel (Lamiastrum) has worked its way through the shady areas, covering the ground.</p>
        <p>And then there are the flowering shrubs. A row of rugosa roses has grown into a short hedge and now displays cherry-tomato-size rose hips. Mrs. Badagliacca is especially fond of euonymus and has installed several. Lilac and holly hug the edges of the property, as does variegated wiegela. Many of the shrubs are spring bloomers, but in midsummer, the hydrangeas come into their own. Mophead varieties in shades ranging from medium blue to a dark bluish-purple flourish near the vegetable garden and in a border planting that clings to one of the property's boundaries. This same site is home to a magnificent lacecap hydrangea, stunning in contrast to the double tawny day lilies that surround it. Two crepe myrtles are also apparently happy there. ''And they said they wouldn't survive this far north,'' Mr. Badagliacca said triumphantly.</p>
        <p>Fruit from Ann Badagliacca's raspberry, blackberry and gooseberry bushes, and the peach and nectarine trees find their way into her baked goods, jams and jellies. This year she is also growing grapes.</p>
        <p>Thrift is an ingrained habit for the Badagliaccas, children of the Depression. Most of the hundreds of plants now growing on the property started small, as cuttings, seedlings on the kitchen windowsill, or whips purchased from nursery catalogs.</p>
        <p>For over a decade, Ralph Badagliacca has helped to implement his wife's ideas, from mowing down the original hayfield to building raised beds. Though he speaks with pride about the many lovely plants, he is clearly most proud of his wife. ''Out there,'' he said, his arm sweeping toward the garden, ''she is in her glory.''</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
