<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Piazza a Spectator, Dodgers' Sheffield Supplies the Power</title>
    <meta content="Y20MET$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Dodgers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E5DA103EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1098" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Piazza a Spectator, Dodgers' Sheffield Supplies the Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Los Angeles Dodgers defeat New York Mets, 4-1; photo (M)2</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most fun Mike Piazza ever had in baseball, he said, came last season, when the Mets won a playoff series. Another fun year was 1990, when he hit .250 for a Class A team that won its league title. When he set a single-season home run record for Los Angeles Dodgers in 1997, the year was a bitter disappointment: his team missed the playoffs and traded him the next May.</p>
        <p>So it held no special meaning for Piazza when someone matched that mark today. Piazza had the day off as Gary Sheffield hit his 39th and 40th homers to lead the Dodgers and Chan Ho Park to a 4-1 victory over the Mets. Piazza had been the only Dodger to hit 40 homers in a season since the franchise moved from Brooklyn in 1958.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The most fun Mike Piazza ever had in baseball, he said, came last season, when the Mets won a playoff series. Another fun year was 1990, when he hit .250 for a Class A team that won its league title. When he set a single-season home run record for Los Angeles Dodgers in 1997, the year was a bitter disappointment: his team missed the playoffs and traded him the next May.</p>
        <p>So it held no special meaning for Piazza when someone matched that mark today. Piazza had the day off as Gary Sheffield hit his 39th and 40th homers to lead the Dodgers and Chan Ho Park to a 4-1 victory over the Mets. Piazza had been the only Dodger to hit 40 homers in a season since the franchise moved from Brooklyn in 1958.</p>
        <p>Piazza says he is motivated strictly by winning, not by records. If the Mets reach the playoffs, he will be the favorite to win the Most Valuable Player award. If the Dodgers enter the pennant race, Sheffield will be a prime challenger. The two stars, traded for each other when Piazza left the Dodgers for the Florida Marlins before landing in New York, are linked again.</p>
        <p>''I had visualized playing with the guy,'' said Sheffield, whose 40th homer today tied him with Sammy Sosa of the Chicago Cubs for the major league lead. ''I always wanted to play with a great player, and he fit that mold. I always talked about if I had the uniform he had on, we'd win it, just me and him by ourselves. I always wanted to play with him.''</p>
        <p>Sheffield has played with Derek Bell, the Mets' right fielder, in the majors and in Little League in Tampa, Fla. The two are still close -- they had dinner together tonight -- and after Bell homered in the first inning, Sheffield answered in the third.</p>
        <p>With one out and one on, Mets starter Rick Reed tried to bounce a curveball on his first pitch to Sheffield. But he left it over the plate, and the left fielder pounced on it, driving it into the left-field bullpen for a two-run homer. The Dodgers led, 2-1.</p>
        <p>Two batters later, Reed's curveball betrayed him again. He had struck out Eric Karros with it in the first and wanted the pitch outside. It was not, and Karros ripped it for another home run. Reed (7-4) did not allow any more runs over seven innings, but he paid for his mistakes.</p>
        <p>''There are some games you get away with a lot,'' Reed said. ''Today was one of those days I didn't get away with them. Other than that, I felt like I did my job: kept us in the game, gave us a chance to win. What more can you ask?''</p>
        <p>Not much, unless Reed could have somehow stopped Park (12-8). After Bell's home run, no Met reached second base until there were two out in the ninth inning. Pitching on seven days' rest after a bout with the flu, Park dominated the Mets with a four-hitter, striking out 10 and walking 2.</p>
        <p>Bell has hit Park well, but three Mets in the lineup had never faced him, and the other four hitters now have a combined .104 career average against him. The Mets' Darryl Hamilton has also hit Park well, but he had mild soreness in his arthritic left big toe and did not play. The Mets were helpless.</p>
        <p>''He kind of pitched us a little backward,'' said center fielder Jay Payton, who singled but was picked off first by catcher Chad Kreuter after a botched hit-and-run in the fifth. ''He has a 95-mile-per-hour fastball and he was throwing breaking balls early in the count. Then, late in the game, he was throwing his fastball up early when guys were looking for breaking balls.''</p>
        <p>The Dodgers gave Park his final run in the eighth, when Pat Mahomes relieved Reed and gave up Sheffield's second home run. With three more homers, he will match Duke Snider's franchise record (43), set in 1956, and surpass his personal high (42), set in 1996.</p>
        <p>Bell said he had never seen Sheffield hit with such power; when Sheffield is getting his pitch, Bell said, he is not missing it.</p>
        <p>''I always tell everybody, if my homeboy stays healthy, he'll put up some awesome numbers,'' Bell said. ''That's what he's doing this year.''</p>
        <p>Piazza watches Sheffield's bat speed and patience with admiration. The big deal of 1998 is no big deal now. Sheffield is welcome to his records, Piazza seemed to say. His Dodgers days are a memory.</p>
        <p>''Trades are a part of the game,'' Piazza said. ''I'm really oblivious to it.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Mets left-hander MIKE HAMPTON will try to throw in the bullpen on Sunday if he feels better than he did on Saturday. But Hampton, who left Thursday's start in the fourth inning with a stress fracture in his right ribs, showed no improvement Saturday and might not make Tuesday's start. ''If I'm too sore, I'm not going to try to be a tough guy,'' Hampton said. Manager BOBBY VALENTINE said PAT MAHOMES's one-inning relief outing Saturday will not preclude him from a spot start Tuesday, but the Class AAA Norfolk pitchers GRANT ROBERTS and BOBBY M. JONES are being considered.</p>
        <p>Negotiations have stalled between the Mets and their first-round draft pick, the Loyola Marymount left-hander BILLY TRABER. Traber can return to school before the end of the month, and if he enrolls in classes, the Mets will lose rights to him. The Mets are hesitant to give Traber a large bonus because of concerns about his elbow, but the club is still hoping it can sign him and send him to instructional league next month.</p>
        <p>The two Mets under consideration for the United States Olympic baseball team, which will be announced next week, are first baseman MARK JOHNSON and the right-handed pitcher TYLER WALKER from Norfolk. Johnson has been up with the Mets twice this year, and if they decide they want him for September, he will not play in the Olympics. The Mets are not thinking of promoting Walker this year.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
