<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Samantha Atkins, Kenneth Ahdoot</title>
    <meta content="20ATKI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224030"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ATKINS, SAMANTHA WESLEE (SAMANTHA WESLEE AHDOOT)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">AHDOOT, KENNETH MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE2DE123EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Samantha Atkins, Kenneth Ahdoot</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Samantha Weslee Atkins, the daughter of Linda Keep Atkins and Dr. Jerry Atkins of New York, was married last evening to Dr. Kenneth Michael Ahdoot, a son of Deborah Ahdoot of Port Republic, Md., and Dr. Habib Ahdoot of Alexandria, Va. Rabbi Bonnie Cohen officiated at the home of the bride's family in Woodstock, N.Y.</p>
        <p>The bride and the bridegroom, both graduates of the Georgetown University School of Medicine, are residents at the New England Medical Center in Boston, she in pediatrics and he in obstetrics and gynecology. The bride, 30, graduated from Wesleyan University; the bridegroom, 28, from the University of Virginia at Charlottesville.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dr. Samantha Weslee Atkins, the daughter of Linda Keep Atkins and Dr. Jerry Atkins of New York, was married last evening to Dr. Kenneth Michael Ahdoot, a son of Deborah Ahdoot of Port Republic, Md., and Dr. Habib Ahdoot of Alexandria, Va. Rabbi Bonnie Cohen officiated at the home of the bride's family in Woodstock, N.Y.</p>
        <p>The bride and the bridegroom, both graduates of the Georgetown University School of Medicine, are residents at the New England Medical Center in Boston, she in pediatrics and he in obstetrics and gynecology. The bride, 30, graduated from Wesleyan University; the bridegroom, 28, from the University of Virginia at Charlottesville.</p>
        <p>The bride's father, a psychiatrist, has a practice in New York and is a partner in Atkins &amp; Breskin, a New York real estate development firm. Her mother is a psychoanalyst practicing in New York and the author of ''Jamaica and Me: The Story of an Unusual Friendship'' (Random House, 1998), a memoir of her relationship with a homeless child and her journey through the child welfare system of New York City.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom's mother is a psychiatric nurse at Fairfax (Va.) Hospital. His father, an obstetrician and gynecologist, works in a group practice in Alexandria. The bridegroom is a stepson of Anne Ahdoot.</p>
        <p>The couple's romance began amid a swirl of formaldehyde and bright lights. They met in an anatomy class in 1995, at the beginning of their freshman year of medical school.</p>
        <p>''I thought he was cute, and so I would go over to check out his cadaver and ask questions,'' Dr. Atkins said. To draw his attention away from the bodies, she ''made a point of wearing make-up to class,'' she remembered. The class met three times a week, and her presence was not unnoticed, yet he showed no overt romantic interest in her. ''I decided to play it cool,'' he said.</p>
        <p>After about a month, she took the scalpel by the blade and asked him to join her on what she now calls their first date: to study a human skull for class. He accepted. Other ''dates'' included a study of an arm and a study of a leg.</p>
        <p>Their first conventional date followed an anatomy exam. The couple went to a restaurant in Georgetown, the neighborhood in Washington that surrounds the school. During the celebratory dinner, the affection that had been held in check for three months began to bubble up.</p>
        <p>''She used to be an actress, so she is more of a liberal spirit,'' Dr. Ahdoot said. ''She is not the conservative, bookworm type that you usually find in med school.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Atkins liked that he was ''smart, but not arrogant.''</p>
        <p>After dating about two years, they hit their first real rough patch. It was time to think about where they were going to do their residencies, a process that medical school students call the match. Students can apply for programs either as individuals or in pairs. Requesting a match as a couple is viewed as practically a pre-engagement announcement.</p>
        <p>''In medical school it is common for people to get the 'pre-match jitters,' '' Dr. Ahdoot said. ''There are a lot of breakups going on around that time.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Atkins added, ''We had to make a life decision, and both got cold feet. We were afraid to make the final commitment of matching together.''</p>
        <p>And so, in January 1998, they split up.</p>
        <p>That June, while on vacation in Ireland, Dr. Atkins reflected on the relationship. When she returned she told Dr. Ahdoot she wanted to get back together.</p>
        <p>''I was a little upset that it took six months,'' he said. ''But deep down I was happy.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
