<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Small Town Comes Up Big In Baseball</title>
    <meta content="20LITT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224147"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Little League</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Goffstown (Nh)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, James C Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Little League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E3DB103EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1575" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Small Town Comes Up Big In Baseball</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES C. McKINLEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, James C Jr</byline>
      <dateline>GOFFSTOWN, N.H., Aug. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coaches and Little League officials in Goffstown, NH, say victory by small town's team in Eastern Regional championship caps five-year drive to make team national contender; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the all-star team from this town on the outskirts of Manchester won the Eastern Regional championship on Thursday night in Bristol, Conn., and a ticket to the Little League World Series, it was hard to tell who was more excited -- the 11- and 12-year-olds who mobbed their pitcher on the mound or the parents in the grandstands.</p>
        <p>''Unbelievable,'' Mark Collins, the vice president of the league and the father of the pitcher, Ben Collins, said over and over. ''This was David and Goliath and we won. Unreal.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the all-star team from this town on the outskirts of Manchester won the Eastern Regional championship on Thursday night in Bristol, Conn., and a ticket to the Little League World Series, it was hard to tell who was more excited -- the 11- and 12-year-olds who mobbed their pitcher on the mound or the parents in the grandstands.</p>
        <p>''Unbelievable,'' Mark Collins, the vice president of the league and the father of the pitcher, Ben Collins, said over and over. ''This was David and Goliath and we won. Unreal.''</p>
        <p>Despite the stunned reactions of the parents and coaches from Goffstown, the team's 1-0 victory over a team from the Bronx was no fluke. It had as much to do with the efforts of adults in the stands as with their children on the field. Coaches and league officials say it capped a five-year campaign to make their team a national contender.</p>
        <p>''It's one thing to go out there and teach them the game,'' the manager of the team, Frank Szumiesz, said. ''But fun is not only playing the sport. It's striving to win.''</p>
        <p>''We were on a mission for the last five years to get to where we are,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Szumiesz said a core group of league officials decided in 1995 that they wanted their league to become a contender for the state championship. They were spurred on by their rivalry with neighboring Bedford, which won the state title in 1993 and went to the Little League World Series. The Goffstown coaches went to school on more successful programs in New Hampshire, borrowing drills and coaching tips and adopting voluntary indoor practices in the winter.</p>
        <p>''We looked at some of the other towns that had quality programs and we weren't afraid to ask questions,'' one of the Goffstown coaches, Phil Bradley, said.</p>
        <p>The league also expanded and improved its five fields, which had been built years before. Three years ago, the organizers drummed up about $20,000 in donations from local businesses to put lights on one field to allow for later practices and night games.</p>
        <p>They also set up a Web site for coaches, referring them to the latest information on coaching, and sent some coaches to Little League seminars.</p>
        <p>''There definitely has been a concerted effort,'' said Collins, 40, a physical therapist who has coached his son Ben's teams for eight years. ''We have a great group of talented kids, but for us to get to this point a lot of other factors went into it.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most important change was to begin pushing the best players to work on fundamentals outside the baseball season. ''You have to be concerned with baseball all year round,'' said Bradley, a 53-year-old Federal Aviation Administration employee.</p>
        <p>For the last three years, many of the boys on the championship team have spent every Sunday morning from January until April at an indoor practice facility, built in an old Manchester mill, called Good Rips. (It helped that one of its owners was Tom French, a coach whose son, Tom, is on the all-star team.) On snow-covered mornings, the core of the team arrived at 7:30 a.m. to practice their swings in eight batting cages and hone their pitching techniques on two indoor dirt mounds. They also performed fielding drills, snapping up ground balls and throwing into socklike targets representing first base. Those weeks of extra work, while voluntary, proved invaluable, the coaches said.</p>
        <p>The league has also used school gyms in the winter for fielding and pitching seminars. League officials even tried a fall program two years ago, but found the players were getting burned out and dropped the idea.</p>
        <p>Little League baseball has been helped by the absence of other strong sports programs in Goffstown, a community of 15,600. The youth hockey program started only a year ago, and soccer has not caught on here as it has in other towns.</p>
        <p>The local high school lacks a football team, but it won state championships this year in basketball and baseball. The girls' high school softball program has also chalked up several state titles. One Goffstown resident, Morris Allard, built a private stadium for the state Babe Ruth League baseball championships.</p>
        <p>Baseball is so ingrained in the local fabric that the town holds a parade, complete with marching bands and a barbecue, for the opening day of the Little League and Babe Ruth League seasons. On Friday nights, the Little League games are often well attended by people who do not have children on the teams, but come out for an evening of baseball and the simple pleasure of a hot dog from the concession stand. The league has more than 100 volunteers.</p>
        <p>''In the spring, the whole town turns to baseball,'' Bradley said. ''It's hard to emphasize how special baseball is in Goffstown.''</p>
        <p>That was evident today along the main street where business owners were putting up banners congratulating the team.</p>
        <p>''People are so excited,'' said Robbie Grady, who oversees a program helping to refurbish the town center. ''I've had several phone calls today saying we need to do a parade. How are we going to do this? It was the talk of the local coffee shops.''</p>
        <p>Grady said support for the Little League program was part of a larger trend of civic-minded efforts in Goffstown. For example, residents recently raised $200,000 to pay for the treatment of a 13-year-old boy, Evan Kavenell, who had a rare form of brain cancer.</p>
        <p>Even though it is a bedroom community for Manchester, Goffstown is not a run-of-the-mill suburb of tract housing and strip malls. The residents include bricklayers and stonemasons and high-technology executives. The town is carved out of the hilly forested country west of Manchester and includes the Uncanoonuc Mountains. The Piscatoquog River runs through the heart of town, green, deep and cold.</p>
        <p>At one end of Goffstown is the quaint row of Colonial buildings and churches around the commons. Although some of the buildings need painting, Goffstown's center brings to mind an idyllic New England hamlet where baseball would surely be played on grass in the golden dusk as it was meant to be, with the whack of horsehide on wood and cleats stirring up the dust.</p>
        <p>At the other of town is Pinardville, a nondescript commercial strip of shopping malls and supermarkets just across the river from the old textile mills of Manchester. In between lies the New Hampshire State Prison for Women.</p>
        <p>The Goffstown Junior Baseball fields are just down the road from the prison, sandwiched between the main road and a gash of forest, opposite a power substation. On the outfield fences are signs of local sponsors: True Value Hardware, Blue Ribbon Fencing, J &amp; G Roofing, Goffstown Auto Parts.</p>
        <p>But for all the effort that parents have made, Goffstown has not poured money into its baseball program like some Little League powerhouses. Toms River, N.J., spent more than $308,000 on a new field and an indoor practice facility. That team won the world series in 1998.</p>
        <p>Still, the baseball program here has become a powerhouse, in part by people working together. The Goffstown group going to Williamsport, Pa., for the Little League World Series, which begins Sunday, has been playing together for five years. As 10-year-olds, they were champions of the New Hampshire Little League Division I and were runners-up for the state championship.</p>
        <p>At that point, the fathers and coaches of the boys began to believe they could make it to the World Series.</p>
        <p>''We had this 10-year-old team that were district champs and runner-up in the state,'' said Scott Desjarlais, whose son, Stephen, is the team's catcher. ''We knew the team had the talent to do this. We knew we could compete at that level.''</p>
        <p>The critical decision was made to keep the players focused on improving their baseball fundamentals even through the long winters and cold springs.</p>
        <p>''The thing that we work on the most from Day 1 is fundamentals,'' said Howard Sobolov, a football coach in Hudson, N.H., who has helped coach the all-star team and whose son, Alex, is on the team. ''As soon as the regular season ends and we pick the all-star team, we are going right back to fundamentals.''</p>
        <p>Between June 15, when the all-star team was chosen, and July 3, when the tournaments leading to the World Series began, the boys practiced every day and twice on many days, Sobolov said.</p>
        <p>The players' parents say they try to instill good sportsmanship and say it matters not whether you win or lose, but how you play. Still, the zeal with which the parents have pursued victory for their children begs a question: why do so many people care so much about a children's league?</p>
        <p>''We all have a passion for this sport,'' Szumiesz said. ''We are all baseball nuts.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
