<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Alabama Victory, Jostle Steps to Head of the Class</title>
    <meta content="MB002112" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224198"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alabama Stakes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE3D9103EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="999" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Alabama Victory, Jostle Steps to Head of the Class</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>SARATOGA SPRINGS, N.Y., Aug. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jostle wins Alabama Stakes at Saratoga; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With 10 minutes to post time of the 120th running of the Alabama, Saratoga's showcase race for 3-year-old fillies, Jostle, the 2-1 second choice on the morning line, was inexplicably 7-1 on the tote board today.</p>
        <p>Just minutes before the start of the Grade I race, Jostle was still listed at 4-1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With 10 minutes to post time of the 120th running of the Alabama, Saratoga's showcase race for 3-year-old fillies, Jostle, the 2-1 second choice on the morning line, was inexplicably 7-1 on the tote board today.</p>
        <p>Just minutes before the start of the Grade I race, Jostle was still listed at 4-1.</p>
        <p>''My oldest son, Blaine, looked up at me and said, 'Dad, they're not respecting us much,' '' John Servis, Jostle's trainer, said after watching his charge cement her credentials as the top 3-year-old filly in training with a surprisingly easy three-and-three-quarter-length victory over her heavily favored archrival, Secret Status. ''I said, 'That's good.' Now, maybe she'll get the respect she deserves.''</p>
        <p>Eventually sent off as the 7-2 second choice, Jostle returned $9.50 to win, $3.40 to place, and $2.70 to show, as she covered the mile and a quarter in 2 minutes 4.72 seconds. Secret Status pulled a length in front of Spain for second, as Spain held off Critical Eye by a head for third. Classy Cara, Resort, Sincerely and Valleydar completed the order of finish of the $750,000 race.</p>
        <p>The winner's share of $450,000 in the $750,000 race pushed Jostle's career earnings over the $1 million mark to $1,118,170 for her owners, Fox Hill Farms. But it was almost as if the crowd of 35,226 here today felt that Jostle's front-running three-and-a-quarter-length victory in the mile and a half Grade 1 Coaching Club American Oaks at Belmont on July 22, a performance that was four lengths better than that of third-place Secret Status, was a fluke.</p>
        <p>In front of a crowd of 35,226 today, Jostle toyed with her seven rivals for her seventh career victory in 12 starts, and second in three meetings with Secret Status, whose only victory over Jostle came in their first meeting. That was in the Grade I Mother Goose, at Belmont, July 1.</p>
        <p>But Secret Status was again no match for Jostle here today. And this time, Jostle did not even need the early lead to carry the day.</p>
        <p>Instead, the jockey Mike Smith was quite content to rate Jostle in third through the first three-quarters of a mile, as Secret Status's stablemate, Valleydar, set not-fast-enough fractions of :24.10, :48.75 and 1:13.22 over the first six furlongs of the race.</p>
        <p>''When I saw what they went the first quarter in, and Jostle was that close, I thought that was a genius move by Mike,'' Servis said.</p>
        <p>''The race unfolded like I pictured it in my mind,'' Smith said. ''Jostle proved today that she has no problem rating off the pace. And I actually think she's a better horse when she does rate.''</p>
        <p>So must Neil Howard, the trainer of Secret Status and Valleydar.</p>
        <p>''Jostle is a nice filly, there's no two ways about it,'' Howard said.</p>
        <p>Not only was Valleydar unsuccessful in her role as rabbit, but also Secret Status's jockey, Pat Day, was forced to keep much closer to the pace. ''They were walking,'' Day said. ''There was no pace in the race. My filly jumped right in.''</p>
        <p>And then right back out.</p>
        <p>The result was that Secret Status was third after a quarter-mile, fourth after a half, fifth after three-quarters, and her anticipated final rally came up far short.</p>
        <p>Jostle, meanwhile, was able to put away the D. Wayne Lukas-trained filly, Spain, heading off the far turn and into the homestretch, after both had dispatched Valleydar at the start of the far turn. And Smith only needed to tap Jostle twice midway through the stretch as she pulled away.</p>
        <p>''I was really surprised she won as easily as she did,'' said Servis, who bases his stable out of Philadelphia Park in Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>The victory was the 41-year-old trainer's first at Saratoga, long considered the elite of American racetracks. ''This is a nice way to break your maiden,'' Servis said.</p>
        <p>After the race, Servis threw out the possibility that he might not enter Jostle in the Breeders' Cup, where she would run against older mares. But, after today's performance, it was clear that Jostle had nothing to prove in her own division.</p>
        <p>''As far as the 3-year-old filly championship goes,'' Servis said, ''I don't know what else you could ask for.''</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Chester House Wins</p>
        <p>ARLINGTON HEIGHTS, Ill., Aug. 19 -- (AP)</p>
        <p>Chester House won the Arlington Million today, squeezing through a small opening at the top of the stretch and moving past the small but congested field.</p>
        <p>The 5-year-old son of Mr. Prospector captured the 18th running of the lucrative race by three and a quarter lengths, giving the jockey Jerry Bailey his second big victory of the day and ending the trainer Robert Frankel's 0-12 streak in the Million.</p>
        <p>Chester House won the one-and-a-quarter-mile turf race -- held for the first time since 1997 -- in 2:01.37. His winner's share of the $2 million purse was $1.2 million.</p>
        <p>Manndar, at 3-1, finished second and Mula Gula, at 25-1, third. Chester House, at 7-2, returned $9.60, $4.40 and $3.40. Manndar returned $4 and $3, and Mula Gula $4.60 paid to show.</p>
        <p>''You never know until the moment of truth whether you can get through the hole; and the older you are, the smaller the holes are,'' said Bailey, who earlier today won the $500,000 Beverly D. aboard Snow Polina. ''You either make it or not. That's when you look like a hero or a goat. The question is whether you have enough acceleration to get through. You know the hole won't stay open too long.''</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
