<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If a Transaction Goes Sour, Where Do You Turn?</title>
    <meta content="20SEBA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ebay Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E2DE123EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If a Transaction Goes Sour, Where Do You Turn?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes services eBay utilizes to help protect successful bidders against disappointment; Internet auction site claims less than one percent of sales involve fraud; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE diamond advertised by ''mrwatch'' on eBay was precisely what Robert and Teri La Plant wanted.</p>
        <p>A 1.41 carat marquise-cut diamond that was of good quality and could be used to upgrade her old engagement ring for their 10th wedding anniversary last September. They were told by mrwatch, a seller of estate jewelry, that the diamond had not been artificially enhanced and, though it had a small flaw, it was described as not visible to the naked eye.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE diamond advertised by ''mrwatch'' on eBay was precisely what Robert and Teri La Plant wanted.</p>
        <p>A 1.41 carat marquise-cut diamond that was of good quality and could be used to upgrade her old engagement ring for their 10th wedding anniversary last September. They were told by mrwatch, a seller of estate jewelry, that the diamond had not been artificially enhanced and, though it had a small flaw, it was described as not visible to the naked eye.</p>
        <p>The La Plants checked mrwatch's feedback rating, which had more than 600 positive responses, zero neutral comments and one negative comment. So they felt that mrwatch, who is now an eBay ''power seller'' -- one who has achieved certain levels of sales and service -- would be a safe bet. For reassurance, they checked eBay's insurance and fraud policies. EBay insures an item for up to $175 ($200, less a $25 deductible), but Mr. La Plant was pleased to find that the company pledged to remove sellers involved in cases in which insurance was paid out.</p>
        <p>He was soon disappointed. When his $2,950 purchase disintegrated into finger-pointing over who was responsible for a chip in the diamond, Mr. La Plant said, he received no support from eBay. Even today, he added, the seller, despite an insurance payment in the case, has never been removed or suspended.</p>
        <p>Mr. La Plant, who lives in the Houston area, is trying to organize a class action suit against eBay, contending that it failed to act against fraud, particularly when it comes to big sellers. Ebay is currently facing a class action lawsuit in California that contends that it failed to act against sale of fake sports memorabilia despite years of warnings. The suit contends that designations like ''power seller'' give buyers a false sense of security.</p>
        <p>Robert Chesnut, associate general counsel for eBay, said the company has several services to protect buyers. Three were in place at the time of Mr. La Plant's purchase -- the feedback system providing buyer comments about transactions, an escrow service to hold funds until deals are successfully concluded and the insurance policy, which is free.</p>
        <p>But, Mr. Chesnut said, eBay does not become directly involved in trying to resolve such situations. Instead, when fraud is suspected, he said, eBay tries to facilitate notification of law enforcement officials.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chesnut disputed Mr. La Plant's accusation that the site goes easy on power sellers, noting that he personally had suspended dozens of such sellers in the last year. Mrwatch was not suspended -- although Mr. La Plant said he was told in an e-mail message that action would be taken if a claim were paid -- because mrwatch has a high approval rating, more than 1,800 positive responses and only 8 negatives.</p>
        <p>''Should eBay jump in and say, 'We are not going to let you do business on our Web site because your satisfaction rate is 99 percent'?'' Mr. Chesnut asked, adding, ''We're not in a good position to evaluate in a singular instance who's right and wrong.''</p>
        <p>Mr. La Plant said he found a chip on the diamond immediately after receiving it by U.P.S. and, within an hour, took it to a jeweler for a professional assessment.</p>
        <p>Mr. La Plant returned the diamond and asked for a refund. In response, mrwatch replied that there was nothing wrong with the diamond when it was shipped and accused him of damaging the diamond.</p>
        <p>Al Bagon, who, along with his wife Judy, trades on eBay as mrwatch, said, ''we've done nothing wrong.''</p>
        <p>According to the Bagons, the diamond went out with an appraisal verifying its quality. They speculated that Mr. La Plant received the diamond, thought he overpaid and then either tried to switch the diamond or chipped it himself so he get a refund.</p>
        <p>In response, Mr. La Plant said the appraisal was a year and a half old.  The La Plant dispute is one of many  about sales on eBay. But most involve far less money, and the company has regularly said that less than 1 percent of sales on its site involve fraud.</p>
        <p>Other disappointed customers are more philosophical. Shelley Sangmaster, of Rodeo, Calif., said putting much faith in merchant ratings might be misguided. She said she bought three autographed business cards for about $430 from a highly rated site but never received them.</p>
        <p>''I sort of consider it gambling,'' she said. ''Generally, I stick to things that aren't more than $25. Then, if it doesn't show up, oh well.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
