<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wall Street's Fundamentalists Face a New World</title>
    <meta content="20BERN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224056"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Institutional Investors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Sanford, &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berenson, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DA123EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2651" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wall Street's Fundamentalists Face a New World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX BERENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berenson, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sanford C Bernstein &amp; Co focuses on management of money and offering research to institutional investors; because it is not a true investment bank, it does not face potential conflicts of interest confronted by analysts and researchers at rival firms in its industry; photos; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FAYE I. LANDES had some bad news for investors in Amazon.com.</p>
        <p>On Aug. 9, Ms. Landes, a research analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, told shareholders in Amazon, the online retailer, that a Bernstein-run focus group had found that most Amazon customers believed that the company sold only books and music. The findings called into question Amazon's plans to sell big-profit items like consumer electronics, Ms. Landes argued.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FAYE I. LANDES had some bad news for investors in Amazon.com.</p>
        <p>On Aug. 9, Ms. Landes, a research analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, told shareholders in Amazon, the online retailer, that a Bernstein-run focus group had found that most Amazon customers believed that the company sold only books and music. The findings called into question Amazon's plans to sell big-profit items like consumer electronics, Ms. Landes argued.</p>
        <p>As a result, she issued Bernstein's first report on Amazon, saying it would ''underperform'' the market; its stock fell 6 percent. (Amazon disputes Ms. Landes' conclusions, saying that sales in its new product lines will reach $500 million this year.)</p>
        <p>But for experienced investors, the way Ms. Landes reached her judgment about Amazon was at least as interesting as the call itself.</p>
        <p>A focus group? Convened by Bernstein? An analyst conducting original research on a company she covers?</p>
        <p>Glory be, glory be.</p>
        <p>It is a truth universally acknowledged on Wall Street that original research is on life support. Serious research can be bad for business, as well as expensive. The biggest profit center for investment banks is the hefty fees they charge for underwriting stock offerings and giving financial advice, and analysts put those profits at risk if they publish negative conclusions about the companies that pay the fees.</p>
        <p>Instead, many analysts choose to work hand-in-glove with the companies they cover, designing projections that closely track internal corporate forecasts. At the same time, they rely on executives for tidbits of information about sales and new products, a practice that the Securities and Exchange Commission tried to limit earlier this month.</p>
        <p>Then there's Bernstein. Founded in 1967, the firm, with 1,400 employees, is not a true investment bank. It does not advise on mergers or serve as a lead underwriter on offerings. Instead, Bernstein, based in Midtown Manhattan, focuses on managing money -- and offering research to institutional investors, the fund managers who pay for the reports by sending stock trades and commissions to Bernstein's trading desk.</p>
        <p>As a result, Bernstein and its fans say, the company does not face the potential conflicts of interest confronted by analysts at investment banks like Merrill Lynch and PaineWebber. Its analysts can spend their time on research, not pitching potential investment banking clients. And they can report what they find to portfolio managers without fear of angering those potential banking clients.</p>
        <p>''All I want to do is do research all day long, and that's all they do here,'' said Ms. Landes, who has previously worked for Salomon Smith Barney and Thomas Weisel Partners. ''Things change when you're answering to more than one master. Here we only do one thing. That's the difference.''</p>
        <p>Henry Berghoef, co-manager of the $1.7 billion Oakmark Select mutual fund, said that Bernstein's research is usually ''much more detailed than the typical sell-side research'' and that ''their work has somewhat more credibility.''</p>
        <p>Yet Ms. Landes' bold call left one question unanswered: What did Bernstein think of Amazon earlier this year, as the stock lost more than half its value? Or last year, as Amazon became one of the most heavily traded and closely watched stocks in the United States?</p>
        <p>What did Bernstein think about Amazon? Absolutely nothing, because Bernstein did not cover the company, or any other Internet retailer, until Ms. Landes started working for the firm in May. And Internet retailing is not the only market sector where Bernstein has been absent. With biotechnology companies routinely reporting scientific breakthroughs, Bernstein has no biotechnology analyst. Perhaps most surprising, a combination of turnover and slow hiring has left Bernstein with only three analysts publishing reports on the high-technology sector, which accounts for one-third of the market value of all stocks in the United States. Other firms have dozens of analysts following high technology.</p>
        <p>NOW Bernstein is at a crossroads as it prepares for life under Alliance Capital Management, a fund manager based in New York that agreed in June to buy it for $3.5 billion. Institutional investors are crying out for good fundamental research on the technology stocks that drive American stock markets. Bernstein must either find a way to give it to them -- or watch its prestige and importance, which has waned as the technology sector has grown, continue to dwindle.</p>
        <p>Bernstein's research has won acclaim over the years, both for its willingness to buck convention on the outlook for individual stocks and for its broad, deep analysis of industry trends.</p>
        <p>The best-known stock picks include Gary Black's 1993 prediction that cigarette pricing would come under pressure. It came months before Philip Morris slashed prices on Marlboro, its flagship brand, in a move that caught nearly everyone else by surprise and caused the company's stock to fall by 22 percent in a day. More recently, Bernstein analysts have offered contrarian and correct views on energy stocks and on Qualcomm, which makes software that runs cellular telephones.</p>
        <p>At its best, Bernstein research focuses on important trends rather than on the day-to-day minutiae of new product announcements or weekly sales figures. In addition to using secondhand data from companies, the firm regularly conducts its own focus groups and surveys to gain exclusive insights on where industries are heading. Information seekers find the firm's distinctive black-covered reports pure joy, filled with enough charts to turn anyone who bothers to read them into experts.</p>
        <p>Richard T. Evans, Bernstein's drug company analyst, surveyed more than 100 physicians for a March report that predicted that a crucial new drug from Bristol-Myers Squibb would initially be prescribed less than expected. In May, Bernstein released its annual consumer personal computer survey, a 76-page report complete with 104 charts and graphs, including data on ''PC Extended Service Plan Attachment Rates by Retailer'' and ''Frequency of Cartridge Replacement'' for printers.</p>
        <p>''If you want to do pure Wall Street research, Sanford Bernstein is the only place on Wall Street to work,'' said Steve Galbraith, a Bernstein veteran who left in June to join Morgan Stanley Dean Witter as a strategist. ''It's sort of 'Revenge of the Nerds' -- incredibly bright people who won through analytical excellence.''</p>
        <p>Bernstein has always prided itself on being different from larger Wall Street companies. ''Get a copy of our reports and then look at copies of others, and then see where you've learned something,'' said Bernstein's president, Roger Hertog.</p>
        <p>The firm looks for ''people for whom the pursuit of truth is important,'' said Marc Mayer, the senior vice president who oversees Bernstein's research department, at an interview at Bernstein's headquarters last week.</p>
        <p>He added: ''We want a certain type of personal integrity, iconoclastic nature, comfort with controversy. Sometimes, he said, the firm takes itself too seriously. ''At the end of day,'' he said, ''we're trying to forecast earnings for companies,'' not cure cancer.</p>
        <p>Sallie Krawcheck, Bernstein's research director, said, ''The goal is to think deeply, to be creative, to be thought-provoking.''</p>
        <p>IN practice, those goals mean that Bernstein rarely hires from other Wall Street firms, preferring to find its analysts in the industries they will be covering. It is usually slow to hire, requiring many rounds of interviews. After hiring, it gives new analysts as long as a year to deepen their knowledge about the industries before they publish ratings on specific companies.</p>
        <p>In addition, Bernstein's research department is relatively small and tightknit. The firm has about 30 analysts covering both domestic and international stocks, compared with hundreds of analysts at firms like Goldman, Sachs. That reduces the risk of turf battles, Ms. Krawcheck said.</p>
        <p>''We try to hire the very best and give them a lot of room,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Jaine Mehring, a former Bernstein analyst who now covers the food industry for Salomon Smith Barney, half-jokingly calls Bernstein a cult. ''It was a great place to learn to be an analyst, because you're very protected from other constituencies,'' Ms. Mehring said. ''But it was very enclosed, cloistered in a way.''</p>
        <p>Despite the firm's strengths, its franchise is under strain.</p>
        <p>In 1994, Bernstein's 19 analysts occupied 24 of 529 places in Institutional Investor magazine's All-America Research Team survey, an important gauge of sentiment among the money managers who are the audience for the company's research. While larger investment banks had more ranked analysts than Bernstein, the firm's ratio of rankings to analysts -- better than one to one -- was the best on Wall Street.</p>
        <p>But in 1999, Bernstein's 18 analysts won only 12 of 429 places in the magazine's survey, half as many as five years earlier. Four other firms had a higher percentage.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Bernstein has suffered a notable loss of talent, with several of the firm's best-known analysts leaving for potentially bigger paydays at other financial firms. Weston Hicks, a first-teamer for six consecutive years, headed to J. P. Morgan. So did third-teamer Tod Jacobs, Bernstein's only ranked analyst in telecommunications or technology. Other recent departures include an auto analyst, Gary Lapidus; a bank analyst, Moshe Orenbuch;  and Mr. Galbraith, who covered consumer companies.</p>
        <p>The loss of that much talent would crimp even the largest research departments on Wall Street. For Bernstein, the departures have punched noticeable holes in its coverage. Many of the analysts who remain at the firm focus on staid industries like metals or savings institutions.</p>
        <p>Rick Schutte, who parlayed a stint at Bernstein into a career as a computer industry analyst at PaineWebber and Goldman, Sachs before leaving Goldman earlier this year to become a money manager, said he deeply respects the research that Bernstein produces. But he does not read it, because it does not focus on the industries he cares about. ''If they had some more tech analysts, I would definitely read their stuff,'' Mr. Schutte said.</p>
        <p>Bernstein is hardly down for the count. The report by Ms. Landes last week won widespread attention. But at best, Bernstein has missed an opportunity to meet a growing demand for technology research. At worst, the firm faces a slow death of its unique culture, as its best remaining analysts leave for other Wall Street firms more quickly than Bernstein can train replacements.</p>
        <p>To fill holes in its coverage of technology, communications and health care, Bernstein recently hired four analysts -- one each for software, computer services, medical-device makers and international drug companies. It is actively seeking a biotechnology analyst.</p>
        <p>''More tech and more telecom is on the way,'' Ms. Krawcheck said.</p>
        <p>But hiring analysts will not solve Bernstein's problem, unless the firm can keep its employees -- old and new -- from jumping to larger investment banks. Until a couple of years ago, that was not a problem. Bernstein paid competitively, and its culture appealed to many analysts.</p>
        <p>''I have half the responsibilities of my colleagues, but I get paid the same amount,'' said Lisa Shallet, a Bernstein analyst who covers capital goods companies like Caterpillar. ''I'm never here at midnight working on the deal.''</p>
        <p>But in technology and telecommunications, where the fees for investment banking and underwriting are flooding firms like Goldman, Sachs, Bernstein is having an increasingly difficult time paying competitively.</p>
        <p>One person who recently left Bernstein for another firm said he doubled his pay at the new job. In addition, Bernstein has been stingy in distributing equity to employees. Before the sale to Alliance Capital, employees said, most of the company was owned by the chief executive, Lewis Sanders; Mr. Hertog; and the estate of the founder, Zalman Chaim Bernstein.</p>
        <p>''This certainly was not and is not an egalitarian partnership a la Goldman Sachs,'' Ms. Shallet said.</p>
        <p>The Alliance deal might alleviate those complaints. Although Alliance is controlled by AXA, a diversified French financial services company, Alliance shares are publicly traded. So the new Alliance Bernstein would be able to offer Bernstein employees stock options comparable to those of other publicly traded companies -- if it chose to do so. An AXA spokesman declined to comment on his company's plans for Bernstein, noting that the takeover would not be completed until the fall.</p>
        <p>Even if Bernstein can pay its analysts competitively, it may face a more subtle problem in analyzing biotechnology and other fast-changing sectors. In those industries, investment bankers often see companies before analysts do, because the young companies come to them to raise money. That gives analysts at full-service investment banks a source of information that Bernstein researchers do not have, said Mr. Jacobs, the former Bernstein telecommunications analyst who is now J. P. Morgan's telecommunications strategist.</p>
        <p>Bernstein analysts do not cover small new companies, which are important in fast-growing industries. ''In an area like telecom, you miss too much of what's going on if you just cover large-cap companies,'' Mr. Jacobs said.</p>
        <p>Vadim Zlotnikov, Bernstein's top technology analyst, said his firm keeps smaller technology companies on its radar screen. But he added that Bernstein's priority is covering large firms, both because many small companies do not survive and because big institutional investors are much more interested in coverage of large companies where they can make big bets.</p>
        <p>''We don't get paid to follow the smallest of the small guys,'' he said.</p>
        <p>BERNSTEIN must also adapt to the fact that Wall Street's attention span is shorter than ever. Each day, newspapers report mutual fund prices, giving investors an instant score card on their funds' performance. And a year or two of bad performance can destroy even hedge-fund managers with decades of success, like Julian H. Robertson Jr. of Tiger Management. The resulting short-term attitude of managers plays to the strengths of analysts who follow every tick of a company's sales, rather than to Bernstein's traditional focus on the big picture.</p>
        <p>Despite the recent defections and Bernstein's slippage in Institutional Investor, Ms. Krawcheck says the firm's future is brighter than ever. Bernstein's new analysts will bring the firm's intellectual rigor to technology, where analysis independent of investment banking relationships is at a premium, she said.</p>
        <p>A new S.E.C. rule that requires companies to disclose sensitive information more freely would also help Bernstein, by preventing companies from offering extra information to favored analysts, Ms. Krawcheck said. In that environment, she added, Bernstein's proprietary studies and research would stand out even more.</p>
        <p>In fact, she said, Bernstein plans to increase its use of focus groups, surveys and other proprietary research, and the firm is well aware that it must offer investors insights into both long-term trends and short-term trading opportunities.</p>
        <p>''The value of doing the stuff that we do has just increased,'' Ms. Krawcheck said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
