<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Dancers in Their 80's Turn Into Time Travelers</title>
    <meta content="20BUZZ$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: FLUSHING -- BUZZ"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Selfhelp Benjamin Rosenthal Senior Center (Flushing, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'grady, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E4DF123EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Dancers in Their 80's Turn Into Time Travelers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM O'GRADY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'grady, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene at Selfhelp Benjamin Rosenthal Senior Center in Flushing, Queens, described as seniors dance in makeshift ballroom to tunes spun by 90-year-old DJ Irving Langsner; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE SETTING  -- Wednesday afternoon in the auditorium of the Selfhelp Benjamin Rosenthal Senior Center, where 25 elderly couples dance with a faraway look in their eyes.</p>
        <p>Standing aside from the dancers' patterned whorls, you can almost see a dream sequence playing out on  their retinas. It is 1940 at the Roseland Ballroom as 25 lithe-limbed couples, lit by mirror-splintered light, trip to the big-band sound. They are wiry and flush. They throw their heads back as they swing and never tire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE SETTING  -- Wednesday afternoon in the auditorium of the Selfhelp Benjamin Rosenthal Senior Center, where 25 elderly couples dance with a faraway look in their eyes.</p>
        <p>Standing aside from the dancers' patterned whorls, you can almost see a dream sequence playing out on  their retinas. It is 1940 at the Roseland Ballroom as 25 lithe-limbed couples, lit by mirror-splintered light, trip to the big-band sound. They are wiry and flush. They throw their heads back as they swing and never tire.</p>
        <p>Then it's 2000, and the music stops. The dancers untangle and shuffle toward a table near a wall decorated with faded cardboard flags. Panting, they line up for coffee and marble pound cake.</p>
        <p>THE BUZZ  -- If you Lindy-hop and fit in with a group whose average age  is 80, the center is the place to be on Wednesdays from 1 to 4 p.m. That is when Irving Langsner, 90, spins tunes that demand coordinated movement. Waltzes, merengues, mambos and the sounds of Nat King Cole and Lawrence Welk. Mr. Langsner plays them all. He presides from a raised stage strung with Christmas lights and puff-plastic musical notes.</p>
        <p>''Mambo No. 5!'' he shouted as a Latin rhythm filled the room. They clinched and started to glide.</p>
        <p>Mr. Langsner, who opened the makeshift ballroom 10 years ago, is a retired butcher from East Harlem. He briefly worked the vaudeville circuit in the early 1930's as a hoofer and comedian.</p>
        <p>Asked to tell a vaudeville joke, he offered a story filled with Yiddish puns and the vocalization of bodily functions that cannot be repeated here. He hinted at dark activities during Prohibition.</p>
        <p>''Here he is, Irving's right hand!'' Mr. Langsner shouted. (Because of hearing impairments and the volume of the music, everyone shouts at the center.) He introduced Bill Sternberg, 82, who was in labor camps in Yugoslavia and Hungary during World War II.</p>
        <p>''I entertain the old ladies,'' Mr. Sternberg said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Langsner spotted Gloria Osborne, age willfully obscured, making her way across the stage. ''This is my little chippy,'' he said, and grabbed her around the waist.</p>
        <p>Ms. Osborne smiled, but pushed Mr. Langsner off and broke into a single-time tap dance step. She was graceful in pearls and a flower-print dress.</p>
        <p>''She wants to go on Broadway,'' Mr. Sternberg said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Langsner said, ''I'll be her booking agent.''</p>
        <p>Then he grabbed the microphone and announced to the dancers that it was time for a break. A cry came up from the crowd: ''One more. One more!''</p>
        <p>JIM O'GRADY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: FLUSHING -- BUZZ</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
