<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Puzzlement In a Land Where Rates Seldom Rise</title>
    <meta content="20INSI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224012"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET INSIGHT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Scudder Kemper Investments</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bank of Japan</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Allan, Elizabeth J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Insight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E3D6153EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Puzzlement In a Land Where Rates Seldom Rise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kenneth N Gilpin Market Insight column interviews Elizabeth J Allan, Scudder Kemper Investments analyst, regarding Japanese central bank, which recently raised short-term interest rates for the first time in a decade, and Japanese equities; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PUSHING on a string must get tiring. Or maybe just tiresome.</p>
        <p>Admittedly, these are probably not the best attempts to explain why the Bank of Japan decided on Aug. 11 to lift short-term interest rates for the first time in a decade. But they may not be the worst explanations either, since the central bank's loose money approach -- a zero-interest policy had been in effect since February 1999 -- seems to have done little to lift the Japanese economy out of recession.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PUSHING on a string must get tiring. Or maybe just tiresome.</p>
        <p>Admittedly, these are probably not the best attempts to explain why the Bank of Japan decided on Aug. 11 to lift short-term interest rates for the first time in a decade. But they may not be the worst explanations either, since the central bank's loose money approach -- a zero-interest policy had been in effect since February 1999 -- seems to have done little to lift the Japanese economy out of recession.</p>
        <p>The central bank, however, asserts that the economy is showing ''clearer signs of recovery.''</p>
        <p>The Japanese stock market, which should be a leading economic indicator, does not reflect those signs. The Topix index, which hit a 52-week low on Aug. 4, is down more than 14 percent this year in local currency terms.</p>
        <p>Last week, Elizabeth J. Allan, a senior vice president at Scudder Kemper Investments and an analyst for the Japan Fund, talked about the Bank of Japan and the outlook for Japanese equities. Following are excerpts from the conversation:</p>
        <p>Q. The decision by the Bank of Japan has perplexed a lot of very smart folks. Why do you think it raised rates?</p>
        <p>A. Nothing in Japan is ever made explicit, and people are scratching their heads to understand this. But there are a number of interpretations.</p>
        <p>One is that the bank wanted to assert its independence. Masaru Hayami, the governor, had been saying it was abnormal to have zero-interest rates. The subagenda there was the fact the government has been piling up too much debt. In that context, I suspect his thinking was that some cost for that borrowing is different from essentially no cost.</p>
        <p>Another factor to bear in mind is that Japan is an aging country with a lot of people on fixed incomes. They want there to be some kind of return on savings.</p>
        <p>A third explanation is that Mr. Hayami is on a personal mission to force a restructuring of the Japanese corporate and financial structure. The thinking here is that if companies have free cash, they will postpone making hard decisions. By putting a price tag on the cost of money, you are pushing companies to restructure. If you are a company on the edge of bankruptcy, an increase in interest rates of 25 basis points could make a difference.</p>
        <p>Q. The bank seems to think the economy is gaining strength. Do you agree?</p>
        <p>A. It is not clear if the economy is actually recovering. And I don't think anybody expects the rate increase we saw will lead to a series of tightenings. Politically, it would be very difficult for the Bank of Japan to raise interest rates a second time without much more concrete signs of recovery than we have had. That said, the export sector has been extremely strong, as has investment spending in technology by Japanese companies. But private demand remains weak.</p>
        <p>However, as equity investors we are not completely wedded to how the economy does on a macro basis. We see a lot of good things going on at the micro level. A lot of companies are restructuring and are doing things like providing employees with incentive-based compensation.</p>
        <p>And this economy has been in a slump for over 10 years. That means the potential for improvement is large.</p>
        <p>Q. If demand is still slack, how can companies improve the bottom line?</p>
        <p>A. Companies that have a lot of fat are getting rid of it. That means if the economy stays in the doldrums and revenue growth remains stagnant, the bottom line is expanding.</p>
        <p>The Shinko Research Institute did a survey of companies listed on the Tokyo Stock Exchange for the fiscal year ended March 31 that illustrates this point. The companies surveyed showed a 1 percent decline in sales, but a 28.6 percent increase in profits.</p>
        <p>I don't know if the survey is representative or not. But the magnitude of the numbers is impressive.</p>
        <p>Q. Japan was hit hard by the energy crisis in the 1970's. Has the runup in oil prices this year done much damage?</p>
        <p>A. The rise in oil prices has not had much of an impact. The Japanese used to be very dependent on imported oil, and the 1970's were a very scary experience for them. But they have cut their dependence on imported oil a great deal, in part by becoming heavily dependent on nuclear power.</p>
        <p>Q. So far this year, the Japan Fund is down about 10 percent, compared with an average decline of around 19 percent for mutual funds that concentrate on Japan. What are you investing in?</p>
        <p>A. Electrical machinery companies make up about 25 percent of our portfolio, a group that includes stocks like Sony and Kyocera.</p>
        <p>We also have a reasonable position in the banks on the expectation that a lot of bad news is already in the price. Bank of Yokohama is our biggest bank holding.</p>
        <p>And our biggest holding is in Nippon Telegraph and Telephone.</p>
        <p>MARKET INSIGHT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
