<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>They May Not Get This in Des Moines</title>
    <meta content="20SP8NWS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COVER STORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metro (Cable TV Channel)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moyer, Gregory</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E1DE103EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1340" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>They May Not Get This in Des Moines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City cable channel Metro is car</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LORRIE and Bob and Cindy and Brandon are out on a date. There is laughter. A playful argument. Meaningful glances. Holding of hands under the tale, over the table, behind the table. And sharing of the clams and mussels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LORRIE and Bob and Cindy and Brandon are out on a date. There is laughter. A playful argument. Meaningful glances. Holding of hands under the tale, over the table, behind the table. And sharing of the clams and mussels.</p>
        <p>But this is not a double date. Only Lorrie and Bob are out on the date. Cindy and Brandon are recording the date with video cameras. And being paid to do so.</p>
        <p>So goes episode No. 7 of ''Third Date,'' perhaps the most ambitious show from Metro, a cable channel that is trying to reinvent itself with new programming about New York and New Yorkers. Originally a going-out guide on television, with restaurant reviews and what-to-do-with-the-kids features, Metro is now carrying only-in-New-York shows like ''Third Date'' and ''Subway Q &amp; A'' that take television to a local level in a way not seen since individual stations stopped doing dance-party shows a generation ago.</p>
        <p>Metro, one of three MetroChannels (Metro Learning and Metro Traffic &amp; Weather are available only on the Long Island cable systems of their parent company, Cablevision), sees itself as an alternative to local news and sports fare. ''We want to capture the New York experience, and that's not always possible through the prism of journalism,'' said Gregory Moyer, who oversees Metro along with Cablevision's other New York - area operations, including all-news channels in the Bronx, Connecticut, Long Island and New Jersey.</p>
        <p>It helps that Metro is not seen beyond the New York area. ''When we do a comedy showcase,'' Mr. Moyer said, ''we can do jokes people won't get in Des Moines.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Moyer, who exported Discovery Channel to 140 countries in the 1990's, is betting that Metro's New York cachet will make it easy to syndicate shows abroad. ''Subway Q &amp; A,'' for example, could appeal to straphangers in London and Tokyo. The host, Tad Low, who created ''Pop Up Video'' on VH1, heads underground with a camera crew, stopping passengers and asking questions like ''What's the most expensive pair of shoes you've ever bought?'' or ''What's the strangest place you've ever had sex?'' The answers (to the second question, anyway) ranged from - surprise - ''the subway'' to ''I can't believe you asked that question.''</p>
        <p>Not everything in Metro's lineup is hormone-dependent. ''New Joke City With Robert Klein'' is a weekly one-hour series videotaped in comedy clubs. ''Club La Bomba'' is a reincarnation of 1950's television dance shows like ''American Bandstand,'' but with a twist: the M.C. is Sofia Vergara, a mainstay of the Spanish-language network Univision. ''Studio Y'' is a live weekday discussion show for teenagers. ''New York Stories'' is a documentary series about the city that has featured interviews with everyone from the actor John Turturro to Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani. ''Rhythm &amp; Dues'' provides a weekly showcase for New York-based performers.</p>
        <p>The difference in programming between now and 1998, when Metro went on the air (on Cablevision systems only), is especially apparent to someone like me, who was asked to be a guest on a talk show in Metro's early days. As I was leaving for the studio, at 34th Street and Eighth Avenue, my wife said, ''Don't talk about the house.'' There wasn't time to ask what she meant, so I didn't mention our weekend retreat - or our contribution to Long Island's clogged highways. And I didn't say much else to that polite panel - not even the name Buttafuoco, one of those all-purpose words that one can usually work into any conversation about Long Island.</p>
        <p>Now, instead of talking heads in its studio, the new Metro is sending cameras out, and not even as far as Long Island. Having won a place on the Time Warner cable systems in New York City, Metro has a back-to-the-future flavor: this is the closest thing to television the way it was in the 1950's, when television was live and local stations had shows people wanted to be on.</p>
        <p>''There is a great vacuum in local television for material that is about the place where you live,'' said Josh Sapan, Mr. Moyer's boss at Cablevision's Rainbow Media subsidiary. ''It can be entertaining and fanciful and informational. Without criticizing anyone too much, the local television one finds on broadcast television tends to be more tabloid-oriented news or obligatory Sunday-morning do-good-but-inert material. If you ever watched Soupy Sales or Duck Clark, both had their genesis in local markets and were about personalities and getting on TV in the place you lived.''</p>
        <p>Ambitious though it is, Metro's locally produced programming cannot fill the channel's entire schedule. So it is rounding out its prime time lineup with reruns of New York shows, including the classic 1960's sitcom ''Car 54, Where Are You?'' (nightly at 7:30); ''Welcome Back, Kotter,'' the comedy about a Brooklyn teacher and his impossible class of underachievers, which made John Travolta a star (weeknights at 7); ''NY Daze,'' a sitcom about the big dreams of two city slackers originally called ''Too Something'' during its brief run on Fox in 1995 (Wednesdays at 9 p.m.); ''The Days and Nights of Molly Dodd,'' Blair Brown's 80's series, which critics loved (Mondays at 8 p.m.); and ''Central Park West'' (Mondays at 9 p.m.), the short-lived 1995 show from Darren Star, who went on to create ''Sex and the City.''</p>
        <p>As for ''Third Date,'' it is not only local television, it is reality television. But as Steve Rosenbaum, one of the show's executive producers, said: ''This is not 'Survivor.' The greatest compliment you could pay to this show is if you watched it and said it's sweet.''</p>
        <p>The premise of ''Third Date'' is explained in the opening montage: the third date on which two people decide whether they have a future together. As Metro camera crews are discovering, the decision-making is sometimes clumsy and complicated, but Cindy and Brandon seem to be enjoying Lorrie and Bob's date (in an East Village restaurant) as much as Lorri and Bob are. Lorrie - a talkative woman in her 20's who is studying to be an art teacher - does not want her last name used here. ''I really don't want any weirdos out there looking up my phone number,'' she says. (They will not see her last name on ''Third Date'' either; the show uses only first names.) But letting Metro viewers see Bob's every move?</p>
        <p>That was Bob's idead.</p>
        <p>''I was very nervous,'' Lorrie recalled. ''I've honestly never been this close to anyone this soon, and it's kind of funny it was caught on tape.''</p>
        <p>But she liked Cindy and Brandon. ''We just had a good time with them,'' she said. ''By the time we got to dinner, we pretty much ignored the cameras. We thought, should we play it straight? But we decided we're just going to be ourselves.''</p>
        <p>Being themselves is generally not something New Yorkers have a problem with - and Metro's ''Third Date'' and, by coincidence, Metro's third year, may depend on it.</p>
        <p>COVER STORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
