<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Angels' Erstad Hits With All He's Got</title>
    <meta content="20ERST$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Anaheim Angels</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erstad, Darin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Angels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EFDD103EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1170" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Angels' Erstad Hits With All He's Got</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anaheim Angels' Darin Erstad is batting .357 with 189 hits and has chance to approach single-season record for hits, 257, set in 1920; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Darin Erstad decided to give himself a week away from baseball at the end of last season, a major concession. His instinct has always been to try harder, and he had just finished a frustrating season in which he batted .253, and he wanted to know why. He wanted to understand.</p>
        <p>But he forced himself to take a vacation. Seven days, he determined.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Darin Erstad decided to give himself a week away from baseball at the end of last season, a major concession. His instinct has always been to try harder, and he had just finished a frustrating season in which he batted .253, and he wanted to know why. He wanted to understand.</p>
        <p>But he forced himself to take a vacation. Seven days, he determined.</p>
        <p>After four days, he pulled out videotape at his home in Fargo, N.D., and began reviewing his at-bats -- all of his at-bats -- charting the pitches, searching for trends. When he finished the 1999 season, Erstad did the same for all of his at-bats in 1998, and all of his at-bats in 1997 and in 1996. Erstad, who had tried to keep hitting as simple as possible, believes he has developed a better understanding of his swing and his approach, as borne out by his production this year.</p>
        <p>Erstad is batting .357, and with 189 hits and six weeks to play in the regular season, he has a chance to approach the single-season record for hits. George Sisler had 257 hits for the St. Louis Browns in 1920, and if Erstad maintains his current pace, he would finish the year with 249.</p>
        <p>Erstad was 0 for 1 yesterday before leaving the game with a muscle spasm in his left rib cage. But he had two hits Friday, including the game-winning home run off Mike Stanton in the top of the 11th inning, as the Angelscame back from a five-run deficit to beat the Yankees, 9-8.</p>
        <p>Erstad also saved the game for Anaheim in the bottom of the 10th inning by making a spectacular diving catch in left-center field with two outs and the winning run on third base; Roger Clemens called it one of the three best catches he had seen in his 17 years in the majors.</p>
        <p>''He plays so hard,'' Joe Torre, the Yankees' manager, said. ''He's a throwback. I don't think there's ever a day they can hang his jersey in his locker. They've always got to throw it in the washer.''</p>
        <p>In an era when adolescents are often forced to specialize in one particular sport, Erstad is something of a throwback. Growing up in North Dakota, he played hockey and football and baseball.</p>
        <p>''I can't say what my best sport was,'' Erstad said, ''but I can say I was most comfortable on skates.''</p>
        <p>The baseball seasons were short, his instruction simple. Keep your left elbow high when you hit, his father told him, the standard advice given to all kids by their parents. Except that Erstad turned out to be a better athlete than other kids, scoring bundles of goals as a forward in hockey, punting for the University of Nebraska on its national championship team in 1994. In spite of his limited experience in baseball, the Mets drafted him in the 13th round in 1992.</p>
        <p>Erstad stayed in college and was the first pick in the 1995 draft. Yankees catcher Chris Turner was in the Anaheim organization at that time and when Erstad advanced to Class AAA in 1996, Turner and the others waited to see if Erstad was a prima donna, if he would flash around his money. Erstad kept mostly to himself, however, and played hard. Someone brought a hockey net into the Vancouver clubhouse, just for fun, and someone donned the catcher's gear and pretended to be a goalie -- not Turner. The puck they used was small and hard and made of plastic, and Erstad's teammates gawked as he peppered the fringes of the net with slap shots.</p>
        <p>Erstad jumped to the majors in 1996, hit .299 in 1997 and .296 in 1998. He was seen as a potential candidate for the most valuable player award in 1999, but he started slowly and soon scouts chattered about how he seemed to fight himself at the plate, how he turned his intensity on himself and how it hurt him. It's the same thing scouts once said about Yankees right fielder Paul O'Neill.</p>
        <p>''The saying that people always give me is, 'Try easier,' '' said Erstad, sitting at his locker at Yankee Stadium Friday.</p>
        <p>He looked his questioner directly in the eye and continued, evenly. ''But I don't necessarily agree with that,'' he said. ''I've tried that, and I end up standing up there and not having any intensity. You need to have an intensity, a calm intensity.</p>
        <p>''I'm trying to think how to put this into words. It's almost like a volcano -- calm, calm, calm, building, building, building. And then you go to swing and -- bwap!''</p>
        <p>His hands moved, as he mimicked the motion of a swing.</p>
        <p>''Don't go, tight, tight, tight, and then swing,'' he continued. ''It's got to be bop-bop-bop, and then you go. Every time you swing, you want to feel like you're exploding on the ball. Sometimes I do that too early. You see a pitch you want to hit and you try to reach back for more or want to hit it further and harder. I do that, especially on fastballs.''</p>
        <p>Realizing all this, Erstad waited four days after last season before diving into the videotape. ''People had told me, 'Just forget about it like it never happened,' '' Erstad said. ''That just never made any sense to me. So I said, O.K., I'm going to stare this thing in the face and figure out what the heck is going on. You want to know: 'What's going on out there? Why did I stink so badly?' ''</p>
        <p>Erstad does not possess the sweeping, arching swing typical of left-handed batters; rather, he swings with a chopping motion, almost downward. He made some mechanical adjustments he chooses not to discuss, and tried to relax his approach. Rod Carew, the Angels' former hitting coach, told Erstad repeatedly that he should ''take what the pitchers give you'' -- in other words, if there is a tough pitch outside, then hit it to left field, and if you get a good pitch inside, then drive it. ''Maybe I was too stubborn last year,'' Erstad said.</p>
        <p>He singled in his first at-bat this year, against the Yankees, went 9 for 14 in that three-game series and batted .449 in April. He has 62 multihit games, 12 more than any other American League player.</p>
        <p>O'Neill said: ''He's an intense player, and after last year, he came back and really found his confidence in April. He has just battled and battled to the point where he's probably afraid to go back to where he was.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
