<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEHIND THE WHEEL/Lexus IS 300 and Acura 3.2 CL -- Who's That Knock, Knock, Knocking on BMW's Door?; A Facsimile Of Germany's Solid-Gold Sport Sedan</title>
    <meta content="20LEXU$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224026"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lexus Division of Toyota Motor Sales Usa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bayerische Motorenwerke Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neil, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E3DE123EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEHIND THE WHEEL/Lexus IS 300 and Acura 3.2 CL -- Who's That Knock, Knock, Knocking on BMW's Door?; A Facsimile Of Germany's Solid-Gold Sport Sedan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN NEIL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Neil, Dan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dan Neil compares Lexus IS 300 sports sedan to BMW's 328i; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1996, the Bureau of Engraving and Printing began to distribute paper currency that incorporated anticounterfeiting measures like color-shifting ink, microprinting and a security thread woven into the paper. These days, it's nearly impossible to make high-quality money at home.</p>
        <p>It is likewise difficult to reproduce the exact mechanical alchemy that gives certain cars their living spirit. Lexus, for example, put BMW's 328i on its color copier and came up with the IS 300, a car that is nearly identical to the BMW sport sedan in all the crucial dimensions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1996, the Bureau of Engraving and Printing began to distribute paper currency that incorporated anticounterfeiting measures like color-shifting ink, microprinting and a security thread woven into the paper. These days, it's nearly impossible to make high-quality money at home.</p>
        <p>It is likewise difficult to reproduce the exact mechanical alchemy that gives certain cars their living spirit. Lexus, for example, put BMW's 328i on its color copier and came up with the IS 300, a car that is nearly identical to the BMW sport sedan in all the crucial dimensions.</p>
        <p>In height, width and length, the Lexus is within an inch of the BMW. Both cars' profiles are what horse trainers call short-coupled, with compact, athletic dimensions.</p>
        <p>Both are motivated by in-line six-cylinder engines with highly efficient variable valve timing. Both wear oversized antilock disk brakes behind lightweight alloy wheels and low-profile tires. Both interiors are richly appointed with leather and brightwork; both dashboards are jammed with avionics-style displays.</p>
        <p>But the 3-Series's legendary quality is its high-performance handling. Once you are in the Bimmer's deeply bolstered driver's seat, the contoured leather wheel in your hands, it seems that your nerve endings stretch out to each wheel; control becomes less a matter of speculation than a matter of limbic certainty. It's not that the 3-Series has such incomparable limits -- it is, after all, a luxury car on street tires -- but that those limits are so palpable.</p>
        <p>How, exactly, BMW designers achieve such a lyric quality is something even they might find difficult to explain, but if they could bottle it, other companies would buy it. In vigorous cornering, the Bimmer's rear tires slide in a controlled and progressive way, allowing the car to change directions like a skier schussing his way through a slalom. The ability of a car to behave this way, called oversteer, is designed in. Oversteer makes a car more lively and more fun to drive near the limit.</p>
        <p>Most cars are designed with a lot of the opposite quality, understeer, built in -- meaning that in a hard corner the front tires scrub and scuff like a novice skier on the bunny slope. Understeer is inherently safer because it requires less driving skill.</p>
        <p>With 215 horsepower and slightly less weight, the Lexus has a better power-to-weight ratio than the 2000-model BMW. But while it has the mechanical credentials to challenge the 3-Series, the IS 300 ultimately fails to clone the soul of the German car. In aggressive driving, the Lexus tends to plow through tight corners and hairpins, scrubbing the shoulders of its 17-inch Goodyear Eagle GS-D's. It is possible to get the tail to pitch around by chopping the throttle, but when tossed about, the IS 300 never seems as comfortable and controllable as the BMW.</p>
        <p>The Lexus's speed-sensitive steering felt a little leaden, accurate but immoderately heavy, particularly at slow speeds. The 3-Series, with its joystick quickness, remains the gold standard of vehicle dynamics.</p>
        <p>Which isn't to say the Lexus is a slug -- far from it. Even with an automatic transmission, which dampens the flame of any performance car, the IS 300 is gloriously quick. The charcoal-metallic test model had gone more than 3,000 miles and seemed, by benefit of that break-in period, quicker than the cars tested by enthusiast magazines. Motor Trend paced the IS 300 to 60 mph at 7.4 seconds; I saw 7.1 seconds on my handheld stopwatch.</p>
        <p>Deactivate the traction control and the Lexus will smoke the tires nicely. The brakes are fabulous, stout and fade-free, the calipers seizing the ventilated discs with a longshoreman's grip long after the pads begin to stink from the effort. Sitting on a well-damped and tautly sprung suspension, the IS 300 exhibits excellent control of body roll, and the ride is first-rate, cloudlike and supple in the hovercraft way that Lexus has perfected. At its most harried, the IS 300 hums like a transformer.</p>
        <p>About 25,000 Americans are expected to pick up copies of this Lexus, and many will be drawn, no doubt, by the IS 300's haute-couture interior. The car's signature piece is the instrument panel styled like a Breitling chronograph. The IS 300 gives you plenty to look at: the many climate and audio buttons, the drilled-out aluminum foot pedals and a hefty globe of polished aluminum atop the shifter. (Be warned, however, that the shift knob reaches palm-searing temperatures when the car is parked in the summer sun.)</p>
        <p>But ultimately, the IS 300 seems to lack the BMW's maturity and seriousness, a quality that political pundits might call gravitas.</p>
        <p>If the Lexus yields to the BMW in driving pleasure, it surrenders nothing in value. The test car, with leather, sunroof, heated seats and more, came in at $34,635 -- roughly $3,000 less than a comparably equipped 3-Series. And even with the siren call of the BMW's delightful handling, 3 grand is to most buyers a lot of money. Unless they print their own.</p>
        <p>INSIDE TRACK: First-degree forgery.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
