<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>May Is in Contention, But Claims No Jitters</title>
    <meta content="20BOOK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224152"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pga Championship</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">May, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">PGA Championship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EEDB103EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>May Is in Contention, But Claims No Jitters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>LOUISVILLE, Ky. Aug. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Golf Notebook article focuses on strong recent play of Bob May, who is one stroke behind Tiger Woods at PGA Championship (M)1</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sometime during Sunday's final round, Bob May will almost undoubtedly hear someone say this: Who's that guy playing with Tiger Woods?</p>
        <p>May, a 31-year-old native of Lynwood, Calif., has spent most of his professional career playing in Europe. He is competing in his first P.G.A. Championship. Since the spring, May has made 10 consecutive cuts, and he tied for second at the FedEx St. Jude Classic in June.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sometime during Sunday's final round, Bob May will almost undoubtedly hear someone say this: Who's that guy playing with Tiger Woods?</p>
        <p>May, a 31-year-old native of Lynwood, Calif., has spent most of his professional career playing in Europe. He is competing in his first P.G.A. Championship. Since the spring, May has made 10 consecutive cuts, and he tied for second at the FedEx St. Jude Classic in June.</p>
        <p>After a successful 1999 in Europe, including a victory in the British Masters, his first victory as a pro, May brought his confidence with him when he returned to the United States. He says he is not fearful of his impending showdown with Woods.</p>
        <p>''I don't feel intimidated by him at all,'' said May, who shot a 66 today and is one stroke behind Woods. ''I am very impressed with what he can do with the golf ball and how he performs. I am looking forward to playing with him. I haven't had a chance to yet.''</p>
        <p>A Putting Display</p>
        <p>Tom Watson held a share of the course record at Valhalla Golf Club today, for about 90 minutes.</p>
        <p>Shooting a seven-under-par 65, Watson vaulted to five under par after three rounds of the P.G.A. Championship, giving himself a chance to finish in the top 10 at age 50. But a few hours later, Jose Maria Olazabal broke the course record with a 63, stealing Watson's thunder.</p>
        <p>It was an unusual round for Watson, one of the game's premier ball-strikers, but a player who has struggled with his putting at times in his career. Today, Watson had trouble hitting the fairways. But his putting was sensational. He made a 10-footer at No. 2, a 12-footer at No. 6, a  15-footer at No. 7, a 15-footer at No. 10, a 35-footer at No. 12, a  35-footer at No. 15, a 25-footer at No. 17 and a 12-footer at No. 18.</p>
        <p>On the back nine, he knew he had a chance to equal the course record of 65 set by Russ Cochran in 1996.</p>
        <p>''I knew the course record was 65 from the 10th hole,'' Watson said. ''After the 10th hole, I made the putt and a guy said, 'Shoot a course record today.' I said to myself, 'I wonder what it is?' He said, 'You have got to shoot 65.' I figured out what it was then.''</p>
        <p>Asked why he thought so many players shot low rounds today, Watson did not hesitate.</p>
        <p>''It's a forgiving golf course after the three inches of rain we had two days ago,'' said Watson, who is tied for 15th, eight strokes behind Tiger Woods.</p>
        <p>Missed Opportunities</p>
        <p>If both Phil Mickelson and Davis Love III fail to win the P.G.A. Championship, they will both regret today's third round. Love shot an even-par 72, failing to make a move on a day when so many others did. Love could not buy a putt today, missing many birdie opportunities as one putt after another slid past the hole.</p>
        <p>As for Mickelson, he shot a 31 on the front nine, but he faltered to a 38 on the back nine and settled for a 69. Mickelson and Love were both seven under par for the tournament, six strokes off the lead, not totally out of the tournament, but with slim chances unless everything goes right for them.</p>
        <p>''I played a poor back side,'' Mickelson said. ''If I had played a very good back side, I would be right in the thick of it and just a couple off the lead. Tomorrow, I am going to have to go exceptionally low. I think it is very possible for someone to come from behind and shoot 8, 9, or 10 under par.''</p>
        <p>GOLF: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
