<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation: The Wave; The Conventions Are Over. The Party's Just Starting.</title>
    <meta content="20TONE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224068"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toner, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EFDF133EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1396" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation: The Wave; The Conventions Are Over. The Party's Just Starting.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Toner, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on end of nominating conventions explains that party attachment is still considered one of best predictors of how people will vote; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR all the talk about the great race to the center this year, nobody who watched the two conventions, skimmed the parties' platforms or scrutinized the candidates' stands would mistake the Democrat for the Republican.</p>
        <p>Yes, much of the time a certain rhetorical sameness wafted from the main stages of the convention halls, and there was little of the partisan bite of yesteryear. But political passions kept bubbling up, just offstage. And even among the voters at large, at a time of peace and prosperity, with few great burning issues pushing people in one direction or another, two-thirds of Americans still consider themselves Democrats or Republicans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR all the talk about the great race to the center this year, nobody who watched the two conventions, skimmed the parties' platforms or scrutinized the candidates' stands would mistake the Democrat for the Republican.</p>
        <p>Yes, much of the time a certain rhetorical sameness wafted from the main stages of the convention halls, and there was little of the partisan bite of yesteryear. But political passions kept bubbling up, just offstage. And even among the voters at large, at a time of peace and prosperity, with few great burning issues pushing people in one direction or another, two-thirds of Americans still consider themselves Democrats or Republicans.</p>
        <p>Party, in other words, still matters.</p>
        <p>Party attachment is still considered one of the best predictors of how people will vote -- if they vote. But appealing to those loyalties, while still wooing the Independents who decide elections, is a complicated challenge these days. Particularly for Vice President Al Gore, many analysts say.</p>
        <p>The New York Times/CBS News Poll shows that the Democrats have a slight edge when it comes to party affiliation: Asked in four national polls this year how they identify themselves, an average of 35 percent of Americans said they were Democrats, 30 percent Republicans, 28 percent Independents and 7 percent (probably the least likely to vote) said they had no opinions.</p>
        <p>In a Times/CBS poll conducted last month, the Democratic Party was still considered the party that would do a better job on health care, education and ''making the right decisions'' on Social Security -- all issues high on the voters' agenda.</p>
        <p>The Republican Party was given the edge on upholding traditional family values, making sure the military stays strong and ensuring a healthy economy. Each party, in other words, brings its nominee certain strengths this fall.</p>
        <p>But until last week, Democratic voters have not embraced Mr. Gore's candidacy with the enthusiasm Republicans have brought to Gov. George W. Bush; the last pre-convention Times/CBS poll showed Mr. Gore drawing 75 percent of the Democrats, while Mr. Bush got 86 percent of the Republicans. ''I think they wasted half their convention just trying to get strong Democrats and soft Democrats home,'' said Bill McInturff, a Republican pollster. (Post-convention polls will tell how successful they were.)</p>
        <p>There are obvious reasons why Mr. Gore has had to work harder for voters who should be rightfully his: The Democratic Party has held the presidency for eight years. The strains are showing between liberals and ''New Democrats'' who want to keep the party in the center. And the Gore candidacy has had its fits and starts.</p>
        <p>This was the landscape for Mr. Gore's acceptance speech Thursday night: He needed to energize his base, but he was also keenly aware of the swing voters turned off by partisan appeals. On one level, his speech was profoundly Democratic. He offered himself as a populist crusader willing to fight ''powerful forces'' -- like big H.M.O.'s and profit-hungry pharmaceutical companies -- on behalf of ''working families.''</p>
        <p>But in sharp contrast to convention speeches of yesteryear, Mr. Gore's never mentioned the words Democrat or Republican, noted Martin Wattenberg, a political scientist at the University of California-Irvine.</p>
        <p>''It's populist, but it's a broad populism,'' said Stan Greenberg, Mr. Gore's pollster. ''It's saying, let's make sure the whole society is able to do well.''</p>
        <p>To galvanize his party, and to pull back many of the Independents who lean their way, Mr. Gore needs to draw sharp contrasts with the Republicans, many Democratic strategists agree, particularly on basic issues like tax cuts and health care.</p>
        <p>But Republicans have not made it easy.</p>
        <p>Frustrated Democrats say Mr. Bush is preaching a message -- that he is a different kind of Republican, more sensitive and moderate -- that is distinctly at odds with his basic conservatism.</p>
        <p>''Part of the task that Gore and the Democrats face in the fall is to tell voters that George W. Bush really is an old-style Republican,'' said Geoff Garin, a Democratic pollster. In other words, to block Mr. Bush's move to the center, now that he has consolidated his own party.</p>
        <p>Many Democrats are eager to make that case and highlight the stakes: What kind of Supreme Court justices would a Bush administration, operating with a Republican Senate, appoint?</p>
        <p>Who would most profit from his tax cuts?</p>
        <p>What would his budget proposals mean for Medicare?</p>
        <p>How does Mr. Bush's health care record in Texas, which ranks high among states in the percentage of uninsured, gibe with his promise to provide health coverage nationwide?</p>
        <p>But the Gore campaign is in something of a strategic box, one Republican strategist argued, speaking on condition that he not be identified. While the Democrats need to highlight the differences between the parties, overt partisanship gives the Bush campaign the higher moral ground.</p>
        <p>Day after day, the Bush campaign chastised the Democrats for any hint of partisan attacks at their convention. In fact, party strategists say, Mr. Bush is convinced that the voters are weary of such fights.</p>
        <p>''Bush has seriously studied what has happened since Republicans gained control of Congress in 1994,'' said Linda DiVall, a Republican poll taker. ''Frankly, Republicans don't do well when we get into a fight with Clinton or a fight among ourselves.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, of course, has the luxury of denouncing partisanship and muting the differences. Eight years in the wilderness, and a profound disdain for the Clinton administration, go a long way toward keeping Republican voters unified and motivated.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Mr. Bush has ably capitalized on his party's traditional strengths -- most notably, in the aftermath of the Clinton scandals, the notion that Republicans have stronger moral values. And he has dealt with his party's vulnerabilities, presenting a multi-ethnic, family-friendly convention program.</p>
        <p>WITH all his ''rhetorical convergence,'' as the political scientist Thomas Mann puts it, some voters might well ask just whether there's much difference between the parties -- an argument at the heart of Ralph Nader's third-party campaign.</p>
        <p>But, of course, in their attitudes toward government, their approach to social issues like abortion and gay rights, their economic philosophy and their approach to restructuring Medicare and Social Security, the differences are large and enduring.</p>
        <p>And each party's reliable supporters are quite distinctive, too.</p>
        <p>Party affiliation is still, quite often, passed down from parent to child, some political scientists say.</p>
        <p>Economic status is still strongly linked with party attachment, although Republicans have attracted more lower-income members through the party's embrace of social conservatives, while Democrats have drawn more white-collar voters.</p>
        <p>Larry Bartels, a professor of politics at Princeton University, maintains that party loyalty was a greater factor in presidential voting in the 1990's than at any time since the 1950's.</p>
        <p>And Mr. McInturff notes that, if anything, partisan voters have become even more so thanks to the polarizing figures of President Clinton and former Speaker Newt Gingrich -- but for the same reason people in the middle may have become even more turned off by partisanship.</p>
        <p>All of which suggests the complicated politics that awaits the voters this fall: a fierce, nonpartisan partisan struggle. For Mr. Gore, the campaign will be about ''fighting for working families,'' and for Mr. Bush, ''compassionate conservatism.'' In other words, the parties are dead, long live the parties.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
