<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</title>
    <meta content="20S38NWS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content/>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1DE103EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="408" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anita Gates</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEE a movie based on a Jane Austen novel and you're sure of three things: glorious English scenery, beautiful 19th-century costumes and people speaking in full sentences. Roger Michell's PERSUASION (1995) seems a little less Technicolor than the rest of the bunch made in the 90's, but in many ways it's the most powerful. Amanda Root is heartbreaking as Anne Elliot, who refused a proposal of marriage years ago (because her family disapproved) and is sinking into door spinsterhood. Ciaran Hinds is Captain Frederick Wentworth, the man who proposed. He's back in town, surrounded by giggling young women who consider him a very desirable suitor. It's a Cinderella stroy in many ways, with an abundance of wicked-stepsister surrogates. Sophie Thompson is priceless as Mary Musgrove (''I am so ill I can hardly speak''), one of the most obnoxious - Sunday at 9 p.m. on Channel 13.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEE a movie based on a Jane Austen novel and you're sure of three things: glorious English scenery, beautiful 19th-century costumes and people speaking in full sentences. Roger Michell's PERSUASION (1995) seems a little less Technicolor than the rest of the bunch made in the 90's, but in many ways it's the most powerful. Amanda Root is heartbreaking as Anne Elliot, who refused a proposal of marriage years ago (because her family disapproved) and is sinking into door spinsterhood. Ciaran Hinds is Captain Frederick Wentworth, the man who proposed. He's back in town, surrounded by giggling young women who consider him a very desirable suitor. It's a Cinderella stroy in many ways, with an abundance of wicked-stepsister surrogates. Sophie Thompson is priceless as Mary Musgrove (''I am so ill I can hardly speak''), one of the most obnoxious - Sunday at 9 p.m. on Channel 13.</p>
        <p>If you remember MR. SMITH GOES TO WASHINGTON (1939) as a sweet political fairy tale, you haven't seen it in a while. Frank Capra's classic comic drama about a naive young man (James Stewart) appointed to serve out the term of a dead senator does give Stewart lines like ''That Lincoln Memorial - gee whiz!'' and ''Liberty's too precious a thing to be buried in books,'' but he's surrounded by cynics, scoundrels and crooks. These include a bought-and-paid-for governor, the machine boss who owns him and his home state's senior senator (Claude Rains, giving a particularly touchng performance), who has just a trace of decency left. Jean Arthur is Saunders, Smith's hard-boiled secretary who's seen it all (or thinks she has) - Saturday at 8 p.m. on Channel 55.</p>
        <p>Cary Grant and Ingrid Bergman make a beautiful couple in Alfred Hitchcock's NOTORIOUS (1946), as smooth and sophisticated as the film itself. Bergman is a spy investigating Nazi exiles in South America; Grant is the intelligence agent assigned to her. They fall in love before either knows that the case will require her to marry a Nazi (Claude Rains again) in order to get the goods on him - Sunday at noon on AMC.</p>
        <p>- Anita Gates</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
