<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Powers Behind the Auctions</title>
    <meta content="20EBAY$15" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224058"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Small Business</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ebay Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guernsey, Lisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Small Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EFDA123EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3417" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Powers Behind the Auctions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA GUERNSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Guernsey, Lisa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Small businesses, not individuals attempting to clean out their attics, are fueling eBay's success as Internet auction site; they include liquidators, wholesalers, small retail shops and stay-at-home entrepreneurs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN people think of online auctions, they probably envision retirees selling bean bags from their basements and collectors trading baseball cards or limited-edition lunch boxes. After all, the founder of eBay, Pierre M. Omidyar, and its chief executive, Meg Whitman, are considered ingenious precisely because they created the first efficient global marketplace where consumers could sell directly to one another.</p>
        <p>But occasional sellers are hardly what have made eBay, with more than $87.9 million in online revenue in the second quarter, one of the most successful Internet businesses to date. Log on to eBay and you can easily find brand-new air-conditioners, boxes of unused printer cartridges and cases of 7-inch zippers, all nylon, all black. Rather than just items destined for garage sales, plenty of new merchandise is available. ''This is not just mom and pop cleaning out their attics,'' said Evie Black Dykema, a senior analyst at Forrester Research. ''There is this whole subeconomy of small businesses who use eBay.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN people think of online auctions, they probably envision retirees selling bean bags from their basements and collectors trading baseball cards or limited-edition lunch boxes. After all, the founder of eBay, Pierre M. Omidyar, and its chief executive, Meg Whitman, are considered ingenious precisely because they created the first efficient global marketplace where consumers could sell directly to one another.</p>
        <p>But occasional sellers are hardly what have made eBay, with more than $87.9 million in online revenue in the second quarter, one of the most successful Internet businesses to date. Log on to eBay and you can easily find brand-new air-conditioners, boxes of unused printer cartridges and cases of 7-inch zippers, all nylon, all black. Rather than just items destined for garage sales, plenty of new merchandise is available. ''This is not just mom and pop cleaning out their attics,'' said Evie Black Dykema, a senior analyst at Forrester Research. ''There is this whole subeconomy of small businesses who use eBay.''</p>
        <p>The real powers behind eBay's success are those small operators -- the liquidators, wholesalers, small retail shops and stay-at-home entrepreneurs -- that offer the bulk of goods for sale on eBay, underpinning its entire business.</p>
        <p>Call them power sellers -- eBay does. By putting dozens of new items up for sale every day, these sellers keep buyers coming back to bid and bid again. Of the four million items listed on the site on any given day, the top 20 sellers are responsible for 72,000 listings, and the top 38,000 sellers account for 2.7 million items, according to AuctionWatch.com, an online auction services company. At last count, eBay had 15.8 million registered users, or Internet names for people who use the site to buy or sell or both.</p>
        <p>And because power sellers, like all other sellers, pay eBay listing fees and commissions ranging from 1.25 to 5 percent of the value of each item sold, they contribute a huge proportion of the company's revenues.</p>
        <p>Some sellers list goods on other auction sites, either as an alternative or supplement to eBay. Yahoo Auctions, the biggest of those rivals, has 2.5 million listings. But as the first company to exploit the online auction model, eBay dominates, holding nearly 90 percent of the online auction market, measured by sales. That sheer volume, said Steven Johnson, director of the e-commerce program at Andersen Consulting, drives more buyers to eBay, which in turn attracts even more high-volume sellers.</p>
        <p>Who are these overachievers? A power seller, by eBay's definition, has met at least one of three levels of standards in volume and customer service -- designated as bronze, silver and gold. To earn the bronze label, a seller must have minimum monthly sales of $2,000; for silver, $10,000 a month; for gold, at least $25,000 a month -- more than many small businesses ever achieve, online or off. Would-be power sellers must also have received at least 100 comments from buyers in the feedback forum, where buyers and sellers rate each others' performance, and 98 percent of their ratings must be positive.</p>
        <p>EBay says it has 20,000 to 25,000 power sellers, though it will not disclose how many have hit any particular level. But those numbers do not include people who may be meeting the power-seller standards but have not had the time or the inclination to join eBay's program, which offers them perks like full-time customer service support and permission to display an official power-seller logo.</p>
        <p>EBay declined to disclose financial details about the sellers who make its business hum. But Andale Inc., an auction management company in Mountain View, Calif. that provides e-mail tools and database services to online sellers, has pored over eBay's listings and determined that 10 percent of eBay's sellers are responsible for 80 percent of its sales. That 10 percent thus sold about $1 billion of the $1.3 billion worth of toys, jewelry, computers, sporting goods, real estate and other merchandise that changed hands on eBay in the last quarter.</p>
        <p>And they may be making hefty profits. Again, eBay would not give details of its users' businesses, but a survey conducted by Andale in March found that sellers made a 40 percent profit margin, on average. By contrast, many online retailers are not yet in the black, according to Forrester. According to a report that Forrester released in April, and based in part on interviews with 50 companies, less than 40 percent of the e-tailers expected to make money before 2002.</p>
        <p>''Online auctions are a seriously lucrative way to sell,'' said Munjal Shah, chief executive of Andale. ''There are a whole troop of merchants that have grown up around that realization.''</p>
        <p>For these sellers, there are obvious advantages, mainly that they can attract buyers without spending money on marketing and that commissions are low. By contrast, Amazon.com spent about 25 percent of its sales on marketing last year -- and that proportion is ''significantly lower than everyone else's online,'' according to Mike May, a senior analyst for Jupiter Communications.</p>
        <p>EBay's role as an inexpensive marketing channel, however, may also make it a breeding ground for fraud. The company does not attempt to police transactions, enabling it to keep its own costs low. But that raises the possibility that sellers may be hawking stolen, counterfeit, damaged or fake merchandise on its site. One dissatisfied buyer is trying to organize a class action suit by customers who believe they were defrauded by big sellers.</p>
        <p>And while some buyers, in comments left on feedback forums, rave about individual power sellers, others complain that eBay coddles its power sellers at the expense of buyers.</p>
        <p>But as long as eBay thrives, power sellers appear to be here to stay, and their numbers will probably grow. In recent months, a new category of businesses has emerged that is dedicated to helping them. These companies, like Andale, AuctionWorks and AuctionWatch.com, provide billing and shipping services and software to track and respond to hundreds of auction listings simultaneously.  ''This has become a real business,'' said Ms. Dykema of Forrester, ''and there are now real tools to manage it.''</p>
        <p>So exactly who are these small businesses that use eBay as a staging ground for e-commerce? Here are four whose revenues meet power-seller standards.</p>
        <p>The Retailer  A Small Business Triples Its Volume</p>
        <p>On a Sunday night a year and a half ago, Nang Nguyen was sitting at his computer, looking at jewelry listings on eBay. He had decided to bid on a diamond ring in a platinum setting; it would be a present for his wife, Kim. The ring was listed by a store he had never heard of -- Sun Jewelry, a tiny shop in a Los Angeles shopping mall, thousands of miles from his home in Hershey, Pa.</p>
        <p>When he won the bidding, he and his wife were thrilled. ''The price was incredible,'' remembered Mr. Nguyen (pronounced ''win''). He immediately called Los Angeles to talk with the shop's owner, Abit Uygan. They hit it off.</p>
        <p>Mr. Uygan said he was a new seller on eBay. Mr. Nguyen responded that he was a rookie buyer. Mr. Uygan described the bad luck he had experienced with other forms of online sales, including several failed attempts to run a Web site. Mr. Nguyen, who was working in his father's shoe store in Hershey, offered to help Mr. Uygan sell other pieces of jewelry on eBay.</p>
        <p>Their partnership, Mr. Nguyen said, has thrived. Since last year, the two men have owned Sun Jewelry together. While Mr. Uygan continues to oversee the production of the jewelry, which he and a few employees make by hand in the back room of the Los Angeles shop, Mr. Nguyen runs the administrative side, including the eBay listings, from an office next door to his father's shoe store in Hershey.</p>
        <p>Sun's sales have tripled in the last year and a half, Mr. Nguyen said. They sell up to 800 pieces of jewelry a month, about 90 percent online. The two men are now considering taking the company public.</p>
        <p>''Without the online auction, I don't think it would be possible to be where we are today, thinking about an I.P.O.,'' Mr. Nguyen said.</p>
        <p>But at the beginning, he was not sure that eBay was the answer. Sun Jewelry already had its own Web site (www.sunjewelry.com) and Mr. Nguyen had decided to try several Internet marketing avenues at once. Those included banner and classified advertising, links with other Web sites and requests for listing on search engines.</p>
        <p>''Listing your Web site -- trust me, it doesn't work,'' he said. Selling items through eBay was the only thing that did. ''It has put us in an area where everyone can see us,'' he added. ''Before, we were just a small store, tucked away.'' Now Mr. Nguyen does not even try to advertise the Sun Jewelry Web site, although it still attracts customers who remember seeing it on eBay.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nguyen has also started using eBay as a test bed for pricing. He will list a ring on eBay and watch how many bids it gets, and how many people click through to see the photograph and the closing price. If the ring sells well, he may offer a few more of a similar design on eBay or decide to showcase it on his Web site at a set price.</p>
        <p>Of course, the surge in business has brought trials. During the holiday season last year, the company had a three-week backup in orders. And maintaining friendly and accessible customer service has been a challenge. Mr. Nguyen said he calls almost every one of his customers himself. His phone bill, he said, runs from $800 to $1,000 a month.</p>
        <p>In the last few months, he has bought services from Andale, the auction-management company that automates his listings, allows for different forms of payment and reminds him to send feedback to each buyer.</p>
        <p>Amid all the activity, in fact, he still has not yet visited the Sun Jewelry store in Los Angeles, or even met his partner face to face. ''I have no idea what he looks like,'' Mr. Nguyen said. ''But I'm going out to his wedding next year, so I'll finally see him there.''</p>
        <p>The Home Business  Clearing Out Closets And Making Money</p>
        <p>Three years ago, Kimberly Crockett was working for a regional investment company, selling mutual funds from her home in Panama City Beach, Fla. Still in her 20's, she had already built a fine life, with a three-bedroom house within walking distance of the beach on the Gulf of Mexico.</p>
        <p>But these days, Ms. Crockett does not have much time to get to the beach, and her fund work is on the back burner. Since the spring of 1998, she has built a booming business from her home, selling collectible toys on eBay.</p>
        <p>Always enchanted by ''The Wizard of Oz,'' Ms. Crockett had secretly hoped she might be able to make money by collecting television and movie memorabilia. In 1989, she decided on a whim to buy two shopping carts full of Pee Wee Herman toys that were on sale in a store for a few dollars apiece. It was a smart gamble: several pieces now sell for more than $200 each.</p>
        <p>But until the Web came along, she never imagined being able to make a good living from her hobby. Today, she sells 1,000 to 2,000 toys a month on eBay, and has just hired her first employee. She declined to divulge details of her profits, but said she was having no trouble making money.</p>
        <p>''I always double my money,'' Ms. Crockett said in a phone interview from her home, barely distracted by her light-brown cat, Panama, which sat beside her crouched on a Three Stooges mouse pad.</p>
        <p>Ms. Crockett, who goes by the name SillyOzibul on eBay, started collecting toys with a fervor about three years ago, after helping a ''Star Wars'' fan find a rare Princess Leia figurine. After a few months of scouring toy shows, garage sales and collectors' conventions, she realized that she had developed a sizable collection without any plan for what to do with it.</p>
        <p>''One day I opened one of the bedroom doors, and there were just bags and bags of stuff,'' she said. ''I couldn't even walk in. And I said: 'What are you doing, Kim? You just can't horde this stuff.' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Crockett decided to try eBay. The first item, one of those Pee Wee Herman dolls, sold for $18, and within a few months she had built a company called Oz Wars Toys, a title that blends ''Wizard of Oz'' and ''Star Wars.'' Two of the three bedrooms in her house are now storage areas, and the living room is a packaging site, strewn with boxes and bubble wrap. The kitchen is the only area that is devoid of collectibles --  except for the Oz plates that hang above the cabinets.</p>
        <p>Her house is so full of toys, Ms. Crockett said, that she is looking to rent about 1,000 square feet of space nearby where she can operate the online business and sell a few items to local residents who stop by.</p>
        <p>As the business grows, it is becoming more professional. She has bought services from AuctionWorks to help manage the business; the move saved her the 30 hours a week she had spent writing e-mail messages to customers and filling out feedback forms rating her buyers.</p>
        <p>But regardless of how much her business grows, Ms. Crockett said, she is not ready to part with all of her collectibles, especially those related to Dorothy and the Yellow Brick Road. ''I've just sold a bunch of 'Wizard of Oz' flags for $50 apiece,'' she said. ''They are really nice ruby-slippers flags, with slippers that sparkle and a sign that says, 'No Place Like Home.' ''</p>
        <p>''Several bidders fought over them on eBay,'' she said, ''but I've got to keep one for me.''</p>
        <p>The Liquidator  A Hot Market For Unsold Clothes</p>
        <p>Andrew J. Waites, a tall, tan, well-dressed man with a thick Southern accent, jumped into e-commerce last year. But he has no intention of moving his liquidating business to Silicon Valley from West Front Street in Hattiesburg, Miss.</p>
        <p>For starters, he would not fit in, he declared in a recent interview. ''In south Mississippi,'' he said with a playful smile, ''we're not smart enough to figure out how to make money by selling merchandise and losing money on each item.''</p>
        <p>Instead, he has turned to eBay, which he will use as the infrastructure for a new site, eValueville.com.  His company, Inventory Procurement Services, specializes in selling the shirts, coats, jeans and dresses that retail shops want to get rid of, usually because they want to make room for new styles and more seasonable clothing.</p>
        <p>Previously, he distributed those goods to small retail shops that have closeouts. Then, last summer, he received a box of Kenneth Cole leather coats of different shapes and sizes. ''We said, 'How are we going to sell these in the summer in Hattiesburg, Mississippi?' '' he recalled. ''We put them on eBay, and we were amazed at the final sales price.'' As a result, something that would have been almost impossible to sell at $69 in his hometown became a hot $200 item.</p>
        <p>But one real advantage of the online auction sites, he said, is the ability to reduce expenses, especially for marketing. Sometimes, he said, he does not bother paying eBay's $2 fee for putting a listing in bold type, yet he has sold 100 percent of the clothing that he has tried to sell and has made a profit on each item.</p>
        <p>Mr. Waites also uses eBay as a hook. He sometimes starts items at $1 each, regardless of what they must sell for to recover costs, to draw just-lookers -- in hopes that they will go to the Evalueville site. By mid-September, he added, he will be listing 5,000 items a week on eBay.</p>
        <p>He has also been visiting department stores and manufacturers, trying to sell them on his new business plan. He is betting that he will be able to get them better prices than they might through conventional liquidation channels. ''I think we can improve their recovery by 2 to 3 percentage points,'' he said. ''We think eBay will be for us the biggest outlet mall in the world.''</p>
        <p>The Wholesaler  Giving the Consumer Economies of Scale</p>
        <p>For more than 20 years, Larry Bence has been supplying retail stores with collectible cards and coins. And he has been using computers for 15 years -- he was part of a proprietary network of dealers who were sending messages back and forth in the very early days of the Internet. So in the mid-1990's, when everyone started talking about expanding commerce on the Web, he was all for it.</p>
        <p>But after setting up a Web site, he found that the effort was not worth it. He and his staff, including his daughter, Julie, would spend hours listing the prices of sports cards, posters, toy cars, and dinnerware with football logos. Then something in the news would bump the prices up or down, and the site would have to be updated.</p>
        <p>''It's just impossible to maintain that many different pricing ranges,'' said Mr. Bence, whose company is called Abon Cards and Coins Ltd.  After trying six times with different Web site designs, he gave up.</p>
        <p>''The only people that I've seen who make money on Web sites,'' he said, ''are the people who design them.'' Mr. Bence still has a Web site, but it is just a few pages.</p>
        <p>As a wholesaler with more than 100,000 square feet of warehouse space in Ohio, Mr. Bence did not have to worry about finding a place for inventory to feed his online business. And he could have settled for a continuation of his conventional business, selling pallets of cards and memorabilia to retailers. But he wanted to tap into the consumer market, too, without doing any advertising.</p>
        <p>That is why he turned to eBay, he said. He now assigns about a dozen of his 22 staff members to manage his  eBay listings of cards, coins and related items. His eBay business is now large enough that he has chosen to become an eBay gold power seller. He has developed software to help his company manage all of the accounts; one of his homemade software packages runs checks on credit card numbers and addresses to make sure that a buyer is not using a stolen card. ''It's hairy,'' he said. ''We are gritting our teeth. That's the one area that is very vulnerable.''</p>
        <p>The venture has turned his business into a blend of wholesale and retail, a mix that he said is becoming increasingly common on the Internet. Ultimately, he is able to sell small quantities of goods to consumers at wholesale prices, while still selling pallets of merchandise to retailers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bence said his presence on eBay had also built his contact base, enabling him find more items to sell:  ''There are people who see us on eBay who contact us and say, 'I wonder if he'll want to buy stuff.' '' he added. ''I just bought a bunch of collegiate dinnerware -- Michigan State dinnerware. In Ohio, not many people may want Michigan State dinnerware. But on the Internet, there are probably plenty of Michigan State fans who will have no problem paying up.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
