<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pettitte Wipes Away the Angels, and the Bitter Memories of Friday Night</title>
    <meta content="Y20YAN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224144"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Anaheim Angels</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Angels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E6DB103EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pettitte Wipes Away the Angels, and the Bitter Memories of Friday Night</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Anaheim Angels, 9-1; photo (M)9</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Andy Pettitte departed Yankee Stadium Friday in the sixth inning, before the Yankees' collapse, before they blew their five-run lead in the ninth. Pettitte saw the 11th inning in his living room, saw Anaheim's Darin Erstad slug the game-winning home run, and Pettitte became cognizant of the burden shifting onto his broad shoulders.</p>
        <p>Pettitte, the Yankees' starting pitcher yesterday, knew he had to quickly establish himself -- and the whole team, for that matter -- and quickly exorcise the feelings lingering from Friday's terrible defeat. The left-hander struck out Erstad with a cut fastball to start the game, the Yankees struck for seven runs in the first three innings and ultimately smashed the Angels, 9-1. Pettitte threw a complete game and is 15-6, having won his last six starts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Andy Pettitte departed Yankee Stadium Friday in the sixth inning, before the Yankees' collapse, before they blew their five-run lead in the ninth. Pettitte saw the 11th inning in his living room, saw Anaheim's Darin Erstad slug the game-winning home run, and Pettitte became cognizant of the burden shifting onto his broad shoulders.</p>
        <p>Pettitte, the Yankees' starting pitcher yesterday, knew he had to quickly establish himself -- and the whole team, for that matter -- and quickly exorcise the feelings lingering from Friday's terrible defeat. The left-hander struck out Erstad with a cut fastball to start the game, the Yankees struck for seven runs in the first three innings and ultimately smashed the Angels, 9-1. Pettitte threw a complete game and is 15-6, having won his last six starts.</p>
        <p>Luis Sojo lined a two-run homer in the first inning, and David Justice mashed a pair of home runs, his 33rd and 34th. ''We just had to forget about yesterday,'' Sojo said. ''We just had to forget about it and come back today.''</p>
        <p>As many of his players fled the Yankees' clubhouse after Friday's disaster, Torre lingered in his office and identified a silver lining: Thank goodness, Torre said, that the Yankees had an afternoon game in about 13 hours, so that they could immediately go about the business of pushing Anaheim's staggering comeback into their past.</p>
        <p>It was not easy. Mariano Rivera, who had surrendered the game-tying home run to Mo Vaughn in the ninth, said the loss bothered him more than any in his career. Torre passed Tino Martinez in the clubhouse and Martinez asked the manager how he was feeling, perhaps trying to decide whether the look on Torre's face betrayed tiredness or the hangover of disappointment.</p>
        <p>But Torre said before the game he expected they would rebound. ''They've been through this so many times before,'' he said. The Yankees had not taken batting practice outdoors for three days, skipping Wednesday's session because of the hot weather in Texas, missing Thursday because of overnight travel from Texas and Friday because of the rain that showered the Bronx.</p>
        <p>The sun was out and the air was pleasantly cool yesterday morning, and shortly after 11 a.m., the Yankees started departing their clubhouse and warming up on the field, Martinez and Scott Brosius and others playing catch in front of the Yankees' dugout. It was impossible to tell whether Friday's defeat weighed on any of them, if they were even thinking about it.</p>
        <p>Sojo had been more concerned about whether he was in the lineup, waiting in front of his locker until the hitting coach Chris Chambliss posted the batting order on the clubhouse door, then walking across the room to find his name.</p>
        <p>Sojo started at second base, batting second, and after the Anaheim starter Brian Cooper (4-8) nailed Derek Jeter with a fastball leading off the first, Sojo drilled a two-run homer into the left-field stands. The Yankees added a walk and three singles for two more runs, freeing Pettitte to pitch aggressively. He was throwing hard, and his fastball had unusually sharp movement, and Pettitte attacked, striking out four of the first six batters he faced, breezing through the Anaheim lineup most of the afternoon.</p>
        <p>Pettitte has compiled a 2.41 earned run average in his last six starts, and has a chance to win 20 games for the first time since 1996, when he finished 21-8. ''This is probably about as strong as I've felt this late in the season,'' he said. ''Even in my bullpen work, I feel like everything is in a real good slot.''</p>
        <p>Ron Gant misplayed one fly ball in the third and forgot how many outs there were when catching another, helping the Yankees score three times on three sacrifice flies, tying a one-inning major league record. The game was an 8-0 wipeout after five innings, and already Friday's debacle seemed like just another forgettable result during the course of the long season.</p>
        <p>When the Angels began to stir in the sixth, putting runners at second and third with a walk and a double, Pettitte snagged Tim Salmon's hard grounder through the middle and caught Kevin Stocker off third base -- Anaheim's fourth major base-running mistake in the first three games of this series. Sojo dived to stop a grounder by Vaughn and threw to first to end the sixth.</p>
        <p>The rest was just window dressing, the home runs by Justice, Torre clearing his bench and resting some of his regulars. The good thing, from the perspective of the Yankees, was that they don't play again until this afternoon, giving them one full day to remember this crisp victory, and one more day to forget Friday's nightmare.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Yankees are a little banged up and bruised after the first three games of this series. Center fielder BERNIE WILLIAMS was scratched from the starting lineup because of a twinge in his rib cage; he is not sure if he will be able to play today. DEREK JETER, who fouled pitches off his left leg Thursday and Friday, was hit on the left knee by a pitch in the first inning yesterday and, moving stiffly, was replaced before the eighth; Jeter does expect to play today. First baseman TINO MARTINEZ was hit on his right wrist by a throw in the third inning, requiring brief attention.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
