<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AD BLITZ TO START AS BUSH AND GORE DEFINE KEY STATES</title>
    <meta content="20CAMP$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TACTICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Virginia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Michigan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ohio</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Missouri</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Midwestern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/West Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/West Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/West Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DA103EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AD BLITZ TO START AS BUSH AND GORE DEFINE KEY STATES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Presidential contenders plan to open biggest television advertising blitzes of their campaigns, hoping to capitalize on afterglow from their conventions; Gov George W Bush will emphasize education and Vice Pres Al Gore will trumpet himself as champion of 'working families'; both sides begin making critical decisions about where to campaign and where to funnel resources, including infusion of $68 million in federal subsidies each; Bush plans to advertise and campaign in historically Democratic states, including West Virginia, and swing states of Pennsylvania, Michigan, Ohio and Missouri; Gore officials say they will focus largely on battleground states of Midwest and make particular appeals to women; say they will continue to cite Bush's record in Texas as failure; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moving on several fronts to capitalize on the afterglow from their conventions, the presidential contenders plan next week to open the biggest television advertising blitzes of their campaigns, in which Gov. George W. Bush will emphasize education and Vice President Al Gore will trumpet himself as a champion of ''working families.''</p>
        <p>Both sides said they were preparing for the hectic 80-day marathon to Election Day and had begun making critical decisions about where to campaign and where to funnel resources, including an infusion of nearly $68 million in federal subsidies each.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Moving on several fronts to capitalize on the afterglow from their conventions, the presidential contenders plan next week to open the biggest television advertising blitzes of their campaigns, in which Gov. George W. Bush will emphasize education and Vice President Al Gore will trumpet himself as a champion of ''working families.''</p>
        <p>Both sides said they were preparing for the hectic 80-day marathon to Election Day and had begun making critical decisions about where to campaign and where to funnel resources, including an infusion of nearly $68 million in federal subsidies each.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is seizing the offensive and plans to advertise and campaign in historically Democratic states. Among the 21 states chosen for an advertising drive that begins on Monday is West Virginia, which Republicans have not carried since 1984. The commercials will also appear in the swing states of Pennsylvania, Michigan, Ohio and Missouri,  and states like Oregon, Washington and New Mexico, where President Clinton prevailed in 1992 and 1996 but where Mr. Bush thinks his chances are good.</p>
        <p>''This is the point at which the campaign pivots,'' said Karl Rove, Mr. Bush's chief strategist. ''Our focus has been preparing for the conventions. Now we're making major forays onto the turf that the other guy considers his own.''</p>
        <p>The commercials lay out Mr. Bush's broad goals for education, including greater local control of schools, stricter standards and increased federal spending to promote reading and strengthen teacher training and math and science.</p>
        <p>Gore officials said they would focus largely on the battleground states of the Midwest and make particular appeals to women who seemed enticed by the Republicans. They also said they would continue to cite Mr. Bush's record in Texas as demonstrating his failure to tackle health care for children, improving the environment, gun control and other issues.</p>
        <p>''The battle lines are drawn,'' said Robert Shrum, one of Mr. Gore's leading strategists. ''Al Gore comes out of the convention much more clearly defined to people. There's a choice on a thematic dimension: Who's going to stand up and fight for middle-class families on prescription drugs, a patients' bill of rights and education?''</p>
        <p>Starting Monday, the two 30-second Bush commercials will run in rotation for several days in more than 40 media markets across the 21 states. Described by one aide as a ''heavy, multimillion-dollar'' advertising buy, it is the largest for a single period that the Bush campaign has made to date.</p>
        <p>''We've expanded the battlefield,'' said Ari Fleischer, a spokesman for the Bush campaign. ''The fact that we're running ads in states that are traditionally Democratic while the vice president is still trying to shore up his base is an interesting reflection of where this election is.''</p>
        <p>Bush campaign officials said they were working with state Republican Party organizations to develop programs to identify potential supporters and encourage them to vote. The Gore campaign is making such efforts as well, but is more reliant on unions to help drive turnout.</p>
        <p>Before the Democratic convention, polls showed that Mr. Bush was ahead of Mr. Gore. The Gore campaign's objective has been to build on the publicity and good feeling from the convention to help Mr. Gore pull even with Mr. Bush by the end of the month.</p>
        <p>In 1984 and in every presidential campaign since, the candidate who was ahead in the polls after the conventions won the election. But because there is an open race and both camps seem relatively evenly matched, Republican and Democratic strategists predict that the 2000 race may more resemble 1980, when President Jimmy Carter and Ronald Reagan were neck-and-neck in the polls after the convention and Mr. Reagan pulled out a victory in the closing days.</p>
        <p>''I don't see how it can be anything but a competitive race,'' said Tom Cole, chief of staff for the Republican National Committee. ''Our biggest advantage right now is our base unified quicker than theirs. But that's going to happen at some point for them. Then we're going to be in a very close race.''</p>
        <p>Speaking of Mr. Gore and his running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, Mr. Cole added, ''They're not going to go gently into that good night.''</p>
        <p>Gov. Tommy G. Thompson of Wisconsin, a Republican, said the best evidence of the competitiveness was in his state, which was Clinton-Gore territory in the last two elections but now appears to be a tossup.</p>
        <p>''George W. Bush has every opportunity to win this election,'' Mr. Thompson said. ''To give you an idea, George Bush has already been here three times and Al Gore has been here four or five times. And both of them are going to be in Milwaukee next week.''</p>
        <p>Representative Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri, the Democratic leader, said now that the public might be beginning to pay attention to the contest, Mr. Gore should hammer away at a theme he introduced at the convention: how the policies of a president can touch the lives of ordinary Americans.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people weren't watching this -- they were watching 'Survivor' or something else,'' Mr. Gephardt said. ''Al Gore should articulate the stakes in this election and in people's everyday lives.''</p>
        <p>Public opinion needs to settle for at least several days before polls can give an accurate picture of how the relative standing of Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush might have shifted from the two biggest political events of the summer: the conventions and selection of running mates.</p>
        <p>But the consensus in interviews with a range of strategists and campaign officials on both sides is that both campaigns did themselves some good on both counts -- or, at the very least, did not lose ground.</p>
        <p>Gov. Tom Vilsack of Iowa, a Democrat, said his initial fears that Mr. Clinton's appearance would siphon attention from Mr. Gore had been allayed. ''This whole issue of contrasting Clinton and Gore -- I wasn't sure how this would all work out,'' Mr. Vilsack said.</p>
        <p>Then, referring to Mr. Gore's speech, he added, ''But I will tell you -- with no disrespect at all to the president -- I thought halfway through the speech, 'Bill who?' ''</p>
        <p>Though both conventions seemed to be helpful to the nominees, strategists in both parties agreed that Mr. Bush put on a slightly better convention than Mr. Gore. Several experts said that was because the Republicans appeared more harmonious and laid out a broader message of inclusion. By contrast, many strategists said, the vice president's convention was a bit more uneven and seemed less successful in reaching beyond the party's core voters.</p>
        <p>''Bush had a better convention week, but not a better speech,'' said David Axelrod, a Democratic strategist in Chicago.</p>
        <p>Gore campaign officials said they were pleased that during their convention they had made significant inroads in presenting Mr. Gore as more than a vice president but as a nominee with a populist streak who will energetically fight for ''working families'' -- a favorite Gore phrase -- on issues ranging from health care to Social Security.</p>
        <p>But even loyal Democrats here expressed some distress about Mr. Gore and his difficulty in winning clusters of voters -- like women -- who are historically inclined to vote Democratic. And they cited the ball and chain of Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>''I'm worried that the people of America will not give him a fair hearing,'' said Raymond Ensher, a Colorado delegate. ''They continue to associate him, I think unfairly, with the problems Bill Clinton has had.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ensher added: ''What really worries me are the women. That really worries me.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove, Mr. Bush's strategist, noted that Mr. Bush had already succeeded in staking out issues that Bob Dole, the nominee four years ago, did not dare discuss. ''Can you imagine if Bob Dole had stood up and said, 'I want to reform Social Security,' '' he asked. ''The race would be over. Can you imagine a Republican candidate saying, 'We've got to get rid of so many nuclear bombs?' We did it and got away with it.''</p>
        <p>Despite the slightly better reviews for the Republican production, people in both parties said Mr. Gore's choice of Senator Lieberman seemed, at least in the short term, to be a better pick than Dick Cheney, the former secretary of defense, on the Republican side. That is because Mr. Lieberman, the first Jew on a major party ticket, was greeted with euphoria among many Democrats  and caused people to take more notice of Mr. Gore. The choice of Mr. Cheney underscored Mr. Bush's determination to pick a competent No. 2 who would know how to govern. Yet it stirred little excitement.</p>
        <p>''It was a good pick for him,''  Senator Sam Brownback, a Kansas Republican, said of Mr. Lieberman.  ''It generated some excitement and interest that wasn't there. Cheney solidified Bush but I couldn't really measure what he's done broader.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brownback warned, however, that the Lieberman pick could come back to haunt Mr. Gore. If the Democrats attack Mr. Bush for their positions on Social Security privatization and education reform, he said, Republicans can simply invoke Mr. Lieberman's record on those issues, which is not too far from Mr. Bush's.</p>
        <p>Both sides are also looking to the nationally televised debates beginning in October -- three presidential debates are tentatively scheduled -- to give them one last big opportunity to scramble the dynamic. Unless a candidate performs poorly, as Ronald Reagan did in the first debate against Walter F. Mondale in 1984, debates usually do little more than reinforce allegiances. (Mr. Reagan, however, improved in later debates and went on to win in a landslide.)</p>
        <p>Mike Sturla, a Democratic state representative in Pennsylvania who was a delegate here, said the debates would be critical. But in the next breath he wondered aloud whether the build-up of Mr. Gore as an accomplished debater -- and criticism of Mr. Bush as lackluster -- could play right into the Bush strategy.</p>
        <p>''The Republicans, knowing they will get crushed, have lowered expectations so much that Bush would have to wilt and slither off the stage,'' Mr. Sturla said, ''for his performance to be judged a surprise and a failure.''</p>
        <p>Bush campaign advisers and supporters seem almost preoccupied over the possibility that the Democrats will begin broadcasting harsh commercials that try to scare voters away from their candidate -- all in a drive to gain an edge over Bush.</p>
        <p>The Democrats, preferring not to portray the commercials as negative, say they will not shrink from what they call issue comparisons. Some Democratic operatives say it seems that the Republicans want to goad Mr. Gore into a slash-and-burn posture so they can turn around and paint him as mean-spirited, and then attack him right back.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's advisers said their hope was that in the speech on Thursday, the vice president diffused some of the concern that he was not sufficiently likable, leaving voters more inclined to warm up to Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TACTICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
