<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brooklyn Journal; In Court, Families Sit Waiting On the Law</title>
    <meta content="20JOUR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Family Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sengupta, Somini</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4DE103EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1186" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brooklyn Journal; In Court, Families Sit Waiting On the Law</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOMINI SENGUPTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sengupta, Somini</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brooklyn Journal on scene in Family Court, which handles domestic cases, mostly involving city's poor; more than half of those passing through are black and more than forty percent are Hispanic; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the cramped law library on the top floor of Kings County Family Court, the day begins with frilly dresses, wide grins and cheers of congratulations.</p>
        <p>A 3-year-old twig of a boy, an orphan since birth, gets parents of his own. A pair of brothers -- one 20 and disabled, the other, 10, with eyes like darts -- are adopted by the quiet couple who took them in seven years ago. A 5-year-old girl with a lispy whisper of a voice gets a new name.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the cramped law library on the top floor of Kings County Family Court, the day begins with frilly dresses, wide grins and cheers of congratulations.</p>
        <p>A 3-year-old twig of a boy, an orphan since birth, gets parents of his own. A pair of brothers -- one 20 and disabled, the other, 10, with eyes like darts -- are adopted by the quiet couple who took them in seven years ago. A 5-year-old girl with a lispy whisper of a voice gets a new name.</p>
        <p>The dozen or so adoptions completed this morning represent the rare moments of brightness in this theater of boredom and despair -- not least because they have been so long in coming. The woman adopting the 5-year-old girl, for instance, has been waiting to do so ever since the birth of the child, left by her 13-year-old biological mother in a Queens hospital. The woman, whose name was not revealed because of confidentiality laws governing adoption, could almost feel the birth pains, she said.  She has cared for the baby ever since.</p>
        <p>''Gimme a kiss!'' she demands, showing the girl the adoption papers. The girl climbs on top of her, smothering her face and arms with kisses.</p>
        <p>Waiting is the leitmotif of Family Court. Well before court begins at 9 a.m., hundreds of men, women and children line up to pass through a metal detector. Then they line up to get on an elevator. Then they wait to see a judge. Sometimes, they wait past sundown.</p>
        <p>One day last week, it seemed fitting that the clock in the waiting room in front of the intake court -- Family Court's emergency room -- was more than two hours slow.</p>
        <p>On this day, the hard wooden benches are packed in this windowless waiting room in the courthouse on Adams Street in downtown Brooklyn. The water fountain on this floor doesn't work. The women's bathroom lacks the luxuries of many  restrooms -- no diaper-changing stations, no toilet seat covers, only one functioning stall.</p>
        <p>Only a handful of people in the waiting room on this day have brought something to read. Most of the others stare into space. A few rest their heads on their arms in an effort to sleep, which seems impossible in the din. Children wail. Every now and then, someone becomes agitated and starts muttering or yelling. Every few seconds, a court officer bellows the name of the next person to appear before a judge.</p>
        <p>''This is like a circus,'' declares Debra Benders, 40, who was seeking custody of her granddaughter.</p>
        <p>''It's not only what you're going through, but what everybody else is going through,'' says Urcelina Ortiz, a mother from Bushwick who was there to try to prevent her son, accused of selling drugs, from being  locked up. (Family Court handles most criminal charges against children under 16.) She watched another mother, whose son was released from custody, burst into tears. She stared at a woman covered with bruises. It was a painful reminder for Ms. Ortiz, 41, who years ago had come into this very courthouse seeking an order of protection from her ex-husband.</p>
        <p>Tara Caver, 29, a slight, soft-spoken mother of four, arrived at 10 a.m. to try to prevent the termination of her parental rights. Her children were placed in foster care four years ago, when she was diagnosed with manic-depressive disorder. Since then, she said, she had tried to do all that was asked of her -- taken medications, attended therapy. Mostly, she has waited for the legal system to return her children.</p>
        <p>On this day, she and her husband, Burnard Hayes, 36, spent the hours holding each other tightly on a bench, dozing off on each other's shoulders. Not until 5 p.m. did she learn that her case would be adjourned.</p>
        <p>Some people call Family Court the  candy store of melodrama. But it is also a theater of the most ordinary betrayals, the place where the most intimate details of domestic life are revealed, where the violations of trust and love between men and women, parents and children are scrutinized by strangers.</p>
        <p>Family Court, with a branch in every borough, offers a lopsided demographic picture of the city. Most of those passing through it are poor. More than half are black, according to a study by the Vera Institute of Justice, and more than 40 percent are Hispanic. Only 7 percent are white, and 1 percent are Asian.</p>
        <p>Inside Room 276, the intake courtroom, a fluorescent light flickers disconcertingly. Every time the doors open and the court officers yell out a name, they practically drown out Lee Elkins, the quiet-spoken judge handling a roster of 183 cases that day. The telephone rings. Lawyers chat with each other, and when the murmur grows too loud, a court officer yells, ''Order!''</p>
        <p>''If you come into this courthouse, see the facility, suffer the long wait, if you're talking about the most intimate details of your life and doors are opening around you and people are harried, it has to give you the impression that your dignity as a person is not respected,'' Judge Elkins says. ''If anything, Family Court should be the opposite.''</p>
        <p>The physical state of the courthouse alone, he adds, exacerbates what is already a distressing situation. ''It's uncomfortable, it's hot, there's no privacy, the noise level,'' he rattles on. ''If anything, we need an environment that makes people calmer.'' (A new courthouse is scheduled to be built, but work has not yet started on it.)</p>
        <p>When he is not assigned to intake, Judge Elkins, known for his reflective demeanor, handles 25 to 30 cases a day, all involving the perilous decisions of child protection: whether to return children to a mother who beat her son with a hanger; whether to hand over a toddler to a mother with acute depression. Now, there is the urgency imposed by a new federal adoption law; a child who remains in foster care for 15 of the previous 22 months must either be freed for adoption or reunited with parents.  Few believe the city's Family Court system will be able to comply.</p>
        <p>Family Court caseloads are growing faster than those of any other court, state officials say. More than 232,000 cases were handled last year citywide by 42 judges, a caseload that has tripled in the last 20 years. On this day, Judge Elkins's workday began, happily, with the adoption certifications at 9:30 a.m. It didn't end until well past 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>The study by the Vera Institute found that three-fourths of the people interviewed, after waiting for three hours, were still waiting to see a judge. They had been to court an average of 4.7 times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
