<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Rescue Too Far</title>
    <meta content="LTR234156" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224167"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOATS AND BOATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vrolyk, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccormick, Herb</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonard, Ray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EFDA103EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="375" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Rescue Too Far</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Vrolyk letter on Herb McCormick's August 6 praises Ray Leonard for abandoning his boat during storm under orders from officials but holds experienced sailor in well-found boat has better judgment than any remote safety official</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Sports Editor:</p>
        <p>The article by Herb McCormick, ''Sailing Is Smooth in Wake of a Storm'' (Aug. 6), is a wonderful example of why my family reads The Times.</p>
        <p>Ray Leonard did exactly the right thing in abandoning his boat under orders from officials. It was an absurd command, unfortunately quite typical of our various rescue organizations today, but it was correct for him to obey. Had he not, he would have risked the lives of others. However, it must be understood that young helicopter pilots, no matter how well-intentioned, are almost completely unqualified to judge the risk that a sailing boat is in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Sports Editor:</p>
        <p>The article by Herb McCormick, ''Sailing Is Smooth in Wake of a Storm'' (Aug. 6), is a wonderful example of why my family reads The Times.</p>
        <p>Ray Leonard did exactly the right thing in abandoning his boat under orders from officials. It was an absurd command, unfortunately quite typical of our various rescue organizations today, but it was correct for him to obey. Had he not, he would have risked the lives of others. However, it must be understood that young helicopter pilots, no matter how well-intentioned, are almost completely unqualified to judge the risk that a sailing boat is in.</p>
        <p>The fact that the boat subsequently sailed itself to the mainland and ran aground unharmed is evidence of how little risk was actually involved. The loose gear was still sitting on the deck where Leonard had left it.</p>
        <p>Similar problems occurred during the fatal Fastnet Race of 1969 when entire crews died in their life rafts after they were asked to abandon ship, only to have their small sailboats still sailing along crewless after the storm. Sailboats are far more seaworthy than the fishing boats and many large ships with which they share the sea.</p>
        <p>The lesson to be learned here is that an experienced sailor in a well-found boat will always have better judgment about the safety of his or her condition than any remote safety official. It is the reason that the ultimate authority has remained with the captain to this day.</p>
        <p>I have sympathy for the crew aboard Leonard's boat. I'm certain they were afraid. Yet, they didn't have the experience to judge the conditions, and clearly panicked. It is terrible to be locked inside a boat in a strong storm. The violent motion and sounds of water crashing against the hull are terrifying. The Westsail 32, however, is designed to take that sort of weather in stride. A slow and heavy boat, its shining strength is doing exactly what Leonard was asking Satori to do -- weather a storm with her crew safely below.</p>
        <p>To continue the insult to Leonard, Sebastian Junger's book and the movie make him out a fool, which he clearly is not.</p>
        <p>JOHN VROLYK  Burlingame, Calif.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
