<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Curing The Blahs Of August</title>
    <meta content="20CUT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taylor, Patricia a</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EED7153EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Curing The Blahs Of August</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA A. TAYLOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Taylor, Patricia a</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Experts describe how to grow colorful borders; photos (Cuttings column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GEOGRAPHY can play a big role in the August psyche of a gardener. In my travels at this time of year -- through northern New England, around Minneapolis and in the San Francisco Bay area -- I have consistently met gardeners who are proud to display their colorful borders.</p>
        <p>This is in marked contrast to where I live. In the humid, insect-prone mid-Atlantic region, August gardens tend to be worn-out disasters. I've yet to encounter anyone here saying, ''You must see my August garden.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GEOGRAPHY can play a big role in the August psyche of a gardener. In my travels at this time of year -- through northern New England, around Minneapolis and in the San Francisco Bay area -- I have consistently met gardeners who are proud to display their colorful borders.</p>
        <p>This is in marked contrast to where I live. In the humid, insect-prone mid-Atlantic region, August gardens tend to be worn-out disasters. I've yet to encounter anyone here saying, ''You must see my August garden.''</p>
        <p>Lately, though, I've been voicing a modified version of that sentiment, thanks to a wonderful, carefree group of plants. Holding back their flower power until this listless month, their freshness, in whites, pinks, yellows and blues, creates a joyful sight in drooping, mildewed borders.</p>
        <p>Several sweet pepperbushes (Clethra alnifolia) start the month with an intoxicating oomph. Their  panicles -- two to four inches, in light to white pink -- emit a lush fragrance that permeates muggy humidity. Those in sun start their bloom period of two to three weeks in early August, and those in shade a week later. A dwarf form, Hummingbird, is only three feet high, and the species plant tops out at 6 to 10 feet.</p>
        <p>The cheerful golden yellow flowers of brown-eyed Susans (Rudbeckia triloba) usually open the first week of August. This little known, three- to three-and-a-half-foot biennial cousin of the popular black-eyed Susan resists mildew and thrives in full sun to part shade. Its numerous branches, jutting out from the sturdy main stem, are dotted with one-to-two-inch flowers for more than six weeks.</p>
        <p>In the quiet of deep shade, the soft yellow, two-inch dangling flowers of wax-bells (Kirengeshoma palmata) usually open in mid-August and hold for almost a month. The maplelike leaves on this three-to-four-foot perennial contrast handsomely with hosta foliage.</p>
        <p>Three tried and true hostas are flowering stalwarts in my August borders: H. lancifolia, H. plantaginea and H. Royal Standard.</p>
        <p>Lancifolia has slim, dark green leaves that are only five by two inches. The abundant flowers are a rich bluish purple, last three to five weeks, and float 12 inches above neat mounds that are about 36 inches wide and 18 inches tall.</p>
        <p>Plantaginea is an old-fashioned hosta treasured for its fragrant, gleaming white flowers. These bloom for more than three weeks and are lovely in arrangements. The warm green heart-shaped leaves measure about five by seven inches and form mounds similar in size to those of lance lily.</p>
        <p>Closely related, Royal Standard differs significantly in that it thrives in full sun as well as shade. It's a much bolder plant, too, with densely packed upright leaves that form large clumps two feet tall. While the flowers are not as fragrant as plantaginea's, their bloom period is one or two weeks longer.</p>
        <p>The elegant pink buds, flowers and seed capsules of hardy begonia (B. grandis subsp. evansiana) start their eight-week color presence in early August. Technically a tuber but generally sold as a perennial because it is hardy to Zone 6, hardy begonia looks like an angel wing begonia.  Two to three feet tall, it has large leaves with soft red undercoats.</p>
        <p>Garlic chives (Allium tuberosum) are usually found in vegetable beds. I've sprinkled them about my sunny flower borders, where they bloom for three weeks in August. They are two-  to three-feet tall and feature white umbrella-shaped flowers heads that crown slim stems. And yes, you can use the ribbonlike foliage as a mild food seasoning.</p>
        <p>The September Charm anemone hybrid, despite its name, blooms throughout most of August in my garden. Its lovely lavender pink flowers bob about in sunny areas on slim three-foot stems.</p>
        <p>Two other perennials' bloom period of six weeks or longer starts in mid-August, adding elegant coolness to sunny and partly shaded areas.</p>
        <p>One -- hardy ageratum (Eupatorium coelestinum) -- is covered with blue flowers that to a nonscientific eye look the same as those on the annual ageratum. The fuzzy swaths of blue, crowning stems of one to three feet, are smashing. Be warned that this is an aggressive spreader. But I resist yanking it all out in early spring because of its beautiful August presence.</p>
        <p>And then there is what many view as the piece de resistance in August gardens: Lobelia Ruby Slippers. This magnificent hybrid was created by the North Carolina breeder Thurman Maness 15 years ago and has gone on to win fame and fans across the country. Its luscious wine red petals cluster on imposing spikes four to five feet tall and thrive on side shoots after the spikes are cut.</p>
        <p>All these newly opening flowers soothe my psyche in this hot, humid month. They may do the same for yours.</p>
        <p>Bluestone Perennials, 7211 Middle Ridge Road, Madison, Ohio 44057; (800) 852-5243; free catalog.</p>
        <p>Forestfarm, 990 Tetherow Road, Williams, Ore. 97544; (541) 846-7269; catalog, $4.</p>
        <p>We-Du Nurseries, Route 5, Box 724, Marion, N.C. 28752-9338; (828) 738-8300; catalog, $2.</p>
        <p>Willow Pond Nursery, P.O. Box 192, Hewlett, N.Y. 11557; (516) 374-2522; catalog, $2.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
