<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Homeless Take Control of Their Lives on the Web</title>
    <meta content="20HOME$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crow, Kelly</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E6DC123EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Homeless Take Control of Their Lives on the Web</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KELLY CROW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crow, Kelly</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on homeless New York City people who are using computers in rescue missions and public libraries to surf Internet for jobs, build Web pages and use e-mail to reunite with family members; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Back home in Puerto Rico, Angel Mora's family calls him Maestro, because he is so good with computers and because they are so proud of him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mora, 34, a former auto mechanic, cherishes the nickname, because when he walked into the New York City Rescue Mission nearly two years ago, the closest he had ever come to a computer was a pocket calculator.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Back home in Puerto Rico, Angel Mora's family calls him Maestro, because he is so good with computers and because they are so proud of him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mora, 34, a former auto mechanic, cherishes the nickname, because when he walked into the New York City Rescue Mission nearly two years ago, the closest he had ever come to a computer was a pocket calculator.</p>
        <p>By contrast, Shawn, a 28-year-old from New Jersey who preferred not to give his last name, regularly surfed the Internet before going to the mission a few months ago. He has since taught himself how to build a Web page.</p>
        <p>Thanks to rescue missions and public libraries, a number of the city's 50,000 homeless people are finding the Internet. They are using it to get jobs and apply to colleges. They are building Web pages and using e-mail to reunite with family members. They do not have a physical address, but they are claiming a free and permanent one in cyberspace.</p>
        <p>''It's reassuring to know you have a place that's yours, a way to get the basics,'' Shawn said. ''Some of these other homeless guys, how can they get a fax, a phone call?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mora and Shawn spend hours in the mission's Career and Learning Center, on Lafayette Street south of Canal Street, which is stocked with eight computers and books like ''Unleashing Unix.''</p>
        <p>Most of the men at the mission have been out on the street less than a year, and one in five knew something about the Internet before winding up there, said Andy Duncan, who oversees the three-year-old computer center. The rest are eager to learn.</p>
        <p>The men first take tutorials on typing and word processing. Then they are given e-mail accounts with Yahoo! or Hotmail, Mr. Duncan said. Most check their e-mail once or twice a week, but a few visit daily.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mora is one such student. He downloads G.E.D. practice tests and looks up information about cars and about treating his diabetes. He sends e-mail to his niece and gets e-mail jokes from Shawn.</p>
        <p>Shawn receives e-mail updates from Web sites like USAjobs.com, CareerMosiac, and How Stuff Works. He also swaps e-mail with  friends who do not know he is homeless and with family members who do. He recently re-enrolled online for the fall semester at the New Jersey Institute of Technology after dropping out last year.</p>
        <p>Until he goes back, he is posting his resume online. So far, three mission residents have found jobs through the Internet: Billy as a truck driver; Michael as a mortician; and another man who joined a pharmaceuticals company in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Homeless techies are also taking advantage of the public library.</p>
        <p>''Someone who rents a book needs a physical address, but they can use any of the facilities without needing an identity,'' said Joanne King of the Queens Borough Public Library, explaining the allure.</p>
        <p>Ned Richards of the New Amsterdam branch of the New York Public Library in Lower Manhattan said his homeless patrons preferred to be left alone.</p>
        <p>''They are so smart, but a lot of them feel threatened by everything,'' he said.</p>
        <p>KELLY CROW</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
