<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business; Real Estate Commissions Endure a Web Assault</title>
    <meta content="20REAL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000827T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224045"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Assn of Realtors</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Realtor.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Jayson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E1DC123EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1471" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business; Real Estate Commissions Endure a Web Assault</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blair, Jayson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Critics and competitors of Realtor.com, four-year-old Web site of National Assn of Realtors, complain that it has stifled innovation and kept costs high for consumers; prominent Manhattan real estate agents create new Web service with their listings; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH a few clicks of the mouse and about 160,000 listings to start, the National Association of Realtors promised in 1996 that its Web site, called Realtor.com, would increase efficiencies and cut the costs of selling homes.</p>
        <p>But four years and about 1.2 million listings later, critics and competitors complain that the Realtor.com, the nation's dominant real estate Web site, has done the opposite of what was promised. It has stifled innovation and kept costs high for consumers, they say, even as it reduces expenses for agents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH a few clicks of the mouse and about 160,000 listings to start, the National Association of Realtors promised in 1996 that its Web site, called Realtor.com, would increase efficiencies and cut the costs of selling homes.</p>
        <p>But four years and about 1.2 million listings later, critics and competitors complain that the Realtor.com, the nation's dominant real estate Web site, has done the opposite of what was promised. It has stifled innovation and kept costs high for consumers, they say, even as it reduces expenses for agents.</p>
        <p>Although the Internet has become a tool for reducing all sorts of costs -- allowing stock trades for just pennies a share, for example -- real estate agents have been able to keep their commissions for selling a home at 6 percent. Instead of replacing the Multiple Listing Services -- where brokers' exclusive access has helped guarantee them their commissions -- the Web has allowed brokers to defend these services and preserve their way of doing business. Not even Bill Gates has been able to muscle in.</p>
        <p>The critics argue that agents across the country have sought to prevent online competitors from gaining a share of the market and changing the business. ''The National Association of Realtors has acted to co-opt the Internet to protect its high-margin structure,'' said Paul Sealey, a former chief technology officer at Coca-Cola and a professor at the Haas School of Business at the University of California in Berkeley.</p>
        <p>Buying and selling homes thus remains far more cumbersome and expensive than it has to be, he said. ''There are too many agents driving people to too many places that they don't want to see,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Just last month, three of Manhattan's largest brokerage firms, the Corcoran Group, Douglas Elliman and the Halstead Property Company, announced the creation of a new service on the Web with all their listings. Officials from these firms acknowledged that they feared a planned onslaught  by other Web sites that could offer more comprehensive listings and discounts on the standard 6 percent. Buying an apartment in Manhattan has been particularly cumbersome, because agents do not share their listings on any central source.</p>
        <p>Agents say that buying a home is a far more complicated transaction than buying airline tickets or stocks. Each property and each buyer is unique, and only a qualified real estate agent can match them, then handle the intricacies of the sale, they say.</p>
        <p>''In the end, consumers will be better served by experts in the real estate business who run Internet sites, as opposed to experts in technology and the Internet who just want to make a quick buck off of real estate,'' said Scott Durkin, Corcoran's chief operating officer. ''This is a very personal business and people want an expert, a sounding board who can hold their hand through the process.''</p>
        <p>People in the industry estimate that the typical transaction involves 50 to 60 people, including buyers, brokers, bankers, clerks, appraisers and sellers. The Internet could reduce that number, speeding a process that can now take months.</p>
        <p>ALREADY, the Web has promoted efficiency by allowing more buyers to  preview listings on their own, eliminating ones that they do not want to see in person. But Mr. Sealey said the Internet could also reduce the time it takes to bid, write contracts, obtain mortgages and handle other paperwork.</p>
        <p>The threat of competition has prompted real estate agents to introduce some efficiencies. ''Our worst fear was that some third party with deep pockets would come in and take over our business,'' said Scott Durkin, chief operating officer of Corcoran.</p>
        <p>In Manhattan, one third party, Goldman  Sachs, is backing the creation of an online listing service that could expand nationally. Some of its potential partners may charge commissions as low as 2 percent.</p>
        <p>Daniel Levy, the president of CityRealty.com, one of the New York real estate companies that Goldman has backed,  said the industry's own online efforts have been purely defensive. He remembers that Mr. Gates, in ''The Road Ahead,'' his 1995 book, dared real estate agents to ignore the impact of the Internet. Mr. Gates said that, within a year or two after online classifieds and listings became available, they would become the primary means of matching buyers and sellers. ''The whole system of real estate agencies and commissions may be changed,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>But Microsoft's HomeAdvisor.com, the company's effort to list homes online, has been trumped by the National Association of Realtors. The Web sites that the association controls, Realtor.com and HomeStore.com, accept listings only from registered real estate agents, generally with the full 6 percent commissions.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, HomeAdvisor.com set out to streamline the process and lower commissions. The Realtors association responded not only by lobbying against Microsoft in its antitrust battle, but also by requiring brokerage firms to list exclusively with Realtor.com online.</p>
        <p>Since then, HomeAdvisor has backed away. Most of its listings are sold through agents with the usual commissions.</p>
        <p>Bryan P. Misetle, general manager of HomeAdvisor Technologies, said that having the Realtors association as an online competitor placed other companies at a disadvantage. ''We have seen them operate in a manner that is not in the best interest of consumers or innovation,'' Mr. Misetle said.</p>
        <p>THE association is frank about its intentions. ''One of our central goals is to keep the Realtor at the center and integral to the real estate transaction, but along the way I think we have helped innovation,'' said Stephen Cook, the group's vice president. ''When the dust settles and the survivors are left, we wanted to see a Realtor-dominated site on the top.''</p>
        <p>Experts say the agents remain vulnerable. Several companies, like yhd.com in New Jersey and eHomes.com in Southern California, already offer reduced commissions for sellers who do tasks like posting their own listings and advertisements on the Web, or having open houses. Some other sites, like Homegain.com, require brokers to bid, with the one offering the lowest commission receiving the right to list a property.</p>
        <p>Rolf T. Wigand, an information studies professor at Syracuse University, said the process of unbundling services, aided by the Internet, could reduce commissions. But he doubted that the Internet would eliminate real estate agents and commissions.</p>
        <p>''I am convinced that many real estate purchases start with the Internet, but end up with the help of a local agent,'' he said. ''It is a much too personal purchase.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sealey expects brokers to become ''consultants, not just pencil pushers and drivers,'' with various commissions determined by the level of service provided.</p>
        <p>''Both that commission structure and the number of real estate agents are going to be cut in half,'' he said, ''because there are gross inefficiencies in the current process.''</p>
        <p>Searching for That Dream House, on Your Computer</p>
        <p>Here are several Web sites for house-hunting.</p>
        <p>* Homegain.com Allows sellers to post their listings. Real estate brokers bid with various packages of services for reduced commissions.</p>
        <p>* Corcoran.com An international Web site affiliated with the Corcoran Group of New York. Allows buyers to search for properties listed with agents everywhere from Kenya to Scandinavia. Sellers generally pay 6 percent commissions.</p>
        <p>* Brokersnyc.com A New York site with negotiable commissions.</p>
        <p>* Realtor.com and Homestore.com Affiliated sites controlled by the National Association of Realtors. They have the largest collection of listings. Charges 6 percent commissions.</p>
        <p>* HomeAdvisor.com A Microsoft site that offers the second-largest number of listings, usually with 6 percent commissions. Includes peripheral services like assistance in finding home insurance, or lawn chairs for the deck.</p>
        <p>* Homebytes.com Lists and sells homes for a flat $499 plus, at the seller's discretion, a commission for a buyer's agent, typically 3 percent.</p>
        <p>* eHomes.com Offers three levels of service, including a ''for sale by owner'' program that charges a $95 flat fee and one that charges a 4 percent commission. Serves only Southern California, but plans to expand to the remainder of the state.</p>
        <p>* yhd.com Stands for ''your home direct.'' Similar to eHomes, with a top rate of 3.9 percent, serving New Jersey.</p>
        <p>* eRealty.com Serves Boston and parts of Texas with a 3.5 or 4.5 percent commission depending on how much of the paperwork the seller handles.</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 27, 2000, Sunday  An article last Sunday about online home sales misstated the given name of a business professor at the University of California at Berkeley who said the National Association of Realtors had used its Internet presence to protect its profit structure. He is Peter Sealey, not Paul.</p>
        <p>The article also misstated Professor Sealey's former title. He was chief marketing officer at the Coca-Cola Company, not chief technology officer.</p>
        <p>The article also referred incorrectly to the arrangements that the association and its affiliated Web sites have with real estate brokerage firms for online listings. The firms are required to list their properties exclusively on the sites in order to receive payments for their listings. They can also list properties with other Web sites, but receive no payments from the association's sites if they do so.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 27, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about online home sales misstated the given name of a business professor at the University of California at Berkeley who said the National Association of Realtors had used its Internet presence to protect its profit structure. He is Peter Sealey, not Paul.</p>
        <p>The article also misstated Professor Sealey's former title. He was chief marketing officer at the Coca-Cola Company, not chief technology officer.</p>
        <p>The article also referred incorrectly to the arrangements that the association and its affiliated Web sites have with real estate brokerage firms for online listings. The firms are required to list their properties exclusively on the sites in order to receive payments for their listings. They can also list properties with other Web sites, but receive no payments from the association's sites if they do so.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
