<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Venezuela Finds Source of Wealth Is Also a Curse</title>
    <meta content="20VENE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224115"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Venezuela</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chavez, Hugo (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EFD7133EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1513" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Venezuela Finds Source of Wealth Is Also a Curse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>CARACAS, Venezuela</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Venezuela's abundance of oil has come to be regarded there not as blessing but as curse; while 80 percent of Venezuelans believe their country is one of world's richest, because of its oil reserves, equal number complain that they have not benefited from oil riches; Venezuelans blame their leaders rather than oil bonanza mentality that has discouraged individual initiative; sense of entitlement is so deeply engrained that when past governments attempted to raise gasoline prices, there was rioting, looting and hundreds of people killed; Pres Hugo Chavez has support of overwhelming majority of population, but his government appears just as intimidated as its predecessors by specter of popular resistance to any effort to bring local gasoline prices in line with international rates and thereby discourage excessive consumption (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like motorists everywhere, Venezuelans love to complain about the price of gasoline, and they have been doing a lot of that lately. But one thing sets them apart from almost everyone else in the world: at less than 40 cents a gallon, gas is cheaper than bottled water here.</p>
        <p>To Americans who are now paying nearly $2 a gallon for gas, such carping may seem absurd. But the constant griping about gasoline prices among Venezuelans is emblematic of their complicated and conflicted relationship with a commodity that so dominates their national life that it accounts for half of all government revenues and four-fifths of this country's exports.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like motorists everywhere, Venezuelans love to complain about the price of gasoline, and they have been doing a lot of that lately. But one thing sets them apart from almost everyone else in the world: at less than 40 cents a gallon, gas is cheaper than bottled water here.</p>
        <p>To Americans who are now paying nearly $2 a gallon for gas, such carping may seem absurd. But the constant griping about gasoline prices among Venezuelans is emblematic of their complicated and conflicted relationship with a commodity that so dominates their national life that it accounts for half of all government revenues and four-fifths of this country's exports.</p>
        <p>This nation of 23 million people has the greatest petroleum reserves outside the Middle East. Venezuela has also been the largest oil supplier to the United States in recent years and, with prices now at their highest level in a decade, it is looking forward to record oil revenues of $21 billion this year. Yet oil has come to be regarded here not as a blessing but as a curse.</p>
        <p>When petroleum first emerged as the core of the economy back in the 1930's, governments were urged to follow a policy of ''sowing the oil,'' in the famous phrase of the writer Arturo Uslar Pietri, to encourage investment instead of mindless consumption. But the reality turned out to be different, and a saying often heard here in recent years cynically summarizes Venezuelan history this way: ''Columbus discovered us, Bolivar liberated us, and oil ruined us.''</p>
        <p>''This is a sick society, and it is sick as a result of an illness called oil,'' said Anibal Romero, a professor of political science at Simon Bolivar University here. ''Oil is easy to produce, it can be done by others with imported equipment, and it always sells. As a result, it has asphyxiated the rest of the economy and led the majority of Venezuelans to believe that if they are not rich, it is because someone has stolen what belongs to them.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, in poll after poll conducted over the past decade, Alfredo Keller and Associates, a leading public opinion research firm here, has found that 80 percent of Venezuelans believe that theirs is ''one of the richest countries in the world'' because of its oil reserves.</p>
        <p>Roughly the same percentage believe that the main function of government is ''to share this wealth among all'' but also complain that they themselves ''have not benefited from these riches.''</p>
        <p>But rather than point their fingers at an economic model that favors oil over all other activities, thus engendering a bonanza mentality and discouraging individual initiative, Venezuelans prefer to blame their leaders. Up to 80 percent believe, Mr. Keller said, that the responsibility for their own poverty ''lies with government and politicians,'' and that it is ''because of corruption'' that the state has failed to serve them.</p>
        <p>''People here have never thought of this country's problem as economic,'' said Carlos Sabino, a sociologist at the Central University of Venezuela who has written extensively about oil's impact on Venezuelan society. ''They have always considered it a moral and political problem.''</p>
        <p>It was exactly that sense of resentment and moral outrage that President Hugo Chavez rode to power in the December 1998 presidential election, in which he won 58 percent of the vote. But with the price of Venezuelan crude having quadrupled in the 18 months since he was sworn in, he too is facing pressure to deliver the ''golden age'' of prosperity and social justice that Venezuelans expect and that he promised as a candidate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chavez, 46, a former army colonel who in 1992 led an unsuccessful coup, has stoked such expectations by claiming to have almost singlehandedly engineered the worldwide rise in oil prices. During his successful campaign for re-election last month to a new six year term, he reminded voters that it was his decision to cut back production that has given a new vigor to the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries, or OPEC.</p>
        <p>As a result, the current boom in oil prices may have reawakened memories of the 1970's and expectations that a new round of spending and subsidies will follow. The 1970's, after all, were an era in which oil revenues were so plentiful and Venezuelans so affluent that other Latin Americans referred to them as ''los damedos,'' or ''the gimme twos,'' a reference to their lavish spending habits.</p>
        <p>''To get out of the mess we put ourselves in then, we are going to have to make sacrifices,'' said Luis Cortillo, 69, a retired airline crew supervisor. ''But we don't want to accept that solution; we want to go on living just like in the days when the money flowed like water.''</p>
        <p>That sense of entitlement is so deeply ingrained that past governments here have attempted to raise gasoline prices at their peril. In February 1989, President Carlos Andres Perez did just that, and the immediate result was riots, looting and hundreds of people killed -- events followed three years later by Mr. Perez's fall from power and Mr. Chavez's own coup attempt.</p>
        <p>''The country is rich, but its people are not,'' said Lido Araque, a 48-year-old gas station attendant who earns about $200 a month, when asked why Venezuelans should continue to enjoy low energy costs.</p>
        <p>''So I would say the price of gasoline has to be kept at this level for at least three more years, because when gas prices go up, food and transportation costs rise too.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chavez calls his movement to reform the Venezuelan state a ''revolution,'' and he clearly has the support of the overwhelming majority of the population.</p>
        <p>But his government appears just as intimidated as its predecessors by the specter of popular resistance to any effort to bring local gasoline prices in line with international rates and thereby discourage excessive consumption.</p>
        <p>''In determining the prices of energy, it is not just economic factors that must be taken into account,'' Ali Rodriguez, minister of energy and mines, said in a recent interview. ''We have a critical social situation.''</p>
        <p>Eventually, ''there will be an adjustment made in the price of gasoline,'' Mr. Rodriguez, who is also the president of OPEC, added. ''But it has to be done at the proper time, when there is an economic recovery and employment is picking up.''</p>
        <p>At the moment, however, Mr. Chavez faces a situation that has no precedent in Venezuelan history. Even with the price of a barrel of locally produced crude rising so dramatically, the Venezuelan economy shrank by 7.2 percent last year, and more than half the work force is either unemployed or working off the books in what is euphemistically called ''the informal economy.''</p>
        <p>To placate his supporters, Mr. Chavez has spent hundreds of millions of dollars on a military-run civic assistance program called Plan Bolivar 2000, providing subsidized food and free medical care. He has also proposed populist initiatives like the subsidized manufacture of a relatively cheap ''People's Car'' that would obviously encourage even greater gasoline consumption.</p>
        <p>But he has conspicuously hesitated to take steps that might hit ordinary Venezuelans in their pocketbooks. Even the idea of trying to prepare for the day when oil prices start to decline again by raising taxes is controversial, and not just because the economy is mired in a recession.</p>
        <p>''Historically, the problem of the state here has not been how to obtain resources through taxes to cover public spending, but how to distribute this growing income,'' Mr. Rodriguez said. ''For that reason, because money was so abundant, we were not charged taxes, and that had a cultural impact on Venezuelan society, in the sense that no one here developed the habit of paying taxes or a sense that not to pay taxes is a crime.''</p>
        <p>In a speech in early August, just before he embarked on a tour of OPEC nations aimed at keeping oil prices at their current high levels, Mr. Chavez announced ambitious plans to develop tourism, agriculture, mining and fishing.</p>
        <p>But the reality, with the rest of the economy hobbled by a recession, is that Venezuela is probably more reliant on oil than ever, and thus more susceptible to the impact of a downturn when it eventually comes.</p>
        <p>''Governments here are always like a gambler at a casino,'' Dr. Sabino said. ''They have their run of luck, and they come to believe that everything can be resolved with an increase in the price of oil. Nothing that Chavez is doing tells me that he is any different from the others, and that is the problem.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
