<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>12 Hurt as Buses Collide Near Lincoln Tunnel, Snarling Traffic</title>
    <meta content="14BUS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/14/nyregion/14BUS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lincoln Tunnel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Olympia Trail</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Transit</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Maria</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E3DC1238F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="551" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>12 Hurt as Buses Collide Near Lincoln Tunnel, Snarling Traffic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIA NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Maria</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Two buses collide head-on in express bus lane leading into Lincoln Tunnel from New Jersey, injuring 2 drivers and 10 passengers and snarling traffic for several hours in morning rush; injured passengers are treated at hospitals and released; drivers are hospitalized; accident occurs when Olympia Trail bus veers into express bus lane, which carries traffic going other way, and into New Jersey Transit bus (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two buses collided head-on yesterday morning in the express bus lane leading into the Lincoln Tunnel from New Jersey, injuring the 2 drivers and 10 passengers and snarling traffic for several hours in the morning rush.</p>
        <p>The injured passengers, five from each bus, were treated and released after being examined at two New Jersey hospitals. But the bus drivers, who were listed in fair condition, were being kept overnight at the Jersey City Medical Center for observation, said Lynn McFarlane, director of public affairs for the Liberty Healthcare System, which oversees the hospital.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two buses collided head-on yesterday morning in the express bus lane leading into the Lincoln Tunnel from New Jersey, injuring the 2 drivers and 10 passengers and snarling traffic for several hours in the morning rush.</p>
        <p>The injured passengers, five from each bus, were treated and released after being examined at two New Jersey hospitals. But the bus drivers, who were listed in fair condition, were being kept overnight at the Jersey City Medical Center for observation, said Lynn McFarlane, director of public affairs for the Liberty Healthcare System, which oversees the hospital.</p>
        <p>The accident occurred just before 7 a.m. when the driver of an Olympia Trail bus veered into the express bus lane, which carries traffic going the other way, and into a New Jersey Transit bus heading into Manhattan from Elmwood Park, said Steve Coleman, a spokesman for the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, which operates the tunnel and is investigating the collision.</p>
        <p>The Olympia bus, an airport shuttle ferrying passengers from Manhattan to Newark International Airport, had been heading west on Interstate 495 near John F. Kennedy Boulevard less than two miles from the tunnel. The other bus was in an eastbound express lane, called a ''contraflow lane,'' that is divided from westbound traffic only by orange cones, Mr. Coleman said.</p>
        <p>William Schafer, director of operations for Olympia, which is based in Elizabeth, N.J., would not provide any information on the bus driver, but said that it had not yet been confirmed that it was his company's bus that went into the wrong lane.</p>
        <p>''No final determination has been made about who was in whose lane,'' he said. ''The investigation is ongoing.''</p>
        <p>But a spokeswoman for New Jersey Transit said that the company had learned, through other drivers and witnesses it interviewed, that the Olympia bus driver was trying to avoid running into a car in front of her, and that an overnight rain may have made the road slick.</p>
        <p>''She tried to apply her brakes to avoid hitting the car that had just rear-ended a truck,'' said Anna Farneski, a public information officer for New Jersey Transit. ''She skidded on the wet pavement and hit our bus.''</p>
        <p>The Port Authority said it could not confirm that account.</p>
        <p>Ms. Farneski identified the New Jersey Transit driver as Jack Paventud, and said he had a spotless record during his 17 years as a bus operator for the service.</p>
        <p>The contraflow lane is reserved  for buses during the morning rush, saving riders about 30 minutes because they do not have to travel in the more heavily congested eastbound lanes, Mr. Coleman said. He said that in the 30 years or so that the Port Authority has set aside the lane, there have been few accidents.</p>
        <p>''We've had accidents, but we can't recall one as serious as this in many, many years,'' he said. In the last four years, there have been 13 accidents in the lane, he said, most of them minor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coleman said 1,700 buses use the lane every morning, carrying 60,000 passengers.</p>
        <p>''When you think about how many buses and passengers use it every day, and the number of accidents there have been over the years, I think that lane is extremely safe,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
