<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>France Warns Iraq on Weapons Inspections</title>
    <meta content="Y14NATI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/14/world/14NATI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230378"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wren, Christopher S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vedrine, Hubert (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aziz, Tariq (Deputy Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5D81538F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="512" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>France Warns Iraq on Weapons Inspections</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER S. WREN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wren, Christopher S</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Sept. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>French Foreign Min Hubert Vedrine, who has criticized sanctions against Iraq, nonetheless says he has warned Iraq's deputy prime minister, Tariq Aziz, not to expect any weakening of Security Council's determination to send United Nations inspectors back into Iraq to eliminate weapons of mass destruction before sanctions can be lifted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>France has warned Iraq not to expect any weakening of the Security Council's determination to send United Nations inspectors back into Iraq to eliminate weapons of mass destruction before sanctions can be lifted.</p>
        <p>France's foreign minister, Hubert Vedrine, who has criticized the sanctions, nonetheless said today that he told Iraq's deputy prime minister, Tariq Aziz, on Monday that it would be ''a very serious mistake'' to think that an erosion of the Council's resolve would lead it to lift the sanctions, which were imposed when Iraqi forces occupied Kuwait in 1990.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>France has warned Iraq not to expect any weakening of the Security Council's determination to send United Nations inspectors back into Iraq to eliminate weapons of mass destruction before sanctions can be lifted.</p>
        <p>France's foreign minister, Hubert Vedrine, who has criticized the sanctions, nonetheless said today that he told Iraq's deputy prime minister, Tariq Aziz, on Monday that it would be ''a very serious mistake'' to think that an erosion of the Council's resolve would lead it to lift the sanctions, which were imposed when Iraqi forces occupied Kuwait in 1990.</p>
        <p>''I in fact met with Tariq Aziz the day before yesterday, and I told him the only solution for Iraq was to comply with Resolution 1284 and to cooperate,'' Mr. Vedrine said during a breakfast interview with reporters.</p>
        <p>The resolution, which the Security Council adopted last Dec. 17, created a new arms inspection plan for Iraq. The previous inspection system collapsed in December 1998, when American and British warplanes bombed Baghdad to punish President Saddam Hussein for failing to cooperate.</p>
        <p>As an incentive for Baghdad, the resolution lifted a ceiling on the amount of oil that it could sell abroad to buy food and other essentials, and also relaxed controls on the import of some other supplies. Otherwise, the economic sanctions were kept in place.</p>
        <p>Eleven of the 15 Security Council members voted for the resolution at the time. But France joined Russia, China and Malaysia in abstaining, prompting the Iraqis to infer that support for sanctions was waning. The split emboldened Iraq to reject the Council's resolution. United Nations officials have been concerned that Iraq keeps balking in hopes of forcing a further dilution or even lifting of sanctions. Baghdad has refused to allow arms inspectors back into the country, though the new inspection commission's executive chairman, Hans Blix, says they are ready to begin inspections.</p>
        <p>Mr. Aziz recently met several other diplomats at the United Nations besides Mr. Vedrine to assess the Security Council's mood. But Ewen Buchanan, Mr. Blix's spokesman, confirmed that ''Aziz made no effort to come near Blix.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Vedrine, after meeting with Mr. Aziz, said he foresaw no short-term change in Iraq's refusal to comply. ''I regret that,'' he added.</p>
        <p>He told reporters today that France had helped broker the 1999 resolution and had abstained from the vote because the resolution could have been improved. France, which maintains commercial and diplomatic relations with Iraq, continues to abide by the resolution, he said.</p>
        <p>The French foreign minister today called the sanctions ''primitive,'' and ''a cruel measure'' in their impact on ordinary Iraqis, and ''completely absurd'' economically.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Mr. Vedrine said, ''we take the security concerns of Iraq's neighbors very seriously.''</p>
        <p>Kuwait's foreign minister, Sabah al-Ahmad al-Jaber al-Sabah, urged in a speech to the General Assembly today that pressure be maintained on Iraq, which, he said, continued to reveal ''non-peaceful intentions and policies of aggression'' toward its neighbors.</p>
        <p>''Indeed,'' he said, ''it is regrettable that for 10 years now the government of Iraq has failed to meet its obligations under Security Council resolutions.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
