<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Design Chosen for Memorial to Dr. King</title>
    <meta content="14KING" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/14/national/14KING.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230474"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROMA Design Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">King, Martin Luther Jr (1929-68)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Molotsky, Irvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">King, Coretta Scott</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">King, Bernice Albertine (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Young, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EEDA1238F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Design Chosen for Memorial to Dr. King</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRVIN MOLOTSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Molotsky, Irvin</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Monument with 'stone of hope' to represent nonviolent civil rights movement is selected as memorial to Rev Dr Martin Luther King Jr that will be built on Washington Mall; winning design is submitted by ROMA Design Group; likeness of King will be cut into rock facing neaby Jefferson Memorial; approvals are still needed from three federal commissions and National Park Service; photo of Coretta Scott King, King's widow, Bernice King, their daughter, and Andrew Young, at Washington event marking selection (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A monument with a ''stone of hope'' that represents the nonviolent civil rights movement was selected tonight as the memorial to the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. that will be built on the Washington Mall.</p>
        <p>''It will convey the meaning of Martin's life,'' said Coretta Scott King, Dr. King's widow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A monument with a ''stone of hope'' that represents the nonviolent civil rights movement was selected tonight as the memorial to the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. that will be built on the Washington Mall.</p>
        <p>''It will convey the meaning of Martin's life,'' said Coretta Scott King, Dr. King's widow.</p>
        <p>The winning design was submitted by the ROMA Design Group, an architecture firm in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>A likeness of Dr. King will be cut into a rock facing the nearby Jefferson Memorial.</p>
        <p>Boris Dramov, president of the design firm, said the position of Dr. King's statue would represent the unkept promises that were due to blacks and members of other minorities.</p>
        <p>''It is not intended to be a eulogy,'' Mr. Dramov said. ''It is about life and positive social change.''</p>
        <p>The memorial will be built next to the Tidal Basin between the Jefferson Memorial and the Lincoln Memorial. In keeping with its surroundings, it will be edged with flowering cherry trees.</p>
        <p>Bonnie Fisher, a landscape architect with the design firm, said the cherry trees were appropriate because, each spring, ''they happen to bloom at the moment of Martin Luther King's death.''</p>
        <p>The selection of company was made by Alpha Phi Alpha fraternity, which was established in 1906 and later counted Dr. King among its members. Congress granted authority to the fraternity to select the winning design and to raise money for the memorial.</p>
        <p>Asked how much the monument would cost, Adrian L. Wallace, the president of the fraternity, said, ''We don't have a definitive figure.''</p>
        <p>Among those participating in the announcement today were the clothing designer, Tommy Hilfiger, whose company pledged a contribution of at least $5 million for the construction.</p>
        <p>The selection of the designer is an early step in the process that will lead to the building of the first monument to an African-American on the Mall.</p>
        <p>Approvals are still needed from three federal commissions and the National Park Service.</p>
        <p>The design will include a wall, streams of water, and a path with niches to commemorate others who contributed to the civil rights movement. Among them will be memorials to the four girls killed in 1963 in the bombing of a church in Birmingham, Ala., and to Medgar Evers, the murdered Mississippi civil rights leader.</p>
        <p>Dr. King was assassinated in 1968 in Memphis, and the place where his memorial will be built is not far from the steps of the Lincoln Memorial where he made his famous ''I have a dream'' speech in 1963.</p>
        <p>There were two other developments today regarding monuments on the Mall.</p>
        <p>A proposed monument to former President Ronald Reagan received its first approval when the House Committee of Resources sent it to the full House of Representatives on a voice vote.</p>
        <p>Some Democrats complained about the haste with which the monument was approved; it was acted on without any hearings.</p>
        <p>Harvey B. Gant, chairman of the National Capital Planning Commission, wrote to the House committee to express the commission's concern over the manner in which the monument is progressing.</p>
        <p>A law, which the current measure could pre-empt, Mr. Gant said, calls for waiting for 25 years after the death of a person before a memorial is approved in the capital.</p>
        <p>''This 25-year period provides for enough time to pass following an individual's death for policymakers to gain an appropriate perspective on such individual's impact on the nation,'' Mr. Gant said.</p>
        <p>There are two tributes to Mr. Reagan in Washington. National Airport has been renamed in his honor and the new world trade building near the White House bears his name.</p>
        <p>The other development was a recommendation by the staff of the planning commission that it approve the location and building plans of the World War II Memorial at its proposed site on the Mall.</p>
        <p>That site is just west of 17th Street, with the memorial essentially replacing the Rainbow Pool.</p>
        <p>The Commission of Fine Arts approved the design of the war memorial on July 30, and the planning commission usually follows the lead of the arts commissions on matters of aesthetics.</p>
        <p>The planning commission is scheduled to vote on the memorial next Thursday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
