<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jornada Handheld Gets a Makeover</title>
    <meta content="14GEE1$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/14/technology/14GEE1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEWS WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hewlett-Packard Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Austen, Ian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DA1538F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="400" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jornada Handheld Gets a Makeover</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN AUSTEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Austen, Ian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hewlett Packard revamps its Jornada handheld PC as a tool for people who travel--but not very far--while on the job, like a doctor making hospital rounds; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They're smaller than a laptop -- and a breadbox -- but bigger than a Palm Pilot. Unlike their digital siblings, however, handheld PC's never fulfilled predictions that they were destined to become mass-market gadgets.</p>
        <p>Still, there is enough interest in the in-between-size PC's that Hewlett-Packard has revamped its Jornada handheld. Cherie Britt, a spokeswoman for the company, said that handhelds were mainly used by people who traveled -- but not very far -- while on the job. ''They might only be around the campus or at work,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They're smaller than a laptop -- and a breadbox -- but bigger than a Palm Pilot. Unlike their digital siblings, however, handheld PC's never fulfilled predictions that they were destined to become mass-market gadgets.</p>
        <p>Still, there is enough interest in the in-between-size PC's that Hewlett-Packard has revamped its Jornada handheld. Cherie Britt, a spokeswoman for the company, said that handhelds were mainly used by people who traveled -- but not very far -- while on the job. ''They might only be around the campus or at work,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Typical customers include doctors who carry the devices while making their rounds in large hospitals, Ms. Britt said.</p>
        <p>Handheld PC's also offer a feature missing from most personal digital assistants: a keyboard.</p>
        <p>''That allows people who are on the road to create small documents and not just access them,'' Ms. Britt said.</p>
        <p>But there is a catch. To squeeze everything into a package that is roughly twice the size of a large P.D.A., the Jornada's keyboard is only three-quarters the size of a laptop keyboard. The most obvious, and perhaps least important, difference between the Jornada 720 and early models is color. The new model is dark blue instead of purple.</p>
        <p>The new unit's processor speed has been increased to 206 MHz from 133 MHz. But unlike laptops with more powerful C.P.U.'s, the revised Jornada has improved battery life. Hewlett-Packard says that the 720's lithium-ion cell will run for nine hours on a single charge.</p>
        <p>The new Jornada also has a standard feature not commonly found on PC's of any size: a built-in smart card reader. Among other things, Ms. Britt said, the device will read the cards that many employees need to open doors in their workplace and to prevent unauthorized access to their computers.</p>
        <p>But the Jornada is not all work and no play. Unlike earlier models, the 720 includes a jack and a volume switch for stereo headphones. Ms. Britt said she anticipated that the feature would mostly be used for listening to downloaded music.</p>
        <p>IAN AUSTEN</p>
        <p>NEWS WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
