<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chinese for Young Collectors: High Style, Lower Prices</title>
    <meta content="14CHIN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/14/living/14CHIN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Furniture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Louie, Elaine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Furniture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E0DF1538F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1020" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chinese for Young Collectors: High Style, Lower Prices</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE LOUIE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Louie, Elaine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Antique Chinese furniture has become a focus for younger, less affluent collectors over past 10 years; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SINCE the late 19th century, when Westerners began trading extensively with China, there have been established wealthy collectors seeking Chinese antiques. But in the last 10 years, a group of younger, less affluent collectors has emerged. ''There are two separate markets,'' said James Godfrey, the director for Chinese works of art at Sotheby's auction house in Manhattan. ''There are buyers of classical furniture -- 16th-, 17th- and 18th-century material of huanghuali and zitan,'' two of the most sought-after hardwoods. (In 1996, a 17th-century Chinese huanghuali and marble screen sold for $1.1 million at Christie's.)</p>
        <p>The second market is for furniture made of camphor, elm, ironwood or bamboo, said Theow H. Tow, the international director for Chinese works of art at Christie's. Next week is Asia Week for Sotheby's and Christie's, who will be offering Chinese camphor, elm and bamboo furniture that has brought estimates from $4,000 to $10,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SINCE the late 19th century, when Westerners began trading extensively with China, there have been established wealthy collectors seeking Chinese antiques. But in the last 10 years, a group of younger, less affluent collectors has emerged. ''There are two separate markets,'' said James Godfrey, the director for Chinese works of art at Sotheby's auction house in Manhattan. ''There are buyers of classical furniture -- 16th-, 17th- and 18th-century material of huanghuali and zitan,'' two of the most sought-after hardwoods. (In 1996, a 17th-century Chinese huanghuali and marble screen sold for $1.1 million at Christie's.)</p>
        <p>The second market is for furniture made of camphor, elm, ironwood or bamboo, said Theow H. Tow, the international director for Chinese works of art at Christie's. Next week is Asia Week for Sotheby's and Christie's, who will be offering Chinese camphor, elm and bamboo furniture that has brought estimates from $4,000 to $10,000.</p>
        <p>Ten years ago, said Lark E. Mason Jr., the director for online auctions at Sothebys.com, he saw little Chinese furniture outside of New York, Los Angeles and San Francisco. This year, he said, he saw it being sold in Tulsa, Okla.</p>
        <p>Furniture made of camphor, bamboo and elm, along with simple domestic objects like lacquered water jugs and ceramic planters, are coveted by young collectors. For many, the minimalist, simple lines of Chinese pieces work in a modern interior.</p>
        <p>Frank Didik, a producer of CD-ROM's, who is in his 30's, grew up with parents who revered Asian things, and inherited this passion rather like a gene. This year, Mr. Didik brought home to Brooklyn a 1905 Chinese chair that he bought for $1,200 from Xiaoping Cao, who sells antiques and her interpretations of Chinese furniture in her SoHo shop. ''The simplistic design can blend with modern pieces,'' Mr. Didik said. ''You can't do that with Louis XVI.''</p>
        <p>Still others begin collecting Chinese furniture after going to China. Mary Peng, who sells $50 Chinese wedding baskets and $3,500 Chinese antiques out of her Manhattan loft, said, ''The younger collectors are seasoned travelers in their 20's, coming back to the United States, who want to purchase the furniture they had seen overseas, and who know that antiques don't have to be $10,000 to start.''</p>
        <p>When Tish Durkin, a reporter for The New York Observer, went to Beijing in 1995 to cover the World Conference on Women, she went to an antiques market in search of a souvenir. Instead, she bought a chicken coop/vegetable bin made of camphor wood; it stood 6 feet tall, and was 39 inches wide.</p>
        <p>''I love this thing,'' said Ms. Durkin, who is in her 30's and has studied Chinese language and history. ''It was so solid. I love Chinese language, and there are the characters for spring, summer, winter and fall carved in the four little doors.'' The price was $150. Cheaper than a halogen lamp, she noted.</p>
        <p>For Audrey Wu, a corporate events specialist in her 30's, who works at Fulcrum Information Services in Manhattan, collecting Chinese furniture began spontaneously. She was at an aunt's house in Manhattan, saw a small wood Chinese kitchen cabinet, and said something innocuous like ''Oh, what a cute piece of furniture.'' Her aunt gave it to her. The next year, Ms. Wu went to Shanghai and met Annly Chyn, a furniture dealer, who took her to her warehouse filled with chests, tables, chairs and screens.</p>
        <p>''They were dusty, moldy and fading,'' said Ms. Wu, who saw chests painted with hunters and dragons in a background of golden mist, and promptly bought one for $300.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Didik, Michael Stark, 29, an actor and graphic designer in Manhattan, grew up in a family that loved all things Chinese. His grandfather, Alexander Stark, who lived in Denver, collected Chinese and Japanese art and furniture, and kept it in a private room (no children allowed). Mr. Stark now collects small Chinese wood chests fitted with bronze, while nurturing the desire to buy a Chinese table someday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mason of Sothebys.com has some advice for neophyte collectors. ''Think in terms of what you can use in your own home, because it's tough to be a furniture collector of things you can't use,'' he said. ''Second, think in terms of classic forms.'' As for the lacquered box or bamboo basket, ''it can be fragile if you're considering using a basket for magazines,'' he said. And finally, he said, ''Look for dynamism.''</p>
        <p>Treasures Old and New</p>
        <p>NEXT week, Chinese furniture will be auctioned at Christie's and Sotheby's. There are also shops where baskets and cabinets (many of them restored) can be bought at reasonable prices. When you buy an antique, ''you are not going to find a perfect piece of furniture,'' said Theow H. Tow, the international director for Chinese works of art at Christie's, ''because in every category -- French, English or Chinese -- these things were used and have a part that's been replaced.''</p>
        <p>CHRISTIE'S, 20 Rockefeller Plaza. The Chinese auction will be Thursday, Sept. 21, at 10 a.m. and at 2 p.m. Information: (212) 636-2000.</p>
        <p>SOTHEBY'S, 1334 York Avenue (72nd Street). The Chinese auction will be Wednesday, Sept. 20, starting at 10:15 a.m. Information: (212) 606-7332.</p>
        <p>XIAOPING DESIGN, 73 Hudson Street (Worth Street). Xiaoping Cao sells antiques and her own interpretations of Chinese furniture. A new garden bench starts at $400. Information: (212) 962-4080 or www.xiaopingdesign.com.</p>
        <p>PENG VILLAGE ANTIQUES. Mary Peng sells bamboo baskets ($50) along with cabinets ($3,500). By appointment: (212) 316-7006 or www.pengvillage.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
