<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Undercover Buying, Fake Names and All</title>
    <meta content="14SHOP$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/14/technology/14SHOP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ONLINE SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ecount (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PrivateBuy.com</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Amazon.com Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slatalla, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Online Shopper</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E0DF1538F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1119" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Undercover Buying, Fake Names and All</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michelle Slatalla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slatalla, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Slatalla column on protecting privacy of one's purchasing habits online in light of change in privacy policy at Amazon.com; describes PrivateBuy.com, a new service from Ecount that promises to create an untraceable online identity; cartoon (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE are a lot of things I do on Amazon.com that I don't necessarily want everyone to know about.</p>
        <p>The day I compared prices on home pregnancy tests comes to mind. So does the time that I placed a Bruce Springsteen CD in my shopping cart, then removed it after being teased by my husband (who refers to the aging Mr. Springsteen as ''the Wayne Newton of our generation''). I am embarrassed about the hours I waste checking the sales ranks of books I have written.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE are a lot of things I do on Amazon.com that I don't necessarily want everyone to know about.</p>
        <p>The day I compared prices on home pregnancy tests comes to mind. So does the time that I placed a Bruce Springsteen CD in my shopping cart, then removed it after being teased by my husband (who refers to the aging Mr. Springsteen as ''the Wayne Newton of our generation''). I am embarrassed about the hours I waste checking the sales ranks of books I have written.</p>
        <p>So it hit me hard when Amazon.com recently announced a change in its privacy policy. Under the old policy, the company said it didn't sell, trade or rent its customers' personal information to other companies. Under the new policy? I have no idea how many people are someday going to get hold of my ''click stream data'' and find out that I had once priced ''Jane Fonda's Yoga Exercise Workout'' video. (It was a gag gift, I swear.)</p>
        <p>Suddenly Amazon.com's cheery personal greeting -- ''Hello, M. Slatalla. We have recommendations for you in Books, Music and more'' -- seemed a little sinister. So the next time I shopped at Amazon.com, I decided to slip on a disguise.</p>
        <p>I had a lot of choices. A number of escrow services and online-payment companies have begun to act as go-betweens to limit buyers' exposure to sellers. Last week, for example, American Express announced that within a month, cardholders would be able to use disposable credit-card numbers when shopping online. That is happening because of growing concerns over how online shoppers can preserve their privacy. (I think it's fair to say that all of us who searched for Play-Doh at Disney's Toysmart.com felt a little burned recently when the company threatened to sell its customer list.)</p>
        <p>I wanted to hide everything about myself, so I went to PrivateBuy.com, a new service from an e-commerce payments company called Ecount, in Conshohocken, Pa. PrivateBuy promised to create an untraceable online identity.</p>
        <p>Here's how it works. You give information to PrivateBuy -- your e-mail address, your name and address, a credit card number and expiration date -- and PrivateBuy issues you a secret identity to use when shopping online. Your camouflage includes a name (the worldly yet mysterious Private Buyer), a MasterCard account number and expiration date to use when making purchases, and a billing address (the stately 7156 Private Buy Lane, Privacy, Pa. 00000). Before making a purchase, you must finance your PrivateBuy account with a real credit card payment; PrivateBuy then will authorize payments on your MasterCard up to that amount.</p>
        <p>That all sounded fine, but then something occurred to me: why should I trust PrivateBuy.com any more than Amazon.com? Just because the service had the word ''private'' in its name? Call me paranoid, but what if Ecount someday changed its privacy policy and decided to share information?</p>
        <p>''Well, there's no guarantee,'' said Paul Raden, Ecount's co-founder. ''But our whole product is based on getting people to trust us. Our credibility would diminish.''</p>
        <p>Somewhat mollified, I then took a look at PrivateBuy.com's prices. It costs $3.95 every time you put money into your Privatebuy.com account. Either you put in a specific amount and then spend it gradually -- most customers add $100 at a time, Mr. Raden said -- or you wait until you are on the verge of making a purchase, then add that exact amount. (PrivateBuy.com also charges online merchants a standard MasterCard transaction fee.)</p>
        <p>Sorry, but $3.95 seemed awfully steep for a single purchase. On the other hand, you might as well spend: PrivateBuy.com does not have a mechanism to refund unused balances you have deposited.</p>
        <p>''This is a premium service for someone who might want to make an anonymous gift or a discreet purchase,'' Mr. Raden said, ''and in those instances, people are willing to pay for that.''</p>
        <p>Was I? I feared that I wouldn't be able to answer because when I arrived at Amazon.com, the site greeted me by name as usual after recognizing the cookie it had sent to my computer at an earlier date. So I found the file on my computer where cookies are stored and deleted those that seemed to relate to Amazon.com. When I restarted my browser, Amazon no longer greeted me by name, but after I anonymously put a few items into a shopping cart (don't ask -- it's none of your business) and tried to check out, I was informed  that I would have to use an e-mail address to create a customer account. PrivateBuy.com did not give me an anonymous e-mail address, so I had to set up my own: PrivateBuyer@hotmail.com. It was free, but setting it up took about five minutes.</p>
        <p>When I returned yet again to Amazon.com, I realized that I had overlooked another obvious point: if I entered a fake shipping address, where would Amazon.com send my stuff? To Privacy, Pa. 00000?</p>
        <p>Mr. Raden suggested that I get a post office box to use as an anonymous shipping address, so he clearly has no idea just how lazy a shopper I am.</p>
        <p>I mean, why don't I just buy a factory in Taiwan and make my own merchandise?</p>
        <p>Amazon.com's new policy was suddenly seeming much less ominous. I phoned Amazon.com to find out how likely it was that the company was planning to share my secrets.</p>
        <p>Patty Smith, a spokeswoman for Amazon.com, tried to put things in perspective: ''You are worried people will know you are looking to see if your books are moving up in rank? Like, 'I was ranked 112,000, and now I'm 98,000?' ''</p>
        <p>''I was 24,497,'' I said coldly.</p>
        <p>She then explained that Amazon would share customer information with a third party only under two conditions:</p>
        <p>1. If Amazon.com was sold or acquired.</p>
        <p>2. If a customer bought products from one of the independent merchants who operate stores on the Amazon.com site.</p>
        <p>The bad news? Amazon.com has no control over what those independent merchants, like Drugstore.com (which sells home pregnancy tests), do with the information.</p>
        <p>''It's safe to say that our partners treat customers as carefully as Amazon does,'' Ms. Smith said. ''But if you're going to transact business with one of the partners on our site, read their policy as well.''</p>
        <p>Or maybe I'll just walk down to the real drugstore and plunk down $9.99 in cash for the E.P.T. pregnancy test. (It's a gag gift, Mom.)</p>
        <p>ONLINE SHOPPER E-mail address: Slatalla@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: Slatalla@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
