<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dream Team Seeks a Challenge</title>
    <meta content="14HOOP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mourning, Alonzo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E5DC1238F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1037" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dream Team Seeks a Challenge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>PENRITH, Australia, Sept. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Basketball Notebook article focuses on United States team at Summer Olympics; Alonzo Mourning comments on difficulty of getting motivated to play inferior basketball nations; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alonzo Mourning acknowledged today what his teammates already knew: getting motivated to annihilate inferior basketball nations is hard work.</p>
        <p>''It's really difficult to get yourself up to play against international competition because, first of all, you know you're superior to them,'' Mourning said today as the United States men's basketball team prepared for its opening game of the 2000 Olympics against China on Sunday (Saturday Eastern time).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alonzo Mourning acknowledged today what his teammates already knew: getting motivated to annihilate inferior basketball nations is hard work.</p>
        <p>''It's really difficult to get yourself up to play against international competition because, first of all, you know you're superior to them,'' Mourning said today as the United States men's basketball team prepared for its opening game of the 2000 Olympics against China on Sunday (Saturday Eastern time).</p>
        <p>''It's not like we're competing against the guys we compete against in the league,'' Mourning said. ''It's like Gary Payton says, 'We're getting ready for the Clippers.' ''</p>
        <p>The American men are a lock to capture a third consecutive gold medal. With a 40-0 mark in international play since National Basketball Association players were allowed to compete in 1992, the pressure is not merely to win. They have to win by astronomical scores to keep up with distant Dream Team cousins.</p>
        <p>''Each one of those Dream Teams are different,'' Mourning said. ''International competition has gotten better and better. They've improved from back when Jordan was playing eight years ago. It's improved dramatically.''</p>
        <p>Mourning will miss two games next week to return home to be with his wife, Tracy Wilson-Mourning, who is expected to give birth to a baby daughter, Myka Sydney. He will travel 9,330 miles roundtrip over four days.</p>
        <p>Today's rousing half-court scrimmage in a community center gymnasium about an hour's drive west of Sydney may be the best competition Mourning and his teammates face.</p>
        <p>''While we're here, we've got to get something out of this, even if it's in practice against ourselves,'' he said. ''Execute, work and let our talents take over. We do that, this thing will care of itself. We want to put on a show for the world and let everybody know that USA Basketball is still the best.''</p>
        <p>They did not endear themselves to Australians during an exhibition in Melbourne last Saturday night that featured an altercation between Vince Carter and Andrew Gaze and as much physical play as a Heat-Knicks series. The crowd, ready to embrace the N.B.A. All-Stars before the game began, chanted derisively at Carter in the second half of an 89-64 victory by the United States.</p>
        <p>Several players admitted that playing the dual role of international good sportsman and dominant gold-medal favorite can be a chore. The talking and shoving on Saturday night was more than excessive.</p>
        <p>''You can't go and tell Tim Hardaway not to play the way he's been playing for 25 years,'' Payton said. ''Off the court, we're great people. But on the court, we're trying to get a job done and win. And if it comes across bad, we've got to be that way. As long as we don't do anything to really embarrass our country or team -- like a big altercation or fight -- then it's great.''</p>
        <p>Allan Houston said: ''We're worried about winning. Who we are is who we are. We don't have any knuckleheads on this team that's going to misrepresent the United States anyway. We're not going out there to do anything crazy.''</p>
        <p>Mourning also divulged another badly kept secret. The Americans have no chance of losing, he said.</p>
        <p>''We're not worried about that,'' he said. ''If we played five players the whole game, I couldn't see us losing.  We might not win by a big margin, but I still can't see us losing.''</p>
        <p>Support for Knight</p>
        <p>Nearly 10,000 miles from Bloomington, Ind., one of Bobby Knight's longtime rivals and the point guard on his first national championship team was surprised and disappointed over the Indiana coach's firing.</p>
        <p>''I'm disappointed for basketball because he's a great mind,'' said Quinn Buckner, USA Basketball's vice president, who won a national championship with Knight. ''I'm disappointed for the university because they lose a great coach. I'm obviously disappointed for him because he loses not just a job but also a program that he built. Indiana basketball was Bob Knight basketball.''</p>
        <p>Buckner, who started on the last undefeated team in men's Division I basketball, in 1976, added: ''I still remember when we won the championship. I hadn't seen him happy before that. His hair was mussed; he used to wear those ugly checked suits. But he was finally happy when we won.''</p>
        <p>Gene Keady, an assistant coach with the men's team and a fixture at Purdue for two decades, said he was stunned by the news delivered to him by an assistant coach in his hotel room on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>Even though they were fierce rivals in the Big Ten Conference, Keady, who has been involved with USA Basketball for 21 years, helped Knight select the 1984 Olympic team. He conceded that calling Knight to express his condolences would probably not be a good idea.</p>
        <p>''I've never done much of that because we've always just played each other,'' Keady said. ''I don't think Coach Knight would return a call to me. It'd be wasted money. He's got more important things to worry about. I'll miss mostly the competition and what it took to prepare for his teams.''</p>
        <p>Houston Sprains Wrist</p>
        <p>Allan Houston sat out most of practice after spraining his right wrist as he was driving to the basket against Shareef-Abdur Rahim.</p>
        <p>''It feels like I kind of jammed it,'' Houston said of his shooting hand, which was surgically repaired after the 1996-97 season. ''I don't feel like I did anything serious, but hopefully by tomorrow I can shoot the ball. If I can shoot, I'm all right.''</p>
        <p>Houston said he would put off any decision on X-rays until Thursday.</p>
        <p>''Am I worried? If I can't practice, it's going to worry me a little,'' he said. ''I want to be able to play in practice and in the Games.''</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
