<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Challenge, Iraqi Jet Flew Over Saudi Desert, U.S. Says</title>
    <meta content="Y14IRA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/14/world/14IRAQ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Saudi Arabia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myers, Steven Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hussein, Saddam (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D61538F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Challenge, Iraqi Jet Flew Over Saudi Desert, U.S. Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myers, Steven Lee</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>State Dept says Iraqi fighter jet flew into Saudi Arabian airspace last week in suspected attempt to provoke confrontation with United States on eve of United Nations summit meeting in New York; flight heightens what American officials describe as sense that Pres Saddam Hussein is determined to test American resolve; in United Nations, tensions over Iraq are running high as Baghdad continues to refuse to cooperate with new team of weapons inspectors or with other UN humanitarian efforts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An Iraqi fighter jet flew into Saudi Arabian airspace last week in what officials here suspect was an attempt to provoke a confrontation with the United States on the eve of the United Nations summit meeting in New York, State Department and military officials said today.</p>
        <p>The jet, passing through a ''no flight'' zone over southern Iraq, darted over a thinly populated desert in Saudi Arabia on the morning of Sept. 4 and quickly left, the officials said. Nevertheless, the flight heightened what officials here described as a sense that President Saddam Hussein of Iraq is determined to test American resolve.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An Iraqi fighter jet flew into Saudi Arabian airspace last week in what officials here suspect was an attempt to provoke a confrontation with the United States on the eve of the United Nations summit meeting in New York, State Department and military officials said today.</p>
        <p>The jet, passing through a ''no flight'' zone over southern Iraq, darted over a thinly populated desert in Saudi Arabia on the morning of Sept. 4 and quickly left, the officials said. Nevertheless, the flight heightened what officials here described as a sense that President Saddam Hussein of Iraq is determined to test American resolve.</p>
        <p>American and British jets that patrol the southern ''no flight'' zone, below the 32nd parallel, were not flying that day and were unable to scramble quickly enough to challenge the Iraqi plane before it left, military officials said.</p>
        <p>Iraqi jets have entered the southern zone more than 150 times since the United States and Britain launched four nights of air and missile strikes in December 1998.</p>
        <p>Iraqi jets have also veered into Iranian airspace, but commanders at the Pentagon said it was the first time an Iraqi had flown over Saudi Arabia in at least a decade, the officials said.</p>
        <p>In the days leading up to the incident, the Iraqi Air Force dispersed its aircraft in central Iraq, evidently to protect them from a potential retaliatory attack, the officials said. Those aircraft have since returned to their bases.</p>
        <p>''This does lead people to believe he was trying to provoke a confrontation,'' a senior administration official said, ''and was taking steps to protect himself if that happened.''</p>
        <p>The United States did not respond, fearing that new air strikes could play into President Hussein's strategy of sowing division among the United States and other members of the Security Council. But they warned that American forces remained prepared to counter any threatening military moves.</p>
        <p>''We are obviously very careful not to overplay our hand,'' the senior official said.</p>
        <p>Tensions over Iraq are running high. Baghdad has steadfastly refused to cooperate with a new team of weapons inspectors or with other United Nations humanitarian efforts. Iraq has also sharply criticized Saudi Arabia, Kuwait and Turkey for allowing the United States and Britain to base aircraft in their countries.</p>
        <p>Administration officials have sought to counter Iraq's diplomatic efforts to end the sanctions imposed at the outset of the Persian Gulf war in 1990 by citing Iraqi intransigence and threats as evidence of Mr. Hussein's hostile intentions.</p>
        <p>At the United Nations on Tuesday, Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright blamed Mr. Hussein for shortages of food and medicine, saying, ''He is the one that is victimizing his own people.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright went on to make an oblique reference to the Iraqis ''violating the no-fly zone and the airspace of neighboring countries.'' The officials confirmed today that she was referring to the flight over Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>Saudi officials in Washington did not respond to requests for comment.</p>
        <p>In her remarks on Tuesday, Dr. Albright said the administration had ruled out the use of force to press President Hussein to accept new weapons inspectors. But she reiterated the administration's warnings that the United States was prepared to act if Iraq threatened its neighbors, attacked the Kurdish minority in northern Iraq -- where there is another ''no flight'' zone -- or rebuilt its weapons of mass destruction.</p>
        <p>The United States had placed its forces in the region on a higher state of alert even before the overflight.</p>
        <p>The officials who confirmed the flight declined to discuss the incident in detail. They declined to identify the type of Iraqi aircraft and the exact distance it flew inside Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>The officials said such a flight by a single Iraqi fighter posed little military threat to Saudi Arabia or to American forces stationed at Prince Sultan Air Base, southeast of Riyadh, the capital. In the past, Iraq has flown into the ''no flight'' zones in an effort to lure American jets into areas with surface-to-air missiles.</p>
        <p>''We saw this as an attempt to bait us,'' another senior administration official said. ''We were very careful not to take the bait.''</p>
        <p>Anthony H. Cordesman, a military analyst at the Center for Strategic and International Studies in Washington, said the Iraqi flight followed a pattern and appeared to be intended to challenge not only the United States but also Saudi support for the ''no flight'' zone over the south.</p>
        <p>''To probe resolve is something he does again and again and again -- and in fairly adventurous ways,'' he said of President Hussein.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
