<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Strahan, Without a Sack, Remains Confident</title>
    <meta content="14GIAN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/14/sports/14GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Eagles</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strahan, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Philadelphia Eagles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1DA1238F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Strahan, Without a Sack, Remains Confident</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Sept. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Strahan, New York Giants defensive player whose lack of sacks has become issue, comments on his strong play against Philadelphia Eagles; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michael Strahan wore a big smile and his eyes grew big as he gazed at Giants fans standing above the tunnel at Veterans Stadium last Sunday. He pumped his fist, urging them to cheer louder.</p>
        <p>Today, he conceded a feeling of satisfaction in playing ''a game that people don't expect you to play.'' Not many thought the Giants would manhandle the Eagles, 33-18, or that Strahan would dominate Jon Runyon, the Eagles' mammoth 6-foot-7, 330-pound offensive tackle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Michael Strahan wore a big smile and his eyes grew big as he gazed at Giants fans standing above the tunnel at Veterans Stadium last Sunday. He pumped his fist, urging them to cheer louder.</p>
        <p>Today, he conceded a feeling of satisfaction in playing ''a game that people don't expect you to play.'' Not many thought the Giants would manhandle the Eagles, 33-18, or that Strahan would dominate Jon Runyon, the Eagles' mammoth 6-foot-7, 330-pound offensive tackle.</p>
        <p>''I think people are looking to go, 'Oh, no, he doesn't have 20 sacks,' '' Strahan said after team meetings. ''I guarantee you I'm still the best at what I do. You can look around the league and I don't think there's a team I wouldn't be starting on. And I realize that. For me to look at a guy like Jon Runyon and think Strahan can't play with him, that's almost crazy. I have confidence in what I can do.''</p>
        <p>Sacks, or lack of them recently, are one reason Strahan is a target for critics. Speaking his mind is another.</p>
        <p>Last season, Strahan questioned why Coach Jim Fassel would silence a team leader like Jessie Armstead, who vented his frustration at the Giants' inept offense. Strahan's timing couldn't have been worse. His outburst to reporters came while Fassel was flying to California to bury his mother.</p>
        <p>Strahan apologized when Fassel returned but said today that he had no regrets. He said he had been trying to defend both Armstead and Fassel.</p>
        <p>He said Fassel should not be blamed for not having the offensive weapons to succeed. Strahan suggested the incident strengthened their relationship.</p>
        <p>''My relationship with Jim is great,'' Strahan said. ''The only way it's changed is how I interact with the media.''</p>
        <p>This season, Strahan is rarely visible in the locker room when reporters are present. He spends the time lifting weights. That allows him to avoid questions about his sack total, although he claimed that wasn't his intent. He recorded a career-high 15 sacks in 1998, but that total fell to five and a half last season, including one in the final nine games. This season he has yet to record one.</p>
        <p>Strahan played through several nagging injuries last season but had no answer today for why his sack numbers have decreased so dramatically, other than to say that luck plays a factor.</p>
        <p>After practice today, Strahan allowed reporters to ask three questions by his locker. When one tried to add a fourth, Strahan responded, ''You obviously didn't hear me.''</p>
        <p>Fassel and his defensive coordinator, John Fox, each credited the defensive line with applying more pressure on Eagles quarterback Donovan McNabb than it did against Arizona in the season opener.</p>
        <p>''Mike's been relentless,'' said Fox, who noted Strahan may have been set back by contract negotiations that dragged into training camp last season. ''He worked hard in the off-season.''</p>
        <p>Strahan said he could have had three sacks against the Eagles.</p>
        <p>''When I had 14 and 15, I can take you and show you film where I'm the luckiest man in the world,'' Strahan said. ''I'm nowhere near the play. I probably stopped rushing on the play and the guy runs into me.''</p>
        <p>Strahan's sack total dropped over the past two seasons, coinciding with the departure of defensive end Chad Bratzke to Indianapolis. But Strahan said he was double-teamed when Bratzke was with the Giants.</p>
        <p>''I don't put any pressure on myself to get sacks,'' Strahan said.</p>
        <p>The Giants held Eagles running back Duce Staley, who had run for 201 yards against Dallas, to 11 yards. In two games, Giants opponents have totaled 99 rushing yards. On Sunday, they will face an 0-2 Bears team that was shut out at Tampa Bay last week, 41-0, for the first time since 1989.</p>
        <p>Strahan was not about to call the victory over the Eagles a breakout game for the defense, which has slipped since Fassel's first year in 1997. Strahan recalled last season's opening victory over Tampa Bay, in which the defense scored two touchdowns and forced two turnovers. The Giants followed that with a 50-21 embarrassment of Washington.</p>
        <p>''I'm not jumping to any traps that we're great,'' Strahan said.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, Armstead praised the offense for eating up the clock and keeping the defense fresh in the Giants' dominating 33-18 victory. He cited Kerry Collins, who completed 21 of 29 passes for 220 yards and 2 touchdowns without an interception.</p>
        <p>Strahan echoed Armstead today, saying he appreciated offensive players who congratulate the defense when it comes off the field. The defense, in turn, has full confidence the offense will convert third downs, he said.</p>
        <p>''Right now there's peace between us,'' Strahan said. ''There's no animosity anywhere.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Safety SAM GARNES (concussion) and tight end PETE MITCHELL (knee) returned to full practice and were listed as probable for Sunday.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
