<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campaign Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y14CAM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/14/politics/14CAMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EFDA1238F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campaign Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by B. Drummond Ayres Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS</p>
        <p>BUSH EXPANDS MESSAGE TEAM -- With the presidential contest now a dead heat, Gov. George W. Bush has added a Washington-based Republican consultant, Ed Gillespie, to his communications team to help sharpen his campaign message. Mr. Gillespie, 39, has been senior adviser to the House majority leader, Representative Dick Armey of Texas, director of policy and communications for the House Republican Conference and a senior staff member at the Republican National Committee. He was one of six Washington advisers named by the Bush campaign earlier this year when national Republicans complained that the Austin-based Bush campaign was too insular. His hiring for the new job comes at a time when Vice President Al Gore has caught Mr. Bush in the polls and some Republicans have been urging Mr. Bush to sharpen his campaign themes.</p>
        <p>Alison Mitchell (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS</p>
        <p>BUSH EXPANDS MESSAGE TEAM -- With the presidential contest now a dead heat, Gov. George W. Bush has added a Washington-based Republican consultant, Ed Gillespie, to his communications team to help sharpen his campaign message. Mr. Gillespie, 39, has been senior adviser to the House majority leader, Representative Dick Armey of Texas, director of policy and communications for the House Republican Conference and a senior staff member at the Republican National Committee. He was one of six Washington advisers named by the Bush campaign earlier this year when national Republicans complained that the Austin-based Bush campaign was too insular. His hiring for the new job comes at a time when Vice President Al Gore has caught Mr. Bush in the polls and some Republicans have been urging Mr. Bush to sharpen his campaign themes.</p>
        <p>Alison Mitchell (NYT)</p>
        <p>A REUNION FOR CHENEY AND FORD -- Dick Cheney paid a call yesterday on his old boss, former President Gerald R. Ford, in a campaign swing through Grand Rapids, Mich. Twenty-five years ago, Mr. Cheney, then 34, became Mr. Ford's White House chief of staff. Warmly greeted by Mr. Ford and his wife, Betty, outside the Gerald R. Ford Museum, on the banks of the Grand River, Mr. Cheney said: ''It's fun just to come back and spend some time with the president, get words of wisdom from somebody who has been where I'm trying to go, as vice president.'' And what wisdom did Mr. Cheney get during the 10-minute meeting? ''I've always kept my conversations with him private over the years,'' Mr. Cheney said.</p>
        <p>Michael Cooper (NYT)</p>
        <p>CAMPAIGN FINANCE</p>
        <p>ATTACK ON SOFT MONEY -- Three advocates of stronger campaign finance laws asked a federal court in Washington yesterday to rule that coordination of advertising and other expenditures between a presidential candidate and a political party represents an illegal campaign contribution. The three -- Fred Wertheimer, president of Democracy 21; Scott Harshbarger, president of Common Cause, and Archibald Cox, the former Watergate special prosecutor -- argued that the use of so-called soft money by the Democratic National Committee and Republican National Committee on behalf of Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush constituted a ''massive'' violation of election law. Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore have accepted $68 million in public funds for the general election and are not supposed to receive any other direct contributions. Under federal law, soft money commercials are not supposed to advocate the election or defeat of a specific candidate, and the advertising campaigns are not supposed to be coordinated with candidates.</p>
        <p>John M. Broder (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE STATES</p>
        <p>CLOSE RACE IN FLORIDA -- Two new polls indicate that Vice President Al Gore's support among voters in Florida has surged and that he now is neck and neck with Gov. George W. Bush, who once appeared to have a lock on the state's 25 electoral votes. The first poll, conducted by the Mason-Dixon survey group for several Florida media outlets, found Mr. Bush only two percentage points ahead; the second poll, conducted by the University of Connecticut's polling organization, showed the contest dead even.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>THE ISSUES</p>
        <p>MOBILIZING ON ABORTION RIGHTS -- Abortion rights groups are planning a multimillion-dollar effort to mobilize women to vote for Vice President Al Gore. The campaign is being led by the National Abortion and Reproductive Rights Action League and Planned Parenthood and is being partly financed by the Turner Foundation, established by the media magnate Ted Turner to deal with world population growth and environmental concerns. ''We have identified 2.9 million women in key states and will be contacting at least 2.1 million of them by phone to persuade them how important this election is to preserve reproductive choice,'' Kate Michelman, the league president, said. Anti-abortion forces are using similar tactics to help George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>THE PRIMARIES</p>
        <p>FINAL DEBATE IN WASHINGTON -- The two candidates for the Democratic nomination for senator from Washington clashed yesterday at their final scheduled debate before Tuesday's primary. Speaking before the Rotary Club of Seattle, the state insurance commissioner, Deborah Senn, and former Representative Maria Cantwell traded barbs over their records, Internet privacy issues and Ms. Cantwell's largely self-financed and more lavish campaign spending. Ms. Senn identified protecting prescription drug coverage for older Americans as her top legislative priority, while Ms. Cantwell, a millionaire high-tech executive, singled out campaign finance reform.</p>
        <p>Sam Howe Verhovek (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
