<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Fierce Opening Debate</title>
    <meta content="14THU1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/14/opinion/14THU1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE0DC1238F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="582" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Fierce Opening Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says first debate between Repr Rick Lazio and Hillary Rodham Clinton, candidates for Senate seat from New York, offered unusual combination of substance and personal ferocity; says Lazio showed he can perform smoothly in high-pressure situations and came across as smoother and more aggressive, but risked seeming overbearing or even rude; says Clinton showed she can handle tough questions and aggressive rival without crumbling; says both performances seemed to promise even hotter exchanges ahead (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a debate last night that put a fresh jolt of personal confrontation into the New York Senate race, Representative Rick Lazio and Hillary Rodham Clinton expressed sharp policy differences and engaged in some surprisingly tough talk about each other's trustworthiness. Both were composed and vigorous, but Mr. Lazio came across as a smoother, more aggressive performer. He attacked Mrs. Clinton's health care and education record while defending his charge in a fund-raising letter that the first lady had ''embarrassed our country.'' But Mrs. Clinton did not fold. She countered that Mr. Lazio was waging a campaign of insults, and sought to lash him to the policies of Newt Gingrich.</p>
        <p>Going into the debate, Mr. Lazio was rated by many analysts as having the most to gain. His biggest challenge was to come across as a figure of stature who could plausibly succeed the respected incumbent, Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan. His best line came when he dismissed Mrs. Clinton's comparisons to Mr. Gingrich by turning to her and declaring: ''Mrs. Clinton, you, of all people, shouldn't try to make guilt by association.'' It was an obvious reference to President Clinton's personal conduct. He also scored the evening's theatrical coup when he approached his opponent's lectern and dared her to sign a pledge to swear off soft money. But Mr. Lazio also ran the risk of seeming overbearing, or even rude, and he stumbled a bit when questioned about an independent campaign ad with a doctored picture of Mr. Lazio and Senator Moynihan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a debate last night that put a fresh jolt of personal confrontation into the New York Senate race, Representative Rick Lazio and Hillary Rodham Clinton expressed sharp policy differences and engaged in some surprisingly tough talk about each other's trustworthiness. Both were composed and vigorous, but Mr. Lazio came across as a smoother, more aggressive performer. He attacked Mrs. Clinton's health care and education record while defending his charge in a fund-raising letter that the first lady had ''embarrassed our country.'' But Mrs. Clinton did not fold. She countered that Mr. Lazio was waging a campaign of insults, and sought to lash him to the policies of Newt Gingrich.</p>
        <p>Going into the debate, Mr. Lazio was rated by many analysts as having the most to gain. His biggest challenge was to come across as a figure of stature who could plausibly succeed the respected incumbent, Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan. His best line came when he dismissed Mrs. Clinton's comparisons to Mr. Gingrich by turning to her and declaring: ''Mrs. Clinton, you, of all people, shouldn't try to make guilt by association.'' It was an obvious reference to President Clinton's personal conduct. He also scored the evening's theatrical coup when he approached his opponent's lectern and dared her to sign a pledge to swear off soft money. But Mr. Lazio also ran the risk of seeming overbearing, or even rude, and he stumbled a bit when questioned about an independent campaign ad with a doctored picture of Mr. Lazio and Senator Moynihan.</p>
        <p>For Mrs. Clinton the most awkward moment  came when Tim Russert, the NBC moderator, showed a film clip of the first lady asserting that her husband's denial of an improper sexual relationship would eventually be proven correct. She was obviously uncomfortable in discussing a subject that, whether she likes it or not, has to be on the minds of voters in New York. Asked to apologize for misleading the country, her response was that ''obviously I didn't mislead anyone -- I didn't know the truth.'' She notably distanced herself from her husband's mendacity by saying that he ''did mislead the country as well as his family.''</p>
        <p>Although it was a moment when she did not display her usual self-confidence, Mrs. Clinton did show that she could handle tough questions and an aggressive rival without crumbling. Mr. Lazio, for his part, showed that he could perform smoothly in high-pressure situations.</p>
        <p>Much of the debate, which took place in Buffalo, focused on the difficulties of the upstate economy. On this subject, Mrs. Clinton probably gave a more convincing answer when she declared that drastic solutions were needed. Mr. Lazio's assertion that upstate New York had turned the corner, and his suggestion that the first lady stop denigrating the region, may come back to haunt him among voters eager for solutions to the loss of jobs in that part of the state.</p>
        <p>Otherwise, the general themes of the debate reflected much of what the two candidates have been saying on the campaign trail. The first lady repeated her claim to be in better tune with New Yorkers on school aid, health care, the environment and taxes. Mr. Lazio seldom missed a chance to categorize himself as a real New Yorker, and he seized the initiative in depicting himself as a champion of campaign finance reform.</p>
        <p>It was, on balance, a debate that offered an unusual combination of substance and personal ferocity. Both performances seemed to promise even hotter exchanges ahead.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
