<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Discovering Dinosaurs on 2 CD-ROM's</title>
    <meta content="14REVU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/14/technology/14REVU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230325"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cd-Rom (Compact Disc-Read Only Memory)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Korling Kindersley</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Field Museum (Chicago)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Memory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">CD-ROM (Compact Disk-Read Only Memory)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFD71438F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Discovering Dinosaurs on 2 CD-ROM's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALICE KEIM</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alice Keim reviews I See Sue...The T. Rex, a CD-ROM game based on Tyrannosaurs rex at Field Museum of Chicago, and Dinosaur Hunter Deluxe, a program from Korling Kindersley; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I See Sue . . . The T. Rex  (Simon &amp; Schuster Interactive; for Windows 95 and 98, and Macintosh Power PC; $19.95; ages 4 to 7.)</p>
        <p>Dinosaur Hunter Deluxe  (Dorling Kindersley; for Windows 95, 98 and 2000; $19.95; ages 7 and up.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I See Sue . . . The T. Rex  (Simon &amp; Schuster Interactive; for Windows 95 and 98, and Macintosh Power PC; $19.95; ages 4 to 7.)</p>
        <p>Dinosaur Hunter Deluxe  (Dorling Kindersley; for Windows 95, 98 and 2000; $19.95; ages 7 and up.)</p>
        <p>LONG before Barney sank his purple talons into preschoolers, dinosaurs fascinated children. Fortunately for parents, the study of dinosaurs can develop important scientific inquiry skills in young students, and the academic appeal lasts long after children learn to distinguish Hollywood fiction from fact.</p>
        <p>I had high expectations for I See Sue, a CD-ROM game developed with the Field Museum of Chicago and based on Sue, the largest and most complete Tyrannosaurus rex ever discovered. Sue was found in South Dakota 10 years ago and went on display in May.</p>
        <p>The Field Museum's Web site (www.thefieldmuseum.com) provided more extensive educational information about Sue and her environment than the CD-ROM itself.</p>
        <p>The disk starts with a catchy jingle and flashes some dinosaur images as a song explains the game. The program then shows a main menu screen with four levels of difficulty, sound options and a choice of playing  against the computer or a friend.</p>
        <p>Square color-coded game tiles appear in the bottom third of the screen, each featuring the head, tail or body of a specific dinosaur. The object of the game is to match the parts to complete a dinosaur.</p>
        <p>After you match three tiles, a completed dinosaur moves along a trail. There are shortcuts for some species. If they have wings, they can fly over part of the trail, and if they are light and graceful, they can take a log bridge. The first player to complete the trail is rewarded with a picture of Sue and a dinosaur drawing to print out and color. Facts on each dinosaur are presented in clever rhyming sentences that, if re-enforced throughout the program, could have helped players retain information.</p>
        <p>Sadly, the game is buried in its limitations. Names and facts are in audio only, and young users will have trouble remembering them. There is a help screen, but it offers only pictures of each dinosaur and details like ''crosses log bridges.''</p>
        <p>For a game based on one of the most exciting modern dinosaur discoveries, I See Sue is anticlimatic. After finishing the trail, the player sees a bit of Sue accompanied by some uninspiring animation. The real Sue deserves better.</p>
        <p>By comparison, DK's Dinosaur Hunter Deluxe is buried treasure. The program has two main sections: a virtual museum and 3-D environments representing the environments in which the dinosaurs lived. The environments are interesting, but the museum, an interactive environment with exhibits and activities that bring more than 50 species of dinosaurs to life, is a gem.</p>
        <p>The virtual visitor can wander the dark museum halls and follow a time line through the Jurassic, Triassic and Cretaceous Periods. Along the way they can learn about specific dinosaurs and their characteristics through videos, displays and puzzles. The central exhibit hall, the Arena, provides extensive information about dinosaur anatomy and behavior. The second main exhibit area focuses on discoveries, including information on where and how dinosaur fossils were found and details about great discoverers.</p>
        <p>The program has brilliant explanations of the dinosaur's characteristics and habits. For example, many explanations combine animation with videos of modern animals. A section on how ancient herbivores chewed uses clips of camels to demonstrate a circular grinding motion and reptiles using an up and down movement, then uses animation to show a dinosaur jaw in motion, which looks like a combination of the above.</p>
        <p>Visitors can also go to the Dinosaur Excavation Site, a room that features the Excavator, a virtual machine that allows the user to uncover dinosaur bones. The visitor excavates several layers and uses tools to find the bones.</p>
        <p>Bones can be identified by relative age, body part and shape. The dig is not difficult, but it requires patience. Once all the bones are recovered, the dinosaur comes to life and roams the museum corridors. The program features wonderful graphics and explanatory animations. Young dinosaur fans will delight in their prehistoric encounters here.</p>
        <p>Before leaving the museum, visitors visit the Museum Store. While the very name may have parents clutching their wallets, the area offers free program accessories. Shoppers can download images and sounds to their hard drives or print out masks, stationary and postcards. I enjoyed the jukebox, where you could hear the sounds of 12 dinosaurs. The museum products are an excellent way to extend the activities beyond the program.</p>
        <p>Dinosaur Hunter Deluxe is full of information and educational activities, but navigating the program was frustrating. For example, I found myself going in circles as I searched for the excavation area. There is a Help section that explains each area of the museum, but that did not get me where I wanted to go. The halls feel like the corridors of a true natural history museum but, sadly, without the guards to guide you.</p>
        <p>REVIEW Alice Keim, a teacher, is the technology coordinator for the Horace Mann Lower School in the Bronx.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Alice Keim, a teacher, is the technology coordinator for the Horace Mann Lower School in the Bronx.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
