<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It Seems the MetroStars Peaked a Month Too Soon</title>
    <meta content="14MLSS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/14/sports/14MLSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230403"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metrostars</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zambrano, Octavio</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E0D61538F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It Seems the MetroStars Peaked a Month Too Soon</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Slumping MetroStars are out of sync, especially on defense, going into Major League Soccer playoffs; coach Octavio Zambrano comments; playoffs diagram; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The MetroStars were the best team in Major League Soccer last month. And they had aspirations of capturing a soccer triple: finishing first in the regular season, winning the league championship and taking the United States Open Cup.</p>
        <p>But the MetroStars finished third in the regular season by losing two of their last three games, and were eliminated from the United States Open Cup on Tuesday night by Miami by 3-2; Miami did not make the M.L.S. playoffs. The MetroStars are out of sync, especially on defense, going into the playoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The MetroStars were the best team in Major League Soccer last month. And they had aspirations of capturing a soccer triple: finishing first in the regular season, winning the league championship and taking the United States Open Cup.</p>
        <p>But the MetroStars finished third in the regular season by losing two of their last three games, and were eliminated from the United States Open Cup on Tuesday night by Miami by 3-2; Miami did not make the M.L.S. playoffs. The MetroStars are out of sync, especially on defense, going into the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Eight of the league's 12 teams make the playoffs, which start tonight with Los Angeles visiting Tampa Bay. They will continue tomorrow night with Dallas visiting the MetroStars at 8 p.m. and New England at Chicago. Colorado's visit to Kansas City on Saturday will conclude the opening games of the first round.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars will play their second game in Dallas on Wednesday night. If a third game is necessary, it will be played on Saturday, Sept. 23, at 3:30 p.m. at Giants Stadium.</p>
        <p>With the MetroStars floundering since losing goalkeeper Mike Ammann to a season-ending injury six games ago and the backup Tim Howard to the United States Olympic team, Chicago and Kansas City are emerging as the favorites to reach the M.L.S. Cup on Oct. 15 in Washington.</p>
        <p>''We're not the same team we were last month, and I'm very concerned,'' MetroStars Coach Octavio Zambrano said Tuesday night after his team was eliminated from the United States Open Cup. ''I am not happy with anyone's play.''</p>
        <p>Zambrano is more concerned about his defense than anything else. He may use four defenders in the first game against Dallas instead of the three he has used almost all season.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars have allowed 16 goals in the last five games and will face a severe test against Dallas's Ariel Graziani and Jason Kreis, who have accounted for 26 of Dallas's 54 goals.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars beat Dallas in both regular-season encounters, one each with Ammann and Howard in goal, but this time the MetroStars will have Paul Grafer, who has no M.L.S. experience, playing in goal.</p>
        <p>To add to the MetroStars' woes, Clint Mathis is in a slump. He has missed many full chances, including a penalty kick against New England in the regular-season finale. But Zambrano said Mathis would start against Dallas.</p>
        <p>For the MetroStars to get past the first round, their key players like Lothar Matthaus, Tab Ramos, Adolfo Valencia, Roy Myers and Mathis must excel. They have not played well in recent games, and it will be difficult to turn it on now.</p>
        <p>LOS ANGELES AT TAMPA BAY -- Tampa Bay has been shut out in its last three playoff games, spanning a total of 324 minutes, but this time the Mutiny has the league's leading goal scorer in Mamadou Diallo with 26 goals. The teams split their two games during the regular season, but Los Angeles will be missing several players because of injury and the Olympics, including Dan Califf, perhaps the only man capable of marking Diallo.</p>
        <p>NEW ENGLAND AT CHICAGO -- The New England Revolution is the only team not to lose to Chicago in the regular season, winning one and tying one. But the Fire has a way of raising its game in the playoffs and it will have Hristo Stoichkov for the series. Stellar play by the experienced Stoichkov and Peter Nowak makes the Fire a favorite, especially if Carlos Bocanegra and Diego Gutierrez overcome their injuries.</p>
        <p>COLORADO AT KANSAS CITY -- If defense wins championships, then Kansas City has the defense to go to the title game. Tony Meola is the league's best goalkeeper with 17 shutouts and 37 for his career. With Coach Bob Gansler in his first full season with the Wizards, the team went to the top of the league after finishing next to last a year ago. Gansler has the Wizards adjusting to every kind of strategy by the opposition.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
