<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y14BRI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/14/world/14BRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230387"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E3D71538F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1039" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: KURSK WILL BE RAISED -- Russia is not reconsidering its decision to raise the submarine Kursk from the Barents Sea, Deputy Prime Minister Ilya Klebanov said. He added that he was surprised by remarks by the minister for atomic energy, Yevgeny Adamov, who suggested that it might be safer to leave the Kursk and its twin-reactor power plant on the seabed indefinitely. Mr. Klebanov, who heads the commission looking into the disaster, said the sub would be raised after the dead are recovered this fall.</p>
        <p>Patrick E. Tyler (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: KURSK WILL BE RAISED -- Russia is not reconsidering its decision to raise the submarine Kursk from the Barents Sea, Deputy Prime Minister Ilya Klebanov said. He added that he was surprised by remarks by the minister for atomic energy, Yevgeny Adamov, who suggested that it might be safer to leave the Kursk and its twin-reactor power plant on the seabed indefinitely. Mr. Klebanov, who heads the commission looking into the disaster, said the sub would be raised after the dead are recovered this fall.</p>
        <p>Patrick E. Tyler (NYT)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: TREATY SIGNED -- Russia became the 112th country to sign the treaty setting up an international criminal court to try those accused of war crimes, genocide and crimes against humanity. Nineteen countries have also ratified the treaty, of the 60 ratifications needed for the court to begin functioning. The United States has not signed, and is demanding an exemption for American soldiers and officials.</p>
        <p>Barbara Crossette (NYT)</p>
        <p>TURKEY: EX-PREMIER'S JAILING DELAYED -- Prosecutors agreed to a four-month delay in jailing former Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan for remarks he made in 1994. A warrant was issued for Mr. Erbakan, 73, after he failed to show up to start serving a one-year sentence for telling a political rally Turkey had abandoned its Islamic roots and politicians had divided Kurds from other Turks. Mr. Erbakan's lawyers said his jailing would prevent him from defending two other cases.</p>
        <p>Douglas Frantz (NYT)</p>
        <p>NORTHERN IRELAND: REBEL ACTION -- A mortar fired from a van on a hotel building site damaged a Royal Ulster Constabulary station in Armagh, and two bombs were deactivated before they could go off at a British Army training center near Londonderry. No one was hurt in the incidents, which were attributed to the dissident group the Real I.R.A.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>BELGIUM: UNION SLAYINGS -- At least 140 union activists were killed last year, mostly in Latin America and Asia, and organizing efforts were not adequately protected in industrialized economies, the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions said in its annual survey. Rights of union organizers were violated around the world, the Brussels-based group said, ranging from union busting to ''ruthless repression.''</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Olson (NYT)</p>
        <p>BOSNIA: CROAT SURRENDERS -- A Bosnian Croat charged with war crimes against Muslims in Mostar in 1993 turned himself in to a regional court, officials said. The United Nations mission in Bosnia welcomed the surrender of Zoran Soldo, the second member a five-man gang that terrorized Mostar to give himself up. It also called on the police to arrest the three others.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CANADA: JOURNALIST SHOT -- A columnist for Quebec's largest selling paper, Journal de Montreal, was shot in what a police spokesman called an assassination attempt. Michel Auger, 56, an expert on organized crime, was in stable condition. Paule Beaugrand-Champagne, the newspaper's editor in chief, noted that the attack came a day after a column by Mr. Auger detailed a drug turf war between Quebec's biker gangs and Mafia groups.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>SOUTH AFRICA: WAR ON VIGILANTES -- Law enforcement officials said South Africa is at war with the vigilante group suspected of orchestrating a string of bombings in and around Cape Town for two years. The statement came hours after a bomb exploded near a community center where the provincial premier was about to speak. Several people were hurt.</p>
        <p>Henri E. Cauvin (NYT)</p>
        <p>BURUNDI: TUTSI TO SIGN PACT -- The last three holdout Tutsi parties have agreed to sign an accord aimed at ending the country's civil war, Nelson Mandela, the mediator in the civil war, said after meeting with the leaders of the three groups at his home in Johannesburg. All 19 parties to the accord have now signed it, but two Hutu rebel groups continue to oppose the agreement.</p>
        <p>Henri E. Cauvin (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>JAPAN: CLINTON ORDERS SANCTIONS -- President Clinton ordered the first sanctions against Japan for expanding its hunting of whales, ordering that Japanese fishermen will be prohibited from fishing in United States waters if they are opened to foreign fleets this year. He acted after the Commerce Department ruled that Japan is undermining efforts to protect whales, saying he would consider more sanctions in the next 60 days.</p>
        <p>David E. Sanger (NYT)</p>
        <p>INDIA: SURGERY FOR PRIME MINISTER -- Prime Minister Atal Behari Vajpayee will have surgery on his left knee after he returns from his two-week visit to the United States, a government spokesman said. Mr. Vajpayee's health has been the cause of great speculation recently but the prime minister, who is 73, has insisted that his ailments begin and end with a bad knee.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: CHANGING DESIRES -- Under the headline ''The Jewish Mother No Longer Wants Her Son to Be a Doctor,'' the Yediot Ahronot published results of a poll of Israeli mothers. It showed that 40 percent want their children to go into the high-tech industry, 15 percent want them to become doctors, and only 2 percent want them to be rabbis.</p>
        <p>Deborah Sontag (NYT)</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: SLOW JUSTICE -- The Israeli-Arab family that won a landmark Supreme Court case this year, earning the right to settle in the Jewish community of Katzir, has still not been able to move into the town. The Association for Civil Rights in Israel petitioned the state attorney to comply with the court's decision and allocate land to the family.</p>
        <p>Deborah Sontag (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
