<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Jukebox Comes Home</title>
    <meta content="14STAT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/14/technology/14STAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230348"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="STATE OF THE ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recording Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jukeboxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Escient (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Creative (Singapore Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ReQuest Multimedia</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marriott, Michel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/State of the Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recording Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5DC1538F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1445" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Jukebox Comes Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michel Marriott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marriott, Michel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michel Marriott article rates several digital 'jukeboxes' now on the market that are designed to store and play large collections of music in MP3 and other digital formats; they include machines from ReQuest Multimedia, Creative and Escient; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MENTION the word jukebox and most of us imagine some garish, pot-bellied machine that spins a few records (or compact discs) for a handful of coins.</p>
        <p>No more. The new jukeboxes, born of a fledgling marriage of traditional audio and newfangled computer technology, are intended for home use and play music in MP3 and other digital formats. They come in different sizes, shapes and prices (none cheap), but all are designed to store or sort large collections of music for easier playback. They are intended to appeal to music lovers with crates full of CD's or hard drives overloaded with music files.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MENTION the word jukebox and most of us imagine some garish, pot-bellied machine that spins a few records (or compact discs) for a handful of coins.</p>
        <p>No more. The new jukeboxes, born of a fledgling marriage of traditional audio and newfangled computer technology, are intended for home use and play music in MP3 and other digital formats. They come in different sizes, shapes and prices (none cheap), but all are designed to store or sort large collections of music for easier playback. They are intended to appeal to music lovers with crates full of CD's or hard drives overloaded with music files.</p>
        <p>Nobody really needs any of these players (except perhaps some traveling, tech-forward D.J.). That has apparently not stopped their makers from introducing more and more of these hybrid players in recent months. Of all the models I have seen and tried, at least one of them could be hard to resist, if you have the cash.</p>
        <p>The AudioReQuest ARQ1 Digital Music System by ReQuest Multimedia, at $800, provides a place to store and play an entire music collection. The device is crammed with PC technology, including a 17.3-gigabyte hard drive, and is about the size of a large multidisc CD player. It is designed primarily to copy songs from CD's (it can also copy from cassette tapes and vinyl records), translate their tunes into MP3 files, store them and play them. It can also play individual CD's.</p>
        <p>The AudioReQuest, which was introduced this year, can hold up to 320 hours of music if the songs are recorded at the near-CD-quality bit rate of 128 kilobits per second. The device is capable of much higher-quality recordings, but at the expense of holding fewer songs.</p>
        <p>No matter what rate is chosen, translating CD's into MP3 files is a bit of a chore. Recording a 55-minute CD at 128 kbps, which is recommended, took 19 minutes.</p>
        <p>Using a standard computer keyboard, which is not included, and plugging the system into a conventional television set for a monitor, I was able to create playlists of my favorite songs. The AudioReQuest also permits users to locate music quickly on its hard drive by song, album and artist via the device's wireless remote control. The remote is more than a handful, mostly because it has too many buttons, including a keyboard that is close to useless -- the tiny keys are laid out in alphabetical order, not QWERTY style, forcing you to hunt and peck.</p>
        <p>The device comes with cables to make it simple to connect the unit to a PC, a PC monitor or TV. To take full advantage of the AudioReQuest's best features, you need to link it to a home stereo system, an Internet-linked PC and a television set -- but its cables are too short to connect everything at once.</p>
        <p>Once the music is placed on the AudioRequest hard drive -- MP3 files stored on a personal computer can also be imported into the device -- the playback of the music files is remarkably good. This machine is expensive and may be a harbinger of the future of home audio, but it is easy enough to resist buying right now.</p>
        <p>The only device I tested that is truly tempting was made by Creative, a Singapore-based technology company that was an early innovator in PC sound. Its Nomad Jukebox, introduced this month, is a portable music player about the size of a portable CD player, but it is heavier and holds the equivalent of 150 CD's of music.</p>
        <p>The Nomad Jukebox has a modest-size L.C.D. screen, a smattering of buttons on its contoured face and a headphone jack on its right side. But the device's resemblance to a CD player stops there. The Nomad Jukebox doesn't play CD's. What it does, once linked to a PC or Mac by way of a U.S.B. cable, is store more than 100 hours of MP3 music files on its six-gigabyte, shock-resistant hard drive.</p>
        <p>The Nomad Jukebox will also store up to 2,600 hours of spoken-word files and will store and read multiple sound file formats, including WMA and WAV.</p>
        <p>The Creative PlayCenter 2 software for the Nomad was easy to install on a standard PC, but not always the easiest to use. I ran into a few glitches in setting up the encoding, often called ripping, of scores of CD's I eventually loaded into the Nomad Jukebox. Once I got under way, each CD took about 10 minutes to be turned into MP3 files and moved into the jukebox.</p>
        <p>Once the music was in the Nomad Jukebox, its sound, heard on a set of included headphones, was very good. There are spatial effects that can make, for example, the Red Hot Chili Peppers sound as if they were performing in an empty recital hall. And the jukebox reverberation, bass and treble controls were good. Best of all was the easy access to all the music, which can be called up by playlist name, artist, album or style.</p>
        <p>The player also lets you search for a song by typing in a few letters of the title. But the typing is more like pecking, using a couple of tiny buttons. Another downside is that for a device that is supposed to be so mobile, its battery life is extremely limited. I never got more than four hours of continuous play from four rechargeable nickel-hydride batteries.</p>
        <p>At $500, the Nomad Jukebox may seem expensive, but compared with equally costly MP3 players, all of which have only a fraction of the storage capacity, it seems like a bargain.</p>
        <p>That could not be said for the Escient TuneBase 100. It is a $3,000, 15-pound set-top box, 3 1/2 inches tall and 17 inches wide. The TuneBase plugs into an Internet connection, a CD changer holding 100 or more CD's and a television, or an optional $2,000 L.C.D. touch-screen controller.</p>
        <p>In other words, to use this device, you can already have a CD changer with at least 100 slots (more expensive models come with much larger CD changers). Then you presumably  have a lot more on your mind other than remembering whether ''James Brown Live at the Apollo'' is in Slot 191, or that Joni Mitchell's ''Misses'' is the 20th CD out of 300 ready to play.</p>
        <p>So since you are obviously the sort of person who spends a lot on music, you might buy the TuneBase, too. Here's what it will do for you:</p>
        <p>It will list every CD loaded into a changer. Drawing upon PC technology, the TuneBase locates a unique identification code for each CD and automatically goes online to the Compact Disc Database, which contains all the information a CD would ordinarily display on its cover, like the name of the artist, the song titles, album cover art and liner notes. That information is then downloaded into the TuneBase's hard drive and shown on any display screen connected to the system.</p>
        <p>All of that is done at PC speed and usually works without a hitch. Sometimes the database doesn't have any information on an obscure CD. But the result is usually a real-time listing, by name of artist, genre or song, of every CD loaded into the system. Then you can create a playlist and hear the songs you like in the order you like.</p>
        <p>With additional CD changers, either very large and expensive ones or daisy-chained multiple changers, the TuneBase can handle more than 4,500 CD's.</p>
        <p>A similar $7,500 system by Escient called PowerPlay works with DVD movies as well as CD's. The number of people who have enough DVD's to warrant a $7,500 sorter is probably even smaller than the number of people who want a $3,000 CD sorter, but technology marches on.</p>
        <p>The most time-consuming part of the process is the time it takes to load your CD collection into the changer and to wait for the TuneBase to read, retrieve and remember all the music data it requires to operate. But if you give it a weekend, the TuneBase can slice and dice your music collection into favorite playlists or call it up at the touch of a remote-control button, displaying and playing any piece of music you have in the system.</p>
        <p>Note that the TuneBase does not actually play the CD's. It has neither speakers nor amplifiers. Your music system has to be all set up and ready to go. What it does, for $3,000, is store, identify and organize the tunes.</p>
        <p>STATE OF THE ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
