<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INVESTING WITH: Oscar A. Castro; Montgomery Global Communications Fund</title>
    <meta content="18INVO$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208388"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Montgomery Asset Management</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Legomsky, Joanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Castro, Oscar a</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Investing With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E0DF1631F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INVESTING WITH: Oscar A. Castro; Montgomery Global Communications Fund</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE LEGOMSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Legomsky, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oscar A Castro, manager of Montgomery Global Communications Fund, oversees team of 18 analysts and managers; Castro and his team favor stocks with lower multiples than their peer group, but he is willing to pay more for a company that is growing faster than its peers, so he also looks at stock's peg rate, or its price-to-earning ratio, divided by long-term earnings growth rate; Global Communications fund has returned 47.2 percent a year, on average, for three years ended June 9, while peers have returned 43.3 percent; photo, chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU need to learn the game well to play it well,'' said Oscar A. Castro, manager of the $590 million Montgomery Global Communications fund, over breakfast at the Mark Hotel in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>In the ever-changing global telecommunications markets, learning the game well means gaining a thorough understanding of industry dynamics, he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU need to learn the game well to play it well,'' said Oscar A. Castro, manager of the $590 million Montgomery Global Communications fund, over breakfast at the Mark Hotel in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>In the ever-changing global telecommunications markets, learning the game well means gaining a thorough understanding of industry dynamics, he said.</p>
        <p>At Montgomery Asset Management in San Francisco, where Mr. Castro has worked since 1993, that is the task for the Global Research Platform, an 18-member team of analysts and managers that Mr. Castro oversees. The unit is the source of investment ideas for Global Communications and two smaller funds that Mr. Castro helps run.</p>
        <p>Global Communications has returned 47.2 percent a year, on average, for the three years through June 9, versus 43.3 percent for its peers, according to Morningstar Inc.</p>
        <p>Mr. Castro, 45, attributes his fund's performance, at least in part, to its research process. While many analysts and money managers focus on information gleaned from corporate management, the Montgomery analysts pay special attention to company rivals, suppliers and industry regulators.</p>
        <p>After a visit with telecommunications regulators in Italy two years ago, for instance, Mr. Castro and Montgomery analysts concluded that the details of the country's impending deregulation plan would favor the large incumbent operators. So Mr. Castro added to his holdings of Telecom Italia, which has risen.</p>
        <p>In general, Mr. Castro and his team favor stocks with lower multiples than their peer group, based on their prices compared with both past and expected future earnings or cash flow.</p>
        <p>But he is willing to pay more for a company that is growing faster than its peers. So he looks at the company's peg ratio -- defined as its price-to-earnings ratio, in turn divided by its long-term earnings growth rate. The lower the peg, the better.</p>
        <p>Using Montgomery analysts' forecasts, Mr. Castro wants a stock to have an expected return of 25 percent in the first year he owns it, 50 percent in two years and 100 percent in three years.</p>
        <p>Other measures are more esoteric. For example, he looks at a company's enterprise value -- the market value of its equity and debt, less its cash -- in relation to future cash flow.</p>
        <p>Geography plays only a minor role selecting the portfolio's 90 or so stocks. At the end of April, 42.1 percent of its assets were in Europe, 34.9 percent in the United States, 14.9  percent in Asia and the small remainder elsewhere or in cash.</p>
        <p>The fund, with an annual turnover rate of 146 percent, uses a fairly strict discipline for selling stocks. Mr. Castro is likely to unload a stock that breaches its upside price target, or if he foresees deteriorating sales. He will also drop a stock if he believes management has steered him wrong, or sometimes if executives take too long to return his phone calls -- a sign of possible trouble.</p>
        <p>The spring sell-off has provided some opportunities, and Mr. Castro has been buying of late. ''It gives us a chance to get into stocks we've always wanted to own but that were too expensive,'' he said.</p>
        <p>MR. CASTRO is bullish on the Atmel Corporation, a San Jose, Calif., maker of high-performance memory chips. He said the company was benefiting from strong demand for its flash memory chips, used in personal digital assistants and other wireless devices, and that it was gradually becoming a global player.</p>
        <p>The fund started buying Atmel shares in May, 1999 when they were trading for less than $10. They now trade at $42.9375, down 27.8 percent from their peak on March 22 and 28.1 times his 2001 earnings estimate of $1.53 a share. His 12-month price target is $70, and he calculated the company's peg ratio at 0.37 recently, versus 0.75 for peer companies like LSI Logic.</p>
        <p>One recent purchase was Bookham Technology of Oxfordshire, England, which makes components that generate and control light signals in fiber optic networks. He bought shares at $:10 at the initial offering on April 11.</p>
        <p>Mr. Castro recently raised his 12-month price target on Bookham to $:65, from $:50, because of stronger-than-anticipated revenue growth. At his new target, the company would trade at a 50 percent premium to the shares of peer companies like JDS Uniphase, based on its price-to-sales multiple. But Bookham has ''much higher growth prospects at this stage,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The stock closed on Friday at $:35. He expects Bookham to turn a profit of 4 pence a share in 2001 versus a loss this year.</p>
        <p>He also likes Cable and Wireless Optus in Australia. The company provides a wide range of telecommunications services, including long-distance and mobile telephone, pay television and Internet connections. ''They've assembled a huge broadband network that can soon deliver all of these services,'' Mr. Castro said. He expects earnings to nearly double, to 16 Australian cents a share for the year ending in March 2001.</p>
        <p>He bought the shares at an average price of 4.46 Australian dollars, starting in April 1999; they now trade at 4.26 dollars. He calculates that the company's enterprise value as a multiple of 2001 cash flow is 18, and has a 12-month price target on the stock of 8.60 dollars.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
