<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Musical Voyage To Lost Worlds</title>
    <meta content="18KALI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION/RADIO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kalish, Jon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shulberg, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Conte, Pat</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E3DD123EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1291" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Musical Voyage To Lost Worlds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON KALISH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kalish, Jon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jon Kalish article on Secret Museum of the Air, world music radio show taped by audiophile Pat Conte and mixed by partner Richard Shulberg; weekly program is broadcast over cultish WFMU/91.1 in Jersey City and is streamed over Web; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AND now to western Formosa and a song for the gathering of tea,'' intones a calm, sonorous voice during a typically arcane, hourlong installment of ''The Secret Museum of the Air,'' which may just be the most singular world music show on radio.</p>
        <p>The ensuing a cappella duet in a plaintive minor key was recorded before World War II by an anonymous ethnic music collector for Nippon Columbia, the Japanese division of Columbia Records. And it's part of ''Herds and Pastures,'' a program of work songs and animal calls in which listeners heard a Peruvian Indian song recorded by an Yma Sumac sound-alike, a choral ode to the Sumatran rice goddess, a tune featuring the Serbian bagpipe and what the mellow-sounding host considers ''some of the most emotional yodeling on record.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AND now to western Formosa and a song for the gathering of tea,'' intones a calm, sonorous voice during a typically arcane, hourlong installment of ''The Secret Museum of the Air,'' which may just be the most singular world music show on radio.</p>
        <p>The ensuing a cappella duet in a plaintive minor key was recorded before World War II by an anonymous ethnic music collector for Nippon Columbia, the Japanese division of Columbia Records. And it's part of ''Herds and Pastures,'' a program of work songs and animal calls in which listeners heard a Peruvian Indian song recorded by an Yma Sumac sound-alike, a choral ode to the Sumatran rice goddess, a tune featuring the Serbian bagpipe and what the mellow-sounding host considers ''some of the most emotional yodeling on record.''</p>
        <p>The idiosyncratic voice -- and global taste -- belong to Pat Conte, audiophile, guitarist, postal worker and once-a-week radio host; and the vintage discs from which his shows are culled belong to what he calls ''The Secret Museum of Mankind,'' after a book of ethnographic photographs published in the 30's. The museum, which fills the basement of his mother's Long Island ranch house, includes dinosaur bones, tribal masks, a pipe collection, antique microphones and stereo gear from the 1950's and 60's. But at its heart is the music of a lost time, when adventurers and entrepreneurs fanned out across the continents with 78-r.p.m. and wax cylinder recording equipment in search of indigenous music.</p>
        <p>Some 30,000 such records from all over the world have landed in Mr. Conte's basement since an aunt presented him, when he was 16, with a gift of Italian 78's. In addition, he has 5,000 LP's, close to 1,000 45's and more than 5000 hours of music on reels of tape and cassettes. Every Tuesday at 6 p.m., gems from Mr. Conte's collection are broadcast -- along with his appreciative comments and historical insights -- over the cultish WFMU/91.1 in Jersey City (it is streamed at the same time on the Web at www.wfmu.org, and in July will be available to other radio stations on CD).</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Conte's records provide the content and his voice provides the context, he's not solely responsible for ''The Secret Museum of the Air.'' His partner, who sometimes turns up on the program to schmooze about the records or help interview a guest but whose main responsibility is turning the often murky sound of the old records into broadcast-quality music, is Richard Shulberg, better known to listeners as Citizen Kafka.</p>
        <p>Mr. Conte usually records the 78's, along with his commentaries, on a digital audio tape and sends the tape to Mr. Shulberg, who lives in Brooklyn. The Citizen, as friends call him, then spends between 40 and 50 hours working on each show with digital equipment to get rid of the decades of static and scratches that muffle the sound, using Cedar noise reduction and sound restoration software. He mixes the programs digitally on a Sadie digital audio workstation tucked in a corner of his bedroom.</p>
        <p>Early segments of ''The Secret Museum,'' which was broadcast on Pacifica Radio's WBAI-FM from 1990 to 1996 and moved to WFMU in 1997, featured Kafka and Mr. Conte chatting informally about the records; these days the programs rely mostly on Mr. Conte's commentaries. To Mr. Conte, sequencing the cuts in the radio program is the artistic equivalent of composing music. The elements in his ''compositions'' are the often anonymous performers whose renditions of songs -- coughs and mutterings included -- are devoid of the show-biz flourishes that adorn even amateur music today. ''There is a heartfelt type of delivery that somehow leaps out at you,'' Mr. Conte says.</p>
        <p>''These records have a tremendous value outside of mere entertainment,'' he continues. ''They represent lost worlds and lost cultures.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Conte, 44, and Mr. Shulberg, 52, aspire to make each show, which they encourage listeners to record, a voyage of sorts. Sometimes they take listeners on a trip to a particular region -- the Athens nightclub scene of the 1920's, say, for bouzouki music; sometimes they create a thematic journey: in addition to the two ''Herds and Pastures'' programs, Mr. Conte has devoted shows to harvest and fishing chants, May Day songs, white blues singers and clarinet tunes. ''Pat could do an entire show of recordings of instruments made out of fish parts,'' Mr. Shulberg says.</p>
        <p>SITTING behind his cluttered desk in his basement archive, Mr. Conte says that each disc in his collection has a story: ''They came from various places and are the fruits of various adventures.''</p>
        <p>He has hunted down treasures in curbside garbage piles and used-book shops, at garage sales, flea markets and Salvation Army stores -- where, he says, 78's could once be had for a dime apiece. But much of his library came to him: as a teenager, he would discuss his obsession in short-wave radio conversations with people in distant lands who would then mail him records. ''It got to the point where every day the packages arrived was like Christmas for me,'' he recalls. ''I would open a box and sample another world and another time. It was an amazing feeling.''</p>
        <p>Over the years, Mr. Conte's records have turned him into something of a scholar, which he never was at school. He has acquired dictionaries for obscure languages. He relies on a wide circle of collectors and musicians fluent in foreign tongues, and has conducted voluminous correspondence with academics around the world.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Conte is a kind of ethnic-music scholastic, ranging the world from his monk's cell in Massapequa Park, Mr. Shulberg is more of a free spirit. He loves the old music at least as much as Mr. Conte does, but his own collection of over 30,000 records remains unorganized. His resume includes stints as an opal prospector, a film projectionist, a theremin player and an antiques vendor. He is the leader of the Wretched Refuse String Band, a 30-year-old ensemble that counts such bluegrass virtuosos as Kenny Kosek, Andy Statman and Tony Trischka as alumni. And he produced and performed ''The Citizen Kafka Show,'' a comedy program that was broadcast monthly on WBAI-FM during most of the 1980's and that featured an actor, then unknown, by the name of John Goodman. When the Shirah Kober Zeller Foundation, which supports theater and environmental projects, began underwriting ''The Secret Museum of the Air,'' Mr. Shulberg traded in his job as manager of a SoHo bookstore-cafe for full-time work on the broadcast.</p>
        <p>In addition to creating the radio show and performing with the blues band the Otis Brothers, Mr. Conte has also edited a series of CD's on Shanachie Records' Yazoo label. ''The Secret Museum of Mankind Ethnic Music Classics: 1925-48'' includes five globetrotting anthologies that jump from, say, New Caledonia to Bulgaria to Puerto Rico, and that will force many record buyers to their atlases: Simbo Island? Lukachukai, Ariz.? There are also individual albums dedicated to the music of North Africa, East Africa and Central Asia.</p>
        <p>''Some collectors put old 78's in safe deposit boxes, and there they sit,'' says Richard Nevins, the president of Shanachie. ''Pat's excited about sharing it. It's a pretty high calling.''</p>
        <p>TELEVISION/RADIO Jon Kalish is a freelance newspaper and radio journalist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jon Kalish is a freelance newspaper and radio journalist.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
