<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Children's Books</title>
    <meta content="RV070831" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000625T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">McCormick, Patricia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clements, Andrew</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Janitor's Boy, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EED8113FF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Children's Books</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Patricia McCormick</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">McCormick, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia McCormick reviews book The Janitor's Boy by Andrew Clements; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE JANITOR'S BOY</p>
        <p>By Andrew Clements.</p>
        <p>140 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster</p>
        <p>Books for Young Readers. $15.</p>
        <p>(Ages 8 to 12)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE JANITOR'S BOY</p>
        <p>By Andrew Clements.</p>
        <p>140 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster</p>
        <p>Books for Young Readers. $15.</p>
        <p>(Ages 8 to 12)</p>
        <p>When Ursula Nordstrom, the legendary children's book editor, was asked to explain her gift for discovering great authors, she replied, ''I am a former child.'' An obvious enough qualification, it would seem. But the best children's writers, as she found, are a rare breed of adults: grown-ups with a keen recollection of childhood past, as well as an uncanny feel for childhood present.</p>
        <p>Teachers -- the people who usually introduce such writers to their readers -- are also on the lookout for authors with this particular kind of perfect pitch. A few teachers who turned to writing come to mind: Jon Scieszka, with his sly, sophisticated sendups of classic fairy tales (''Squids Will Be Squids''); Jerry Spinelli, who renders the joy and sorrow of childhood in true-to-life language (''Maniac Magee''); and, of course, Beverly Cleary, who has written extraordinarily real and funny stories about ordinary kids (the ''Ramona'' series).</p>
        <p>Andrew Clements, author of ''The Janitor's Boy,'' is a relatively recent teacher's pet of an author. Middle-grade teachers -- and, more important, middle-grade readers -- love his books (''Frindle,'' ''The Landry News'') precisely because they reflect the emotional and cultural reality of today's children and their school life. And, unlike many children's books that are criticized for presenting a world full of absent or childish adults, Clements's novels are stocked with flesh-and-blood grown-ups, some of whom are even teachers or parents.</p>
        <p>In ''The Janitor's Boy,'' the adult is ''John the janitor''; the boy is his fifth-grade son, Jack. Jack is relatively oblivious of his father's occupation until he starts middle school in the old building where his father works. But when he and his peers see John cleaning up after Lenny Trumbull gets sick on cafeteria ravioli, the teasing begins. Jack retaliates -- not against his classmates, but against the person he blames for his embarrassment: his father. His plan backfires, though, when he covers the underside of a chair with wads of sticky gum (13 pieces of ''watermelon Bubblicious . . . the smelliest gum in the universe''), gets caught and is sentenced to a three-week detention scraping gum off the bottoms of chairs and desks.</p>
        <p>If Jack were a kindergartner, being a junior janitor helper might be a plum assignment. Very young schoolchildren, especially little boys, often develop a fascination with the janitor. For one thing, the custodian is usually one of the few men in school, and he has lots of keys and cool tools. (My son actually thought the kindly uniformed man who greeted us outside school every day was the principal.) But by middle school, any appreciation of custodial workers has long since given way to a benign unconsciousness -- or worse, condescension.</p>
        <p>Clements makes that life visible. In a series of achingly awkward (and therefore very real) experiences, Jack comes to a fuller, more complicated understanding of his father. But ''The Janitor's Boy'' has a more subtle magic. Not only will young readers think twice about the workaday lives of their own parents; they'll also come away with a better appreciation for the ubiquitous but inconspicuous men and women who keep their schools humming. All this makes it a perfect book for a classroom ethics discussion, even if it is entertaining.</p>
        <p>Few contemporary writers portray the public school world better than Clements, who taught for seven years before turning to writing. He isn't didactic or -- one hesitates to use the word -- schoolmarmish. Quite the contrary; his books feature the kind of humor that rings true for savvy young readers. For general grossness, he invokes (or perhaps coins) the term ''vomit-o-domino effect'': the tendency of other children to throw up at the sight of vomit. And he knows the ways of school grapevines, noting that ''a really juicy story that involves crime and punishment can hit speeds of one or two hundred mouths an hour.''</p>
        <p>Although it may not be immediately obvious to readers, the central theme of ''The Janitor's Boy'' also lies at the heart of the middle-grade experience: the passage from child to adolescent. Clements captures this emotional tug-of-war with clarity and humor. Jack, for instance, makes a list titled ''Ways I Am NOT Like My Dad,'' including such important differences as ''I am not going to live in Huntington when I grow up'' and ''I am going to go to college,'' along with the rather weak postscript, ''I hate tomatoes.'' To his credit, Clements mainly treats this tender topic with understatement, even if the ending is a bit treacly.</p>
        <p>Today's middle-school readers are, of course, overexposed to media images of a world supersaturated with drugs, sex and violence. This doesn't mean they are sophisticated; it does mean they can sniff out a phony at 28,880 bits per second. I'd wager it also means they're eager to see a reflection of childhood present that is as real as it is respectful of them. ''The Janitor's Boy'' is such a book.</p>
        <p>Patricia McCormick's first novel for young adults, ''Cut,'' will be published this fall.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 25, 2000, Sunday  A picture caption in last Sunday's Book Review misidentified the jacket artist for the children's book ''The Janitor's Boy.'' He was Brian Selznick, not Steve Scott; Mr. Scott was the jacket's graphic designer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 25, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption in last Sunday's Book Review misidentified the jacket artist for the children's book ''The Janitor's Boy.'' He was Brian Selznick, not Steve Scott; Mr. Scott was the jacket's graphic designer.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Patricia McCormick's first novel for young adults, ''Cut,'' will be published this fall.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
