<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dwindling Few in Search of Value</title>
    <meta content="18VALU$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000625T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fabrikant, Geraldine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenwald, Bruce (Prof)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DD1631F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dwindling Few in Search of Value</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALDINE FABRIKANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabrikant, Geraldine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Columbia University Business School's annual seminar on value investing draws only 16 participants this year, down from 60 in 1999, a reflection of investors' infatuation with high-priced technology stocks, many of which lack proven franchise power, obvious asset value or profits, key measures of value; Prof Bruce Greenwald leads faithful few in study of value factors; Greenwald defends value investing as an attempt to make intelligent use of all available data, though value stocks have underperformed growth stocks in recent years; photo; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SAY this about brand-name value investors: There seem to be fewer of them of late.</p>
        <p>This year, Julian Robertson of Tiger Management handed in his slide rule. And Robert Sanborn, manager of the Oakmark Fund, surrendered his post, as did Gary Brinson, a chief investment officer at UBS A.G.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SAY this about brand-name value investors: There seem to be fewer of them of late.</p>
        <p>This year, Julian Robertson of Tiger Management handed in his slide rule. And Robert Sanborn, manager of the Oakmark Fund, surrendered his post, as did Gary Brinson, a chief investment officer at UBS A.G.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, value investing still has its core loyalists, at least as seen at a recent two-day executive seminar on the subject at the Columbia University Business School. The session is offered each June.</p>
        <p>This is not just any value investing seminar. Over the years, the audience has included luminaries like Charles H. Bruni, chairman emeritus of Oppenheimer Capital; Herbert Allen Jr. of Allen &amp; Company; and Michael Overlock, the former head of investment banking at Goldman Sachs.</p>
        <p>Last year, attendance swelled to 60 people. But this year, as the market has remained infatuated with high-priced technology stocks, many of which lack proven franchise power, obvious asset value, or profits -- the number of participants fell sharply, to just 16.</p>
        <p>The motley roster of guests lacked some of the glamour of former years. It included an Icelandair executive who worries about the value of his company's Internet investments, an executive at a Puerto Rican food distribution company and an executive from Cattolica Populare, an Italian investment firm.</p>
        <p>These hard-core acolytes of Warren E. Buffett would not be swayed from the value outlook. Jeffrey Todd Hamm, recently out of college, is investing a bit of his own money while he looks for a job. Over a lunch break, he compared notes with Francesco Azzolini,  who had flown in from the Molfetta, Italy,  headquarters of Cattolica Populare, which  manages $70 million in assets.</p>
        <p>''How do you figure the underlying value of a stock without getting distracted from the noise?'' Mr. Hamm asked. ''I haven't bought the Internet stocks, and I have still made money. I feel more proud of myself if I follow my discipline.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hamm is looking for an investing job in a market obsessed by the new economy, so his attention to valuations may make him appear old-fashioned. Getting the right position is taking time. ''I want to find a job where I can hold my investment strategy firm,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The man whom these guests paid up to $2,900 to hear is Prof. Bruce Greenwald, who appeared adamant about the worth of his chosen discipline as he walked his audience through the rigors of searching for attractive value stocks. Unlike many proponents of value investing, who dwell on price-to-earnings and price-to-book multiples, Professor Greenwald focuses just as much on a company's franchise and earnings predictability.</p>
        <p>The seminar's case studies zeroed in on Sealed Air, a packaging company, and Liz Claiborne, the apparel maker.</p>
        <p>But perhaps as a concession to the market's infatuation with growth, some of the discussion centered on dissecting the worth of new-economy stocks.</p>
        <p>Professor Greenwald pointed out that there are technology value stocks. Back in 1994, for example, Intel traded at just 12 times earnings but had a juggernaut franchise and proven earnings power.</p>
        <p>Of course, many value investors have ignored the sector because they cannot  make heads or tails of it.</p>
        <p>''This approach helps you understand the difference between buying an Intel, which has real values, if not at current prices, and some Internet stock that has no value at all or very little,'' Professor Greenwald said.</p>
        <p>Is it possible that value investing may never again return to favor? ''No, it is not over,'' the professor said. ''Value investing is really an attempt to use all the information you have intelligently.''</p>
        <p>Still, most people continue to shun value stocks. ''The fact is they love to buy lottery tickets,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But not Steinn Bjornsson, 40, senior vice president for marketing and sales at Icelandair, a privately held company that has been doing deals with Internet-based travel companies. ''I am asked to invest in small companies that have computer-driven travel operations,'' Mr. Bjornsson said. ''Sometimes the guy with the biggest hype and the strongest arguments gets the investment money, but the company has no cash flow,'' he said. ''At least I can ask them to prove what they are promising.''</p>
        <p>Vincent Bazi, a senior manager at Oddio &amp; Company, a French brokerage firm, flew in from Paris because he is planning to redeploy some of his clients' money -- out of the technology sector and into value stocks. ''We did 25 percent of the I.P.O.'s in France, making a lot of money for our clients,'' he  said. ''Some investors will come back to traditional stocks to diversify their portfolios.''</p>
        <p>As for Professor Greenwald, he is not much of an investor himself, because he does not feel that he has the time to devote to it. So he is not agonizing over value stocks' underperformance.</p>
        <p>But he is suffering in other ways. His mother, Virginia, 78, pays scant heed to his value outlook, having bought bought Cisco Systems at $2.50 a share in 1995, and Oracle at about $15 in early 1999. Before the April meltdown in technology, he said, she sold Cisco for $80.25 and Oracle for $83. ''How would you feel with a mother who's a genius?'' he asked ruefully.</p>
        <p>INVESTING  Correction:  June 25, 2000, Sunday  An article last Sunday about a seminar at the Columbia Business School on value investing misidentified a French brokerage firm that employs one of the participants. It is Oddo &amp; Company, not Oddio.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 25, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about a seminar at the Columbia Business School on value investing misidentified a French brokerage firm that employs one of the participants. It is Oddo &amp; Company, not Oddio.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
