<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Raising the Stakes In Punk Rock</title>
    <meta content="18MARC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208148"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (AUDIO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SLEATER-KINNEY (MUSIC GROUP)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNSTEIN, CARRIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TUCKER, CORIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEISS, JANET</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARCUS, GREIL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E4DC123EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Raising the Stakes In Punk Rock</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREIL MARCUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARCUS, GREIL</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Olympia, Washington-based three-woman punk rock group Sleater-Kinney, comprised of Carrie Brownstein, Corin Tucker and Janet Weiss; members, just days after performing at Soupstock 2000 in San Francisco's Mission District, comment on their music and recently released fifth album; photos (M)0</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TWO Sundays ago, some 10,000 people gathered in Dolores Park in the Mission District here for Soupstock 2000, a day of music celebrating the 20th anniversary of Food Not Bombs. With chapters around the country and overseas, the anarchist collective was founded to fight militarism; more recently, in San Francisco, the group has organized tenants to oppose gentrification and often clashed with police over unauthorized, on-the-street food distribution to homeless people. But this was a sunny day. The riotously tattooed crowd was very young, no one was hungry (''Have you had any of the food?'' asked an announcer from the stage; ''It's free; everything here today is free''), and Sleater-Kinney, a three-woman punk band founded in Olympia, Wash., in 1994, was out of place.</p>
        <p>The guitarists Carrie Brownstein and Corin Tucker and the drummer Janet Weiss -- all three sing -- put out their records on Kill Rock Stars, a small independent label that functions very well as the center of its own universe: its slogan used to be ''Olympia, Birthplace of Rock,'' which was a way of saying that rock 'n' roll can be born again and again, anywhere and at any time. ''There's nothing that we do that can be separated from where we're from,'' Ms. Weiss said four days after Soupstock: she lives in Portland, Ore., as does Ms. Tucker; Ms. Brownstein lives in Olympia. ''It's rainy. And it's gray. It allows you to be more internal than a place with an outdoor, extroverted climate. It allows for and fosters our ability to break out. To get away. To make a difference. And it fosters our ability to go home and regroup and rebuild.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TWO Sundays ago, some 10,000 people gathered in Dolores Park in the Mission District here for Soupstock 2000, a day of music celebrating the 20th anniversary of Food Not Bombs. With chapters around the country and overseas, the anarchist collective was founded to fight militarism; more recently, in San Francisco, the group has organized tenants to oppose gentrification and often clashed with police over unauthorized, on-the-street food distribution to homeless people. But this was a sunny day. The riotously tattooed crowd was very young, no one was hungry (''Have you had any of the food?'' asked an announcer from the stage; ''It's free; everything here today is free''), and Sleater-Kinney, a three-woman punk band founded in Olympia, Wash., in 1994, was out of place.</p>
        <p>The guitarists Carrie Brownstein and Corin Tucker and the drummer Janet Weiss -- all three sing -- put out their records on Kill Rock Stars, a small independent label that functions very well as the center of its own universe: its slogan used to be ''Olympia, Birthplace of Rock,'' which was a way of saying that rock 'n' roll can be born again and again, anywhere and at any time. ''There's nothing that we do that can be separated from where we're from,'' Ms. Weiss said four days after Soupstock: she lives in Portland, Ore., as does Ms. Tucker; Ms. Brownstein lives in Olympia. ''It's rainy. And it's gray. It allows you to be more internal than a place with an outdoor, extroverted climate. It allows for and fosters our ability to break out. To get away. To make a difference. And it fosters our ability to go home and regroup and rebuild.''</p>
        <p>The band had flown in from Denver near the end of a five-week, 29-date tour. They were flying, you could imagine, on the momentum generated in their recently released fifth album, ''All Hands on the Bad One.'' It's get-out-of-the-way music: ''Is It a Lie?,'' a song that steps back from itself, viewing the disaster it recounts as if it were a reverie, starts in the middle of a dead run.</p>
        <p>Most punk bands get less fierce, less demanding, as they learn to play better; they substitute technique for bravado, because they're so pleased to discover they can master a technique. Though from ''Sleater-Kinney'' (1995), ''Call the Doctor'' (1995), ''Dig Me Out'' (1997) and ''The Hot Rock'' (1999) to ''All Hands on the Bad One,'' Sleater-Kinney's sound has gone from crankily primitive to frighteningly grand, the band has grown not out of ferocity but into it: ''Instead of a locked room,'' as the critic Howard Hampton says of ''All Hands on the Bad One,'' it is ''a storming of 'The Shining's' castle-keep's endless corridors, haunted rooms and menstruating elevators,'' until everything is in jeopardy and no destiny is fixed.</p>
        <p>THIS was the argument many made from the stage in Dolores Park, but not the feeling. Everything was in jeopardy -- the right to live in a city being transformed by unlimited amounts of new dot.com money, with long-time tenants evicted and people working ordinary jobs forced to flee rents they could never imagine paying (''You're no longer wanted here,'' a speaker told the crowd, and for a moment the sunny day chilled) -- but everything was enclosed in that locked room. The speakers seemed tired of their own words, their outrage rote. Their worry that the people gathered before them were present only to hear bands they'd already heard of was inescapable. When Diamond Dave Whitaker, Bob Dylan's mentor in Minneapolis's Dinkytown in 1960, introduced the combo Folk This as a link to a long tradition of song and protest -- ''Back to 'Cisco, Woody and Lead Belly too,'' Mr. Whitaker said, quoting Dylan's 1962 ''Song to Woody'' -- you could hear him try to unlock the door. Offering a smug version of ''There'll Be Pie in the Sky When You Die,'' a broadside by Joe Hill, the I.W.W. songwriter who was executed by a Utah firing squad in 1915, the group went right back to nothing-new-under-the-sun. They followed with a horrible workers' anthem (''March, march, you toilers''), translated from the Polish.</p>
        <p>What wasn't hectoring was sentimental, and Sleater-Kinney were out of place because they were neither. ''We're more interested in raising the stakes,'' Ms. Brownstein, 25, said here on June 8, just before the last show of Sleater-Kinney's tour, at the Fillmore. That's just what the band did at Dolores Park -- that, and change the language.</p>
        <p>Setting up, they were three demure-looking women. There was no hint of the world-claiming hugeness of the voice that comes out of Ms. Tucker, 27 -- probably the biggest voice in pop music since Arlene Smith of the Bronx's Chantels, and that was in the 1950's -- or of the magnetic, absolutely determined presence of Ms. Weiss, 34, or Ms. Brownstein's leaps all over the stage. But by the time the band reached ''Call the Doctor,'' four songs into its set, everything had changed.</p>
        <p>Some of the words to ''Call the Doctor'' could have been read out by one of the day's speakers (''They want to socialize you'' is the first line). But a lyric sheet is not a song. ''It's the ability of the sounds and the melodies and the rhythms to sometimes counteract, to create tension, sometimes to work as a complete whole,'' Ms. Weiss said. ''Sometimes the sound of the song can create the meaning of the words -- create a duality for the words.'' That is what happened. It was as if the shibboleth that opened the song was there only for its language to be destroyed by the Superman leaps of the band's sound -- a sound Ms. Weiss always kept open even when Ms. Tucker's wail seemed so big it would blow the performance up.</p>
        <p>''The sound of Bob Dylan's voice had more to do with changing the world than anything he sang about,'' Robert Ray, a musician and professor of English at the University of Florida, has written; the same is true of the sound Sleater-Kinney makes. One could imagine that first line was there only to remind a listener of how far one had come by the shocking end of the piece, with Ms. Brownstein screaming into her microphone, making a noise that went in human and came out inhuman, and Ms. Tucker commanding: ''Call the doctor! Call the doctor!'' as if more than one life was at stake. ''I was frustrated,'' Ms. Brownstein later said of the moment. ''But sometimes when there's a sense of desperation when we play, I can muster up that kind of inner . . . monster.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Tucker's whole performance can seem like Ms. Brownstein's moments. ''I'm your monster, I'm not like you,'' Ms. Tucker chants a few lines into ''Call the Doctor'' (following later with ''I'm no monster, I'm just like you'' -- but then, you think, with her voice ringing in your head, which? who am I?). It can be thrilling, confusing, scary, but it's no effect: it's a voice that was discovered, and passed on.</p>
        <p>The story goes back to the teenage radical feminist milieu that called itself riot grrrl, an explosion of bands, fanzines and cross-country committees of correspondence, a milieu with an especially strong presence in Olympia. ''I was 18,'' Ms. Tucker said on the last night of the band's tour. ''I went to a show that Bratmobile and Bikini Kill played'' -- respectively, the three-woman punk band that would open the Fillmore show, and the startlingly extreme three-woman, one-man riot grrrl band led by the singer Kathleen Hanna. ''It was Feb. 14, 1991. And Kathleen Hanna was . . . terrifying. People were just freaking out. She was saying things'' -- with the slogan ''Revolution Girl Style Now,'' singing songs about rape, incest and resistance, sometimes with words like ''Slut'' scrawled on her stomach -- ''that were really direct and really emotional at the same time. She was so powerful. People were crying. And some people were like, 'They're the worst band ever.'</p>
        <p>''It was the first time I'd seen feminism translated into an emotional language,'' Ms. Tucker went on. ''That I saw those kinds of thoughts and ideas put into your own personal life, that's not in a textbook or an academic discussion. For young women to be doing that, basically teenagers on stage, to be taking that kind of stance, that kind of power, was blowing people's minds. And it totally blew my mind. I was like,'' Ms. Tucker said with happy determination, ''O.K., that's it. That's it for me -- I'm going in a band, right now. You had the feeling they had started the band the week before: you can do it too'' -- that is, you too can stand up and speak in the town square, even if you have to create the town square yourself.</p>
        <p>As a kind of public secret society, riot grrrl became an almost instant meal for the media, and the movement turned inward. ''The outside world reacted so intensely we had to band together,'' Ms. Tucker said. ''We suddenly had Newsweek reporters hiring women to come to our shows, and not tell us they were journalists, and say that they were fans, and this was so important to them, buying our really personal fanzines. And the press that happened about riot grrrl was extremely sexist, and really targeted. Taking these young women and trying to make them look absolutely inarticulate. That it was just a fashion thing, that people were doing it just to get attention. There were valid issues that were being presented in the music, or in the words that we were saying: rape and sexual abuse, issues that young women face, that we face.''</p>
        <p>As Ms. Brownstein added, it was a small revolution in many hearts that was soon enough ''completely collapsed into the Spice Girls: T-shirts with 'Girls Rule' or 'Girl Power' -- even if the Spice Girls would never know where that came from.'' But this was also the voice that is passed on by Sleater-Kinney. Ms. Tucker has a particular gift that turns that voice into a thing in itself: a force of will disguised as a force of nature.</p>
        <p>Over seven years, Sleater-Kinney have found an intense following all over the country. Though their music is almost never played on commercial radio, and for good reason -- like Sex Pistols music, it is so strong, so quick and far-reaching, it makes nearly everything that today might surround it on the radio feel cowardly -- their albums now sell about 100,000 copies: a figure, Ms. Brownstein said as Ms. Weiss and Ms. Tucker nodded in agreement, that ''seems like so much. It's still amazing for us to think that many people have our record, who sit there and listen to it.''</p>
        <p>The three make a living as musicians, and manage themselves financially. ''I don't think people realize,'' Ms. Tucker said, ''how important it is for a band to know about how records are sold, how things are made, what percentage of profits you're going to get, how touring happens, how to make money on tour.''  All three agreed that collaborating with a small, independent label strengthened, not weakened, their ability to treat a musical career as at once a form of free speech and real work.</p>
        <p>''I give you the best band in the world,'' an announcer said from the wings as Sleater-Kinney walked onto the stage at the Fillmore. The impossible encomium didn't seem pretentious, didn't seem like anything anyone had to live up to -- not the band, not the crowd, which in contrast to the two-thirds female audience in Los Angeles two nights before was at least two-thirds male; in contrast to the crowd at Dolores Park, where people who looked over 30 were a rarity, here there were a lot of people who looked over 50. The feeling was all anticipation: Aren't we lucky to be here?</p>
        <p>For an encore, the band chose ''White Rabbit,'' with Ms. Tucker walking in the footsteps worn into the Fillmore stage floor in 1966 when Grace Slick sang it with the Jefferson Airplane. It sounded unnatural -- for punk bands, pre-punk rock numbers often feel like they're being performed in a second language, because they are -- as Creedence Clearwater Revival's ''Fortunate Son'' had not when Sleater-Kinney played it at Dolores Park. Whatever its chords or its melody, Creedence's old, still-fresh curse on privilege had the hurry and worry that is Sleater-Kinney's first language.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes,'' Ms. Brownstein said in between the two shows, ''when we're listening to music in the van, from the 60's and 70's, we always are so surprised that some of these songs that are so political and so meaningful ever were on the radio, and hits. You miss that feeling of such cultural power, such belief, that music could have an effect on so many people. Because right now, I feel like people have lost faith in music, in popular music, having the kind of efficacy it did before.''</p>
        <p>''In the 60's,'' Stanley Booth writes in the new edition of his ''The True Adventures of the Rolling Stones,''  ''we believed in a myth -- that music had the power to change people's lives. Today we believe in a myth -- that music is just entertainment.''</p>
        <p>''I like that first myth so much better,'' Ms. Weiss said. ''Bob Dylan -- for someone saying those words, to break into the mainstream, I think it's amazing. I think he handled it really well. He developed, and changed, and took chances. It's like he was the original punk rocker. And still is.''</p>
        <p>Bob Dylan was not exactly missing when Sleater-Kinney went into their last number at both the Fillmore and Soupstock 2000 -- that last number in both cases being the storming ''Dig Me Out.'' He was present as an imagined comrade, just as, keeping his own counsel, he had been present in spirit at Soupstock's progenitor, the Woodstock festival of 31 years before. ''Dig Me Out'' was a desperate celebration at the Fillmore -- the end of a traverse of the nation, a cry of having made it through with nothing lost, with other musicians from the tour, male and female, madly go-going across the stage in full ''Shindig'' absurdity. In the crowd, you had to wonder how long it would be before you saw anything so funny, or heard anything so unafraid. But at Dolores Park, the feeling was different. There were still shows to play after this one, and the song was not an occasion for revelry; it seemed like a last chance.</p>
        <p>SLEATER-KINNEY came out of the self-created community of riot grrrl. When you ask what a community is for, one answer is to create events like the one at Dolores Park. In a conversation years ago about what ''politics'' would mean in the political philosopher Hannah Arendt's ideal city, where what she called ''the social question'' -- hunger, want, poverty -- had been solved or banished, one person answered seriously, ''People would decide what plays to put on.'' They'd decide if they wanted to take a chance on a play as extreme as that performed inside ''Dig Me Out.'' Dig me out, dig me out -- as the words were chanted in Dolores Park, chanted as if they were the whole of the language Sleater-Kinney was speaking, you could in the instant feel buried by the social question, by the money that was changing the city and that you would never have, buried by whatever you feared was set against you in the world at large.</p>
        <p>Then ''Dig me out'' was no longer a line in a song by a punk band but something in the air, a warning, or a promise, or an event taking place as you listened. ''They will do it again, the threads of youthful dissidence in Paris and Texas and Prague and Berkeley and Chicago and London,'' Jan Hodenfield ended his Rolling Stone report on Woodstock in 1969, ''criss-crossing ever more closely until the map of the world we live in is viable for and visible to all of those that are part of it and all of those buried under it.''  ''The Drama You've Been Craving,'' Sleater-Kinney titles one of their songs; that is the drama they are craving, and the drama they are making.</p>
        <p>Greil Marcus's ''Double Trouble: Bill Clinton and Elvis Presley in a Land of No Alternatives'' will be published in September by Henry Holt.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Greil Marcus's ''Double Trouble: Bill Clinton and Elvis Presley in a Land of No Alternatives'' will be published in September by Henry Holt.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
