<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Message Was Received By Surging MetroStars</title>
    <meta content="18SOCC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208500"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metrostars</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New England Revolution</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3DD1431F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="694" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Message Was Received By Surging MetroStars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., June 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>MetroStars defeat New England Revolution, 4-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The message had been pounded into the MetroStars during practice, that after a lackluster effort a week ago they were still readying for their biggest game of the year and had much to play for. And if the words of Octavio Zambrano did not get through, the elbow that Tab Ramos took just minutes into today's game from Leonel Alvarez relayed the message again that this game was important.</p>
        <p>And, for the first time that even Ramos could recall -- he has been with the team since its inception -- the MetroStars responded. Falling behind by a goal in the first half, the MetroStars scored three consecutive goals to defeat the New England Revolution, 4-2, at Giants Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The message had been pounded into the MetroStars during practice, that after a lackluster effort a week ago they were still readying for their biggest game of the year and had much to play for. And if the words of Octavio Zambrano did not get through, the elbow that Tab Ramos took just minutes into today's game from Leonel Alvarez relayed the message again that this game was important.</p>
        <p>And, for the first time that even Ramos could recall -- he has been with the team since its inception -- the MetroStars responded. Falling behind by a goal in the first half, the MetroStars scored three consecutive goals to defeat the New England Revolution, 4-2, at Giants Stadium.</p>
        <p>While the victory still left the MetroStars 4 points behind the first-place Revolution in the Eastern Division of Major League Soccer, the game seemed to revitalize the team's belief that it could hope to achieve something special this year. The victory evened the team's record at 7-7 and matched its victory total of last season.</p>
        <p>''That's how we looked at it,'' said Ramos, who was back in the starting lineup because of injuries sidelining Roy Myers and Petter Villegas. ''Normally in a season there are four or five games that you look back at. If we lost today, we'd be 10 points back, and now we would not be contenders anymore. Now we're looking at trying to get first place in our division. That's what we're shooting for and today we showed we're at least contenders. It was a big game, and finally, we came through.''</p>
        <p>The MetroStars did it by answering the early intimidation attempts with their own rugged play, committing 32 fouls, a franchise record. The MetroStars were assessed five yellow cards, while the Revolution had four, and Daniel Hernandez was ejected for an illegal tackle. Alvarez drew a second yellow card and an ejection in the 84th minute.</p>
        <p>''We prepared mentally for that,'' Zambrano said of the physical play. ''I think that the guys understood what happened last game against Tampa when we basically were not motivated enough. I think the way we prepared for this match, a lot of it was our approach mentally to the importance of playing the team that is in front of us. This is a six-point game. I have to say I'm very proud of them.''</p>
        <p>The MetroStars took a 1-0 lead in the 20th minute when Clint Mathis slipped a pass to Billy Walsh, who blasted a shot from 35 yards into the left corner of the net for his first goal of the season. The lead disappeared quickly when the Revolution was awarded a penalty kick in the 24th minute, the referee ruling that Mark Chung had taken down Joe Franchino in the box. Ramos and Mathis each drew yellow cards as they argued the call furiously, but the call stood and Imad Baba converted the penalty kick.</p>
        <p>New England then pushed in front five minutes later, pelting three shots at Mike Ammann, who knocked the first two away, but Wolde Harris rolled the rebound under Ammann for a 2-1 advantage.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars did not shrink from the challenge. They scored  twice before the half was over to take a 3-2 lead. First, Mike Petke stole a pass just outside the New England box and Adolfo Valencia picked up the ball, beat two defenders and ripped a low shot past Jeff Causey to tie the score.</p>
        <p>Two minutes later, Valencia made a pretty feed to Chung on the run and Chung fired a shot that hit the crossbar, bounding to Steve Shak, who curved a shot into the right corner of the net for his first M.L.S. goal.</p>
        <p>''I liked our mindset,'' Zambrano said.</p>
        <p>The lead was increased to two goals four minutes into the second half when Chung was fouled by Alvarez just outside the box. Mathis took the free kick and beat a diving Causey with a shot into the upper right corner.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
