<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.O.P. Pushing New Plan for Primaries</title>
    <meta content="18PRIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nicholson, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DD1431F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="662" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.O.P. Pushing New Plan for Primaries</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jim Nicholson, chairman of Republican National Committee, says three-fourths of American people who say they want national primary to pick their presidential nominees are wrong; Nicholson finds current nominating process excessively dependent on money and giving too much influence to states with early primaries; instead, he advocates plan that would have smallest states hold primaries first, followed by small and medium-size states, with largest states voting last; biggest obstacle to his plan is objection of several big states (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most politicians do not go out of their way to say the public does not know what it is talking about. But Jim Nicholson cheerfully takes on the three-fourths of the American people who say they want a national primary to pick their presidential nominees.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nicholson, the chairman of the Republican National Committee, responded to that finding, in a New York Times/CBS News Poll in May, by saying the public was ''wrong, wrong, wrong.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most politicians do not go out of their way to say the public does not know what it is talking about. But Jim Nicholson cheerfully takes on the three-fourths of the American people who say they want a national primary to pick their presidential nominees.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nicholson, the chairman of the Republican National Committee, responded to that finding, in a New York Times/CBS News Poll in May, by saying the public was ''wrong, wrong, wrong.''</p>
        <p>''They haven't thought about it enough,'' he said. ''I don't think there has been a rational public dialogue for them to have made a rational decision.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nicholson is no supporter of the current nominating process, which he finds excessively dependent on money, giving too much influence to states with early primaries. ''It is not totally broken down yet, but it is breaking.''</p>
        <p>Instead he advocates a plan adopted last month by the Rules Committee of the Republican National Committee. It would have the smallest states hold primaries first, in February, followed by small and medium-size states in March and April, with the big states voting in May.</p>
        <p>That approach, Mr. Nicholson argues, would maintain public interest until May, unlike this year's contests, which were over in March. He said it would encourage more face-to-face campaigning and less reliance on campaign commercials and airport stops to get on the local television news. And that in turn would make it possible for unknown, underfinanced candidates to build on early success and make a race of it.</p>
        <p>The biggest obstacle to Republicans' adopting this plan is the opposition of several big states, which fear that whatever the mathematics of delegate selection (about half would be chosen in May), the nominations would be effectively settled before they got to vote. He conceded, ''We don't see any movement on that yet.''</p>
        <p>But, he added, ''We plan to have more discussions with the big states between now and when we go to Philadelphia'' for the convention at the end of July. Under Republican rules, only the convention can change party procedures, although the proposal would also give the Republican National Committee power to adjust things between conventions. The Democratic National Committee already has that authority.</p>
        <p>Another alternative, one many big states prefer, would be rotating regional primaries, with a different bloc of states going first every four years. Such a system, Mr. Nicholson said, ''has a lot of advantages over the current system, but you would have to change the statutes of the states every four years.''</p>
        <p>The worst alternative, he said, would be a national primary. The public might think that would get the process over more quickly, but in fact ''the buildup to it would be a lot longer and more intense than it is now,'' he said. ''All the marbles would be riding on that one day.''</p>
        <p>A national primary, he said, would require ''an enormous amount of money, even more reliance on advertising and less on retail campaigning.''</p>
        <p>''It would also lead to a lot more negative campaigning for 'knockout' day, with candidates doing a lot more to trip up their opponents,'' he said.</p>
        <p>It ''would greatly favor people who were either very famous or very rich,'' Mr. Nicholson said.</p>
        <p>Nor is it a matter of choosing whether to keep the present system or a national primary. Because states want to rush to the earliest permissible date, he said, ''we are on an inexorable path to a national primary day,'' which would intensify ''all the things that are wrong with the present system.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nicholson said he was disappointed that Democrats had poured cold water on the idea this spring, but said he hoped that if the Republicans could pass it, Democrats would consider it afresh after the election. ''That is the responsibility of the parties,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
