<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lower Morale, Yes. But Apathy?; Police Say They Are Diligent as Ever, and the Numbers Agree</title>
    <meta content="18COPS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puerto Rican Day</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Central Park (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EFDD1431F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1320" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lower Morale, Yes. But Apathy?; Police Say They Are Diligent as Ever, and the Numbers Agree</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Kevin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Several statistical measures indicate many New York City police, despite morale slump and sexual assaults on dozens of women near parade patrolled by 4,000 officers, remain actively involved in Giuliani administration's aggressive law enforcement efforts; arrests are up 12 percent this year, underwritten by huge infusion of overtime money, despite 7.5 percent crime drop; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The murder rate is up 6 percent. The Wendy's killings and a spate of livery-cab driver murders have revived a long-dormant image of a dangerous New York. And here and there, when New Yorkers talk about crime and remember the bad old days, many have come to assume that a police force tired of pay disparity, relentless pressure to produce and public second-guessing has grown sluggish.</p>
        <p>The impression of arms-folded indifference by the police was reinforced last weekend when, in a city where the tiniest crimes have long been vigorously pursued, dozens of women were sexually assaulted in the environs of an event, the National Puerto Rican Day Parade, that was being patrolled by 4,000 officers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The murder rate is up 6 percent. The Wendy's killings and a spate of livery-cab driver murders have revived a long-dormant image of a dangerous New York. And here and there, when New Yorkers talk about crime and remember the bad old days, many have come to assume that a police force tired of pay disparity, relentless pressure to produce and public second-guessing has grown sluggish.</p>
        <p>The impression of arms-folded indifference by the police was reinforced last weekend when, in a city where the tiniest crimes have long been vigorously pursued, dozens of women were sexually assaulted in the environs of an event, the National Puerto Rican Day Parade, that was being patrolled by 4,000 officers.</p>
        <p>But by several statistical measures, indications are that whatever the slump in morale, many officers remain actively involved in the aggressive law enforcement efforts that have become a hallmark of the Giuliani administration.</p>
        <p>Arrests are up 12 percent this year, after falling by nearly 9 percent last year. Gun arrests, which declined by nearly 15 percent last year, have increased by 1.4 percent this year, and criminal summonses for lesser offenses like trespassing and public urination have increased by 16.6 percent.</p>
        <p>To be sure, arrests can be an imprecise measure of enforcement efforts, especially when they are being underwritten by a huge infusion of overtime money, as they are this year. Arrests also will often be sent soaring by a surge in crime.</p>
        <p>But this year, crime is down by 7.5 percent across the city, and police supervisors say the reduction itself is a sign that there has been no lapse in energy on the part of their officers.</p>
        <p>''Sure, when there is a lot of criticism it wears on morale,'' said Assistant Chief Joseph Fox, the police commander for southern Brooklyn, where 10 percent more summonses have been issued this year. But, he said, ''there is still that focus on crime reduction and making arrests.''</p>
        <p>To many citizens accustomed to the Giuliani administration's zero tolerance approach to crime, an approach that saw the arrest several years ago of a man for riding a bicycle without a bell, there was little evidence of that crime-fighting focus as the Puerto Rican Day Parade broke up last weekend. Several women have complained that officers did nothing when they complained of sexual assaults inside Central Park. Several other people have said officers seemed to tolerate the rampant use of marijuana and alcohol.</p>
        <p>Police officials, who deny that drug use or criminal activity were routinely overlooked, spent several days last week compiling statistics to show that enforcement at this year's parade was as diligent as in the past. For example, they said, police issued 686 summonses that day for a variety of offenses like public drinking, nearly double the prior year's total.</p>
        <p>If there is an enforcement issue, several officers said, it is that police historically use more discretion at the Puerto Rican Day Parade because many officers believe that their superiors are not interested in seeing any confrontations between a largely white police force and Hispanic paradegoers.</p>
        <p>Police officials say statistics from other parades clearly demonstrate that officers are as aggressive at the Puerto Rican event as at any other. For example, they said there were only 200 bottles or cans of beer and liquor confiscated at the St. Patrick's Day Parade this year, while police took away 2,601 bottles and cans from revelers last Sunday.</p>
        <p>To some who spent last Sunday in Central Park, however, the numerical data seem like a lot of statistical legerdemain. Peter N. Duhamel, who jogs in the park each week, said that during his afternoon run through the park that day, officers seemed to have turned a blind eye to misbehavior like public drinking.</p>
        <p>''They were in a stand-down posture,'' said Mr. Duhamel, a former assistant United States attorney. ''From South Drive to 110th Street, it was the same posture, depending on your perspective, either cavalier or casual.''</p>
        <p>Police Commissioner Howard Safir has said no one was given orders to look the other way on any illegal activity at the parade. Asked if it were possible that some officers did not act because they were concerned about being accused of racial insensitivity, Mr. Safir said: ''That is always a possibility. With all of the hyperbole that has gone on over the years, certainly that could be in the police officer's mind.''</p>
        <p>Many officers, including those who acknowledged lapses in police tactics last weekend, said they felt stung by the speed with which, in the eyes of their critics, they have gone from overaggressive to indifferent.</p>
        <p>''Now we go to a parade and the criticism is that they did not enforce the law strictly enough,'' a senior police supervisor said. ''I think they would like to know what the plan is.''</p>
        <p>The aggressiveness of police enforcement efforts has been a source of debate for several years, in large part because city officials have credited their focus on quality-of-life offenses and their use of proactive patrol strategies as having been central to the city's dramatic reduction in crime.</p>
        <p>More recently, however, experts like former Police Commissioner William J. Bratton have questioned whether the city's approach, which he helped fashion at a time of high crime, is outdated, even counterproductive at a time when the murder rate has declined by two-thirds.</p>
        <p>The debate grew particularly heated after the police shooting last year of Amadou Diallo, when many critics questioned whether the seeds of the tragedy had been planted in an enforcement strategy they characterized as overzealous. In the weeks following that shooting, as the public outcry grew, police officials said many officers demoralized by the withering criticism were no longer patrolling as aggressively and cited this as a leading factor in the rising murder rate.</p>
        <p>But several months later, officials said that morale had improved and that enforcement efforts, particularly seizures of illegal guns, were returning to previous levels. Earlier this year, the scrutiny of police enforcement tactics returned with a vengeance when an undercover narcotics officer, pushing to make drug arrests in Midtown Manhattan, ended up in a dispute with Patrick Dorismond, a man who had objected to being solicited for drugs. Mr. Dorismond was fatally shot in an incident that is still being investigated by a grand jury.</p>
        <p>In the aftermath of that shooting, many public officials questioned whether patrol strategies had become too confrontational and their targets too trivial. But the furor had died down in recent weeks, especially after Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani bowed out of the race for the United States Senate. Some people inside and outside Police Headquarters say the pressure that officers felt to produce ever-declining crime rates has waned in tandem with Mr. Giuliani's political ambitions.</p>
        <p>The Police Department denies that there has been any change in policy or any relaxation in enforcement. A police union official, Sgt. Bernard Pound, the president of the Sergeants Benevolent Association, said he agreed. ''I get no sense that cops are doing anything other than what comes naturally to them,'' he said. ''If they see something wrong, they are righting it.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, several commanders said they had overheard the talk in the locker rooms and muster rooms of the city's station houses about whether a department that has been under great pressure to produce for several years may now get a chance to catch its breath.</p>
        <p>''I have heard this ever since Rudy stopped running,'' said one investigative supervisor from Brooklyn. ''People on the job will say, 'Now maybe things will calm down a bit.' But that is just the lazy people who are looking for an excuse. It goes back to being a professional.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
