<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Camilla Journal; New Role for the Gator: Chicken Farmer's Friend</title>
    <meta content="18GATO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208490"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poultry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alligators</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Camilla (Ga)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glass, Mark A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reptiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poultry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6DE1431F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Camilla Journal; New Role for the Gator: Chicken Farmer's Friend</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>CAMILLA, Ga., June 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark A Glass, who has flock of 500,000 chickens on farm in Camilla, Ga, has found novel way to dispose of the 5 percent of his flock that can be expected to die for variety of reasons; he feeds dead chickens to alligators he keeps in separate gator pens; Glass is now one of largest alligator farmers in Georgia, with 6,500 alligators; when they get too big he kills them and sells their hides; his calls his process purest form of recycling; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ah, American ingenuity. See a need? Find a way to fill it. Got a problem? Find a way to fix it. And if you can make a buck in the process, all the better.</p>
        <p>Mark A. Glass had a problem. A product of the Atlanta suburbs and a graduate of Georgia Tech, he moved in 1993 to his wife's hometown in southwest Georgia, bought a farm and decided to raise chickens. It was a business he knew little about, but he had drive and ambition and an entrepreneurial streak.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ah, American ingenuity. See a need? Find a way to fill it. Got a problem? Find a way to fix it. And if you can make a buck in the process, all the better.</p>
        <p>Mark A. Glass had a problem. A product of the Atlanta suburbs and a graduate of Georgia Tech, he moved in 1993 to his wife's hometown in southwest Georgia, bought a farm and decided to raise chickens. It was a business he knew little about, but he had drive and ambition and an entrepreneurial streak.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Glass had not realized, though, was that about 5 percent of his 500,000 birds would succumb to heat, injury or disease before they could be processed into Chicken McNuggets at a nearby plant. And the dead chickens, sometimes enough to fill the bed of his pickup four times over, had to be disposed of each day. Many farmers simply buried their dead in pits. Some tried composting, and then spread the chicken mulch over their fields. Mr. Glass chose to incinerate his chickens in a metal furnace, but soon found he was spending $5,000 to $10,000 a year on propane.</p>
        <p>''The volume of dead birds was overwhelming,'' said the 32-year-old Mr. Glass, blowing a swarm of gnats out of his face. ''It just took an incredible amount of money to burn them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Glass discussed his problem with a University of Georgia extension agent, and the agent suggested an unusual disposal method being pioneered by Gene Frazier, a poultry farmer in nearby Americus, Ga. Mr. Glass did some research and decided to give it a try. And that is why Mark Glass is up to his shins in alligators.</p>
        <p>It is, he says, the purest form of recycling. Each day, his farmhands collect the dead from his 20 chicken houses. They toss the birds -- feathers, beaks and all -- into a tractor-powered grinder that quickly reduces the chicken into a white, pasty slop. It is gathered in buckets and taken to the three low-lying buildings where Mr. Glass now raises 6,500 alligators.</p>
        <p>Wearing shorts and rubber boots, Mr. Glass and his workers then climb through wooden hatches into the 20 foul smelling gator pens in each of the buildings. As they open the doors and sunlight floods into the darkened rooms, the gators, startled, slap the foot-deep water with their tails and scramble into far corners. The reptiles, some of them as much as five feet long, largely avoid the workers as they pour the gruel onto platforms suspended just above the surface of the water. And then it is dinner time, as the alligators slide atop the platforms, grab a mouthful of mush and retreat politely to enjoy their meals.</p>
        <p>After five years, Mr. Glass is now one of the largest alligator farmers in Georgia, and one of 10 in the state who are exploring the synergies of raising chickens beside gators. Officials with various poultry associations said that there might be a few such operations in other states but that Georgia, which calls itself the largest chicken-producing state, seemed to be the epicenter of experimentation.</p>
        <p>When the alligators reach a length of four or five feet, usually after about two years, Mr. Glass harvests them. He and his workers wade into the pens, catching gators with their bare hands. Once they remove the alligators from the pens, they strap their jaws shut with a strip of black electrical tape, kill the animals swiftly by hammering a steel blade into their spinal cords, slice off the hides and carve off the meat.</p>
        <p>If the hide has not been marred by scratches or bite marks, it may bring $75 in Italy or some other overseas market where alligator is used for belts, purses and shoes. The meat may bring an additional $20 regionally. The heads are sold to a taxidermist for $1 apiece.</p>
        <p>At first, Mr. Glass said, he ''figured that if I could break even and get rid of my chickens I'd be ahead of the game.'' But in fact he has had to invest hundreds of thousands of dollars in the construction and maintenance of his alligator pens, and he has struggled to break even. He expects to turn a profit in the next two years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Glass said he had made plenty of costly mistakes before finding the right method. At first he tried raising the alligators in a pond. But he soon discovered they were susceptible to scratches and bite marks, which devalued their hides. He also learned that they hibernated when air and water temperatures dropped, and showed little interest in helping him dispose of his chickens. In his indoor pens, the air and water are artificially heated. ''Trial and error,'' Mr. Glass observed, ''is a very expensive way to learn.''</p>
        <p>There are also occupational hazards, of course. ''If you catch enough alligators, you're going to get bit,'' said Mr. Glass, who has been nipped and has watched two workers suffer more serious injuries. ''It kind of goes with the territory. And what's worse than the bite is the infection that comes afterward, because their teeth are so nasty. We peel open the wound and just pour the Clorox in.''</p>
        <p>His own alligator bite did not break his skin, but it scared him nonetheless. ''I had one by the tail and his head was underwater and he just bent in half and grabbed my finger,'' Mr. Glass said. ''He let go, but if he had locked his jaws he'd have had me. Basically, you've just got to be faster than they are.''</p>
        <p>As might be expected, the working conditions tend to make hiring a challenge. ''It makes it harder to find employees,'' Mr. Glass explained, ''when you have to ask, 'Are you afraid of alligators?' in the interview process.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
