<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marriage Insurance for the Young</title>
    <meta content="18PREL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208389"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRELUDES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prenuptial Agreements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ellin, Abby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Preludes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E7DE1631F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marriage Insurance for the Young</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY ELLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ellin, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Abby Ellin Preludes column notes more young couples are signing prenuptial agreements, a trend that reflects their improved economic standing and greater objectivity regarding the prospects of divorce; notes prenuptial contracts had been more common among older couples on their second or third marriages, while younger couples started out with nothing much to protect; observes prenuptial agreements can still be point of contention with couples; often monied spouse wants one, while the other spouse does not; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HERE is a happy thought during this month of matrimony, this saison d'amour: Of the nearly 230,000 marriages that begin in June, more than half will end in divorce, and of those, about 60,000 will involve heated legal battles.</p>
        <p>Young adults, of course, account for the bulk of the people making trip No. 1 to the altar: in 1998, the average bride was 25 years old, the average groom 26.7.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HERE is a happy thought during this month of matrimony, this saison d'amour: Of the nearly 230,000 marriages that begin in June, more than half will end in divorce, and of those, about 60,000 will involve heated legal battles.</p>
        <p>Young adults, of course, account for the bulk of the people making trip No. 1 to the altar: in 1998, the average bride was 25 years old, the average groom 26.7.</p>
        <p>The good news is that young people today -- some of whom, as we have heard ad nauseum, are worth millions -- know full well the connubial risks. To combat them, they seek preventive medicine in the form of prenuptial agreements.</p>
        <p>''I see lots of kids,'' said Raoul Felder, a divorce lawyer, who writes 150 to 200 prenuptial contracts a year, 70 percent of them for people under 35 -- up from 20 percent just four years ago. In the past, he said, most of the clients were on their second or third marriages -- jaded, older and presumably wiser. Not these days.</p>
        <p>''What used to happen is that people would start out with nothing but a big bag of hopes, so they didn't need a prenup,'' Mr. Felder said from his Manhattan office. ''But young kids today have economic clout. Marriage is usually thought of as a disease of the young, and money is flowing into young people as it never has before, so they want to protect what they have.</p>
        <p>''One kid came in wearing sneakers,'' he said. ''I thought he was the delivery boy. He didn't have much money, but he had these options worth $12 million.''</p>
        <p>Prenuptial agreements have grown in specificity. Once they mainly protected an inheritance, ''but now you can protect everything -- business, homes, how much child support there will be,'' said Seymour J. Reisman, a divorce lawyer with Reisman, Peirez &amp; Reisman in Garden City, N.Y., who also sees many young clients. ''There are a lot of different choices for people to make.'' And waltzing down an aisle need not be one of them: many lawyers write these agreements for unmarried people who live together.</p>
        <p>Kalman C. Sporn runs a New York Internet management company with his name on the door. He is 29, worth in the low single millions, presently unmarried and completely pro-prenup. Many of his clients in the dot-com world have them, and he would insist that any spouse of his sign one. ''You look at the people who were in love and are now divorced, and you realize that so many had hidden agendas,'' he said. ''I'm a purist. I believe a couple should share everything. But a part of me is distrustful: I want to know I'm protected if something goes wrong.''</p>
        <p>Of course, there is still a stigma attached to the little document, which typically costs from $500 to $1,000. Plenty of people hesitate to acknowledge marrying for any reason but dewy-eyed wonder -- or that their assets might mean more than their mates. ''Usually the moneyed spouse wants to sign and the other doesn't,'' said Mr. Reisman, who has seen couples split up over the terms.</p>
        <p>Some people attribute the rise in prenuptial agreements among the dot-com set to youthful anxiety in an uncertain economy.</p>
        <p>''The prenup is just another way of young kids' pumping up their ego or being underconfident about what their real abilities are,'' said Avi Moskowitz, 36, chief executive of Virtual Communities, which builds online portals. ''No one's seen these Internet companies exist for more than three or four years, so no one knows what's going to happen.''</p>
        <p>This week, Mr. Moskowitz will celebrate his 14th wedding anniversary. He says he understands why some people might want a prenuptial agreement as a safety net, but he and his wife and business partner, Helen Moskowitz, do not have one. ''A prenup essentially says we may stay together, but we may also carve out some things that are yours and some that are mine, which overemphasizes the material aspects of the relationship,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He is right. Ideally, anyway, we should all say ''I do'' with the proper amount of optimism and hope; we shouldn't worry in advance about who'll get the stock options, the Lexus or the 'N Sync CD's. We should plan for the best -- or at least learn to part amicably without needing written instructions.</p>
        <p>Or maybe, as Mr. Felder suggests, society needs to rethink the matrimonial institution. ''There never was an instrument people would buy if it only worked half the time,'' he said. ''Yet people are getting married knowing there's a failure rate of 50 percent. It's truly amazing.''</p>
        <p>PRELUDES Abby Ellin is a Manhattan writer. Her column on starting out in the world of money appears the third Sunday of each month. E-mail: preludes@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Abby Ellin is a Manhattan writer. Her column on starting out in the world of money appears the third Sunday of each month. E-mail: preludes@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
