<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Can (and Did) Go Wrong on Concert Stage</title>
    <meta content="18MUSI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208275"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kandell, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE7DF1E3EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Can (and Did) Go Wrong on Concert Stage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KANDELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kandell, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leslie Kandell recounts what went wrong during recently concluded New Jersey classical music season (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LOOKING back at the classical music season, it becomes clear that New Jersey and New York energize each other's concert scenes -- sometimes by tripping each other up. Concerts can be exciting beyond their musical programs: sheer quantity of offerings exposes them to those mischances pretentiously called acts of God.</p>
        <p>These trip-ups fall into categories: unavoidable, avoidable and so untidy that it's fruitless to place blame. Take last spring's Rouse muddle -- category three.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LOOKING back at the classical music season, it becomes clear that New Jersey and New York energize each other's concert scenes -- sometimes by tripping each other up. Concerts can be exciting beyond their musical programs: sheer quantity of offerings exposes them to those mischances pretentiously called acts of God.</p>
        <p>These trip-ups fall into categories: unavoidable, avoidable and so untidy that it's fruitless to place blame. Take last spring's Rouse muddle -- category three.</p>
        <p>Zdenek Macal, the director of the New Jersey Symphony Orchestra, scheduled Christopher Rouse's memorial-mode Second Symphony to precede the premiere of his concerto ''Seeing'' at the New York Philharmonic. Mr. Rouse is one of the few composers who has won a Pulitzer Prize and then gone on to become better known, and concertgoers had a chance to consider his work in an evolving context.</p>
        <p>But a power outage caused chaos at the New Jersey Performing Arts Center ticket booth -- that sort of thing makes for a frustrated audience. Added to that, rain plus President Clinton's visit to Manhattan caused a traffic jam in the Lincoln Tunnel. Orchestra members who got out of the tunnel slipped onstage after the performance had begun, but Mr. Macal arrived too late to conduct the difficult piece.</p>
        <p>David Commanday, the assistant conductor, took the baton and reportedly did a creditable job, but couldn't capture the spirit that first enticed Mr. Macal. Unfairly to composer and audience, most listeners new to Rouse didn't like it, or worse, concluded that contemporary music isn't worth getting their shoes wet.</p>
        <p>Renee Fleming's recent recital fell into mishap category two, avoidable. The celebrated soprano sang only brand-new works -- a laudable mission. But it didn't meet the audience need for something familiar, if only to prove that one day, the program would sound equally familiar to future audiences. People were complaining, and leaving early.</p>
        <p>''Recitals and orchestra programs are not questions of a Chinese menu,'' said Bill Lockwood, McCarter Theater's special programming director and the Arts Center's principal programming associate. ''It's their decision. Sometimes it's a choice of program A or program B. With the Boston Symphony Orchestra, never -- inevitably it's in Carnegie Hall the two preceding evenings. With soloists it's totally their call -- it's a bit of a crapshoot. If someone happens to plan all Beethoven in 2002, after you've booked them, that's what you get.''</p>
        <p>The situation could have been remedied somewhat by simply rearranging the songs. Ms. Fleming might have moved her Ellington encore to before intermission, or else to end, and left out the Andre Previn encore, since he was represented earlier. New Jersey listeners seem blessed with extraordinary goodwill, but after that program, they craved the encore comforts of ''Ave Maria'' or ''An Die Musik'' -- not more Previn. However, Mr. Previn, the well-known conductor who composes for her, was at the piano.</p>
        <p>''If Renee Fleming wants to do an all-American new generation program,'' Mr. Lockwood said, ''she chooses. For anyone who wants to come in advance, that's the chance they take. In contrast to what the audience might expect, this soloist chose a non-traditional approach.''</p>
        <p>Category three, the unavoidable, happens when illness forces a performer to cancel. True, there can be rewards, as demonstrated by famous step-ins like Andre Watts and Jane Eaglen, but it's a hectic and scary moment. When Krystian Zimerman was ill for performances of Rachmaninoff's Second Concerto under Seiji Ozawa, the Boston Symphony Orchestra asked the Brazilian pianist Nelson Freire to substitute.</p>
        <p>Mr. Freire is a marvelous pianist, and by the time the rocky show made it to the Arts Center, it had come together somewhat, but Boston and New York concerts were hampered by the conductor's inflexibly different view of the piece, which rattled the shy pianist.</p>
        <p>Why hire a soloist and not give him artistic privilege? Because last summer he had played a riveting Chopin concerto with the Boston at Tanglewood, and was then invited by Martha Argerich to join her wildly hailed Carnegie Hall recital.</p>
        <p>Further sleuthing, however, shows that at Tanglewood he had performed under Charles Dutoit, former husband of his old friend and fellow South American Ms. Argerich, who has the same management. Herself a frequent performer with Mr. Dutoit, she obviously adores Mr. Freire, who would have a good Dutoit connection.</p>
        <p>He had not previously worked with Mr. Ozawa, who was unwilling or unable to to follow the concept, so they did their uneven best. The Newark Star-Ledger reported Mr. Freire's ''uncommonly crystalline view of the music's interior,'' and said ''Ozawa's approach, unfortunately, did not completely follow suit.''</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Lockwood, ''Sometimes expectations are fulfilled -- I like to think more often than not.'' One can seldom predict illness or power failures, but looking ahead to next year's programs, he said, ''If we announce a Penderecki concerto and a Schnittke symphony, they won't expect the Brahms First. We do make it pretty clear. If the palette is broad enough, that's part of the challenge.''</p>
        <p>Next year the Arts Center is to present a new violin concerto by Mr. Rouse. It's like a second chance.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
