<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>West Nile Virus Spraying May Aid Mosquito-Bitten Area</title>
    <meta content="18MOSQ$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: ARVERNE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Day, Sherri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E4D91F3EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="543" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>West Nile Virus Spraying May Aid Mosquito-Bitten Area</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERRI DAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Day, Sherri</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents of Arverne section of Queens, long plagued by mosquito problem, laud actions by New York City in spraying against West Nile Virus; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No matter how hot it gets in the summer, Monique Hough wears her coat when she walks her dog. Evan D. Gray rarely wears shorts, and Patricia Jordan ends her outdoor barbecuing on Memorial Day.</p>
        <p>In the Arverne neighborhood, ''people have a culture of their own, born out of the mosquito population,'' said Sarah Colson, a member of the Arverne Civic Association. ''For the past 10 to 12 years, we've really been like prisoners in our own homes. We're not able to go outside at all without being bitten by mosquitoes.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No matter how hot it gets in the summer, Monique Hough wears her coat when she walks her dog. Evan D. Gray rarely wears shorts, and Patricia Jordan ends her outdoor barbecuing on Memorial Day.</p>
        <p>In the Arverne neighborhood, ''people have a culture of their own, born out of the mosquito population,'' said Sarah Colson, a member of the Arverne Civic Association. ''For the past 10 to 12 years, we've really been like prisoners in our own homes. We're not able to go outside at all without being bitten by mosquitoes.''</p>
        <p>But while the mosquitoes are not new, residents say getting help from the city is.</p>
        <p>''I think if those people had not gotten killed last year, we would not have gotten anything done,'' said Gloria Muir, referring to the seven people in the New York region who died after being bitten by mosquitoes carrying the West Nile virus. ''We've been fighting this for years.''</p>
        <p>Sandra Mullin, a spokeswoman for the Health Department, agreed. ''We certainly receive more complaints from residents there than any other part of the city,'' she said. ''In some ways, the Rockaways will certainly now benefit from a much more stepped-up mosquito control program throughout the city.''</p>
        <p>But there's a twist. While the Rockaways are home to mosquitoes that breed in both salt and fresh water, it is the saltwater mosquito that is the residents' chief nemesis. The saltwater types fly farther than the freshwater ones, travel in swarms and bite 24 hours a day, not just at night. However, unlike the infamous Culex pipiens, a freshwater mosquito, saltwater mosquitoes are not known to carry the West Nile virus or other diseases.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, as part of its efforts to stem the virus, the Health Department is trapping and testing adult mosquitoes in the Rockaways, putting larvicide in standing water, where mosquitoes breed, and encouraging residents to empty containers of water. Dr. Jim Miller, who heads the Health Department's surveillance and mosquito control unit, said the city could do more if the federal government would allow it.  Much of the breeding area for saltwater mosquitoes is in the Gateway National Recreation Area, which the National Parks Service oversees. Dr. Miller said the Parks Service has barred the city from using larvicide within the park.</p>
        <p>''We only work to eradicate pests when they become a health hazard,'' said Brian Feeney, a spokesman for the National Parks Service. ''We just don't disturb the natural ecosystem because something is a pest.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Feeney said the service is working to eradicate Culex pipiens throughout the federal park.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Monique Hough is questioning her decision to buy a home in the Arverne area four years ago.</p>
        <p>''If I'd known there were that many mosquitoes,'' she said, ''I probably would not have purchased that home.''</p>
        <p>SHERRI DAY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: ARVERNE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
