<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Perspective; The Good, the Bad and the Distracting: Life Off the Football Field</title>
    <meta content="18ROUN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cross, Howard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garnes, Sam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Comella, Greg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toomer, Amani</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barber, Tiki</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Ray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carruth, Rae</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chmura, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E3D81731F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3306" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Perspective; The Good, the Bad and the Distracting: Life Off the Football Field</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with five players from New York Giants--Howard Cross, Sam Garnes, Greg Comella, Amani Toomer, Tiki Barber; players discuss criminal charges against Ray Lewis, Rae Carruth and Mark Chmura and attendant media coverage; assert that professional athletes are held to higher standard of behavior than ordinary people; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Instead of draft picks and free-agent signings, much of the news of professional football this off-season has involved prosecutors, indictments and trials. For the first time, two active National Football League players were accused of murder. Another was charged with sexually assaulting a 17-year-old baby sitter.</p>
        <p>With the new season looming-training camps open next month -- The New York Times invited five members of the Giants to participate in a round-table discussion with Thomas George, a reporter who covers pro football, and other sports reporters and editors. Tiki Barber, Greg Comella, Howard Cross, Sam Garnes and Amani Toomer spoke last week for more than an hour about many issues, both off the field and on the field. Here are excerpts of their remarks, in the first of two articles.</p>
        <p>Q. What did you think of the coverage in the news media of the murder charge against Rae Carruth, the murder trial of Ray Lewis and the charges of sexual assault filed against Mark Chmura?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Instead of draft picks and free-agent signings, much of the news of professional football this off-season has involved prosecutors, indictments and trials. For the first time, two active National Football League players were accused of murder. Another was charged with sexually assaulting a 17-year-old baby sitter.</p>
        <p>With the new season looming-training camps open next month -- The New York Times invited five members of the Giants to participate in a round-table discussion with Thomas George, a reporter who covers pro football, and other sports reporters and editors. Tiki Barber, Greg Comella, Howard Cross, Sam Garnes and Amani Toomer spoke last week for more than an hour about many issues, both off the field and on the field. Here are excerpts of their remarks, in the first of two articles.</p>
        <p>Q. What did you think of the coverage in the news media of the murder charge against Rae Carruth, the murder trial of Ray Lewis and the charges of sexual assault filed against Mark Chmura?</p>
        <p>HOWARD CROSS -- I think, first of all, that back in the old days when players were doing something, they would be famous and it didn't matter what they did. Now that we have such high standards -- quote, unquote -- that if we do anything wrong, it's in the news. Now, these guys got caught in bad situations or did whatever they did wrong and the media covered it. But it doesn't make us any different than anybody else.</p>
        <p>Because if I get stopped in a D.U.I. [driving under the influence], it's on ESPN. If I go to a bar and some guy has too much to drink and wants to fight me and I defend myself, not only am I on ESPN, but I'm also in jail, probably. I'm getting sued by the guy. If the guy beats me up, I get sued and beat up. So I got a lot going on there. We do live normal lives like everybody else and we do live our lives to a higher standard, or most of us try to. There's a lot fewer of us making mistakes than the others. And as for the coverage, if it was the I.R.S. and they had the chance between getting you and getting me, they're going to get me. That's just the way it works.</p>
        <p>GREG COMELLA -- I think we as athletes do have a responsibility first of all to ourselves and to our families, and along with that, to our teammates, to our coaches, to the organizations we represent, to society, because whether we like it or not, you know, people do look up to us. But at the same time, I think professional athletes probably get into trouble no more or no less than the average person working at Microsoft or working at The New York Times, for that matter. The difference is when I make a mistake, it's going to be in the paper.</p>
        <p>TIKI BARBER -- People don't look to find the truth. They just look to put the story out there and whatever spin they feel is going to be more attractive. The prosecutor in the Ray Lewis case, he charged Ray Lewis because he felt like it was going to be something that was going to be big. He didn't get the facts. He wasn't looking for the truth. He was just looking to charge Ray Lewis.</p>
        <p>Most media outlets, when they first ran this story, it was Ray Lewis is charged with murder. It wasn't that Ray Lewis may not have been involved at all. Later down the road, that comes out. But initially it's always the thing that's going to get the most impact. It's always going to be the thing that sells papers. It's always going to be the thing that draws attention to the prosecutor. And it's not necessarily the truth. That's unfortunate, but that's just the way society is. I mean, you'd much rather hear bad news than good news.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- And the funny thing is that Ray Lewis went through this whole trial and they got him in jail and got him on TV and he even pleads, says that he did some misdemeanor. Then the guys that were accused of murder got off. Now Ray has to do community service. He testifies, his friends get off and he's doing community service. It's not right. But that's the way it works.</p>
        <p>COMELLA -- Probably the first thing that comes to all our heads, or at least it should, is, you know, it's obviously sad events for the victims in this one, and sometimes that gets overlooked. Sometimes we become numb to it, because you see it so much on television, you see it in the newspapers, but when something hits home, if you see a family member or a friend that's been through something like that, certainly your heart goes out to the family that has something tragic like that happen in their lives.</p>
        <p>Q. How do you respond when a teammate gets involved in a situation at a bar or in a domestic problem that becomes public?</p>
        <p>AMANI TOOMER -- When I see a story about one of the N.F.L. players getting involved, I may be skeptical, but I always think that the media blows it up somehow. A month later you'll see the headlines, the guy doesn't have anything to do with it. So I usually try to wait and hold my judgment till after I get more facts.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- For our team, we're here talking to a person every day. It's like, everything O.K.? Yeah, everything's all right, man, thanks for asking. We go on with our lives. We've got to. The only distraction maybe is for the player after practice when there's a thousand cameras there and when people have their mikes up there and they're like, well, did you do it or didn't you do it? And that's bad for the player, we feel bad for him, but you have to keep going.</p>
        <p>Q. Are you concerned that people may perceive you differently because of the notorious cases over the last seven or eight months involving N.F.L. players?</p>
        <p>SAM GARNES -- I'm from the Bronx. I hang out with some of my friends, just the typical guys that you might think look like troublemakers, but we're just regular guys and we're not going to change just because I'm in the N.F.L. I've been a good person up to now, and I'm not going to change the way I dress or what kind of car I have just because I'm in the N.F.L.</p>
        <p>And you know, you don't see or hear about how he's got foundations or we're giving up our tight-scheduled time to go talk to kids. But as soon as we make a slight mistake, you know somebody might go out to a bar, might be having dinner, have a couple of drinks, been there a little longer than expected, have four, five drinks. Made a mistake.</p>
        <p>It's no good to drink and drive because a lot of things come from it, but they made a mistake. And as soon as they get pulled over, it's in the paper even though there wasn't any violation. Notice they didn't get into trouble, get into accidents or anything like that. It's in the paper and we're a bad guy. That's all you remember, that one pullover by the police.</p>
        <p>I take up my time and I love the kids. Just because I make a mistake doesn't mean I don't love doing the right thing. I just made a mistake just like any human being. That bothers me a lot, personally.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- We don't want any awards or anything.</p>
        <p>GARNES -- No, we don't want any awards.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- But we're doing it because we're trying to give back to the community and everything. And I don't need the press there.</p>
        <p>GARNES -- Definitely.</p>
        <p>COMELLA -- What amazed me is, when Derrick Thomas passed away last winter, it took an event like that, a death, for all those wonderful news reports about the type of person he was. It's just sad that you don't see more reports about the type of individuals some of these guys are, like a Derrick Thomas, that it has to take such a tragic event like that for that stuff to come out.</p>
        <p>Q. Sam, you mentioned that you hang out with your friends. Acquaintances, entourages, hangers-on, that's become part of the problem now?</p>
        <p>GARNES -- Not really. I don't think so. I mean, my friends aren't troublemakers.</p>
        <p>Q. No, no. Not you, but in general. That's what people were saying about Ray Lewis, that he was hanging out with the wrong crowd.</p>
        <p>GARNES -- Like I said, I'm from the Bronx, so you know there's a lot of things going on in the Bronx, and I know I had to cut certain people off. They're still my friends, but they respect the fact that I can't be around that. I think you have to make choices on your own, who you hang out with, because they could do something -- I mean, they might not even want you involved in what they're doing -- but if you go out with them and they get in some trouble, they're going to say, well, Sam Garnes was there also. And that's going to sell newspapers, like Tiki said.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you think that now you have to be more careful?</p>
        <p>BARBER -- I think guys take the responsibility that they have to be careful as soon as they get into the professional ranks. You know, people think they don't have to be role models all the time, but we are role models, whether we like it or not. Kids are going to look up to you. I believe it should be the parents' job to say -- O.K., say I'm a good role model, a parent should say, O.K., Tiki does the right things. But say you have someone who gets in trouble all the time, he should be able to say, well, this guy isn't doing the right things. Compare and contrast, don't just let the kid decide, because sometimes he'll think that the guy who's doing the bad is the cool guy.</p>
        <p>But as far as hanging out with your friends, you don't want to cut them off, because these are the guys, when you were nobody, when you were growing up, these were your friends. They supported you. That's when you build most of your friendships that you're going to have for the rest of your life. And sometimes it's hard to cut that off. But you have to when you're a professional athlete, because things are different, times change. It's not the same. Even though guys would like it to be, it's not.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you think pro athletes are held to an unfair standard?</p>
        <p>CROSS -- Yes.</p>
        <p>BARBER -- Oh, without a doubt. I think athletes are held to the standard of society is great, so they should be great. We're not all great. We're not always doing the right things. Sometimes we do falter and take bad steps.</p>
        <p>COMELLA -- I don't think that we are held to too high of a standard. I think we've been given a lot of opportunities. I think we've had chances to do things that 99 percent of this country never even conceives, never thinks about. So is the standard that we're held to different? Absolutely.</p>
        <p>BARBER -- Well, doesn't different mean higher?</p>
        <p>COMELLA -- Yeah, it may be higher, but what I think is, we're given a lot.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- Blessed a lot so you're required to do a lot.</p>
        <p>COMELLA -- That's what I believe.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- See, the problem is not that we're held to a higher standard, which we are. It's just that it is unfair. Because everybody puts you, like, O.K., you have made it. Blessed with skills, whether it's speed or height or strength or whatever. I didn't ask to be 6-6 and 270. I didn't ask for that. And thank God for it. I didn't even want to be a football player. I thought I was going to be in the N.B.A. It didn't work out that way.</p>
        <p>And I get a higher standard. When I go out I'm really nice to kids. I'm really nice to people that come up and speak to me, even when they're rude. I've had guys step up and, ''Excuse me, miss,'' put their hand on my wife and move her out of the way just so they can talk to me. And she's like, ''Are you kidding me?'' And I'm like, ''Honey, don't hit him.''</p>
        <p>COMELLA -- I think the standard is such because people look at us and very much admire what it is we're doing.</p>
        <p>BARBER -- You know what it is, it's a dream. When you're a little kid you dream to be a professional athlete. And now that we're professional athletes people think that our lives are a dream. How would you dream the perfect life? I want to be a professional basketball player, have a big Mercedes, a big house and live a perfect life.</p>
        <p>Q. So you think it's the money?</p>
        <p>BARBER -- No, it has nothing to do with the money. It's just the dream. Athletes aren't the only dreams now. Bill Gates is a dream now for kids. Times have changed, society has changed.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you think that the kids see you as any less of an idol or role model than kids did when Y. A. Tittle was playing?</p>
        <p>BARBER -- I don't think so. They have more role models now, not just athletes. It's transcended into other sectors of life, which I think is a good thing. But I also think it's a bad thing. They get caught up in not experiencing life fully.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- We've got a society of people that want to see gore, right? Like movies with blood and gore, everybody runs to the theater to see people get shot up. When there's an accident on the highway, almost every car stops and looks over. We are held to a higher standard, because our society decides we like to see blood and gore. You guys better be good or else we're going to tell on you.</p>
        <p>TOOMER -- I think some of it has to do with the fact that they want to set you up to be kind of a star and then they want to know the dirt behind you. They want to know the faults of everybody. They just don't want to see somebody up there who has no faults. They kind of get bored with that. They want to know the person more than just the good things they do. They want to know what are the faults, what are his weaknesses.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- They don't want you to be perfect. Like how many of you guys, in all honesty, when you watched the U.S. Open last year and John Daly took that 11 on that hole, how many of you were like, oh, yeah, I could do that. He kept hitting the ball, hitting the ball. He took an 11 on the hole, everybody's done it. But John Daly, now, he's a pro, he shouldn't do that. But it was something you wanted to see.</p>
        <p>Q. Some people have said that some football players have a hard time leaving the violence on the field. Is it difficult to be asked to be violent on the field and then to be model citizens when you walk off it?</p>
        <p>CROSS -- You're Christmas shopping or whatever, you're going to the mall. Somebody accidentally cuts you off. What do you do?</p>
        <p>Q. I'm pretty meek about it usually.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- Ma'am, what about you?</p>
        <p>Q. I go nuts.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- Exactly. You're human. I've seen people in the car, like ladies, will just give me the finger. What are you doing? But if an athlete does it, we can't separate our two worlds. So I want to know what's the difference between a lady having road rage, and a man getting upset at another man and one of the men happens to be an athlete?</p>
        <p>COMELLA -- The thing is, that's who we are, we're football players. And the bottom line is on the football field we are positively reinforced the more we destroy. That's the nature of the game.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- It's not close to that, Greg. You're making it sound like that. When we're playing football, Greg has a play, the draw. The fullback leads up on the linebacker. They're running at each other. Linebacker's got to fill a hole; Greg's got to knock him out of the hole.</p>
        <p>That's a violent play to you guys. To Greg, it's just doing his job. That's not like a really violent thing, that's just Greg doing his job. The linebacker's doing his job.</p>
        <p>When Greg gets in his car to go home that day, somebody cuts him off and he yells at him, he's not taking his job off the field. He didn't take his car and ram it into the guy. His insurance wouldn't pay, he'd lose his insurance. Instead, he just keeps going.</p>
        <p>TOOMER -- I don't know. I think what he's talking about is not just those type of incidents. I'm talking about if you go to a club and then somebody touches you or grabs you or something like that, then I can understand his question.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- Physically, I'm a meek person, I wouldn't fight for nothing. But if you put your hands on me, I've got to defend myself. I'm not going to let you hurt me.</p>
        <p>Q. Let's talk a little about entitlement, which is the flip side of being held to a higher standard. By the time you get to be an all-American, there are people who ordinarily would not give you the time of day who suddenly want to know you. The answers become yes, instead of no.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- You get a lot more of that than anything else. You get that celebrity status and people do know you and people are offering you meals and cutting you into the front of the line. For every one of those that happens, there's another group of people that are like, ''Oh, he doesn't deserve anything.'' There are some places still in Alabama -- ''Hey, that's Howard Cross from the Giants. He played for Alabama. That's a black guy, man.'' You're still black. I didn't do anything special.</p>
        <p>GARNES -- You get more good things from being an athlete, being a professional football player. But it's just that when that one thing happens that's negative, that's how everybody views you from then on.</p>
        <p>(Tomorrow: the Giants talk about the coming season.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
