<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shaking Things Up in Japan Inc.</title>
    <meta content="18PROF$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208392"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRIVATE SECTOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Business and Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Tatsuyuki Saeki</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nasdaq Japan</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Assn of Securities Dealers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myerson, Allen R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saeki, Tatsuyuki</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DE1631F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1113" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shaking Things Up in Japan Inc.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Tatsuyuk Saeki, president and chief executive of Nasdaq Japan, National Assn of Securities Dealers' biggest effort so far to go global; Nasdaq Japan, which begins trading June 19, will cater to small companies that would otherwise be unable to find funding in Japan's clubby, hidebound and heavily bureaucratized financial system; Saeki intends Nasdaq Japan to radically overhaul Japanese capital market and initiate revolution in the way Japan Inc functions, breaking up cozy relationship between government, banks and industry; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEE this guy?'' asks Tatsuyuki Saeki, pointing to a painting of a pastel-clad matador skewering a bull. ''That's me.''</p>
        <p>The painting hangs incongruously in his sleek mahogany and black leather office. As for the bull -- his finger jabs it -- ''that's the Japanese financial system.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEE this guy?'' asks Tatsuyuki Saeki, pointing to a painting of a pastel-clad matador skewering a bull. ''That's me.''</p>
        <p>The painting hangs incongruously in his sleek mahogany and black leather office. As for the bull -- his finger jabs it -- ''that's the Japanese financial system.''</p>
        <p>A former senior executive at I.B.M. Japan, the voluble Mr. Saeki, 59 and known as Ted, now finds himself on the attack as the president and chief executive of Nasdaq Japan, which opens for trading on Monday. It is the National Association of Securities Dealers' biggest effort so far to go global, steering through one of the most hidebound, idiosyncratic and bureaucratic financial systems in the world.</p>
        <p>If successful, he will have radically overhauled the capital markets here and, in the process,  started nothing short of a revolution in the way Japan Inc. functions.</p>
        <p>In the past, business success depended as much on cultivating bureaucrats and bankers as on a competitive edge. Acting on government orders, bankers funneled money to the enterprises deemed crucial to Japan's recovery after World War II. Japan's  leviathans -- its Toyotas, Sonys and Hitachis -- thrived, but untold others found it impossible to get financing.</p>
        <p>Nasdaq Japan is seeking to change that. Young companies will be able to raise financing. Established companies that move from other exchanges will be able to prove their mettle alongside the likes of Microsoft and Starbucks. By the end of the year, Nasdaq Japan hopes to allow such companies to apply for listings on a foreign section, then let Japanese companies be traded on the American market. ''This is going to force the Japanese government, Japanese industry, Japanese society to change,'' Mr. Saeki promised. ''This is going to be one of those events that comes along only once or twice every 100 or 200 years and fundamentally changes things.''</p>
        <p>Others are less certain. ''It depends on how active the new market will be,'' said Kenji Ikeda, general manager of the initial public offering department at Daiwa Securities, which is underwriting three of the eight companies that will be listed on Nasdaq Japan. ''If it turns out to be very active, it will be a stimulus for changes. But right now, the possibility of Nasdaq Japan bringing big changes is small.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Saeki must overcome regulations limiting small companies to floating only a thousand shares. He must convince companies to adopt new disclosure standards. He must woo skeptical Japanese brokerage firms that dominate initial public offerings. He must learn to curb his tongue.</p>
        <p>''Please, clean up my language,'' he pleaded in a recent interview, having thrown officials at Nasdaq headquarters in Washington into a tizzy over a question-and-answer magazine interview  that included the four-letter words he uses when talking about bureaucratic obstacles.</p>
        <p>His biggest test so far was hammering out an agreement with the Osaka Securities Exchange.  Nasdaq's dream was to set up shop on its own, but a thicket of regulatory requirements made that virtually impossible within the one year its backers gave themselves.</p>
        <p>The Osaka talks were torture, according to several people involved. One hour before a March 15 news conference to announce the formation of the market's board, the two sides were far apart on five major issues. Mr. Saeki worked feverishly to resolve them, wielding a hard-nosed analysis of the cost of failure. Ten minutes before the conference began, all signatures were in place.</p>
        <p>Wrangling over complex partnership agreements was not on Mr. Saeki's agenda a year ago when Masayoshi Son, the charismatic founder of Softbank, rang him up and told him his future was with Nasdaq Japan. At the time, Mr. Saeki was weighing the merits of various ventures that would allow him to enjoy his planned retirement from I.B.M. Japan while leaving plenty of time for  golf. (He has a handicap of 9 and a wife, Junko, who can hold her own on the fairways. )</p>
        <p>But for every good retirement project that Mr. Saeki had, Softbank, a huge backer of Internet ventures, got there first. ''All of a sudden, I started seeing Son's shadow everywhere,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In November 1998, he had dinner with Mr. Son. He had met Mr. Son 20 years earlier and dismissed him as a dreamer. Then, in 1995, Mr. Son startled Mr. Saeki by buying Comdex, the big computer technology trade show.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saeki played golf three or four times a year with Mr. Son, and at the 1998 dinner, Mr. Son suggested that they start Nasdaq Japan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saeki demurred, but Mr. Son persisted, calling each day. Then I.B.M. threatened to take away Mr. Saeki's stock options if he left before the company's mandated retirement age of 60, and he got mad. He started thinking about how the 35 years he spent at an American company  mirrored Japan's limited role on the world stage.</p>
        <p>''Have you ever noticed in those pictures they take after summit meetings,'' he said, ''the Japanese prime minister is always standing at the end of the line of world leaders, appearing as a small figure in the corner of your TV screen? We Japanese are not accepted as leaders. I know this personally, unfortunately, because I spent 35 years at I.B.M. Japan, and yet a Japanese has never been elected to a senior executive job in Armonk.'' In fact, I.B.M. promoted a Japanese executive last November to lead its Asia-Pacific operations, and Minoru Makihara, the chairman of the Mitsubishi Corporation, is on I.B.M.'s board.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saeki, who relinquished his retirement benefits by leaving early, says he believes that Nasdaq Japan will win Japan a larger role in the global economy. But the Japanese establishment is fighting back. Last December, the Tokyo Stock Exchange established a market to attract entrepreneurial companies. So far it has 10 listings.</p>
        <p>The mere existence of the rival exchange, some financiers say, confirms the impact that Nasdaq Japan and Mr. Saeki will have here. ''The fact is that this was a direct response to the threat posed by Nasdaq Japan,'' said Karl K. Fooks, a managing director at J. P. Morgan. ''That response, in and of itself, is a huge victory.''</p>
        <p>PRIVATE SECTOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
