<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.Y.I.</title>
    <meta content="18FYI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208200"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Swinburne Island (Nyc)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Durante, Jimmy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, Daniel B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E1DE103EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="656" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.Y.I.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schneider, Daniel B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>FYI column answers questions about identity of comic Jimmy Durante's Mrs Calabash, red steel '9' sculpture outside skyscraper at 9 West 57th Street and whether anyone has ever lived on Swinburne Island off Staten Island; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Calabash Dreams  Q.: The gravelly voiced comic Jimmy Durante used to end his radio programs with a wistful phrase, ''Goodnight, Mrs. Calabash, wherever you are.'' Who was Mrs. Calabash?</p>
        <p>A.: Jimmy Durante, the big-nosed vaudeville headliner, actor, radio comedian and television star who died in 1980, never explained his signature farewell, but a number of theories have been advanced by Schnozzola scholars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Calabash Dreams  Q.: The gravelly voiced comic Jimmy Durante used to end his radio programs with a wistful phrase, ''Goodnight, Mrs. Calabash, wherever you are.'' Who was Mrs. Calabash?</p>
        <p>A.: Jimmy Durante, the big-nosed vaudeville headliner, actor, radio comedian and television star who died in 1980, never explained his signature farewell, but a number of theories have been advanced by Schnozzola scholars.</p>
        <p>Durante, the son of an Italian immigrant barber, was born in 1893 and lived on Catherine Street in Lower Manhattan. As a teenager, he started playing ragtime piano at Diamond Tony's, a Coney Island honky-tonk.  Later, as Ragtime Jimmy, he played in saloons throughout New York.</p>
        <p>When Dixieland jazz became the rage, he formed Jimmy Durante's New Orleans Jazz Band, and then, in the 1920's, opened his own club. He later performed in a vaudeville act with Lou Clayton and Eddie Jackson, billed as the Three Sawdust Bums. They made their first movie in 1929. In the 1940's and 50's, when he starred in radio and television programs, his forlorn farewell to Mrs. Calabash became as much a part of the Durante ethos as his battered felt hat, sly malapropisms and signature song, ''Inka Dinka Doo.''</p>
        <p>Many, The New York Times included, have asserted that Mrs. Calabash was Durante's nickname for a childhood sweetheart; others said it was his first wife, Maude Jeanne Olson, who died in 1943 after a long series of illnesses. Some have suggested that Mrs. Calabash was a racehorse that cost Durante a bundle, while others spun the tale of a widow named Calabash who sent Durante a letter about her polio-stricken son, an ardent fan. Then there was the restaurant in Calabash, N.C. . . .</p>
        <p>The most recent and most likely  theory attributes the line to Durante's stable of comedy writers, who heard John Charles Thomas, a singer, close his radio program with  ''Good night, Mother,'' and wanted something similar for their show. According to a producer, one writer studied his pipe, a calabash, and mused aloud, ''Good night, Mrs. Calabash.'' A few nights later, they added ''wherever you are.''</p>
        <p>Sidewalk '9'  Q.: The red, three-dimensional ''9'' in the middle of the sidewalk in front of 9 West 57th Street occupies a substantial chunk of city property. Did the owners get special permission?</p>
        <p>A.: Actually, the Solow Development Corporation, owner of the bell-bottomed skyscraper at 9 West 57th Street, rents the sidewalk space from the city, for $1,000 a year. The steel, tomato-red, 10-foot-high, 5-foot wide  9, which identifies the building while providing a kind of supergraphic exclamation point, occupies about 50 square feet of sidewalk, and weighs six tons. The sculpture -- titled ''9'' -- was designed by Ivan Chermayeff, and appears backward when viewed from the west. It has been blocking the sidewalk since 1972.</p>
        <p>Islands for the Unlucky  Q.: Has anyone ever lived on Swinburne Island, the little speck off the eastern shore of Staten Island?</p>
        <p>A.: Only the unlucky. Swinburne and its sister speck, Hoffman Island, were created in the 1860's out of sand dredged from the harbor, and were used to quarantine immigrants and seamen with contagious diseases. Swinburne, originally Dix Island, was named for John S. Swinburne, who oversaw construction of the islands. Swinburne was used to treat those with cholera, yellow fever and other diseases; Hoffman was used to quarantine those exposed.</p>
        <p>After immigration waned in the 1920's, the island was used to house to soldiers with venereal diseases, then closed in 1928. Most of the buildings burned in a 1934 fire, and Swinburne Island is now inhabited by colonies of sea birds.</p>
        <p>DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</p>
        <p>E-mail address: daschn@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: daschn@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
