<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Aliens in the Delaware Are Welcome to Stay</title>
    <meta content="18OUTD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208469"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trout</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Delaware River</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bodo, Pete</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Delaware</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Delaware</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E6D81731F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="933" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Aliens in the Delaware Are Welcome to Stay</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Pete Bodo</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bodo, Pete</byline>
      <dateline>DEPOSIT, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses fishing for trout in Delaware River; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The angler staggering up the steep bank to the hardtop road where Richard Franklin and I were stringing up our fly rods appeared dazed and contented, proving once again that people who grouse about ''too much of a good thing'' probably never experience it. This lean gent had caught so many trout that he regarded even the dense poison ivy carpeting the bank with delight: oh, the waxy sheen of those leaves! Oh, that subtle crimson tint on the triple-leaf clusters!</p>
        <p>''The Baetis were hatching heavy all morning,'' he said breathlessly, referring to a small mayfly commonly called the blue-winged olive. ''There were sulfur spinners, too, and some caddis. Every fish in the river was up, feeding.'' He allowed the requisite beat before the punch line: ''They turned off about an hour ago. Must be this wind.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The angler staggering up the steep bank to the hardtop road where Richard Franklin and I were stringing up our fly rods appeared dazed and contented, proving once again that people who grouse about ''too much of a good thing'' probably never experience it. This lean gent had caught so many trout that he regarded even the dense poison ivy carpeting the bank with delight: oh, the waxy sheen of those leaves! Oh, that subtle crimson tint on the triple-leaf clusters!</p>
        <p>''The Baetis were hatching heavy all morning,'' he said breathlessly, referring to a small mayfly commonly called the blue-winged olive. ''There were sulfur spinners, too, and some caddis. Every fish in the river was up, feeding.'' He allowed the requisite beat before the punch line: ''They turned off about an hour ago. Must be this wind.''</p>
        <p>Undaunted, my partner and I soon scrambled down the footpath to the West Branch of the Delaware River. It was 3 p.m. on a sunny day in early June, a time we frequently fish in this area just a few miles below the Cannonsville Reservoir. The river is braided up here, the islands dense with flowering briars, bleached-out deadfalls and the detritus of the spring floods, which invariably includes a pair of navy blue New York Giants sweat pants grotesquely twisted around a willow root.</p>
        <p>I find the flotsam intriguing, in a morbid way, but these islands are valuable as well as compelling. Inundated all spring, they explode with life as soon as the floods recede and quickly become so dense that bushwhacking across even the most slender of them in waders is impossible. While it's inconvenient negotiating around them, they provide quality habitat for nesting birds and secure bedding areas for deer.</p>
        <p>Islands also multiply the amount of bank habitat for trout and add to the available amount of food, provided the volume of water is sufficient to push up against them. Thanks to a wet spring, the West Branch was flowing at a robust 1,200 cubic feet a second, almost double the norm.</p>
        <p>When a river is bank full, its foliated banks provide juvenile trout with places to hide, adult trout with ideal feeding stations and freshly hatched aquatic insects with good cover in which they rapidly mature before mating and sowing their eggs back into the river from which they sprang. Trout often take up bankside lies along islands for the same reasons that dogs like to feign sleep beneath dining room tables: just in case something falls off the edge.</p>
        <p>It took some looking, but Richard and I found fish rising sporadically in the broad back channel of the river. In a typical June, this flat would be glassy and the trout hard to fool. But the current was brisk and the surface simmered, tilting the odds our way. Reflections of purple and white dame's rocket shimmered in the late afternoon light, and then a fish rose within casting range, completing the tableau.</p>
        <p>As soon as my size-16 parachute Adams alighted on the surface, the trout grabbed it. It was a fat, footlong brown that burped at me as I slipped the barbless hook from its jaw. Strictly speaking, dame's rocket (a member of the mustard family, it closely resembles phlox) and brown trout are both aliens in the local ecosystem, but as far as I'm concerned they are more than welcome to stay. Just minutes later, Richard hooked and landed a considerably larger fish. Our reverie was interrupted by a thunderstorm. We scowled at the sky, huddling in our flimsy rain jackets.</p>
        <p>Clearing, the skies were clotted with orange. It was so still that droplets fell audibly from the leaves. The broad channel before me was the color of pewter, open and inviting. But I kept casting glances over my shoulder at the island, expecting fish to rise there as dusk approached. They would be tight to the bank, in the dark band of water below the dank overhanging boughs that tippled the surface here and there.</p>
        <p>Sulfurs, tiny yellow mayflies, began emerging in the failing light. Here and there, a snout poked through the surface. Trout in bank lies, where the current is usually slow and even, rise deliberately. Often, their dorsal fins wag in the surface film. If you don't have a seizure at the sight, you can accurately judge the size of the fish.</p>
        <p>None of the fish up against the island were giants. But in that micro-environment, even the little dumb ones can be challenging. Presenting a fly accurately, delicately and realistically to a bank feeder is, to many anglers, the height of the art.</p>
        <p>I patiently worked on the largest of the fish for half an hour. Just before dark, I finally hooked it on a size-18 sulfur emerger. I don't know which of us was more surprised. By the time I released the lovely 15-inch brown, it was dark. The chill air was heavy with the scent of alluvial earth. I'd have to wade around the edge of the entire island in the dark to get back to the car, and that was just fine by me.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
