<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends; When Testing Upstages Teaching</title>
    <meta content="18ZERN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208411"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zernike, Kate</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EFD81631F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1064" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends; When Testing Upstages Teaching</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE ZERNIKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zernike, Kate</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>European and Japanese schools use rigorous system of tests to cull elite students from the merely literate; US educators have pushed for similar regime of tests to force schools to raise standards for everyone; evidence so far suggests US schools, too, are using tests to sort students, often by the time they are in grade school; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS every child knows, school these days is spelled t-e-s-t: preparing for them, taking them, passing them -- or else.</p>
        <p>Beginning in the 1990's, American educators, lusting after the academic successes of European and Japanese schoolchildren, imported the idea of a rigorous system of tests, which those countries use to cull the elite from the merely literate. But educators here insisted that America would instead use testing to snap schools to attention, forcing them to raise standards for everyone. They would lift up, not weed out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS every child knows, school these days is spelled t-e-s-t: preparing for them, taking them, passing them -- or else.</p>
        <p>Beginning in the 1990's, American educators, lusting after the academic successes of European and Japanese schoolchildren, imported the idea of a rigorous system of tests, which those countries use to cull the elite from the merely literate. But educators here insisted that America would instead use testing to snap schools to attention, forcing them to raise standards for everyone. They would lift up, not weed out.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the evidence so far suggests that schools here are doing the very sort of gardening they promised to avoid, employing tests to sort children, often by the time they are in grade school.</p>
        <p>In several other countries, it is illegal to track students before they are teenagers, said Marc Tucker, president of the National Center on Education and the Economy in Washington. But in the United States, teachers have decided by the early grades who is bright and who isn't, giving some students the message that they will never rise out of the lower track.</p>
        <p>''This is the country that has the most vicious tracking system in the world because we start to do it so young,'' Mr. Tucker said. ''The results are far more irrevocable than we will admit to ourselves. If you've assigned kids in fourth and fifth grade to the lower rungs of the English ladder, there's no way in the world for them to become accomplished readers and writers. It creates an utter disaster in terms of expectations.''</p>
        <p>No wonder there has been a well-publicized outbreak of cheating.</p>
        <p>''The people who think about testing didn't think through the implications,'' says Philip G. Altbach, professor of education at Boston College. ''They just thought, the Europeans are doing this and they have a good outcome. But what comes along with their system is an entire baggage of selection.''</p>
        <p>Americans, of course, have always tested their students. But the tests used in decades past -- apart from the SAT, which was never intended to drive how schools teach -- tested samples or groups of students. The European or Japanese notion was to test individual students.</p>
        <p>Now, Chicago schools use test scores to hold children back a grade, an example President Clinton would like to replicate nationwide. In New York City, tests are used much like SAT cutoff scores by some competitive middle schools; in other communities, the scores determine who enters the ''gifted'' track.</p>
        <p>The result is what Merry White, a scholar of Japan and a professor of anthropology at Boston University, calls ''a great American mixed message.''</p>
        <p>''We wanted to say that at any point in life you can make yourself over, that's part of our ideology,'' she said. ''We're supposed to believe that getting off track is okay. We had this idea of equality. But we don't know how to implement it in a meritocracy.''</p>
        <p>Defenders of the tests argue that American schools have always sorted students, and the new tests sort more fairly and more openly, so that the bald test scores force teachers and parents to pay attention and demand more from all students.</p>
        <p>Indeed, there is some evidence suggesting that tests may spur children to perform at higher levels. Scores are up across New York State in the second year of the fourth grade reading tests. Texas offers perhaps the best example. There, scores have gone up dramatically in the 10 years since the state began publicly reporting school-by-school scores. With a large state and local campaign to do better on tests, Texas has begun to shrink the stubborn test score gap between blacks and whites.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to know, however, what the scores mean. New York City Schools Chancellor Harold Levy cautions that the improvement in his students' scores may simply reflect more familiarity with the new tests. And even those who applaud the Texas example question whether those students are really learning at high levels.</p>
        <p>William Schmidt, the director of the United States branch of the Third International Math and Science Study, a widely respected survey of about three dozen nations, has examined dozens of the new state tests, as well as more traditional tests.</p>
        <p>''The idea of reform may be to say do more algebra, but the tests are pushing basics,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The problem is that when the United States imported tests, it did not import the rigorous curriculum that shapes other countries' schools. Teachers in most states still don't have a clear sense of what the tests are supposed to be testing, or what constitutes high achievement. Instead, everyone becomes obsessed with the scores.</p>
        <p>THAT might explain why American students continue to lag in international comparisons, even as their scores on national tests improve.</p>
        <p>Countries that continue to outperform the United States, Professor Schmidt said, are teaching the math that Americans learn in the eighth grade at the fourth and fifth grades.</p>
        <p>Most important, they also have well-defined sets of standards about what students need to learn, which dictate a curriculum that is narrower, but deeper. That curriculum is tightly tied to the test, and students are not sorted until the upper grades, by which time they have been thoroughly schooled in the curriculum.</p>
        <p>In the United States, ''the whole notion has been deformed in some ways,'' said Sue Bastian, head of Teaching Matters, a group of former teachers devoted to teacher training. ''The standards which should have guided us have bowdlerized into standardized tests,'' she said, which are then used to punish low-scoring schools, rather than improve the curricula or teachers' skills.</p>
        <p>The result is essentially the same system as before, only with more tests squeezing teachers' time.</p>
        <p>''I think there are some people making state policy who think that teachers have known all along how to raise performance, they've just been lazy, that all you have to do is raise the bar and they will do it,'' said Mr. Tucker. ''I don't think that's true at all. All the tests will do is measure kids' performance. But you're not going to improve performance unless teachers do something different in the classroom.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
