<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Cuban Missile Crisis, Angioplasty and Other Show Stoppers</title>
    <meta content="18LSID$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208265"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mccarter Theater</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lockwood, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genzlinger, Neil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Angioplasty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E7D6113EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Cuban Missile Crisis, Angioplasty and Other Show Stoppers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genzlinger, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bill Lockwood, who books acts into McCarter Theater, recalls problems with several acts; some incidents recalled (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOMENTS of truth,'' Bill Lockwood calls them -- the times when things don't go quite according to plan. In the presenting business they are frequent, as small as a broken guitar string, as large as a missed flight or a curtain-time illness. Even with 40 years' experience, they never go away; at best, they become tempered with a bit of perspective.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lockwood's baptism came early, while he was still in college at Princeton in the late 1950's. He and some friends were trying their hand at bringing some entertainment to the campus, and for the big spring weekend they landed one of the hottest acts of the moment, the Kingston Trio. The student body was buzzing with anticipation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOMENTS of truth,'' Bill Lockwood calls them -- the times when things don't go quite according to plan. In the presenting business they are frequent, as small as a broken guitar string, as large as a missed flight or a curtain-time illness. Even with 40 years' experience, they never go away; at best, they become tempered with a bit of perspective.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lockwood's baptism came early, while he was still in college at Princeton in the late 1950's. He and some friends were trying their hand at bringing some entertainment to the campus, and for the big spring weekend they landed one of the hottest acts of the moment, the Kingston Trio. The student body was buzzing with anticipation.</p>
        <p>''The Kingston Trio was the coup of all time,'' Mr. Lockwood said. ''We were kings of the campus.''</p>
        <p>Between 3 and 5 every afternoon the young promoters held office hours in a dorm room, taking money from ticket-buyers eager to see the folk threesome.</p>
        <p>''Then, three days before the concert, one of them got pneumonia, and they called and said, 'We're going to have to postpone,' '' Mr. Lockwood recalled, still sounding incredulous. ''That was like the day the Ivory soap sank.''</p>
        <p>So between 3 and 5 every afternoon the young promoters again held office hours in a dorm room, this time giving refunds. But in a backhanded sort of way, it was just as well: they soon noticed there was something odd about some of the tickets that were coming back. Someone had been running a counterfeit-ticket scam. Had the show taken place, they would have had hundreds more people than could be accommodated. ''We would have had a horrendous security problem,'' Mr. Lockwood said.</p>
        <p>That mess wasn't enough to discourage Mr. Lockwood. A few years later he and his friend Tom Sternberg had a nascent presenting business in San Francisco, where, in 1962, they encountered Moment of Truth No. 2.</p>
        <p>They had booked the Bolshoi Ballet, the pride of the Soviet Union. It was a major undertaking. ''We spent thousands of dollars putting a new stage floor in the great old Fox Theater,'' Mr. Lockwood recalled. ''It was going to be a weeklong engagement, to great fanfare.'' They even had the Bolshoi's logo painted on the side of the theater.</p>
        <p>''And then, the third day into the run of the Bolshoi Ballet, Kennedy put the blockade around Cuba,'' he said. ''People were seriously afraid that this was going to expand, implode into an event of worldwide crisis and possibly involve us in a world war. The minute that happened, ticket sales absolutely came to a standstill.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lockwood said he didn't think it was that people were trying to send a protest message to the Soviet Union; it was just that they were caught up in the news. Going to the ballet was suddenly not on anyone's agenda. The result was a financial disaster for the fledgling presenters. Only an appeal to their backer got them through.</p>
        <p>Moment of Truth No. 3 came courtesy of the Boss. It was 1978, Mr. Lockwood was back at Princeton, and Bruce Springsteen brought his band to the campus. The McCarter is not exactly a rock 'n' roll place, so, as he had done for other concerts, Mr. Lockwood arranged to use Jadwin Gymnasium. As for other concerts, folding chairs were set up on the gym floor atop a cloth cover. The chairs were the aluminum kind with protective rubber tips on the legs.</p>
        <p>But, as Mr. Lockwood learned, Springsteen fans are not exactly the sit-and-listen-politely type. People stood on the chairs, jumped on them, and the protective rubber tips failed. The sharp aluminum legs were driven right through the cloth floor cover.</p>
        <p>''The morning after the concert, what you had was a basketball floor with lots of little circles,'' Mr. Lockwood said. ''You get a call from the university administration saying, 'Come down to Jadwin Gym immediately.' And there you have a little group of men huddled around the basketball court, including the director of athletics and the basketball coach and somebody from Nassau Hall administration. And what they're looking at, essentially, is a basketball court that's been ruined.''</p>
        <p>This was particularly unfortunate because it was November, and the basketball team was getting ready to start the season. An emergency floor refinishing was ordered. ''They were very understanding about it,'' Mr. Lockwood recalled. ''But essentially the message came down, 'We don't think there should be any more rock concerts in this facility.' ''</p>
        <p>So James Taylor is about as raucous as the gym has been since. Mr. Lockwood still never knows when another moment of truth might come along. As he sat down to be interviewed for these articles, a phone call came from Ravi Shankar's people. The great sitarist, who turned 80 this year, was due to play the McCarter a few days later. But a small matter of an angioplasty had come up. . . .</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
