<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rockies Are Better But Not on the Road</title>
    <meta content="Y18BAS$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208505"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Colorado Rockies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bell, Buddy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Colorado Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E0DD1431F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rockies Are Better But Not on the Road</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Murray Chass discusses improvements in Colorado Rockies, from first-year manager Buddy Bell to 15 new players in key positions; home record is best in majors but factoring in road record leaves team in second place in National League West; (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the words of an executive with a competing club, ''They changed everything from top to bottom and they wind up with the same animal.''</p>
        <p>The animal that is the Colorado Rockies, though, is a more attractive species this season. Many of the Rockies' ingredients look similar to last year's, but the team has made impressive improvements in some key areas, and the difference is in the standings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the words of an executive with a competing club, ''They changed everything from top to bottom and they wind up with the same animal.''</p>
        <p>The animal that is the Colorado Rockies, though, is a more attractive species this season. Many of the Rockies' ingredients look similar to last year's, but the team has made impressive improvements in some key areas, and the difference is in the standings.</p>
        <p>Keeping with the character of their eight-year-old franchise, the Rockies have played as two different teams home and away. Following their 14-5 victory over Arizona last night, the Rockies have a 36-27 record, 24-8 at home and 12-19 on the road. But their home record, the best in the majors, was enough to place them only one game behind the first-place Diamondbacks in the National League West. After the same number of games last season, the Rockies had a 31-32 record and were 7 games behind the first-place Diamondbacks.</p>
        <p>''We need to play better on the road,'' said Buddy Bell, who as the first-year manager is one of many new members with the club. ''Only time will tell if we can do that.''</p>
        <p>When Dan O'Dowd, another newcomer, became general manager last September, he set out to change the personality of the team. The slugging attack had not worked, so he decided to put together a collection of players who could get on base and score without relying on home runs. He also wanted pitchers who could throw strikes.</p>
        <p>O'Dowd's efforts have given the Rockies 15 new players on their 25-man roster. Two of the departed, Vinny Castilla and Dante Bichette, were two of the team's sluggers who produced a .472 slugging percentage last season. The slugging percentage this season? It's .471.</p>
        <p>But O'Dowd's changes have produced the desired effect in putting runners on base. The Rockies' on-base percentage last season was .348. It's up to .371 this season. Last season Bichette had a .354 on-base percentage and Castilla .331. Among the newcomers this season Jeffrey Hammonds is at .435, Tom Goodwin .422 and Jeff Cirillo .404. As a team, the Rockies are drawing more walks, averaging one more walk a game (4.15) than last year (3.14). ''We have a pretty good chemistry,'' Bell said. ''Guys understand what's needed at the time. They're not afraid to take a walk. That's something Danny really felt was one of the most important things for how our offense was. Our on-base percentage last year wasn't very good so he was determined to make that better. It's become more of a contagious thing.''</p>
        <p>If the Rockies were to score runs without a ton of home runs, they were going to have to go for more stolen bases, and they have succeeded there, too. Last year the team had 70 stolen bases, tied for the next-to-lowest total in the league. This season they have 62, second in the league. But the home/road disparity continues. Hammonds is hitting 178 percentage points better at home, Todd Helton 131 points, Cirillo 112, Goodwin 102 and Larry Walker 100. Imagine how good the Rockies' league-leading batting average (.296) could be if they could hit in other teams' parks.</p>
        <p>On the pitching side of the ledger, the Rockies have made significant improvement. From a franchise-record 6.01 earned run average last season, the Colorado staff has sliced half a run, compiling a 5.46 e.r.a. so far this season.</p>
        <p>One of the reasons is the pitchers' improved control. As O'Dowd designed it, they are throwing fewer balls and walking fewer batters. They have averaged one fewer walk this season (3.50) than last (4.55), giving them a total of 217, the third-lowest total in the N.L. Last year they walked a league-record 737.</p>
        <p>Bell credited his relief corps with doing a solid job. Leading that corps is the closer, Jose Jimenez, who as a rookie starter last season pitched a no-hitter for St. Louis. The 26-year-old right-hander has made a seamless transition to relieving, earning 11 saves in 13 opportunities. ''Jimenez has helped solidify the roles everybody performs,'' O'Dowd said. ''We didn't say it, but that was the role we got him for. We didn't know his durability or how he would handle things mentally, but he's been fine.''</p>
        <p>So has the team's defense. From the middle of the pack last season the Rockies have rocketed to the top, committing the fewest errors (35) in the league. Besides being more sure-handed, the infielders have demonstrated greater range. The combination makes the pitchers better.</p>
        <p>Combine all of the improvements, and look at the Rockies in second place, challenging the Diamondbacks for first place this weekend. And if there are players out there who could make the team even better, Bell is betting that O'Dowd will find them.</p>
        <p>''He is one relentless man,'' the manager said. ''I'm sure if somebody told us we'd be in this position now we'd have taken it. But he's always going to try to make us better.''</p>
        <p>Indians Sink to Past</p>
        <p>The last time the Cleveland Indians were this far from first place (seven and a half games behind), Jeff Treadway and Felix Fermin were their double-play combination, Junior Ortiz was their catcher, Wayne Kirby their right fielder and Sam Horn their designated hitter. Candy Maldonado and Randy Milligan were on the team, and Manny Ramirez was there as a September callup. Dave Mlicki and Bob Milacki were on the pitching staff, as was Jason Grimsley, now with the Yankees. Jose Mesa was in his last season as a starting pitcher.</p>
        <p>The season was 1993, and the Indians finished it a season-high 19 games from first place. The furthest the Indians have been from first since that year was four games in 1994. In the past four years their biggest deficits totaled seven games.</p>
        <p>Striking Out at Sosa</p>
        <p>In what has become an orchestrated or an impromptu campaign to denigrate Sammy Sosa -- in some instances to try to demonstrate why the Yankees should not trade for him -- much has been made of the frequency of his strikeouts and his weight. Sosa might have become chubbier, but he is really not striking out at any greater rate than he has in recent seasons.</p>
        <p>Sosa has struck out 74 times in 259 times at bat, or once for every 3.5 times at bat. In his 66-homer season in 1998, he struck out once for every 3.76 at-bats, and last season his ratio was 1 for every 3.65. In each of those seasons he struck out 171 times. In 1997, he struck out 174 times, or once for every 3.69 at-bats.</p>
        <p>If he were to bat this season the approximate number of times he did in those seasons and continue striking out at this season's ratio, he would finish the season with 183. That would be a negligible increase in frequency.</p>
        <p>In other words, it's S O S -- Same Old Sammy.</p>
        <p>Morgan's Dozen</p>
        <p>It took Mike Morgan nearly two and a half months, but he finally extended one of his major league records to 12 teams last week. When he started for Arizona and lost to Los Angeles, it marked the 12th team with which he has lost games. Morgan, who is 40 years old, has played for more teams than any other player in any major sports league (12), and he has won games for more teams than any other major league pitcher. The Diamondbacks became No. 11 when Morgan gained a victory in relief in April.</p>
        <p>Jeff Zimmerman, a Morgan teammate last season with Texas, has allowed 22 earned runs and 24 runs over all in 29 games and 28 2/3 innings. Last season he gave up 23 earned runs and 24 runs over all in 65 games and 87 2/3 innings. Zimmerman, a rookie in 1999, gained a spot on the American League All-Star team and pitched a hitless, scoreless inning. This year he has gained a three-day vacation.</p>
        <p>Self-Control Problems</p>
        <p>When the Atlanta Braves sent John Rocker to the minor leagues two weeks ago, they said it was for his pitching control, not his self-control. When he returned to the Braves last week following an injury to another reliever, he demonstrated that he had not solved his control problem. He threw six pitches in his first game back, and all were balls. It remains to be seen if he will demonstrate an improvement in his self-control.</p>
        <p>Albert Belle, who has had his own problems with self-control, was sent to the minors in 1991 after he failed to run out a double-play grounder. That incident occurred a few weeks after he threw a baseball at a fan in the stands. Did the three-week demotion have a positive effect on him?</p>
        <p>''I think it did,'' John Hart, the Indians' general manager, said. ''Maturity comes at different times. At that point in his career, I remember very clearly Albert was young and struggling at the major league level. He had the incident with the fan and he didn't run out two or three balls. He wasn't playing well. It was a message to Albert. When he came back, he became a poster child.''</p>
        <p>Mike Hargrove, a coach at Cleveland who became the manager 10 days after Belle returned to the Indians, said the outfielder was different when he rejoined the team.</p>
        <p>''He was always intense batting,'' Hargrove said, ''but he played the rest of his game with more intensity. He took his game in the field more seriously. He was still a work in progress, but we had something to work with in trying to get him to modify his outlook.''</p>
        <p>Belle was 24 going on 25 at the time. Rocker is 25.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
