<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vroooom! Kapow! Smash! C-r-r-runch!; At Riverhead Demo Derby, the Race, Such as It Is, Goes to the Durable</title>
    <meta content="18DEMO$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208206"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Riverhead (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leduff, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E5DC103EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vroooom! Kapow! Smash! C-r-r-runch!; At Riverhead Demo Derby, the Race, Such as It Is, Goes to the Durable</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE LeDUFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leduff, Charlie</byline>
      <dateline>RIVERHEAD</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on popularity of demolition derbies on Long Island, NY; island once boasted 40 tracks that held demo derbies, but development boom has brought number down to one, at Riverhead; racers and fans comment; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE ain't really much to understand,'' explains Ed Jager, a king of the demolition derby. ''In most motor sports, the winner is the car that finishes first. In demo, it's the car that finishes. You smash things. It don't take a genius.''</p>
        <p>The demolition derby seems to be a uniquely American sociopathic pastime, ranking somewhere above midget-tossing and somewhere below jai alai and harness racing. Strategy demands that the drivers smash into each other, full speed, tail end first. This metaphor of annihilation-in-reverse is so compelling, it is said, the Soviet authorities used the demolition derby as a telling example of American decadence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE ain't really much to understand,'' explains Ed Jager, a king of the demolition derby. ''In most motor sports, the winner is the car that finishes first. In demo, it's the car that finishes. You smash things. It don't take a genius.''</p>
        <p>The demolition derby seems to be a uniquely American sociopathic pastime, ranking somewhere above midget-tossing and somewhere below jai alai and harness racing. Strategy demands that the drivers smash into each other, full speed, tail end first. This metaphor of annihilation-in-reverse is so compelling, it is said, the Soviet authorities used the demolition derby as a telling example of American decadence.</p>
        <p>''It's true,'' says Mr. Jager, 41, who is generally so black with grease that one might mistake him for a chimney sweep. ''Why do you think all the Russians and Commies came here? Cause they heard we got cars to smash.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jager, who is known on the tracks from Kansas to California as Speedo, is a wiry, amiable fellow, a father of two and a capable auto mechanic. But when Memorial Day rolls around, the demo-derby season begins and men like Mr. Jager channel the year's depressions, defeats and dejections squarely through the cross-hairs of their hood ornaments.</p>
        <p>''It's been a tough year,'' Mr. Jager said as he began reworking his '75 Chevy Wagon in the garage of the Garden City Exxon where he works. ''I'm splitting with my wife, and that makes me want to split heads.''</p>
        <p>His powder-blue station wagon was bent to the shape of a banana by the punishment it sustained in last year's championship at Riverhead Raceway. He took a look at the broken car and laughed, ''I'm on a suicide mission this year.''</p>
        <p>Exactly how many derbies are run a year seems an unanswerable question. The estimates range from 750 to 5,000, most run on the dirt fields of county fairgrounds. Because the event is something between a sport and sideshow, fans seem a little ashamed of their affection.</p>
        <p>''It's more of a spectacle than anything else,'' said John Griffin, a spokesman for the National Association for Stock Car Auto Racing, organizers of the Daytona 500 and other races where the crashes are unintentional but more spectacular. ''Local operators usually add it to the end of the day's events just to enhance the entertainment value.''</p>
        <p>The Island, where there are 2,024,078 registered vehicles for 1,948,152 licensed drivers, once supported 40 racetracks that held demo derbies. But development is raging, so despite the fact that motor sports are the fastest-growing spectator sport in the nation, the only track left on Long Island is the quarter-mile oval at Riverhead.</p>
        <p>''It's pretty ironic,'' said Jim Cromarty, who owns Riverhead Raceway along with his wife, Barbara. ''This is one of the first paved tracks in the nation, and we're just holding on by our fingernails. The derby is the added attraction.''</p>
        <p>(In an interesting bit of Long Island convergence, in 1984 the Cromartys became the operators of the Islip Speedway. That same year they moved into a home where a boy had butchered his parents, two sisters and two brothers. The home would later be immortalized in ''The Amityville Horror.''</p>
        <p>(''There were no flies or blood in the toilet,'' Mr. Cromarty reported happily. ''And the only spirits in the house was the bottle of Johnnie Walker Red I kept.'')</p>
        <p>The Islip Speedway, now the site of a cookie factory, was the site of the first demolition derby in 1958.</p>
        <p>The sport, if such it be, was invented by a young stock-car driver named Larry Mendelsohn, who realized that not all fans enjoyed the monotony of watching cars go round in circles but preferred the trauma and violence of the wrecks. Why not invent a race where the whole premise was cataclysm and fire?</p>
        <p>''He was a genius, pure genius,'' said Marty Himes, curator of the Himes Museum of Motor Racing and Nostalgia, which is operated out of his home and garage in Bay Shore. ''He really left the country something.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Himes said Mr. Mendelsohn had also left the world figure-8 racing, where the excitement comes when cars come to pass at the X.</p>
        <p>The demo-derby season at Riverhead Raceway began Memorial Day weekend and culminates on Sept. 16 with a national championship, so called. This is the ''national championship'' of the track, not the nation. Since there is no governing body for these exhibitions, most promoters assign outrageous titles to events and drivers. Mr. Jager, for instance, is the reigning ''New Jersey State World Champion.''</p>
        <p>Last year's track champion is Ed Genovese, 28, a tow-truck operator known as Whiplash who lives in his mother's basement in Farmingdale.</p>
        <p>Whiplash is a Chrysler man, and he was busy last month modifying his '78 Newport -- 360 cubic inches of mastodon -- at his garage in Amityville, a run-down shack of weeds and auto guts.</p>
        <p>''I bought it from a little old man in Massapequa,'' he said. ''It's getting hard to find these old pigs.''</p>
        <p>The men who create demolition derby cars -- there are few women -- are savants of the salvage yards, able to take a $100 crate of a car and transform it into a battering ram. They are at once welders, wet-nurses and washroom attendants to their wagons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Genovese's coterie includes his girl friend, Annmarie Donadeo, 6 feet 2 inches of blonde. They met at a bar some years ago and she knew about engines. It was love. She had oil in her nails and tan marks where she wears her rings when not working on motors. They are joined by Dan Sweeney, a 17-year-old stray dog the couple has adopted.</p>
        <p>''It ain't for the money and it ain't for the girls,'' Mr. Genovese said between oil-stained cigarettes. ''It's for the thrills. When I run, I run to win.''</p>
        <p>His tricks of the trade include chaining the motor down so it does not buckle into the fire wall. He epoxies the electrical wires so they will not pop loose. He puts the battery in the passenger-side floor. The seats are removed, and the gas can in back is covered with an oil drum so if it catches on fire, the flames will die out quickly.</p>
        <p>Whiplash Genovese will have to run hard this year. His old buddy Speedo Jager wants him and wants him bad. Despite winning five events last year to Whiplash's none, Speedo finished second in the final standings because of an arcane points system.</p>
        <p>Memorial Day weekend, as the well-bred and well-fed ushered in the season in the Hamptons with pate and chardonnay, a few miles north in Riverhead they partook of cold Buds and beef jerky. Throughout the day 3,000 people watched a full schedule of races with cigarettes butts stuffed in their ears. Even from miles away, the speeding cars sounded like hive of swarming hornets.</p>
        <p>Near the pits, the Whiplash crew was drinking and cussing. Then Speedo arrived, spinning doughnuts in the lot, kicking up a cloud of dust. The Whiplash crowd went silent. ''He looks tough,'' somebody mumbled.</p>
        <p>Speedo was wild-eyed. His youngest son would not to speak to him. It's the divorce. The boy, Michael, is 12 and having a hard time. The other, Anthony, is 17 and seems to understand.</p>
        <p>Speedo is busted up about his boys. About his wife. About the new apartment. He was going to take it out on someone on the track.</p>
        <p>The sun had set. The stadium lights were on and a cloud of exhaust hung in the air. The drivers were called to the pit and read the rules: No sandbagging or stalling. No deliberate head-on crashes. No hitting the driver's door. Bumpers and frames cannot be reinforced.</p>
        <p>Speedo hardly listened, more concerned about his boys than anything else.</p>
        <p>''Hey, you don't mind if I'm a weekend warrior type of dad, do you?'' he asked, wincing as he said it.</p>
        <p>''Naw,'' said Anthony. ''Get 'em, Dad.''</p>
        <p>Even before the announcer counted down to zero, a countdown largely drowned out by the roar of cranking engines, Speedo was doing 30 miles per in reverse, with his elbow folded out the window as if he were on a country drive. He walloped someone in the rear end. The race was on.</p>
        <p>Cars broke into flames, tires rolled loose, stray metal ground like sparklers. Whiplash's black car disappeared into the smoke. Speedo bogged down. Then he was running again. And 20 minutes into it, there were two: Whiplash and Speedo.</p>
        <p>They stopped and idled for a moment. Then Speedo came whipping around a smoldering wreck, his tires akimbo, and busted Whiplash cleanly across the motor. Whiplash could move no more.</p>
        <p>Speedo did a victory lap and then hugged his boys. The young one was smiling. All was right. Another Saturday night at the derby.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to dedicate this victory to my boys and to family values,'' he said over the public announcement system as they handed him his trophy.</p>
        <p>In the distance you could hear his boys shout, ''Speedo!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
