<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Resolute Artists Who Learned to Endure</title>
    <meta content="18TRUC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Ballet Theater</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jaffe, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trucco, Terry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDC123EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1092" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Resolute Artists Who Learned to Endure</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRY TRUCCO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Trucco, Terry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of American Ballet Theater principal dancer Susan Jaffe, 38, whose longevity has helped transform her into powerful, dramatic artist and dancer; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUSAN JAFFE, the luminous classical ballerina with the flashing emerald eyes, gets straight to the point. ''It's neat that I've lasted this long,'' she says with a broad smile.</p>
        <p>Longevity is admirable, particularly in a profession where careers are notoriously short. Two decades spent in the same company, American Ballet Theater, is also estimable. Only the character dancer Victor Barbee has been with the company longer than Ms. Jaffe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUSAN JAFFE, the luminous classical ballerina with the flashing emerald eyes, gets straight to the point. ''It's neat that I've lasted this long,'' she says with a broad smile.</p>
        <p>Longevity is admirable, particularly in a profession where careers are notoriously short. Two decades spent in the same company, American Ballet Theater, is also estimable. Only the character dancer Victor Barbee has been with the company longer than Ms. Jaffe.</p>
        <p>But to many people, what has made Ms. Jaffe's vibrant, if tumultuous, career so remarkable was her breathtaking transformation from a pleasing, technically proficient dancer with an easy extension into a powerful dramatic artist and dancer of amazing classical purity. Her metamorphosis was especially impressive for two reasons: it came after a period of mental and physical duress and it came relatively late, around the time Ms. Jaffe turned 30 and almost 10 years after she became a high-profile principal dancer.</p>
        <p>At 38, Ms. Jaffe remains the quintessential Ballet Theater ballerina, adept at bringing off a plotless Balanchine classic one night and morphing into an Odette, or a Juliet, the next. ''It's all come together for her at a point when she can enjoy it,'' said Kevin McKenzie, the company's artistic director. ''After dancing for 20 years, she's still at the peak of her powers.''</p>
        <p>Except for a big party given in her honor by a Ballet Theater trustee (and for her successful effort to quit cigarettes), the current season, which continues through July 1, has been business as usual for Ms. Jaffe, who is dancing a familiar combination of new and longtime roles. Though a painful foot injury sidelined her from a performance of ''Don Quixote'' and muted her debut in the company's new production of ''Swan Lake,'' her characteristic intensity, joy and exacting artistry were on full display in her delicate Medora in ''Le Corsaire'' and her surprisingly empathetic Kate in ''The Taming of the Shrew.''</p>
        <p>A highlight for Ms. Jaffe was a midseason performance of Jerome Robbins's plotless ''Other Dances.'' ''It was one of those times when everything came together and I could lose myself in the dance,'' she said. ''It's like riding a wave -- you get on top of it and enjoy it and just allow the performance to happen instead of forcing it to happen.''</p>
        <p>At this stage of her career, Ms. Jaffe can bask in the sweet pleasures that come with experience. ''What's most fun at this point is being able to externalize a thought physically without having to think about what it looks like,'' she said during a recent interview in her flower-filled dressing room at the Metropolitan Opera House the day after her birthday. ''I've also reached a point where I'm able to be myself. When I was younger, I tried too hard to be other people, to copy other people in order to learn. I ended up not being myself.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Jaffe's perfectionist work habits are legendary within the company, particularly for acting roles, in which she analyzes each move and character motivation. ''I can't do anything halfway,'' she said. But the unusual trajectory of her career no doubt convinced her that hard work was the way to succeed. A native of Bethesda, Md., Ms. Jaffe decided she would be a ballerina at the age of 8. She recalls, ''My mother would drive me, and I would get this adrenal rush up my spine as we'd go around the corner and I'd see the ballet studio.'' In 1978, she joined A.B.T. II, the Ballet Theater farm team at the time, and two years later made the big leap into the main company.</p>
        <p>What happened next could come out of an old movie musical. Three months after joining, the 18-year-old Ms. Jaffe was plucked from the corps by Mikhail Baryshnikov, the new artistic director at the time, and sent onstage as a last-minute opening-night replacement for the ballerina Gelsey Kirkland, who had been fired for missing a dress rehearsal.</p>
        <p>''The experience was surreal,'' Ms. Jaffe recalled. ''My partner was Alexander Godunov, who had just defected, and there was all this attention.'' A beneficiary of Mr. Baryshnikov's eagerness to groom American dancers, Ms. Jaffe was soon showered with leading roles. But the riches proved a mixed blessing. ''It was a little like 'The Truman Show,' being Odette/Odile at 19 with 4,000 people staring at you,'' she said. ''It all happened so fast, I had to work hard for years to catch up and feel worthy.''</p>
        <p>Everything fell apart in 1989. Mr. Baryshnikov left the company. The plum roles suddenly went to other dancers. And Ms. Jaffe suffered a breakdown. The next year, a severe bout of tendinitis left her crippled for several months. ''I had to start over, throw everything I knew out the window, and look at ballet from a different angle,'' she recalled. She found a new teacher, hired a drama coach and began working with the ballet mistress Irina Koplakova. And her dancing changed, becoming more resonant and deeply felt as Ms. Jaffe pulled herself out of the difficult years.</p>
        <p>She credits much of her artistic growth to the soul-searching forced on her by the bad times. ''It just came out of the need to have answers to questions that can't really be answered,'' she said. ''My dancing became a reflection of my soul's experience, not just my personality.''</p>
        <p>Her searching continues, though these days her focus is life after ballet. ''I'm not ready to stop, but I know now I won't be one of those people who's dancing at 50,'' she said. At present, she's studying the healing arts, reading books on kinesiology and psychology, possibly to become a therapist. ''It's not that different from being an artist,'' she said. ''You work with physicality, energy and the mind.'' But in the end, she says, she'd like to be a ballet master. After a lifetime, the dance world is home. ''I may leave for a while,'' she said. ''But eventually, I'll want to go back.''</p>
        <p>DANCE Terry Trucco's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about a performance of ''Anastasia'' at American Ballet Theater with Viviana Durante in the title role.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Terry Trucco's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about a performance of ''Anastasia'' at American Ballet Theater with Viviana Durante in the title role.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
