<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Science Fiction</title>
    <meta content="18SCIFIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208063"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jonas, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">westerfeld, scott</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">scott, melissa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aldrin, Buzz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barnes, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aldiss, Brian W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">penrose, roger</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">evolution's darling (book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">jazz, the (book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">return, the (book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">white mars: or, the mind set free: a 21st century utopia (book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Science Fiction</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D7133FF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1188" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Science Fiction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gerald Jonas</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jonas, Gerald</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gerald Jonas reviews books Evolution's Darling by Scott Westerfeld; The Jazz by Melissa Scott; The Return by Buzz Aldrin and John Barnes; and White Mars: Or, The Mind Set Free: A 21st Century Utopia by Brian W Aldiss with Roger Penrose (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The prologue to EVOLUTION'S DARLING (Four Walls Eight Windows, paper, $15.95), by Scott Westerfeld, is breathtaking. Rathere, the 14-year-old daughter of a space-roving journalist, has trouble getting her father's attention. Her constant companion is an Artificial Intelligence (A.I.) with so much computing capacity that it can pilot a starship, baby-sit for Rathere and ponder the mysteries of the universe at the same time. The danger, for Rathere's financially strapped father, is that the A.I. will raise its ''Turing Quotient'' to 1.0, which would make it, in the eyes of the law, an independent person rather than a useful piece of property. Realizing that his daughter's relationship with the A.I. is driving the machine toward sentience, the father separates them. Rathere fights back in the only way she can. To nudge the A.I. over the threshold to personhood, she makes love to it -- in a scene of eerie beauty that begins with the words, ''It's me, darling.''</p>
        <p>While the rest of this far-future novel does not quite live up to the prologue, the entire narrative brims with energy and invention. The A.I., now known as Darling, secures a body of its own (male) and earns a living tracking down rare works of art throughout the galaxy. When an apparently new work by a supposedly dead artist surfaces, Darling is dispatched to collect it. So is Mira Santiarre Hidalgo, a young woman of surprising gifts and unusual tastes, whose employers are even more shadowy than Darling's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The prologue to EVOLUTION'S DARLING (Four Walls Eight Windows, paper, $15.95), by Scott Westerfeld, is breathtaking. Rathere, the 14-year-old daughter of a space-roving journalist, has trouble getting her father's attention. Her constant companion is an Artificial Intelligence (A.I.) with so much computing capacity that it can pilot a starship, baby-sit for Rathere and ponder the mysteries of the universe at the same time. The danger, for Rathere's financially strapped father, is that the A.I. will raise its ''Turing Quotient'' to 1.0, which would make it, in the eyes of the law, an independent person rather than a useful piece of property. Realizing that his daughter's relationship with the A.I. is driving the machine toward sentience, the father separates them. Rathere fights back in the only way she can. To nudge the A.I. over the threshold to personhood, she makes love to it -- in a scene of eerie beauty that begins with the words, ''It's me, darling.''</p>
        <p>While the rest of this far-future novel does not quite live up to the prologue, the entire narrative brims with energy and invention. The A.I., now known as Darling, secures a body of its own (male) and earns a living tracking down rare works of art throughout the galaxy. When an apparently new work by a supposedly dead artist surfaces, Darling is dispatched to collect it. So is Mira Santiarre Hidalgo, a young woman of surprising gifts and unusual tastes, whose employers are even more shadowy than Darling's.</p>
        <p>Just when the story seems about to degenerate into yet another high-tech shoot'em-up, it takes a more promising turn. If machines can become intelligent by learning to love, what experiences will jolt them into making art? Westerfeld is a witty writer who knows how to dramatize complex ideas; he is never willfully obscure, although his explanations tend to raise more questions than they answer. Of the ''Turing meter'' used to decide when machines become people, he says, ''It was understood that the determination of sentience was far too complex an issue to leave up to a human.''</p>
        <p>THE JAZZ (Tor/Tom Doherty, $23.95), by Melissa Scott, is a story of the Internet that, refreshingly, does not rely on the wonders or terrors of virtual reality to sustain interest. Set in a near-future America dominated by media corporations, the novel deals with a theme as current as the latest e-mail gossip or virus alert. In a world awash in information of dubious provenance, whom can you trust to tell you the truth?</p>
        <p>Tin Lizzy, a street-smart young woman of many names, is a sought-after ''back-tech'' programmer; she fills in the backgrounds of virtual chat rooms and other online environments with convincing details that enhance the user's sense of reality. But her true love is ''the jazz'' -- an emerging art form in which people manipulate the flow of information itself, to entertain or deceive, enlighten or punish. For reasons having to do with her outlaw past, she agrees to help a young hacker known as Keyz, who has got hold of a program so powerful that a major media mogul is willing to kill for it.</p>
        <p>Much of ''The Jazz'' is taken up with a cross-country chase that pits corporate goons against Lizzy, Keyz and their motley allies. But in the end, the survival of the good guys depends on Lizzy's ability to create plausible stories online that capture the attention of enough people to have serious consequences in the real world. I tend to skip jargon-filled descriptions of hackers doing their thing with keyboards or computer-linked brain implants. But Tin Lizzy's skills have as much to do with mass psychology as with source code. Anyone who has ever come across a tantalizing nugget of news on the Internet and wondered whether to believe it will appreciate the way she feeds, and exploits, the public's lust for inside information.</p>
        <p>Buzz Aldrin, the second man on the moon, has collaborated with the science fiction writer John Barnes on another novel about the importance of maintaining a strong space program. Like their ''Encounter With Tiber'' (1996), THE RETURN (Forge/Tom Doherty, $25.95) is packed with hard facts about rocket science. But where the earlier book alternated between human and alien narrators who sounded remarkably alike, ''The Return'' offers dovetailing accounts of a space emergency and rescue by three narrators -- brothers Nick and Scott Blackstone and Scott's former wife Thalia -- who sound like the same person.</p>
        <p>Although each section begins with the name of the speaker, I had so much trouble remembering who was talking that I yearned for some kind of typographical coding -- like the name badges that remind you at a glance who is guiding you through a high-security facility. The authors know all about high-security facilities, high-level bureaucratic infighting and engineering constraints. The plot updates the Apollo 13 scenario. When a ''proton bomb'' explodes in space, an ''invisible cloud'' of ''ionizing radiation'' threatens the lives of three astronauts in an orbiting space station. Getting them down before the radiation kills them will take all the political and technical ingenuity of the Blackstone brothers, not to mention Thalia's legal expertise. Along with uncomprehending politicians, a fickle public and the implacable equations of space science, they must also battle a hidden villain able to infiltrate the nation's best-protected industrial sites.</p>
        <p>This is a tale with a clear moral: When space beckons, only rascals and cowards will fail to respond. And the way to the stars will be opened not by daredevils with the right stuff but by clear-minded engineers with a sound business plan.</p>
        <p>The full title of Brian W. Aldiss's new novel is WHITE MARS: Or, The Mind Set Free: A 21st Century Utopia (St. Martin's, $23.95). The cover also tells us that it was written ''in collaboration with Roger Penrose,'' a world-renowned mathematical physicist who worked with Stephen Hawking on the understanding of black holes.</p>
        <p>Aldiss and Penrose have combined their considerable talents to produce a parable about right thinking and right living set on a recently colonized Mars. When the economy of the home planet self-destructs, the 6,000 colonists are left alone to work out their destiny. Led by a flawed prophet named Tom Jefferies, they muddle through to a sort of utopia that resembles Plato's Republic without a philosopher-king.</p>
        <p>One nice thing about inventing your own utopia is that you get to institutionalize all your theories, dreams and crotchets. ''White Mars'' embraces both Penrose's speculations about the mind as a quantum-mechanical computer and what I presume to be Aldiss's notions about birth as an exclusively female mystery and about the obsolescence of marriage. But even at its quirkiest, this is a good-natured attempt to rethink the basic rules of human society, and alert readers will find something to applaud and dispute on every page.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
