<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oh, What a Fine Plot We Hatched. (And Here's What to Do the Next Time).</title>
    <meta content="18WORD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WORD FOR WORD/ABC'S OF COUPS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iran-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Risen, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mossadegh, Mohammed</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6D61631F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1420" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oh, What a Fine Plot We Hatched. (And Here's What to Do the Next Time).</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES RISEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Risen, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Word for Word column excerpts Central Intelligence Agency's secret history of its role in 1953 overthrow of Iranian Prime Min Mohammed Mossadegh, intended to serve as blueprint for coup plots elsewhere; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN the Central Intelligence Agency helped overthrow Mohammed  Mossadegh as Iran's prime minister in 1953, ensuring another 25 years of rule for Shah Mohammed Reza Pahlevi, the C.I.A. was already figuring that its first effort to topple a foreign government would not be its last.</p>
        <p>The C.I.A., then just six years old and deeply committed to winning the cold war, viewed its  covert action in Iran as a blueprint for coup plots elsewhere around the world, and so commissioned a secret history to detail for future generations of C.I.A. operatives how it had been done. The history, which remains classified, was recently obtained by The New York Times; excerpts were published this spring and a more complete version is now available on the Times Web site (www.nytimes.com).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN the Central Intelligence Agency helped overthrow Mohammed  Mossadegh as Iran's prime minister in 1953, ensuring another 25 years of rule for Shah Mohammed Reza Pahlevi, the C.I.A. was already figuring that its first effort to topple a foreign government would not be its last.</p>
        <p>The C.I.A., then just six years old and deeply committed to winning the cold war, viewed its  covert action in Iran as a blueprint for coup plots elsewhere around the world, and so commissioned a secret history to detail for future generations of C.I.A. operatives how it had been done. The history, which remains classified, was recently obtained by The New York Times; excerpts were published this spring and a more complete version is now available on the Times Web site (www.nytimes.com).</p>
        <p>Written in the heady aftermath of Tpajax, the code name for the plot, the C.I.A. history enthusiastically recounted the accomplishments of the agency's officers. In fact, the coup would turn out to be the high point in the spy career of its director, Kermit Roosevelt, a grandson of Theodore Roosevelt who died 10 days ago at the age of 84.</p>
        <p>But in a section on what could be learned from the experience, the history also drew lessons for future conspirators, and today reads as a prescient warning of the political and strategic risks that similar covert operations would pose for the United States.</p>
        <p>For example, amid the sometimes curious argot of the spy world -- ''safebases'' and ''assets'' and the like -- the C.I.A. warns of the possibilities of ''blowback.'' The word must have been unfamiliar to the public in 1953 but it has since come into use as a shorthand for the unintended consequences of covert operations. The C.I.A.'s covert action in Afghanistan in the 1980's, which led to the empowerment of anti-Western Islamic fundamentalists there in the 1990's, saw to that.</p>
        <p>''Possibilities of blowback against the United States should always be in the back of the minds of all C.I.A. officers involved in this type of operation,'' the history cautions.</p>
        <p>That was only one of the lessons drawn -- not all of which seem to have been heeded. Here is a sample.</p>
        <p>JAMES RISEN</p>
        <p>The history warns that the C.I.A. should always count on things getting very messy:</p>
        <p>''The possibility of civil war must be accepted by our military planners and measures taken within the plan for that eventuality. Such an eventuality might possibly include the necessity for establishing a safebase for the new friendly government. Possibilities and eventualities stemming from civil war can only be seen upon the analysis of each local situation, but they are not difficult to foresee and should certainly be planned for. . . . The possibility of action against mobs must be considered, including action against Communist paramilitary forces from factories, etc. Where this contingency exists it may be necessary to dispose friendly forces in such a way as to neutralize entire cities through the use of roadblocks, strong points, traffic control, curfews, new documentation, etc.''</p>
        <p>The Iran operation very nearly failed, and the C.I.A. was on the verge of abandoning it when the tide turned in its favor. The chief planner of the coup, Dr. Donald N. Wilber, who wrote the history, thus came away from Iran with a fatalistic view of covert action.</p>
        <p>''Military planning should include the possibilities of complete failure and, therefore, should include an evacuation scheme for C.I.A. and indigenous personnel who might be exposed. Aircraft of American military attaches, evasion and escape nets, and other operations assets might have to be employed.</p>
        <p>If none of these assets exists then hiding places should be created in advance of the operation which are kept sterile throughout. . . .''</p>
        <p>''Military planning should be based upon the principle that some elements without our friendly forces will be exposed, and that our operation must not collapse on that account. Therefore, danger signals should be included which automatically call for movement from one phase to the other depending upon who or what units have been exposed to the hostile government. In Iran there was good reason to believe that danger signals so noted prior to the change of government were instrumental in keeping alive an operation which, to an outsider, appeared to have failed.''</p>
        <p>The decision to topple the Iranian government was made quickly in Washington in early 1953 by the new Eisenhower administration, and it represented an abrupt policy change. So the C.I.A. had not done its homework when called on by President Eisenhower. The C.I.A.'s history discusses its frustrating efforts to get up to speed, including fruitless contacts with Army intelligence (G-2 in military shorthand) and draws a cautionary lesson for planners of future C.I.A. plots: know a little about a country you may be called upon to transform.</p>
        <p>''Throughout the summer (of 1953) cables were exchanged with the Tehran Station in an effort to procure the latest information on the order of battle of Iranian armed forces. The Iranian desk, G-2, Pentagon, was queried in an effort to obtain whatever information they could get which might help accomplish the above tasks. Information available in G-2 was almost nonexistent. Biographical information on leading Army figures was extremely scanty. G-2 did not possess a tactical map showing the military situation in the city of Tehran. It must also be admitted that C.I.A. too was unprepared for this type of operational plan and a heavy burden had to be laid upon the field at a time when the Tehran station was already occupied with the opening phases of Tpajax.</p>
        <p>''The primary difficulty in staff planning at this time was the fact that neither the field nor Headquarters possessed detailed information on military figures in Iran. C.I.A. had heretofore never placed particular emphasis on that type of operational reporting, and we learned as the days went by how extremely important, indeed vital, that type of reporting is.''</p>
        <p>One reason the coup nearly failed was that the  Mossadegh government found out about the coup plot just before it was begun. Iranian officers working for the C.I.A. were arrested as they tried to take control of the government. Although the coup succeeded on a second attempt, the history warned that if the C.I.A. hoped to keep trying to overthrow governments, it had to keep its plans secret. Unfortunately, it was a lesson that the planners of the Bay of Pigs operation in Cuba in 1961 did not learn well enough.</p>
        <p>''A final subject of interest concerns the security problem connected with such an operation. From the moment the project got underway, the N.E.A. [Near East and Africa] Division made a serious effort to put special security measures into effect; within the N.E.A. Division and even within the NE/4 Branch the rule of need to know came into effect. However, by the time the operation had been concluded, a considerable number of people British and Americans were aware of what was going on.</p>
        <p>From the viewpoint of NE/4 Branch, which has listed all the individuals whom it knows were aware of the project and its purpose, the number was excessive -- it totaled 89. How many others were told by people without the NE/4 Branch being aware of this, there is no way of knowing. It is true that the knowledge that there was direct U.S.-U.K. collaboration on the project was kept to a more restricted number. It is, however, suggested that in the future when an operation of similar magnitude and sensitivity is contemplated a special security officer be brought into the operation at its inception and be given the responsibility for keeping track of exactly who knows what about the project.''</p>
        <p>The history included a haunting reminder to C.I.A. planners of the future that promises to spies and agents must be made in a form that could be kept, a lesson that the United States seemed to forget in Vietnam.</p>
        <p>''Commitments to friendly persons should be kept well within our ability to make good. . . . Forethought should also be given to the problem of care and keep of wives and families of friendly officers.''</p>
        <p>WORD FOR WORD/ABC'S OF COUPS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
