<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="18FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208494"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7DD1431F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-11</p>
        <p>Korean Accord Stirs Missile Defense Debate  The summit meeting between the Korean leaders has left the Clinton administration divided over North Korea's intentions, but has not diminished its resolve to go ahead with a missile defense, officials say.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-11</p>
        <p>Korean Accord Stirs Missile Defense Debate  The summit meeting between the Korean leaders has left the Clinton administration divided over North Korea's intentions, but has not diminished its resolve to go ahead with a missile defense, officials say.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Hundreds of protestors demanding the withdrawal of American troops clashed with riot police in South Korea, leaving at least 20 people injured.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Reservists Adapt to New Role  Guard and Reserve commanders argue that the nation's citizen-soldiers, with their experience and skills honed in the civilian world, may in fact be better prepared than their active-duty counterparts for the subtle tasks of rebuilding a nation devastated by war, like Bosnia.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Syria Unites Behind New Leader  Syria's Baath Party, the structural support beneath the 30-year rule of the late Hafez al-Assad, gathered to pledge allegiance to his son, Bashar, and to vest him formally with the political authority he has quietly exercised for the last two years.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Zimbabwe Election Approaches  President Robert Mugabe of Zimbabwe, with parliamentary elections a week away, blamed campaign violence on the opposition and urged thousands to keep the peace.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>Air Control Fails in Britain  The failure of an air traffic controller computer delayed flights in and out of British airports as well as flights crossing over the country. The National Air Traffic Services promised a thorough investigation.</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>12-22</p>
        <p>Parties' Differences On Drug Plans Widen  Medicare drug benefits have emerged as one of the more potent political issues in this year's elections. Both Republicans and Democrats say the goal is to make drug coverage available and affordable, but the parties' differences on the details are widening by the day.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Border Ranches Besieged  Ranches around Douglas, Ariz., have come under siege by migrants seeking illegal entry into the United States as other crossing points have become harder to penetrate.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Reversal in Crime Feared  Law enforcement officials and criminologists believe that the decline in violent crime may have finally come to an end, with the number of homicides in some big cities rising in recent months.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>California Official in Scandal  California's insurance commissioner is fighting charges that he allowed insurance companies to shortchange earthquake victims in return for contributions to a political slush fund.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>A Virginia Senate Race Tightens  Senator Charles S. Robb of Virginia has rallied in a race to defend his seat. Once trailing, he is now about even with the Republican challenger, former Gov. George F. Allen.</p>
        <p>18</p>
        <p>Bush Criticizes Security Lapses  Gov. George W. Bush crisscrossed Florida and criticized security lapses at the Los Alamos National Laboratory, saying ''America's nuclear security should not be a matter of lost and found.''</p>
        <p>18</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>25-30</p>
        <p>Defective Aircraft Cable Draws Different Responses  After a company from upstate New York acknowledged that it had sold faulty cable for years to both military and civilian aircraft manufacturers, the response from the military was starkly different from that of the F.A.A.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Way Off Broadway  On any given night there are 20 to 30 small, low-budget plays or musicals performed in the city that are unknown to even the most stalwart of theatergoers. They are supported in a city that is full of talented people, forgotten material, willing audiences and not enough work for actors.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Plan for Spraying Canceled  New York City health officials called off plans to spray insecticide in Queens after two laboratories concluded that a chicken thought to have contracted the West Nile virus was not infected.</p>
        <p>29</p>
        <p>Fresh Air Fund</p>
        <p>29</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>31-32</p>
        <p>Garrett Eckbo  A pioneer of modern landscape design and a leading practitioner of California landscape architecture, he was 89.</p>
        <p>32</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>31  Weather</p>
        <p>33</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
