<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Shrinking Violet The Dahlia Is Not</title>
    <meta content="18CUT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dahlias (Flowers)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peterson, Cass</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E7DA1F3EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Shrinking Violet The Dahlia Is Not</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CASS PETERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Peterson, Cass</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cass Peterson column on growing dahlias; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOST of my gardening this year will be done on an apartment balcony and in a timber-edged flower bed about 4 feet wide and 10 feet long. Gardening on such a scale after enjoying the extravagant space of a farmstead requires an adjustment.</p>
        <p>Already I mildly regret giving space in the flower bed to three clumps of Siberian iris. I like perennials in clumps of three or five, but I'm not used to running out of room so fast. So I planted the iris too close together, telling myself this is a temporary garden, and the iris -- like me -- will have more space before the crowding becomes intolerable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOST of my gardening this year will be done on an apartment balcony and in a timber-edged flower bed about 4 feet wide and 10 feet long. Gardening on such a scale after enjoying the extravagant space of a farmstead requires an adjustment.</p>
        <p>Already I mildly regret giving space in the flower bed to three clumps of Siberian iris. I like perennials in clumps of three or five, but I'm not used to running out of room so fast. So I planted the iris too close together, telling myself this is a temporary garden, and the iris -- like me -- will have more space before the crowding becomes intolerable.</p>
        <p>Aside from the space crunch, there's a sun problem. Both the flower bed and the balcony face northwest and get direct sun for only a few hours before sunset. That isn't enough for many of my favorite sun-loving plants. I'm going to miss the cascading petunias, Mexican heather, ivy geraniums and Yubi portulaca that I grew on my former sun deck, and the sunflowers, hollyhocks and lavender that I grew in the yard.</p>
        <p>What I'll miss most are dahlias. I have a weakness for tropical-looking plants with flamboyant blossoms, and the dahlia -- the national flower of Mexico, after all -- plays to all my addictions. The foliage is luxurious and abundant; the flowers are eyepoppers in racy colors. They also bloom in late summer and fall, generally a slack period for flowers.</p>
        <p>The late garden writer Henry Mitchell said dahlias look best ''in a sunny field among the corn and pumpkins,'' which was his elegant way of suggesting that they display, if not downright vulgarity, at least a lack of refinement. He grew them anyway. Who wouldn't?</p>
        <p>But it isn't just the sheer size of dahlia plants that eliminates them from consideration in my space-constrained garden. It's true that exhibition dahlias -- those with flamboyant blooms the size of dinner plates -- grow on immense plants, easily shoulder high. But I've known people to grow bananas on fire escapes. I've no problem with a potted dahlia elbowing out the patio chairs.</p>
        <p>Besides, there are smaller dahlias, like pompons, collarettes (the ones with a ring of petals around a fluffy center) and mignons (single-flowered). Bedding-plant varieties, like Figaro, produce two-inch flowers on plants about a foot tall.</p>
        <p>However, dahlias like sun, the more the better, and a few hours of late afternoon sunshine will not be enough to make them happy.</p>
        <p>Dahlias have passionate fans. Serious devotees flock together in societies and attend dahlia shows, where they admire new varieties and collect tubers of named dahlia cultivars to add to their collections.</p>
        <p>I have grown some of those famous dahlias myself, but several years ago I switched to growing dahlias strictly as cutting flowers from seed. The resulting blossoms are a motley lot, some with a formal decorative form and some not so formal; some with slender, quilled petals bursting out of the center like exploding fireworks, some with a single tier of fat flat petals gently turned up at the edges.</p>
        <p>Seed-grown dahlias form tubers their first season in the ground, so I could have reproduced any of those flowers the next year by unearthing the tubers before the first hard freeze and storing them over winter to be replanted the next spring.</p>
        <p>Some gardeners have trouble storing dahlia tubers, possibly because their houses lack a storage spot that is dark, cool and neither too moist nor too dry. In the absence of a root cellar, pack the tubers in a plastic bag with dry peat moss and put them where the temperature goes as low as possible without freezing.</p>
        <p>Mitchell advised planting dahlias at lilac time, but he lived in Washington, which has rather more hot air than other cities and a warmer climate. To keep the tubers from rotting, it's better to wait for the ground to warm thoroughly. A few weeks after lilac time is ideal -- late May or early June in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>When planting dahlia tubers, look for the eye or bud on the tuber. You won't have to divide new tubers bought at garden centers or by mail, but tubers you have saved from your own garden will need dividing. Be sure each division has an eye.</p>
        <p>Plant the tubers about eight inches deep with the eye up. For standard-size dahlias, now is the time to put in a stake to support the plant. Make it a sturdy one, five or six feet tall, and pound it in firmly. A full-grown dahlia plant is amazingly heavy, especially after a rain. Tie the plant to the stake every week or so as it grows.</p>
        <p>It's a good idea to pinch the plant back once when it's about a foot tall, to encourage it to bush out. Because they produce so much foliage, dahlias also need to be fed once or twice during the season. Any general-purpose fertilizer will do.</p>
        <p>Dahlias form buds in clusters of three. If you want the largest, showiest flowers, you'll need to break off the two side buds and let only the topmost bud develop. You will also need to remove any leaf buds that develop on the stem below the flower bud, or your flower may be imperfect. Growers of exhibition dahlias need to be a little obsessive.</p>
        <p>For maximum garden effect, though, you can let all the buds bloom. Even a single dahlia plant in bloom makes a statement.</p>
        <p>Perhaps I'll find space for just one, in a large pot. If it starts to look peaked from lack of sun, I can always take it to the beach for the weekend.</p>
        <p>Garden centers and many garden catalogs carry tubers of named dahlia varieties. Van Bourgondien Brothers (P.O. Box 1000, 245 Farmingdale Road, Babylon, N.Y. 11702, 800-622-9959, free catalog) has a nice selection, or you might try a specialist like Elkhorn Gardens (P.O. Box 1149, Carmel, Calif. 93921, 831-761-2280, free catalog).</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
