<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First-Rate On Second Avenue</title>
    <meta content="18REST$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOOD EATING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Good Eating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DC1F3EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First-Rate On Second Avenue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from previously published reviews of restaurants along Manhattan's Second Avenue (Good Eating column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHIANTI  **  [Rating: two stars]  (212) 980-8686; 1043 Second Avenue, at 55th Street; $$; smoking at the bar; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>Chianti is offering some extremely impressive dishes at very reasonable prices. In addition to fine hand-made pasta, an extensive selection of antipasti and grilled meats, you will see unusual dishes like roasted salmon with balsamic honey glaze. Appetizers include asparagus soup with spinach, potato and goat cheese ravioli; braised boneless short ribs of beef and vegetable risotto; and roasted wild mushrooms with creamy polenta and parmesan. Entrees include herbed baby chicken scarpariello, artichoke and garlic; pan-seared filet of Atlantic sole with Sicilian capers and lemon; pepper-coated aged sirloin steak with Yukon gold mashed potatoes; and ravioli with bufala ricotta, spinach and plum tomato sauce. (Review: 11/11/ 98)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHIANTI  **  [Rating: two stars]  (212) 980-8686; 1043 Second Avenue, at 55th Street; $$; smoking at the bar; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>Chianti is offering some extremely impressive dishes at very reasonable prices. In addition to fine hand-made pasta, an extensive selection of antipasti and grilled meats, you will see unusual dishes like roasted salmon with balsamic honey glaze. Appetizers include asparagus soup with spinach, potato and goat cheese ravioli; braised boneless short ribs of beef and vegetable risotto; and roasted wild mushrooms with creamy polenta and parmesan. Entrees include herbed baby chicken scarpariello, artichoke and garlic; pan-seared filet of Atlantic sole with Sicilian capers and lemon; pepper-coated aged sirloin steak with Yukon gold mashed potatoes; and ravioli with bufala ricotta, spinach and plum tomato sauce. (Review: 11/11/ 98)</p>
        <p>MAISON  *  [Rating: one star]  (212) 879-4824; 1477 Second Avenue, at 77th Street; $$; smoking at the bar; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>Maison's kitchen consistently turns out well executed, imaginative bistro fare that, at its best, is downright thrilling. Appetizers include artichoke and plum tomato tart with eggplant caviar and fresh thyme; seared Hudson Valley foie gras with mango and jerez; and sweet Vidalia onion soup with Gruyere croutons. Main dishes include steak with pommes frites and bearnaise sauce; crispy skate with hazelnut potatoes and beurre noisette; and Guinness-braised short ribs with bone marrow, lentils and crisp onions. Desserts include vanilla panna cotta with macerated raisins. (Review: 8/25/99)</p>
        <p>PALM  +++  (212) 687-2953; 837 Second Avenue, between 44th and 45th Streets; $$$; smoking section; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>Great steak and crisp, buttery  hash brown potatoes can be found at this establishment, which began in 1926. The walls are covered with caricatures and the floor is covered with sawdust. Appetizers include clams oreganato; crab meat cocktail; anchovies and pimentos; shrimp bruno; and fried calamari.  Entrees include swordfish steak; broiled crab cakes; chicken piccata; filet mignon; prime aged New York strip; veal marsala; linguine with clam sauce; and rigatoni bolognese. (New York Today: April 1998)</p>
        <p>TAPERIA MADRID  +  (212) 794-2923; 1471 Second Avenue, between 76th and 77th Streets; $; smoking at the bar; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>From the low timbered ceiling to the wood plank floor and the long family-style tables with wide benches, Taperia Madrid has every appearance of a credible Spanish tapas bar. The tapas include little scallops, cooked quickly and served on the half shell with roe intact; boquerones, or marinated anchovies; Spanish sausage, sliced into neat rounds; shrimp in garlic sauce; a tortilla filled with an omelet and onions and potatoes. Desserts include caramel flan or Spanish cheeses, like torta del casar, a buttery sheep's milk cheese, or Garrotxa, a rich goat's milk cheese. ($25 and Under: 8/4/99)</p>
        <p>THADY CON'S  +++  (212) 688-9700; 915 Second Avenue, between 48th and 49th Streets; $; smoking permitted; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>This Irish restaurant is as cute as an ad for Aer Lingus. It's got four working fireplaces, beer on draft and a menu of mutton, salmon and lots of potatoes. Appetizers include creamy seafood chowder served with homemade breads; steamed mussels in vegetable wine sauce; Irish-style cocktail sausages with curried mayonnaise dip; and twice-baked potato skins with scallions and cheese with bacon. Entrees include Irish smoked salmon plate with horseradish cream and capers; beer-battered cod and homemade french fries; sirloin steak with French fries and mushroom ragout; and fresh fettuccine with roasted vegetables in basil sauce with tofu or chicken. (New York Today: April 1998)</p>
        <p>ZARELA  +++  (212) 644-6740; 953 Second Avenue, between 50th and 51st Streets; $$; smoking at the bar; all major credit cards; www.zarela.com.</p>
        <p>Zarela Martinez has written several excellent Mexican cookbooks, and she does her native cuisine proud by serving some of the city's most exciting and authentic Mexican food. Starters include corn tortillas filled with chicken and cheese, baked with choice of spicy pumpkinseed sauce or Oaxacan mole; baked white cheddar cheese with either pickled jalapenos or homemade chorizo; and fried calamari in a spicy tomato, onion, green olive and pickled jalapeno sauce. Entrees include sauteed shrimp with poblano chilies, onions and queso blanco; roasted half duck served with a tomato red chile sauce with dried apricots, prunes, raisins and pineapple; and tuna steak seared rare, with spicy sesame seed and tomatillo sauce. (New York Today: April 1998)</p>
        <p>Summaries taken from reviews use the star ratings. Others are taken from the $25 and Under column (+) and articles (++), and capsule revies from New York Today: www.nytoday.com (+++).</p>
        <p>What the Stars Mean</p>
        <p>**** -- Extraordinary  *** -- Excellent  ** -- Very Good  * -- Good  None Poor to Satisfactory</p>
        <p>Price Range  Based on the cost of a three-course dinner, per person, tax, tip and drinks not included.</p>
        <p>$ -- $25 and under  $$ -- $25 to $40  $$$ -- $40 to $55  $$$$ -- $55 and over</p>
        <p>Past Reviews -- Good Eating columns back to June 1998, along with reviews from The Times and capsule reviews by Times critics of additional restaurants not reviewed in the newspaper, are available on New York Today.</p>
        <p>GOOD EATING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
