<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>School Superintendents at a Premium</title>
    <meta content="18SCHO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208201"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ain, Stewart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E0DE103EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1392" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>School Superintendents at a Premium</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEWART AIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ain, Stewart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on shortage of candidates for school administrators on Long Island, whch has led many school districts to hire retired superintendents for interim positions; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR an increasing number of Long Island school superintendents, retirement is just the start of another career in education -- as interim school administrators.</p>
        <p>''When I interview for an interim superintendency, I'm interviewing with four or five of my colleagues,'' said Robert Ricken, who retired 12 years ago as superintendent of the Mineola School District but has since served as an interim superintendent in seven districts and as an assistant superintendent in another.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR an increasing number of Long Island school superintendents, retirement is just the start of another career in education -- as interim school administrators.</p>
        <p>''When I interview for an interim superintendency, I'm interviewing with four or five of my colleagues,'' said Robert Ricken, who retired 12 years ago as superintendent of the Mineola School District but has since served as an interim superintendent in seven districts and as an assistant superintendent in another.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ricken and others are being called out of retirement because of what Alice F. Willett, acting executive director of the Nassau-Suffolk School Boards Association, called a ''dearth of leadership.''</p>
        <p>''A lot of people don't want to go into central administrative positions because sometimes senior teachers make more than they do,'' Ms. Willett said, ''and they don't have good bargaining positions.'' Superintendents are the only administrators who cannot earn tenure.</p>
        <p>''Even an assistant superintendent has tenure,'' Dr. Ricken noted. ''Many of them say that they would rather forgo the higher salary of a superintendent and have the security of tenure.''</p>
        <p>In addition to questions about pay and tenure, the supply of candidates has been reduced by the cutbacks in teaching staff in the early 1990's, which left a gap in the flow of midcareer teachers interested in administrative jobs.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ricken said that when he retired 12 years ago, his district received 159 applications for his job. Today, he said, districts get only 20 to 25 applications.</p>
        <p>Finding high school principals and department chairmen is also difficult. ''If I'm a physical education teacher, why would I want to be a chairperson if I could earn another $15,000 coaching a team and work only 10 months?'' Dr. Ricken asked.</p>
        <p>Francis Banta, who retired two years ago as superintendent of the Oyster Bay-East Norwich School District, said he was hired in January as acting assistant superintendent for instruction and administration in Smithtown, which needed someone in the middle of the school year ''who was knowledgeable about administrative practices, state regulations, curriculum and personnel.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Banta works for the Suffolk County Organization for the Promotion of Education, or Scope, and was hired by Scope to be a consultant for the district.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ricken, who is interim superintendent at the Bellmore-Merrick Central High School District, noted that retired superintendents who serve as acting superintendents must first obtain a waiver from the State Education Commissioner to continue receiving their pensions.</p>
        <p>''Getting a waiver used to be a big deal,'' Dr. Ricken recalled. ''But the commissioner now realizes that he has to help out the districts.''</p>
        <p>Also making retired superintendents attractive, he said, is that although districts have to pay competitive salaries, the retirees already have health benefits and pensions, so the total wage package comes to only 40 percent of the usual costs.</p>
        <p>Many superintendents who retired in their 50's have stayed active at any rate. Dr. Banta, for instance, set up a consulting Web site, www.zazz .com/education, that caught the eye of the United States Information Agency, which hired him as a mentor for a group of teachers from Cyprus who wanted to learn administrative and teaching techniques.</p>
        <p>''I also worked with the Middle States Association doing accreditation of schools in Bahrain, Kuwait, Syria and Saudi Arabia,'' he said. ''The schools want to be accredited so their students could attend American colleges.''</p>
        <p>The demand for retired superintendents is such that even before James Brucia retired last June after 11 years as superintendent in the Massapequa district, he had been hired to serve as interim principal of the Newbridge Road School, in North Bellmore.</p>
        <p>''I had met the superintendent here at a conference in October and he alerted me that there might be a need for a principal as an interim because the principal was in line to be superintendent elsewhere,'' Dr. Brucia said. ''Rather than conduct a search in mid-year, he asked if I would do it. I said yes because I had not been an elementary principal and I wanted the experience. I've been delighted.</p>
        <p>''Districts need people with experience to give them leeway to conduct a good search. Otherwise, the district would be thrown into turmoil.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Harry Jaroslaw, president of the Nassau County Council of School Superintendents, said there are at least two high schools on Long Island that have not yet been able to find a principal for next year.</p>
        <p>''There are several reasons for it,'' he said, ''given the job responsibility, the fact that you are constantly out there in the open in terms of decision making, and that your starting salary is not much different than a senior teacher. Relative to the responsibilities, many people don't want the pressure that comes with the job.''</p>
        <p>Frank Carasiti retired in 1990 after 27 years as superintendent in Rocky Point, but on June 30 he will be finishing an 18-month stint as interim superintendent of the new Eastport/South Manor Central High School District, the seventh district in which he has served as interim superintendent.</p>
        <p>''I didn't solicit or actively seek any of the positions,'' he said. ''I enjoy the challenge: It is a heartache kind of job; taxes and money are always a problem. It's an awesome, time-consuming job; it demands so much.''</p>
        <p>Adding to the problem is an ''extraordinary turnover rate'' in Suffolk, according to Candee Swenson, president of the Suffolk County School Superintendents Association. ''The vast majority of districts have superintendents who joined within the last couple of years,'' she said. ''And districts are reporting that they are disappointed by the number of applications.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Swenson, who is superintendent of the Longwood School District in Middle Island, said that to move to a central office position, a person ''must have a significant level of experience and education.''</p>
        <p>''Individuals with those credentials are often tenured and making a salary that is higher,'' she said. ''So we are asking them to give up their salary, benefits and security to accept the challenge and the greater workload of the higher position.''</p>
        <p>She noted also that because of state financial difficulties and shrinking enrollments in the early 1990's, ''many districts had to reduce staff and had to cut the youngest and newest entrants, including administrators.'' As a result, the pool of teachers who might have considered administrative positions after 5 or 10 years' experience is not there.</p>
        <p>''So out of necessity we are using interims,'' she said. ''But I think it's starting to turn around now because we are in better economic times and people are recognizing that to attract candidates, you have to improve salaries and benefits. In the last 12 months, the maximum salary of a superintendent in a middle-sized school district was $130,000. Now it is common to see salaries of $145,000 to $150,000, the first substantial movement we have seen in a decade.''</p>
        <p>In another effort to solve the shortage, the Suffolk group Scope is developing a program to attract talented teachers to be administrators. The key is to provide job security, according to Leonard Adler, who is overseeing the project.</p>
        <p>''We at Scope want to take a successful classroom teacher who shows signs of leadership and ask them to go for their administrator's certificate while we protect their teaching job,'' said Dr. Adler. ''A lot of people who are gainfully employed in education can't take a year off; we will put them in an assistant principal position while they take classes at night in educational administration. And they will get paid what they were making as a teacher.''</p>
        <p>A retired principal serves as a mentor, and after the year, the teacher can apply for the administrative job or go back to the classroom, where the former job would be waiting.</p>
        <p>Dr. Adler said both school districts and a number of teachers have expressed interest in the program.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
