<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Sage to Idiot in Record Time</title>
    <meta content="18DAD.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FATHERHOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robinson, Kenton</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5DC103EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Sage to Idiot in Record Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kenton Robinson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robinson, Kenton</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kenton Robinson Fatherhood column describes Village Idiot stage of fatherhood he recently entered when his 11-year-old daughter asked him to buy her a CD with explicit lyrics sticker attached; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU are standing in a record store. You are looking down at your daughter. She's 11 going on 27. You, on the other hand, are about to go from 47 to 104. But neither of you knows that yet.</p>
        <p>She is holding something behind her back.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU are standing in a record store. You are looking down at your daughter. She's 11 going on 27. You, on the other hand, are about to go from 47 to 104. But neither of you knows that yet.</p>
        <p>She is holding something behind her back.</p>
        <p>She gives you the big-eye.</p>
        <p>''Daddy?''</p>
        <p>''Yes?''</p>
        <p>''Would you buy me this CD without looking at the cover?''</p>
        <p>You think: ''What can it be? She still plays with dolls.''</p>
        <p>You say: ''Of course not. You know I can't do that.''</p>
        <p>She mounts her argument: ''There's nothing wrong with the songs. They're really good, and I really want this. It's just that you might not like the cover. Can't you just buy it for me?''</p>
        <p>''I have to see it.''</p>
        <p>Finally, she gives in, handing you the disk with the sigh, ''You're never going to let me get it.''</p>
        <p>It's a group you've heard of, but still the cover stuns you: a lustful nurse, her bust busting through her blouse's buttons, leers at you as she pulls on a blue rubber glove.</p>
        <p>An ''EXPLICIT LYRICS'' sticker sticks to her elbow.</p>
        <p>You draw in your breath.</p>
        <p>You flip the disk over, but the back's no better: A pack of adolescent boys -- the band -- drools as the nurse -- her back, mercifully, to the camera -- appears to be hiking up the front of her skirt.</p>
        <p>The album is titled ''Enema of the State.''</p>
        <p>''Uh, I don't think so,'' you say.</p>
        <p>''Why not? C'mon. It's just the cover. The songs are all right.''</p>
        <p>It is precisely at this moment that you begin to become a brand new father.</p>
        <p>Not that you aren't a father already. You've been at it now for nearly a dozen years. You've been pooped, peed and puked on. You've done diapers, discipline, first steps and the first days of school. You know that men who are never fathers may have but a single trade, but fathers have them all: You've been storyteller, lawgiver, psychologist and philosopher, doctor, singer, comedian and coroner. When friends have abandoned her, you've been her wise adviser. When her dogs, fish, cats and caterpillars have died, you've ministered their funerals.</p>
        <p>But fatherhood is not a state of being. One does not simply become a father the day his child is born and stay a father from then on. At that point, you're little more than a sperm donor. And you're still in father kindergarten.</p>
        <p>No, fatherhood is always changing. As the philosopher Heraclitus said, ''You cannot step on the same father twice.''</p>
        <p>You even go through a series of stages, and each time you go through one of them, you're a brand new father all over again:</p>
        <p>Stage 1: The Gardener. New babies most resemble butternut squash; their personalities, I mean. At this point your job is to feed and weed them. Easy.</p>
        <p>Stage 2: The Clown. When they start talking and moving around, things get interesting. The best part of this stage is that you get to tell all the old groaners, jokes as old as the seventh day of creation, and be thought the funniest man on the planet.</p>
        <p>Stage 3: The Sage. Suddenly, you're not only funny; you are incredibly wise. Or expected to be. This is when you must know everything, from why birds sing to why they die.</p>
        <p>Stage 4: The Old Fogy. A brief, transitional stage. Now you're stodgy and stiff, and there's a musty smell about you. But at least you're still vaguely amusing and have some sentimental value.</p>
        <p>Stage 5: The Village Idiot. ''Hellooo? Anybody home? Can you say MOR-ON? Can you see how you've just humiliated me TO DEATH?'' Yes, you're a moron. But not just any moron, you're HER moron.</p>
        <p>Fatherhood is like going to graduate school forever and never getting a diploma. You're striving for that Fh.D. degree, but every day they change the requirements, and every day brings another exam that you didn't know you had to study for.</p>
        <p>Such as today's exam in the record store. That's right. You've stumbled straight into Stage 4, fogyhood, transforming before your daughter's eyes: shrinking, wrinkling, wizening, as long white hairs sprout from your ears like fountains.</p>
        <p>''Honey, I can't buy you this,'' you say.</p>
        <p>''Why not? All my friends have it.''</p>
        <p>''Well, you'll just have to listen to it at your friends' houses then.''</p>
        <p>''But why not? It's just the cover.''</p>
        <p>You think: ''What's the answer? I knew I should have studied for this.''</p>
        <p>You look down into that earnest face. You think: ''Because you still take Mr. Kitty on our trips.''</p>
        <p>You say: ''Because it's degrading to women.''</p>
        <p>''But that's not a reason. I want it for the songs. The songs are O.K.''</p>
        <p>''I don't want to support a group that exploits women to sell its music,'' you say, thinking of all your Rolling Stones albums.</p>
        <p>Your daughter scowls and looks right through you.</p>
        <p>You're free falling right through fogyhood, from Sage to Idiot in record time.</p>
        <p>''Besides,'' you say, ''your mother would kill me.''</p>
        <p>FATHERHOOD The author, who has two children, is a writer from West Hartford.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">The author, who has two children, is a writer from West Hartford.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
