<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Man Who Quit 'Blue,' Still Making a Comeback</title>
    <meta content="CARUSO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208566"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COVER STORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weinraub, Bernard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caruso, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Deadlocked (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Nypd Blue (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E6DA1431F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1257" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Man Who Quit 'Blue,' Still Making a Comeback</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD WEINRAUB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weinraub, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with actor David Caruso on his new television movie Deadlocked, and struggles he has had to find good roles since notorious exit from show NYPD Blue; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Six years ago, David Caruso left ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' in a highly-publicized bid for movie stardom. But Mr. Caruso, who had co-starred with Dennis Franz on the acclaimed police drama on ABC for a bit more than a year, fell on his face.</p>
        <p>Not only did his films, like ''Kiss of Death'' and ''Jade,'' fail, but his departure from ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' left a sour aftertaste in Hollywood that, still, to some degree, remains. He was depicted as alternately ungrateful, insecure, greedy and envious of his co-star on the police show. His replacement, Jimmy Smits, who played Det. Bobby Simone, flourished on the show from 1994-1998, To make matters worse for Mr. Caruso, a well-received((RATHER, WELL-REVIEWED?)) 1997 television series, CBS's ''Michael Hayes,'' in which the actor starred as a downbeat district attorney, also floundered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Six years ago, David Caruso left ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' in a highly-publicized bid for movie stardom. But Mr. Caruso, who had co-starred with Dennis Franz on the acclaimed police drama on ABC for a bit more than a year, fell on his face.</p>
        <p>Not only did his films, like ''Kiss of Death'' and ''Jade,'' fail, but his departure from ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' left a sour aftertaste in Hollywood that, still, to some degree, remains. He was depicted as alternately ungrateful, insecure, greedy and envious of his co-star on the police show. His replacement, Jimmy Smits, who played Det. Bobby Simone, flourished on the show from 1994-1998, To make matters worse for Mr. Caruso, a well-received((RATHER, WELL-REVIEWED?)) 1997 television series, CBS's ''Michael Hayes,'' in which the actor starred as a downbeat district attorney, also floundered.</p>
        <p>''My leaving of 'N .Y.P.D. Blue' had become notorious,'' Mr. Caruso said quietly in a recent interview. ''I became the guy who had this great opportunity and walked away from it. People still see me as this enigma.'' He shrugged. ''It was my fault,'' he said. ''But now maybe I can do it differently and maybe I have a chance to get another shot.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Caruso is aware that his starring role in the new Turner Network Television film ''Deadlocked,'' which has its premiere on Sunday, June 18 at 8 p.m., will not fully restore his career to the same lustre he achieved in the days of ''N.Y.P.D. Blue''. But it's a promising step forward.</p>
        <p>In the film, Mr. Caruso plays a prosecutor who helps convict a youth (Jo D. Jonz) of raping and murdering his wealthy employer's wife. But the youth's father, played by Charles Dutton, is convinced his son's innocence. The Dutton character takes the jury hostage with one demand: that the prosecutor, played by Mr. Caruso, find the evidence to clear the young man of his crime in 24 hours.</p>
        <p>''It looks like a slam-dunk case, but we find out that we really haven't looked at all the evidence,'' said Mr. Caruso. ''This guy I play is forced to look at himself and his life. And although he has a pretty shiny exterior, he's really not good at his job and not really a decent human being. And he's forced to see that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Caruso himself seemed uncharacteristically relaxed and forthcoming as he sat late one afternoon, sipping coffee in a near-empty restaurant in Beverly Hills. He spoke effortlessly. Although he often plays brooding and restless men --and has a reputation for privacy -- he was surprisingly blunt in discussing his somewhat troubled career and his elusive quest for stardom.</p>
        <p>He is back home on a brief hiatus from filming ''Proof of Life,'' with Meg Ryan and Russell Crowe. In the film Mr. Caruso plays an investigator specializing in kidnapping and ransom cases, who is seeking the release of a hostage. It's not the starring role in the film, but he was delighted to get it because it reteams the actor with the director Taylor Hayford. Hackford gave Mr. Caruso one of his early career breaks playing a frightened flight cadet in ''An Officer and a Gentleman'' (1982).</p>
        <p>Mr. Caruso said he was happy to take secondary parts in films as long as they are strong and well-written. As for television, he hopes that the shadow still clinging to him because of his departure from ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' will fade, with projects like ''Deadlocked.''</p>
        <p>TNT executives sought out Mr. Caruso for the film.</p>
        <p>Iris Grossman, senior vice president of talent and casting at the network, said that the actor brings an unusual sense of mystery, even darkness, to a role. ''We didn't want the stereotypical hero,'' Ms. Grossman said. ''We were looking for someone with an edge. He brings a life to his characters that's different and interesting. There's something mysterious about David. He gives his characters unusual depth.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, Julie Weitz, executive vice president of original programming at TNT, said that the network had long sought to work with Mr. Caruso. ''He has a lot of energy and anger in him, he has a lot of heart,'' said Ms. Weitz. ''This was a character that needed that. We felt David could demonstrate those emotions. We knew he could pull it off. You could see that in his face.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Caruso's life, and accent, are rooted in New York. His parents were divorced when he was a child. His father, Charles, is a former editor at Newsweek magazine. After graduating from Archbiship Molloy High School in Queens, Mr. Caruso moved to Manhattan to seek an acting career. He worked mostly as a messenger and waiter. Jobs were scarce. On the advice of agents and friends he moved to Los Angeles where his intensity and good looks opened the way for acting roles, often as policemen or psychopaths. Besides ''An Officer and a Gentleman,'' his movies included ''First Blood'' in 1982 and ''China Girl'' in 1987.</p>
        <p>Then, in 1993, came ''N.Y.P.D. Blue.'' In retrospect, said Mr. Caruso, now 44, he was frightened by the show's sudden success and the attention paid to him.</p>
        <p>''In all honesty, I just didn't have the tools,'' he said. ''I didn't know how to handle the responsibility. I handled it like an amateur. I didn't realize how upset people were until the show was over. I didn't get it. And I think it has a lot to do with fear. I mean, I was terrified I couldn't meet the challenge of the job. The quality level was very high for the show, and I was in a full-blown panic. I didn't want to lose it after all those years of being told I wasn't the right guy for the part.''</p>
        <p>''I was in a dream, you know,'' he said quietly. ''It was a fantasy that was terrifying for me because now that my dream was here I felt it would all go away, I would drop the ball, lose it. And I didn't realize it was creating tension on the show, affecting other people. And it was about my fear.''</p>
        <p>Atlhough stardom has eluded him, Mr. Caruso said that he now has a personal contentment that was missing most of his life. He and his wife, Margaret, a former flight attendant, live in Los Angeles and have a condominium in Miami, a city he loves. He's close to Great, his 16-year-old daughter from a previous marriage. In his spare time, Mr. Caruso and a friend, James Lorinz, an actor, work on their Web site, www.eddieanddon.com, in which the play two fictional comedy characters. He hopes ''Deadlocked'' and his feature film role will finally close the door on the ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' chapter of his life.</p>
        <p>''The whole thing came and went in two years -- 'N.Y.P.D Blue,' 'Kiss of Death' and 'Jade,''' -- he said. ''My exit from the show was a ((SO?)) notorious ((SOMETHING LEFT OUT HERE??)) that I felt ((IT??)) ncolored the release of the two movies. I don't think the pictures were looked at fairly because they were under the umbrella of this guy who had this great opportunity and walked away from it. And I'm still living with that today.''</p>
        <p>COVER STORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
