<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The View From Inside the Dream</title>
    <meta content="18DURB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Durbin, Karen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Techine, Andre</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chabrol, Claude</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vinterberg, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Von Trier, Lars</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newell, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Robert</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Voleurs (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ceremonie (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Celebration (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Idiots, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Donnie Brasco (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mccabe and Mrs Miller (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E3DB123EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2187" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The View From Inside the Dream</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN DURBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Durbin, Karen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karen Durbin article, after seeing back-to-back showings of Andre Techine's Voleurs and Claude Chabrol's Ceremonie, assesses what makes a movie intimate; focuses on movies made according to rules of Danish movement known as Dogma 95, such as Thomas Vinterberg's Celebration and Lars von Trier's The Idiots, and American genre, including Robert Altman's McCabe and Mrs Miller and Mike Newell's Donnie Brasco; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1996, starved for a good movie at the end of a job so consuming that I hadn't seen the inside of a theater in months, I rushed off to the Quad and treated myself to back-to-back showings of Andre Techine's ''Voleurs'' (''Thieves'') and Claude Chabrol's ''Ceremonie.'' These are excellent films by first-rank directors, but what made them so soul-satisfying was a quality of intimacy, palpable and immediate. That quality takes the experience of watching to another level. It becomes a privileged state, beyond voyeurism to a kind of collaboration, a sense that the director is disclosing subtle secrets, or trying to -- about behavior, about life, or simply about the possibilities of perception itself -- and that your ability to see is as important as the filmmaker's ability to show.</p>
        <p>I like being engulfed and devoured by a big, glossy spectacle like ''Gladiator'' as much as the next paying customer, but that's not the same as feeling connected. Watching an intimate movie is a quieter experience, but it's a richer, less passive one as well. You're not simply being acted upon, you're being engaged.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1996, starved for a good movie at the end of a job so consuming that I hadn't seen the inside of a theater in months, I rushed off to the Quad and treated myself to back-to-back showings of Andre Techine's ''Voleurs'' (''Thieves'') and Claude Chabrol's ''Ceremonie.'' These are excellent films by first-rank directors, but what made them so soul-satisfying was a quality of intimacy, palpable and immediate. That quality takes the experience of watching to another level. It becomes a privileged state, beyond voyeurism to a kind of collaboration, a sense that the director is disclosing subtle secrets, or trying to -- about behavior, about life, or simply about the possibilities of perception itself -- and that your ability to see is as important as the filmmaker's ability to show.</p>
        <p>I like being engulfed and devoured by a big, glossy spectacle like ''Gladiator'' as much as the next paying customer, but that's not the same as feeling connected. Watching an intimate movie is a quieter experience, but it's a richer, less passive one as well. You're not simply being acted upon, you're being engaged.</p>
        <p>What makes a movie intimate? The word suggests sex and romance on one hand or small, earnest, slice-of-life films on the other. But intimacy in movies has less to do with subject than with subjectivity, the filmmakers' and the characters'. ''Les Voleurs,'' grounded by Catherine Deneuve's most emotionally naked performance in years, is a sophisticated meditation on loyalty and desire disguised as a policier, while ''La Ceremonie'' is a skillfully paced suspense thriller complete with big stars -- Isabelle Huppert, Sandrine Bonnaire and Jacqueline Bisset -- and a climactic, hot and cold running bloodbath. By the same token, ''Donnie Brasco'' and the critically underrated ''Conspiracy Theory'' are Hollywood genre movies, a mob story and an action thriller, but both 1997 films deliver something more resonant and lasting than the usual chills and thrills, although they deliver those, too.</p>
        <p>Within their genres, all these films contain character dramas of considerable subtlety and power. In Mike Newell's ''Donnie Brasco,'' the father-son bond that develops between Johnny Depp's undercover FBI man and Al Pacino's dutiful Mafia foot-soldier take the story and the viewer into a moral and social landscape as confounding and uncertain as any in film. That landscape is a good deal clearer in ''La Ceremonie,'' but as monstrous as the lethally complicit characters played by Ms. Huppert and Ms. Bonnaire are, Mr. Chabrol compels us to understand them -- his movie plays like ''Badlands'' by the sea.</p>
        <p>A smart script (by Brian Helgeland, who wrote ''L. A. Confidential'') helps ratchet ''Conspiracy Theory'' a couple of notches up from the ''Lethal Weapon'' level of amiable entertainment. But what makes the film unexpectedly moving and memorable is Mel Gibson's high-wire performance as a man whose mind has been chemically deranged by a renegade government agency. A friend once summed up the power of ''Leaving Las Vegas'' by saying, ''Nicolas Cage really takes you inside his despair.'' In a tour de force of pathos, humor and intelligence, Mr. Gibson does something similar as he gradually lets us see, a glimpse at a time, the whole human being peering out at us through the lurid static of his cruelly scrambled psyche. Even when they're ostensibly limited in ambition, intimate films have a way of transcending themselves.</p>
        <p>Yet, most movies coming out of Hollywood look too perfect to be intimate. They're so heavily processed they don't just seem slick, they seem laminated, and so does everyone and everything in them. This is just right for a futuristic special effects blow-out like ''The Matrix,'' but it has a way of draining the life out of just about everything else, even light romantic comedy. In the antiseptically tidy ''You've Got Mail'' -- has the Upper West Side ever been so clean? -- Meg Ryan seems to have rolled off the same robot-controlled assembly line as the movie itself.</p>
        <p>Five years ago, the Danish filmmaking movement known as Dogma 95 challenged the Hollywood way of knowledge with a set of contrarian commandments stipulating hand-held camera work and putting severe limitations on what its creators call ''cosmetics.'' This meant everything from standard high-wattage lighting to the emotion-cuing soundtrack music that most conventional movies all but drown in, as well as the other layers of artifice that result from the process known as post-production. With the advance of filmmaking technology, including computer graphics, ''post,'' as it's called, has grown ever more elaborate. In a 1965 essay called ''The Decline of the Actor,'' the film writer Manny Farber anticipated the Dogma critique with an observation about the impact of post-production on dialogue: ''Each word has been created, worked over by a sound engineer who intercepts the dialogue before it hits the audience. There is no longer the feeling of being close to the actor.''</p>
        <p>Dogma movies use their technological limits to narrow the gap, none more so than Thomas Vinterberg's ''Celebration'' (1998) and Lars von Trier's recent and much more controversial ''The Idiots.'' Set at a birthday gala for the hotelier patriarch of a large, wealthy family, ''The Celebration'' is a transfixing tale of incest exposed and denied; it's also an anatomy of the family as a paradigm for power and its corruptions. Shot in digital video, the film has a soft, almost milky surface, as if we were glimpsing the action through one of the old French windows of the family's grand hotel. Once inside, Mr. Vinterberg's endlessly mobile camera becomes a detective, indefatigably searching out secrets, nosing its way -- and ours -- past every shoulder and into every face.</p>
        <p>The Dogma films I've seen vary greatly, but they all feel uncommonly intimate. This is partly due, no doubt, to the inordinate amount of candlelight that illuminates the nighttime scenes, but mostly it's a function of the hand-held rule. Hand-held cameras produce images of distinctly, sometimes distractingly human origin; they're right there with you. But put the camera on a dolly or a crane, which is where cameras mostly are put, and suddenly you've got the world view of a creature -- often a very tall creature -- with eyes but no feet. This isn't necessarily bad, but it can be distancing and impersonal.</p>
        <p>Just how safe that impersonality can be struck me most forcibly when I watched ''The Idiots,'' which opened in April. This faux documentary about a commune whose members try to confront their own and society's hypocrisy by pretending to be mentally handicapped isn't just low-tech, it's raw. It's also intensely moving. The characters are both disturbed and disturbing, particularly a wounded woman with a devastating secret who drifts into the commune almost by chance and quietly confronts its bullying leader. ''The Idiots'' was engaging precisely because it looks so nearly out of control. There was no reassuring technique on view, nothing to insulate me from these alarming people and their endless provocations. It felt as if Mr. von Trier were unspooling his film right into my lap.</p>
        <p>The Dogma manifesto criticizes ''the cinema of illusion,'' but there is no other kind. What the Dogma critique is really aimed at might better be called the cinema of gross manipulation. I've been jolted half out of my seat by competently paced action movies I didn't even like, cried real tears at the skillfully staged deaths of characters I didn't believe in, felt my toes tapping to the infectious rock 'n' roll behind a sadistic scene of torture.</p>
        <p>The first two experiences were irritating, the third was like being mugged.</p>
        <p>Of course much of the time, audiences want to be manipulated -- it's what people mean when they say they just want to be entertained. The way most Hollywood movies work, the relationship between director and audience bears a distinct resemblance to that of hooker and john. Audiences go to the movies hoping to be serviced -- amused or thrilled or scared -- in fairly specific, familiar ways. That's what they paid for. They aren't looking for revelation, they're looking to be stroked. They don't expect to be made uncomfortable or self-conscious or even seriously moved. In other words, they don't expect a real connection, one that's open-ended and unpredictable.</p>
        <p>When ''The Celebration'' was released, it became an art-house hit everywhere it opened, including the United States, and Mr. Vinterberg received many offers from Hollywood (which he turned down). It was as if the Danish film filled a need among filmmakers and audiences alike. In fact, it had. It offered a fresh, accessible alternative to the sort of glossy, airless cinema that has no vision more personal than that of the marketplace and tries to leave nothing to chance. Too many Hollywood movies look like the product of a bunch of control freaks with a stun gun in one hand, a cattle prod in the other, and a 90-piece orchestra booming away in the background.</p>
        <p>It's a bullying aesthetic and just tiresome enough that, every decade or so, upstart directors come out of nowhere to challenge it and audiences respond.</p>
        <p>In 1989 it was Steven Soderbergh's ''Sex, Lies and Videotape,'' which took Sundance by storm, collected the Palme d'Or, the top prize, at Cannes and racked up such impressive numbers at the box office that independent movies became hot items -- so hot that within a few years they had been all but swallowed whole by the big studios. This gave rise to the hip, glossy, and frequently violent hybrid wryly known as Indiewood. It also paved the way for the likes of Mr. Vinterberg.</p>
        <p>Thirty years ago, it was the studios themselves that briefly threw away the rules. Describing the now-legendary golden age of the 1970's in his book ''Easy Riders, Raging Bulls,'' Peter Biskind notes, ''It was the last time Hollywood produced a body of work -- as opposed to the errant masterpiece -- that was character- rather than plot-driven, that defied traditional narrative conventions, that challenged the tyranny of technical correctness, that broke the taboos of language and behavior, that dared to end unhappily.''</p>
        <p>He could be describing Robert Altman's 1971 alternative Western, ''McCabe and Mrs. Miller,'' set in a rain-soaked mountain town so new it looks like a wound in the landscape and starring Warren Beatty and Julie Christie as a small-time hustler with a dreamy streak and the sharp-witted, opium-smoking Cockney madame he dotes on. More about loneliness and loners than it is about love, ''McCabe and Mrs. Miller'' could be subtitled ''How the West Was Really Won,'' the answer being, of course, by brute force, corporate wealth, trickery, greed, desperation and a lot of hard work, some of it verging on slavery. In just about every respect, this is one of the most intimate movies ever made, from its spare soundtrack music -- two eloquent Leonard Cohen songs -- to the famous overlapping dialogue, which, like real speech, is perfectly audible without being perfectly intelligible. There is artistry here but no spurious glamour or ostentatious squalor. ''McCabe and Mrs Miller'' is laced with wit and moments of raucous humor, but in this movie, even the ground looks like it hurts.</p>
        <p>I USED to think that Jean Renoir's 1939 ''Rules of the Game'' was my desert-island movie, the one I couldn't do without, but after seeing ''McCabe and Mrs. Miller'' again, I'm not so sure. Mr. Altman's Western is a rougher film than the exquisite Renoir, but these tragicomedies of manners have much in common. Both are lapidary in their observation of character and emotion, but they're also unobtrusively large -- portraits of flawed civilizations in the throes of violent change, one dying, one emerging into raw, bloody life.</p>
        <p>Maybe all it comes down to is that I'm not French but American, and Mr. Altman's unsparing evocation of the pathologies of power and alienation that undermined a young country's democratic dream of itself speaks to me in my bones.</p>
        <p>One theory of how movies act on an audience is that they're like dreams -- that in a sense, when you watch a film, someone else's dream is playing in your head. This suggests that movies are an inherently intimate medium, setting up shop in your mind whether you want them to or not. Perhaps what gives ''McCabe and Mrs. Miller'' its particular intimacy is that it isn't just a dream of a movie, it's a movie about a dream. The dream is both broken and alive, and it's ours.</p>
        <p>FILM Karen Durbin is a critic-at-large for Elle magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Karen Durbin is a critic-at-large for Elle magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
