<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The View From/Monroe; Forget Mario Andretti, It's Racing Al Dente</title>
    <meta content="18VIEW$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pasta</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ephraim, Bonnie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bailer, Darice</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pasta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E4DF103EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1408" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The View From/Monroe; Forget Mario Andretti, It's Racing Al Dente</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DARICE BAILER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bailer, Darice</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes Great Pasta Race; teacher Bonnie Ephraim's two-week final project integrates math, science and language skills to help fourth-grade students use knowledge they have accumulated over course of school year to create and race miniature cars made out of pasta; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE week before the Great Pasta Race at Stepney Elementary School, Samantha Chirunomula recognized an engineering glitch. Two rotelle wheels on her flat-bed lasagna car would not spin on their bamboo axles.</p>
        <p>Samantha's car, the Fast Flamer 2000, was in trouble. With two wheels immobile, her car wouldn't travel very far down the track on race night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE week before the Great Pasta Race at Stepney Elementary School, Samantha Chirunomula recognized an engineering glitch. Two rotelle wheels on her flat-bed lasagna car would not spin on their bamboo axles.</p>
        <p>Samantha's car, the Fast Flamer 2000, was in trouble. With two wheels immobile, her car wouldn't travel very far down the track on race night.</p>
        <p>Samantha, one of 21 mini-engineers in the fourth-grade math enrichment class at Stepney, sought Bonnie Ephraim's advice.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ephraim teaches the fourth grade and the midday enrichment class during math period. The Great Pasta Race is Ms. Ephraim's two-week final project integrating math, science and language skills. Students design a car out of a piece of lasagna and assorted pasta such as ziti, manicotti and jumbo shells.</p>
        <p>They complete a mock purchase order for the pasta, adding up how much money they'll need for parts, glue and bamboo sticks. They buy materials with $25 in play money and count change. They can purchase insurance for $2 in fake money to replace parts that break. They measure and graph the distance their car travels on race night and interpret race results.</p>
        <p>Students learn important mathematical concepts that meet state and national standards, or expectations, for student learning.</p>
        <p>In Connecticut, there are 10 broad mathematical standards for students in kindergarten through 12th grade. Three of those standards are operations (such as addition, subtraction, fractions and decimals); estimation and approximation; and measurement. In the Great Pasta Race, you're ''hitting on several standards all in one project,'' said Mari Muri, the mathematics consultant for the state Department of Education.</p>
        <p>Jane Pinciaro, the math and science coordinator for kindergarten through eighth grade in Monroe's public schools, called the Great Pasta Race ''one of those pull-it-all together projects. The students actually use the knowledge that they've accumulated over the course of the school year to create a car that achieves the greatest distance down the track.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ephraim examined Samantha's car. Two glue balls gripped one wheel too tightly for it to rotate freely. One bamboo axle was thicker on one side, preventing another rotelle wheel from twirling.</p>
        <p>''Do you think real engineers have problems like this?'' Ms. Ephraim asked. Samantha nodded. ''The most important thing is that you try a variety of things and don't give up,'' Ms. Ephraim said.</p>
        <p>The students can be continually challenged in designing, building and fixing their cars. Ziti axles break. Cars flip over on the ramp and crack in half. ''Things don't work out, but there's a chance to try again,'' Ms. Ephraim said. ''Students begin to discover the excitement of the subject, the talent  within them, and that they can solve problems and have fun in the process.''</p>
        <p>Samantha replaced one wheel axle and moved glue balls on the other. Last Monday, on race night, parent volunteers weighed her car and inspected it. Was it built with at least one piece of lasagna? Did it weigh less than four ounces, the weight of a stick of butter?</p>
        <p>One by one, the fourth graders let their cars whisk down the 7-foot-long track, alongside black-and-white checkered racing banners and beneath red, black and white balloons. Parents, siblings and seven of Ms. Ephraim's former students and pasta-race alumni craned their necks to see whose car sped farthest.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ephraim's car, Flash Lightning, won the first run, going 18 feet 5 inches. But Evan Gravely's F-110 flew even farther on the next run before splitting apart at the finish.</p>
        <p>''Nineteen feet 3 inches! That's better than Ms. Ephraim's by a foot!'' exclaimed Nick Ioannucci, a fellow competitor.</p>
        <p>It was Nick and his classmate Kenneth Sobel who inspired Evan to shorten his axles and weigh down the front of the car with a couple of pasta shells to pull it down the ramp faster.</p>
        <p>Evan won the Great Pasta Race. Caroline Urizar took second place with Hot Rod 2000, and Kevin Joy third with Jet. At the end of the night, each student received a good sportsmanship certificate and an individual award.</p>
        <p>Ronald Gustaitis, the Stepney principal,  and Norman Michaud, the district superintendent, congratulated the students. Mr. Gustaitis, a former math teacher, had been a guest lecturer in Ms. Ephraim's class,  teaching the children how variables such as weight and friction -- aerodynamics -- would affect the speed and traveling distance of their cars.</p>
        <p>From the start of the project, students kept daily journals, recounting their class work or discoveries. Marie Rizio discovered that lighter cars go a little faster than  heavier ones. Caroline Urizar did, too, especially when her car ''went past the rugs and under the table,'' she wrote in her journal.</p>
        <p>When Deidra De Angelis' car veered right down the ramp on a trial run, Deidra noticed that her axles weren't parallel to each other, making her car swerve. With her insurance, she replaced a ziti axle, and her car ran down the middle of the ramp.</p>
        <p>After building their cars, the students wrote and filmed their own television commercials inviting their families to the race. Some discovered a passion with the project.</p>
        <p>Kenneth Sobel, for instance, was hooked on engineering and architecture after designing his car and also a 20-inch span bridge, made of straws and pins, in one of Ms. Ephraim's previous classes.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ephraim got the idea for the Great Pasta Race back in 1995 at a summer program in mathematics and science run by the Project to Increase Mastery of Mathematics and Science at Wesleyan University. The project, founded in 1979, is designed to improve mathematics and science education in Connecticut through professional development programs for teachers and administrators.</p>
        <p>That summer, Anita Gaston, a teacher at Laurel School in Bloomfield, and Ms. Muri presented a workshop on activities and strategies to promote understanding and interest in fractions and decimals to children in grades three through six. The Great Pasta Race was one activity.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gaston, then a fourth-grade teacher at Laurel, had modified a pasta car activity for seventh and eighth graders that she had seen at Saturday Academy in Hartford. Saturday Academy, sponsored by Aetna Life and Casualty Insurance Company in Hartford, is a national enrichment program designed to raise the academic aspirations and achievement of middle school students.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gaston used the Great Pasta Race in her fourth-grade classroom at Laurel to teach her students about decimals. After the students raced their cars, they recorded their times in tenths and hundredths of a second. ''It would make decimals come alive for them,'' Ms. Gaston said.</p>
        <p>This year, Ms. Gaston applied for a Presidential Award for Excellence in Mathematics and Science Teaching using the pasta race project. The award is the nation's highest honor for math and science teachers, and Ms. Gaston was a state finalist.</p>
        <p>''The project is just phenomenal,'' said Deborah Urizar, one of the room mothers in Ms. Ephraim's math class. ''It's a great way to teach math so that it's real and  enjoyable for students.''</p>
        <p>And, ''when students are motivated and like to learn,'' Ms. Muri said, ''they learn much better and deeper.''</p>
        <p>A chief math objective for Connecticut students is that, by the end of 12th grade, they will be proficient enough in math to apply a range of numerical concepts to analyze and solve real-world problems. The Great Pasta Race enabled students to budget, purchase goods with money, and count their change -- skills the children will use throughout their lives.</p>
        <p>''They had fun trying to solve a problem and I think that's the most important thing,'' Ms. Ephraim said. ''A lot of times in life, the struggle is overwhelming. But here they are going to remember that the struggle was fun and everybody was successful. I think that's what I want them to leave with, that you can be lost and struggling and find your way through.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
