<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Army Corps May Give Up Fire Island Plan</title>
    <meta content="18FIRE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Fire Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Army Corps of Engineers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vietri, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/Fire Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E4D6133EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1441" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Army Corps May Give Up Fire Island Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Army Corps of Engineers official Joseph Vietri, noting New York's lack of enthusiasm over $52 million interim project to rebuild beaches and dunes in populated areas of Fire Island, says corps may soon drop plan; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SAYING New York had become ''strangely silent'' about a $52 million interim project to rebuild beaches and dunes in populated areas of Fire Island, a senior official of the United States Army Corps of Engineers said last week that the corps may soon drop the plan.</p>
        <p>The official, Joseph R. Vietri, the deputy chief of planning for the New York regional office, said the corps had written to Governor George E. Pataki last week to make what he described as a final plea that the state take a position on whether the project should go forward.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SAYING New York had become ''strangely silent'' about a $52 million interim project to rebuild beaches and dunes in populated areas of Fire Island, a senior official of the United States Army Corps of Engineers said last week that the corps may soon drop the plan.</p>
        <p>The official, Joseph R. Vietri, the deputy chief of planning for the New York regional office, said the corps had written to Governor George E. Pataki last week to make what he described as a final plea that the state take a position on whether the project should go forward.</p>
        <p>''If we do not get a letter of support, we will terminate all work on the project, and we are very close to being at that point now,'' Mr. Vietri said. He added that he was ''not optimistic'' a letter of support would be received.</p>
        <p>The project would involve pumping 7.47 million cubic yards of offshore sand -- an amount that would fill 830,000 cement trucks -- onto sections of Fire Island near or in summer communities.</p>
        <p>It would be the most extensive and expensive such undertaking on the Island since the closing of a half-mile breach in the residential area of the Westhampton barrier island in the mid-1990's. That event, calamitous by homeowners' standards, was attributed to oceanfront groins that the corps erected in the 1960's and 70's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vietri said that four months after the close of public comment on the environmental study for the Fire Island project, the corps had still not received state position papers or a financial commitment. New York's share of the cost is to be 30 to 35 percent; the federal government would pay 65 to 70 percent. A portion of the state's share, probably more than $5 million, would be paid by local governments.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Mr. Pataki, Michael F. McKeon, declined to say whether the state still supported the project.</p>
        <p>Albany's apparent reluctance to back the project, which state officials had initially asked the corps to design and carry out, seems to signal a distinct waning of political backing for a publicly financed program that could be construed as primarily benefiting private land owners.</p>
        <p>Gerard Stoddard, president of the Fire Island Association, which represents property owners, has said in the past that Fire Island communities would pay up to half the local share. But costs would still be borne by other taxpayers.</p>
        <p>The Fire Island property owners argue that 100,000 residents of mainland areas of the South Shore would be the primary beneficiaries of rebuilding Fire Island because the project would reduce coastal flooding. The corps's environmental study said 80 percent of the benefits would be to reduce mainland flooding.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stoddard said the state's inaction reflected a struggle between the Department of Environmental Conservation, which favors erosion control, and the Department of State, which prefers a policy of retreat from oceanfront areas.</p>
        <p>''What you see here is the State of New York playing Russian roulette with the South Shore in order to effect a philosophic change in the way we manage the coast,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But environmental groups and others say such benefits will not occur. The Department of the Interior, the parent agency of the National Park Service, which operates the Fire Island National Seashore, has also filed strongly negative comments.</p>
        <p>The department, which forbade the dumping of sand in large areas of the national seashore, said the corps's environmental study failed to justify the need for the project. It said shoreline stabilization would reduce breaches that are in fact beneficial to marine habitats.</p>
        <p>Among its 10 objections, the department also said the study failed to comply with federal environmental law by ignoring reasonable alternatives, like preventing further development on Fire Island.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't address a lot of the concerns and issues we have in protecting a national park,'' said Constantine Dillon, park superintendent of the national seashore. ''Our position has been that the beach was never in danger, it just moves. And generally speaking, the best approach to shoreline management is to allow natural processes to occur.''</p>
        <p>New York State and the Interior Department must approve the interim project before work can begin.</p>
        <p>The Fire Island project could be a precursor to a far larger restoration project for 81 miles of the South Shore, from Fire Island Inlet to Montauk Point. That project, first proposed nearly 40 years ago to protect the mainland from hurricane surges, among other objectives, is the subject of a corps study due in 2003.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, in another sign that prospects are dimming, Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York, toured the South Shore by helicopter with Mr. Vietri and other Army officials but refrained from commenting. Instead, Mr. Schumer backed the longer-range approach, saying erosion ''clearly begs for a comprehensive solution that addresses the coastline as a whole, rather than in a piecemeal fashion.''</p>
        <p>Staff workers for Representative Rick A. Lazio, the Republican from Brightwaters, who owns a house on Fire Island, told a delegation from Ocean Beach before his nomination to run for the Senate that he had reservations about the interim project.</p>
        <p>''He has backed away from it,'' said Natalie K. Rogers, the mayor of Ocean Beach. ''They are concerned about people rebuilding.'' Such rebuilding could occur in places where houses destroyed or damaged by storms and erosion were rebuilt.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Rogers, who called those fears unfounded, said village residents were imploring Governor Pataki to stand behind what she said were his promises to help Fire Island.</p>
        <p>''It's time for him to step up to the plate,'' said Mrs. Rogers, who is also a member of the Fire Island Association. ''The Army corps has worked like heck and done a very splendid job, and I think they are totally disgusted and discouraged.''</p>
        <p>But opponents said the corps's withdrawal from the interim plan would be welcomed.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Defense Fund, the Nature Conservancy, the National Audubon Society and other groups have repeatedly attacked the interim plan as ill-conceived, environmentally damaging and likely to foster private development in newly protected oceanfront areas at public expense.</p>
        <p>''The interim project as currently designed would encourage development and redevelopment in state-designated coastal erosion hazard areas,'' said James T. B. Tripp, the general counsel of the Environmental Defense Fund. ''It makes absolutely no sense for the state and federal government to spend tens of millions of dollars on a project that would have that effect.''</p>
        <p>Some of the most pointed criticism has come Stephen P. Leatherman, director of the Laboratory for Coastal Research at Florida International University.</p>
        <p>Dr. Leatherman, who has studied the South Shore, said the argument that the interim project would protect the mainland was fallacious. To say that beach nourishment on Fire Island would prevent flooding on the mainland is ''clearly a stretch,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''It's like building a dam with two gaping holes in it,'' he said, referring to the Fire Island Inlet and the Moriches Inlet, which bracket Fire Island.</p>
        <p>In comments to the corps in February, Dr. Leatherman derided its assertion that the prevention of mainland flooding accounted for more than 80 percent of the benefits and thus justified the project.</p>
        <p>''This is the first time I have ever seen the U.S. Corps of Engineers or any other agency try to base beach erosion abatement for an offshore barrier island on mainland flood protection,'' he said. ''This is a novel and possibly precedent-setting approach of trying to show economic benefits and public good outside the project area in order to protect private real estate vulnerable to gradual, long-term and storm-induced beach erosion.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Rogers said politicians were being cowed by the environmental groups. ''They are all concerned about offending the conservationists,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She called for the governor to reaffirm state support for the project. ''The state, by it's silence, is killing it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Leatherman took another view: ''These communities do everything they can to keep the public out, and now they have this huge spin project to benefit the private property owners at the cost of government. That's not going to wash.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
