<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>There Ain't No Sanity Claus</title>
    <meta content="18GIDDENT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giddins, Gary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marx, Groucho (Julius Henry Marx) (1890-1977)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kanfer, Stefan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">louvish, simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">marx, chico (Leonard Marx)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">marx, harpo (Adolph Marx)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">marx, zeppo (Herbert Marx)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">monkey business: The Lives and Legends of the Marx Brothers (Book</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Groucho: the Life and Times of Julius Henry Marx (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">marx, gummo (Milton Marx)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">essential groucho, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E1D7133FF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2551" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>There Ain't No Sanity Claus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gary Giddins</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Giddins, Gary</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gary Giddins reviews books Groucho: The Life and Times of Julius Henry Marx by Stefan Kanfer; Monkey Business: The Lives and Legends of the Marx Brothers: Groucho, Chico, Harpo, Zeppo With Added Gummo by Simon Louvish and The Essential Groucho: Writings by, for and About Groucho Marx, edited by Stefan Kanfer; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GROUCHO</p>
        <p>The Life and Times</p>
        <p>of Julius Henry Marx.</p>
        <p>By Stefan Kanfer.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 465 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $30.</p>
        <p>MONKEY BUSINESS</p>
        <p>The Lives and Legends</p>
        <p>of the Marx Brothers: Groucho, Chico, Harpo, Zeppo With Added Gummo.</p>
        <p>By Simon Louvish.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 471 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Thomas Dunne Books/</p>
        <p>St. Martin's Press. $25.95.</p>
        <p>THE ESSENTIAL GROUCHO</p>
        <p>Writings by, for, and About</p>
        <p>Groucho Marx.</p>
        <p>Edited by Stefan Kanfer.</p>
        <p>254 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Vintage Books. Paper, $12.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GROUCHO</p>
        <p>The Life and Times</p>
        <p>of Julius Henry Marx.</p>
        <p>By Stefan Kanfer.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 465 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $30.</p>
        <p>MONKEY BUSINESS</p>
        <p>The Lives and Legends</p>
        <p>of the Marx Brothers: Groucho, Chico, Harpo, Zeppo With Added Gummo.</p>
        <p>By Simon Louvish.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 471 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Thomas Dunne Books/</p>
        <p>St. Martin's Press. $25.95.</p>
        <p>THE ESSENTIAL GROUCHO</p>
        <p>Writings by, for, and About</p>
        <p>Groucho Marx.</p>
        <p>Edited by Stefan Kanfer.</p>
        <p>254 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Vintage Books. Paper, $12.</p>
        <p>THE most enduring masks of the 20th century -- likely to take their place alongside Comedy and Tragedy or Pulcinella and Pierrot -- are Frankenstein's monster, as incarnated by Boris Karloff, and Groucho Marx. Groucho's is pure caricature: spectacles, heavy mustache and eyebrows, cigar. ''Groucho glasses,'' marketed as early as the 1940's, turn up today in children's goody bags. The film critic Otis Ferguson wrote in 1935 that Groucho Marx ''would be funny in still photographs,'' and he was right: never did a mask carry so much attitude. Put Groucho glasses on anyone who has ever seen the Marx Brothers and that person will fall into a crouch, raise his hand to flick imaginary ashes and crack wise with a velvety, back-of-the-throat, quasi-Jewish inflection.</p>
        <p>In the early years of the last century, the Marx Brothers, sons of a German Jewish family living in the Yorkville section of Manhattan, were pressured by their mother, Minnie, to quit school and sing in vaudeville. As Stefan Kanfer writes in ''Groucho,'' his smart, briskly appealing but indifferently researched biography, ''She once watched horrified as all three of her sons interrupted their own number to follow the progress of a large bug crossing the stage.'' When they went on the road with an act about school days, the brothers adopted the most commonplace stock characters of the era: Leonard put on a pointy hat and polished his stage Italian, Adolph wore a red fright wig to play an Irish loon, and Julius impersonated a beady-eyed, whiskered German professor in a black swallow-tailed coat and cravat.</p>
        <p>Their uncle, the vaudeville star Al Shean, told Adolph his Irish nut would be a lot funnier without dialogue. Adolph was offended, but when a newspaper critic expressed the same opinion, he resolved to be mute; he added ''an old automobile horn to honk his replies,'' along with ''a raincoat to stow his props.'' Julius, the canniest of the brothers, came up with the bit in which Adolph denies stealing silverware, which proceeds to drop from his sleeves. According to legend -- on which Simon Louvish casts some doubt in his book ''Monkey Business'' -- the brothers were renamed during a poker game in Galesburg, Ill., when a monologuist compared the Marxes to figures in the funny papers. Taking the comic strip ''Sherlocko, the Monk'' as his cue, he dealt them names ending in ''O.'' Leonard, who chased women and affected an Italian accent, became Chico; Adolph, who played the harp and an Irishman, became Harpo; Julius, who was acerbic and hid his money in a grouch bag, became Groucho. Two younger brothers, Milton and Herbert, were called Gummo and Zeppo, but they never developed grotesque masks and had no place in the act; Zeppo seems as out of place in his five pictures as Chico would have in ''The Godfather.''</p>
        <p>After the Lusitania was sunk in 1915, Groucho and many of his compatriots stopped playing Germans; he modulated his accent to a distinctive Jewish singsong. (Decades later, Charlie Chaplin told him, ''I wish I could speak on the screen as well as you.'') One evening, he walked funny, got a big laugh and made the slouched scurrying part of his shtick. In time, the ethnic parodies became surreal, a collection of crazy masks that demolished the old stereotypes. As Al Shean used to sing to his largely immigrant audience, ''It isn't what you used to be, it's what you are today.''</p>
        <p>Groucho's eureka moment occurred when his son was born and he was late getting from the maternity ward to a theater in Queens. Having no time to glue on whiskers, he painted a mustache with greasepaint. It got laughs, but the theater manager fumed, insisting customers had paid to see real false hair. Groucho knew a good thing, however, and defied the manager. When the brothers made their first movie, ''The Cocoanuts,'' in 1929, the director Robert Florey demanded a genuine mustache, arguing that the audience would not believe a painted one. Groucho told him, ''The audience doesn't believe us anyhow.''</p>
        <p>The greasepaint was the necessary touch to finish and perfect the mask. That big rectangular block of black represented the clown's assertion of amiable fantasy, not a difficult concept for a nation raised on the circus as well as minstrels and vaudeville. In their sublimely mad films for Paramount -- The Cocoanuts,'' ''Animal Crackers'' (1930), ''Monkey Business'' (1931), ''Horse Feathers'' (1932) and ''Duck Soup'' (1933) -- the Marx Brothers, in their childlike anarchy, are far more appealing, sane and believable than the creepy lovers, inviolate dowagers and assorted con men surrounding them. As Chico later observed (in 1935 in MGM's ''Night at the Opera''), ''There ain't no Sanity Claus.''</p>
        <p>With the masks in place, despite the accent on fast verbal humor, the Marx Brothers' faces took on an existence independent of the characters they created and became strangely interchangeable. Kanfer's narrative overflows with examples of doppelg</p>
        <p>During the Broadway run of the play ''Animal Crackers,'' Margaret Dumont, the eternal dowager, once opened Captain Spaulding's trunk and a fleet of Grouchos emerged, all stagehands and musicians with the greasepaint mustache and cigar. After movies made the brothers nationally famous, Marx masks turned up everywhere; people gave parties at which guests were obliged to come as the Marx of their choice. By the late 1930's, Kanfer writes, ''the image of Groucho was now so manufactured'' that when he did not appear for a publicity photograph, a writer put on the makeup and posed with Harpo and Chico: ''it was the writer's face and body, not Groucho's, that looked out from a poster'' for the film ''Go West'' (1940). Without the masks, the brothers went unrecognized. Traveling with the Victory Caravan during World War II, Groucho was the only celebrity ignored by fans when the stars stepped off a train. He sneaked back on board to put on greasepaint, glasses and cigar, then disembarked with bent knees to much applause.</p>
        <p>Given the ubiquity of the Marx masks, especially Groucho's, one is startled to realize how briefly the Marx Brothers held the attention of their contemporaries. They did not achieve permanent cultural acceptance until after 1967, when Groucho received the imprimatur of the Museum of Modern Art. Before that, they had enjoyed two three-year stints of Hollywood glory, 1930-32 and 1935-37. As Kanfer notes, Graham Greene put his finger on the moment when the riotous satirists became as toothless as the stereotypes they burlesqued: in an enthusiastic review of ''A Day at the Races'' (1937), he expressed his dismay at a scene in which Maureen O'Sullivan, ''a real person,'' called them ''silly.'' ''Silly,'' Greene continued; ''good God, we cannot help exclaiming since we are real people too, have we been deceived all along?''</p>
        <p>Two years later, in the troubling but vastly underrated ''At the Circus,'' no one could fail to mistake how much of the Marx Brothers' once infallible intuition had been sacrificed to Hollywood journeymen. It was one thing for Chico to tutsi-frutsi Groucho out of money, another thing entirely for him to push him into the mud or for Eve Arden to leave him dangling helplessly in pantaloons. We will accept Groucho deceived, but humiliated? Never.</p>
        <p>Kanfer is on to something when he describes the Marxes as ''boys dressed up as men in funny faces and outlandish costumes, like celebrants en route to a costume party.'' Many of their contemporaries adapted bizarre faces and costumes to play children -- think of Ed Wynn, Fanny Brice, Joe Penner, the Three Stooges. But the Marxes were grown-ups pretending to be children pretending to be grown-ups; we may laugh at adults playing children, but we don't want to be them. We do, however, wish to retain a little of the childhood anarchy that defies the Margaret Dumonts breathing down our necks. That was a hard act to sustain for actors in middle age. Groucho once said he envied Jack Benny, who could get laughs without a mask.</p>
        <p>Then came the wilderness years. Chico, a compulsive gambler and womanizer (when his wife caught him kissing a chorus girl, he protested that he was merely whispering in her mouth), survived by leading a band and playing the piano by ''shooting'' the keys -- an irresistible bit because he made it look so easy when, in fact, it requires the timing of a master comedian. Harpo married late in life, adopted children and enjoyed his family. He sagely remarked that Groucho ''is an imaginary character who needs the other three characters to give him substance.'' Groucho looked lost in the movies he made on his own. He tried to make it as a writer; when a book of his did not sell, he told a reporter, ''I only write first editions.'' Yet he was eventually born again as the hilariously disparaging quizmaster of ''You Bet Your Life,'' during its 14-year stint on radio and television. He grew a real mustache, but by then his face had taken on all the attributes of caricature. If Jack Benny could get a laugh with a stare, Groucho could do just as well wagging his eyebrows.</p>
        <p>Unhappily for his wives and children, the mask had calcified. He could no more turn off the spigot of wisecracks and casual cruelty than he could his insecurity and fear. He drove two of his three wives and one of his three children to drink; he estranged them all. Groucho earned his misogyny the hard way. When he lost his virginity, he contracted gonorrhea. His mother encouraged him to see ''fast women'' to avoid commitments that might hurt the act. A married woman lured him into a dangerous situation that later inspired a line in ''The Cocoanuts'': ''You know, a yes like that was once responsible for me jumping out a window.''</p>
        <p>He was a devoted father as long as his children were small and defenseless. He rushed home from the studio to change diapers and feed the infants, usurping his wives, until the kids were old enough to talk back -- at which point they could no longer win his approval. He spent his last years with a woman Kanfer portrays as greedy, bullying and sexually taunting: Minnie squared. Groucho preferred her to his often cowering and resentful children. When Groucho dies in 1977, at 86, you can't help feeling he lasted a few years too long.</p>
        <p>KANFER, the author of ''Serious Business,'' about animation, and ''A Summer World,'' about the Catskills, has produced a vivid, cleanly written biography. He describes the supporting players splendidly, from the little-remembered gag writer Al Boasberg to the deservedly forgotten critic Alexander Woollcott. He stays away from facile psychology and moves his story along at a clip. His many virtues, however, are undermined by missteps, like a section in the present tense, vain Gallicisms (''au fond,'' ''poitrine''), chronology problems and an almost arrogant lack of scholarship. The absence of a filmography and of information like Groucho's birth date is strange, but the absence of source notes is inexcusable, especially when he alters familiar stories, accepts apocrypha as fact, offers unattributed conversation and appears to know what people are thinking. He is weak on the movies, recycling standard tales and reprinting dialogue, much of it also included in his entertaining anthology, ''The Essential Groucho.''</p>
        <p>Kanfer relies chiefly on previous books, including those by Groucho himself, which he takes a mite too seriously, and Hector Arce's superior ''Groucho'' (1979), out of print and in need of revision but still the best general biography. Kanfer's attacks on Richard J. Anobile are unseemly, since he has taken much from Anobile's ''Marx Bros. Scrapbook,'' including mistakes (like the assertion that ''The Cocoanuts'' was the first film musical or the screenwriter Arthur Sheekman's account of a card-playing incident, since amended by his widow, Gloria Stuart, in interviews and a memoir, ''I Just Kept Hoping'').</p>
        <p>The accretion of small errors in Kanfer's biography and anthology undermines his authority. Bert Granet and Arthur Sheekman did not write ''The Big Broadcast'' (Louvish makes the same mistake but blames Arce, who started the rumor); Kitty Carlisle was not ''an untried singer'' when she made ''A Night at the Opera,'' the fourth and last of her 30's musicals; Humphrey Bogart married Mayo Methot, not Virginia Mayo; NBC paid Groucho $4,800 per episode of ''You Bet Your Life,'' not $48,000; Morrie Ryskind is, in fact, credited as a writer on ''The Cocoanuts''; the bazooka was named after an instrument invented by the comic Bob Burns, not vice versa.</p>
        <p>Louvish is a more committed researcher and has come up with new material. He has elected, however, to publish his research rather than write a book. His occasional error (like crediting Brendan Behan with Thornton Wilder's detection of ''Grouchin'' in ''Finnegans Wake'') is nothing compared with howlers like tagging an unknown girl who may have grown up with the Marxes as an ''embryonic Maggie Dumont.'' His relentlessly jokey, cliche-ridden, pointlessly data-packed prose will repel all but the most ardent fans. The Louvish who published ''Man on the Flying Trapeze,'' a sober biography of W. C. Fields, a few years ago is unrecognizable in ''Monkey Business.'' A pity, because he has interesting things to say about scripts versus finished films and fills in details Kanfer omits -- like when and how Harpo started playing the harp.</p>
        <p>Louvish consistently and Kanfer occasionally fall into an obvious trap: when writing about a comedian, do not attempt to compete for laughs. You cannot top the man who said of the evil tenor in ''A Night at the Opera'': ''You're willing to pay him a thousand dollars a night just for singing? Why, you can get a phonograph record of 'Minnie the Moocher' for 75 cents. For a buck and a quarter, you can get Minnie.''</p>
        <p>Gary Giddins, a columnist at The Village Voice, is the author of ''Visions of Jazz.'' The first volume of his biography of Bing Crosby, ''A Pocketful of Dreams: The Early Years, 1903-1940,'' will be published in January.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gary Giddins, a columnist at The Village Voice, is the author of ''Visions of Jazz.'' The first volume of his biography of Bing Crosby, ''A Pocketful of Dreams: The Early Years, 1903-1940,'' will be published in January.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
