<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Far Off Broadway, Even the Stars Are Paid in Subway Fare</title>
    <meta content="18SHOW$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Editors' Note Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000621T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208498"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Musicals Tonite</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Actors Equity Association</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pogrebin, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Mel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Actors Equity Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E4DD1431F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Far Off Broadway, Even the Stars Are Paid in Subway Fare</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Musicals Tonite is one of many organizations that present theater in New York, unknown to even most stalwart of theatergoers; Musicals Tonite presents plain pipe-rack concert versions of neglected musicals; its unpaid cast receives only carfare, in accordance with Actors Equity Assn rules defined by series of economic yardsticks; Mel Miller, who created Musicals Tonite, says city is full of talented people, forgotten material, willing audiences and not enough work; on any given night in New York City, there are 20 to 30 shows similar to Musicals Tonight productions, in out-of-the-way stages around town; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A show opened on 14th Street last week and will close next week. Most people will never even know it happened. Those who stumble upon it may be disappointed by the lack of scenery, props and costumes or by the fact that cast members read their lines from scripts.</p>
        <p>They may also be bothered by having to follow paper signs up to the second floor and around a corridor to find the 99-seat auditorium in the Sol Goldman Y.M.H.A. on East 14th Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A show opened on 14th Street last week and will close next week. Most people will never even know it happened. Those who stumble upon it may be disappointed by the lack of scenery, props and costumes or by the fact that cast members read their lines from scripts.</p>
        <p>They may also be bothered by having to follow paper signs up to the second floor and around a corridor to find the 99-seat auditorium in the Sol Goldman Y.M.H.A. on East 14th Street.</p>
        <p>But once they pay $15 for a ticket, settle into chipped metal chairs and open photocopied paper programs, audience members may well be pleasantly surprised by what happens on stage. The new production of the 1958 Jean and Walter Kerr musical, ''Goldilocks,'' features the fresh -- and in some cases, slightly weathered -- faces of 14 actors and actresses who can belt out a song, sell a dance number and pull off a slapstick sequence or a love scene.</p>
        <p>All this, even though their only pay is $3 a day for subway fare and they had only two weeks to rehearse for the production, which ends next Sunday.</p>
        <p>The show -- produced by a two-year-old organization called Musicals Tonite, which presents plain pipe-rack concert versions of neglected musicals -- is emblematic of a certain level of theater happening every night in New York City. It flies below the radar of reviews. It is unknown to even the most stalwart of theatergoers.</p>
        <p>There are four tiers of production laid out by the Actors Equity Association, the actors' union, defined by a series of economic yardsticks. Musicals Tonite is in Tier 1, the lowest, in which a producer can pay Equity actors nothing for their work, with the exception of carfare, when needed. On any given night in the city, there are 20 to 30 such shows going on in various, often out-of-the-way stages around town.</p>
        <p>Mel Miller, the 57-year-old former computer salesman behind Musicals Tonite, said he created his company precisely because he realized that the city was full of talented people, forgotten material, willing audiences and not enough work. So he left his most recent career, moderating focus groups, to create a four-show season of musicals, each with a budget of $15,000. In the last two years, the company has produced shows including ''King of Hearts,'' ''Look Ma, I'm Dancing'' and ''Dearest Enemy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller is the company's entire administrative office: he hauls the few pieces of scenery (like the potted trees in ''Goldilocks''), takes the tickets, arranges for the cookies and crudites for the cast party. And, aside from a few small donations so far, Mr. Miller has been footing the bill from his savings. As a result, every costume rental is a calculation.</p>
        <p>For ''Goldilocks,'' Mr. Miller sprang for the only bear suit the play required. It was ''a function of what I can afford, or how much I feel I can afford to lose,'' he said. ''What's a laugh worth every night of a 16-night run? Ten dollars? Twenty dollars? If the director thinks he can get a laugh from a costume that cost $16, that's a dollar a laugh a night. I'm going to spend that. That's worth it.''</p>
        <p>And what's in it for the actors? The opportunity to be seen by casting directors or agents who are invited to the performances, though they don't usually come. A chance to polish their singing, acting and dancing -- and to play a lead role instead of being cast in the chorus.</p>
        <p>They do it because they figure it's better to be working than not working, even if they are working for nothing.</p>
        <p>''It's not like a corporate ladder -- the next step up, the next step up,'' said Michael McKenzie, who has the lead role, a scheming movie director, in ''Goldilocks.'' ''You can be on Broadway and then suddenly you're back in the basement of a church in a corner dressing room with water dripping on your head.''</p>
        <p>While one might expect just a handful of actors to trickle in for auditions for a show that does not pay any money, there was a steady stream of men and women going into the audition room at Actors Equity studios earlier this month -- six people every 20 minutes -- day after day for five days. They proffered their beaming photographs and lengthy resumes and sang their hearts out. (Most casting calls let people get through only a few bars; Musicals Tonite's musical director, Mark Hartman, who also receives the same carfare wages, as does the director, lets actors sing the whole song.)</p>
        <p>The resumes were revealing. Among the venues the actors listed were the Alabama Shakespeare Festival, the Copa Room at the Sands Hotel, the Eugene O'Neill Theater on Broadway and the Disney Cruise Line. Among the ''special skills'' listed at the bottom of the resumes were ''burp on cue,'' ''giving manicures,'' ''lamp repair'' and ''screaming and playing piano with toes.''</p>
        <p>Some of the actors were merely between projects; some were desperate for work. Thomas Mills, who directed ''Goldilocks,'' said the difference was immediately clear.  ''You see it when people walk into an audition if they haven't worked in a while,'' Mr. Mills said. ''They carry an apology with them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mills, 38, who himself has managed to make a living in the theater by directing cabaret acts and industrials -- live presentations for companies -- including a recent show celebrating Sony Walkman's 20th anniversary, said there were also those who came in with palpable confidence. ''They walk into a room with the energy of, 'You should watch me,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>He said he had been struck by the general quality of talent and the number of actors eager to sign on for something with no pay. ''One of my main competitors is the Census Bureau, which is paying $18.50 an hour,'' Mr. Miller said. Musicals Tonite may have a leg up on the government agency by offering actors a forum, he said. But, he added, actors ''also want to eat.''</p>
        <p>Many of those chosen for ''Goldilocks'' support themselves with other work. Mr. McKenzie was recently the maitre d'hotel at a restaurant on the Upper West Side. James Patterson, who plays George, the leading lady's foppish fiance, has worked the front desk and gift shop at a hotel. Erin Malloy, a member of the ensemble, is a hostess and waitress at a restaurant on Columbus Avenue.</p>
        <p>Musicals Tonite rehearses only during the evenings, so that actors can get to their day jobs or go to auditions.</p>
        <p>Although Ms. Malloy, who comes from Pennsylvania and will turn 24 next Sunday, stood out in the ensemble on opening night, she said the last six months had been her longest acting dry spell. ''I'm just not exactly what people are looking for right now,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Doing a show like ''Goldilocks,'' actors say, helps to get through the droughts, along with taking dance, acting and singing classes. (''Sometimes just going out and eating a big old banana split will do it, too,'' said Jen Celene Little, who plays Lois, who aspires to be a star.)</p>
        <p>Even though some of the cast members have been on Broadway or toured in big-budget musicals, several said they did not consider a production like ''Goldilocks'' beneath them. At least they were working, they said, and not having to leave town to do it.</p>
        <p>''There are people who say, 'I'm going to be a star,' '' Mr. Mills said. ''Most of the actors I've met want to be employed.''</p>
        <p>Georgia Creighton, who plays Bessie, a wisecracking matron, in ''Goldilocks,'' said she usually did commercials, but because of a strike by commercial and television actors, she could not take those jobs. ''This was a shot in the arm,'' Ms. Creighton said. ''It was activity. And it was activity that I like.''</p>
        <p>Even though the road from tryout to opening night lasted little more than two weeks, there were bumps along the way, as there always are with Musicals Tonite -- one actor dropped out because he got a paying part. But no one complained about the cramped space at Shetler Studios on Eighth Avenue, where signs warn, ''Absolutely no rehearsing in the halls.'' Nor did anyone complain about weekend rehearsals. The principals never balked at being able to run through songs and scenes only once because big dance numbers needed more of the rehearsal time.</p>
        <p>Mr. McKenzie, who grew up in Nebraska and Massachusetts and moved to New York in 1979, has been in an episode of ''Law and Order.'' He replaced an original cast member in this season's ''Waiting in the Wings'' on Broadway and will understudy a role in ''The Man Who Came To Dinner,'' with Nathan Lane.</p>
        <p>''I stay at it because the rewards, when they come, are so great,'' said Mr. McKenzie, who is in his 40's. ''It carries you through, gets you through the quieter times or the truly frustrating or horrible times.''</p>
        <p>Even though the actors say they try to control their expectations about who might show up at performances, it is difficult. Who might be out there? An agent or producer offering a big break? Most of the time, no. People who come to Musicals Tonite performances find out about the shows through listings in The Village Voice, word of mouth, or industry talk. Mr. Miller also sends out 15,000 postcard announcements through a mailing list provided by the Theater Development Fund, a nonprofit group that runs the TKTS booth and sponsors theater support programs. Musicals Tonite is not listed as a business; people who want information and reservations can call Mr. Miller at (212) 362-5620.</p>
        <p>He said he had about 120 subscribers who pay $60 for the season, not all of whom come to every production. Usually, the auditorium is half full.</p>
        <p>The first performance of ''Goldilocks'' had the excitement of any opening night. A few casting directors, like Warren Pincus of the Goodspeed Opera House, a regional theater in East Haddam, Conn., had reserved tickets for the coming performances. There was even a celebrity in the audience -- Elaine Stritch, who starred as Maggie in the original production of ''Goldilocks'' on Broadway. She came for the first act and went backstage at intermission to offer congratulations.</p>
        <p>''You remind me of me,'' she told Cathy Trien, who plays Maggie. ''Granted, there are 30,000 years between us.''</p>
        <p>There have been a few more ups and downs. One performance had to be canceled because Ms. Trien had a conflict: a part in a Chris Rock film.</p>
        <p>Kelly Mealia, an ensemble member, was also offered a paying role, but stayed put -- which Mr. Miller said brought tears to his eyes.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the players hunker down as if heeding the admonition from Ms. Stritch: ''O.K., kids. Have fun.''</p>
        <p>Editors' Note:  June 21, 2000, Wednesday  A front-page article on Sunday reported on the wide variety of low-budget theatrical productions around New York City making use of the city's huge pool of unemployed talent.</p>
        <p>The article was illustrated by a photograph of four dancers from the unpaid cast of a production of ''Goldilocks'' rehearsing in front of a large mirror. The picture was made with a panoramic camera at a very slow shutter speed, in which the film is exposed from left to right over a period of a full second (compared with a standard speed ranging from one-thirtieth to one-thousandth of a second). Because of the very slow speed, the dancers' images as reflected in the mirror were caught at a slightly later moment, so they looked different.</p>
        <p>This camera technique had an unusual effect in print, raising questions among some readers about whether there had been digital tampering with the image. To forestall such questions, the explanation of the unusual staggering of images should have been explained in the caption.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Editors' Note: June 21, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A front-page article on Sunday reported on the wide variety of low-budget theatrical productions around New York City making use of the city's huge pool of unemployed talent.</p>
        <p>The article was illustrated by a photograph of four dancers from the unpaid cast of a production of ''Goldilocks'' rehearsing in front of a large mirror. The picture was made with a panoramic camera at a very slow shutter speed, in which the film is exposed from left to right over a period of a full second (compared with a standard speed ranging from one-thirtieth to one-thousandth of a second). Because of the very slow speed, the dancers' images as reflected in the mirror were caught at a slightly later moment, so they looked different.</p>
        <p>This camera technique had an unusual effect in print, raising questions among some readers about whether there had been digital tampering with the image. To forestall such questions, the explanation of the unusual staggering of images should have been explained in the caption.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
