<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Branch of the Family</title>
    <meta content="18DOOLITT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Doolittle, W Ford</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tudge, Colin</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Variety of Life, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1D7133FF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1423" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Branch of the Family</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By W. Ford Doolittle</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Doolittle, W Ford</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>W Ford Doolittle reviews book The Variety of Life: A Survey and Celebration of All the Creatures That Have Ever Lived by Colin Tudge (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE VARIETY OF LIFE</p>
        <p>A Survey and a Celebration of</p>
        <p>All the Creatures That Have Ever Lived.</p>
        <p>By Colin Tudge.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 684 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Oxford University Press. $45.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE VARIETY OF LIFE</p>
        <p>A Survey and a Celebration of</p>
        <p>All the Creatures That Have Ever Lived.</p>
        <p>By Colin Tudge.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 684 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Oxford University Press. $45.</p>
        <p>NAMING animals and plants is surely an ancient activity: there is much selective value in recognizing creatures that are similar to others we already know from experience to be edible or noxious, docile or hostile. In ''The Variety of Life,'' Colin Tudge, a very energetic British science writer, has produced a great wodge of a book that attempts to explain and make interesting the whole enterprise of taxonomy (or systematics), the scientific practice that has biological classification as its object.</p>
        <p>I confess that I haven't paid equal attention to all of its 600-plus pages. Fully two-thirds of them are taken up with group-by-group descriptions of all the major kinds of organisms known to exist or to have once existed on earth, and the current best thinking about the relationships among groups. Most descriptions incorporate line drawings and gee-whiz anecdotes: a hundred-ton fungus in Michigan, crabs that climb coconut trees to eat the nuts, eel-like fish that leap high from flooded Amazon waters to capture insects and other prey from the foliage overhead.</p>
        <p>Interspersed among them are discourses on currently unsettled disputes about relationships, such as whether guinea pigs are really rodents, whether modern humans interbred with Neanderthals or whether monocots and dicots are distinct kinds of flowering plants. Although there are errors in descriptions of groups or the recounting of disputes I personally know something about, Tudge has done an enormous amount of homework. Often he errs only in being a year or two out of date on contentious issues: most recent textbooks are no better in this regard. It is hard to keep up.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, the world's species, through their similarities and differences, do seem to arrange themselves into groups that are subordinate to groups, as Darwin put it. Why? Biologists before Darwin saw a pattern, but attributed such regularity to God or to other universal ordering principles. Carl Linnaeus, the 18th-century Swedish botanist, invented modern binomial nomenclature (genus and species, as in Homo and sapiens) and a preliminary version of the contemporary hierarchical classification framework (species, genus, family, order, class, phylum, kingdom and domain) without a consistent view of an underlying process. Darwin's theory had instant appeal, in part because it explained the hierarchical pattern of resemblance: species in a common genus are similar because they evolved from a common ancestral species, the (possibly now extinct) founder of that genus. Species constituting the genera of a common family still look somewhat alike because they share an even earlier antecedent. Following this pattern of coalescing lineages all the way back, Darwin was forced to infer that probably all organic beings that have ever lived on earth have descended from one primordial form, into which life was first breathed. A tree with ever-bifurcating branches is the obvious visual metaphor, and it is the only figure gracing ''The Origin of Species.'' Since Darwin, no classification scheme that is not genealogical (or phylogenetic, as biologists say) could claim to be natural or true. The grand job of systematists seems clear: figure out the tree, all the way down to its single root. And the simplest way to do that seems obvious: construct a hierarchy based on overall similarities.</p>
        <p>But it's not that simple: overall similarity is an unreliable guide to genealogical relationship because different lineages evolve at different rates. For instance, crocodiles and lizards are clearly more like each other over all (four legs, scales, cold blood) than either is like birds. But birds and crocodiles are the closer pair of relatives in a genealogical sense. We are convinced of this because certain key complex traits (such as features of the skull) are shared only by birds and crocodiles; they were gained after the branch leading to their common ancestor diverged from the lizard line. Features common to crocodiles and lizards are ancestral traits present in the first reptile but lost in birds as they adapted to radically nonreptilian lives.</p>
        <p>The need to distinguish these two kinds of traits (derived versus ancestral) in establishing genealogies is one of the essential contributions of the German entomologist Willi Hennig (1913-76) and his followers, who call themselves ''cladists'' and their approach to classification ''cladistics.'' Another key advance, less generally appreciated, is a set of rules for naming groups within any hierarchical classification. For cladists, only clades -- assemblages comprising an ancestral species and all of its descendants (metaphorically, all the branches and twigs attached to a given branch point in the tree) -- deserve names. Either we call birds reptiles or we cannot have such a group as the class Reptilia, because it spawned creatures (in fact two whole classes, Aves and Mammalia) that we don't call reptiles. Disputes about this still rage in the academic literature because there are still those who hold that similarity, if strong enough, should trump relationship, that classification is not just about genealogy.</p>
        <p>Tudge explicates the cladist doctrine quite clearly, while personally adopting an intermediate position (suggesting that we simultaneously recognize a Reptilia that includes mammals and birds and a ''Reptilia'' that doesn't, and would be what most people mean by reptiles). This is the kind of casual ambiguity with which most of us are already comfortable -- without the typographical trickery. I doubt that Tudge's terminology will be embraced by professionals. Similarly, I doubt that all will accept his version of the role of cladists in establishing the general features of the universal tree. The deepest branchings, to the extent that we know them, have been established by molecular biologists who study evolution; they base their conclusions on comparisons between DNA sequences and think very little about Willi Hennig and his rules for naming. It is the application of molecular approaches, as much as cladism, that has transformed the classification business. Modern museums of natural history spend as much on DNA sequencing machines as on fossils, and people who can recognize animals and plants by sight alone are, sadly, ever rarer and less in demand.</p>
        <p>Here too, in trumpeting the molecular approach, Tudge may be overly triumphalist. There are waves of deconstruction sweeping what I call the deep-phylogeny community (those concerned with the tree's earliest branchings, which most likely date back 2.5 billion to 4 billion years). Some think we have placed too much faith in molecules, that too many mutations have occurred in that very long time and thus that the genealogical signals on which we have rooted the universal tree are actually noise. Others think that genes are swapped between species (particularly among single-celled organisms) sufficiently frequently that if you look back far enough, the different genes making up an organism's genome will have different genealogies. In the first case, the universal tree would be unknowable; in the second, there would be no tree to know. Not surprisingly, these are fighting words in the community. Tudge might have quite a different book to write five or ten years down the road.</p>
        <p>The large sections of Tudge's volume that attempt to classify all forms of life occupy an uncertain ground between the coffee table and the reference shelf. The workmanlike drawn figures offer neither the engrossing detail of 19th-century biological illustration nor the vividness of 20th-century color photography. The group descriptions are too breezy, too patchy and too personal (Tudge doesn't hesitate to rule on disputes between the experts) to recommend the book as an authoritative summary of current wisdom in biological classification. (I would choose instead the idiosyncratic but more engagingly illustrated ''Five Kingdoms,'' by Lynn Margulis and Karlene V. Schwartz.)</p>
        <p>Curiously, ''The Variety of Life'' is the second attempt to present the arcana of cladistics and evolutionary reconstruction to a general readership in two years. The first, ''In Search of Deep Time,'' by Henry Gee, has already been reviewed in these pages. Gee is intensely (too intensely, I think) skeptical of all reconstruction efforts. It is probable that we can know more than Gee allows but less than Tudge claims. Nevertheless, there is every reason to promote public interest in this historical science. We, the products of almost four billion years of evolution, are poised to wipe out half the other products. The least we can do is try to name them as they go.</p>
        <p>W. Ford Doolittle, an evolutionary biologist at Dalhousie University in Halifax, Nova Scotia, is the Richard Ivey fellow of the Canadian Institute for Advanced Research.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">W. Ford Doolittle, an evolutionary biologist at Dalhousie University in Halifax, Nova Scotia, is the Richard Ivey fellow of the Canadian Institute for Advanced Research.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
