<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mosley Takes De La Hoya's Title on Split Decision</title>
    <meta content="18FITE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208553"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Boxing Council</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spousta, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De La Hoya, Oscar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mosley, Shane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EFDB1431F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mosley Takes De La Hoya's Title on Split Decision</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM SPOUSTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Spousta, Tom</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shane Mosley defeats Oscar De La Hoya in split decision, capturing World Boxing Council welterweight title, Los Angeles; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shane Mosley shook up the welterweight ranks tonight with a final-round flurry that clinched a split decision over Oscar De La Hoya in a brilliant fight at the soldout Staples Center.</p>
        <p>Mosley, of Pomona, Calif., captured the World Boxing Council title with a strong showing in the middle rounds and carried that momentum to the end. In the 12th, he rocked De La Hoya several times with hard rights from close range.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shane Mosley shook up the welterweight ranks tonight with a final-round flurry that clinched a split decision over Oscar De La Hoya in a brilliant fight at the soldout Staples Center.</p>
        <p>Mosley, of Pomona, Calif., captured the World Boxing Council title with a strong showing in the middle rounds and carried that momentum to the end. In the 12th, he rocked De La Hoya several times with hard rights from close range.</p>
        <p>As the decision was announced, Mosley (35-0) was lifted on his handlers' shoulders as De La Hoya (32-2) stood stone-faced with his hands on his hips.</p>
        <p>''We went toe to toe for 12 rounds,'' Mosley said. ''We went soul-searching in the 12th. I was just the better man tonight. De La Hoya is a great champion. It was a close fight, a great fight. We showed we're both two great warriors from the L.A. area.''</p>
        <p>De La Hoya, an East Los Angeles native, said: ''I knew he was fast, and I felt I matched his speed. He kept coming. There's got to be a rematch. Every great fight like this deserves a rematch.''</p>
        <p>The judges Lou Filippo and Pat Russell gave Mosley the decision by 116-112 and 115-113. The judge Marty Sammon scored it 115-113 for De La Hoya.</p>
        <p>With two rounds to go, De La Hoya found his career on the ropes. His nose was bloody, Mosley appeared to be ahead on all scorecards and De La Hoya was still searching for a knockout blow that would never come.</p>
        <p>The fight dramatically shifted in the 9th and 10th rounds. Mosley's quickness continually beat De La Hoya to the punch. Mosley took both rounds, scoring often with flurries.</p>
        <p>Mosley confused De La Hoya in the eighth by switching to a left-handed stance and stole the round with his counterpunches. The fight appeared even at that point, leaving the pro-De La Hoya crowd to wonder if their fighter was fading.</p>
        <p>Through seven rounds, De La Hoya appeared to have a slight edge. His strength was wearing down Mosley, who landed two big right hands in the seventh but never seemed to hurt De La Hoya. Still, Mosley's persistence kept gnawing at De La Hoya, who was frustrated by not being able to pin down Mosley with his attacks.</p>
        <p>Mosley's speed won the first round, as he landed several right jabs and a left hook that lifted De La Hoya's front foot off the ground.</p>
        <p>De La Hoya quickly took control in the second round. Measuring Mosley from the start, he landed several combinations and a couple of left hooks that easily gave him the round.</p>
        <p>The third round began with Mosley firing two quick right hands that should have done some damage but did not. De La Hoya gradually picked up steam and scored with several jabs. A solid left hook stunned Mosley for an instant and clearly won the round for De La Hoya.</p>
        <p>De La Hoya rallied from a poor fourth round to dominate the fifth. He rocked Mosley with a combination to the head and a left hook to the body late in the round. Mosley staggered somewhat, but quickly recovered.</p>
        <p>After nearly every round, De La Hoya nodded his head as though he was in control of his destiny.</p>
        <p>Mosley was trying to become the sixth fighter to win both the lightweight and welterweight titles, joining De La Hoya, Roberto Duran, Pernell Whitaker, Henry Armstrong and Barney Ross.</p>
        <p>His lack of championship fight experience was considered his biggest weakness heading into tonight. He was also thought of by some as a blown-up lightweight after having jumped two classes to become a 147-pound welterweight.</p>
        <p>But was he? In his debut, he dispatched the highly regarded Wilfredo Rivera with a final-round knockout. Rivera had never been knocked out, not even by De La Hoya in their 1997 fight. In his only other welterweight bout, Mosley had scored a third-round technical knockout of Willy Wise in January.</p>
        <p>Mosley's plan was obvious from the opening bell: use his quickness, movement around the ring and determination to take De La Hoya's title.</p>
        <p>De La Hoya did not offer any surprises, either, using his size and power to press the attack in hopes of setting up Mosley for his vaunted left hand.</p>
        <p>De La Hoya was making the first defense of his W.B.C. title since beating Derrell Coley in an elimination bout in February. De La Hoya was awarded the title again when Felix Trinidad relinquished it after beating David Reid for the super welterweight championship.</p>
        <p>PUNCH LINES</p>
        <p>Also on Saturday night's card, DIEGO CORRALES (32-0, 25 knockouts) defended his International Boxing Association junior lightweight title with a knockout of JUSTIN JUUKO (34-4-1) at 2 minutes 35 seconds of the 10th round. . . . The World Boxing Council super bantamweight champion ERIK MORALES (37-0, 26 knockouts) moved up to featherweight and knocked out MIKE JUAREZ (22-9-1) at 1:12 of the third round.</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
