<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Not Easy Being Equal</title>
    <meta content="18RYANLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208061"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ryan, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dworkin, Ronald</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sovereign Virtue: The Theory and Practice of Equality (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E0D7133FF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Not Easy Being Equal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Ryan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ryan, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Ryan reviews book Sovereign Virtue: The Theory and Practice of Equality by Ronald Dworkin (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sovereign Virtue</p>
        <p>The Theory and Practice of Equality.</p>
        <p>By Ronald Dworkin.</p>
        <p>511 pp. Cambridge, Mass.:</p>
        <p>Harvard University Press. $35.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sovereign Virtue</p>
        <p>The Theory and Practice of Equality.</p>
        <p>By Ronald Dworkin.</p>
        <p>511 pp. Cambridge, Mass.:</p>
        <p>Harvard University Press. $35.</p>
        <p>Ronald Dworkin is perhaps best known today for his part in a recent and acrimonious argument with Judge Richard A. Posner. The bone of contention was Posner's reflections on the assorted forms of misconduct that had brought President Clinton to the brink of impeachment; and Dworkin caused a stir by arguing that a sitting judge had no business making the adverse comments on President Clinton's honesty that enlivened Posner's little volume. ''Sovereign Virtue'' is far removed from that controversy, though certainly not from all controversy. Indeed, the arguments in ''Sovereign Virtue'' are highly controversial. Dworkin makes a plausible case for the strikingly implausible idea that equality is the sovereign political virtue, and then illustrates this claim with sharply pointed discussions of such topics as abortion, affirmative action and the role of money in politics.</p>
        <p>The first half of the book is political philosophy of the most austere sort, impressively well argued, and difficult enough to provide a well-trained graduate student with a semester's work. It pursues into the last recesses of analysis the proposition that the fundamental principle that should govern our politics is equality. Contrary to the intuitions of most of us, Dworkin argues, it is equality rather than liberty, equality rather than national glory, equality rather than the inculcation of virtue in the citizenry, that we must pursue. The second half applies Dworkin's views on equality to a variety of contested political questions: Is the high cost of health care in the United States an affront to justice? Does the role of money in American politics frustrate a democratic dedication to free speech? May the state criminalize behavior -- prostitution, for instance, or the sale of pornography -- that it considers a sign of bad character? Does the new knowledge provided by the science of genetics call for the government to play God in deciding what we may and may not do to enhance the genetic endowment of our children?</p>
        <p>The chapters on these subjects are for the most part slightly reworked essays from The New York Review of Books, but they read as though they were written for the present book. For two decades Dworkin has been an astonishingly coherent and consistent thinker -- not, to all readers, a wholly persuasive thinker, and to many critics entirely unpersuasive. Still, almost everyone who has read his polemical essays agrees that they all hang together, that there is an underlying philosophy that lends an almost startling unity to Dworkin's views on the most disparate subjects. A belief in campaign finance reform is not, on the face of it, a conviction that necessarily suggests passionate views on abortion or genetic modification; nor do most of us feel that our views on abortion run naturally into our views on affirmative action.</p>
        <p>Many of Dworkin's critics have complained that he treats commitments that are in the final analysis purely political as if they were the dictates of pure reason. Other critics have complained not so much that the positions advanced are political, as that the philosophy behind them is continuously adjusted, reinterpreted and shaded in such a way that we never know quite what his underlying philosophical convictions are. And some, of course, have complained of both things at once. For those of us who admire his work, the pleasure of following him into the most intricate corners of jurisprudential and philosophical speculation outweighs whatever doubts we may have about its coherence.</p>
        <p>Dworkin devotes the stiffest part of ''Sovereign Virtue'' to an explication of the thought that the fundamental virtue of any society is equality. The equality in question is not a simple equality of income or wealth -- not, that is, the equality we would get if we simply divided the gross national product of the United States by the entire population and arrived at so many dollars per head. Why not? The question is not absurd; the French revolutionary Gracchus Babeuf advocated something very like it in the early 1790's, and was guillotined for his pains.</p>
        <p>Jeremy Bentham, too, began from the view that because most people get a decreasing amount of happiness from each successive addition to their income and wealth, the way to maximize the total happiness of a society is to distribute wealth and income equally. It is not equality but departures from equality that need explaining and justifying. An equal share-out of society's goods is self-evidently the place to start from. The plausibility of this view does much to explain why economists who would defend capitalism to their last breath still feel obliged to justify the inequalities and injustices of a capitalist economy as an inevitable part of a system that is a better bargain than an egalitarian economy, not so much for the rich as for the poor.</p>
        <p>Dworkin is, one might say, to the left of Bentham and to the right of Babeuf. He does not think that equality consists in sharing out whatever we happen to have available at present; but he does not believe that inequality is justified whenever it produces more happiness in total. What he cares about is fairness, not maximizing happiness. How do we know whether people have a fair share of the good things our society's productivity makes possible? We make what economists, following the physicists, call a ''thought experiment.''</p>
        <p>Imagine that everyone starts with an equal amount of something -- cowrie shells, iron bars, glass beads -- that serves as a currency. We then auction off everything that will help us in leading an interesting and fulfilling life; after one round of the auction we ask if all are happy with the lots they have purchased. If anyone isn't, we run the auction again. That is equality of resources; and that is a fair distribution of whatever we find necessary, useful and agreeable.</p>
        <p>To decide whether our society is a fair society, we ask whether we can imagine it being the way it is simply on the strength of what people might have done with the resources they got in the auction. A very inegalitarian society might well be a just one. If my deepest wish is to sit on a beach in Maine fishing for bass, I might cheerfully forgo stock options in Microsoft to do it. If I have a passion for gambling, my fortunes might ricochet up and down without anyone having reason to think it all very unfair.</p>
        <p>But the differences in wealth, income, health, education, access to political influence and the rest of it in countries such as the United States and Britain are so extreme, and persist so powerfully from one generation to another, that it is impossible to believe that they merely reflect different tastes and talents, and different preferences about how we should spend our time. It is impossible not to believe that most -- by no means all -- of the inequality reflects the fact that the better-off can buy the political influence that enables them to ensure that they can pass on their good fortune to their children and their friends without hindrance.</p>
        <p>It takes no great imagination to see that an egalitarian of Dworkin's stripe will wish to deprive money of the role that it plays in American politics. The claim that buying politicians is an expression of the principle of free speech gets short shrift. What a democracy is supposed to be about is the equalization of political impact, and buying politicians is as likely to be a threat to freedom of speech as it is to be an example of it. It is only slightly harder to see that Dworkin's egalitarianism would support a more extensive welfare state than the United States so far possesses, and that it would also support a national health service more generous than Medicaid and Medicare -- and better financed than the British system.</p>
        <p>When buying resources at our imaginary auction, one of the things we'd buy is insurance against ill health, unemployment, destitution in old age and so on. A theorist who can work out how much insurance the average person would buy knows how large a welfare state a rational society ought to provide. Individuals can then top up social provision as they like. But it is less obvious that Dworkin's egalitarianism will take us far into the realm of contentious social issues like abortion. Indeed, it is clear that egalitarianism is beside the point. What decides the moral argument in the case of abortion is the wickedness of making other people's deepest and most difficult decisions for them and enforcing your own view by law. True enough, there is an inequality involved in this: in effect, I decide about both my life and your life, and you don't decide about either. Still, it remains far from obvious that it is this inequality that matters rather than -- as the Supreme Court decided -- the privacy and the sanctity of our intimate relations. But the pleasure of reading ''Sovereign Virtue'' is that although few of Dworkin's conclusions are self-evident, his arguments are dazzlingly clever.</p>
        <p>Alan Ryan is the warden of New College, Oxford.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Alan Ryan is the warden of New College, Oxford.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
