<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Express to the Highlands</title>
    <meta content="TRAIN.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208080"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Scotland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodwin, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Scotland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E5DB103FF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Express to the Highlands</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON GOODWIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodwin, Jason</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jason Goodwin travel article on trip through Scottish Highlands; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Highlands of Scotland are split by a long geological fault line, the Great Glen, which slants across the country from sea to sea, and is mostly filled with fresh water. Loch Ness lies near the middle. The region's turbulent past can be read in the names of three towns along the Glen: Fort George in the northeast, Fort Augustus in the center, and Fort William in the southwest.</p>
        <p>The forts, like their later namesakes on the Great Plains, were built in the 17th and 18th centuries to subdue the locals. They were duly subdued.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Highlands of Scotland are split by a long geological fault line, the Great Glen, which slants across the country from sea to sea, and is mostly filled with fresh water. Loch Ness lies near the middle. The region's turbulent past can be read in the names of three towns along the Glen: Fort George in the northeast, Fort Augustus in the center, and Fort William in the southwest.</p>
        <p>The forts, like their later namesakes on the Great Plains, were built in the 17th and 18th centuries to subdue the locals. They were duly subdued.</p>
        <p>After the Rebellion of 1745, the clan chiefs were transformed into dukes and earls, and in their new roles as landed proprietors, they were encouraged to replace clansmen with sheep. Up and down the country, tenant crofters were evicted. The Highland population sank to a few thousand, and the Highlands became a glorious wilderness.</p>
        <p>Yet something did remain, some irrepressible question of attitude. Highlanders can be very charming -- like John Brown, Queen Victoria's devoted gamekeeper -- and very dry, too. Like porridge, you can take the Highlands sweet, or salty.</p>
        <p>The sweet began for me on a September evening in London as a black cab rushed me away from a gallery-opening to Euston station. I had a weekend to myself, and I meant to make the most of it by hitting the Highlands of Scotland on a Caledonian Sleeper, a working train also affectionately known as the Deerstalker Express. Its existence is a kind of open secret vouchsafed to belted earls and dedicated fishermen. I saw it as an escape hatch to walks in the heather, fly-fishing and baronial luxury.</p>
        <p>The Deerstalker Express first thundered north to Fort William when Victoria was on the throne. It survived the decline of aristocracy, world wars and nationalization only to be threatened by the privatizing ax in 1996. But the accountants in charge had not reckoned with the Deerstalker's loyal following, and an unlikely band of landowners, sportsmen and environmentalists promptly joined forces to save the last scheduled overnight service to the Western Highlands.</p>
        <p>A train is a very public place, but a berth on the sleeper is one of the most private. I was shown to my little first-class cabin -- little bed, little basin, window, night light and an extra blanket, trim as a toy house. I took a nightcap in the comfortable, modern dining car, planned a breakfast of Loch Fyne smoked salmon and scrambled eggs, and retired to bed. London had slipped away, and it was black out there. I pulled the blind, put out the lamp, and arranged myself for sleep.</p>
        <p>Around 5:30 in the morning, I woke to a change in the music of the wheels, and a blue dawn revealed a sheet of water, dark hills in the distance, a few lights winking through trees. I stayed awake to watch the sun rise while the train lurched up a gradient, whirrs following pauses, clanks following tugs, at about 15 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>By the time we reached level ground, the sun was up, and I crossed the bleak expanse of Rannoch Moor, all bog and moss, lying in bed: one of the most delicious experiences of travel I know.</p>
        <p>After this, things began to go a little awry -- a touch of the salt. At the smart little station at Ardlui, I caught sight of the Royal Scotsman, getting up steam across the platform. The people on this luxury touring train were at the windows of their dining car, and I rather pitied them their comfortable $2,000-a-head cocoon -- I paid a tenth of that for the round trip from London to Fort William. Seeing them tuck into croissants and kippers reminded me of my own tryst with salmon and scrambled eggs.</p>
        <p>I bustled along to the dining car for my breakfast and -- horrors! -- the dining car had disappeared. The train had split in the night, and my breakfast was thundering away to Aberdeen. The tea tray delivered by the attendant was not the same thing -- muesli bars and a croissant wrapped in plastic. I had nothing left to do, and was feeling rather tired, so I lay back in my berth and fell asleep.</p>
        <p>Fort William stands between Loch Linnhe and the tallest mountain in Britain, Ben Nevis, which at 4,406 feet isn't terribly tall, but several climbers die on it every year. It is mostly the weather that kills: sudden, extreme reversals are common, and what may begin as a sunny walk to the summit can rapidly turn into a slippery battle with fog, sleet and driving winds.</p>
        <p>The train pulled into the station at 9:43 a.m. The center of Fort William, I quickly learned, is but a street's length of fishing and hiking shops and liquor stores, with a slather of concrete, an expanse of lawn, a spiky Victorian church or two, a handsome stone hotel commanding a stretch of grass called the parade, and the loch running alongside. I was aiming for something grander, the Inverlochy Castle, a Relais and Chateaux establishment outside town. But before I took a cab to the hotel, I wandered up High Street to find the local paper and a cup of tea.</p>
        <p>''Carradale fisherman Raymond Gosling thought the creature which slithered out of his net was just another eel. But closer inspection. . . .''</p>
        <p>I read this item from The Oban Times (''The Highland's Biggest Selling Weekly Newspaper,'' circulation 18,000); it sounded like a Loch Ness Monster story. But Mr. Gosling's eel was unquestionably real, and had holes along the side, such as no one in Carradale had ever seen before. Using his local library, Mr. Gosling identified it as a Caspian lamprey, which ordinarily live in the landlocked Caspian Sea south of the Russian steppes. The newspaper went on to say that ''although it is unlikely that the unusual marine specimen found its own way out of the Caspian, . . . the fish sometimes get carried to far-off places on the backs of sharks. Suction occasionally builds up and they stick onto their skin.''</p>
        <p>There's a line of Highland humor so dry it can be taken for earnestness, but -- and here's the beauty of it -- there's a streak of Highland seriousness so honest it can be mistaken for humor.</p>
        <p>I was reminded of this peculiar story a few hours later, when I found myself standing up to my knees in the River Lochy, casting for trout with the expert assistance of a local guide, Martin Brown. I had already checked into the Inverlochy, which turned out to be one of those big baronial structures that industrialists used to build for themselves in Scotland, California and Australia. It is, as the brochures say, sumptuously appointed, with stags' heads and roaring fires. But I had elected to sleep in a much cheaper annex in the grounds, the Factor's House, a stiff walk from the castle. My room was big and comfortable, but the annex was completely deserted.</p>
        <p>The hotel staff, though, was quite helpful and had arranged the outing with Martin. My aim was to learn the rudiments of fly-fishing, how to cast a brilliant little twist of pheasant feathers and catgut so that it kissed the water and hooked a trout. While Martin effortlessly handled yards and yards of fishing line so that his fly touched a small pool across the river, I yanked up short lengths of twine and splashed my fly into the river a few yards off.</p>
        <p>As the afternoon advanced, we sidled down the river, heading for a low branch that marked a pool where bigger fish might be lurking. He told me that there are large pools, or little lochs, called murrains, high up on the mountains, where the water is very clear, very cold, and frequently frozen over in the winter. You wouldn't expect to find fish in them, Martin pointed out, but you do. You can go up with a rod and land yourself a brown trout and wonder, how in creation did this fish get in there?</p>
        <p>''I couldn't understand it myself,'' Martin said, ''so I looked it up on the Internet. There are two schools. One says the Victorians seeded the lochs. Another thinks the fish were carried there in the last ice age. I don't know what to think.''</p>
        <p>Nor do I, but I would bet that the story of the Highlands lies in there, between the ice age and the Internet, among people who can mention them in the same breath without blinking.</p>
        <p>My first few casts were a mess, but I gradually improved. Soon, I had hooked something. The rod grew heavy and lively. I reeled in a three-inch trout and Martin unhooked it and put the fish gently back in the water, facing upstream. It was gone before I could blink. Eventually, I got very cold feet and aching arms and some sense of the pleasures of fishing, just as I had hoped.</p>
        <p>That evening, after Martin dropped me off at the hotel, I found a place to sit among the armchair atolls in the oceanic great hall. Later, I was summoned to my table in one of the dining rooms, walls hung with prints, windows swagged, where everyone down to an American honeymooning couple took his cue from the waiters and acted as if Uncle Hamish had just died upstairs. I had a tasty bit of game pie, pigeon with a teaspoonful of lentils and a bit of cheese that cost only a tad more than my afternoon's fishing.</p>
        <p>The following morning, I discovered that the Tourist Information Center in Fort William has a wall exhibit that explains all about ice and gneiss, and reminds you that you are among the oldest mountains in the world. If you take a hike up Glen Nevis, round the base of the Ben, you can see for yourself that this is true.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of feet above the river stands a granite cliff sculptured and smoothed by centuries of running water. At the head of the gorge, the valley opens out into a broad water meadow; the river lilts and meanders over pebbles, and on the far side of the valley you can see the Nevis Falls, hardly moving at this distance, but spurting and thundering as you approach their base.</p>
        <p>I struck out on the well-marked walk that takes just a few hours but plunges you immediately into the grandeur of the Highlands. In the distance I saw an odd sight: a group of hikers dancing madly about the stream, waving their arms and shaking their heads, apparently engulfed in some kind of chemical or religious ecstasy. They moved off as I approached.</p>
        <p>I spread my coat on the grass and settled down to my picnic -- superior crab sandwiches provided by the hotel. In a moment, I was on my feet, slapping my face and rubbing my hair while grabbing up my sandwiches with a free hand. I had forgotten the bane of the Highlands: midges, which are particularly active in late summer.</p>
        <p>In the end, I had lunch in the ruins of a sheil, or farmstead, beside the track to Rannoch Moor. Even on a sunny afternoon it was a somber place; one had only to imagine it in winter -- miles from anywhere, night fallen and the snows lying deep -- to come up with a picture of scarcely credible self-reliance.</p>
        <p>At Fort William's excellent West Highland Museum, housed in a late Georgian building on Cameron Square, you can learn how people have scratched and subsisted on this ancient landscape. They have worked its trees and stones, leaving beautiful ax heads from the Stone Age, Celtic jewelry, the blade of a bronze sword. There are suggestions of myth and magic, the cement that connected people to their surroundings and the darker world beyond: amulets and cures, keepsakes and trophies. And there are objects so rare and weird that they seemed to have dropped from the world beyond: so-called drift-seeds, which  floated ashore from the West Indies and were turned into charms, odd-shaped or queerly colored pebbles that drew fevers, or brought a loved one home.</p>
        <p>THIS sense of having been touched by something greater than life attaches even to the cabinet of mementos of the '45, the last Highland rebellion, touched off in 1745 by the return of the 25-year-old Bonnie Prince Charlie, Charles Edward Stuart, the Young Pretender to the British throne, from France. It was a wild plan, doomed to failure as soon as the weakness of the prince's support was known: but it brought the last full Highland charge in history, when the terrible Gaelic war cry whooped down the glen, and the clansmen bounded forward on the Redcoats.</p>
        <p>When order was reimposed from Edinburgh and London, people still hung on to bits and pieces of that time -- a cup, a bit of a saddlebag that went through the whole '45 campaign, a clipping of Charlie's kilt, and even one of his supposed teeth, ''hardly worn, suggesting he lost it early in life,'' as the caption in the museum dryly notes.</p>
        <p>They made secret portraits like the one here, a meaningless smear of paint on a wooden plate that reveals the features of the prince when viewed in a silver cylinder. If ever there was a place where myths could endure, it was among the isolated glens and islands of Scotland.</p>
        <p>Hard on the heels of the Rebellion of '45, though, the Highlanders started moving out. Drawn by the hope of a fresh start, they found themselves pushed abroad by poverty, by rapacious new landlords who wanted villages cleared for sheep and deer, and by overcrowding. Sir Walter Scott thrilled the whole world with the old legends and exploits of the highland heroes, but meanwhile their descendants turned Fort William into an emigrant port, through which thousands of dispossessed crofters passed on their way to a new life in Australia or North America.</p>
        <p>It was not yet dark when the London sleeper slid out of Fort William Station. I did not brood for long on the triumphs and tragedies of Highland history. When I next opened my eyes, I saw the huddled rooftops of suburban London, and a cheerful attendant, passing me a cup of tea.</p>
        <p>Castles and myths by the loch</p>
        <p>The Caledonian Sleeper known as the Deerstalker Express runs from London to Fort William every night except Saturday. It leaves Euston Station in London at 9:33 p.m. and arrives in Fort William at 9:43 a.m. Tickets cost about $208, $253 in first class, or $163 booked a week or more ahead, at the rate of $1.50 to the pound. Information: ScotRail, (44-845) 755-0033.</p>
        <p>The Fort William Tourist Information Center, on Cameron Square, (44-1397) 703-781, is open 9 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. weekdays; in July and August, it is open till 8:30 daily except 10 to 6 p.m. Sunday. It provides all manner of information, from maps to lodging. Anyone contemplating an ascent of Ben Nevis, which can be treacherous, should get advice here.</p>
        <p>In high season, June through September, double rooms at Inverlochy Castle Hotel in Fort William start at about $520, including tax and breakfast for two. Dinner is a four-course set menu at $68 a person. At the Factor's House, a guest house on the grounds, high-season doubles start at $143, breakfast extra. From the United States, (888) 424-0106 or (44-1397) 702-177, fax (44-1397) 702-953.</p>
        <p>The hotel can arrange fishing with a guide for about $82 a half day or $128 all day for up to three people.</p>
        <p>Crannog, (44-1397) 705-589, is an excellent seafood restaurant on the loch at Fort William. Dinner for two with wine, about $75.</p>
        <p>West Highland Museum, opposite the tourist office, (44-1397) 702-169, illuminates the area's history. Open Monday to Saturday 10 a.m. to 4 p.m., till 5 p.m. and on Sunday 2 to 5 p.m. in July and August. Entry $3, 75 cents under age 18.</p>
        <p>JASON GOODWIN's latest book is ''Lords of the Horizon: A History of the Ottoman Empire'' (Holt).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">JASON GOODWIN's latest book is ''Lords of the Horizon: A History of the Ottoman Empire'' (Holt).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
