<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Americana, Otherwise Called Junk</title>
    <meta content="18SALE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AT HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yard Sales</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kinnane, Karen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFDF1E3EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Americana, Otherwise Called Junk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, George</byline>
      <dateline>POMPTON PLAINS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Karen Kinnane, antiques dealer, collector and appraiser of Americana who offers courses on holding successful yard sales in New Jersey; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hosting a successful yard sale is a lot like sex,'' Karen Kinnane likes to say. ''If it isn't fun, you're probably not doing it right.''</p>
        <p>Apparently a lot of people are having a lot of fun -- the sellers and the buyers -- transforming their backyards into valuable pieces of summer real estate for commerce and recreation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hosting a successful yard sale is a lot like sex,'' Karen Kinnane likes to say. ''If it isn't fun, you're probably not doing it right.''</p>
        <p>Apparently a lot of people are having a lot of fun -- the sellers and the buyers -- transforming their backyards into valuable pieces of summer real estate for commerce and recreation.</p>
        <p>Witness the signs tacked to telephone poles shouting YARD SALE; the heavy traffic on normally tranquil streets; the glassy-eyed husbands, tagging along behind wives saying, ''You've got to be kidding.''</p>
        <p>They're even doing it on the Internet now, said Ms. Kinnane, by going to yard sales looking for junque and selling it on eBay.</p>
        <p>''Yard-saling is a way of life,'' said Ms. Kinnane, who has elevated this suburban avocation into a vocation as an antiques dealer, collector and appraiser of Americana. In addition, for the last five years she has offered courses in Wayne, Pequannock and Ridgewood called ''The Best Yard Sale Ever!''</p>
        <p>''It's coast to coast up into Canada, all over,'' she said in an interview at her home here, the Jacob Slingerland Farmhouse, built around 1750. ''Yard sales in America and in Canada are a tremendous multi-, multi-billion dollar business.''</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of people who buy nothing at all retail,'' she said. ''You can buy cars at yard sales, appliances, clothing, toys, food.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Kinnane began to hold yard sales 25 years ago for much the same reason most people do.</p>
        <p>''I collected too much stuff and it was either that or buy another house in which to live and one to keep the stuff in as a museum,'' she said. After a while, she branched out and began holding sales for other people too.</p>
        <p>She estimates that 20 years ago one in 20 households had a sale at least once every five years. Today, she says, 7 in 20 do.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people in the beginning were ashamed that anyone should see their discards,'' she said. ''So that's why they would give them to charities. But then it became more fashionable as time went on and everyone realized the social benefits, not only the recycling part, but having all the neighbors coming over and chit-chatting.''</p>
        <p>It is not uncommon for whole blocks and even whole towns to stage a yard sale and pool their resources for advertising.</p>
        <p>As a result, she said, charities that specialize in reselling items are having a harder time because they're getting the yard sale leftovers.</p>
        <p>So who are these yard sale ''junque-ies''?</p>
        <p>''There are so many different types,'' she said. ''There's the casual person who will show up at noontime and poke around and see if there's something small that would interest them.''</p>
        <p>There are ''occasionals,'' who show up occasionally, the ''never-beens,'' who have never been to a yard sale before and kind of wander around; young housewives looking for childrens' clothes and toys; and businesspeople looking for expensive suits and other clothes.</p>
        <p>The last type of junque-ie is the dedicated collector. ''They've bought so much that the family will not let them bring it home.'' So, she said,  ''Collectors eventually become dealers, especially now with eBay.''</p>
        <p>''They are the customers we like the best, because these people travel with large amounts of cash, large vehicles that they start out having empty and fill up by the end of the day,'' she said. ''They'll hit sometimes 30 or 35 sales in one day on Friday or Saturday.''</p>
        <p>''Some people start out in the morning and have a route where they go through certain towns every Friday and different towns every Saturday, and they head out down Route 46 looking for leftover sales on Sunday,'' she added.</p>
        <p>The avid buyer will show up an hour or two before the sale officially begins and start shopping. Ms. Kinnane recalled that for a sale of books by the author Albert Payson Terhune a woman from Ohio arrived the previous day and slept in her van.</p>
        <p>Almost anything will sell at a yard sale if it is priced right, even old photographs of family members. ''Instant ancestors,'' said Ms. Kinanne. ''There are a lot of Americans who have no roots.''</p>
        <p>AT HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
