<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Music As Muse For Art</title>
    <meta content="18JOUR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208176"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Huntington School of Fine Arts</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Garden City Hotel (Garden City, Ny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purcell, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burrage, Ronnie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garrison, Matthew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dell, Lenny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2DA133EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Music As Muse For Art</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Journal column: Students at Huntington School of Fine Arts, their portfolios for the semester complete, switch mediums and create art works by candlelight as musicians John Purcell, Ronnie Burrage and Matthew Garrison perform world music; pianist Lenny Dell, lounge player in lobby of Garden City Hotel, comments on his craft and celebrities he has met; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS the quirky tones of a jazz trio resonated, Emily Tanner, 17, of Centerport picked at the large chunk of clay on the sculpture stand in front of her. She scratched out a skyscraper, hewed an old man's face, then rotated the mound to the other side to carve out a pregnant woman holding a baby. ''It's like the blurbs of ink with the psychiatrist,'' Emily said, chiseling fastidiously with a plastic tool as the improvised strains of world music being played in the center of the art studio became more strident. ''I'm just looking and seeing what I see. Tonight it's a little more risky. I wanted to do something I wasn't as comfortable with.''</p>
        <p>Most of the time, the high school students at the Huntington School of Fine Arts sculpture, paint and draw in silence. Usually, the lights in the waterfront warehouse that serves as a studio are on. And, nearly always, the parameters under which they work are strictly defined.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS the quirky tones of a jazz trio resonated, Emily Tanner, 17, of Centerport picked at the large chunk of clay on the sculpture stand in front of her. She scratched out a skyscraper, hewed an old man's face, then rotated the mound to the other side to carve out a pregnant woman holding a baby. ''It's like the blurbs of ink with the psychiatrist,'' Emily said, chiseling fastidiously with a plastic tool as the improvised strains of world music being played in the center of the art studio became more strident. ''I'm just looking and seeing what I see. Tonight it's a little more risky. I wanted to do something I wasn't as comfortable with.''</p>
        <p>Most of the time, the high school students at the Huntington School of Fine Arts sculpture, paint and draw in silence. Usually, the lights in the waterfront warehouse that serves as a studio are on. And, nearly always, the parameters under which they work are strictly defined.</p>
        <p>But on this evening, their portfolios for the semester complete, the 100 aspiring artists put aside convention. They snapped off the lights and lighted dozens of candles. And as the musicians, John Purcell, Ronnie Burrage and Matthew Garrison, performed ''Art in Concert,'' an improvisational gig on keyboards, woodwinds and bass guitar, sculptors worked in oil, painters opted to mold in clay, sketchers smeared paint with their fingers and painted words instead of flowers. Only a nude model posing on a platform in the center of the drawing room seemed impervious to the sound.</p>
        <p>''The music helps isolate the creativity and with that the creativity is able to flourish,'' Emily said. ''The music relaxes you. They are offbeat and crazy and it influences you to do the same in your artwork. It helps you to forget academics and go with  emotions. As the music is spontaneous, you become more spontaneous.''</p>
        <p>The music screeched, whined and whirled, briefly mellifluous. Building to a crescendo, the sound boomed, reverberating through the studio. Mr. Burrage cried out. Mr. Purcell wailed.</p>
        <p>The idea of a concert in art class, said Joseph Mack, 79, a sculptor and founder of the 19-year-old school, was to remove constrictions and inspire creativity among his students. Most of the participants are enrolled in the school's college-prep portfolio program, believed to be the only one of its kind on the Island.</p>
        <p>Mr. Purcell, who splits his time between New York and California, visited the school earlier this year to see the artwork of his 17-year-old daughter, Alicia. Convinced that sound waves were the way to bring music and art together, he offered to perform. This was his second concert at the school this year.</p>
        <p>''This is an opportunity to cross examine the visual essence of expression through the sonic release of the creative process,'' Mr. Purcell said, hoping to introduce the program in other artistic communities. ''Normally it is always the art world and the music world. Let's bring them together; it's time.''</p>
        <p>Improvisation, Mr. Mack agreed, was no different for artists than for musicians. One medium could only enhance the other. And he told his students to translate the music into form and color.</p>
        <p>''What is art all about but conceptual work,'' Mr. Mack said. ''There are many people who can replicate what they are looking at, which is not necessarily art. We are trying to open up creative doors for all of them.'' Mr. Mack is a former advertising and promotions professional. He claims to have invented the first plastic bag with handles and promoted the first Princess telephone when AT &amp; T was his client. Always challenged to spur his students on, at the end of June Mr. Mack will be taking a class to paint medieval villages in France, sculpture stone in a quarry and study cave paintings.</p>
        <p>Kristyn Bellino, 18, of Cold Spring Harbor spends most of her nine hours a week at the studio drawing figures. But the concert inspired her to create a painted thank-you note to a good friend instead. She stood at an easel, streaking red, black and purple oils across her canvas, not quite sure in the semi-darkness how her work would look in the light.</p>
        <p>''The music is helping me express myself more easily,'' Ms. Bellino said, describing her usual style as Picasso-like. ''The music gives you courage to do new stuff.''</p>
        <p>And sometimes, it helps revive old techniques. On a mural in front of the band, Brendon Semigran, 18, of Huntington was finger painting. Keeping time with the music, he made sweeping circles, using oranges, reds and yellows when the tempo slowed and dipping his fingers into the purple as the beat picked up. ''I get more inspired by the music,'' Mr. Semigran said, admitting he hadn't used his digits instead of a brush to paint since the first grade. ''I took a risk and I feel great about it.''</p>
        <p>But Jason Visentin, 18, of Manhasset planned to totally ignore the sound, sculpturing a Navy Seal diver out of clay, putting a skull on its belt and a dagger in his hand. ''I went into this with a predetermined idea of what I was going to do,'' Mr. Visentin said, continuing to mold his figure even when the band stopped playing.</p>
        <p>Despite his concentration, it was impossible to remain impervious.  ''The music helped it to flow freely,'' he admitted. ''Where there were gaps in my ideas, everything went smoothly. I was able to focus. The music inspired me on a subconscious level. It was really helpful.''</p>
        <p>Crooning Away</p>
        <p>Working in the lobby of the Garden City Hotel for the past 10 years, Lenny Dell has watched a lot of celebrities pass by. The actor Ben Stiller stayed at the hotel earlier this year. So did Lady Thatcher, Hillary Rodham Clinton and Howard Stern, the shock jock.</p>
        <p>Usually they don't notice Mr. Dell, otherwise known as Leonard Del Giudice of Commack. He's the 57-year-old in the tuxedo with the curly hair behind the grand piano in the Polo Lounge. The one crooning Neapolitan love songs and belting out Tony Bennett classics like ''I Left My Heart in San Francisco.'' Oh him. That guy.</p>
        <p>Such is the life of the piano player.  ''In cocktail lounges, you have to form a thick skin in the sense that you are performing,'' Mr. Dell said between sets recently. ''And naturally, when you are performing, you want everybody's undivided attention. Every performer wants that.''</p>
        <p>Couples huddled in conversation in the lounge, a crowd schmoozed at the bar, patrons conversed over dinner in the Polo Grill next door. The music was merely a pleasant backdrop.</p>
        <p>''But the fact is I am fully aware of where I am and the circumstances in which I am performing,'' Mr. Dell said. ''A cocktail lounge is a cocktail lounge. The people come to gather and talk to one another and perhaps even here in the hotel have business meetings.''</p>
        <p>Is anybody listening? Earlier this spring, Robert Goulet did. Jong Umali, a bellhop, told Mr. Dell that Mr. Goulet was in the hotel. Immediately, Mr. Dell launched into a rendition of Mr. Goulet's big hit ''The Impossible Dream.''</p>
        <p>From across the lobby, Mr. Goulet waved. Later that night, after performing at Westbury Music Fair, Mr. Goulet bounced up on the Polo Lounge stage. He sang ''If Ever I Would Leave You'' and ''On a Clear Day'' and several other songs. Mr. Dell, who accompanied him, felt like he had reached lounge-player heaven.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dell started his career at the top. In 1960, fresh out of high school, performing with the Demensions, a group that included two friends from his Bronx high school choral group plus his Uncle Phil filling in as tenor, Mr. Dell recorded a hit. His doo-wop arrangement of ''Over the Rainbow'' rode the charts and the radio waves for nine months, reaching No. 2 in the New York market. He appeared on Dick Clark's ''American Bandstand''  three times.</p>
        <p>In 1963, the Demensions had a top-40 hit with ''My Foolish Heart,'' their only album. When the group split up not long after, Mr. Dell started playing the cocktail lounge circuit.</p>
        <p>''Music has been my mainstay,'' he said. ''I am doing it now professionally for 40 years.'' Tuesdays through Saturdays at the hotel are his only gig. ''Cocktail lounges were a very good vehicle for me to earn a living. I just stayed with it. I was fairly successful. I had local notoriety.'' And the thrill of never knowing when a big name might drop in.</p>
        <p>The singer Tom Jones stopped by a few months ago. He just listened. Last summer Bobby Rydell came on stage and sang along. One snowy late December night in 1993, Billy Joel sat at a table and drummed his fingers to Mr. Dell's rendition of a Beatles' medley. A few nights later, on New Year's Eve, Mr. Joel came back to the lounge at 4 a.m. after completing his own gig at the Nassau Coliseum.</p>
        <p>''I have some nights where the audience gives me their undivided attention, where it's nothing but focus on me and applause,'' Mr. Dell said, counting a crowd of about 75 who regularly stop by. He gets requests. He gets tips. Patrons dance and sing along.</p>
        <p>But with ballgames frequently playing on the large-screen television in front of him, Mr. Dell sometimes seems all but invisible. He improvises on the keyboard as the game tension mounts. ''You are up there and people are in conversation and doing what they are doing,'' he said. ''But just when you think perhaps you are not being appreciated or listened to, people will let you know otherwise.''</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL E-mail address: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
