<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Demons That Have Driven 'N.Y.P.D. Blue'</title>
    <meta content="18WEIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208140"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION/RADIO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milch, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weinraub, Bernard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Nypd Blue (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EEDE123EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Demons That Have Driven 'N.Y.P.D. Blue'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD WEINRAUB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weinraub, Bernard</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bernard Weinraub interviews David Milch, 55, co-creator and writer of NYPD Blue, who describes his reasons for leaving series after seven years; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DAVID MILCH, the co-creator and architect of ''N.Y.P.D. Blue,'' is one of television's most successful writers. So it's not surprising to learn that he works out at a fancy sports club and has a summer estate on Martha's Vineyard, that he met his wife, Rita, at Yale and that he dotes on her and their three children. He would, in fact, appear to have it all.</p>
        <p>But appearances can be deceiving. The 55-year-old Emmy Award-winning writer, who is leaving ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' after seven years, has had his share of torments. On the one hand, Mr. Milch was a Yale University lecturer who was mentored by -- and who idolized -- Robert Penn Warren, the Pulitzer Prize-winning writer. On the other hand, he was a heroin addict, an alcoholic and a compulsive gambler who once destroyed a police car's roof lights with a shotgun blast, who spent time in a Mexican jail and who more than once came close to death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DAVID MILCH, the co-creator and architect of ''N.Y.P.D. Blue,'' is one of television's most successful writers. So it's not surprising to learn that he works out at a fancy sports club and has a summer estate on Martha's Vineyard, that he met his wife, Rita, at Yale and that he dotes on her and their three children. He would, in fact, appear to have it all.</p>
        <p>But appearances can be deceiving. The 55-year-old Emmy Award-winning writer, who is leaving ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' after seven years, has had his share of torments. On the one hand, Mr. Milch was a Yale University lecturer who was mentored by -- and who idolized -- Robert Penn Warren, the Pulitzer Prize-winning writer. On the other hand, he was a heroin addict, an alcoholic and a compulsive gambler who once destroyed a police car's roof lights with a shotgun blast, who spent time in a Mexican jail and who more than once came close to death.</p>
        <p>''It was a very violent life and stupid and criminal,'' said Mr. Milch, his voice drifting off. ''I lived a shadow life. Somehow I was able to find more constructive accommodations for all these impulses. There was my work. There aren't too many people that I write about that I can't imagine being.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Milch's decision to leave ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' -- to create television series and movies for Paramount in a multi-million dollar deal -- was in part inspired by exhaustion. Working nonstop on the scripts of the police show, often writing scenes just hours before the actors were to perform them, he realized he had had enough. ''I will not work that way again,'' Mr. Milch said.</p>
        <p>''I've watched David over the last three years become increasingly burnt out,'' said Steven Bochco, who brought Mr. Milch to Hollywood from Yale in the early 1980's and created ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' with him. ''I don't mean in terms of talent or enthusiasm. But the level of intensity and single-mindedness that he brings to his work takes its toll.''</p>
        <p>The departure of Mr. Milch will, most certainly, alter the award-winning police drama, whose central figure, Det. Andy Sipowicz, played by Dennis Franz, is a complicated, tormented, angry ex-alcoholic. Mr. Milch said that the character is based not on his own personality but that of his father, Elmer, who died in 1979.</p>
        <p>''My father's mother's name was Sapowitch,'' said Mr. Milch. ''He was a surgeon, a professor of medicine at the State University at Buffalo and chief of staff at a hospital. He was also challenged the way Sipowicz is challenged, in terms of his habits, his addictions, his temperament.'' Mr. Milch said that in addition to suffering from serious emotional problems, his father, who often treated criminals in his medical practice, was also a habitual gambler.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milch, seated in the 20th Century Fox commissary at lunchtime, was eating his usual lunch of steamed vegetables and fish. He worries about his health: he has lost about 50 pounds over the past few years, and his gym workouts are less about vanity than about survival -- shortly after the premiere of ''N.Y.P.D. Blue,'' Mr. Milch underwent seven angioplasty procedures.</p>
        <p>The heart problems that caused the death of the show's Bobby Simone, played by Jimmy Smits, mirrored Mr. Milch's own health battles. The disease that threatened the young son of Sipowicz echoed a scare that Mr. Milch and his wife faced when their son became ill.</p>
        <p>If his real life has a way of insinuating itself into his work, it's also true that he seems to incorporate the stuff of drama into his life. Only the previous night, Mr. Milch said, he had begun weeping at the sight of a man who reminded him of someone he had known: a drug dealer and male prostitute who went from New York to New Haven three times a week to sell Mr. Milch drugs while he was teaching at Yale. Between trains, the drug dealer would read the homosexual Greek poets in the Yale library.</p>
        <p>H E died before either of us turned our lives around,'' said Mr. Milch. ''And as I experienced this man last night, my friend was alive again and sober and he didn't have to suffer every day. And that was because I was able to experience him.</p>
        <p>''I feel that way about Sipowicz too,'' Mr. Milch continued. ''My dad doesn't have to suffer the way he suffered because I'm able to experience that character in all of his complexities and scope and humanity.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Milch grew up in Buffalo, N.Y., and attended Yale and the graduate school of the University of Iowa before going on to Yale Law School to escape the draft (at the same time as President Clinton).</p>
        <p>His career at Yale was bizarre. His attempts at writing novels came to the attention of Robert Penn Warren and R. W. B. Lewis, the literary critic and historian. But Mr. Milch's talents were matched by his demons: it was in New Haven that he shot out the police car's roof lights; addicted to gambling as well as to drugs, he lost thousands of dollars. But Mr. Milch also taught, under the guidance of Warren, who secured him jobs.</p>
        <p>For years, he used one addiction to manage the others: ''Heroin saved my life,'' he said, ''in the sense that it normalized my existence. Up to that point, as an alcoholic and doing the other stuff, I would have been dead.''</p>
        <p>In 1982, Mr. Milch was offered a script assignment by Jeffrey Lewis, a former roommate at Yale, who was a writer-producer on ''Hill Street Blues.'' The writing so impressed Mr. Bochco -- the series's co-creator -- that he offered Mr. Milch a staff job. ''His writing was a rare and huge gift,'' Mr. Bochco said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milch managed to write without ever giving up all his addictions. ''I got clean for two years but I was never sober,'' he said. ''There is nothing worse than a dry addict. You have all the behavior and nothing to medicate it.''</p>
        <p>After ''Hill Street Blues'' and before ''N.Y.P.D. Blue,'' Mr. Milch worked on shows that were less than successful. In 1987, he helped create an NBC spinoff of ''Hill Street Blues'' called ''Beverly Hills Buntz'' (with Dennis Franz). But the show ran only five months because critics and viewers were confused about whether it was a comedy or a drama. Another series, ABC's ''Capital News,'' about a newspaper like The Washington Post, ran only four weeks.</p>
        <p>The heart problems he had following the start of ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' triggered a crisis, Mr. Milch said. He went back to using drugs and experienced what he termed ''a real suicidal sense of futility.'' He said, ''I became so isolated emotionally -- and I have a beautiful family and I love my wife and our children. And I was just gone. I wasn't. . . .'' His voice trailed off. ''I accepted my helplessness and asked for God's help.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Milch's resolve about overcoming his addictions -- which included writing and overseeing virtually every episode of ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' -- contributed to his decision to leave the show.</p>
        <p>His new series, to be made at Paramount for CBS, will also have a law-enforcement theme. Mr. Milch said he was, essentially, fascinated with the police as dramatic figures. ''Cops have guns,'' he said. ''And drama requires jeopardy and resolution. And one comes by those things most naturally in a cop show.''</p>
        <p>What's ahead for ''N.Y.P.D. Blue,'' without the dominant creative force behind it? ''David's leaving will have a significant impact,'' Mr. Bochco said. ''There's only one David. The show needs to make that transition and adjustment. It will not be the same. Hopefully, it will be just as good. Hopefully, it will allow other voices to emerge in the process.''</p>
        <p>The show itself remains strong. It is ABC's second-highest-rated drama, after ''The Practice,'' and its audience base seems loyal. This season, in fact, the audience has grown: the show averaged 15.6 million viewers, a 7 percent increase over last season.</p>
        <p>''In 'N.Y.P.D. Blue,' '' Mr. Milch said, ''none of those characters are tired of life. Their lives are an adventure, a source of joy and grief. The characters are very unfinished. They are works in progress. And their lives are largely mysteries to them, like so many of our lives.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bochco said that Mr. Milch's gifts as a writer were based at least in part on the mystery of his own life. ''His writing is informed by a huge intellect and a huge degree of life experience unrivaled by most normal human beings,'' he said. ''He's got remarkable voices in there rattling.''</p>
        <p>TELEVISION/RADIO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
