<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Egan Faces Test in Role of Shepherd and C.E.O.</title>
    <meta content="18EGAN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208512"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Edward Michael (Bishop)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodstein, Laurie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E7DC1431F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1321" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Egan Faces Test in Role of Shepherd and C.E.O.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE GOODSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodstein, Laurie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bishop Edward Michael Egan, set to be installed as New York archbishop, has record as consummate executive and shown himself attentive to public relations; question being raised by many familiar with his past performance is whether he will also prove to be spiritual shepherd; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a ceremony at St. Patrick's Cathedral today, Bishop Edward Michael Egan of Bridgeport, Conn., will present a parchment letter in Latin from Pope John Paul II that formally appoints Bishop Egan the ninth archbishop of New York.</p>
        <p>It is still, to many church observers, a surprise choice. Bishop Egan's name was not among the three candidates recommended to the pope to succeed Cardinal John J. O'Connor, and he has not been particularly prominent among the nation's Catholic bishops.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a ceremony at St. Patrick's Cathedral today, Bishop Edward Michael Egan of Bridgeport, Conn., will present a parchment letter in Latin from Pope John Paul II that formally appoints Bishop Egan the ninth archbishop of New York.</p>
        <p>It is still, to many church observers, a surprise choice. Bishop Egan's name was not among the three candidates recommended to the pope to succeed Cardinal John J. O'Connor, and he has not been particularly prominent among the nation's Catholic bishops.</p>
        <p>And yet, a look at his record and his reputation suggests that perhaps it is no surprise at all. New York is an archdiocese badly in need of a corporate caretaker, and Bishop Egan is a consummate corporate executive.</p>
        <p>He has mixed with the wealthy and the prominent at fund-raisers and dinner parties, bringing in millions to support Catholic charities and schools. He has been an attentive boss to his employees, the clergy, from their training as seminarians to their care in their retirement. He has been decisive at downsizing and consolidating schools and parishes.</p>
        <p>And in the five weeks since he was named as Cardinal O'Connor's successor, he has proved attentive to public relations in New York. His picture has already been posted on the archdiocese's World Wide Web site. He bantered with reporters in two news conferences. And when he is asked about accusations of pedophilia by clergy members in Bridgeport, he already knows to respond with a terse ''No comment,'' to avoid supplying any usable television sound bites.</p>
        <p>But no leader is good at everything, and the question raised by many familiar with Bishop Egan's past performance is whether he will also prove to be a spiritual shepherd to New York's Catholic laity, the common Christian faithful who make up the church's soul and 98 percent of its membership.</p>
        <p>''Cardinal O'Connor was a great pastor, and Ed Egan is a great official,'' said Eugene Kennedy, a writer and former Maryknoll priest who knows Bishop Egan. ''Ed Egan has always viewed the church from behind a desk, while O'Connor saw men die and held them in his arms in Vietnam. The great genius of the church is to be pastoral -- not to be an efficient organization, or even a dominant organization.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy, a retired professor of psychology at Loyola University in Chicago, said Bishop Egan was a model of what the Vatican now prefers in its bishops.</p>
        <p>''There is a certain class of cleric to whom you apply the word 'churchman,' and that is what Ed Egan is, to his fingertips,'' Mr. Kennedy said. ''These men live and die for the institutional church. They are therefore strong pillars. Even if the rest of the institution may be eroding in high winds or from internal problems, such as priestly pedophilia, these pillars will stand.''</p>
        <p>In 1993, the Bridgeport diocese was sued by 31 plaintiffs claiming abuse by 8 priests over more than 30 years. Under Bishop Egan, the diocese's lawyers have aggressively fought the complaints, and he has been criticized for refusing to discuss the accusations and for making no overtures to the plaintiffs.</p>
        <p>Having now mounted one of the highest peaks in church leadership, Bishop Egan will have an opportunity to make his mark on an archdiocese that is badly in need of just the kind of administrative experience that he brings.</p>
        <p>The New York archdiocese, which spends more than $527 million annually, encompasses 413 parishes, 238 elementary schools, 55 high schools, 17 hospitals, 13 day care centers and 11 mental health residences. Many parishes can no longer support their neighboring schools. Church finances are not public record, but some hospitals are believed to face millions of dollars in debt.</p>
        <p>''You have to be able to manage a complex entity, and he is very capable of that,'' said Bill Baker, the president of WNET, who belongs to a parish in Riverside, Conn., and knows Bishop Egan. ''There are a lot of hard decisions that have to be made, and unlike the popular press's portrayal of the Catholic Church, it is actually a very poor entity. It's got a lot of real estate, but the homes and the orphanages aren't for sale. The cathedral is not for sale.''</p>
        <p>If Bishop Egan decides to consolidate or close parishes, schools or hospitals, his abilities as a pastor and diplomat will be tested. When he merged two congregations in Stamford, Conn., the Hispanic parishioners at one said that he ignored their opposition to joining with the Slovak congregation, and that he came across as an autocrat.</p>
        <p>Bishop Egan, known as a man who does his homework, said he would spend the summer traveling around the New York archdiocese.</p>
        <p>''I think the key project for me now will be to learn about the archdiocese,'' Bishop Egan said at a farewell news conference in Connecticut last week. ''I don't know what the situation is in the schools, about Catholic Charities, or with the priests and the religious. The truth of the matter is that all I can do is spend this summer listening.''</p>
        <p>He is also unlikely to celebrate Mass each week at St. Patrick's Cathedral, and instead plans to spend Sundays visiting a variety of parishes, his spokesmen said.</p>
        <p>To the people he will serve, the new archbishop is largely unknown. In conversations at parishes on Friday, some did not recognize his name, and others said they did not know anything about him.</p>
        <p>''I don't know in depth about him, but I hope he does good because we need it,'' said Rhudy Correra, who is 15 and works at the Church of the Incarnation in Washington Heights. ''I hope he reaches out to the people that are less fortunate.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Correra's friend, Franklin Rodriguez, made an observation that illustrates just the sort of chasm facing Bishop Egan in an archdiocese so divided by race and class.</p>
        <p>''He's not really well known in the minority community,'' said Mr. Rodriguez, who is 16, ''because the church only explained him to the upper-class areas.''</p>
        <p>In Connecticut, Bishop Egan courted the higher social castes, playing the piano at benefit dinners and talking art history at parties. He persuaded the executives and chairmen of such companies as General Electric, Xerox, PepsiCo, Merrill Lynch, Citi-Group and IBM to serve on the board of a charity he founded, the Inner City Foundation for Charity and Education, said Richard T. Stone, the foundation's director. The group raises money for Catholic and nonsectarian schools and charities.</p>
        <p>''The bishop is an eloquent speaker,'' Mr. Stone said, ''and he has an excellent way of presenting a case and engaging individuals and corporations to support his endeavors.''</p>
        <p>As Cardinal O'Connor came to understand, the archbishop of New York has a large constituency outside the church to charm.</p>
        <p>He is constantly being challenged to ideological duels by a variety of religious and secular groups.. The archbishop's reputation will be partly defined by how he responds to these challenges.</p>
        <p>''With the political situation in New York, the Hispanics, the blacks, the Jews, in many ways it is the fish bowl of the world, and if you sneeze, everyone knows,'' said Rabbi Jack Bemporad, director of the Center for Interreligious Understanding, in Englewood, N.J., who used to run a similar center at Sacred Heart University in Fairfield, Conn., where Bishop Egan is chairman.</p>
        <p>''The archdiocese has a kind of exposure that I don't think Bishop Egan is used to,'' Rabbi Bemporad said. ''I think that Bishop Egan can learn in the trenches, but I think he's got a way to go. This is a very complicated position here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
