<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Home Again</title>
    <meta content="18MORGANT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000709T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208058"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morgan, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bahr, Howard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Year of Jubilo, The: A Novel of the Civil War (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0D7133FF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Home Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert Morgan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morgan, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert Morgan reviews book The Year of Jubilo: A Novel of the Civil War by Howard Bahr; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Year of Jubilo</p>
        <p>A Novel of the Civil War.</p>
        <p>By Howard Bahr.</p>
        <p>376 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Henry Holt &amp; Company. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Year of Jubilo</p>
        <p>A Novel of the Civil War.</p>
        <p>By Howard Bahr.</p>
        <p>376 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Henry Holt &amp; Company. $25.</p>
        <p>It would be hard to exaggerate the importance of fiction to our understanding of history. Much of what many of us know about the past comes from reading novels and watching films based on novels. Our Napoleon will always be tinged by Tolstoy's sarcasm, and our Civil War will always be touched by the pen of Margaret Mitchell and the extravagance of David O. Selznick.</p>
        <p>No single event or period in American history has been so often written about or filmed as the Civil War. From ''Birth of a Nation'' and ''Gone With the Wind'' to ''Glory'' and Ken Burns's ''Civil War,'' we have been transfixed by the narrative of that national cataclysm. The story continues to unfold in the controversy over the flying of the Confederate flag.</p>
        <p>I admire the complexity of Howard Bahr's second novel, ''The Year of Jubilo,'' a tale of the immediate aftermath of the Civil War in the small ruined town of Cumberland, Miss. Bahr offers no easy moral. His former soldiers -- Gawain Harper, a onetime schoolteacher, and Harry Stribling, a onetime lawyer -- are gaunt, confused and homesick as they stumble homeward; they know their wartime adventures were the most intense and significant experiences they have had. They are as addicted to the war as Gawain's Aunt Vassar is addicted to laudanum.</p>
        <p>There is a scary, sickening emptiness to peace, which the men must pass through as a stage of withdrawal. Those at home cannot understand their ambivalence. They feel like strangers in their own lives: ''The war had brought him to this sorry pass, yet Gawain Harper, kneeling by the smoky fire, found himself longing for the war again, for the things he had found there that he knew could be found nowhere else, not ever again. . . . He understood once more the singularity of what he'd been given, and that he wouldn't trade it in for any memory of peace.''</p>
        <p>Much of the tension in the first third of the book comes from Gawain's reluctance to return home, even though he is drawn back to his family and a young widow named Morgan Rhea. ''There was too much mystery to peace. . . . War was a good deal simpler.''</p>
        <p>Yet as Gawain trudges home, he notices a new scent in the air and recognizes that it is ''what freedom smells like.'' It is the year of Jubilo, of jubilation. The ruined world is coming alive with spring. There is a wonderful sense of smell and sound as well as sight in this novel. Hemingway said a writer should always tell what the weather was like. Howard Bahr -- whose first novel, ''The Black Flower'' (1998), also set during the Civil War, is a prelude to this story -- is a true poet of weather, of night and of time. Descriptions of weather in this story function as a kind of choral commentary, setting the tone for sections and scenes. Through the continuing drama of the weather Bahr creates a sense of the timeless beyond the devastation: ''There is a moment when the day's axis turns, when time begins to slide away toward night again. The exact moment is imperceptible. . . . Shadows, the first sure tendrils of night, reach into fence corners and woods and up the eastern face of houses, and with the shadows come the birds again, hurrying against the night, and timid feeders move quivering over the grass, who know the hawks have folded themselves away, and the owl not yet awakened.''</p>
        <p>Not since James Agee has someone made the Southern night so alive, so intimate, so orchestral.</p>
        <p>''The Year of Jubilo'' is a huge novel, with many characters and many intertwined narrative threads. On his way home Harper meets up with Stribling, who describes himself as a ''philosopher.'' They quickly form a bond of friendship and dry humor. The Cumberland they return to is under uneasy occupation by a Union battalion commanded by Lt. Col. Michael Burduck, a troubled man subject to trances in which he relives the trauma of battle. Meanwhile a cunning and murderous former Confederate officer named King Solomon Gault is organizing a secret militia and planning a rebellion that he imagines will sweep over the South, drive the occupiers out and bring him to power. He and his assistant, Wall Stutts, are killers who dream of reigniting the slaughter. Gault is a genius of hate and intrigue, ironic contempt and vanity. He represents the worst of the Lost Cause, while Gawain and Harry represent the best of the region.</p>
        <p>But the finest portraits in the novel are those of the secondary characters. These include Molochi Fish, a former slave hunter who was ''boiled alive'' by his mother in a hog scalding pot but survived, his skin hanging in shreds, his mind haunted by demonic birds; and Old Hundred-and-Eleven, an albino prophet and grave digger named for the three streaks of tobacco juice that run from the corners of his mouth and the middle of his lower lip. Bahr has a gift for creating mentally damaged and physically repellent characters who come alive in disturbing and finally endearing ways. The surprise is how deeply we come to understand Molochi. He appears to be one of the true villains of the story, but after the gang rape of his common-law wife he acquires a moral complexity he had not shown before. We come to feel a genuine sympathy for him.</p>
        <p>Another particularly colorful character is a former Confederate spy and actor named L. W. Thomas, who has built a tavern in Cumberland called the Citadel of Djibouti, where Union soldiers and the town ruffians congregate to ease their homesickness and boredom. Thomas is perhaps the most complex and carefully drawn character here. He has been literally and figuratively a double agent in this rapidly evolving world. He is the character no one could have predicted, a former Shakespearean actor alert to life's larger ironies. He is the most modern of the book's characters.</p>
        <p>Yet Old Hundred-and-Eleven may be the greatest pleasure in ''The Year of Jubilo.'' He is a wise grave digger-clown, with a pedigree that goes back at least to ''Hamlet'' and ''King Lear.'' All around him there is turmoil, yet this prophet, who lives in jail by choice and carries his tattered Bible everywhere, provides a certain amount of sanity and saving humor. By the end of the novel I felt that the events centered on him and Molochi as much they did around the reunited lovers. The scene where Gawain returns to Morgan, and they meet in the moonlight, is both eerie and romantic. But it is Old Hundred-and Eleven who makes the book most alive and spiritually rewarding.</p>
        <p>With the large number of characters and interwoven stories, the novel has to cut back and forth often. This cutting often provides a rich sense of simultaneity and gathering crisis, but sometimes the scenes are so short they are just glittering fragments. We try to follow one unfolding scene only to flip after a few paragraphs to another narrative line. In places the narrative reads more like collage than drama.</p>
        <p>Along with the sweeping, cinematic story of rebellion, loyalty, revenge and reawakened romance, Bahr's evocation of place and time is the most enduring achievement of the novel. The affection for the greening countryside and town of Cumberland, the loving detail of forest and river, soil and graveyard, are the true moral and true poetry of this war story, showing that the life of a place transcends any one ruin or atrocity. The book ends not on a note of triumph but with a poignant sense of the vitality of the ordinary -- the humble and merely decent acts that make up the best of our lives and our selves.</p>
        <p>Robert Morgan's most recent books are ''Gap Creek,'' a novel, and ''The Balm of Gilead Tree,'' a collection of stories.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 9, 2000, Sunday  A review of ''The Year of Jubilo,'' a novel by Howard Bahr, in the Book Review on June 18 misstated the publishing history of Mr. Bahr's previous novel, ''The Black Flower.'' It was published in hard covers by the Nautical and Aviation Publishing Company in 1997 and in paperback by Henry Holt in 1998.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 9, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A review of ''The Year of Jubilo,'' a novel by Howard Bahr, in the Book Review on June 18 misstated the publishing history of Mr. Bahr's previous novel, ''The Black Flower.'' It was published in hard covers by the Nautical and Aviation Publishing Company in 1997 and in paperback by Henry Holt in 1998.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robert Morgan's most recent books are ''Gap Creek,'' a novel, and ''The Balm of Gilead Tree,'' a collection of stories.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
