<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Williams's Huge Day Can't Stem A Meltdown</title>
    <meta content="Y18YAN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago White Sox</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E2DC1431F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1053" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Williams's Huge Day Can't Stem A Meltdown</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chicago White Sox defeat New York Yankees, 10-9; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jake Westbrook walked from the bullpen into the steamy fishbowl of Yankee Stadium for his first major league start. He was already mopping his drenched forehead with a towel and choking back his nerves.</p>
        <p>The Yankees brought the 22-year-old rookie up from Class AAA Columbus as a short-term replacement for the injured Roger Clemens. They also hoped he would be the temporary tourniquet for a frustrated club that had lost two straight to the Chicago White Sox, the best team in the American League.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jake Westbrook walked from the bullpen into the steamy fishbowl of Yankee Stadium for his first major league start. He was already mopping his drenched forehead with a towel and choking back his nerves.</p>
        <p>The Yankees brought the 22-year-old rookie up from Class AAA Columbus as a short-term replacement for the injured Roger Clemens. They also hoped he would be the temporary tourniquet for a frustrated club that had lost two straight to the Chicago White Sox, the best team in the American League.</p>
        <p>But Westbrook could not be the savior yesterday, not when emotion gripped him in his first trip to Yankee Stadium, in front of 54,053 fans. He unraveled in the first two innings, spotting the White Sox a six-run lead that carried them to a 10-9 victory.</p>
        <p>The Yankees were already trailing by 9-3 in the fourth when the struggling second baseman Chuck Knoblauch compounded the team's anguish by committing yet another throwing error on a ground ball. It was his first chance to field a grounder since his three-error night on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The Yankees needed someone to stop the horrific cycle, and Bernie Williams was there. He went 4 for 4 and had a season-high seven runs batted in, bringing the Yankees within one run in the eighth. But while the rain-delayed five-hour marathon held the promise of absolution, the game resulted in the Yankees' third straight loss.</p>
        <p>''We just feel we can never stop the bleeding, and that was the bad part,'' Yankees Manager Joe Torre said.</p>
        <p>Williams, who had been 5 for 20 in the homestand entering yesterday's game, could not rectify things with the good part. ''To have a great day and not win the game, it doesn't mean that much,'' Williams said.</p>
        <p>He hit a double for two runs in the third, a double that scored three runs in the sixth, and then, with the Yankees trailing, 10-7, in the eighth, with two outs and designated hitter Paul O'Neill on first base, he blasted a two-run home run to right field, bringing the Yankees within a run.</p>
        <p>''We keep fighting,'' Williams said. ''We just keep coming up a little short.''</p>
        <p>All game, he was the one who mitigated the disaster that began with Westbrook but rippled throughout the team. Westbrook got out of a jam in the first inning, allowing a run on two hits and a walk, but had already thrown 20 pitches.</p>
        <p>The next inning finished him off. He gave up a leadoff double to Carlos Lee, Greg Norton hit a sacrifice fly to center field and Brook Fordyce followed with a shot that right fielder Shane Spencer trapped. Ray Durham hit a shot back up the middle, Frank Thomas singled, and then Magglio Ordonez belted a fastball to left-center, a three-run shot.</p>
        <p>After Westbrook walked Paul Konerko, Torre took the ball from him, telling him, ''Get 'em next time.''</p>
        <p>He had wanted Westbrook to get the team only to the middle of the game. Instead, Torre had to use four more pitchers.</p>
        <p>''I had a little too much emotion and adrenaline, and I just needed to calm down,'' he said. ''I have to put this behind me.''</p>
        <p>That was exactly what Knoblauch had been trying to do, without success, early in the game. On the first ground ball hit to him in two games, he showed that the demons were still lurking. He collected the grounder hit by Norton, cocked his arm and, instead of throwing routinely to Tino Martinez, sent the ball fluttering far wide and high into the seats.</p>
        <p>The error did not lead to a run. For Knoblauch, who did not speak to reporters after the game, it was hard to tell the cost. ''He has the courage to go in there day in and day out,'' Torre said. ''Eventually he is going to overcome it.''</p>
        <p>Knoblauch instead compensated on the field yesterday, coming back after the 57-minute rain delay looking more relaxed. Jason Grimsley had given up three more runs in relief of Westbrook, and Todd Erdos relieved him in the fifth. He came back to the mound after the delay and recorded two quick strikeouts.</p>
        <p>He gave up what would be the winning run, in the sixth inning, however, when Lee hit a double to right that scored Chris Singleton. New York was not finished, however.</p>
        <p>''It's the Yankees,'' Westbrook said, forgetting for a moment he was one of them, for now. ''They're always in the game; you can't count them out.''</p>
        <p>With two outs in the sixth inning, Knoblauch drew a walk and Derek Jeter -- who had committed a baffling error of his own in the second, bobbling an easy line drive -- followed with a single. O'Neill walked to load the bases and finish the starter Cal Eldred (8-2). Against Kelly Wunsch, a side-arming left-hander, Williams promptly doubled to the center-field wall, scoring two runs.</p>
        <p>And then Chicago's second baseman, Durham, committed a throwing error, his relay to the catcher Fordyce wide, allowing O'Neill to score. Martinez cracked a single to short center field off Wunsch to bring the Yankees within 10-7.</p>
        <p>In the top of the seventh, Knoblauch earned some redemption, this time completing a routine throw on a ground ball with ease. The Yankees and Williams then came up swinging in the eighth, nearly capping the comeback. After Williams blasted a home run to right on a 2-2 count, Martinez ended the inning when he flied out to left field.</p>
        <p>''Obviously we'd like to be playing better,'' Jeter said. ''It seems that whenever we get good pitching, we don't swing the bats well, and when we swing the bats, we don't get good pitching. Hopefully we can turn the corner.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
