<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Vote Nears In Zimbabwe, Mugabe Finds Less Support</title>
    <meta content="18ZIMB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208486"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zimbabwe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Harare (Zimbabwe)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swarns, Rachel L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mugabe, Robert (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE0D61731F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Vote Nears In Zimbabwe, Mugabe Finds Less Support</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL L. SWARNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swarns, Rachel L</byline>
      <dateline>HARARE, Zimbabwe, June 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Robert Mugabe of Zimbabwe blames opposition for campaign violence and urges thousands of flag-waving, cheering supporters to keep peace as they rally behind ruling party; Mugabe acknowledges that fiercely contested parliamentary elections scheduled for next week will not be easy, particularly in capital, Harare, where residents are weary of promises of better future amid shortages, inflation and official corruption (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just seven days before fiercely contested parliamentary elections, President Robert Mugabe today blamed the opposition for campaign violence and urged thousands of flag-waving, cheering supporters to keep the peace as they rally behind the ruling party.</p>
        <p>While rallying the faithful, Mr. Mugabe acknowledged that the election would not be easy, particularly here in the capital, where residents have grown weary of promises of a better future amid chronic fuel shortages, skyrocketing inflation and official corruption. ''We must accept that we have a real battle here,'' the veteran 76-year-old leader said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just seven days before fiercely contested parliamentary elections, President Robert Mugabe today blamed the opposition for campaign violence and urged thousands of flag-waving, cheering supporters to keep the peace as they rally behind the ruling party.</p>
        <p>While rallying the faithful, Mr. Mugabe acknowledged that the election would not be easy, particularly here in the capital, where residents have grown weary of promises of a better future amid chronic fuel shortages, skyrocketing inflation and official corruption. ''We must accept that we have a real battle here,'' the veteran 76-year-old leader said.</p>
        <p>On Friday, a survey of 6,000 voters conducted by the Public Opinion Institute here suggested that the opposition would win 70 of the 120 parliamentary seats up for grabs. Officials from the ruling party, which currently controls all but three seats in Parliament, quickly dismissed the survey as biased.</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Mugabe stood behind the microphone in his charcoal suit overlooking the crowd in the sports field here, it was clear that his support had waned. Twenty years ago, when he stood in this very place after a triumphant return from exile, an estimated 100,000 people filled the field to hear his message.</p>
        <p>Today, despite the availability of free transport and the heavy publicity surrounding the rally, which is expected to be the president's last major address in the capital before the vote, the field stood nearly half empty. And rally organizers found themselves repeatedly using the public address system to urge local bus drivers to round up more spectators.</p>
        <p>The provincial party chairman, Tony Gara, apologized for the low turnout, saying: ''Your excellency, we have a low crowd here because a lot of our people are at work today.'' Unemployment is over 50 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mugabe accused opposition party members of provoking the violence that has claimed at least 26 lives and left more than 150 people injured, mostly black supporters of the new Movement for Democratic Change. ''We don't want to break the law,'' he said. ''We want the people to go and vote in peace.''</p>
        <p>He reminded supporters that his party had led the country to political independence and he promised that it would continue to fight for the people by redistributing white farms to blacks and reinstituting price controls on basic foodstuffs.</p>
        <p>The elections next weekend represent the toughest challenge that the ruling party has ever faced. In February, the party suffered its first major defeat since independence 20 years ago when voters rejected a draft constitution that would have expanded the president's powers and enabled him to seize land from white farmers without compensation.</p>
        <p>For the first time, opposition candidates are contesting all of the 120 parliamentary seats.</p>
        <p>The battle for the vote is particularly fierce in rural communities, home to roughly 60 percent of the nation's 5.1 million registered voters and traditionally a stronghold for the ruling Zimbabwe African National Union-Patriotic Front.</p>
        <p>Amnesty International, the human rights group, and other foreign observers have accused the government of either instigating or condoning the political violence in the countryside in an effort to hold power, dismissing the claims of the ruling party that the opposition is to blame.</p>
        <p>The opposition is led by Morgan Tsvangirai, a union activist, who has sharply criticized the government's support of blacks who have invaded hundreds of white-owned farms since February. Mr. Mugabe has repeatedly defended the squatters and disregarded court orders to evict them.</p>
        <p>But in recent days, the ruling party has seemingly responded to the barrage of criticism. Government officials have repeatedly denounced violence. The state-controlled media has offered air time to the opposition, which is routinely derided on television and radio as a puppet of whites. And officials have also vowed to accept the result of the vote, whatever the outcome.</p>
        <p>''In the very unlikely event that ZANU-PF is defeated, we will accept the result in the same way as we accepted the result over the draft constitution,'' John Nkomo, the campaign manager for the ruling party, said in a radio interview today.</p>
        <p>The stadium crowd seemed sure of victory. As former guerrilla fighters sang liberation songs, the supporters clapped and ululated when one speaker after another called on the ruling party to march forward.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mugabe told the crowd that he understood the hardships that it was experiencing. But he suggested that the opposition movement, supported by blacks and whites, would only make the situation worse.</p>
        <p>William Tsakatsa, a 26-year-old carpenter, agreed. ''We don't want the white man to be a leader in this country,'' he said. ''The M.D.C. has white people in it, and the people of Zimbabwe don't want them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
