<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Still Ahead, Lakers Look Forward to Blase Home Crowd</title>
    <meta content="Y18PAC$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208506"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="N.B.A. FINALS: LAKERS VS. PACERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DD1431F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Still Ahead, Lakers Look Forward to Blase Home Crowd</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, June 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Basketball Association Finals return to home court of Los Angeles Lakers after three games at Indiana Pacers Conseco Fieldhouse; Lakers are glad to be returning to Staples Center despite often blase attitude of privileged fan base; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the past week, the Indiana Pacers have fed off playing at the Conseco Fieldhouse, the National Basketball Association's version of Mayberry. Considered the best home-court advantage in the league, the Pacers' new old-style digs helped them produce three outstanding efforts, even though one ended in a loss.</p>
        <p>But the championship series will return to the new millennium Monday night when Game 6 is played at the Staples Center in Los Angeles. And while the Lakers' cavernous corporate palace may not have the charm or decibel level of Conseco, its powers of rejuvenation have been just as beneficial for the home team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the past week, the Indiana Pacers have fed off playing at the Conseco Fieldhouse, the National Basketball Association's version of Mayberry. Considered the best home-court advantage in the league, the Pacers' new old-style digs helped them produce three outstanding efforts, even though one ended in a loss.</p>
        <p>But the championship series will return to the new millennium Monday night when Game 6 is played at the Staples Center in Los Angeles. And while the Lakers' cavernous corporate palace may not have the charm or decibel level of Conseco, its powers of rejuvenation have been just as beneficial for the home team.</p>
        <p>The Lakers led the league with a 36-5 home record during the regular season, and their 10-2 mark in the playoffs is one game better than Indiana's (9-3). That is a major reason there is no panic in the Lakers, even after they were stuffed offensively and pulverized defensively in Friday's embarrassing 120-87 loss in Game 5. Ahead by three games to two and needing to win just one of two home games, the Lakers are certain they will still be crowned champions.</p>
        <p>''We'll just put it behind us and go home,'' Kobe Bryant said after a subpar 8-point performance in Game 5. ''That's what we played all season for, to have home-court advantage. We came here, did what we had to do, we got one. Now we're going back to Staples.''</p>
        <p>The Staples Center, despite the often blase attitude of its privileged fan base and three stories of midlevel loges that kill the possibility of having an insanely boisterous crowd, has been a place of refuge for the Lakers this postseason. They have taken a few beatings on the road, winning only 4 of 10 games on opponents' floors, but have usually been able to return to form at Staples.</p>
        <p>In the first round, they bounced back from a 13-point loss at Sacramento to win the deciding game by 27 points at home. In the second, they came off a 19-point loss at Phoenix to eliminate the Suns with a 22-point victory two days later in Los Angeles. Portland broke the Lakers' aura of invincibility at home, winning two of the four games at Staples, but the Lakers fought back from a 13-point fourth-quarter deficit in Game 7 to prevail.</p>
        <p>While the crowd noise at Staples may not reach the ear-splitting levels of arenas such as Conseco, the Rose Garden in Portland, ARCO Arena in Sacramento and Madison Square Garden -- all arenas where the fans are seated closer to the court -- the Lakers say they thrive on whatever degree of clamor their fans manage to produce.</p>
        <p>''Our place is going to be rockin','' Shaquille O'Neal said. ''Our place is going to be loud. Our place is going to be hostile. We'll be ready.''</p>
        <p>The worst parts of the Lakers' game on Friday were their defense and their rebounding. The offense was bad as well, but take away Bryant's unsightly 4-for-20 shooting and the Lakers shot 45.7 percent. They also committed only 12 turnovers.</p>
        <p>The Lakers were outrebounded by 12, and their small-forward combination of Glen Rice and Rick Fox grabbed a total of zero rebounds in 45 minutes. Defensively, the Lakers were all but absent. Rice and even Bryant could not slow down Jalen Rose (32 points) and Reggie Miller (25), each of whom made four 3-pointers and scored on driving treks to the basket.</p>
        <p>The Lakers had the best defense in the league in the regular season, holding opponents to 41.6 percent shooting and allowing teams to shoot 50 percent or better just four times. But Indiana shot a blazing 57.4 percent on Friday in scoring at least 118 points for the second straight game.</p>
        <p>While the Lakers' defense has not been as stiff during the postseason -- perhaps a natural byproduct of playing better teams -- they had held opponents to just 42.9 percent shooting heading into Game 5.</p>
        <p>Like the other facets of their game, their defense improves at Staples. In Games 1 and 2, they held Indiana to 39.6 percent shooting despite losing Bryant for all but 9 minutes of the second game. In the next three games at Conseco, the Pacers shot 50.8 percent.</p>
        <p>Despite the statistics, and the odds that Indiana will not win the next two games, A. C. Green, a member of Lakers championship teams in 1987 and 1988, offered a voice of reason and caution. He advised his teammates against resting on the fact that they are now back at home.</p>
        <p>''It's important for people like myself who have been there to tell the guys that we can't extend this thing any farther,'' Green said. ''We can't give them any more life. It's not about just winning one of the next two games because we're at home.''</p>
        <p>N.B.A. FINALS: LAKERS VS. PACERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
