<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pacers Are Alive and Putting On Their Spin</title>
    <meta content="Y18LAK$15" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Reggie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EEDD1431F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1119" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pacers Are Alive and Putting On Their Spin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mike Wise</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Indiana Pacers Reggie Miller revels in 33-point blowout over Los Angeles Lakers in Game 5 of National Basketball Association Finals; says he is shocked by Lakers scuffling style of play when asked about growing tension between teams; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The game was in the vault an hour before. Reggie Miller had pulled the pin on his last 3-pointer, and Jalen Rose had peeled and sliced a defense purported to be the league's most stingy.</p>
        <p>So all the two emotional scorers for the Indiana Pacers had left to do was not anger the gods any further, be happy with their 33-point knockout over Shaquille O'Neal, Kobe Bryant and the Los Angeles Lakers in Game 5 of the National Basketball Association finals. Catch a flight to Los Angeles for Game 6. Maybe a humble statement or two, and that's it. Move on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The game was in the vault an hour before. Reggie Miller had pulled the pin on his last 3-pointer, and Jalen Rose had peeled and sliced a defense purported to be the league's most stingy.</p>
        <p>So all the two emotional scorers for the Indiana Pacers had left to do was not anger the gods any further, be happy with their 33-point knockout over Shaquille O'Neal, Kobe Bryant and the Los Angeles Lakers in Game 5 of the National Basketball Association finals. Catch a flight to Los Angeles for Game 6. Maybe a humble statement or two, and that's it. Move on.</p>
        <p>But they could not help themselves.</p>
        <p>''Well, a lot of the scuffles are coming from them, which is a shock,'' Miller replied with biting sarcasm when asked about growing tension between the teams. ''Everyone thinks they're so nice and pretty and, you know, they're the glamour boys, it's Los Angeles. Evian. Caffe latte, all that.</p>
        <p>''They're doing all the pushing, the holding. They look at the refs like they're not doing anything.''</p>
        <p>Having carved up Glen Rice and anyone else Phil Jackson sicced on him in the 120-87 blowout on Friday night, Rose wondered openly who could stop him.</p>
        <p>''Do you come out on me, contest a 3-pointer and allow me to get my dribble-drive game going, or do you double-team me in the post and allow me to pass and get other guys involved?'' he inquired.</p>
        <p>On the surface, the Shaq-and-Kobe coronation has been temporarily postponed by two stick figures. Outweighed and outmuscled, Miller and Rose are the annoying-gnat-type players you shove aside to grab the rebound, the obnoxious, tagalong siblings you cannot quite ditch.</p>
        <p>But you look again and you realize their edge -- that spiteful guard-me-if-you-can demeanor -- is why the Pacers forced a return trip to L.A. before their loud legions at the Conseco Fieldhouse Friday night. They combined for 57 points and eight 3-pointers, doing most of the damage in a barrage that hit the Lakers hard, shook their foundation and again raised doubts about their ability to close out an opponent ready to drop.</p>
        <p>At the end, Miller was staring coldly at the Laker bench, Rose was laughing at Rick Fox. Miller and Mark Jackson each were assessed technical fouls with 11 minutes left in the fourth period and the game already out of reach.</p>
        <p>It was not Larry Bird's kind of act.</p>
        <p>Hoosiers play by unspoken rules.  You don't show up the opponent. Once you move to Indiana, you're supposed to play how the coach tells you to play. Give up your urban roots and give in to tradition.</p>
        <p>Bird hates the taunting, the shimmying, the finger-pointing of Jackson, Miller and Rose. But can the Pacers coach have it both ways? As one of the game's legendary purveyors of verbal trash, Bird is a bit of revisionist historian.</p>
        <p>The Pacers thrive off their emotions. Rose does not care what the score is or who is defending him. When Miller is ahead by 20, he gets more greedy, yelling at his teammates to give him the ball so he can plunge in another 3-point dagger.</p>
        <p>Jackson is 35 years old. His lack of foot speed prevents him from beating many retired players off the dribble. But there he was, strutting down a corridor of the arena, humming an old rap tune on Friday night -- an old-school player paying homage to an old-school artist.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't put it any better than LL Cool J, who said, 'We're going back to Cali,' '' Jackson said. ''That was our theme song before tonight's game. We went with that mentality.''</p>
        <p>When told Bird was upset by their outbursts, he replied, ''I'm not going to get into, you know, the coach, his opinion. I think as leaders of this basketball team, we have to spark something to make a statement that we're not going to lay down.''</p>
        <p>Miller became prickly when asked if Bird's last game at home meant something to the team. ''It was the last game for a lot of guys in there, not just Larry,'' he said. ''We're facing elimination.''</p>
        <p>He and Rose played the game as well as it can be played on Friday night, finding open spaces and each other, turning the court into a Woodenesque clinic, a hoop choreographer's dream where everyone makes the right play.</p>
        <p>In the first half alone, the Rose and Miller detonated for 42 points. The defining play came with Miller racing down the court, leading the break, dumping it off to Rose for a two-handed dunk on the left side.</p>
        <p>The evolution of Rose and Miller thriving in the same lineup together is more impressive than Allan Houston and Latrell Sprewell sharing the same floor space and complementing each other's games. Rose did not start last season. He took Chris Mullin's spot and cut into Derrick McKey's playing time, adding a new dynamic to the motion offense.</p>
        <p>It was so new, Miller's head spun early in the season. ''It took some time for us to find a balance with one another, you know,'' he said. ''I was so used to working with Derrick as well as Chris Mullin the last two and three years. But it took time for us to get our rhythm, especially our motion play, on which side both of us liked. Now that we found a comfortable balance between the two, it's starting to show just a little bit.''</p>
        <p>The Pacers still have a steep climb, but who believed they would last this long? Two irrepressible, rangy scorers -- one allegedly past his prime and the other not yet an All-Star -- giving the team with two of the top players in the N.B.A. a genuine scrap for the title.</p>
        <p>''They're still the team in control, but we're still the team that has fight,'' Rose said. ''We know California is going to be ready to celebrate. We heard about the parade that they have planned. That won't be tomorrow, though.''</p>
        <p>Said Miller: ''We absolutely, positively have nothing to lose and everything in the world to gain. So we are going to play loose, free, we don't care. There's no pressure on us. All the pressure is on them. From the get-go, they were supposed to beat us. They were supposed to sweep us.''</p>
        <p>According to Bird, they were supposed to make a humble statement or two. Catch a flight. Move on. But Miller and Rose cannot help themselves. They're not Hoosiers at heart. They're ballplayers, looking for one more decent run.</p>
        <p>ON PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
