<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Sling and a Prayer</title>
    <meta content="18MILEST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miles, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McKenzie, Steven L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">King David: A Biography (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E0D7133FF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1341" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Sling and a Prayer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Miles</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miles, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Miles reviews book King David: A Biography by Steven L McKenzie; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>KING DAVID</p>
        <p>A Biography.</p>
        <p>By Steven L. McKenzie.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 232 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Oxford University Press. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>KING DAVID</p>
        <p>A Biography.</p>
        <p>By Steven L. McKenzie.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 232 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Oxford University Press. $25.</p>
        <p>Was King David a Jew? For decades, scholars have quietly entertained doubts. When the Bible lists David's 30-man personal bodyguard by name and hometown (II Samuel 23:24-39), entries like ''Helez the Paltite,'' ''Maharay the Netophathite,'' ''Azmawet the Barhumite'' and ''Gareb the Yithrite'' seem to be written in a near Hebrew, as if one had come across the register of a Catalonian brigade in the French Army. David's larger armed force, which carried him to power and remained loyal to him through one native Israelite rebellion after another, is referred to in most Bible translations as ''the Cherethites and the Pelethites,'' opaque terms that may be more revealingly translated as ''the Cretans and the Philistines.'' For these and other, less linguistic reasons, the possibility has loomed for a long while that the greatest Jew in the Hebrew Bible may not have been born Jewish.</p>
        <p>Marginal figures, of course, have often risen to power, even redemptive power, in the cultures to which they were born marginal. Siddhartha Gautama, the Buddha, was born in Nepal, just outside India. Alexander the Great was born in Macedonia, just outside Greece. Rodrigo Diaz de Vivar, known to history as El Cid (from the Arabic al-Said), was a very Moorish Spaniard. Napoleon, born in Corsica, was a very Italian Frenchman. If something like this was David's story, at what margin did he arise?</p>
        <p>According to the Bible, David was born in Bethlehem in the territory of Judah, but it was at Hebron, farther south in Judah, that he was first anointed king. In American terms, this is like saying that he was born in Dallas but had his political base at San Antonio, down where Tex starts to morph into Tex-Mex. A political base at the southern extreme of this southern extreme would in itself have made David a marginal Israelite. In fact, David's political base extended across the southern border of Judah into Edom and across the western border into Philistia. David was a cross-cultural adventurer, in short, and, in his wild early years, a virtual border bandit.</p>
        <p>The story of this charismatic talent fighting, loving and even singing his way to power through a tangle of divided loyalties has often been told and is well worth telling again. What Steven L. McKenzie offers, however, in this alert and energetic new book is not a retelling of that story. McKenzie's ''King David: A Biography,'' despite its subtitle, takes the form less of a narration than of a historian's cross-examination. This is surprising on two counts.</p>
        <p>First, McKenzie begins the introduction to his work with a discussion entitled ''Images of David in Literature,'' and he opens most of the chapters with provocative epigraphs plucked from that literature -- everyone from John Dryden to Joseph Heller. Attention to fiction and poetry inspired by I Samuel 16 through I Kings 2 -- the biblical books that tell David's story -- might predict attention to that account as itself literature. But no: McKenzie's concern is resolutely historical rather than literary.</p>
        <p>Second, and again at the outset, McKenzie cites with approval the declaration of his teacher, the biblical scholar P. Kyle McCarter: ''The Bible is our only source of information about David. No ancient inscription mentions him. No archaeological discovery can be securely linked to him. The quest for the historical David, therefore, is primarily exegetical.'' Expanding pointedly on McCarter, McKenzie writes that the story of David in the Bible ''is as close to the historical David as we can get. It appears to contain genuine historical information about him. But that information is not immediately accessible. It is clothed in literary and apologetic garb. So we have to read critically in order to make use of it.'' The occasion for this new historical study, in other words, is not any new historical information.</p>
        <p>Apologetic garb is apologetic because it is woven of faith that David was the divinely chosen king of a divinely chosen people. Literary garb is literary because it is woven of writerly skill that, historical truth aside, makes the biblical story entertaining and moving. But neither of these costumes interests McKenzie. He is after the naked truth, or what he calls elsewhere in his book, using a hoarier scholastic metaphor, the ''historical kernel'' -- the stone of the peach as distinct from the literary or religious fruit.</p>
        <p>His tactic for stripping off the garb or paring away the fruit is, as noted, cross-examination, and at this McKenzie is little short of brilliant. Like a prosecuting attorney forced to build his case on the testimony of one intermittently deceptive witness, he relentlessly exposes both unnoticed inconsistencies in the testimony and inadvertent consistencies yielding unintended clarifications. McKenzie's witness is ''Dtr,'' an unpronounceable abbreviation that he treats as if it were a personal name (it abbreviates the learned construct ''Deuteronomistic Historian''). Dtr believes that David is the elect of God and, accordingly, makes excuses for David's crimes. McKenzie demolishes the excuses. Dtr embroiders David's achievements. McKenzie tears away the embroidery. If you enjoy the intellectual spectacle of a coldly logical attorney making mincemeat of a glib and sometimes pious poseur, you will enjoy McKenzie having at the hapless Dtr.</p>
        <p>To give just one example, Dtr implies that Saul died in battle against the Philistines on Mount Gilboa because he had lost the favor of the Lord. McKenzie asks: ''What brought about this sudden and devastating loss? The answer may be David, or more precisely, the league between David and the Philistines. Saul was prepared to confront the Philistines to his west, as they encroached from the coast. But he did not anticipate that a formidable enemy would threaten him from the south. David forced Saul to defend two fronts.''</p>
        <p>THIS is a geographically and strategically astute new reading of very old evidence, and as such it has an undeniable fascination. At the end of the book-length cross-examination, however, one has the odd feeling that whatever the fun in watching Dtr squirm, he has been convicted only of being himself (or herself). Once the historical truth about David has been established, how interesting is it? Is the adulterated literary account not more rewarding as literature than the purified historical account is as history? And as for any specifically religious power in this text, McKenzie, whatever his personal beliefs, writes as a methodological atheist. Yahweh appears in ''King David'' only as a cipher in David's and Dtr's political calculations. The deity serves their purposes; he is allowed none of his own.</p>
        <p>A heated debate has arisen over the past several years among historians of ancient Israel between the maximalists, who believe that, due qualification made, the biblical account is historically reliable, and the minimalists, who believe the opposite. McKenzie, to my eyes, is a minimalist in maximalist company (another of his teachers is the maximalist archaeologist William Dever). In the wings of his book, however, lurking in the literary allusions that he has so assiduously assembled but does not pursue, is the possibility that neither side is right. On the contrary, both may be not wrong but irrelevant to the continuing popular and even intellectual appeal of the Bible. If the Israeli schoolchildren who sing the Hebrew jingle ''David, melekh yisra'el, chay chay veqayyam'' (loosely, ''David, the king of Israel, is alive, alive and well'') were told tomorrow that David was a legendary rather than a historical figure, would they stop singing? I think not; and as for the children, so also, analogously, for their elders, both there and here.</p>
        <p>Jack Miles is the author of ''God: A Biography.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jack Miles is the author of ''God: A Biography.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
