<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of the Times; Differing Viewpoints On Problems</title>
    <meta content="Y18RHO$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhoden, William C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cross, Howard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garnes, Sam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Comella, Greg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toomer, Amani</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barber, Tiki</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Ray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD91731F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of the Times; Differing Viewpoints On Problems</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William C Rhoden Sports of The Times column discusses interview with five members of New York Giants, Howard Cross, Sam Garnes, Greg Comella, Amani Toomer and Tiki Barber; players discussed issues surrounding trial of Ray Lewis, who was charged with murder and subsequently pleaded guilty to misdemeanor, and how this and other incidents have been handled by news media (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MORE than once, Howard Cross or one of his Giants teammates looked across the table at the editors and reporters and prefaced a remark with ''No offense to you guys'' or ''Nothing personal, but. . . .'' Then the players would offer a polite but pointed critique of the sports news media.</p>
        <p>This was Thursday afternoon. Five members of the Giants graciously agreed to march behind the lines and meet with the enemy. Cross, Amani Toomer, Sam Garnes, Greg Comella and Tiki Barber sat in a conference room with New York Times editors and reporters, engaged in a two-pronged discussion. We talked about the coming football season and then tackled issues surrounding the rash of off-the-field incidents that have marred the image of the contemporary professional athlete.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MORE than once, Howard Cross or one of his Giants teammates looked across the table at the editors and reporters and prefaced a remark with ''No offense to you guys'' or ''Nothing personal, but. . . .'' Then the players would offer a polite but pointed critique of the sports news media.</p>
        <p>This was Thursday afternoon. Five members of the Giants graciously agreed to march behind the lines and meet with the enemy. Cross, Amani Toomer, Sam Garnes, Greg Comella and Tiki Barber sat in a conference room with New York Times editors and reporters, engaged in a two-pronged discussion. We talked about the coming football season and then tackled issues surrounding the rash of off-the-field incidents that have marred the image of the contemporary professional athlete.</p>
        <p>The impetus for this meeting was a new season, and the serious and troubling issues surrounding the trial of Ray Lewis, who was charged with murder and subsequently pleaded guilty to a misdemeanor. What came through was the players' mistrust of, frustration with and resentment of the news media. There was the notion that athletes have targets on their backs, and the news media aim and shoot, acting like a civilian review board.</p>
        <p>What athletes do and how the news media interpret what they do, how reporters cover and uncover the actions, deeds and misdeeds and disseminate information to the public are sources of tension between the athletes and the editors and reporters. ''What do people want to hear?'' Barber said. ''I mean, your job is to sell papers, right? And you don't want to put out news that nobody wants to read.''</p>
        <p>Barber said what bothers him is that ''people don't look to find the truth.'' He added: ''They just look to put the story out there and whatever spin they feel is going to be more attractive.''</p>
        <p>But even the players didn't agree on everything. Are pro athletes held to unfair standards?</p>
        <p>Cross: ''Yes.''</p>
        <p>Barber: ''Oh, without a doubt.''</p>
        <p>Comella: ''I don't think that we are held to too high of a standard. I think we've had chances to do things that 99 percent of this country never even conceives.''</p>
        <p>For all of the complaints about being targets, Cross conceded that pro athletes were also objects of affection, that they were given many things.</p>
        <p>''You get that celebrity status, and people do know you and people are offering you meals and cutting you into the front of the line,'' he said. ''For every one of those that happens, there's another group of people that are like, 'Oh, he doesn't deserve anything.' There are some places still in Alabama -- 'Hey, that's Howard Cross from the Giants. He played for Alabama. That's a black guy, man.' You're still black.''</p>
        <p>Sam Garnes disagreed. ''You get more good things from being an athlete, being a professional football player,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Someone asked the players why public sentiment seemed to be turning against professional athletes, particularly basketball and football players.</p>
        <p>Toomer said he felt that news media portrayals and the public's penchant to know dirt were greater factors than any problem that might exist in the league. ''They want to set you up to be kind of a star and then they want to know the dirt behind you,'' he said. ''They want to know the person more than just the good things they do.''</p>
        <p>The news media oblige by dredging up the dirt and dishing it. Of course, if there's no dirt to be dredged up, it can't be dished. In fact, I think we love heroes more; we choose the fallen and the wretched because they are in such abundance. We love the heroic instinct, the heroic attempt. Outside of stadiums and arenas, there is so little room for heroes; the individual has been reduced and minimized by the onslaught of progress. Minimized by corporations devouring corporations. The monster eventually begins feeding on itself.</p>
        <p>Professional athletes -- Cross, Comella, Garnes, Barber, Toomer, the star goalie, the swimmer -- rely on arms, legs and muscles. They play on a level field, or as level as possible. They play by a set of rules enforced by officials -- sometimes for better, sometimes for worse -- who drop the flag or blow the whistle to keep the field level.</p>
        <p>The games are so unlike the real world, where wealth and power usually reign side by side with skulduggery in pursuit of wealth and power. The athlete, in an odd way, offers salvation. Maybe this is the underlying reason for fan anger when an athlete falls from grace.</p>
        <p>''They don't want you to be perfect,'' Cross said.</p>
        <p>After more than an hour, the meeting broke up. Everyone shook hands and headed back to his or her own world.</p>
        <p>The meeting raised more questions than answers. Some of us want to see more introspection from athletes about problems in the professional leagues. From the athletes' perspective, the problem is we, with our pens and cameras. Taking it all in.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
