<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For a Kasparov Opponent, Same Story, Different Day</title>
    <meta content="18CHES$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208463"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CHESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chess</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Byrne, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kasparov, Garry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chess</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E1D91731F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="619" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For a Kasparov Opponent, Same Story, Different Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert Byrne</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Byrne, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert Byrne Chess column on play used by Garry Kasparov in winning recent tournament; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Garry Kasparov kept up his winning ways by taking first prize in the Bosna 2000 International Tournament in Sarajevo, which ran from May 16 to 19. He scored 8 1/2-2 1/2 in this power-packed all-grandmaster competition.</p>
        <p>Michael Adams of England and Alexei Shirov of Spain tied for second at 8-3.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Garry Kasparov kept up his winning ways by taking first prize in the Bosna 2000 International Tournament in Sarajevo, which ran from May 16 to 19. He scored 8 1/2-2 1/2 in this power-packed all-grandmaster competition.</p>
        <p>Michael Adams of England and Alexei Shirov of Spain tied for second at 8-3.</p>
        <p>In the final round, Kasparov needed to win to escape his pursuers, and he came through in spectacular style, playing the very model of a speculative gambit to defeat Sergei Movsesian of the Czech Republic.</p>
        <p>It's well known that, if you play 1 e4 against Kasparov, you will face the Sicilian Defense Najdorf Variation, beginning with 5 . . . a6.</p>
        <p>Like Bobby Fischer, he clearly believes that this is the best way to counter a kingside opening.</p>
        <p>He dares his opponents to prepare for him, but his preparation is more penetrating and his understanding of this mode of play unequaled. In this game, he gets another customer.</p>
        <p>Movsesian's 11 Qf2 was unwise in that it pressed Kasparov to make an improvement in his position with the retreat 11 . . . Nfd7.</p>
        <p>After 13 Bd3, another consequence of taking the queen away from d2 arose: Kasparov's 13 . . . Rc3!? bc left Movsesian with a fractured king position and great danger of his king falling to a mating attack.</p>
        <p>Kasparov said that he had not worked everything out to the end, but felt that he did not need concrete proof.</p>
        <p>Before making a direct attacking probe, Kasparov finished his mobilization with 14 . . . Qc7, 15 . . . Be7 and 16 . . . O-O.</p>
        <p>Movsesian, having no way of improving his king's situation, threw everything into a mating attack of his own with 16 g5, 17 h4 and 19 h5.</p>
        <p>After 20 . . . Bd6, Kasparov gave as better 21 Bf4 b4 22 cb Rc8 23 Rc1 d4 24 Ka1 Nc3 25 Nd4 Bb4 26 Nb3 (not 26 Be5? Qa5!) Qd7, commenting, ''Black's attack is still very dangerous.''</p>
        <p>After 22 . . . b4!, Kasparov thought that perhaps the most obstinate stand could be put up by 23 c4, but that Movsesian would not be able to withstand 23 . . . dc 24 g6 Be5 25 h6 cd 26 gh Kh8 27 hg Bg7 28 Rd3 Qc4 29 Rhd1 Nc3 30 Nc3 bc 31 Qh2 Qb4.</p>
        <p>Indeed, after 32 Kc2, the riposte 32 . . . Bc6! sets up the annihilating 33 . . . Ba4.</p>
        <p>After Kasparov's shattering 25 . . . Be4! Movsesian could not recapture with 26 de because 26 . . . Be5 27 Nd4 Bd4 28 Rd4 Qc1 29 Rc1 ends in 29 . . . Rc1mate.</p>
        <p>After 28 gf, Kasparov could have played the mundane 28 . . . Qf7, but he was hot for the kill, so he ducked a possible check by playing 28 . . . Kf8.</p>
        <p>If Movsesian plays 29 Bb2, then 29 . . . Qc2 30 Rb1 Qe2 31 h6 Bc3! 32 hg Kf7 33 Qb7 Kf6 and White has come to the end of his rope.</p>
        <p>After 31 Nd4, Kasparov came up with a cute queen sacrifice: 31 . . . Nd1! 32 Ne6 Kf7.</p>
        <p>Movsesian, unwilling to hang around for 33 Nc7 Bc3, gave up.</p>
        <p>CHESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
