<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jones's Mediocre Jumping Gives Competitors Hope</title>
    <meta content="18TRAC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208503"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRACK AND FIELD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Marion</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sturrup, Chandra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E1DD1431F93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jones's Mediocre Jumping Gives Competitors Hope</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>RALEIGH, N.C., June 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marion Jones's hope of winning five Olympic gold medals in Sydney appears to be in jeopardy following poor performance in long jump at Grand Prix event; Chandra Sturrup, Jones's training partner, wins while Jones fouls twice (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marion Jones turned on her computer this morning and learned the surprising news that Jackie Joyner-Kersee, two years retired, had entered the long jump at next month's United States Olympic track and field trials. Then Jones jumped at a Grand Prix meet here and gave the 38-year-old Joyner-Kersee no reason to believe that a comeback would be ill advised.</p>
        <p>Jones leapt 21 feet 6 inches -- 11 inches beyond a limp performance in Japan last month. But she lost to her training partner, came up 18 inches short of what her coach had hoped for and fell nearly two feet short of the world's best this year. Her chances of winning five gold medals at the Summer Olympics in Sydney, Australia, appear to be in jeopardy with the Games opening in three months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Marion Jones turned on her computer this morning and learned the surprising news that Jackie Joyner-Kersee, two years retired, had entered the long jump at next month's United States Olympic track and field trials. Then Jones jumped at a Grand Prix meet here and gave the 38-year-old Joyner-Kersee no reason to believe that a comeback would be ill advised.</p>
        <p>Jones leapt 21 feet 6 inches -- 11 inches beyond a limp performance in Japan last month. But she lost to her training partner, came up 18 inches short of what her coach had hoped for and fell nearly two feet short of the world's best this year. Her chances of winning five gold medals at the Summer Olympics in Sydney, Australia, appear to be in jeopardy with the Games opening in three months.</p>
        <p>Chandra Sturrup of the Bahamas, who trains with Jones here and who won eight collegiate titles at Norfolk State, scored an impressive double victory, winning the women's 100 meters in 11.09 seconds, then reeling off a personal best of 21-11 3/4 to win the long jump. Meanwhile, Jones fouled twice on six jumps with her line-drive style and landed awkwardly on each jump, propelling herself forward onto her knees with her horizontal momentum.</p>
        <p>The world-champion shot-putter, C. J. Hunter, who is married to Jones, fared much better today, setting a personal best with a throw of 71-8 3/4. No one has thrown farther this year, and Hunter has become the prohibitive favorite to win in Sydney.</p>
        <p>Not so with his wife in the long jump.</p>
        <p>Abandoning her attempt to get a powerful bound on the takeoff board, Jones has decided to let her speed as the world's fastest woman propel her in the long jump. She could take satisfaction in knowing that she improved nearly a foot in the last month and that she beat the top American competition she will face at the Olympic trials that begin on July 14. The bad news was, she was mediocre in a meet in which she did not have to sprint the 100 or 200, which will be required at the trials and the Olympics. Today's jump was well short of her personal best of 23-11 3/4, set in 1998, as well as this year's world best of 23-3 3/4, by Fiona May of Italy.</p>
        <p>Trevor Graham, who coaches Jones, said that she appeared to slow on her approach and was not assertive enough in blasting off the runway. Still, he said he was pleased that she had improved considerably over her previous meet.</p>
        <p>''If I get her to accelerate more and attack the board, she'll be back where she was in '98,'' Graham said.</p>
        <p>Jones appeared relieved that her jump of a month ago had been an aberration and said that better jumps were ahead.</p>
        <p>''I feel very confident,'' she said. ''I'm the same person that was jumping in '98. I have to get a little more confident and everything will fall into place.''</p>
        <p>She could face a serious challenge at the trials if Joyner-Kersee actually comes out of retirement. Greg Foster, her agent, said there was a 75 percent chance that she would compete. ''She is in training and in shape,'' he said. ''The important thing is that she wants to be competitive in the Olympic Games. She's not doing this just to make the team.''</p>
        <p>Joyner-Kersee twice won gold medals in the Olympic heptathlon, and once won the Olympic long jump. She owns the American record in the long jump at 24-7 and has the seven longest jumps among American women. It remains to be seen whether she can regain her form. Her last jump before retiring was 20-11 3/4. Given the ordinary jumping in the world, Graham said he could see how Joyner-Kersee would be encouraged to make a comeback.</p>
        <p>''If she's entering the trials, she's definitely going to be ready,'' Jones said of Joyner-Kersee. ''It's going to make things that much more interesting.''</p>
        <p>TRACK AND FIELD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
