<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senior Tour Is Made for the Late Bloomer</title>
    <meta content="18EICH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Senior Pga Tour (Golf)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Haven (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eichelberger, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moss, Marven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/New Haven</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E6D9133EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senior Tour Is Made for the Late Bloomer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARVEN MOSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moss, Marven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Dave Eichelberger, 56, transplanted Texan who now lives in New Canaan, Conn; Eichelberger has revived his professional golfing career on Senior PGA Tour, where he has won six tournaments and $3.5 million over six seasons; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DAVE EICHELBERGER is a transplanted Texan who resettled in Connecticut 15 years ago.</p>
        <p>Moving from Texas to Connecticut might not seem such an unusual move, unless you are a professional golfer, which is Eichelberger's profession. Next week Eichelberger, 56, will be trying to defend his title at the United States Senior Open at the Saucon Valley Country Club in Bethleham, Pa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DAVE EICHELBERGER is a transplanted Texan who resettled in Connecticut 15 years ago.</p>
        <p>Moving from Texas to Connecticut might not seem such an unusual move, unless you are a professional golfer, which is Eichelberger's profession. Next week Eichelberger, 56, will be trying to defend his title at the United States Senior Open at the Saucon Valley Country Club in Bethleham, Pa.</p>
        <p>His move to the less-temperate clime of the Northeast was preceded by meeting his wife-to-be, D.C. (Dorothy Christine), in 1984 at the Westchester Country Club in Harrison, N.Y., where she was a volunteer scorekeeper at the old Westchester Classic.</p>
        <p>Two years ago D.C., a Greenwich antique dealer and non-golfer, and Eichelberger, purchased a 7,000-square-foot, three-story colonial within walking distance of the center of town in New Canaan where they live with their 2 1/2-year-old twins, Davis and Emalia. Eichelberger has two other children, Martin and Clinton, and two grandchildren from an earlier marriage.</p>
        <p>Recently, he became a member of the Stanwich Club in Greenwich, one of the most challenging courses in the state. He also belongs to the Connecticut Golf Club at Easton.</p>
        <p>The Senior PGA Tour, a $54.1 million prize-money bonanza this year for golfers 50 and older, resuscitated Eichelberger's fervor for golf. In six full seasons with the seniors, he has won six tournaments and $3.5 million, compared with four victories and earnings of $1.1 million in 26 seasons on the regular tour. (This month, he played in his 1,000th tournament as a professional.) His prize-money total as a senior was enriched by his largest single paycheck as a golfer, a $315,000 payoff last July for his three-shot victory over Ed Dougherty in the 1999 United States Senior Open at the Des Moines Golf and Country Club in Iowa.</p>
        <p>His best finish this season was a tie for fifth place at the Toshiba Senior Classic in March.</p>
        <p>His renaissance is not an anomaly. The Senior Tour has become a lucrative arena of achievement by lesser-accomplished figures such as Bruce Fleisher, Allen Doyle, Dana Quigley and Vicente Fernandez most recently among the current genre who regularly outplay the bigger names from the regular tour. Here Tom Wargo has perhaps had no less an impact than Tom Watson, Tom Kite and Tom Weiskopf.</p>
        <p>Do the skills of some golfers deteriorate less precipitously than others? Is the pressure less intense outside the regular tour? Are some motivated because they have more to prove?</p>
        <p>Eichelberger's pal and partner in winning the 1994 Diners Club team match, Ray Floyd, offers a perspective on what's behind the belated productivity by Eichelberger and others like him.</p>
        <p>''The golf courses we play on the Senior Tour are different,'' Floyd says. ''Berger's problem has always been driving. Now we're playing shorter courses with a more liberal, forgiving rough, what you might call 'member's rough.' The penalty for an errant drive is not nearly as severe as it is on the regular tour.''</p>
        <p>In the past, Eichelberger concedes, his driving had been erratic, ''even wild.''</p>
        <p>But he feels he has improved the precision of his tee shots by going to a fade (the airborne ball travels from left to right) rather than the draw (from right to left) he has basically played since he was a high school golfer in Waco, Tex. That change gives him a softer, more predictable bounce and greater control.</p>
        <p>Metal woods with their lightweight shafts and oversize heads, plus the latest generation of perimeter-weighted irons, have more than compensated for any loss of distance induced by age. In fact, Eichelberger said that as far as he knows no player on either men's tour uses anything but metal woods now.</p>
        <p>Finally, Eichelberger says his success has been a consequence in part of a transition into an age group ''where everybody, at least initially, is older than you. When you eliminate people younger than yourself, it's like starting all over again and your outlook is rejuvenated.''</p>
        <p>At one time Eichelberger would bang out 700 ore more practice balls a week. Now he hits no more than 150. ''The only senior who still claims to hit 700 or even 800 balls now is Trevino,'' Eichelberger said of Lee Trevino, ''and I wouldn't put it past him.''</p>
        <p>Joe Inman, another senior golfer, describes Eichelbelger's swing today as still ''short and aggressive.''</p>
        <p>''Berger's got a great attitude,'' Inman says. ''He never backs off. He's not afraid to win. And he never gets down on himself. The game is frustrating enough without beating yourself up. And it doesn't matter if the fairway is only 10 yards wide. Berger's going to hit his driver.''</p>
        <p>Both Floyd and Inman say golfers on the Senior Tour regard Eichelberger as a favorable pairing.'' His temper may flare once in a while,'' Floyd says, ''but he will blurt out things that are off-the-wall funny and he keeps you loose.''</p>
        <p>Floyd says the secret to playing in team competition ''is to let the other fellow play his own game. Some guys try to tell you which way the putt breaks. I don't believe that works. I let them do it their way.''</p>
        <p>As a professional golfer, Eichelberger is unconventional in that he is associated with no full-time manager. He works with agents on a project basis and gets up to $15,000 for a corporate appearance. And, he is not a follower of any swing guru as many on the tour are.</p>
        <p>Ben Hogan, the golf icon and fellow-Texan, once told Eichelberger: ''Son, work it out for yourself. There's nobody that knows.''</p>
        <p>''Coaches in high school and college have helped me,'' Eichelberger says. ''But I'm largely self-taught. I don't allow anyone to tinker with my swing. The tour is riddled with golfers who got worse by listening to gurus.''</p>
        <p>The best golfer Eichelberger ever saw?</p>
        <p>''Mr. Hogan, by far,'' he said, referring to the legendary Ben Hogan. ''No one ever hit the ball straighter.''</p>
        <p>''Nicklaus undoubtedly deserves to be considered and Tony Lema might have left a legacy for consideration,'' he adds about the golfer who died at 32 in a 1966 plane crash.</p>
        <p>''Tiger Woods? He could become the all-time best in time, but he's got years to go before we can evaluate the totality of what he accomplishes,'' Eichelberger says.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
