<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where a Large Appetite Could Be an Asset</title>
    <meta content="18DINE$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208207"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Terra Mar Grille (Old Saybrook, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Patricia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E5DC103EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where a Large Appetite Could Be an Asset</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooks, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia Brooks reviews Terra Mar Grille in Old Saybrook, Conn (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TERRA MAR GRILLE in Old Saybrook is well named, for its menu speaks of both land and sea, with perhaps a slight list seaward. That's as it should be, considering the restaurant's location, smack on the water, with grand views (from almost any seat) of marina, sea birds, boats and lighthouse.</p>
        <p>The views are so great the food could be secondary. But it isn't -- a big change from our last visit 10 years ago when the restaurant had another name, configuration, chef and menu. Times, they have improved.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TERRA MAR GRILLE in Old Saybrook is well named, for its menu speaks of both land and sea, with perhaps a slight list seaward. That's as it should be, considering the restaurant's location, smack on the water, with grand views (from almost any seat) of marina, sea birds, boats and lighthouse.</p>
        <p>The views are so great the food could be secondary. But it isn't -- a big change from our last visit 10 years ago when the restaurant had another name, configuration, chef and menu. Times, they have improved.</p>
        <p>We realized this with our first bite of the risotto of the day, an entree-size appetizer that combined tiny, spicy rock shrimp with roasted garlic, tomato and an expertly made, creamy risotto, so ample and so rich we could have, should have stopped right there.</p>
        <p>But our entree was on the way. It was such a gargantuan plate of expertly grilled dry aged Porterhouse steak with a lavish pancetta and wild mushroom demi-glace, caramelized  carrots and spinach, with narrow ribbons of fried (but limp) onions, that we had to bag most of it. It was too delicious to waste, too sizable to eat.</p>
        <p>One member of our party found the grilled duck breast salad -- replete with plum tomatoes, fresh mozzarella, balsamic glace and slivers of delightful crisp-fried sweet potato -- rewarding, even though the duck was too thickly sliced. His entree, ginger and sesame grilled Atlantic salmon, was perfect all by itself, embellished nicely by a scallion-couscous pancake, sauteed snowpeas and slices of crisp lotus root, a felicitous combination.</p>
        <p>By the time we visited Terra Mar Grille for lunch, we were smarter about the generous portions, so three of us shared a light and tasty salad before embarking on our entrees. The salad of field greens with dabs of fresh goat cheese and whole pistachios in an airy champagne vinaigrette was just the right size as a preliminary course.</p>
        <p>Then followed steamed Prince Edward Island mussels in a subtle garlic-shallot-crushed red pepper broth. Sauteed lobster meat (fresh and full of flavor) piled high on a toasted New England roll came with house-made crispy potato chips and ordinary coleslaw.</p>
        <p>Pennette with asparagus and wild mushrooms, our third entree, consisted of a pile of boringly naked pasta topped with generous pieces of fresh asparagus, excellent and varied wild mushrooms, a wisp of basil and roasted garlic cloves. Poking our fork through the mound of quill-like penne (larger than pennette) we discovered at the bottom a spoonful of broth.</p>
        <p>Pleasing as the various ingredients were singly, the dish needed a real wake-up sauce to bind everything together.</p>
        <p>A cranky aside: why, when dishes have broths, like our steamed mussels and penne, do we have to flag down the waitress for spoons, which should be part of the service? Our waitress seemed puzzled, even burdened by the request.</p>
        <p>Desserts ran the gamut from a seductive warm chocolate bread pudding with an intense Belgian chocolate sauce and vanilla ice cream and a luscious, light-textured lemon mascarpone cheesecake topped with lemon confit, sitting in a pool of strawberry coulis with fresh berries, to a mundane chocolate fudge tart with a tough, cardboardy crust and sabayon of candied fruit that was mostly over-sweetened fruit and scant, thin sabayon saucing.</p>
        <p>Dinner for two, three courses apiece, was $75, while lunch for two, two courses each, cost $37.65, before tax, tip and drinks in both cases.</p>
        <p>A well-chosen wine list, priced from $25, is mostly West Coast and French, with a few Italian vintages.</p>
        <p>Terra Mar Grille has a lot going for it now, with only minimal slippage. The waterside views are just half the story.</p>
        <p>Terra Mar Grille  Saybrook Point Inn and Spa  2 Bridge Street, Old Saybrook  (860) 395-2000</p>
        <p>Very Good</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Well-spaced tables, overlooking a marina.</p>
        <p>SERVICE -- Ranges from experienced and friendly to careless and indifferent.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Steamed mussels, shrimp risotto, duck breast salad, ginger-sesame grilled salmon, grilled porterhouse, sauteed lobster meat on roll, chocolate bread pudding, lemon mascarpone cheesecake.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE -- Lunch entrees $8.75-$13.95, dinner entrees $10-$31.95; Sunday brunch buffet: $24.95, $15.95.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS -- Most major cards.</p>
        <p>HOURS -- 11:30 a.m.-2 p.m. Mon.-Sat., 6-9 p.m. Sun.-Thurs., 6-10 p.m. Fri.-Sat.; Sunday brunch 11 a.m.-2 p.m.</p>
        <p>RESERVATIONS -- Accepted.</p>
        <p>ACCESSIBILITY Ground level.</p>
        <p>THE RATINGS Extraordinary, Excellent, Very Good, Good, Poor to Satisfactory.  Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambiance and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
