<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marriages May Come and Go, but the Wedding Dress Lives On</title>
    <meta content="18MAP.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208246"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE MAP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Beach Island Museum (Beach Haven, Nj)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gruber, Mary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nash, Margo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3D9113EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1188" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marriages May Come and Go, but the Wedding Dress Lives On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGO NASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nash, Margo</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mary Gruber, longtime volunteer at Long Beach Island Museum in Beach Haven, NJ, answers questions on exhibit of collection of bridal gowns donated by year-round and summer residents; photo (On the Map column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Long Beach Island Museum in Beach Haven was founded by the Long Beach Island Historical Association in 1976. It is in a building on Engleside and  Beach avenues that used to be the Holy Innocents' Episcopal Church. (The church moved to another location.) Among the exhibits -- which include a ''Barnegat Bay Sneak Box'' for duck hunting, a Victorian living room, photos and scrapbooks of great storms and disasters and a display about the old eel grass  industry -- is a collection of bridal gowns brought in by year-round and summer residents. Mary Gruber, who has volunteered at the museum for about 15 years, is in charge of accepting items that become a part of the museum's collections.</p>
        <p>Q. How many bridal gowns are on exhibit?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Long Beach Island Museum in Beach Haven was founded by the Long Beach Island Historical Association in 1976. It is in a building on Engleside and  Beach avenues that used to be the Holy Innocents' Episcopal Church. (The church moved to another location.) Among the exhibits -- which include a ''Barnegat Bay Sneak Box'' for duck hunting, a Victorian living room, photos and scrapbooks of great storms and disasters and a display about the old eel grass  industry -- is a collection of bridal gowns brought in by year-round and summer residents. Mary Gruber, who has volunteered at the museum for about 15 years, is in charge of accepting items that become a part of the museum's collections.</p>
        <p>Q. How many bridal gowns are on exhibit?</p>
        <p>A. Twelve, but we have 20 in the collection. We rotate them.</p>
        <p>Q. Which is oldest and which the most recent?</p>
        <p>A. The oldest gown is from 1800 and the newest is from 1982. We have a  Quaker wedding dress from 1870. It is brown faille with hand-crocheted buttons, and it's trimmed with velvet. It was not white because Quakers were plain people who did not wear bright colors. It was worn by Rachel Orum Longstreth when she married John Lancaster Longstreth on Dec. 25, 1870. The Longstreths were a prominent family in Philadelphia. Someone in Beach Haven gave us an 1885 dress with a hoop skirt, leg o'mutton puffed sleeves and a veil.  We also have a dress from 1905 with satin sleeves, a jabot of seed pearls in the front and loops of seed pearls at the waist which came from the mainland, from a lady in Barnegat right across the bay. There is a dress worn in 1911, a V-neck bodice, with a lace cape, a train with lace at the bottom, and net with little flowers over a matching petticoat. The original wearer's daughter also wore it at her wedding in 1954. They lived here on the island. One dress that I think is adorable is a short flapper wedding dress from 1924. It has short sleeves and silver bangles.</p>
        <p>Q. Were the oldest dresses smaller?</p>
        <p>A. Yes. The frames of the women who wore them were much smaller, and their waists were much smaller. In order to display the dresses, we had to get wicker mannequins from Italy. We can squeeze them so that we can get the fasteners closed.</p>
        <p>Q. Describe some gowns from other periods.</p>
        <p>A. We have one from 1953 that has a crinoline slip, veil and matching mitts to go with it. Mitts are gloves  without the fingers. There a moire wedding gown worn in 1936 at St. Joseph's Church in Newark That one was valued at $350 when they bought it, which was expensive at that time. Another wedding gown, a size 8 from 1982, was valued at $1,000 when it was bought.</p>
        <p>Q. Is there anything else having to do with weddings that are on exhibit?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, we have a Quaker marriage certificate from Nov. 13, 1813. It shows that in order for Quakers to marry they appeared at a public meeting and everyone at the meeting  had to sign the certificate to show they were married.</p>
        <p>Q. How do the people who visit the museum like the bridal gowns?</p>
        <p>A. Most people who come are summer visitors. On the first rainy days  they're looking for places to go, and they flock in here, and when they get to the bridal exhibit it stops them cold. The little girls love the dress with the long train.</p>
        <p>Q. What did you wear at your wedding?</p>
        <p>A. I'm a maiden lady.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you ever say to yourself, it would have been nice to wear one of these dresses?</p>
        <p>A. No, no. I'm very happy the way I am.</p>
        <p>MARGO NASH</p>
        <p>ON THE MAP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
