<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sharon Kass, Kevin Higgins Jr.</title>
    <meta content="18KASS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208368"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KASS, SHARON SEPTEMBER (SHARON SEPTEMBER HIGGINS)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HIGGINS, KEVIN MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D91F3EF93BA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sharon Kass, Kevin Higgins Jr.</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sharon September Kass, a daughter of Dr. Aileen Kass of Scarsdale, N.Y., and the late Philip Kass, was married last evening to Kevin Michael Higgins Jr., the son of Mr. and Mrs. Higgins Sr. Ascher Katz, a retired town justice of Greenburgh, N.Y., officiated at Le Chateau, a restaurant in South Salem, N.Y.</p>
        <p>The bride, 31, is a senior media planner in the advertising department at Fidelity Investments in Boston. She graduated from the University of Vermont and received a master's degree in elementary education from George Washington University. Her mother is an anesthesiologist at New York Presbyterian Hospital and an associate professor at the Weill Medical College of Cornell University. Her father owned CPC Services, a commercial finance company in Tarrytown, N.Y.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sharon September Kass, a daughter of Dr. Aileen Kass of Scarsdale, N.Y., and the late Philip Kass, was married last evening to Kevin Michael Higgins Jr., the son of Mr. and Mrs. Higgins Sr. Ascher Katz, a retired town justice of Greenburgh, N.Y., officiated at Le Chateau, a restaurant in South Salem, N.Y.</p>
        <p>The bride, 31, is a senior media planner in the advertising department at Fidelity Investments in Boston. She graduated from the University of Vermont and received a master's degree in elementary education from George Washington University. Her mother is an anesthesiologist at New York Presbyterian Hospital and an associate professor at the Weill Medical College of Cornell University. Her father owned CPC Services, a commercial finance company in Tarrytown, N.Y.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 29, is an analyst who tracks the performance of investment managers for Russell/Mellon Analytical Services in Everett, Mass. He served in the Marines in Saudi Arabia during the Persian Gulf war, and later graduated from the University of Rhode Island. His mother, Lois Higgins, is a senior clerk in North Kingstown for the Rhode Island Department of Human Services. His father, a mathematician and computer scientist, is a project consultant working for the Navy in Newport, R.I.</p>
        <p>The couple met over negotiations for a used couch, a table and a set of chairs.</p>
        <p>After Ms. Kass's father died two years ago, her friends thought it would be good for her state of mind to move out of her apartment in Tuckahoe, N.Y., in Westchester County, and into the city. They found her an apartment on the East Side of Manhattan, but Ms. Kass then needed to find someone to take over the lease on the Westchester apartment.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Higgins was relocating to Westchester because of a job he had taken at the Home Loan and Investment Bank. A real estate broker took him to Ms. Kass's place in Tuckahoe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Higgins said the one-bedroom apartment was all right, but the photograph of a woman on the refrigerator caught his attention.</p>
        <p>''Blond, blue-eyed and, well -- the smile really did it,'' he remembered. The agent told him that it was Ms. Kass.</p>
        <p>He took the apartment but determined to find a way to meet her. He asked the agent to see if he could buy some of her furniture. The next day the realtor arranged a phone conversation between them. ''I asked to buy her couch,'' Mr. Higgins said. But Ms. Kass didn't want to sell it. She offered instead a table and set of chairs. ''I didn't want them,'' he said, ''but I wanted to meet her, so I said O.K.''</p>
        <p>Their conversation stretched for an hour and a half, during which he agreed to buy the dining set for $250, which was ''more than what I paid for them,'' Ms. Kass recalled. She agreed to leave the set behind and asked Mr. Higgins to leave a check at the apartment, which she would pick up before she turned over the keys.</p>
        <p>That wouldn't give Mr. Higgins the chance to meet her, so he told her he didn't have a checking account and would give her cash over dinner the following Friday night.</p>
        <p>She rejected his offer but agreed to meet him at her apartment in New York, just before a weekend trip to the Hamptons.</p>
        <p>''It was love at first sight,'' she remembered. ''He was 6 feet 4, dark and handsome.'' She eventually got to Long Island, but not before joining Mr. Higgins for a sushi dinner.</p>
        <p>They began dating right away. Exactly one year after their initial meeting, on the last day of a vacation in Salzburg, Austria, Mr. Higgins made an announcement that startled Ms. Kass.</p>
        <p>''I don't want you to be my girlfriend anymore,'' he said. He paused, and added, ''I want you to be my wife.''</p>
        <p>They still have the table, the chairs and the couch.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
