<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Appearances; Warm and Fuzzy</title>
    <meta content="MFOT13T" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Men's Fashions of The Times Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="56" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232976"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shaving and Shavers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norwich, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hair</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFDE1738F937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Appearances; Warm and Fuzzy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Norwich</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norwich, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Norwich article recalls rituals, history and art of shaving as he receives his first straight razor shave from a professional barber; drawing (M) (special section: Men's Fashions of The Times) (part 2 of 2-part section) (part 2 of 2-part section)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I guess I should be flattered. A lady I hadn't seen in several years kissed me on the cheek at a funeral recently, and exclaimed: ''You haven't aged! It's because you shave. I should start shaving.''</p>
        <p>Well, what could I say? Go with the grain?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I guess I should be flattered. A lady I hadn't seen in several years kissed me on the cheek at a funeral recently, and exclaimed: ''You haven't aged! It's because you shave. I should start shaving.''</p>
        <p>Well, what could I say? Go with the grain?</p>
        <p>Oddly enough, it wasn't the first time shaving reared its head as a topic in my fuzzy world that day. The following Saturday, I had an appointment at the Art of Shaving on Madison Avenue for a genuine barber's shave, straight razor and all; a new experience. When I told friends about my impending shave, several conversations ensued regarding our first scrape and, in particular, who taught us or who didn't, as the case might be. Half the friends couldn't remember their first. ''No one taught me anything,'' one friend said. ''I did it all myself.'' Another cursed his father for the inheritance of ingrown facial hairs aggravated by shaving. A gym trainer of my acquaintance could only remember the first time he shaved his chest and legs, not his face. Someone suggested I find a copy of ''The Big Shave,'' a short film by Martin Scorsese. It is the story of a man who shaves himself to death.</p>
        <p>More recently, Chronicle Books has published ''Shaving Lessons: A Memoir of Father and Son,'' by Kurt Chandler. The author is entering middle age as his son, Ben, is becoming a man, needing a shave, dating girls, riding motorcycles. ''The experience of shaving is ceremonial for a father and a son, at once a clumsy farce and a triumphant rite of passage,'' Chandler writes. ''It's an acknowledgment both of vanity and maturity.''</p>
        <p>Remember Floyd's Barbershop on ''The Andy Griffith Show''? At Floyd's Barbershop the good men of Mayberry convened for gossip and consolation while Floyd, played by the actor Howard McNear, dreamed of someday owning a two-chair shop.</p>
        <p>''Shaving used to be the only grooming ritual a man could indulge in without being considered feminine -- a shave and a shoeshine,'' said Dr. Steven Lamm, the Manhattan internist and author. ''Nowadays, men's grooming means facials, pedicures, manicures, the gym, massages, aroma-therapy. Shaving, by comparison, is less interesting. No one focuses on it.''</p>
        <p>Except at the Art of Shaving, where the goal is to bring ''passion and art to a daily routine.'' As far as the decor goes, it's Martha Stewart meets Wyatt Earp at a Christie's mahogany love fest. The front room of the Madison Avenue location features all kinds of shaving accouterment, such as lotions, potions, brushes and razors, for sale. The second room is home to two barbers, their chairs, hot foam dispensers and straight razors. A variety of barber services is available. I settled for the cheapest, a traditional shave, for $25. First came a hot towel wrap followed by a preshave oil and then the hot foam. I could not open my mouth for the foam, but the sleek man in the next chair somehow managed to get shaved with a straight razor and bark into his cell phone at the same time. Someone might consider this the essence of sophistication these days.</p>
        <p>Between applications of foam, I asked the barber if he remembered the first time he shaved. He didn't. He asked if I remembered, as he swamped my face with potions. I recalled that my father died when I was 9 and that, when I was 13, my mother asked the family lawyer to teach me how to shave. One Saturday morning, the lawyer called at our house and presented his case for shaving with an electric razor. That same morning he taught me how to tie a necktie. I had been relying on clip-on ties since my father died.</p>
        <p>I do not remember when I began shaving daily, or when I switched to using a razor and shaving cream. At some point, shaving became just another unexamined fact of life, like refrigeration and Coca-Cola.</p>
        <p>I kept my eyes closed during the shave because I don't cotton to razors. As with a lot of life, I haven't always liked looking. I thought about Sylvester Stallone and Rambo for some reason. I realized it was also Brad Pitt's wedding day and I wondered if he'd shaved for the occasion. (He had.) I wondered what the experience would have been like had it been Moby's CD playing rather than Billie Holiday's on the sound system. I wondered how many Art of Shaving products I would be suckered into buying. (Just one: the preshave oil formulated with ''botanical ingredients''; about $22.) I listened a lot to the man in the next chair. I gathered that he was a lawyer; he was barking into his cell phone about bastards and judges. I remembered my father's shaving brush, which my mother kept in the medicine cabinet until we moved houses, the year after he died.</p>
        <p>When he was finished, the barber told me I had a tough beard. But worse things have been said about me to my face.</p>
        <p>William Norwich is the entertaining editor of The New York Times Magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">William Norwich is the entertaining editor of The New York Times Magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
