<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Case of the Missing Childhood</title>
    <meta content="24GORRA2T" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232991"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gorra, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ishiguro, Kazuo</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">When We Were Orphans (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E2D81238F937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1535" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Case of the Missing Childhood</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michael Gorra</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gorra, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Gorra reviews book When We Were Orphans by Kazuo Ishiguro; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN WE WERE ORPHANS</p>
        <p>By Kazuo Ishiguro.</p>
        <p>336 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN WE WERE ORPHANS</p>
        <p>By Kazuo Ishiguro.</p>
        <p>336 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>In one of his many shrewd essays on the carpentry of fiction, Graham Greene suggested that a writer's ''technique is more than anything else a means of evading the personally impossible, of disguising a deficiency.'' A good novelist, Greene wrote, has an acute ''consciousness of what he cannot do,'' and that is something that ''on their march to oblivion the second-rate'' never quite manage to learn. I can't presume to say what it is that the British writer Kazuo Ishiguro knows he cannot do. But for all their varied settings -- prewar England and postwar Japan, the Mitteleuropa of ''The Unconsoled'' or the Shanghai of this slippery and rewarding new novel -- his books share in a body of technique, a set of rigorously observed narrative protocols. None of them takes place in contemporary England and each of them features a first-person narrator who is in some sense hiding from the past and its attendant emotions. Each narrator seems at first reliable, a figure whose weaknesses the novel only slowly uncovers. And each is defined by a prose caught between awkwardness and elegance, a language obsessively concerned with small details but somehow also impersonal.</p>
        <p>Yet despite this thematic and stylistic consistency, Ishiguro has with each novel become a stranger and less predictable writer; it is almost as if his career were going backward in everything except accomplishment. His first substantial audience came in 1989 with ''The Remains of the Day,'' an account, half P. G. Wodehouse and half Henry James, of a butler's inability to step outside his role. The novel well deserved its Booker Prize, even though it is perhaps too smoothly made, a craftsman's masterpiece whose perfection cries out to be noticed. I myself was unconvinced by Ishiguro's next novel, ''The Unconsoled,'' a 500-page faux-Kafka chronicle of embarrassment and interruption that some regard as a triumph; but I admired his willingness to abandon the tight control of his earlier work. Now, with ''When We Were Orphans,'' Ishiguro appears to have found his synthesis, not only in its expansive yet finely modulated narrative but also in the way it bends the hallucinatory world of its immediate predecessor toward the surface verisimilitude of the butler's story.</p>
        <p>As a new boy at his English boarding school, Ishiguro's narrator, Christopher Banks, quickly learns to reproduce his classmates' mannerisms with such expertise that ''not a single of my fellows noticed anything odd or thought to make fun.'' And so his life will go. Englishness -- in fact, human interaction of all kinds -- will remain for him a form of learned behavior, in which he compounds the simulacrum of a character from both the gestures of the people around him and his reading in ''The Wind in the Willows'' or Sherlock Holmes. Conan Doyle's fiction will even be of professional use to Banks, who soon establishes himself as a private detective in a London that resembles that of an English mystery of the 1920's and 30's.</p>
        <p>''It was the summer of 1923, the summer I came down from Cambridge, when despite my aunt's wishes that I return to Shropshire, I decided my future lay in the capital and took up a small flat at No. 14b Bedford Gardens in Kensington.'' That's the book's first sentence, and it's one no talented young novelist of Banks's own generation -- Greene himself, or Evelyn Waugh -- would have thought worth writing. But Banks doesn't have his contemporaries' cool eye, and that first sentence belongs instead to the world of John Buchan, to the guilty pleasures of such thrillers as ''The Thirty-Nine Steps.'' In Banks's London, the private eye has become a public figure, burdened by ''the scale of responsibility that befalls a detective with any sort of renown,'' and in constant danger not from criminals but from the ''fashionable circles'' that ''are forever trying to recruit'' him. Our hero modestly alludes to such triumphs as the ''Mannering case'' or the ''Trevor Richardson affair,'' allusions that, in proper Holmesian fashion, remain unencumbered by details. We never see him follow a case to what I am sure he would call its denouement.</p>
        <p>The knowingness with which Ishiguro employs this excessively bookish machinery might make ''When We Were Orphans'' seem like another deft postmodern exercise, a historical novel that's not concerned with the life of the past so much as with its literary assumptions. Yet Ishiguro stops just short of parody, and though he won't let his readers surrender to the genre, he doesn't condescend to it either. For by placing its cliches in Banks's mind, Ishiguro makes their slight pomposity an essential part of the man's character, a mark of both his limitations and of the psychic necessity that moves him.</p>
        <p>This isn't a detective novel, it only looks like one. As in his earlier books, Ishiguro's real concern is with his main character's unerring ability to miss the call of freedom, in the blindness that his sense of obligation imposes upon him. For Banks, those obligations stem from his childhood in the International Settlement of Shanghai, a childhood that ends with his parents' unexplained disappearance: first his father and then, not long after, his mother. The boy is sent ''home'' to an England he's never seen, but already his professional and personal future have been determined.</p>
        <p>The novel's first half, though nominally set in London, moves back and forth between Banks's present and his past in China with a dexterity that recalls Ford Madox Ford's classic novel ''The Good Soldier.'' One scene, one moment, slips effortlessly into its antecedent; an aside or an afterthought buds into revelation. And Ishiguro's handling of time isn't his only echo of Ford; this too is a novel about its narrator's self-deception. Banks has always believed that his mother's outspoken criticism of the opium trade was responsible for his parents' disappearance. Somebody must have wanted them out of the way. Yet the plot has never been cracked open, and Banks sees his early career as merely a preparation for his own attempt to take up the trail in crime-ridden and polyglot Shanghai. It is a trail that, in the novel's second half, involves him in the eruption of the Sino-Japanese War in 1937.</p>
        <p>On his arrival, Banks is taken by Shanghai's business community to be a kind of diplomatic fixer, as though the looming conflict were as easy to solve as a case of ''stolen jewels.'' This is a world in which people depend on the well-spoken consulting detective, in which Banks seems to be taken at his own valuation. Ishiguro has, however, suggested from the start that his narrator is rather an ''odd bird,'' and at this point begins to orchestrate an ever-growing dissonance between the detective's own judgments and those the book presents as ''normal.'' For Banks sees an equation between his parents' mysterious disappearance and the onset of the war, believing that his mother and father have remained trapped in Shanghai all these years, that their situation is the cause of the struggle. Such delusions of narrative coherence lend a sense of indeterminacy to the long climactic sequence, itself a catalog of literary borrowings, in which Banks proceeds through what looks like the worst of the fighting. Some moments here possess a genuine horror, and others -- a chance meeting with a person he believes to be a childhood friend -- seem both absolutely necessary and entirely implausible. Banks's quest is at once ludicrous and terrible, a journey in a landscape that seems to change along with his psychological state, but one that can nevertheless be plotted on a map of the actual battle.</p>
        <p>The Japanese-born Ishiguro has described his own style as one that ''suppresses meaning'' and has attributed his success to ''tackling on a thematic level the implications'' of this style, of the voice his narrators use to avoid self-knowledge. For Ishiguro, the orphans of his title are bereft of parents and yet also defined by them; they can never get over their loss because their parents are always already absent. The orphan's life is never fully his own, but seems instead as secondhand as the form of this novel itself, so brilliant in its tireless echoes of earlier texts. ''When We Were Orphans'' goes much farther than even ''The Remains of the Day'' in its examination of the roles we've had handed to us. It suggests that the butler's inability to get beyond his professional script may be endemic in a world in which we are all eventually orphans. Whatever the sense of Graham Greene's ''personally impossible'' that has so persistently drawn him to such material, I have little doubt that Kazuo Ishiguro will himself avoid the oblivion into which his narrators all finally sink. ''When We Were Orphans'' is his fullest achievement yet.</p>
        <p>Michael Gorra is the author of ''After Empire: Scott, Naipaul, Rushdie.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michael Gorra is the author of ''After Empire: Scott, Naipaul, Rushdie.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
