<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Golem Knows</title>
    <meta content="24KALFUST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kalfus, Ken</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chabon, Michael</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Amazing Adventures of Kavalier &amp; Clay, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E2D81238F937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Golem Knows</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ken Kalfus</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kalfus, Ken</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ken Kalfus reviews novel The Amazing Adventures of Kavalier &amp; Clay by Michael Chabon; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE AMAZING ADVENTURES</p>
        <p>OF KAVALIER &amp; CLAY</p>
        <p>By Michael Chabon.</p>
        <p>636 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $26.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE AMAZING ADVENTURES</p>
        <p>OF KAVALIER &amp; CLAY</p>
        <p>By Michael Chabon.</p>
        <p>636 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $26.95.</p>
        <p>Michael Chabon's third novel celebrates the golden age of the adventure comic book, the ''great, mad new American art form,'' which spanned the years between the late 1930's and the early 50's. It was a thriving time for popular culture, and Chabon vividly recalls the swing music, the pulp novels, ''Citizen Kane,'' the bars of midtown New York, the bar mitzvahs of midtown New York, men's bulky suits and the patriotic kitsch inspired by the Second World War. Although suffused with tragedy, ''The Amazing Adventures of Kavalier &amp; Clay'' proves to be a comic epic, generously optimistic about the human struggle for personal liberation.</p>
        <p>As in his acclaimed first novel, ''The Mysteries of Pittsburgh,'' Chabon paces his story with the throttle open. The novel's perversely rollicking first 65 pages, set in Prague during the Nazi occupation, introduce its two interrelated themes: escape and the mystery of the Prague golem, a legendary automaton-giant created from mud by a 16th-century rabbi. For the purposes of the novel, Chabon offers the conceit that the golem actually existed and was hidden in a Prague apartment house, where it awaits the day it will deliver the Jews from their enemies. As the noose tightens around the city's ghetto, 18-year-old Josef Kavalier makes a daring flight abroad in which he abets the removal of the golem before it can be found by German anthropologists and shipped to a Berlin museum. The inanimate figure is given a new hiding place in Lithuania, but it is recalled repeatedly in the novel, every time one character provides another with the passage to freedom.</p>
        <p>The next escape occurs upon Joe's arrival in America, when he immediately rescues his cousin Sammy Clay, ne Klayman, who has been ''sealed and hogtied inside the airtight vessel known as Brooklyn, New York.'' Seventeen-year-old Sammy, an admirer of Houdini and a would-be commercial artist, has been trying to draw his way out of the stock room of the Empire Novelty Company. Joe also has artistic ambitions. His drawings win Sammy's admiration, and a promise from him to ''get us into the big money,'' which Joe hopes will allow him to bring his family to America. On Joe's first day in New York, they approach Shelly Anapol, Sammy's finagling boss, who advertises his wares (whoopee cushions, amazing midget radios) on the back pages of Superman comic books. They propose that he publish his own comics and save the cost of advertising. For Anapol, the cousins invent and draw a new superhero, the Escapist, inspired by their fantasies of liberty and power.</p>
        <p>In naming one of the cousins Clay, Chabon gently points to the novel's mainspring: the character's intensely dependent, synergistic relationship. Sammy Clay, the Brooklyn golem, lies inanimate until Joe arrives (indeed, Joe first meets him in the bed they're forced to share). And soon Sammy, a protean storyteller, has vivified his friend and partner Joe, who turns into a kind of superhero himself, as if conjured from his cousin's imagination: he is agile, good-looking, suave and deft at drawing, language, dancing and sleight of hand.</p>
        <p>Sammy also appears to have conjured for Joe the flamboyant Rosa Luxemburg Saks, an avant-garde artist who inspires the cousins' girl hero, Luna Moth, a crime-fighter ''with the legs of Dolores Del Rio, black witchy hair and breasts each the size of her head. . . . The pair of furry antennae hung at playful angles, as if tasting the viewer's desire.'' Joe loves Rosa; Sammy loves her too, but without a touch of antennae-quivering desire. Sammy is slow to realize that he is what in those days was called, with nearly universal disgust, a ''fairy.'' Once the conclusive discovery takes place, in one of the novel's most moving scenes, his sexuality becomes the box from which the forlorn Sammy needs to escape.</p>
        <p>For mere mortals, the process of escape is often dependent on transformation, and New York, ''the city of freedom and swing,'' is the place in the 1940's where immigrants become Americans and orphans become superheroes. In Chabon's telling, prewar New York, freeing itself from the shackles of the Depression, abounds with raw, confident energy. Popular culture runs rampant, and the months before Pearl Harbor rank as ''a moment unsurpassed in this century for verve, romanticism, polish and a droll, tidy variety of soul.'' American big-band music spills off the novel's pages, in moving counterpoint to Joe's increasingly frustrated attempts to get his family out of occupied Europe.</p>
        <p>The cousins entertain few illusions about the trashiness of the comic book genre and its imitative heroes and stories, most of them ''Superman'' knockoffs. In their frustration with America's prewar neutrality, Kavalier and Clay time and again send the Escapist into battle against Hitler, thinly disguised as Attila Haxoff, whose Razis and Iron Chain cabal occupy Zothenia, Gothsylvania and Draconia. (Anapol, quite ridiculously, fears being sued.) The cousins know that, even as propaganda, the Escapist throws lame, errant punches against fascism. Furthermore, Joe sadly fears that his comic book superheroes represent a ''mirror-image fascism . . . assuring the creation of another generation of men who revered only strength and domination.''</p>
        <p>Despite the creative straitjackets within which the cartoonists worked, Chabon plausibly identifies in the successful comic book many of the qualities of genuine artistry: craftsmanship, provocative themes and the artist's personal investment. Its pioneers were men of great talent and ambition. Stan Lee, Spider-Man's esteemed progenitor, has a brief walk-on; Chabon makes warm references to Batman, Superman and all the other menschen dreamed up by young, mostly Jewish cartoonists. (Sammy muses: ''Superman, you don't think he's Jewish? Coming over from the old country, changing his name like that. Clark Kent, only a Jew would pick a name like that for himself.'') The era's comic book artists are depicted as working in a hotbed of graphic invention, flitting in and out of a bohemian apartment house in the West 20's that served as a pen-and-ink Tin Pan Alley.</p>
        <p>These halcyon days lasted barely a decade. Comic books suffered with other forms of popular culture in the big chill of the early 1950's, when the forces of reaction repressed and infantilized our music, films, politics and personal behavior. Estes Kefauver, the Tennessee senator who led an investigation of the comic book industry, also makes a cameo appearance in the novel, rather balefully, at the end.</p>
        <p>The cousins' adventures are leavened by buoyant good humor, wisecracks and shtick, but the story never loses its awareness of the tragedy that roils beneath the surface of our everyday lives and the lives of men in tights. Batman's parents were murdered. Superman's planet was destroyed as thoroughly as any shtetl. Some enormous heartbreak awaits the cousins as the Kavalier family in Prague succumbs to the Nazi terror and the world goes to war. Chabon reflects on the superhero and his precursor, the golem. ''It was the expression of a yearning that a few magic words and an artful hand might produce something -- one poor, dumb, powerful thing -- exempt from the crushing strictures, from the ills, cruelties and inevitable failures of the greater Creation.''</p>
        <p>According to some legends, a golem can be activated by saying the Hebrew word emet (''truth''), which was inscribed on its forehead. Despite Chabon's enthusiasm for narrative-linked-with-image, he always returns to the incantatory power of the word: ''Every universe, our own included, begins in conversation. Every golem in the history of the world, from Rabbi Hanina's delectable goat to the river-clay Frankenstein of Rabbi Judah Loew ben Bezalel, was summoned into existence through language, through murmuring, recital and kabbalistic chitchat -- was, literally, talked into life.'' Chabon talks his novel into life with passionate, expressive language and occasionally recherche words that have forced me to rechercher the dictionary myself, words such as ''omniveillant,'' ''ruelle,'' ''aetataureate'' and ''nudzhing'' -- well, O.K., ''nudzhing'' I knew. In ''The Amazing Adventures of Kavalier &amp; Clay,'' Chabon may romanticize the comic book, but it's unillustrated prose that he makes love to.</p>
        <p>Novels conventionally draw a good deal of their power from surprising plot turns. ''The Amazing Adventures of Kavalier &amp; Clay'' fulfills its quota of surprises, but most of its unexpectedness resides, comic-book-style, in its challenging situations, lushly written, in which you know beforehand that the heroes will prevail. It would make a nice comic book series -- the cousins square-jawed and ham-fisted -- but the depth of Chabon's thought, his sharp language, his inventiveness and his ambition make this a novel of towering achievement.</p>
        <p>Ken Kalfus is the author of two short story collections, ''Thirst'' and ''Pu-239 and Other Russian Fantasies.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ken Kalfus is the author of two short story collections, ''Thirst'' and ''Pu-239 and Other Russian Fantasies.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
