<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Born and Bred (And Banned) In Boston</title>
    <meta content="BOSTON$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/travel/BOSTON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lear, Martha Weinman</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E3DF173BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1160" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Born and Bred (And Banned) In Boston</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTHA WEINMAN LEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lear, Martha Weinman</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Martha Weinman Lear travel essay describes changes in Boston, Mass, which has become much less prudish and more urbane; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Boston I grew up in was a consummately dull town. If you wanted to get a snack after the show, you would have been better off in Philadelphia, because Boston closed up too early to put a baby to bed.</p>
        <p>Possibly it went back to the Pilgrims, and possibly it hadn't worked then, either. All I know is, when you and a date got out of the movies and it was too late to get a hamburger and too early to go home, the only thing left to do was go parking on Memorial Drive, by the sweetly flowing Charles, for a deliciously agonizing hour of Please and No.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Boston I grew up in was a consummately dull town. If you wanted to get a snack after the show, you would have been better off in Philadelphia, because Boston closed up too early to put a baby to bed.</p>
        <p>Possibly it went back to the Pilgrims, and possibly it hadn't worked then, either. All I know is, when you and a date got out of the movies and it was too late to get a hamburger and too early to go home, the only thing left to do was go parking on Memorial Drive, by the sweetly flowing Charles, for a deliciously agonizing hour of Please and No.</p>
        <p>There are cities that are geared to commerce and cities that are geared to fun. Boston was geared to the vigilant suppression of sin. Every few years, sin would be discovered in the motels along the Newburyport Turnpike, north of town, and there would be police raids and moral outcry and front-page stories every time. The sin squad -- elected, self-appointed, who knew? -- was forever trying to sweep sin out of Scollay Square, that meaty concentration of strip joints and fleabag establishments, where the burlesque queen Sally Rand awed the college boys by twirling her pastie tassels (I never saw it, but I heard sworn testimony) in opposite directions at once. And periodically, lava would flow in Harvard Yard over the issue of whether students should be allowed to entertain overnight guests in their rooms.</p>
        <p>J. Kenneth Galbraith got it just right  when he wrote to The Crimson in 1968:</p>
        <p>''I can't tell you how depressing it is to find Harvard having another discussion of those so-called parietal rules. . . . Those who (one hopes on the basis of some special competence) are fascinated by the question of whether undergraduates are improved or damaged by fornication can organize private discussion groups or, if married, talk about it with their wives.''</p>
        <p>If you remember the 50's, you remember the phrase ''banned in Boston.'' It was not empty. Being banned was just about the best thing that could happen to a bad book,  as with the immortal turkey ''Forever Amber.'' But in Boston, after all, anyone might think of banning a book. It took Locke-Ober, the most venerable restaurant in town, to think of banning women.</p>
        <p>Female persons could not set foot in the main dining room, which was the only room anyone wanted to sit in. There were just two occasions when this ban could be lifted. One was New Year's Eve. The other was -- ah, but surely you've guessed -- the day of the Harvard-Yale game, any year it was played at home.</p>
        <p>I dined there recently and asked our waiter, a 40-year employee, if he could remember when (''roughly when,'' I believe I said) the bars had come down.</p>
        <p>He: ''Aug. 21st, 1971.''</p>
        <p>I : ''Twenty-fifth?''</p>
        <p>He (to the saltshaker): ''First. First. Aug. 21st, 1971.''</p>
        <p>It was not much of a hotel town, either. There were (and are) the Copley Plaza and the Ritz-Carlton, grand dinosaurs. The Copley was where you went for proms, and the Ritz, across from the Public Garden, was where rich men from New York were rumored to bring their girlfriends, which I thought -- sex overlooking the swan boats! -- was the most romantic thing I'd ever heard. And the Parker House was where they had those rolls, and the dear dowager Somerset was where I got married, and I remember no other hotels.</p>
        <p>I left Boston in the mid-50's and was glad of it. When I went back, it was to see family. Now, alas, the family is mostly the dear departed, but I keep going back for pleasure.</p>
        <p>What was always wonderful -- those grand avenues -- Newbury, Marlborough, Commonwealth, Beacon, stretching eastward toward the Garden and Boston Common; Beacon Hill's Louisburg Square, as pretty an oval as any in London, where we children of assorted ethnic persuasions went on Christmas Eve to serenade the Brahmins, who stood at their windows giving us little Queen Mum salutes; Symphony Hall, the Isabella Stewart Gardiner, the Esplanade concerts, my beloved Filene's Basement, without which I would have gone to my proms in a potato sack -- all that is wonderful still. What is changed is the climate, that low-lying cloud of sanctimoniousness that used to hang over the city, blocking the sun.</p>
        <p>What caused the change? You cannot discount the influence of the young people who poured into Boston in the 60's and 70's, the hippies and Beats and Vietnam War protesters who came for 10 minutes and stayed for good, settled in, settled down, carved their initials into the gestalt of the city. And there was the development of the harborfront and the Fanueil Hall area, which not only brought in tourists but also gave Boston a sense of itself as a city that lives on water -- a sense that New York, for all its gorgeous waterfront potential, has yet to achieve.</p>
        <p>You can't say today that Boston swings. That is just not in its DNA. Call it a semi swing, which is a nice beat, actually -- urbane yet easy. There are the smart hotels, restaurants, all those pricey tourist treats, but more: downtown does not just live, it lives outdoors, where anyone can play for the price of a cappuccino.</p>
        <p>I stayed recently at a nifty Cambridge hotel, in a room with views of the Charles and the downtown skyline.</p>
        <p>IN the evening, my companion and I meandered down to the river, where couples strolled and lolled in creatively intertwined positions. We crossed Harvard Bridge and followed Commonwealth Avenue to Kenmore Square, gone vertiginously upmarket since my college days, and then turned into Newbury Street. For shopping, it could have been Madison Avenue or the Via Condotti or Rue St.-Honore, but for ambience it was one great big outdoor cafe.</p>
        <p>After dinner, and our nice chat with that Locke-Ober waiter, we went back to Harvard Square. It was pretty late. Students, troubadours, panhandlers shoulder to shoulder. Boites, bars, the requisite cheap Indian restaurants and expensive coffeehouses, mostly open.</p>
        <p>In one of them, an amiable young grinder of $13-a-pound coffee beans asked if I was a tourist. Yes and no, I said.</p>
        <p>And he? A native, he said, but longing to get out.</p>
        <p>Well, I said, I was born and bred here, schooled here, got out as fast as I could. But if I had to leave New York, which I hope I never have to do except in a box, Boston today is a place where I could live in contentment.</p>
        <p>Yes, the boy said wistfully, that's exactly the right word: contentment. Meaning, not excitement.</p>
        <p>Oh, kiddo. You should have seen it back when.</p>
        <p>MARTHA WEIMAN LEAR, the author of ''Heartsounds,''  is working on a novel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">MARTHA WEIMAN LEAR, the author of ''Heartsounds,''  is working on a novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
