<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peru's Deep-Rooted Spy System Could Outlast Promised Purge by Fujimori</title>
    <meta content="24PERU$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/world/24PERU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233429"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Peru</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Panama</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fujimori, Alberto K (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boehm, Peter (Amb)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Montesinos, Vladimiro</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salas, Federico (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Panama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Panama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5DB173AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1149" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peru's Deep-Rooted Spy System Could Outlast Promised Purge by Fujimori</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>LIMA, Peru, Sept. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Experts and diplomats say Peru's powerful National Intelligence Service has so thoroughly penetrated government and society that complete purge would be hard to carry out even if Pres Alberto K Fujimori intends to keep pledge; hold it can be dismantled only if very corrupt elite that controls blackmail and bribes loses power altogether; Canadian Amb Peter Boehm reportedly says intelligence service head Vladimiro Montesinos is out of job and could well leave Peru; Panama says it rejected request by Peruvian Prime Min Federico Salas to grant Montesino asylum (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hoping to blunt the crisis that threatens to drive him from office, President Alberto K. Fujimori has promised to dismantle the powerful National Intelligence Service. But the spy agency has so thoroughly penetrated Peruvian government and society, experts and diplomats say, that a complete purge of the security system will be hard to carry out even if Mr. Fujimori really means what he says.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't matter what name they have or what laws change, they are going to continue to do what they want,'' said Fernando Rospigliosi, author of ''The Art of Deceit'' and other books about Peruvian politics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hoping to blunt the crisis that threatens to drive him from office, President Alberto K. Fujimori has promised to dismantle the powerful National Intelligence Service. But the spy agency has so thoroughly penetrated Peruvian government and society, experts and diplomats say, that a complete purge of the security system will be hard to carry out even if Mr. Fujimori really means what he says.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't matter what name they have or what laws change, they are going to continue to do what they want,'' said Fernando Rospigliosi, author of ''The Art of Deceit'' and other books about Peruvian politics.</p>
        <p>''This is a personalized dictatorship, rather than an institutional one, in which a very corrupt elite has maintained control through blackmail and bribes. And only if they lose power altogether can you take the state security apparatus apart.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fujimori has been fighting to remain in power since the broadcast of a video late last week that shows his national security adviser, Vladimiro Montesinos, paying $15,000 to an opposition congressman, apparently to get him to go over to the government side. Mr. Fujimori's response was to call new elections in which, he said, he will not be a candidate and to announce the ''deactivation'' of the intelligence agency, which Mr. Montesinos controls.</p>
        <p>A week later, though, Mr. Montesinos's whereabouts and status continue to be a mystery. On Thursday, the armed forces announced their support for Mr. Fujimori, ending fears of a coup. But they conspicuously avoided any reference to Mr. Montesinos, who had a hand in the selection of most of the members of the military high command.</p>
        <p>Today, Reuters quoted the Canadian ambassador to the Organization of American States, Peter Boehm, as saying that Mr. Montesinos was out of the job and could well leave the country. And hours later, Panama said it had refused a request by Prime Minister Federico Salas of Peru to grant asylum to Mr. Montesinos.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fujimori has said that Mr. Montesinos still has a full security detail to protect him and that no criminal charges have yet been filed against him. On Friday the government sent a bill to Congress that would formally disband the spy agency within 15 days and also promised to announce Mr. Montesinos's dismissal by Monday.</p>
        <p>The location of an estimated 2,500 videotapes that were said to have been in Mr. Montesinos's possession -- an electronic dossier on leading political, business and military figures -- is also unclear. Susana Higuchi, Mr. Fujimori's former wife and now a member of the opposition group that released the tape showing Mr. Montesinos, said this week that the group had other tapes but hesitated to release them because ''the result could be chaos.''</p>
        <p>Even before the video scandal, the government, trying to deflect a barrage of criticism of Mr. Montesinos, had presented legislation that would create a new National Intelligence Center to oversee state security affairs. But independent experts dismissed the efforts as inadequate.</p>
        <p>''Montesinos has suffered a major blow and is not going to be able to regain the position of supreme power he had,'' said Carlos Tapia, a former lecturer at the Army Intelligence School. ''But the apparatus he created, though weakened, remains in place.''</p>
        <p>In fact, all three branches of the armed forces as well as the National Police have intelligence services. But they too have been implicated in human rights abuses and what Jose Miguel Vivanco, executive director of the Americas division of Human Rights Watch, called ''the whole system of bribes, threats, extortion, privileges and surveillance by which this government has preserved and accumulated power.''</p>
        <p>On paper, the National Intelligence Service, known by the Spanish acronym SIN, is meant to be a supervisory body, with fewer than 100 employees divided among three divisions: terrorism, counternarcotics and public security. But Mr. Tapia estimates that the agency's ranks have swelled to more than 1,200 people, not including several thousand informants in the military and the police.</p>
        <p>Mr. Montesinos and his associates have infiltrated other important institutions -- from the customs service and electoral commission to the news media and the court system. That makes it highly unlikely, experts maintain, that he will ever be held legally accountable for any actions that violated the law.</p>
        <p>''I believe there is a better chance to eventually prosecute Pinochet in Chile than Montesinos in Peru,'' Mr. Vivanco said, referring to Chile's former military strongman. ''I don't see an independent court or judge in a country where Montesinos, and not Fujimori, has been able to rule the country for seven years by firing and transferring judges, drafting legislation and changing constitutions.''</p>
        <p>The intelligence service was created during the authoritarian military government that ruled Peru in the 1970's, when there were fears that border disputes with Ecuador and Chile could turn to war. The complaints about its domestic activities accelerated after Mr. Fujimori was first elected in 1990 and set about crushing left-wing guerrilla groups like Shining Path, and they intensified after Mr. Fujimori shut down Congress and the courts in 1992.</p>
        <p>''Everyone closed their eyes because it was the most difficult period of the war against terrorism, so the attitude was that anything that works is fine,'' Mr. Tapia said. ''But then it became a monster.''</p>
        <p>Throughout the 1990's, Mr. Montesinos and the intelligence service also gave valuable help to the United States that resulted in a pronounced drop in coca cultivation and trafficking here. But experts contend that Mr. Montesinos has exhausted American patience, pointing to accusations of his involvement in a still-unresolved scandal over the sale of arms to Colombian guerrillas.</p>
        <p>''It's like a Noriega situation,'' Mr. Rospigliosi said, referring to the Panamanian strongman who after  years as an American ally was deposed. ''The C.I.A., which has been his support, has now let him fall.''</p>
        <p>But experts also say that any effort to reform the apparatus Mr. Montesinos created is certain to run into practical obstacles. This country, they argue, does not have the legal framework, institutional capacity or civilian expertise that would be required to bring the agency to heel.</p>
        <p>''The key to any dismantling of the intelligence service is to create mechanisms of control, and right now we don't have those,'' said Santiago Pedraglio, a political expert. ''Even if Montesinos and his people leave, no laws enable any entity outside of the executive to monitor and supervise the intelligence service by looking into its activities and accounts, and so what you are left with is an untouchable power.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
