<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chateau du Basement: The '00 Vintage</title>
    <meta content="24WINE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233121"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E1DF133BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1288" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chateau du Basement: The '00 Vintage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD G. GOLDBERG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOME winemaking is a well-worn first step toward a commercial career, as Kip Bedell, the North Fork merlot master on Long Island, can attest. The hobby that began in his Garden City basement in 1970, when he made five gallons from riesling grape concentrate, culminated in February in the $5 million sale of Bedell Cellars. Not a bad return.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Bedell remembers it, his first wine was terrible. ''I'll never forget it,'' he said. ''It was a challenge it was so bad. That's why I made more.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOME winemaking is a well-worn first step toward a commercial career, as Kip Bedell, the North Fork merlot master on Long Island, can attest. The hobby that began in his Garden City basement in 1970, when he made five gallons from riesling grape concentrate, culminated in February in the $5 million sale of Bedell Cellars. Not a bad return.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Bedell remembers it, his first wine was terrible. ''I'll never forget it,'' he said. ''It was a challenge it was so bad. That's why I made more.''</p>
        <p>These days, trainloads of crated refrigerated grapes from California are arriving in the Northeast, and Saturdays are especially frantic at fruit wholesalers and retailers as home winemakers converge.</p>
        <p>The odds are every serious home winemaker in Westchester County -- indeed, in the New York metropolitan region -- knows about the Prospero Equipment Corporation in Pleasantville.</p>
        <p>Since 1974, Prospero has provided amateurs and pros with grapes, equipment and hand-holding on technical problems like stuck fermentations. (Prospero is also a byword among commercial wineries for imported paraphernalia, and last year the newly established Prospero Winery made its first vintage with purchased grapes.)</p>
        <p>Gene Spaziani of Mystic, Conn., the principal author of the just-published paperback ''Home Winemaker's Companion'' (Storey Books, Pownal, Vt., $18.95), has driven to Prospero to pick up grapes.</p>
        <p>So has Frank C. Aquilino of West Keansburg, N.J., in Monmouth County, a home winemaker for 13 years. (He has also gone to Mudd Vineyard in Southold, on Long Island.) If necessary he would probably fly to the moon to buy muscat ottonel to make ice wine, a dessert treat.</p>
        <p>It's doubtless no surprise that while many nationalities and ethnic groups foster home winemakers, numerically Italians tend to be numero uno. The Old Country, top to bottom, is one big vineyard.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spaziani, 66, a retired professor of hospitality management who  has been a home winemaker for 40 years, tells an archetypal story: ''We lived with my grandparents as a child in West Haven. My grandfather made wine every fall. It was part of  the family way of life, like tending a garden. There were no mysteries about wine. We accepted it as a beverage or a food.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, immigrants made wine by instinct, habit and rustic handed-down techniques. That meant that ''my grandfather was drinking vinegar by March,'' Mr. Spaziani said. Today, amateurs subscribe to magazines like WineMaker, a quarterly, that emphasize science, technology and sanitation: sterilize those bottles; hose down those re-re-reused oak barrels; use sulfur dioxide to kill bacteria and wild yeasts.</p>
        <p>Such caveats flow through the programs and literature of the American Wine Society, a national organization in Rochester devoted to education and appreciation. As a past president, Mr. Spaziani dispenses such advice in the community-college classes he teaches.</p>
        <p>''Chemistry scares guys,'' Mr. Spaziani said. ''They are embarrassed because they never had chemistry classes. But wine chemistry isn't rocket science. You just follow the instructions.'' Women, he said, tend to be more successful than men at home winemaking, but he could not explain why.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spaziani, who calls himself ''a blue-collar writer for the guy who doesn't know a lot,'' is also a wine columnist for three Connecticut newspapers: The Journal Inquirer in Manchester, The Middletown Press and The Record-Journal in Meriden.</p>
        <p>His colleague Mr. Aquilino, the American Wine Society's regional vice president in New Jersey, seems no less committed. ''I've made ice wine in '94, '95, '96, '97, '98,'' he said. ''It's won four gold medals and one silver. It's been an awesome wine. It's like an elixir. I didn't make this wine. It was made from above. I was just an instrument.''</p>
        <p>''I up the production every year,'' he continued. ''I give a lot away. I have more new friends every year. In '98, I made 200 half bottles. I always make one three-liter bottle and put it away for my two daughters. It's their legacy.''</p>
        <p>For six years, Mr. Aquilino has nursed 10 vines of a native American red grape called Norton (it's big in Missouri and Arkansas) to teach himself about grape-growing, ''what happens when you prune or use pesticide, for example.''</p>
        <p>He has made a Bordeaux blend of cabernet sauvignon, merlot, cabernet franc and malbec; a viognier; a chardonnay and chardonnay-based blanc de blancs sparkling wine; and a muscat-based sparkling wine that resembled Asti spumante. ''I have a nice shiraz going now,'' he said. ''Next year, we may try a sherry.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Aquilino, an air-conditioning and ventilating technician, became hooked on winemaking when a co-worker was about to buy grapes.  ''Oh, get me a bunch, too,'' he said.</p>
        <p>'' 'You don't understand,' '' came the reply. '' 'I'm getting 20 cases.' ''</p>
        <p>''Something excited me about winemaking,'' Mr. Aquilino said. ''It was like a light went on.''</p>
        <p>''I am extremely scientific, up-to-date, very high-tech, and that's where I differ from the old Italian winemakers,'' he said. ''I go to market with a refractometer, to check the sugar content. It's sugar that determines the amount of alcohol. I don't want grapes too sweet. I go around checking, and soon these old guys are following me, three, four, five. I'm like the Pied Piper.''</p>
        <p>When the California grapes arrive, ''I tell my boss I won't be in the next day if I buy them,'' Mr. Aquilino said, ''and that's the way it is.''</p>
        <p>Doesn't that endanger his job? ''No, I give the boss a bottle at Christmas, and he forgets it all.''</p>
        <p>Because he can draw a union pension, Mr. Aquilino, 48, is thinking about retiring early and becoming a full-time winemaker. ''I am past amateur,'' he said. ''I want to become commercial. It's up to God, if he says yes or no. Every winemaker dreams of opening a winery. We went to Virginia a few years ago. The farmers wanted too much for land. But it's on my back burner.''</p>
        <p>Commercial winemaking is on Kurt Eckert's front burner. He is the wine director at Jean-Georges Vongerichten's restaurants in Manhattan and a wine consultant for the boss's restaurants in other cities.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Eckert does not literally make wine at home, he has been receiving some training at at Wolffer Estate in Sagaponack on the South Fork of Long Island, under the watchful eye of Roman Roth, its winemaker.</p>
        <p>In 1998, Mr. Eckert began with 23 cases of chardonnay from grapes bought from Wolffer. He sold much of the output to Vongerichten restaurants as well as the Gramercy Tavern, Aureole, Judson Grill and Union Square Cafe. (If wine doesn't make the grade, personal connections don't usually compensate.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Eckert's '99 chardonnay, from Wolffer, was bottled the other day, and a '99 red blend -- cabernet sauvignon plus some merlot -- from grapes bought from the Mudd Vineyard in Southold is being made with Larry Perrine at Channing Daughters in Bridgehampton.</p>
        <p>''This offers an opportunity to pick two brains,'' Mr. Eckert said. ''I am making the wines in a natural style without cosmetic adjustments.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Eckert, who has been in the restaurant business for 20 years, said: ''I have tasted a lot of wine daily and visited lots of wineries in the United States and around the world. I pay attention to how it matches up, and doesn't match up, with food. Now, managing the raw material and following it through to the finished product has been wonderful.'' Although Mr. Eckert doesn't yet own the real thing, he plans to go public soon with a virtual vineyard on the Web: www.crucellars.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
