<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clemens Limps Off, But Yanks Finally Win</title>
    <meta content="24YANK$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/sports/24YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D9173AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1044" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clemens Limps Off, But Yanks Finally Win</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Roger Clemens limped off the field at the end of the fifth inning, the back of his bruised right thigh pounding from the ground ball he absorbed there in the third, he had given up seven runs and lost a 5-1 lead. The crushing blow was an upper-deck grand slam that he yielded to Billy McMillon, the Detroit Tigers' best minor-league player this year.</p>
        <p>The Yankees, desperate for their first victory in seven games, were deflated. But this time, they were not done.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Roger Clemens limped off the field at the end of the fifth inning, the back of his bruised right thigh pounding from the ground ball he absorbed there in the third, he had given up seven runs and lost a 5-1 lead. The crushing blow was an upper-deck grand slam that he yielded to Billy McMillon, the Detroit Tigers' best minor-league player this year.</p>
        <p>The Yankees, desperate for their first victory in seven games, were deflated. But this time, they were not done.</p>
        <p>''This team has come back time and time again,'' Yankee shortstop Derek Jeter said. ''We haven't been doing it recently, but we know we're capable of it.''</p>
        <p>He certainly proved that yesterday. With the Yankees trailing by 7-6 in the sixth inning, Jeter lifted a three-run home run just over the right-field wall to give the Yankees a lead they never relinquished. When David Justice delivered another three-run drive in the eighth inning, his second home run of the game, the Yankees had secured a 13-8 comeback triumph.</p>
        <p>''You don't want it this way,'' Manager Joe Torre said of the Yankees' struggle in snapping their longest losing streak in three years. ''It would have been nice if Roger could coast with a 5-1 lead. But when you digest it all, it did us more good this way. We didn't back off. It was a big game for us.''</p>
        <p>Jeff Nelson (8-3) relieved Clemens and got the victory. Mariano Rivera, who was fresh after resting for eight games, came in during the eighth inning, one inning earlier than usual, and finished the game to secure his 35th save of the season.</p>
        <p>With Toronto defeating Tampa Bay, the Yankees reduced their clinching number for winning the American League East title to five.</p>
        <p>''It means that much more when you have to work for it,'' said Paul O'Neill, who collected his 100th run batted in for the fourth straight season by singling in two runs in the fourth inning.</p>
        <p>Everyone in the starting lineup got a hit, and the 40,029 slicker-clad fans responded with roaring instead of booing. The Yankees blasted 4 home runs and had 18 hits, the first time they had double digits in that category since their previous victory, on Sept. 16.</p>
        <p>Tino Martinez broke out of his 0-for-28 slump, Scott Brosius hit two singles after going 2 for 20, Jorge Posada hit his 27th home run, his first since the losing streak began, and Justice's second homer was his 40th, which tied his career high. But, with four hits, Jeter had the biggest afternoon of anyone. He now has eight hits in his last 10 at-bats.</p>
        <p>''Any time the situation gets hot and sticky, he finds a way to lead us,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Jeter agreed that this victory was a relief. ''It was huge,'' he said. ''We've played like the Bad News Bears for a while. It's embarrassing.''</p>
        <p>But as much as the team sighed relief, there was also some concern after the victory about Clemens, who is penciled in to start the first game of the division series for the Yankees.</p>
        <p>''I'm not feeling great right now, but we won the game and that's the most important thing,'' Clemens said, adding that he could already see bleeding inside the back of his leg.</p>
        <p>He said he hoped not to miss his next start, and did not cite the shot from Brian Ausmus as the cause of his shaky fifth inning.</p>
        <p>Clemens began the third inning by giving up a leadoff home run to Damion Easley. Ausmus then grounded a ball that hit Clemens, who grabbed it and threw to first for the out. After Torre and the team trainer inspected Clemens on the mound, he retired the next two batters to get out of the inning.</p>
        <p>But his leg stiffened while the Yankees scored three runs in the fourth, Jeter keeping alive a rally with a run-scoring single and O'Neill collecting two R.B.I. Just as Denny Neagle unraveled the night before for the Yankees, Clemens teetered yesterday in his fifth inning.</p>
        <p>Clemens gave up a leadoff single to first baseman Hal Morris, then followed with a walk to Easley. Ausmus doubled, scoring Morris.</p>
        <p>For Clemens, it got worse. He hit Jose Macias before walking Juan Encarnacion, which brought in another run, making the score 5-3. With the bases loaded, McMillon, the Tigers' minor-league player of the year, blistered a breaking ball over the middle of the plate to the upper deck in right field, and Yankee Stadium fell into a stunned silence.</p>
        <p>''We were down, 7-5, but it was only two runs, at home, and it was early,'' Torre said. Harkening to the Yankees who have won three World Series titles in the last four seasons, the team regrouped for a comeback.</p>
        <p>In the sixth inning, Luis Sojo, who was playing second base, singled to center field off the Tigers' right-handed reliever Willie Blair (10-5). Brosius followed with his second hit of the game before Chuck Knoblauch, the designated hitter, fisted a singled to short center that scored Sojo.</p>
        <p>Jeter's three-run shot put the Yankees ahead by 9-7, and saved Clemens from his second straight loss.</p>
        <p>Nelson, who had come on to start the sixth inning, allowed a leadoff single in the seventh inning to Encarnacion.</p>
        <p>Mike Stanton relieved him, and while he gave up two singles that scored a run, 9-8 would be as close as Detroit would get.</p>
        <p>Bernie Williams blooped a single in the eighth inning to score one run and Justice hit his three-run home run for a 13-8 lead. When Rivera came on for his second inning, he had a five-run cushion. ''It was good to be out there, seeing this team fight for a win,'' Rivera said.</p>
        <p>Torre had this perspective: ''This game today starts us on something positive, and now it's up to us to build on it and help us clinch the pennant.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
