<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>End-of-the-Season Dishes Made Easy With Corn and Tomatoes</title>
    <meta content="CNFOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E1DD163AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>End-of-the-Season Dishes Made Easy With Corn and Tomatoes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE calendar may say autumn, but summer lingers at produce stands. There's still time to enjoy fresh sweet corn and ripe tomatoes. And with them, the pungent seasoning provided by fresh cilantro is always welcome.</p>
        <p>Each of the following recipes calls for corn kernels stripped from the cob, along with cilantro and ripe tomatoes. Once the local season is finished for these treasures, the recipes can still be made using kernels stripped from corn that has come from the South and ripe plum tomatoes from California, which are often available until winter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE calendar may say autumn, but summer lingers at produce stands. There's still time to enjoy fresh sweet corn and ripe tomatoes. And with them, the pungent seasoning provided by fresh cilantro is always welcome.</p>
        <p>Each of the following recipes calls for corn kernels stripped from the cob, along with cilantro and ripe tomatoes. Once the local season is finished for these treasures, the recipes can still be made using kernels stripped from corn that has come from the South and ripe plum tomatoes from California, which are often available until winter.</p>
        <p>In one recipe, the trio of ingredients is married with cheese and chilies to fill wedges of warm quesadilla. Another adds corn and cilantro to the typically Tuscan bread soup, pappa al pomodoro. A verdant cold soup tasting richly of corn is served over its diced tomato garnish. Once the weather makes cold soup unsuitable, you can use a cup of cream instead of the yogurt, spike it with some lemon juice and even substitute diced cooked shrimp or lobster for the tomato to make an invitingly, rich bisque-like hot soup.</p>
        <p>Quesadillas With Corn, Cilantro and Tomatoes  Total time: 30 minutes</p>
        <p>1tablespoon extra-virgin olive oil  1jalapeno, seeded and slivered  Kernels from 3 ears fresh corn  68-inch flour tortillas  4ounces soft Monterey Jack or gruyere cheese, shredded  1large ripe tomato, cored and sliced thin</p>
        <p>1/4cup chopped cilantro leaves.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 350 degrees. Cover a baking sheet with foil.</p>
        <p>2. Heat oil in skillet. Add jalapeno and corn and saute three minutes. Remove from heat.</p>
        <p>3. Spread tortillas on work surface. Divide cheese among them, spreading it on half of each tortilla. Spoon corn mixture on cheese, top with tomato slices and sprinkle with cilantro. Fold each tortilla in half.</p>
        <p>4. Put in oven and bake five to seven minutes, just until cheese melts. Cut each tortilla in four pieces and serve as hors d'oeuvres.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 to 8 servings.</p>
        <p>Bread Soup With Corn, Tomatoes and Cilantro  Total time: 30 minutes</p>
        <p>3tablespoons extra-virgin olive oil  2cloves garlic, minced  1jalapeno, seeded and minced  Kernels from 3 ears fresh corn  3large ripe tomatoes, peeled, seeded and chopped  1tablespoon tomato paste, preferably sun dried  3cups diced crustless stale French bread  Salt and freshly ground black pepper to taste  2tablespoons minced cilantro leaves</p>
        <p>1/4cup freshly grated Parmesan.</p>
        <p>1. Heat two tablespoons oil in large saute pan. Add garlic and jalapeno and saute until soft. Add corn and tomatoes and cook over medium-low heat until tomatoes become very juicy, about five minutes. Remove from heat and stir in tomato paste.</p>
        <p>2. Stir in bread and allow to sit five minutes, until bread starts to soak up mixture. Stir several times. Season to taste with salt and pepper. Stir in remaining olive oil.</p>
        <p>3. Serve the soup either warm or at room temperature, sprinkled with cilantro. Pass cheese alongside when serving.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 to 6 servings.</p>
        <p>Corn and Cilantro Soup  Total time: 45 minutes</p>
        <p>2tablespoons extra-virgin olive oil  1medium onion, chopped  1tablespoon minced fresh ginger  1hot green chili, seeded and minced, or to taste  Kernels from 4 ears fresh corn  1large bunch cilantro, bottom inch of stems removed  1 1/2cups plain fat-free yogurt  Salt and freshly ground black pepper to taste  6ripe plum tomatoes finely chopped.</p>
        <p>1. Heat oil in three-quart saucepan. Add onion, ginger and chili and saute until softened. Add corn, saute three minutes, then add cilantro. When cilantro starts to wilt, add a cup and a half of water, bring just to a simmer and remove from heat.</p>
        <p>2. Transfer to blender and process until finely pureed. Transfer to large stainless steel bowl. Add a cup of ice water. Whisk in yogurt and season to taste with salt and pepper. If soup is not cold enough, refrigerate until ready to serve, or set mixing bowl in large bowl of ice water and allow to cool about 20 minutes, stirring occasionally.</p>
        <p>3. To serve, put a mound of tomato in the center of each soup plate and spoon soup over it.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
