<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>I Think, Therefore I'll Garden</title>
    <meta content="24CUT.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/living/24CUT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233292"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raver, Anne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4D81E3BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>I Think, Therefore I'll Garden</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raver, Anne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anne Raver describes gardens on her farm in Maryland; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FALL has always felt like the beginning of the garden. That first crisp day, when the sumac leaves start to redden, I walk around the farm in Maryland looking at what worked and didn't work and my head starts filling with pictures again. Anything seems possible.</p>
        <p>But this year, I'm not running to the catalogs. I've stopped ordering things for a while -- to let the farm speak. I see how flimsy some of my plans are, so I am just standing back, trying to divine what really needs doing, or more to the point, what I can do. I leave the rest alone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FALL has always felt like the beginning of the garden. That first crisp day, when the sumac leaves start to redden, I walk around the farm in Maryland looking at what worked and didn't work and my head starts filling with pictures again. Anything seems possible.</p>
        <p>But this year, I'm not running to the catalogs. I've stopped ordering things for a while -- to let the farm speak. I see how flimsy some of my plans are, so I am just standing back, trying to divine what really needs doing, or more to the point, what I can do. I leave the rest alone.</p>
        <p>It is very restful. It leaves time to sit in the old barnyard in the morning and watch the light play along the stone wall. And mentally tag which trees should be weeded out of the little grove of Norway maples and locusts that seeded themselves years ago on the south side of the wall. All the maples should go, I think. Then the locusts will stand straight and tall, and more light will pour through their filigreed leaves.</p>
        <p>We never got around to burning the brush pile, which sits on the edge of a cornfield. Two years now, and we haven't got a fire permit. And a fine black walnut and a weeping willow have taken hold there.</p>
        <p>''I think we'll have to move the brush pile,'' I say to Bernie Eckenrode, who keeps things running around here. He gives me his that's-easy-for-you-to-say look. But just try to start a black walnut tree yourself. It's next to impossible.</p>
        <p>To tell the truth, while I am still addicted to Gardening, capital G, I'm fascinated by what happens when I don't. Three years ago, a hurricane took out the top of an old cedar tree near the barn. It looked terrible for a while, like a robust person taken off at the waist. But now, it seems to have adjusted itself, and trudging past it the other day, I realized that it would look beautiful with a climbing rose winding through its dangling branches. In a fit of lust, I'd ordered 18 old roses from Heirloom Roses, in St. Paul, Ore., fired with the image of them growing against the wall of the old barnyard. Only to find, as I watched the light against that wall this spring, there isn't enough light for roses. So I stuck the bare-root plants in a vegetable patch and waited. One by one, they are suggesting places for themselves. (Except a single pink named Complicata, which died of complications.)</p>
        <p>I'm thinking Graham Thomas, my yellow climber, would look good climbing up the sturdy metal pergola Bernie made me a few years ago when I mentioned it would be nice to have a rose arbor. Its near industrial size was a little incongruous even in the eclectic mix of plants I have collected in the old chicken yard -- our potager, we joke -- so it was exiled to the edge of the vegetable patch, where it stands on the brow of the hill like our version of the Gateway Arch in St. Louis.</p>
        <p>I've grown morning glories on it, and purple hyacinth beans. But this summer, a trumpet vine seeded itself on one post. So its fiery orange blossoms will tumble over one side, with sunny Sir Graham climbing up the other.</p>
        <p>I kept my mouth shut this summer when Bernie mowed right over a woody stem of a hardy hibiscus I was given years ago on Fire Island by a gardener called Mrs. Moore. I call it Mrs. Moore's plant, and every year in late August, its gaudy red blossoms open wide, as if surprised they're in Maryland and not in the tropics. I was upset when I discovered its little stump, poking through the fresh grass clippings. But Bernie would have felt worse than I, and we try to keep his spirits up. If he ever left, this old house might fall down. So I just put a few rocks around the stump, and waited. By midsummer, it had sprouted five graceful shoots, all blooming now, in a shower of red.</p>
        <p>The brambles we never got around to chopping down bore the most delicious, fattest blackberries I've ever eaten.</p>
        <p>The wet weather made a bust of my tomato patch. I allowed them to ramble on a thick bed of straw, the way my cousin Janice does, but this summer's rainy, cool weather has kept the straw too wet, so my big green Brandywines are turning to mush. Slugs are getting fat on them.</p>
        <p>The rabbits ate the beans, because I didn't put up a fence. I left rabbit duty to our dog, Red, the stray from Brooklyn, but she only goes after groundhogs. So last week, as I planted a cover crop -- scattering the seeds of red clover and hairy vetch over the freshly raked soil -- I pictured my fence. Sturdy wire sunk a foot deep, reinforced with a split-rail fence. We have plenty of locust trees. The trick is finding someone who still knows how to split them -- to make a farm fence that lasts.</p>
        <p>That's what interests me these days. Trees. Fences. Things that fit the landscape, as if they've always been here. Except the banana plant. And the Gateway Arch. But that's what makes it my garden.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
