<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>East of Suez</title>
    <meta content="24RIDINGT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riding, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buruma, Ian</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Missionary and the Libertine, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1D81238F937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>East of Suez</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Riding</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Riding reviews book The Missionary and the Libertine: Love and War in East and West by Ian Buruma (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE MISSIONARY</p>
        <p>AND THE LIBERTINE</p>
        <p>Love and War in East and West.</p>
        <p>By Ian Buruma.</p>
        <p>319 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $25.95</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE MISSIONARY</p>
        <p>AND THE LIBERTINE</p>
        <p>Love and War in East and West.</p>
        <p>By Ian Buruma.</p>
        <p>319 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $25.95</p>
        <p>Latin America is a product of Spain and Portugal, Africa still carries the marks of British and French rule, but Asia? It too was colonized of course -- India by Britain, Indonesia by the Netherlands, Indochina by France, the Philippines by Spain and the United States -- yet somehow it never quite surrendered. The colonizers, however, never quite caught on. They saw the Orient as peopled by exotic natives unconcerned with progress, ruled by ritual, in need of Christian enlightenment. When the natives behaved badly, they were also deemed untrustworthy. But these stereotypes hardly prepared the West for, say, the attack on Pearl Harbor, the fight against colonialism, the Japanese economic miracle and the rise of the Asian ''tigers.''</p>
        <p>Ian Buruma belongs to a long tradition of Westerners who have tried to explain the East to the West. He is also better equipped than most. Born in the Netherlands in 1951 to a British mother and a Dutch father, educated in the Netherlands and Japan, fluent in Japanese, he has spent much of his adult life living, studying and traveling in Asia and a good many of those years writing books (''God's Dust,''+ ''A Japanese Mirror,'' ''Behind the Mask'') and articles. His instructive and entertaining new book, ''The Missionary and the Libertine,'' a collection of 25 essays published in The New York Review of Books between 1985 and 1995, reinforces his reputation as a modern Orientalist with an original voice.</p>
        <p>Buruma's approach is neither that of foreign correspondent nor that of travel writer: he writes about eight different countries, but rarely do we feel in any particular place. Rather, as if wary of ''truth,'' he focuses on perceptions, notably those of Asian intellectuals and politicians about both East and West and those of American and European writers and politicians about Asia. These he then filters through his own experiences and pops out as judgments. The result is a complex mirror game, not least because the essays are not published chronologically, but also because, courageously, Buruma has not edited out views he no longer holds. ''I did not want,'' he says, ''to kill the freshness of impressions and observations with the questionable wisdom of hindsight.''</p>
        <p>His basic premise, though, remains valid: that the West's view of the East is still largely shaped by stereotypes, that Asia is not a monolithic bloc beholden to Confucianism, that the East has indeed been profoundly influenced by the West, that Asia is no longer that different. To this he adds an important element: that Asian politicians and intellectuals who promote the creed of ''Asian values'' -- that the East cannot be measured by Western yardsticks -- are cynically defending their own power and privileges.</p>
        <p>Buruma starts by looking at the West's embrace of Asia's cliches about itself through the larger-than-life figure of Yukio Mishima, perhaps Japan's most widely known modern writer, who committed ritual suicide by sword in 1970. For Buruma, Mishima was a phony, ''a very gifted buffoon'' who claimed to personify the samurai spirit when he was in fact quite at home with Western culture. Buruma's real targets, though, are Westerners -- he mentions Marguerite Yourcenar and the documentary filmmaker Paul Schrader -- who took ''Mishima's mythology at face value.''</p>
        <p>In politics too, Buruma adds, Japan was good at mythmaking. It was of course never colonized but after World War II it was occupied by the United States and remodeled as a Western democracy. Did this work? Hardly, Buruma contends. In practice, concerned more with fighting Communism, the United States was quite happy with a political system run for and by ''an elite of bureaucrats, corporations and conservative politicians.'' The joke was that this elite then used the defense of ''Japanese harmony'' to justify protectionist trade barriers. Discussing ''Made in Japan,'' the autobiography of Akio Morita, the founder of Sony, Buruma says ''his cultural explanations for Japanese business success are not only self-serving and disingenuous, but false.'' The real losers, he notes, were Japanese consumers, who paid high prices for local goods, and Japanese citizens, who lived in a disguised dictatorship.</p>
        <p>One bizarre consequence of political control, Buruma argues in an essay inspired by Nagisa Oshima, director of the celebrated art-porno film, ''In the Realm of the Senses,'' was an explosion of sex and violence in entertainment. He dismisses the commonplace that this was born of the lack of religious constraints. (Japan's first boy-girl screen kiss dates only to 1946, ordered by American censors as part of the country's postwar democratic education!) Instead, he interprets unrestrained sex and violence in movies and comic books as a reaction to political constraints, with ''assaults on social taboos'' the only way to rebel. ''From student activism to pornography to show-business dandy,'' he writes of Oshima and other radicals, ''not a bad summing up of postwar Japanese culture.''</p>
        <p>To explore what he considers American misreading of Japan, Buruma looks at others who have been doing the explaining. Edwin O. Reischauer, a scholar and author born in Japan to a missionary family, who served as the United States ambassador to Tokyo from 1961 to 1966, ''could be counted upon to explain Japanese cultural sensitivities to the unthinking and unfeeling barbarians.'' Once Japan was perceived as an economic threat, a response came from so-called revisionists ''who maintain that the Japanese (or East-Asian) version of capitalism is fundamentally different from the Anglo-American system.'' This set the stage for Michael Crichton's thriller ''Rising Sun,'' in which ''they'' -- the Japanese -- are ''sinister forces'' bent on manipulating ''sincere, decent folk.''</p>
        <p>Of course, all that trendy paranoia about American decadence and Asian tigers looks a tad dated today: the United States is booming, Japan is in a deep slump and the Asian bubble burst in 1997. Buruma may not have predicted this, but he certainly saw through the ''Asian values'' line put out by Singapore, Malaysia, Indonesia, China and others as a defense against Western human rights complaints. Lee Kuan Yew, Singapore's longtime prime minister and now senior minister, was the most articulate spokesman for Asian values simply because he ran the most efficient authoritarian state. The twist, Buruma writes, is that the anti-Western diatribes of Lee and Prime Minister Mahathir Mohamad of Malaysia are ''not so distant echoes of their British colonial education.'' He adds: ''Lee and Mahathir still claim to uphold the old standards, even as the West goes to the dogs.''</p>
        <p>The East-West mirror game continues as Buruma ventures into Pakistan (and the rise to power of the Radcliffe and Oxford-educated Benazir Bhutto), the Philippines (with Corazon Aquino's election representing the return to power of the elite installed by the United States in 1946) and Hong Kong (where already in 1990 British-educated Chinese were alarmed over China's scheduled takeover). But perhaps nowhere do echoes of empire reverberate more than in India, albeit less than in 1951, Buruma recalls, when Nirad C. Chaudhuri dedicated his celebrated ''Autobiography of an Unknown Indian'': ''To the memory of the British Empire in India, which conferred subjecthood on us but withheld citizenship, to which yet every one of us threw out the challenge Civis Britannicus sum, because all that was good and living within us was made, shaped and quickened by the same British rule.''</p>
        <p>Buruma's intellectual guides to India are the Romanian writer Mircea Eliade and his autobiographical love story, ''Bengal Nights''; the great Indian movie director Satyajit Ray, perhaps the last Bengali renaissance man; that perennial outsider V. S. Naipaul, whose grandfather left (British) India for (British) Trinidad around the turn of the century and who himself opted to live in Britain; and Chaudhuri, who moved to Britain in 1970 and dedicated himself to ''castigating his former masters for their crudeness, ignorance and illiterate philistinism.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Buruma observes, it was evidently some consolation for Indian intellectuals to know they were culturally superior to their rulers: ''So there was Chaudhuri, lover of Mozart, Pascal, Burke, Wordsworth and Dante, ruled by Englishmen whose tastes were adequately served by Kipling's 'Barrack-Room Ballads.'+'' Chaudhuri himself redefined the ''White Man's Burden'' even more colorfully. ''Any exhibition of knowledge of European life, civilization or history,'' he once wrote, ''drove the British community in India to make the gesture which peasant boys in India make at a passing train. They expose themselves and wave their hips.''</p>
        <p>Alan Riding is the European cultural correspondent of The Times, based in Paris.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Alan Riding is the European cultural correspondent of The Times, based in Paris.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
