<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Watch Emeril, but Learn to Cook in a Class</title>
    <meta content="24COOK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233195"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martone, David P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caparulo, Vicki</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walters, Carole</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'agnese, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E2D6103BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1800" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Watch Emeril, but Learn to Cook in a Class</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH D'AGNESE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">D'agnese, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on cooking classes taught by Vicki Caparulo, Carole Walters and others around New Jersey; list; photo (Special Issue: Entertainment) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VICKI CAPARULO, a petite chef with close-cropped hair and the images of a fried egg and slice of bacon painted on the tips of her clogs, stood at the counter, ready to begin. She was about to make a meal for an audience of 18, including me, expounding on the theme ''No-Cook Summer Sauces for Pasta.'' Before the night was over, students in the cooking class would learn seven different sauces, from a puttanesca to a citrusy lemon-pepper shrimp sauce.</p>
        <p>But before Mrs. Caparulo reached for a single plum tomato, David P. Martone, her host, welcomed the students who had paid $49 each for this night of cookery in the back room of Classic Thyme, the upscale cookware shop in Westfield that Mr. Martone operates with his partner, Sheila Turteltaub.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VICKI CAPARULO, a petite chef with close-cropped hair and the images of a fried egg and slice of bacon painted on the tips of her clogs, stood at the counter, ready to begin. She was about to make a meal for an audience of 18, including me, expounding on the theme ''No-Cook Summer Sauces for Pasta.'' Before the night was over, students in the cooking class would learn seven different sauces, from a puttanesca to a citrusy lemon-pepper shrimp sauce.</p>
        <p>But before Mrs. Caparulo reached for a single plum tomato, David P. Martone, her host, welcomed the students who had paid $49 each for this night of cookery in the back room of Classic Thyme, the upscale cookware shop in Westfield that Mr. Martone operates with his partner, Sheila Turteltaub.</p>
        <p>''If you've never had a class here,'' he said, ''I guarantee you it will be better than any cooking show you've ever seen on TV. You can stop and ask questions, and at the end you can eat everything.''</p>
        <p>His line has been ringing in my head for weeks now.</p>
        <p>I'm sure Mr. Martone and other culinary professionals would agree that Americans all too often learn to cook passively, culling ideas from magazines, cookbooks and, yes, ubiquitous cooking shows.</p>
        <p>But cooking and eating are anything but passive. In any field, true learning comes from doing, and the best cooks do not read or watch; they belly up to the counter, make messes, wield steel, tame fire, learn to taste what they've wrought and judge it critically.</p>
        <p>Recently I left my own kitchen to enroll in a smattering of cooking classes across the state. Most often you can buy a night of flavors for less than $50, a steal compared with cooking classes in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The best schools offer technique, or ''tech,'' classes, which are more expensive and most valuable. At Classic Thyme, for  instance, you can sign up for five consecutive classes that will give you a solid grounding in the world of the kitchen. Week 1: using a knife, roasting, soup stocks, biscuits. Week 2: broiling and marinades; cooking rice, couscous, polenta; working with vegetables; chocolate. By Week 5, you're sauteing and frying to your heart's content, and learning to deal with the tricky properties of eggs. Cost: $329.</p>
        <p>That sounds steep, but if you're just starting to cook, a tech class will be far more meaningful than signing up for a bunch of ''recipe classes'' where you march your way through five or six dishes built around a central theme: Chinese Noodle Dishes. Shrimply Delicious. Great Summer Tarts.  Chances are, if you learn four recipes out of context, you're probably doomed to repeat the same four relentlessly, never realizing how they relate to other meals in the great food web. But nail down your techniques -- what makes a sauce a sauce, the mechanics of braising, things you should never do to chocolate -- and you'll feed yourself (and your delighted family) forever.</p>
        <p>Either you will cook in your class, or you will watch someone cook. I prefer a hands-on lesson, but even professional culinary students must occasionally lay down their knives and take their seat in the gallery to attend lectures. But presumably they've mastered the basics.</p>
        <p>If you watch someone cook, as I did the night I attended Carole Walter's ''Luscious Lemon and Lime Desserts'' demo at the Kings Supermarket Cooking Studio in Hillsdale, you can sit, sip water or coffee, and snack on cheese, crackers and grapes, while the pro walks you through a recipe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martone is right. It was better than any cooking show. And better than paging through a cookbook.</p>
        <p>For example, Mrs. Walter, a West Orange resident and one of the nation's grande dames of baking, dispensed advice you will not find in any cookbook, except perhaps her own. The author of ''Great Pies and Tarts'' and ''Great Cakes'' (both published by Clarkson Potter) told us that most people measure their baking flour incorrectly, using a liquid measuring cup instead of a dry scoop. And even if they use the right utensil, the very act of scooping and scraping off the top can compress the grains.</p>
        <p>She showed us how to do it properly: she emptied the full cup onto a sheet of wax paper, and laboriously refilled it with a spoon. To our surprise, when the cup was full, there was still plenty of flour left over on the wax paper, which she poured back into the flour bin. Egad, I thought, I've been overfilling for years.</p>
        <p>Now maybe a televison chef will perform the same little magic trick for you. But I defy you to get him or her to answer the questions you hurl at the glowing screen -- ''Why?'' ''Can you do it again?'' -- until you understand it. It helps to be able to pick the brains of a live expert.</p>
        <p>That night, Mrs. Walter spent three hours baking four desserts. It took her almost 20 minutes to get the first cake started because not a single ingredient -- butter, sugar, eggs, flour -- went into the mixing bowl unaccompanied by some pithy advice.</p>
        <p>As Mrs. Walter watched her assistant ready a food processor, she spoke of the  importance of keeping the blades sharp. Of avoiding dark pans, which conduct too much heat. Of making sure every inch of your baking pan is buttered, even if you have to use a pastry brush to get into the crevices. The woman had sweated the details, so we didn't have to.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Mrs. Caparulo, a Morristown resident, shed light on the ''science and why'' of cooking: roma tomatoes have thicker cell walls, which translates into more meat for sauces. Olive oil goes rancid; buy only what you'll use for three months. Many summer herbs can be dried in minutes in a microwave.</p>
        <p>It's awfully nice to relax, watch while someone else cooks, and soak up these tidbits. You can take copious notes or even draw diagrams in the margins of your recipe sheets. (I did just that to remind myself how Mrs. Walter piped the Key lime filling into her pie shell.)</p>
        <p>Sooner or later, though, you are going to have to take a hands-on class and get into the kitchen yourself.</p>
        <p>There is no other way to understand how the squishy dough of brioche is supposed to feel. You cannot merely watch someone debone a chicken, and go and do likewise. You are likely to debone your fingers. There is no way you can adequately appreciate the necessity of salt until you have stood over a simmering sauce or soup, adding a touch of the white stuff, stirring, tasting and witnessing the awakening of flavors.</p>
        <p>If a chef's demo is ballet, hands-on classes are operatic hell. Even though hands-on classes are usually smaller than demos, you will share work tables and stoves with about a dozen other people, all of whom, like you, need to use the food processor.</p>
        <p>You will divide your food prep chores so that one brigade works, say, on three recipes, and another tackles three others. Invariably, regardless of the instructor's insistent needling, about two-thirds of the way through the class, just when everyone's about to drop of exhaustion, someone will realize that no one has started the seventh recipe -- dessert.</p>
        <p>More than anything, hands-on classes force you to get your money's worth. You alone are responsible for pushing yourself to visit other tables and see what's going on.  ''How'd you do this?'' you must constantly ask. ''How'd you guys make that? Can I try?''</p>
        <p>If your instructor is a good one, he or she will stop the class often to focus on the new techniques. Gather around and watch, folks: here's how you carve a roast chicken, trim lamb chops, make puff pastry.</p>
        <p>A friend once told me she thought cooking classes were a waste. She had signed up for a class on French cooking and spent the whole time boiling oranges for the duck a l'orange. Whose fault was that? She was not an inquisitive cook, and I'll bet it showed each time she took her place before the stove.</p>
        <p>You make the class.</p>
        <p>The nicest thing about such classes is something hard to define. Call it the mystery of dining.</p>
        <p>One hot night not long ago, I drove south to Monmouth County to check out a class at Brookdale Community College in Freehold, which offers one of the most ambitious cooking programs I sampled. Summer classes are apt to run small, and this one was no exception. Five or six of us sat around the kitchen counter, watching and chatting as Diana Albanese, a cook-instructor from Brielle and a cheerful veteran of the New Jersey cooking school circuit, led us through a menu titled ''Cold Summer Soups and Grilled Salads.''</p>
        <p>The conversation ranged from the menu at hand to the difficulties of raising children, working a job and, of course, cooking. As if underscoring the topic, one woman had brought along her 5-month-old baby, a beautiful child who gurgled as we took our notes.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Albanese, a one-time gallery artist, had a quick mind and a witty line for nearly everything. The cooking done, we set it out, lined up for the buffet, and tasted the creations one by one: grilled eggplant soup with Parmesan croutons. Cucumber soup with smoked trout. Corn soup with grilled shittake mushrooms. Shrimp salad with summer vegetables and chive vinaigrette. Grilled chicken breast with Vidalia onions and tomato salad with goat cheese vinaigrette. And penne with roasted vegetables.</p>
        <p>Heading home that night in the steamy blackness of the Garden State Parkway, I felt like I had done more than just attend a class. I had supped well with friends.</p>
        <p>Adventures in Cooking, 12 Legion Place, Wayne, (973) 305-1114; adventuresincooking.com</p>
        <p>Classic Thyme, 161 East Broad Street, Westfield, (908) 789-5824; classicthyme.com</p>
        <p>Cooktique, 9 West Railroad Avenue, Tenafly, (201) 568-7990; cooktique.com</p>
        <p>Kings Supermarket Cooking Studio: in Short Hills, Hillsdale, Verona and Bedminster, (973) 463-6500.</p>
        <p>Brookdale Community Cooking School, Western Monmouth Higher Education Center, 3680 Route 9 South, Freehold, (732) 224-2108, or e-mail rshapiro@brookdale.cc.nj.us.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
