<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Magic Acts To Drums: Hiring The Life of the Party</title>
    <meta content="24HIRE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233124"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impersonations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magic and Magicians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ventriloquists</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hip Pickles (Performance Groupe)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roy, Rob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spiewak, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brackman, Wendy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dantana, Vince</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magic and Magicians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E6DE133BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Magic Acts To Drums: Hiring The Life of the Party</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles entertainers who can be hired for variety of parties, corporate or school events on Long Island, including Elvis impersonator Rob Roy, dog trainer Leslie Spiewak and his Boston terrier, Magic, Wendy Brackman, who cuts hats out of paper plates, ventriloquist Vince Dantona and his dummy, George, magician Dan Miller and street performance group Hip Pickles; photos (Special Issue: Entertainment) (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HAVING a party? Pin the tail on the donkey and background music from the CD player don't cut it anymore. Whether it's a wedding, bar mitzvah, anniversary, corporate or school event, the entertainment choices are limitless. And the wackier the better. Magicians, prancing drummers, impersonators, belly dancers, face painters, ventriloquists, sword swallowers, male strippers, puppeteers and multi-talented performers who walk on stilts, ride unicycles and play with yo-yos are only a fee away. Here are some of the possibilities.</p>
        <p>Long Live 'The King'</p>
        <p>The bride wore white. And to her surprise, so did Elvis.</p>
        <p>He swept into the ballroom as the salad was being served to 130 guests at the wedding reception of Cherise Buttitta and Matthew Spector at Antun's, a catering hall in Hicksville. The King of rock 'n' roll -- otherwise known as Rob Roy, an impersonator from Center Moriches -- began to gyrate to ''C. C. Rider.''</p>
        <p>The newlyweds, who had arranged only for a disc jockey to provide music for the party, stood at the edge of the dance floor staring. Guests gathered in a semicircle, clapping and singing along, as Mr. Roy approached the bride, serenading her with ''It's Now or Never.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Buttitta's father, Nick Buttitta, 57, a die-hard Elvis fan from Lynbrook who aranged for the surprise, couldn't stop grinning. ''I like him,'' said Mr. Buttitta, referring to the real Elvis Presley. ''I grew up with him. My daughter's a fan through me. I have one daughter, and it's a big night for her. I thought it would be cute. It was something different.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Roy, who wore sunglasses and a black wig with heavy sideburns, worked the crowd, dancing with the flower girl, strutting from table to table hugging the guests as he sang.</p>
        <p>Was he convincing?</p>
        <p>''I think he was funny,'' said Kristin Rio, 9, a cousin of the bride. ''The real Elvis is dead. The real Elvis is better. He has more moves.''</p>
        <p>But the real Elvis didn't have Maria Gaiewski of Smithtown, a lip-syncing Tina Turner impersonator, who joined Mr. Roy for a song, then lip-synced the backup vocals. ''Oh my God,'' the bridegroom said, his mouth dropping. ''I love Tina Turner.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Roy, 57, was an actor when he started impersonating Elvis in 1976. At first it was rough, he said, but when Elvis died the following year, business boomed, and he joined a group called Nostalgia '77.</p>
        <p>''I figured this would be a great way of getting acting experience,'' Mr. Roy said. ''I loved Elvis, and I already knew the songs.''</p>
        <p>Since then, Mr. Roy's acting work has also included roles, mainly as  police officers, in dozens of films, including ''Hello Again,'' ''Prizzi's Honor,'' ''Cadillac Man'' and three ''Death Wish'' movies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roy arrived at the wedding in a pink and white 1973 Cadillac hearse with a portrait of Elvis in front of Graceland on the back door.</p>
        <p>For the more elaborate shows Mr. Roy began offering two years ago, he pops out of a smoking purple-covered, hydraulically operated coffin, hidden by a layer of Elvis memorabilia. Jumping to his feet, he sings, ''Got a Lot o' Livin' to Do.'' Not long ago, he was hired to jump out of the coffin for a party celebrating the 100th anniversary of the birth of a man who had died nearly 40 years earlier.</p>
        <p>The ''coffin shows'' begin at $1,000.  The 20-minute wedding show cost $350. ''Believe me, it was worth every penny of it,'' Mr. Buttitta said.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Roy said: ''I'd be satisfied as long as I'm doing an Elvis show. ''There is no better way to make a living.''</p>
        <p>See Spot Perform</p>
        <p>She can add. She can subtract. She can jump over sticks and through hoops. She can do card tricks. And she can toot a plastic flute.</p>
        <p>Meet Magic, a 3-old-year black and white Boston terrier who looks like Betty Boop and wears a sparkly red clown collar. Best friend to Mr. Lucky -- a k a Leslie Spiewak, a dog trainer for 45 years -- Magic is a show dog cum laude. Their act: Magic the Dog and Mr. Lucky.</p>
        <p>''She's so bright, she's unbelievable,'' said Mr. Lucky, 73, of Dix Hills, after a performance for campers in a summer recreation program at the Lakeside School in Merrick. ''I give her more credit than me. I just show her what to do, and she does it.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Lucky was a child in Brooklyn, his mother wouldn't let him have a pet in the house. ''I got even with her,'' said Mr. Lucky, who has performed with as many as four dogs.</p>
        <p>In 1956, he founded Mr. Lucky's Dog Training School. He also owned the House of Lethal Dogs, training dogs for security duty. Over the years he has had a troupe, Mr. Lucky's Performing Dogs, with two, three or more in the act, and has also spent more than six years doing a show with a pig named Stanley. Mr. Lucky also performs as a jazz saxophonist, with Magic at his side.</p>
        <p>He usually finds his dogs at animal shelters, though he got Magic two years ago through a newspaper advertisement. Mr. Lucky charges $350 to $750, depending on location, for a 45-minute show. To close his show in Merrick, Mr. Lucky performed canine hypnosis, swinging a frankfurter (Mr. Lucky never says ''hot dog'' in front of his pet) back and forth on a string. Magic dropped to the floor, ignoring offers of treats, cookies, pizza and a hamburger.</p>
        <p>''It's the dog catcher,'' Mr. Lucky finally cried. At that, Magic jumped up and took a canine bow.</p>
        <p>Hats Off</p>
        <p>''Would you like a fun hat, a scary hat or something completely off the wall?'' Wendy Brackman asked the young boy standing in front of the Wacky Wendy Bar Mitzvah Battle Buggy during the cocktail hour at Brian Forur's recent bar mitzvah celebration in Melville. Spencer Fogel, 8, of Melville wanted something out of this world.</p>
        <p>Not to worry.</p>
        <p>With a quick snip here and a quick snip there, Ms. Brackman, 45, known on party turf as Wacky Wendy, went to work, cracking jokes as she cut a green paper plate into an alien with nostrils, antennae and funny-looking eyeballs. Then she turned a plastic takeout container lid into a spaceship.</p>
        <p>''When I was your age I used to play with my food,'' she said, fitting the creation onto Spencer's head. ''So my mother said, 'Cut it out!' ''</p>
        <p>Spencer giggled. ''Cool,'' he said, looking in the large blue mirror Ms. Brackman whipped out.</p>
        <p>As the self-appointed queen of the bar and bat mitzvah circuit, Ms. Brackman has been creating wacky hats out of nine-inch paper plates full time since 1986.</p>
        <p>''I am really the incarnation of Edward Scissorhands,'' said Ms. Brackman, a combination paper sculptor and comedian who lives in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>She cuts paper silhouettes at breakneck speed, working freehand, and each hat is an original sculpture.</p>
        <p>''People don't know what I'm doing, and suddenly they have a rooster or the Titanic on their head,'' she said, as a crowd of children and adults watched her cut out an airplane and palm trees as she fashioned a vacation hat for Pamela Wexler, 10, of Melville.</p>
        <p>On her own head she wore an oversized top hat brimming with the Manhattan skyline, three-dimensional buildings and the Statue of Liberty.</p>
        <p>Stacey Forur and her husband, Dr. Lawrence, booked Ms. Brackman for their party the minute they received the date for their son's bar mitzvah two and a half years ago. The theme of the 245-guest party: ''Hats Off to Brian.''</p>
        <p>''Every bar mitzvah has pretty much the same entertainment,'' said Dr. Forur, 46, an optometrist. ''People have video games. Kids can do that anywhere. This is unique, and they can take it home with them. The only problem I have with her is there is only one Wacky Wendy. You need three or four Wacky Wendys in the room to entertain everyone.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Brackman creates about 70 hats in three hours, using an average of six to nine plates for each one. To satisfy the demand, she recently invented the Wacky Hat Factory, which is like a pasta machine for hats. It is sometimes available for parties when she's not.</p>
        <p>''There are very few people who are willing to make things in front of people,'' said Ms. Brackman, who used to run a sculpture studio.</p>
        <p>She charges $2,300 to $2,500 for three hours and is booked for 120 to 150 events a year.</p>
        <p>Some people even collect her creations. Betty Gross, Brian's great-aunt, waited her turn, hoping for a rocket-ship hat for her husband and one in the shape of a crab for herself.</p>
        <p>''I still have the one she made for me to match my green dress five years ago,'' Ms. Gross said.</p>
        <p>Talking for Two</p>
        <p>Vince Dantona sat on a stool on the small stage at Governor's Cabaret and Comedy Club in Levittown. George the dummy sat on his lap, his legs dangling limply, his mouth in a perpetual smile.</p>
        <p>''Watch your tongue,'' Mr. Dantona said. ''I can't -- my nose is in the way,'' replied George, the master of the one-liner, as Mr. Dantona's Adam's apple did a quick bob, though his lips barely quivered.</p>
        <p>The audience of campers from Camp Merrick Woods and Rolling River day camps tittered.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Dantona has five sons of his own, George, a wooden puppet, has been his sidekick for the last 27 years in a two-for-one stand-up comedy routine. His fee starts at $200 for a half-hour show.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dantona's routine depends on the audience, though some of his jokes seemed as old as Charlie McCarthy himself.</p>
        <p>''People look at it as two different people up there,'' Mr. Dantona said. ''He gets away with everything. Nobody ever gets mad at him.''</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Dantona did all the talking, George was delivering the punch lines. ''We've been together a pretty long time,'' Mr. Dantona said.</p>
        <p>''It's been long -- it hasn't been pretty,'' George replied.</p>
        <p>While serving on Okinawa during a 10-year-stint in the Marine Corps, Mr. Dantona, now 51, learned ventriloquism through a correspondence course, practicing in the mirror. He'd always hoped for a career in show business, and the $600 wooden puppet was the only prop he'd ever need.</p>
        <p>Before Mr. Dantona even finished the class, he and George took to the stage as hosts of a two-hour children's program on Armed Forces television and radio. In Japan, Mr. Dantona said, he was recognized as a star wherever he went, and Mr. Dantona and George were the first $10,000 winners on ''America's Funniest People'' on ABC-TV in 1981.</p>
        <p>He started working the Long Island comedy circuit with performers like Eddie Murphy, Rob Bartlett and Dave Nelson at Richard Dixon's White House Inn in North Massapequa.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to do standup, but I needed something there,'' Mr. Dantona said, adding that the one time he went on stage alone, he bombed.  George is ''like my security blanket so I don't have to be there by myself,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At the camp performance, Mr. Dantona had a tough time delivering his punch lines over the children's chatter.</p>
        <p>''The kids are so tough,'' he said later. ''Adults are so much easier. Adults are more easily fooled than the kids.''</p>
        <p>Like Magic</p>
        <p>Standing in line at the Food Emporium in Great Neck, Dan Miller reached over and, abracadabra,  made Etta Wise's package of chocolate squeak. Presto! He pulled a coin out from behind Laura Bardash's ear.</p>
        <p>''Look at that,'' Ms. Bardash exclaimed, laughing. ''From a golden earring I got a silver dollar. I could use a shopping lift like this every time I come into a store.''</p>
        <p>At the bank, Mr. Miller made a deposit. Then he asked the teller, Gloria Li of Fresh Meadows, if she had a $20 bill. ''I'll double it and give you $30,'' he said, folding the bill over and over. ''I'll keep 10.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Li giggled as Mr. Miller, known as Magic Dan, did yet another of his tricks.</p>
        <p>Leaving the bank and walking down the street, he magically made the trees squeak as he passed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller, 67, is a retired pharmacist who works part time as a pharmaceuticals salesman and full time as a magician. As Magic Dan, he performs at adult parties for all sorts of occasions, specializing in tricks with silk scarves, ropes, coins and cards. He charges $600 for two hours.  He has performed for more than 90 groups, he said, but whether he is pitching an antidepressant to a psychiatrist, promoting a drug product at a trade show or just running errands near his home in Great Neck, Mr. Miller is always conjuring up tricks.</p>
        <p>''We all have that little child in us,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His foray into wizardry was serendipitous. While working in middle management at a pharmaceuticals company in 1985, he went to a beginners' magic class at Nassau Community College, accompanying a friend who didn't want to go alone. ''Once I learned how to do it, it took over my life,'' said Mr. Miller, who said he had never liked magic tricks before that.</p>
        <p>On April Fool's Day two years later, he retired from his job to concentrate on magic. He's been at it ever since, even teaching a course on magic at Queensborough Community College.</p>
        <p>The Beat Goes On</p>
        <p>What the Hip Pickles realized during six years of working as street performers at South Street Seaport is that entertaining people isn't enough.  They want to be wowed.</p>
        <p>So when the percussion trio -- Chet Doboe, 51, of Uniondale; Chris Scherer, 28, of Bay Shore; and Zeus Figueroa Jr., 31, of Brightwaters --  developed new shows for the party and arts-in-education circuit a few years ago, they added a little hip-hop, a couple of sing-along songs, dancing, interactivity and a comedy routine to their drumming repertory.</p>
        <p>''Our job is to put energy together in a way that creates a response out of the audience,'' said Mr. Doboe, the group's leader, composer and choreographer. ''You make sounds, and you put them together in a certain way, and it should move an audience. When it's put together the right way, it's magic.''</p>
        <p>When they started the first of two 40-minute shows at Camp Apollo at Plainview-Old Bethpage Middle School recently, the 300 children didn't know where to look first. Mr. Scherer stood on stage, beating a West African drum. With the same rhythm, Mr. Doboe and Mr. Figueroa jumped, danced and played their way from the back of the auditorium.</p>
        <p>Together the Hip Pickles played the Monster, a rack of six tom-toms, three piccolo snare drums, three bass drums worked with a foot pedal and four cymbals custom-designed for synchronized drumming. The group has won the Drum Corps Association's World Championships six times and recently did a 45-minute set at Westbury Music Fair.</p>
        <p>Playing to children's audiences can be frustrating. ''It takes some getting used to,'' said Mr. Scherer, who played to 40 camps last summer. ''We seem to hold their interest. If they do scream, we just talk over it, and somehow in doing that they have no choice but to listen. All of a sudden we have their attention again.''</p>
        <p>To pique interest, the Hip Pickles bring along lollipop drums, rattles,  egg shakers, tambourines and pots and pans, inviting the children to play along.</p>
        <p>''It was great,'' Andy Giron, 11, of Plainview, said after he played a tambourine stick at the Plainview show. ''I like loud music. It was like watching a concert except with a lot more energy.''</p>
        <p>The Hip Pickles recently put out a CD, ''Hip Pickles Out of the Jar.'' They play about 200 dates a year.  Fees vary, averaging $850 for a 45-minute show.</p>
        <p>''We enjoy the challenge of trying to do what we do and make it fit for a special audience,'' Mr. Doboe said. ''It's not just about entertaining the kids. It's trying to pass on some of our passion.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HAVING a party? Pin the tail on the donkey and background music from the CD player don't cut it anymore. Whether it's a wedding, bar mitzvah, anniversary, corporate or school event, the entertainment choices are limitless. And the wackier the better. Magicians, prancing drummers, impersonators, belly dancers, face painters, ventriloquists, sword swallowers, male strippers, puppeteers and multi-talented performers who walk on stilts, ride unicycles and play with yo-yos are only a fee away. Here are some of the possibilities.</p>
        <p>Long Live 'The King'</p>
        <p>The bride wore white. And to her surprise, so did Elvis.</p>
        <p>He swept into the ballroom as the salad was being served to 130 guests at the wedding reception of Cherise Buttitta and Matthew Spector at Antun's, a catering hall in Hicksville. The King of rock 'n' roll -- otherwise known as Rob Roy, an impersonator from Center Moriches -- began to gyrate to ''C. C. Rider.''</p>
        <p>The newlyweds, who had arranged only for a disc jockey to provide music for the party, stood at the edge of the dance floor staring. Guests gathered in a semicircle, clapping and singing along, as Mr. Roy approached the bride, serenading her with ''It's Now or Never.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Buttitta's father, Nick Buttitta, 57, a die-hard Elvis fan from Lynbrook who aranged for the surprise, couldn't stop grinning. ''I like him,'' said Mr. Buttitta, referring to the real Elvis Presley. ''I grew up with him. My daughter's a fan through me. I have one daughter, and it's a big night for her. I thought it would be cute. It was something different.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Roy, who wore sunglasses and a black wig with heavy sideburns, worked the crowd, dancing with the flower girl, strutting from table to table hugging the guests as he sang.</p>
        <p>Was he convincing?</p>
        <p>''I think he was funny,'' said Kristin Rio, 9, a cousin of the bride. ''The real Elvis is dead. The real Elvis is better. He has more moves.''</p>
        <p>But the real Elvis didn't have Maria Gaiewski of Smithtown, a lip-syncing Tina Turner impersonator, who joined Mr. Roy for a song, then lip-synced the backup vocals. ''Oh my God,'' the bridegroom said, his mouth dropping. ''I love Tina Turner.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Roy, 57, was an actor when he started impersonating Elvis in 1976. At first it was rough, he said, but when Elvis died the following year, business boomed, and he joined a group called Nostalgia '77.</p>
        <p>''I figured this would be a great way of getting acting experience,'' Mr. Roy said. ''I loved Elvis, and I already knew the songs.''</p>
        <p>Since then, Mr. Roy's acting work has also included roles, mainly as  police officers, in dozens of films, including ''Hello Again,'' ''Prizzi's Honor,'' ''Cadillac Man'' and three ''Death Wish'' movies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roy arrived at the wedding in a pink and white 1973 Cadillac hearse with a portrait of Elvis in front of Graceland on the back door.</p>
        <p>For the more elaborate shows Mr. Roy began offering two years ago, he pops out of a smoking purple-covered, hydraulically operated coffin, hidden by a layer of Elvis memorabilia. Jumping to his feet, he sings, ''Got a Lot o' Livin' to Do.'' Not long ago, he was hired to jump out of the coffin for a party celebrating the 100th anniversary of the birth of a man who had died nearly 40 years earlier.</p>
        <p>The ''coffin shows'' begin at $1,000.  The 20-minute wedding show cost $350. ''Believe me, it was worth every penny of it,'' Mr. Buttitta said.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Roy said: ''I'd be satisfied as long as I'm doing an Elvis show. ''There is no better way to make a living.''</p>
        <p>See Spot Perform</p>
        <p>She can add. She can subtract. She can jump over sticks and through hoops. She can do card tricks. And she can toot a plastic flute.</p>
        <p>Meet Magic, a 3-old-year black and white Boston terrier who looks like Betty Boop and wears a sparkly red clown collar. Best friend to Mr. Lucky -- a k a Leslie Spiewak, a dog trainer for 45 years -- Magic is a show dog cum laude. Their act: Magic the Dog and Mr. Lucky.</p>
        <p>''She's so bright, she's unbelievable,'' said Mr. Lucky, 73, of Dix Hills, after a performance for campers in a summer recreation program at the Lakeside School in Merrick. ''I give her more credit than me. I just show her what to do, and she does it.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Lucky was a child in Brooklyn, his mother wouldn't let him have a pet in the house. ''I got even with her,'' said Mr. Lucky, who has performed with as many as four dogs.</p>
        <p>In 1956, he founded Mr. Lucky's Dog Training School. He also owned the House of Lethal Dogs, training dogs for security duty. Over the years he has had a troupe, Mr. Lucky's Performing Dogs, with two, three or more in the act, and has also spent more than six years doing a show with a pig named Stanley. Mr. Lucky also performs as a jazz saxophonist, with Magic at his side.</p>
        <p>He usually finds his dogs at animal shelters, though he got Magic two years ago through a newspaper advertisement. Mr. Lucky charges $350 to $750, depending on location, for a 45-minute show. To close his show in Merrick, Mr. Lucky performed canine hypnosis, swinging a frankfurter (Mr. Lucky never says ''hot dog'' in front of his pet) back and forth on a string. Magic dropped to the floor, ignoring offers of treats, cookies, pizza and a hamburger.</p>
        <p>''It's the dog catcher,'' Mr. Lucky finally cried. At that, Magic jumped up and took a canine bow.</p>
        <p>Hats Off</p>
        <p>''Would you like a fun hat, a scary hat or something completely off the wall?'' Wendy Brackman asked the young boy standing in front of the Wacky Wendy Bar Mitzvah Battle Buggy during the cocktail hour at Brian Forur's recent bar mitzvah celebration in Melville. Spencer Fogel, 8, of Melville wanted something out of this world.</p>
        <p>Not to worry.</p>
        <p>With a quick snip here and a quick snip there, Ms. Brackman, 45, known on party turf as Wacky Wendy, went to work, cracking jokes as she cut a green paper plate into an alien with nostrils, antennae and funny-looking eyeballs. Then she turned a plastic takeout container lid into a spaceship.</p>
        <p>''When I was your age I used to play with my food,'' she said, fitting the creation onto Spencer's head. ''So my mother said, 'Cut it out!' ''</p>
        <p>Spencer giggled. ''Cool,'' he said, looking in the large blue mirror Ms. Brackman whipped out.</p>
        <p>As the self-appointed queen of the bar and bat mitzvah circuit, Ms. Brackman has been creating wacky hats out of nine-inch paper plates full time since 1986.</p>
        <p>''I am really the incarnation of Edward Scissorhands,'' said Ms. Brackman, a combination paper sculptor and comedian who lives in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>She cuts paper silhouettes at breakneck speed, working freehand, and each hat is an original sculpture.</p>
        <p>''People don't know what I'm doing, and suddenly they have a rooster or the Titanic on their head,'' she said, as a crowd of children and adults watched her cut out an airplane and palm trees as she fashioned a vacation hat for Pamela Wexler, 10, of Melville.</p>
        <p>On her own head she wore an oversized top hat brimming with the Manhattan skyline, three-dimensional buildings and the Statue of Liberty.</p>
        <p>Stacey Forur and her husband, Dr. Lawrence, booked Ms. Brackman for their party the minute they received the date for their son's bar mitzvah two and a half years ago. The theme of the 245-guest party: ''Hats Off to Brian.''</p>
        <p>''Every bar mitzvah has pretty much the same entertainment,'' said Dr. Forur, 46, an optometrist. ''People have video games. Kids can do that anywhere. This is unique, and they can take it home with them. The only problem I have with her is there is only one Wacky Wendy. You need three or four Wacky Wendys in the room to entertain everyone.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Brackman creates about 70 hats in three hours, using an average of six to nine plates for each one. To satisfy the demand, she recently invented the Wacky Hat Factory, which is like a pasta machine for hats. It is sometimes available for parties when she's not.</p>
        <p>''There are very few people who are willing to make things in front of people,'' said Ms. Brackman, who used to run a sculpture studio.</p>
        <p>She charges $2,300 to $2,500 for three hours and is booked for 120 to 150 events a year.</p>
        <p>Some people even collect her creations. Betty Gross, Brian's great-aunt, waited her turn, hoping for a rocket-ship hat for her husband and one in the shape of a crab for herself.</p>
        <p>''I still have the one she made for me to match my green dress five years ago,'' Ms. Gross said.</p>
        <p>Talking for Two</p>
        <p>Vince Dantona sat on a stool on the small stage at Governor's Cabaret and Comedy Club in Levittown. George the dummy sat on his lap, his legs dangling limply, his mouth in a perpetual smile.</p>
        <p>''Watch your tongue,'' Mr. Dantona said. ''I can't -- my nose is in the way,'' replied George, the master of the one-liner, as Mr. Dantona's Adam's apple did a quick bob, though his lips barely quivered.</p>
        <p>The audience of campers from Camp Merrick Woods and Rolling River day camps tittered.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Dantona has five sons of his own, George, a wooden puppet, has been his sidekick for the last 27 years in a two-for-one stand-up comedy routine. His fee starts at $200 for a half-hour show.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dantona's routine depends on the audience, though some of his jokes seemed as old as Charlie McCarthy himself.</p>
        <p>''People look at it as two different people up there,'' Mr. Dantona said. ''He gets away with everything. Nobody ever gets mad at him.''</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Dantona did all the talking, George was delivering the punch lines. ''We've been together a pretty long time,'' Mr. Dantona said.</p>
        <p>''It's been long -- it hasn't been pretty,'' George replied.</p>
        <p>While serving on Okinawa during a 10-year-stint in the Marine Corps, Mr. Dantona, now 51, learned ventriloquism through a correspondence course, practicing in the mirror. He'd always hoped for a career in show business, and the $600 wooden puppet was the only prop he'd ever need.</p>
        <p>Before Mr. Dantona even finished the class, he and George took to the stage as hosts of a two-hour children's program on Armed Forces television and radio. In Japan, Mr. Dantona said, he was recognized as a star wherever he went, and Mr. Dantona and George were the first $10,000 winners on ''America's Funniest People'' on ABC-TV in 1981.</p>
        <p>He started working the Long Island comedy circuit with performers like Eddie Murphy, Rob Bartlett and Dave Nelson at Richard Dixon's White House Inn in North Massapequa.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to do standup, but I needed something there,'' Mr. Dantona said, adding that the one time he went on stage alone, he bombed.  George is ''like my security blanket so I don't have to be there by myself,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At the camp performance, Mr. Dantona had a tough time delivering his punch lines over the children's chatter.</p>
        <p>''The kids are so tough,'' he said later. ''Adults are so much easier. Adults are more easily fooled than the kids.''</p>
        <p>Like Magic</p>
        <p>Standing in line at the Food Emporium in Great Neck, Dan Miller reached over and, abracadabra,  made Etta Wise's package of chocolate squeak. Presto! He pulled a coin out from behind Laura Bardash's ear.</p>
        <p>''Look at that,'' Ms. Bardash exclaimed, laughing. ''From a golden earring I got a silver dollar. I could use a shopping lift like this every time I come into a store.''</p>
        <p>At the bank, Mr. Miller made a deposit. Then he asked the teller, Gloria Li of Fresh Meadows, if she had a $20 bill. ''I'll double it and give you $30,'' he said, folding the bill over and over. ''I'll keep 10.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Li giggled as Mr. Miller, known as Magic Dan, did yet another of his tricks.</p>
        <p>Leaving the bank and walking down the street, he magically made the trees squeak as he passed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller, 67, is a retired pharmacist who works part time as a pharmaceuticals salesman and full time as a magician. As Magic Dan, he performs at adult parties for all sorts of occasions, specializing in tricks with silk scarves, ropes, coins and cards. He charges $600 for two hours.  He has performed for more than 90 groups, he said, but whether he is pitching an antidepressant to a psychiatrist, promoting a drug product at a trade show or just running errands near his home in Great Neck, Mr. Miller is always conjuring up tricks.</p>
        <p>''We all have that little child in us,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His foray into wizardry was serendipitous. While working in middle management at a pharmaceuticals company in 1985, he went to a beginners' magic class at Nassau Community College, accompanying a friend who didn't want to go alone. ''Once I learned how to do it, it took over my life,'' said Mr. Miller, who said he had never liked magic tricks before that.</p>
        <p>On April Fool's Day two years later, he retired from his job to concentrate on magic. He's been at it ever since, even teaching a course on magic at Queensborough Community College.</p>
        <p>The Beat Goes On</p>
        <p>What the Hip Pickles realized during six years of working as street performers at South Street Seaport is that entertaining people isn't enough.  They want to be wowed.</p>
        <p>So when the percussion trio -- Chet Doboe, 51, of Uniondale; Chris Scherer, 28, of Bay Shore; and Zeus Figueroa Jr., 31, of Brightwaters --  developed new shows for the party and arts-in-education circuit a few years ago, they added a little hip-hop, a couple of sing-along songs, dancing, interactivity and a comedy routine to their drumming repertory.</p>
        <p>''Our job is to put energy together in a way that creates a response out of the audience,'' said Mr. Doboe, the group's leader, composer and choreographer. ''You make sounds, and you put them together in a certain way, and it should move an audience. When it's put together the right way, it's magic.''</p>
        <p>When they started the first of two 40-minute shows at Camp Apollo at Plainview-Old Bethpage Middle School recently, the 300 children didn't know where to look first. Mr. Scherer stood on stage, beating a West African drum. With the same rhythm, Mr. Doboe and Mr. Figueroa jumped, danced and played their way from the back of the auditorium.</p>
        <p>Together the Hip Pickles played the Monster, a rack of six tom-toms, three piccolo snare drums, three bass drums worked with a foot pedal and four cymbals custom-designed for synchronized drumming. The group has won the Drum Corps Association's World Championships six times and recently did a 45-minute set at Westbury Music Fair.</p>
        <p>Playing to children's audiences can be frustrating. ''It takes some getting used to,'' said Mr. Scherer, who played to 40 camps last summer. ''We seem to hold their interest. If they do scream, we just talk over it, and somehow in doing that they have no choice but to listen. All of a sudden we have their attention again.''</p>
        <p>To pique interest, the Hip Pickles bring along lollipop drums, rattles,  egg shakers, tambourines and pots and pans, inviting the children to play along.</p>
        <p>''It was great,'' Andy Giron, 11, of Plainview, said after he played a tambourine stick at the Plainview show. ''I like loud music. It was like watching a concert except with a lot more energy.''</p>
        <p>The Hip Pickles recently put out a CD, ''Hip Pickles Out of the Jar.'' They play about 200 dates a year.  Fees vary, averaging $850 for a 45-minute show.</p>
        <p>''We enjoy the challenge of trying to do what we do and make it fit for a special audience,'' Mr. Doboe said. ''It's not just about entertaining the kids. It's trying to pass on some of our passion.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
