<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Preserving the Forest By Leasing the Trees</title>
    <meta content="24WORL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/business/24WORL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE BUSINESS WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Guyana</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bolivia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cambodia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Conservation International Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abelson, Reed</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bolivia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Guyana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cambodia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Guyana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Cambodia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Bolivia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DA1E3BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1260" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Preserving the Forest By Leasing the Trees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By REED ABELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Abelson, Reed</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reed Abelson Business World column on conservation concession plan being used by Conservation International Foundation to buy long-term logging rights to 200,000 acres of pristine rain forest in Guyana in order to protect land; organization hopes to buy similar development rights in Bolivia, Brazil, Cambodia and other countries as strategy to protect environment and promote economic alternatives; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S a hard sell.</p>
        <p>In trying to persuade developing nations to protect their wilderness areas, environmentalists often meet strong resistance. Why would any country forgo badly needed revenue and the chance to foster economic activity by creating a national park rather than allowing the commercial development of its land?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S a hard sell.</p>
        <p>In trying to persuade developing nations to protect their wilderness areas, environmentalists often meet strong resistance. Why would any country forgo badly needed revenue and the chance to foster economic activity by creating a national park rather than allowing the commercial development of its land?</p>
        <p>One environmental group thinks it has come up with a way to spare governments from such a choice. The  Conservation International Foundation, based in Washington, is in the final stages of buying the long-term logging rights to 200,000 acres of pristine South American rain forest. The group expects to spend several million dollars over the next 25 years to protect the land, in southern Guyana, with what it calls a ''conservation concession.''</p>
        <p>And Guyana is just the start. Peru, Bolivia, Brazil and Cambodia may be next.</p>
        <p>Concessions -- development rights to land -- are often sold by governments to timber or mining companies and are readily available for huge stretches of tropical rain forest. Desperate for development, many governments are willing to lease the logging rights to public lands at an extraordinarily cheap price -- often just a few dollars an acre.</p>
        <p>''Too many of the great ecosystems of the world have a low price on their head,'' said Craig McCaw, the telecommunications entrepreneur and a member of the Conservation International board. He has given $5 million toward the creation of the group's new fund to help conserve wilderness areas.</p>
        <p>Conservation International has always favored using business strategies to protect the environment and has been aggressive in promoting economic alternatives, like ecotourism, to traditional development. In the late 1980's, the group pioneered the concept of swapping debt owed by a government for commitments to conserve land. Its board also includes business luminaries like Gordon E. Moore, a co-founder of Intel; Michael Eisner, the Disney chairman; and Barry Diller, the chairman of USA Networks.</p>
        <p>''If you don't do the economics, you don't win, you don't succeed in the long term,'' said Peter Seligmann, the chairman and chief executive of Conservation International.</p>
        <p>The group worked with Hardner &amp; Gullison Associates, a consulting firm in Palo Alto, Calif., to come up with the idea of competing directly with private businesses to win long-term concessions for public lands. By paying an amount that compensates the government for any lost jobs or economic activity, Conservation International hopes to ensure that local people still benefit -- usually through job-creation or education programs. ''Unless the local people are committed to it, it just isn't going to work,'' Mr. Seligmann said.</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENTAL groups have had limited success with other approaches to protecting wilderness areas. While countries have created some national parks, the process of convincing governments to set aside the land -- and to ensure that it remains undisturbed -- can be slow. The World Bank has spent years trying to help Guyana create a system of national parks, but has only started making some  progress.</p>
        <p>Groups like the Nature Conservancy have had success buying land in the United States but have had difficulty acquiring large wilderness areas elsewhere. In some countries, large sales to outsiders are viewed as threats to sovereignty, although the Nature Conservancy says it tries to prevent such problems by working with local environmental groups on purchases.</p>
        <p>Conservation International and the Nature Conservancy have also bought out private owners of timber rights in Bolivia, where they were able to add the land to the national park system.</p>
        <p>The idea of buying concessions directly from governments has ''great potential,'' said Elizabeth Losos, the director for the Center for Tropical Forest Science at the Smithsonian Institution in Washington. ''There are far more lands slated for timber than for protected areas,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She cautioned, however, that no single approach was the answer to saving rain forests. ''Everyone is looking for the silver bullet,'' she said, adding that environmentalists  were often quick to back away from  ideas if they did not prove to be clear successes.</p>
        <p>In Guyana, which has encouraged timber cutting as a way to stimulate its struggling economy, the idea of encouraging conservation without sacrificing badly needed cash and jobs is appealing.</p>
        <p>''If there is no economic benefit, there may be a populist sentiment that we should use it for other purposes,'' said Bharrat Jagdeo, the president of Guyana, the only English-speaking country in South America.</p>
        <p>He said that his country is committed to conservation and has established an environmental protection agency. But, he added, it needs the support and advice of international conservation groups. Guyana is also working with the Carter Center, created by former President Jimmy Carter, to create a foundation to explore alternatives to resource exploitation.</p>
        <p>Guyana recently approved a three-year exploratory lease for Conservation International; the term could be extended to 25 years once the parties have agreed to various terms, including price. The group had already identified an additional 800,000 acres that it would be interested in protecting if the government views the first concession as a success.</p>
        <p>Conservation International is pursuing similar arrangements in countries like Peru, where the government will auction concessions for some of its land in the Biabo forest.</p>
        <p>Conservation concessions, unlike national parks, might also allow the limited use of public lands for activities like hunting or fishing, by local people who might depend on the area for their livelihood. ''With a simple concept, this is very accommodating to those uses and users and dodges some of the debilitating conflicts that have stymied a lot of traditional conservation efforts,'' said Dan Martin, the director of ecosystems conservation and policy for the John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation, which has helped to finance the group.</p>
        <p>The calculus also has wide appeal to potential donors, many of whom are increasingly interested in seeing tangible results of their gifts, according to Lewis Coleman, the chairman of Banc of America Securities and a board member of Conservation International.</p>
        <p>As promising as the concept may be, it is clearly untested. Shifting political winds in a developing country could undo any long-term agreement that Conservation International managed to reach. And any preserved land must be monitored to prevent unauthorized use.</p>
        <p>Conservation International is quick to acknowledge that these concessions are only a part of the effort  to save the world's wilderness areas,  but it says they are important. ''One of the biggest problems with parks,'' said Richard Rice, an economist for the group who helped to develop the concept, ''is that governments don't want to make more of them.''</p>
        <p>By trying a market-based idea, the group hopes to compete more effectively with commercial interests vying for the same land.</p>
        <p>Conservation International is ''wonderfully entrepreneurial,'' said Thomas E. Lovejoy, the chief biodiversity adviser for the World Bank.</p>
        <p>''There is no reason,'' he added, ''that the conservation business can't be as creative with financing mechanisms as the normal business world.''</p>
        <p>THE BUSINESS WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
