<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INVESTING WITH: Alfred Harrison; Alliance Premier Growth Fund</title>
    <meta content="24INVO$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/business/24INVO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233296"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Alliance Premier Growth Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harrison, Alfred</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Investing With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E3D81E3BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1154" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INVESTING WITH: Alfred Harrison; Alliance Premier Growth Fund</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Danny Hakim Investing With column on Alliance Premier Growth Fund investments manager Alfred Harrison's investment strategies; photo; graph; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THESE days, Alfred Harrison lives in Minneapolis and presides over about $80 billion of investments for Alliance Capital Management. But he developed a horse sense for arbitrage during his youth, when his father took him on trips from their home in Nottingham, England, to the Newmarket racetrack.</p>
        <p>Back then, Mr. Harrison could have used the help of the region's most famous legend, Robin Hood. His parents were classical pianists, and sometimes it was a struggle just to put food on the table. But life was not without its pleasures -- his father had a love of horse racing that he shared with his son.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THESE days, Alfred Harrison lives in Minneapolis and presides over about $80 billion of investments for Alliance Capital Management. But he developed a horse sense for arbitrage during his youth, when his father took him on trips from their home in Nottingham, England, to the Newmarket racetrack.</p>
        <p>Back then, Mr. Harrison could have used the help of the region's most famous legend, Robin Hood. His parents were classical pianists, and sometimes it was a struggle just to put food on the table. But life was not without its pleasures -- his father had a love of horse racing that he shared with his son.</p>
        <p>The son proved to be a lucky bettor, and a good analyst of chance.</p>
        <p>''In those days, each bookmaker offered different odds,'' Mr. Harrison explained. ''The weight of money would bring down the price as you got closer to the race. I would bet on a horse at 5 to 1.</p>
        <p>''But this horse might come down to 2 to 1 right before the race, and another horse that had been at 4 to 1 had moved to 7 to 1,'' he said. ''So I'd have two bets. Both are done at the most propitious price.''</p>
        <p>He said he was ''almost arbitraging between bookmakers, between the different odds.''</p>
        <p>Such calculations helped Mr. Harrison, now 62, pay his way through Cambridge University, where he studied economics. But they also ''got me keenly aware of the importance of price,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That is not to say that Mr. Harrison invests like a riverboat gambler. He has obtained solid returns in his Alliance Premier Growth fund, which has $21.4 billion in six share classes. For a manager of a growth fund, he is quite measured in his approach, and last year he cautiously loaded up on value stocks.</p>
        <p>Of course, value investing -- the search for bargain stocks that have fallen out of favor, in hopes of riding a rebound -- was not the path to  shoot-out-the-lights returns last year. The big winners were growth investors who piled into technology stocks, some of which had dubious earnings or revenue pictures.</p>
        <p>But if Mr. Harrison did not jump wholeheartedly onto the technology bandwagon last year, he did not ignore it, either. At the end of November, 27.6 percent of his portfolio was in technology stocks, led by big positions in Dell Computer and Cisco Systems.</p>
        <p>That percentage was far below that of some other growth funds, which kept more than half their assets in technology. But Mr. Harrison's fund still managed a gain of 29 percent in 1999, a bit behind the average large-company growth fund, though about eight percentage points ahead of the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index. He has beaten the S.&amp; P. in four of the last five years.</p>
        <p>''Last year, prices got silly, particularly in the fourth quarter,'' Mr. Harrison said. And when prices get silly, he gets more conservative, looking at companies for the right blend of fundamentals and price.</p>
        <p>He also uses an approach Alliance calls the V-factor -- the ''V'' being a visual representation of the strategy.  When the market heads south, Mr. Harrison becomes more aggressive. When the market goes up, he becomes more cautious.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, during the technology sell-off in April, Mr. Harrison was a buyer, and by the end of June, the fund had a 39.9 percent weighting in technology. This year, the fund is up 3.3 percent, a couple of percentage points ahead of the S.&amp; P.</p>
        <p>Since its inception in 1992, Alliance Premier Growth has gained 24.5 percent, annualized, about 4.5 percentage points above the S.&amp; P. 500 and in the top 15 percent of its peer group, according to Lipper Inc.</p>
        <p>The ride has not always been smooth. In 1994, the fund lost nearly 6 percent and ranked in the bottom quarter of its peer group. It rebounded with a sterling performance over the next four years, however, ranking among the top 15 percent of its group each year.</p>
        <p>Besides managing Alliance Premier Growth, Mr. Harrison is a vice chairman at Alliance, overseeing its large-company investment team. He leads a group of money managers and analysts who preside over institutional and private accounts and a $2 billion hedge fund.</p>
        <p>''Growth to me is multifaceted,'' Mr. Harrison said. ''It's basically companies you believe have a balance sheet, industry position and management to support a 20 percent or better growth rate over the next two to three years.''</p>
        <p>About two-thirds of the portfolio is invested in the management team's favorite 25 stocks, ''the names most people recognize,'' he said. The top holdings include Intel, Pfizer and Cisco. He is also building a position in Viacom, the media conglomerate that owns CBS and MTV.</p>
        <p>The other third of the portfolio is dedicated to ''areas that aren't traditional growth stocks,'' he said. In that value vein, Mr. Harrison has been mining two beaten-down sectors this year: energy and airlines.</p>
        <p>''The energy stocks are making an enormous amount of money given their prices,'' he said. ''Airlines are doing well, earnings-wise, notwithstanding all of their problems.''</p>
        <p>A new holding is BP Amoco. ''BP has the enormous strengths of the combination of BP, Amoco and Atlantic Richfield, superb management and has had a major cost cutting program,'' he said. ''They are using earnings to step up their exploration and development.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Harrison bought Atlantic Richfield in the first quarter as a cheap way to get into BP Amoco, which completed its takeover of Atlantic Richfield in April. He bought into the combined company between $46 and $47 a share. It closed at $52.88 on Friday. He is bullish on its earnings projections over the next three years but would not hesitate to sell if market conditions shift.</p>
        <p>As for his hobbies, Mr. Harrison now prefers art to horse racing. He and his wife, Ingrid Lenz Harrison, collect German Expressionist art. But when it comes to an appreciation of price, he prefers the hardscrabble lessons of the racetrack and, he said, ''the value of a working-class upbringing in England.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
