<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PLAYING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD</title>
    <meta content="24PLAY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4DC1E3BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PLAYING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREA DELBANCO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOTT HAVEN  Capturing a Killer: Artists' Visions of Asthma</p>
        <p>New York City children are almost three times as likely to be hospitalized for asthma as are children nationwide, and the city's highest rate has been in the Bronx. Local artists have responded with various visual methods of thinking about the problem.</p>
        <p>The Io-Art Gallery and Adverse Possession Gallery are holding a group show on the subject titled ''Arthsma 2000.'' Participants include David Drucker, a cartoonist;  Meyer Tannenbaum, an abstract environmentalist; Catya Plate, who does expressionist body senses painting; and McDonald Layne, who does comparative photography.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOTT HAVEN  Capturing a Killer: Artists' Visions of Asthma</p>
        <p>New York City children are almost three times as likely to be hospitalized for asthma as are children nationwide, and the city's highest rate has been in the Bronx. Local artists have responded with various visual methods of thinking about the problem.</p>
        <p>The Io-Art Gallery and Adverse Possession Gallery are holding a group show on the subject titled ''Arthsma 2000.'' Participants include David Drucker, a cartoonist;  Meyer Tannenbaum, an abstract environmentalist; Catya Plate, who does expressionist body senses painting; and McDonald Layne, who does comparative photography.</p>
        <p>''Arthsma 2000'' through Nov. 4, Saturday and Sunday noon to 4 p.m. and by appointment; Adverse Possession Gallery, 672 East 136th Street, at Cypress Avenue, Mott Haven, Bronx; free; (718) 292-6443.</p>
        <p>HUDSON RIVER WATERFRONT  Science and Sailing At Hudson River Park Day</p>
        <p>Three miles of Hudson River Park will be connected by boat rides, live music and other activities today at the second annual Hudson River Park Day.</p>
        <p>The event opens with the parade of boats at Pier 40. Free boat, tugboat and ferry rides will be offered throughout the day. (Kayakers passing the sloop Clearwater in last year's parade are shown below.)</p>
        <p>There will be live music, beach volleyball and children's activities like face painting and a mini-golf tournament. There will also be interactive educational programs in conjunction with Liberty Science Center, the New York Hall of Science, the American Museum of Natural History, the River Project and the Hudson River Park Trust, sponsor of the event.</p>
        <p>Hudson River Park Day, today  noon to 6 p.m.; Piers 25 and 26 (at North Moore Street), Pier 40 (Houston Street) and Pier 84 (West 44th Street); free; (212) 533-7275.</p>
        <p>RIVERDALE  Balls of Vine And Funky Fungi</p>
        <p>''Beneath the Bark: Under Leaf and Leg'' is an installation created by Sylvia Benitez for Wave Hill as part of its site-specific landscape program, Generated@wavehill.</p>
        <p>Five vine balls, each up to five feet  high (pictured below), lead down a grassy slope to the woodland, where large, fungus-inspired forms emanate from tree trunks and fallen logs. There are also 23 curved steel armatures, from 3 to 12 feet high, with stout woven twine around them.</p>
        <p>''Beneath the Bark'' through Oct. 30, Tuesday through Sunday, 9 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. (until 4:30 p.m. after Oct. 14); West 249th Street at Independence Avenue, Bronx; grounds admission: $4, students and people over 65, $2, children under 6, free; free to all on Tuesdays and 9 a.m. to noon Saturdays; (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC ANTICS -- Check the claim that the ''Atlantic Antic is gigantic'' today. The Downtown Brooklyn fair, in its 26th year, begins with a Parade of Neighbors and continues with seven stages of live entertainment, 10 blocks of performers and 400 vendors of food, antiques, arts and crafts, furnishings and clothing; 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Atlantic Avenue between Fourth Avenue and Hicks Street; admission free (food and some events extra); (718) 875-8993.</p>
        <p>WORDS ON WHEELS -- The ''Poetry in Motion'' series at the New York Transit Museum rolls on with readings by Paul Muldoon, Sonia Sanchez and Grace Schulman; sponsored by the Poetry Society of America; Thursday 7 p.m.; Boerum Place and Schermerhorn Street, Brooklyn Heights; free; (718) 343-8601.</p>
        <p>STREET Y'S -- The 92nd Street Y ''Taste of the Y'' street festival livens up Lexington with demonstrations of Y programs, a musical revue by performers in ''Swing!'' at 12:15, and a chance to take a half-court basketball shot for a $92,000 prize (advance registration required); today 11 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Lexington Avenue from 79th to 94th Streets; free; (212) 996-1100.</p>
        <p>ANDREA DELBANCO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
