<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hollywood Rehearsing for Hearings Sequel</title>
    <meta content="24HOLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/politics/24HOLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233398"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Motion Picture Assn of America</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Trade Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Valenti, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Organizations/Motion Picture Association of America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E2D8163AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hollywood Rehearsing for Hearings Sequel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK LYMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Sept. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hollywood studios brace for second round of Senate hearings over Federal Trade Commission report critical of way some R-rated movies are marketed to children; industry seeks to repair any damage that report might have caused; Jack Valenti, president of Motion Picture Assn of America, says 8 high-ranking executives from 8 companies will testify and answer questions; says MPAA is working to develop initiatives that each member company can sign on to (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the second round of Senate hearings approaches on Wednesday over a Federal Trade Commission report critical of the way some R-rated movies have been marketed to children, the Hollywood studios are in the throes of deciding what exactly they are  going to say and how the movie industry can repair any damage that the report might have caused.</p>
        <p>''Eight high-ranking executives from eight companies will testify and answer questions,'' said Jack Valenti, president of the Motion Picture Association of America, which represents most of the major movie studios in Washington and administers the 32-year-old movie ratings system. ''In addition, the M.P.A.A. is working to develop initiatives that each of our member companies can sign on to, and we are in the last stages of putting that together. I am pleased that what I think we are going to present will be responsive and show that we care about doing what is right.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the second round of Senate hearings approaches on Wednesday over a Federal Trade Commission report critical of the way some R-rated movies have been marketed to children, the Hollywood studios are in the throes of deciding what exactly they are  going to say and how the movie industry can repair any damage that the report might have caused.</p>
        <p>''Eight high-ranking executives from eight companies will testify and answer questions,'' said Jack Valenti, president of the Motion Picture Association of America, which represents most of the major movie studios in Washington and administers the 32-year-old movie ratings system. ''In addition, the M.P.A.A. is working to develop initiatives that each of our member companies can sign on to, and we are in the last stages of putting that together. I am pleased that what I think we are going to present will be responsive and show that we care about doing what is right.''</p>
        <p>None of the studios was interested in saying, on the record, what they intended to tell the senators on Wednesday. ''Frankly, we have been told by every political consultant in the business that it would be political suicide for us to do so,'' said one studio official. ''Plus, it would be rude.''</p>
        <p>But several officials were willing to speculate on what types of proposals the industry would probably put forward in an effort to convince the senators -- and parents -- that they were serious about addressing the issue.</p>
        <p>Many said that the new proposals would probably be similar in tone and thrust to guidelines announced on Sept. 12 by the Walt Disney Company. At that time, Disney promised that it would, among other things, include more information for parents in its advertising, previews and World Wide Web sites about why individual films received their ratings, refrain from testing R-rated films on anyone under 17, prohibit theaters from showing previews for R-rated films before any film bearing the Disney banner (all of which are rated either G or PG) and establish a regular internal review process to make sure that the new guidelines are followed.</p>
        <p>''We are in the last stages of putting together our list and will probably finish it up on Monday or Tuesday, certainly in time to present it to the Senate committee on Wednesday,'' Mr. Valenti said.</p>
        <p>The main thrusts of the industry's response are expected to be self-policing and finding ways to help parents by giving them more information about the content of movies.</p>
        <p>Whatever the studio executives end up saying, the session will be in high contrast to the first round of hearings, on Sept. 13, when Mr. Valenti alone represented Hollywood and not a single top studio executive appeared, much to the consternation of Senator John McCain, Republican  of Arizona, the Commerce Committee chairman, and others on the panel.</p>
        <p>This time, Hollywood will be there in force.</p>
        <p>The F.T.C. report, released on Sept. 11, caught many in Hollywood by surprise. The report cited instances in which it said some of the studios, unnamed in the report, had specifically aimed their marketing campaigns for some R-rated films to entice children under 17. The commission also found instances in which even younger children were used to test-market films that eventually earned an R rating. An R rating means children under 17 must be accompanied by an adult to attend.</p>
        <p>When the Senate held hearings two days after the report's release -- and none of the studios sent representatives, saying that their executives were unavailable or had not been officially invited -- it turned into a political pile-on and a hot issue in the presidential race.</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore, whose campaign has received millions of dollars from the entertainment industry, said that if he were elected he would give the industry six months to clean up its act before considering some sort of government regulation. Last week, however, at a fund-raiser in Beverly Hills, Calif., the vice president took a more conciliatory tone, saying that his administration would never be interested in playing the role of censor.</p>
        <p>This has been seized upon by many Republicans as evidence that the Democrats are hypocritical, beholden to Hollywood donors and unlikely to put muscle behind their threats.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
