<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Prize for Being Smart</title>
    <meta content="24SONBERT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sonenberg, Nina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lichtenstein, Alice</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Genius of the World, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E1D81238F937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="907" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Prize for Being Smart</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nina Sonenberg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sonenberg, Nina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nina Sonenberg reviews novel The Genius of the World by Alice Lichtenstein (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE GENIUS OF THE WORLD</p>
        <p>By Alice Lichtenstein.</p>
        <p>305 pp. Cambridge, Mass.:</p>
        <p>Zoland Books. Paper. $13.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE GENIUS OF THE WORLD</p>
        <p>By Alice Lichtenstein.</p>
        <p>305 pp. Cambridge, Mass.:</p>
        <p>Zoland Books. Paper. $13.</p>
        <p>MANY a younger sister has lost her older brother to cooler friends, new pastimes, even a new family. For Phoebe Stein, the competition is even fiercer: not just girlfriends and skateboards but Buddhism and cancer, each staking a claim on her beloved brother, Ira.</p>
        <p>Alice Lichtenstein's first novel is an intimate record of love and loss. Narrated in part by Phoebe, ''The Genius of the World'' also captures the perspectives of Ira and their grandfather Abbey, an acclaimed physicist. The story follows the Stein family from the Northeast to California and back, jumping in time from Ira's childhood as a suburban Jewish delinquent to his impassioned conversion to Buddhism to his diagnosis -- at the age of 19 -- of terminal brain cancer.</p>
        <p>We first meet Ira as a boy fascinated by the idea that his life is an illusion. How did he come to live among these people who would have him hum Beethoven's Fifth and go to bed when he's told to? ''No matter how hard he tells himself he should listen to this man, this man is his father, it does not feel right. It does not feel right at all.'' Matters are worse at school: ''The letters too fat too tall too tippy sideways, or his hands aren't to himself, or his voice's too loud or his ears don't listen.'' Ira supposes there must be a trick; his teacher suggests a psychiatrist.</p>
        <p>Better able to meet society's demands is his grandfather Abbey. As young Ira understands it, ''a king gave Grandpa Abbey a prize for being smart,'' making Abbey ''the genius of the world.'' The grandson wonders about this mystery too, leaning in during a chess game: ''Ira has never been so close to his grandfather's brain. He wonders if he can hear the mechanism whir and click like the inside of a grandfather clock.'' Only later does Ira conclude that the ''old man didn't seem all that smart.'' The genius of the world has nothing on Ira, would-be genius of the spirit.</p>
        <p>Phoebe's occasional narration is the emotional heart of the story, as she gamely tries to stay close to her brother. Later she begs him for stories about drugs and dangerous friends, absorbing his perspective to fill her own sense of emptiness. But Ira slips away, crossing the country to wander the streets of Berkeley and then joining a community of Buddhists in San Francisco. His conversion bewilders his parents, who make light of his new name, Milarepa. But Phoebe knows that her family has been replaced.</p>
        <p>''The Genius of the World'' often reads more like a journal than a novel. Characters appear and charm us, only to vanish before we're ready to let them go. The narration mimics the speech patterns of characters in their place and time -- generally effectively, although it's hard not to wince at the jive talk of the 1970's. Phoebe herself remains indistinct, often whining about ''the true lump that is me'' and giving a sketchy feel to a novel already strung far over place, time and perspective.</p>
        <p>Still, there are moments of narrative grace. Phoebe dates men who remind her of Ira ''in larval stage,'' noting that ''I'm here to examine the chrysalis, to record the exact moment of emergence, to observe the transformation to wings. How do they do it, these 'light' people, these butterfly sons, how do they leave their families behind?'' Her quest for her brother imbues the story with compassion and longing. Even the august grandfather Abbey appears ''a-courting'' a mistress despite ''his age, which he hardly considers unless he must impress on some young man, some pipsqueak or other, just who he is talking to.'' Blissfully self-absorbed, Abbey confesses at his grandson's hospital bed: ''You can't imagine how much I wanted to believe in nuclear spin.'' But belief is Ira's department. Like Phoebe, Abbey leans in to ponder the mystery of Milarepa and his faith. While few of its characters find answers, ''The Genius of the World'' captures the trickiness and heartbreak of loving a disappearing object.</p>
        <p>Recreational</p>
        <p>We're teed up in windbreakers on the familiar coast, shanking one ball after another into the sea</p>
        <p>as if there is a lesson to be learned from watching a well-conceived idea go off-kilter and vanish.</p>
        <p>We're mired in abject denial of the fact we have taken up weekend roller-blading on soft gravel</p>
        <p>in front of the garage out back because we don't want neighbors to catch sight of us falling down.</p>
        <p>Long ago, we might have driven down to the local trout stream to fish ourselves out of a funk,</p>
        <p>hopefully on one of those forgotten weekday afternoons when the only car in the lot was our own.</p>
        <p>Somewhere along the way all those endorphins that used to kick in after a few miles died off,</p>
        <p>the body one day forsaking running uphill against the wind in the middle of winter to walk home.</p>
        <p>Not that we aren't still capable of waiting patiently to get into a game of five-on-five on the corner,</p>
        <p>it's only that we prefer shooting perfect jumpers by ourselves at the only backboard with no rim.</p>
        <p>By Tony Sanders, from ''Transit Authority'' (Grove)</p>
        <p>Nina Sonenberg is the author of ''New York: Art of the State.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Nina Sonenberg is the author of ''New York: Art of the State.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
