<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ewing Finally Takes Himself Out of the Blame Game</title>
    <meta content="Y24EWI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/sports/24EWIN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D8163AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1413" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ewing Finally Takes Himself Out of the Blame Game</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mike Wise</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An open letter to a former Knick:</p>
        <p>Dear Patrick,</p>
        <p>Before you gather your belongings and move on in your career, one final thought. It is not your fault the Knicks did not win a title the past 15 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An open letter to a former Knick:</p>
        <p>Dear Patrick,</p>
        <p>Before you gather your belongings and move on in your career, one final thought. It is not your fault the Knicks did not win a title the past 15 years.</p>
        <p>You know this already, of course.</p>
        <p>Yet with so many of your fickle legions now willing to spring for a one-way ticket to Seattle, it is a good time to reflect on what was, what might have been and why we all have a hard time coming to grips with how we felt about you and why.</p>
        <p>The fans had their reasons to blame you. You were paid the most money and became the face of the franchise. Occasionally, you were outplayed in a big game.</p>
        <p>Never mind that Michael Jordan did most of the outplaying, and that some of his other playoff conquests -- Karl Malone, John Stockton, Charles Barkley and Gary Payton -- still command reverential treatment from their fans.</p>
        <p>You know more than anyone: this is New York, a city lacking in perspective in the manner of its professional basketball team. No one could possibly view you as Ken Norton, the warrior heavyweight in the 1970's who came along at the wrong time. Somehow, in some twisted, illogical way, you were the culprit in an annual hoop tragedy.</p>
        <p>There are people at fault for not bringing a title back to Madison Square Garden since the Knicks of Willis Reed and Walt Frazier in 1973. None of them, however, had proudly worn No. 33 since 1985, dragging their sore bodies up the floor until they could barely run.</p>
        <p>Some wore Italian wool blazers and feuded with your coaches over power and control. Dave Checketts, Al Bianchi and Ernie Grunfeld came very close to putting the right players around you. But the cast you had in your prime was simply not good enough to get the job done.</p>
        <p>John Starks. Charles Oakley. Derek Harper. Anthony Mason. Heart-and-soul players, every one. But when the day ended, you were a superstar on a team of hod carriers at the construction site.</p>
        <p>When good old Ernie finally got you the bona fide All-Stars and role players you needed to make a run -- Latrell Sprewell, Allan Houston, Marcus Camby -- you were too worn down physically to be the dominating inside presence you once had been.</p>
        <p>In your one clear chance to deliver a championship, even your great coach could not help. Pat Riley admitted as much last summer, saying the one awful regret he had as coach of the Knicks was not giving Starks the hook during his 2-for-18 nightmare against Houston in Game 7 of the 1994 N.B.A. finals. Rolando Blackman, Riley said, could have given him a few minutes to rest Starks. But he stubbornly stayed with a player he respected and admired almost to a fault. He will take that to the Hall of Fame with him.</p>
        <p>Jeff Van Gundy thanks you often for saving his job, for making his career. He, too, should take some of the blame today. So fiercely loyal to you and your talent, he played you for long stretches and big minutes after the lockout ended in 1999. You were not in great shape to start with, given all the time you had spent at the labor bargaining table between October and December. You eventually broke down and could not help the team in the finals against San Antonio, the one team with two 7-foot All-Stars at their disposal.</p>
        <p>Maybe the Knicks don't make the playoffs if Van Gundy doesn't play you all those minutes; maybe he loses his job and the team is rebuilt. Either way, you were pushing the envelope with your body.</p>
        <p>Van Gundy will also take with him another regret. You arguably had the best team in May 1997. All the old and new pieces clicked as you swept Charlotte in the first round and rolled to a three-games-to-one lead on Miami. A date with a dynasty was all but ensured, Michael and the Bulls waiting for you in the conference finals.</p>
        <p>But then you and some careless teammates left the bench against the Heat during a fight on the court in Game 5. As boneheaded as it was on your part, Jeff and his staff did not make sure the team stayed put during the melee, resulting in the suspensions of five players. Your last good shot at Jordan was snuffed out, just like that.</p>
        <p>Your teammates let you down, too. No, not Starks or Charles Smith or anyone who missed a last-second shot. They go down in Garden infamy for their misfires, but at least they had the courage to take the shots. The guys who let you down were the ones who kept whispering to anyone who would listen, ''We're better off without Patrick.''</p>
        <p>Until, at the end, perception became reality.</p>
        <p>So worried about their own shots and roles, they eventually bought into the idea that you were a hindrance instead of a help. Deep down, every contributing player privately voiced that sentiment last season. They know it, and they should be ashamed of themselves.</p>
        <p>As much as they privately took shots at you, not once did you stoop to knocking any of them. Not once in 15 years.</p>
        <p>You also should place a call to your longtime agent and friend, David Falk. And terminate his services.</p>
        <p>Where was the alleged super agent when you were at your pinnacle? Was he working the phones, laying out his All-Star clients like trading cards, trying to orchestrate the one trade to bring you and New York closer to a title? Or was he picking up Jordan's dry-cleaning, making sure his No. 1 client was taken care of again?</p>
        <p>But you must also accept some of the blame. You hurt yourself by never opening up to the people who paid to see you play, who just wanted to feel like you were a part of their city.</p>
        <p>You sped past the working class on your way to your plush home in northern New Jersey, your dust the only thing remaining on many of their autograph pads. However unprofessional, many in my business took your big-time attitude personally. Even in your greatest moments, they could not separate Patrick, the player, from Patrick, the person. You had built up no reservoir of good will.</p>
        <p>Rude, selfish and downright ornery -- you could be all these things. Your great sense of humor never materialized for the masses, your 100-watt smile rarely shown. Some of the only people you treated with genuine respect were other players and coaches. Everyone else was an outsider.</p>
        <p>But then, I suppose all of us would be reluctant to share ourselves with a public that could pen a sign, ''Ewing Can't Read This,'' as some insensitive and sad college students once did while you were at Georgetown.</p>
        <p>But none of your former backers care about that; they just need someone to blame. Instead of a Steinbrenneresque character to confront, the revolving corporate door at the Garden left them one target: you.</p>
        <p>The Eastern Conference titles your teams won, the annual big games when the Garden was full of magic and noise and possibility? Forgotten. It is easier to remember the missed finger-roll against Indiana in 1995, the season-ending heartbreaks, all the times you lost instead of the many more times you won.</p>
        <p>Remember your signature line at the end of interviews, your way of telling us to stop asking questions, to leave you alone?</p>
        <p>''I'm done, fellas,'' you would say.</p>
        <p>And now, after 15 years of both grand and painful memories in New York, you are done.</p>
        <p>Done loping upcourt, carrying everyone's expectations. Done being the scapegoat for a team unwilling to admit the truth.</p>
        <p>Against incredible opposition, you gave your best and it was simply not good enough. Is that so hard and cliched for everyone to understand?</p>
        <p>Good luck in Seattle. It was a pleasure watching you work and play in New York.</p>
        <p>Sincerely,</p>
        <p>Your last fan at the Garden</p>
        <p>ON PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
