<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Sustenance for a Fan of Jazz</title>
    <meta content="24MINO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233141"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Westport Arts Center (Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilk, Max</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Minor, E Kyle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE4DC133BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Sustenance for a Fan of Jazz</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. KYLE MINOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Minor, E Kyle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of writer Max Wilk who, for past 16 years, has run Westport Arts Center's Jazz Series in Westport, Conn; Wilk, along with seven other people are chosen to receive lifetime achievement arts awards from Westport Arts Advisory Committee; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAX WILK is a respected and well-known writer in television, film, theater, fiction and nonfiction. The Westport Arts Advisory Committee in fact will honor Mr. Wilk, along with seven other people, with its lifetime achievement arts award at 2 p.m. today at Westport Town Hall.</p>
        <p>Yet there are many jazz aficionados who, without ever having read or heard a word that he has written, depend faithfully on Mr. Wilk for their musical sustenance. That's because he has run the Westport Arts Centers Jazz Series these past 16 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAX WILK is a respected and well-known writer in television, film, theater, fiction and nonfiction. The Westport Arts Advisory Committee in fact will honor Mr. Wilk, along with seven other people, with its lifetime achievement arts award at 2 p.m. today at Westport Town Hall.</p>
        <p>Yet there are many jazz aficionados who, without ever having read or heard a word that he has written, depend faithfully on Mr. Wilk for their musical sustenance. That's because he has run the Westport Arts Centers Jazz Series these past 16 years.</p>
        <p>''I'm a jazz buff,'' said Mr. Wilk from his home overlooking the Long Island Sound. ''I do this because I enjoy the concerts so much myself.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilk, 80, has, of course, a cabinet packed with the records of Duke Ellington and Ella Fitzgerald alone. He then played an obscure CD with the same enthusiasm as a child showing off his favorite birthday present. ''Heard this last year in Prague,'' he said as the Czech band ripped into a rag tune that would make King Oliver smile. ''These guys can play!''</p>
        <p>So can the talented musicians that Mr. Wilk has booked in his series: Gerry Mulligan, Maxine Sullivan, John Pizzarelli, Larry Coryell, Houston Person and Etta Jones.</p>
        <p>The pianist Bill Charlap will join Warren Vache on the cornet at 4 p.m next Sunday at the Pequot Library in Southport. The saxophonist Jane Ira Bloom and the pianist Fred Hersch will then perform a 4 p.m. concert on Nov. 12, also at the Pequot Library.</p>
        <p>''We try to get Bill Charlap up here every year,'' said Mr. Wilk, who is old enough to have seen Mr. Charlap's father, Moose Charlap, play years ago. ''Bill has a very loyal following up here.''</p>
        <p>The Westport Arts Center Jazz Series started when Don Elliott, who lived in Westport, gave a concert toward the end of his life at town hall. ''Don, who was one of the best of his time, was sick and his wife Doris said we should do a concert,'' Mr. Wilk said, ''The audience loved it. Afterwards, Joyce Thompson, who was head of the arts center, suggested we do a series.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilk eagerly agreed to coordinate the program, which started at the Greens Farms Academy concert hall. It then moved to the arts center on Morningside Drive until the town reclaimed the space to use as a school. Since then the series has been continued at the Pequot Library in Southport. ''Definitely the best acoustics available in the area,'' Mr. Wilk said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilk's love for jazz started when he was 15. ''I remember I was madly in love with Duke Ellington,''  he said. His passion was fed during his years at Yale, where he studied theater.</p>
        <p>''A classmate of mine, George Avakian, was the son of a record producer and used to play a lot of jazz,'' he said. ''We listened to Louis Armstrong and Bessie Smith all of the time.''</p>
        <p>One night in the late 1930's, Mr. Wilk went to an Ellington concert in New Haven. After the concert, another classmate invited Mr. Ellington to have lunch with him at the Jonathan Edwards dining hall the next day. It was memorable for Mr. Wilk because he witnessed an embarrassing display of racial prejudice.</p>
        <p>''I thought, here's Duke Ellington coming to have lunch on campus with us,'' he said. ''And you know what happened? Half of the students got up and left when he sat down at the table.''</p>
        <p>Through the years Mr. Wilk would go to hear the best players of the 40's and 50's play at New York's legendary 52nd Street clubs, where Thelonius Monk and Charlie Parker were creating the bebop style. Whether he was working in television in New York or in Hollywood, Mr. Wilk would catch as many rising stars as he could. He still does.</p>
        <p>''That's why I do this,'' said Mr. Wilk, who volunteers his time booking the acts for the jazz series. ''All you need to know is the right numbers to call and say, Do you want to play with so-and-so? Then I get to sit back and hear some of the best music in the world.''</p>
        <p>The pianist Bill Charlap will join Warren Vache on the cornet at 4 p.m next Sunday at the Pequot Library in Southport. Ticket prices are $20 ($5 for 16 years and under). The saxophonist Jane Ira Bloom and the pianist Fred Hersch will then perform a 4 p.m. concert on Nov. 12, also at the Pequot Library. Ticket prices are $20 ($5 for 16 years and under). Call the Westport Arts Center at (203) 222-7070 or visit the Web site (wwww.westportartscenter.org) for more information.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
