<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Takes an Approach Both Risky and Calculated</title>
    <meta content="24MEMO$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/politics/24MEMO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E2D9173AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1095" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Takes an Approach Both Risky and Calculated</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore hopes to ride public's trepidation about big oil, big drug companies, big health insurers and big polluters all the way to White House; it has been decades since politician denounced such broad array of corporate targets with such pointed language; for Gore, it is part of broader positioning of his campaign as ' for the people,' while portraying Gov George W Bush and Republicans as 'for the powerful'; Gore's tactic is not without risk of being branded hypocrite (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They are bad. Really bad. Malevolent even. And not just bad. They are big. Big and bad, like those nightmarish, saw-toothed meanies that lurk beneath the bed.</p>
        <p>They are Vice President Al Gore's bogeymen -- big oil, big drug companies, big health insurers, big polluters. For good measure, Mr. Gore still throws in big tobacco from time to time. They are out there, threatening America's prosperity. And like politicians before him, Mr. Gore hopes to ride the public's trepidation about them all the way to the White House.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They are bad. Really bad. Malevolent even. And not just bad. They are big. Big and bad, like those nightmarish, saw-toothed meanies that lurk beneath the bed.</p>
        <p>They are Vice President Al Gore's bogeymen -- big oil, big drug companies, big health insurers, big polluters. For good measure, Mr. Gore still throws in big tobacco from time to time. They are out there, threatening America's prosperity. And like politicians before him, Mr. Gore hopes to ride the public's trepidation about them all the way to the White House.</p>
        <p>America has a tradition of populist politics, and in most cases the strategy has worked best when the enemy has been given a face. For William Jennings Bryan it was the banks. For Theodore Roosevelt it was the railroads and other ''malefactors of great wealth.'' William Howard Taft, Woodrow Wilson and Franklin D. Roosevelt busted the trusts. John F. Kennedy took on U.S. Steel.</p>
        <p>But it has been decades since a politician denounced such a broad array of corporate targets with such pointed language. For Mr. Gore, it is all part of the broader positioning of his campaign as ''for the people,'' and the other side -- Gov. George W. Bush and the Republicans -- as ''for the powerful.''</p>
        <p>''I have never hesitated,'' Mr. Gore said on Friday, ''to take on big oil or the big pharmaceutical companies or the H.M.O.'s or whoever was operating in a way that was not in the best interest of the middle-class families of this country.''</p>
        <p>Like most campaign messages these days, Mr. Gore's assault is rooted in extensive polling and focus-group surveys that suggest deep public frustration with rising prices and, in the case of health maintenance organizations, confounding red tape. Populism has proven most effective, historians say, in times of economic inequality, and Mr. Gore's target audience includes those who feel they have not shared in the good times.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gore's tactic is not without risk. Another important component of his message is the taking of credit for the country's economic health, including the 22 million jobs created in the Clinton years. By setting his sights on central industries, Mr. Gore may create the perception that he is fighting the very businesses that have generated those jobs.</p>
        <p>Then there is the risk of being branded a hypocrite. One major industry that Mr. Gore does not group with his litany of corporate offenders is big entertainment, which he condemns separately in speeches for marketing violence to children even as he solicits its executives for hefty campaign contributions.</p>
        <p>Because it has been so long since any prominent politician tried Mr. Gore's approach, it is hard to predict how it will be received, said Alan Brinkley, a presidential historian at Columbia University.</p>
        <p>''Gore is using it very carefully, making attacks against specific targets and not more broadly against concentrated economic power,'' Mr. Brinkley said. ''I don't see how he could be perceived as antibusiness given the very centrist economic policy he's promoting and has been identified with over time.''</p>
        <p>But Jerry J. Jasinowski, the president of the National Association of Manufacturers, said Mr. Gore had convinced the business sector, particularly leaders of small companies, that he is against private enterprise.</p>
        <p>''We know in an election that things are said and done that wouldn't happen in normal times,'' Mr. Jasinowski said. ''But words mean something, and these words are irresponsible.''</p>
        <p>Clearly, Mr. Gore long ago discarded any instinct to soft-pedal his message. In speeches about oil pricing on Thursday and Friday, he pledged to ''work toward the day when we are free forever of the dominance of big oil and foreign oil.''</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Bush and his running mate, Dick Cheney, both served as executives in the oil business, Mr. Gore said the Republican ticket was ''of big oil, for big oil and by big oil.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Gore turns his sights on  managed care, he laments that doctors' decisions are being ''overruled by some bean counter'' who ''doesn't have a right to play God.'' When the target is the prescription drug manufacturers, he describes them as having ''so much power and so much wealth -- by all odds the most profitable industry in America.''</p>
        <p>That claim is true, according to a Fortune magazine survey that placed pharmaceutical profits in 1999 at 18.9 percent. The industry responds that it spends a hefty portion of profits on developing new drugs, though studies show that a larger share is devoted to marketing.</p>
        <p>''While this pattern of attack may be good politics for the vice president,'' said Alan F. Holmer, president of the Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers of America, ''it misleads the public about the industry that continues to develop important new medicines.''</p>
        <p>Oil industry officials and analysts said this week that they were distressed by Mr. Gore's offensive because, they maintain, domestic petroleum pricing is primarily a product of foreign supply. Profits are up this year, but the industry was battered last year by plummeting prices. Oil profit rates for the first half of this year were 6.8 percent, according to Business Week, compared with 7 percent for all United States industries.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Gore is either extremely badly informed or he's being extremely disingenuous,'' said J. Robinson West, the chairman of Petroleum Finance Company, which provides strategic advice to oil companies.</p>
        <p>Karl Rove, the chief strategist for the Bush campaign, said the primary effect of Mr. Gore's ''screechy left-wing populism'' was to stem the flow of liberal support to Ralph Nader and the Green Party. And he pointed out that Mr. Gore's running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut, had received heavy campaign contributions from the insurance and pharmaceutical industries, and that Mr. Gore's family had profited from Occidental Petroleum mineral leases.</p>
        <p>But Mark D. Fabiani, Mr. Gore's deputy campaign director, said the vice president had credibility because he fought against price-fixing in the oil and natural-gas industry in Congress and was an early supporter of generic drugs.</p>
        <p>''In good times,'' he said, ''you have economic power built up and sometimes it builds up to excess. Now it's time to make sure that elements of the economy that are blocking the prosperity of others, primarily families, is brought under control.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
