<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reporter's Notebook; In Real Life, N.Y.P.D. Blue Has Soft Side</title>
    <meta content="24NOTE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="46" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/nyregion/24NOTE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiser, Benjamin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meskini, Abdel Ghani</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DB173AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="824" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reporter's Notebook; In Real Life, N.Y.P.D. Blue Has Soft Side</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN WEISER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weiser, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reporter's Notebook column discusses NYC police interrogation of terrorism suspect Abdel Ghani Meskini (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a member of the F.B.I.'s Joint Terrorist Task Force for more than 15 years, Detective Thomas Corrigan of the New York City Police has interviewed many suspects in terrorism investigations.</p>
        <p>But as he questioned an Algerian man arrested in Brooklyn last Dec. 30, the detective was struck by how differently that interview was going.  ''I mean he was friendly, wanted to be cooperative,'' the detective said in Federal District Court in Manhattan last week. ''I found him actually kind of streetwise, almost loosey-goosey.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As a member of the F.B.I.'s Joint Terrorist Task Force for more than 15 years, Detective Thomas Corrigan of the New York City Police has interviewed many suspects in terrorism investigations.</p>
        <p>But as he questioned an Algerian man arrested in Brooklyn last Dec. 30, the detective was struck by how differently that interview was going.  ''I mean he was friendly, wanted to be cooperative,'' the detective said in Federal District Court in Manhattan last week. ''I found him actually kind of streetwise, almost loosey-goosey.''</p>
        <p>The man, Abdel Ghani Meskini, 32, has been charged with assisting a suspected terrorist plot timed around the New Year's celebrations that authorities said was interrupted with the arrest Dec. 14 of another man, Ahmed Ressam, as he crossed the border into Washington in a car the police said contained explosives.</p>
        <p>Detective Corrigan and several agents of the Federal Bureau of Investigation kept Mr. Meskini talking for almost 11 hours after taking him into custody, records show, and by the detective's account, the conversation was good-humored, even with Mr. Meskini in leg irons and handcuffed to a railing.</p>
        <p>At one point, Detective Corrigan recalled, Mr. Meskini said that he liked to watch ''N.Y.P.D. Blue,'' and was familiar with its star character, Andy Sipowicz, a tough-talking detective known for his willingness to rough up suspects who will not talk.</p>
        <p>''I guess he felt that we were treating him fairly decently as opposed to some of the characters on that show,'' Detective Corrigan testified in court. Mr. Meskini told him something like, ''This isn't like N.Y.P.D. Blue,'' Detective Corrigan said. ''I just remember that I took a lot of ribbing for being Sipowicz.''</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Meskini, who also testified about his interrogation, he made clear that he wanted to talk because he felt wrongly accused. ''I said, 'I have nothing to do with terrorism. The only thing I do is I'm a thief. I do credit card scams. That's all.' ''</p>
        <p>That was putting it mildly. By his own account, Mr. Meskini was an inveterate liar and fraud. When he lived in Boston in the mid-1990's, he became so successful at defrauding banks that he decided to leave the country and go to Canada so that he would not be caught.</p>
        <p>When he arrived at the border, he said, he lied to the immigration officials there, saying he wanted political asylum. Once in Canada, he said, he turned around and sneaked back into the United States.</p>
        <p>When he was arrested in Brooklyn last December, false forms of identification were found in his apartment. He said these were used to defraud credit card companies.</p>
        <p>''So you are generally a dishonest person, right?'' the judge, John F. Keenan, asked him at one point.</p>
        <p>''Yes,'' Mr. Meskini replied.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meskini, who came to the United States from Algeria in 1995, had a good command of the English language, as well as American slang, Detective Corrigan said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meskini, who has pleaded not guilty, confirmed this in his own testimony. He said one of his interrogators warned that he had better assist in the investigation or he would face a long prison sentence.</p>
        <p>''He told me that I'm the 'big fish' and I better, you know, cooperate or I'm going to go for 25 years.''</p>
        <p>He said the agent told him that he would no longer have to worry about ''rent or the problem of Y2K.''</p>
        <p>It was like a line from ''N.Y.P.D. Blue.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Meskini's testimony was intended to support the case he and his lawyer had made in court papers that Mr. Meskini was treated unfairly by the authorities, deprived of his rights and pressured to talk.</p>
        <p>But on the witness stand, Mr. Meskini largely acknowledged that his interrogators did not threaten him, or even raise their voice.</p>
        <p>His lawyer, Roland Thau, gamely pushed on, trying to elicit some useful testimony. Sometimes, Judge Keenan grew testy, but the frostiness did not last long. The judge and Mr. Thau go back a long way. Mr. Thau, 66, practiced as a young lawyer in the criminal courts when Judge Keenan, now 70, was a prosecutor for the Manhattan district attorney.</p>
        <p>So it seemed natural when Judge Keenan paused last Tuesday to say that he had discovered a typographical error in the record of the previous day's hearing.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Thau, just one thing,'' the judge said, ''because the record is always important.''</p>
        <p>Judge Keenan pointed out the mistake, which showed Mr. Thau forming an illogical sentence, and said he would correct it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thau said he was grateful for the catch.</p>
        <p>''My experience up to now has been that judges only correct language that makes them look like fools,'' Mr. Thau told the judge. ''but never language that makes the lawyers look like fools.''</p>
        <p>''It's a sincere thanks,'' Mr. Thau added, ''believe me.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
