<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dallas</title>
    <meta content="DALLAS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/travel/DALLAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S DOING IN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dallas (Tex)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Kathryn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/What's Doing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Dallas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E1DF173BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1946" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dallas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHRYN JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Kathryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>What's Doing In column describes upcoming events, sights, lodging and restaurants in Dallas, Tex; photos; chart; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the sweltering summer (and this year's, with record-breaking heat, was no exception), Dallas comes alive in the fall when cooler temperatures and the State Fair of Texas arrive. The first state fair, in 1886, dazzled visitors with livestock shows, displays of fancy needlework and rides on flying-jennies (primitive carousels). More than 100 years later, Texas' rural roots will still be evident, with blue ribbons awarded for champion bulls, the finest handmade quilts and the best apple pie.</p>
        <p>But Dallas, a high-tech hot spot, isn't playing host in a time warp. This year the fair's theme is Celebrating the 21st Century, and the city is doing so with lots of gadgetry. So after sizing up the pygmy goats and miniature donkeys, visitors can visit a Robot Zoo with gigantic animals -- including a 10-foot chameleon with a tongue that the kids (and grown-ups, too) can control with a joystick. A ''home of tomorrow'' features futuristic appliances and communications gizmos. Then it's time for a low-tech tradition -- a spin on the 20-story-tall Texas Star Ferris wheel. Yes, some things really are bigger in Texas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After the sweltering summer (and this year's, with record-breaking heat, was no exception), Dallas comes alive in the fall when cooler temperatures and the State Fair of Texas arrive. The first state fair, in 1886, dazzled visitors with livestock shows, displays of fancy needlework and rides on flying-jennies (primitive carousels). More than 100 years later, Texas' rural roots will still be evident, with blue ribbons awarded for champion bulls, the finest handmade quilts and the best apple pie.</p>
        <p>But Dallas, a high-tech hot spot, isn't playing host in a time warp. This year the fair's theme is Celebrating the 21st Century, and the city is doing so with lots of gadgetry. So after sizing up the pygmy goats and miniature donkeys, visitors can visit a Robot Zoo with gigantic animals -- including a 10-foot chameleon with a tongue that the kids (and grown-ups, too) can control with a joystick. A ''home of tomorrow'' features futuristic appliances and communications gizmos. Then it's time for a low-tech tradition -- a spin on the 20-story-tall Texas Star Ferris wheel. Yes, some things really are bigger in Texas.</p>
        <p>Autumn also brings a full schedule of cultural activities. Texas' strong connection to Mexico is highlighted at the state fair and at the Dallas Museum of Art with several exhibitions of Mexican paintings and architecture, and the flavors of Mexico's interior are the focus at a number of new cosmopolitan restaurants.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>The State Fair of Texas, (214) 565-9931, is the nation's biggest such festival in length and attendance. This year's fair opens on Friday and runs until Oct. 22 and is expected to draw about three and a half million people. Since 1886 the fair has been held east of downtown in Fair Park, a 277-acre National Historic Landmark with a large number of restored Art Deco buildings that house several permanent museums. ''Sacred Space,'' 150 mural-size color photographs of sacred landscapes and architecture in Mexico, Guatemala, Honduras and the American Southwest by Carolyn Brown, a Dallas photographer, will be held in the Hall of State.</p>
        <p>A new attraction is the Women's Museum: An Institution for the Future, a permanent project (in association with the Smithsonian) that chronicles women's contributions in science, politics, the arts and other fields through computer displays and more traditional exhibits. Admission: $5, $4 under age 12 and $3 seniors and students.</p>
        <p>In addition to the Robot Zoo at The Science Place, children will want to visit an exhibit at the Dallas Museum of Natural History. Life-size models of dinosaurs, including Tyrannosaurus rex, which once roamed Texas, loom above visitors in dioramas with lifelike murals and sounds.</p>
        <p>Standing-room-only concerts, held outdoors in a plaza that gets crowded very quickly, are included in the fair admission price. Performers will include Mary Wilson of the Supremes on Friday, and Destiny's Child and Christina Aguilera on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Fair admission is $10, $6 for those 60 and older or children under 4 feet tall, and free for children under age 2. Rides, games and food (numerous booths serve everything from corn dogs to ethnic fare) cost extra. Hours are 10 a.m. to 10 p.m., but can vary.</p>
        <p>The Dallas Museum of Art, 1717 North Harwood Street, (214) 922-1200, will present the Jacques and Natasha Gelman Collection of modern Mexican painting Oct. 8 to Jan. 28, with works by Diego Rivera, Frida Kahlo, Rufino Tamayo, Jose Clemente Orozco, David Alfaro Siqueiros and Carlos Merida. Museum admission is free (its permanent collection features American, European, Asian and African galleries), but the Gelman exhibition, including audio guides, costs $10, $8 for seniors and students, and $5 for children under 12. Open Tuesday to Sunday 11 a.m. to 5 p.m., and Thursday to 9.</p>
        <p>Dallas's live-music scene picks up in September and October. At the Smirnoff Music Center, an amphitheater in Fair Park, B. B. King brings his blues festival to town on Sunday ($20.50 to $49), and Carlos Santana takes the stage Oct. 5 ($29 to $62). Ticket prices vary with location -- the cheapest are on the lawn, where concertgoers can take their own blankets or chairs.</p>
        <p>The Doobie Brothers perform at open-air Artist Square downtown, 1800 Leonard Street, on Oct. 14. Tickets ($50 to $125) from Ticketmaster: (214) 373-8000.</p>
        <p>The Dallas Symphony Orchestra, (214) 692-0203, conducted by Andrew Litton, continues its fall classical season with music by Ravel, Thursday to Sunday in the I. M. Pei-designed Morton H. Meyerson Symphony Center, 2301 Flora Street. The Mozart Great Mass will be performed Oct. 19 to 22 at 8 P.M, Sunday  matinee at 2:30. Tickets from $12.</p>
        <p>Sightseeing</p>
        <p>Many people still associate Dallas with President Kennedy's assassination in 1963. On any given day, visitors dot the grassy knoll downtown at Dealey Plaza and gaze up at the former Texas School Book Depository. The Sixth Floor Museum at Dealey Plaza, 411 Elm Street, (214) 747-6660, takes its name and location from where Lee Harvey Oswald fired the fatal shots. It sensitively depicts Kennedy's life and assassination with film clips, photographs and records. Open 9 a.m. to 6 p.m. daily. Admission, with an audiotape guide, is $10; $8 for those 65 or older, students and children; and free for children under age 6.</p>
        <p>For a different view of ''what really happened,'' the Conspiracy Museum, 110 South Market Street, (214) 741-3040, explores conspiracy theories related to the assassinations of John F. Kennedy, Robert Kennedy, Martin Luther King and Abraham Lincoln with exhibits and memorabilia. The museum, operated by self-styled ''assassinologists,'' is open daily 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission is $7; $6 for seniors and students, $3 for children 9 to 12 and free for children under age 9.</p>
        <p>Dallas's status as a modern business capital is more a result of its beginnings as a mercantile and financial hub than of its role as a center of the cattle industry, although cattle drives cut through downtown as recently as the 1850's. Now there's a permanent cattle drive in bronze -- the ''Trailing Longhorns'' sculpture at Pioneer Plaza at Young and Griffin streets, where 40 bronze longhorn steers appear to be stampeding down a hill, driven by three cowboys on horseback.</p>
        <p>Though admittedly not in a class with Vermont, Texas has colorful fall foliage, and one of the best shows is at the Dallas Arboretum, 8525 Garland Road on the eastern shore of White Rock Lake, (214) 327-4901. Stands of Japanese maples, sweet gum and other trees blaze with color (peak viewing time is late October to late November). The arboretum has planted more than 17,000 chrysanthemums for its fall festival, America the Bountiful, from Oct. 7 to Nov. 12. Weekends are geared to families, with a maze made of bales of hay that kids can explore, vegetable gardens and a pumpkin patch with rare varieties of pumpkin. Open 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. daily in fall and winter. Admission is $6, $5 ages 65 and older, $3 ages 6 to 12 and free under 6. Parking is $3.</p>
        <p>Dallas has three concentrations of clubs, lounges and live music hangouts: downtown's West End, the Deep Ellum neighborhood east of downtown and lower Greenville Avenue. Poor David's Pub, 1924 Greenville Avenue, (214) 821-9891, is a fixture on the local music scene with an eclectic mix of live music. Covers range with the featured band from zero to $25.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>The recently renovated red brick Melrose Hotel, 3015 Oak Lawn Avenue, (800) 635-7673, fax (214) 521-2470, built in 1924, has 184 rooms in a charming older neighborhood between downtown and the exclusive Highland Park area. Doubles start at $149 for weekends and $219 weekdays. The high-ceilinged rooms are equipped with antique-style furnishings and minibars.</p>
        <p>For a bed-and-breakfast that is centrally situated 15 minutes from downtown but secluded, the Courtyard on the Trail, (214) 553-9700, fax (214) 553-5542, is near scenic White Rock Lake. The three rooms -- a suite with a sitting room, a room with Southwestern decor, and a room with a king-size bed and a marble bathroom -- have French doors leading to a pool or garden. Prices range from $110 to $155.</p>
        <p>Budget: The Clarion Inn, 7138 North Stemmons Freeway, (214) 461-2677, fax (214) 461-2678, is a 10-minute drive from downtown. The hotel's 62 rooms are furnished simply but comfortably, and have small refrigerators. The standard double rate, $79 weekdays and $69 weekends, includes breakfast.</p>
        <p>Luxury: The Mansion on Turtle Creek, 2821 Turtle Creek Boulevard, (800) 527-5432, fax (214) 528-4187, routinely draws the rich and famous. The nine-story hotel is built around  a terra cotta-colored Spanish Colonial mansion that serves as the restaurant. All 141 rooms have chaises longues, love seats and French doors that open onto private balconies. The standard rate is $440 to $530, with discounts based on dates and availability. The Mansion on Turtle Creek restaurant, (214) 526-2121, pioneered upscale Southwestern cuisine (with tortilla soup and lobster tacos). A three-course dinner for two with modest wine is at least $200, but a $20 prix fixe three-course lunch was recently added.</p>
        <p>The Adams Mark Hotel, 400 North Olive Street, (800) 444-2326, fax (214) 922-0308, on the eastern edge of downtown, is Texas' largest hotel. Its 1,844 eclectically decorated rooms are equipped with sitting areas and armoires, and are within walking distance of the Museum of Art, the Meyerson Center and the financial district. Standard doubles: $210.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>At Star Canyon, 3102 Oak Lawn Avenue, (214) 520-7827, the chef, Stephan Pyles, puts a spicy spin on Texas favorites like fried catfish and rib-eye steak -- served under a mound of thin fried onion rings encrusted with ground chilies. Reservations are a must. Dinner for two, with wine, is about $150.</p>
        <p>Ciudad D.F., 3888 Oak Lawn Avenue, Suite 135, (214) 219-3141, is one of the best of a growing number of restaurants that offer Mexico City-style cuisine in a sophisticated setting. Specials include duck flautas and ravioli stuffed with cheese and poblano chilies with vanilla-bean shrimp. Dinner for two, with wine or margaritas, is about $90.</p>
        <p>Gloria's, 3715 Greenville Avenue, (214) 874-0088, is a favorite for  its colorful atmosphere and Latin American cuisine, including Salvadoran dishes like banana-wrapped tamales stuffed with chicken and a full Mexican menu. Dinner for two, with beer or a margarita, about $35.</p>
        <p>For funky atmosphere, head south across the Trinity River to Tillman's Corner, 324 West Seventh at Bishop, (214) 942-0988, a big informal space furnished with 50's knickknacks. Chicken breast grilled with lime and cilantro with stir-fried vegetables and black-bean and corn salsa is excellent; specials, like grilled scallops over angel hair pasta, are reliably good. Dinner for two with wine, about $60.</p>
        <p>One of the cheapest and best meals in Dallas is barbecue, and there are many good spots throughout the city. Peggy Sue BBQ, 6600 Snider Plaza (near Southern Methodist University), (214) 987-9188, has lean, sweet ribs, brisket and turkey, good vegetables and delicious fried pies. A meal for two with beer is under $25.</p>
        <p>WHAT'S DOING IN KATHRYN JONES is a writer-at-large for Texas Monthly magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">KATHRYN JONES is a writer-at-large for Texas Monthly magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
