<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Neighbors and Kin Join as Cast</title>
    <meta content="24BERG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233204"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bergen County Players</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beller, Peter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Oliver! (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6DE113BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1390" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Neighbors and Kin Join as Cast</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER BELLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beller, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>ORADELL</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on close-knit and long-lasting personal and professional relationships among members of Bergen County Players, which is staging production of Oliver; photos (Special Issue: Entertainment) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR a community theater, the Bergen County Players, who perform in the Little Firehouse Theater in Oradell, have an unusually close-knit membership. The group has become a second home to many of the 350 members and long-lasting personal, and professional relationships are common. In some cases entire families participate in productions.</p>
        <p>So it was that during one of the final rehearsals for ''Oliver,'' this season's opening production, that many of the children in the musical had parents in the cast and crew elsewhere in the building.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR a community theater, the Bergen County Players, who perform in the Little Firehouse Theater in Oradell, have an unusually close-knit membership. The group has become a second home to many of the 350 members and long-lasting personal, and professional relationships are common. In some cases entire families participate in productions.</p>
        <p>So it was that during one of the final rehearsals for ''Oliver,'' this season's opening production, that many of the children in the musical had parents in the cast and crew elsewhere in the building.</p>
        <p>All through ''hell week'' -- the term for these last grueling days -- children in period costume packed the backstage, the lights turned out because of the heat.</p>
        <p>Thirteen-year-old Joe Kiely, whose father, John, is in the cast, joked, ''We're only in one scene together so I'll tolerate him.''</p>
        <p>Larry Landsman, whose makeup rendered him instantly recognizable as the character Fagin, said he was thrilled to be working with his wife, Alyson, the stage manager, and his 8-year-old son, Jared.</p>
        <p>''I look at it as a home away from home,'' Mr. Landsman said of the theater. ''We grew up there, my son is growing up there.''</p>
        <p>Jared said: ''You'd think that doing this for so long it would get boring. But I'm still having fun.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Landsman met his wife at the theater in 1984. Sixteen other couples met there for the first time. One even had their wedding there.</p>
        <p>Founded by several small groups of actors in 1932, the company moved to its present location in 1949 after Oradell built a new firehouse, leaving the old one unused. With a budget of $150,000 the company puts on seven shows in its 210-seat theater and three one-performance shows in smaller spaces. In addition, playwrights and other professionals are invited for a series of talks and special performances.</p>
        <p>All members must learn two backstage activities, like lights, sound or props. They can also create and perform workshops at the monthly meetings to showcase their talents in hopes of becoming one of the theater's directors. Instruction is given to anyone who wants to try something new.</p>
        <p>''It's not a community theater in the traditional sense,'' said Lawrence Brustofski, a 42-year-old sales consultant who has the part of the malevolent Bill Sykes, a role he said he relishes. ''The level of production is as good or better than the professional shows I've worked on.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brustofski joined the theater four years ago with very little experience and, after getting a part in ''The Pajama Game,'' began to land acting jobs.</p>
        <p>Now, after 17 shows, 4 of them with the Bergen County Players, and an Oober nomination for best actor in an Off Off Broadway production, Mr. Brustofski is still the head of the House Committee, which cleans the theater.</p>
        <p>''What they don't want is people coming in and doing a big role and never showing up again,'' Mr. Brustofski said. ''The only way a theater like the Bergen County Players can flourish is through people coming down and doing some work.''</p>
        <p>He added that many of the actors he has worked with, including Frank Avellino, who is directing ''Oliver,'' are now close friends. His performance in a play by Mr. Avellino, ''Ice in April,'' got him the nomination. The production won best play' for off-off-Broadway.</p>
        <p>Robert McClure, who just graduated from high school this year and hopes to be a professional actor, joined the Bergen County Players after attending almost every performance of ''Sweeney Todd'' in 1997, which starred Mr. Brustofski. Mr. McClure was invited to the cast party and ended up joining the group, acting in ''Gypsy'' and ''A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum.'' ''I was just blown away by the cooperation,'' Mr. McClure said. ''Everyone is there because they love theater -- for no other reason.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McClure plays Noah Claypole in ''Oliver'' conducted a workshop this month.</p>
        <p>Two of the people in that are from Forum and the other two are from Oliver ''so you can see how closely knit it is,'' he said, adding that he hangs out with his friends from the theater. ''They are not just acquaintances.''</p>
        <p>He also learned to do sound and his first makeup job was Mr. Landsman's, a two-hour endeavor with results that frighten the unsuspecting.</p>
        <p>''They really let you explore what your options are in the theater,'' Mr. McClure said, ''they make you aware that everyone is there to help you.''</p>
        <p>Rob DeScherer has been the president of the Bergen County Players for the last three months. ''You can do anything you want to if you have the energy and desire,'' Mr. De Scherer said. ''Whether you want to get involved in the technical side or the artistic side, you can learn.'' Mr. DeScherer has never appeared on stage but nevertheless puts in the hours.</p>
        <p>Framed letters from Ronald Reagan, Helen Hayes and Frank Sinatra hang on the wall in the basement.</p>
        <p>Allison Smith, Robert Sean Leonard, Beth Fowler and Mary Higgins Clark are among the theater's alumni.</p>
        <p>There are also photographs of all the sets over the years, many of them very elaborate, from ''Mikado'' to ''How to Succeed in Business Without Really Trying,'' in which he played opposite his future wife. ''That was the backstage romance for that year,'' he said. He remembers joining because of ''the need for a larger circle of friends, a need to be accepted by a group of my peers and this was a wonderful outlet.''</p>
        <p>In the frantic final days before ''Oliver'' opened, Frank Avellino, the director and Joseph Scorese, the musical director, were consumed with the largest production the Bergen County Players have ever attempted.</p>
        <p>''A show like 'Oliver' has two challenges musically,'' Mr. Scorese said. ''It has kids, it has accents.'' The younger actors tend to pick up the accent faster, he said. A lawyer who is working with the group for the first time, Mr. Scorese said he thought that ''community theaters as a vehicle are really in jeopardy'' because of the increasing number of hours people work. ''There's a handful of theaters like this in the state.''</p>
        <p>One thing that draws actors and crew alike is a director like Frank Avellino, who has been with the company for 15 years. The first thing Mr. Avellino asked of all the actors, including the children, was to invent a past for their character which would explain every line, every action they perform.</p>
        <p>''I gave him a rough childhood,'' Grant MacDermott, 13, said of his character, the Artful Dodger. An eighth-grader from Teaneck, he said he had intended to walk away from his audition with a rejection -- in the hopes that he could get used to it early on. He said he has learned much from the experience of having a major part and from Mr. Avellino.</p>
        <p>Joshua Zenreich, who is playing Oliver, said Mr. Avellino preached, ''Whatever you want to do, just do it.''</p>
        <p>To perfect his accent Joshua watched episodes of Monty Python. Asked if he was nervous about appearing in front of an audience, he said, ''I'm more nervous with three people than a hundred because I know who those three people are.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Avellino said: ''The thing that I was most afraid of was, how do I talk to a kid? How do I get a kid to see the light?''</p>
        <p>The solution was not to talk down to them.</p>
        <p>The week before the show opens, Mr. Avellino said, the theater is filled with energy. ''I don't yell at people. I'm not good at confrontation,'' Mr. Avellino said, adding that his duties depended on the actors. ''Without them I'd be sitting at home in my living room.''</p>
        <p>Outside at the box office, Mr. Landsman promptly turned around at the sight of patrons, who, upon seeing his face, burst into laughter.</p>
        <p>''There's a magic in the theater which we're seeing right now,'' he said. ''It's a relief when it all comes together.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
