<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Agbayani Turns Focus To the Coming Playoffs</title>
    <meta content="24SHEA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/sports/24BOOK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: METS NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE5D9173AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Agbayani Turns Focus To the Coming Playoffs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Sept. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Benny Agbayani knew the feeling, and it was one he never wanted to have return. Agbayani, the Mets' left fielder, stepped on home plate with his right foot after hitting a ground ball on Friday night, and when he slipped, he strained his right hamstring.</p>
        <p>The injury hampered him in college and in 1998, when he missed a month. He knows the recovery can be frustrating, full of good days and setbacks. With the regular season ending in a week, Agbayani is concerned about his status for the playoffs -- assuming the Mets make them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Benny Agbayani knew the feeling, and it was one he never wanted to have return. Agbayani, the Mets' left fielder, stepped on home plate with his right foot after hitting a ground ball on Friday night, and when he slipped, he strained his right hamstring.</p>
        <p>The injury hampered him in college and in 1998, when he missed a month. He knows the recovery can be frustrating, full of good days and setbacks. With the regular season ending in a week, Agbayani is concerned about his status for the playoffs -- assuming the Mets make them.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to do as much as possible to get back on the field,'' he said. ''It's not like spring training, when I've got time. I've just got three days at least, maybe four. I'm going to try to rehab it as soon as possible. If it was spring training, then I could rest for two weeks and come back. But I don't have that time.''</p>
        <p>Darryl Hamilton started in left field tonight against the Phillies, with Timo Perez starting in center and batting leadoff, where Agbayani has been hitting. Center fielder Jay Payton was feeling better but got another day off because of the flu. Manager Bobby Valentine said he had not thought about who would replace Agbayani on a long-term basis, but he said, ''I think we have plenty of guys.''</p>
        <p>Hamilton and Perez bat left-handed and can play left; Bubba Trammell, a right-handed hitter like Agbayani, can also play left.</p>
        <p>Valentine said that the Mets would check on Agbayani's progress daily and that there was no way of knowing how long it would take for the injury to heal.</p>
        <p>Agbayani said he did not want to set a timetable; as Agbayani knows, hamstring injuries can cost players a month or more.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of frustrating, because if you try to rush back too soon, something else might happen,'' he said. ''It's just a nagging thing. It's usually something that just heals on its own. I've had it so much, I probably don't have anything in them right now. I've popped both of them.''</p>
        <p>If the Mets lose Agbayani, they will be without a productive player Valentine trusts in the leadoff role. Agbayani does not look like the prototypical leadoff man, who is usually slender, speedy and scrappy, but Valentine believes it is important to have a run producer batting first, because often the pitcher sacrifices a runner into scoring position just before the leadoff man bats.</p>
        <p>In 345 at-bats, Agbayani has 60 runs batted in, a better R.B.I.-to-at-bat ratio than Edgardo Alfonzo and Todd Zeile, among others.</p>
        <p>Gridiron Great</p>
        <p>John Stearns, the Mets' first base coach, has been ridiculed mercilessly this year because his alma mater, the University of Colorado, has gotten off to an 0-3 start in football. The Buffaloes did not play today, but the Mets teased Stearns anyway when Manager Bobby Valentine played a videotape of Stearns's highlights as a safety at Colorado in the early 1970's. Most of the team and coaching staff crowded around a clubhouse television as Valentine narrated -- loudly -- and Stearns fled to the coaches' room.</p>
        <p>Quiet Man</p>
        <p>When it was pointed out to the left-handed reliever Dennis Cook that he had quietly put together an impressive string of outings, Cook cut his interviewer short. He would talk about anything but his pitching, Cook said. The last time he talked about his success, he said, he immediately began to pitch poorly. But the numbers are worth mentioning. With a 5.34 earned run average, Cook will probably finish with his highest earned run average since 1993, when he posted a 5.67 in 25 games for Cleveland. But Cook has not allowed a run in his last six appearances, matching his longest scoreless streak this year.</p>
        <p>Twice during that stretch, Cook has gotten five days off in a row.</p>
        <p>''He's throwing more strikes, that's for sure,'' Manager Bobby Valentine said. ''I don't know what we would have done without him. It seems like it's been a pretty efficient situation for him.''</p>
        <p>Braves Matchups</p>
        <p>Pitching matchups are set for the Mets' series with Atlanta. Al Leiter (16-7) will face John Burkett (9-6) on Tuesday; Rick Reed (10-5) will oppose Kevin Millwood (10-12) on Wednesday, and Bobby J. Jones (10-6) will face Greg Maddux (19-8) on Thursday.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: METS NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
