<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Whitewater Course Powered by ITT Pumps</title>
    <meta content="24PUMP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001008T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233139"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kayaks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Canoes and Canoeing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Itt Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lombardi, Kate Stone</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Kayaking and Canoeing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Canoes and Canoeing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE5DC133BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Whitewater Course Powered by ITT Pumps</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE STONE LOMBARDI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lombardi, Kate Stone</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on manmade whitewater course, powered by pumps manufactured by ITT Corp, that Olympic kayakers and canoeists are training on at Penrith, Australia; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALL week, Olympic kayakers and canoeists have been barreling through churning waters, pitching into Class 5 and 6 rapids, avoiding boulders and other hazards as they race through whitewater. But while the challenges the athletes face are very real, the river is not.</p>
        <p>The course is entirely man-made; the water moved by six powerful pumps manufactured by ITT Corporation, based in White Plains. Executives from the company feel particular pride in their role in creating the artificial river because the whitewater events were almost canceled because no site was available.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALL week, Olympic kayakers and canoeists have been barreling through churning waters, pitching into Class 5 and 6 rapids, avoiding boulders and other hazards as they race through whitewater. But while the challenges the athletes face are very real, the river is not.</p>
        <p>The course is entirely man-made; the water moved by six powerful pumps manufactured by ITT Corporation, based in White Plains. Executives from the company feel particular pride in their role in creating the artificial river because the whitewater events were almost canceled because no site was available.</p>
        <p>In fact, a year ago the site of the rushing water was a flat, bone-dry abandoned iron mine. The transformation took a year, $6.5 million and considerable technical skill.</p>
        <p>''There is pretty extensive engineering in terms of measuring and designing this,'' Bjorn Von Euler, a spokesman for ITT, said. ''We supplied the pumps, and the pumps are extremely important in delivering the right flow.''</p>
        <p>Olympic whitewater events were run for the first time in 1972 in Munich. There was a 20-year hiatus before they again became part of the Games. They were included in 1992 in Barcelona and in Atlanta in 1996. But when plans were made for the 2000 Games in Sydney, organizers announced that the whitewater races would be cut because there was no venue, and it would be too expensive to create one. Athletes and supporters lobbied for their inclusion, and Gilles Bernard, three-time world kayaking champion, traveled to Australia to survey the area. Mr. Bernard, who had helped design the Barcelona course (which was also man-made but set in a natural dry river bed) came back and, with engineers from ITT, came up with a proposal for an artificial river at Penrith, about an hour's drive from Sydney.</p>
        <p>The projected cost of the course was about half of what the Olympic Committee had expected when it canceled the events. Organizers gave their approval, and the events were back in the schedule.</p>
        <p>The 320-meter course is horseshoe shaped, allowing 12,000 people a view of the races. It is sculptured from concrete and dotted with movable plastic boulders, which mimic real river conditions. The pumps, which are submerged, cost $1.2 million and were built in Sweden. They are capable of moving 2.8 cubic meters of water a second.</p>
        <p>''What you really want to do is come up with a design that creates the challenges for champions,'' Mr. Von Euler said. ''You need to create a stream which is powerful enough and circulates with a constant flow.''</p>
        <p>He said the course offered the aquatic version of a level playing field to competitors because in a real river, conditions can change by the hour, giving some an unfair edge.</p>
        <p>Once the Olympics are over, the course will be altered, so that amateurs can use it as a recreational water park. The pumps can be adjusted to simulate different classes of rapids. Interest in the flexible design has been widespread, both from  kayaking teams around the world and amusement park operators.</p>
        <p>''We see this as something that can be a product for us,'' Mr. Von Euler said. ''You don't even need a hill, just some space.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 8, 2000, Sunday  An article on Sept. 24 about the whitewater course at the Olympics in Sydney used an outdated name for the White Plains-based manufacturer of the six pumps that create the rapids. The company is ITT Industries, a successor to the ITT Corporation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 8, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on Sept. 24 about the whitewater course at the Olympics in Sydney used an outdated name for the White Plains-based manufacturer of the six pumps that create the rapids. The company is ITT Industries, a successor to the ITT Corporation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
