<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ask a Child to Create a Friend? That's a Ni Ni</title>
    <meta content="MB234242" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="59" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FOR YOUNG VIEWERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Learning Channel</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shattuck, Kathryn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ni Ni's Treehouse (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E6D9173AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="333" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ask a Child to Create a Friend? That's a Ni Ni</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kathrynb Shattuck</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shattuck, Kathryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Learning Channel TV program Ni Ni's Treehouse; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Kenn Viselman polled preschoolers about the qualities they'd most like to find in a playmate, the result was neither fish nor fowl - or even boy or girl.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Kenn Viselman polled preschoolers about the qualities they'd most like to find in a playmate, the result was neither fish nor fowl - or even boy or girl.</p>
        <p>What the survey produced was Ni Ni, a wide-eyed nybrid of dog, cat, pig and cow with the talent of Picasso and an unflappable curiosity. The cuddly little mutt and his friends make their debut on ''Ni Ni's Treehouse,'' to be shown on the Learning Channel tomorrow at 7:30 a.m. and each weekday thereafter as part of TLC's ''Ready Set Learn,'' a commercial-free block of children's programming.</p>
        <p>''Everything about this show, from the original characters to the colors to the name, came from children,'' said Mr. Viselman, the chairman of the Itsy Bitsy Entertainment Company, the show's producer and the importer of British-based shows like ''Teletubbies'' and ''Noddy.'' ''We wanted a character who was innocent and would be learning along the way with the child.''</p>
        <p>''Ni Ni's Treehouse'' propels children into the heart of Oooberryland, to the mysterious orchard where the dwelling in question rests atop the tallest tree. Through sketches that spring to life, Ni Ni introduces children to fantastic characters, among them Horace Hippopotamus, an indeterminate species called the Fingerlings and the mischievous twin sisters Treezle B and Treezle D, whose sole reason for being is to egg Ni Ni on.</p>
        <p>In a twist on standard children's fare, the show takes a didactic approach to education, with half-hour episodes that investigate cognitive skills ranging from the basic (big, hot, cold) to the abstract (polite, right, wrong). Each episode features animation conceived by children asked to illustrate the concepts from their own perspectives.</p>
        <p>Like the best kind of friend, Ni Ni transcends categorization, Mr. Viselman said of his creation, who, though geared to the 3-to-6-year-old set, remains ''ageless.'' ''He's at that stage where everything is interesting for him,'' he said. ''What we've been calling him is a composite of children' imaginations.''</p>
        <p>Kathryn Shattuck</p>
        <p>FOR YOUNG VIEWERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
