<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If You're Thinking of Living In/New Rochelle; In People and Housing, Eclectic Mixes</title>
    <meta content="24LIVI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Rochelle (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weinstock, Cheryl Platzman</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E2DF173BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If You're Thinking of Living In/New Rochelle; In People and Housing, Eclectic Mixes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHERYL PLATZMAN WEINSTOCK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weinstock, Cheryl Platzman</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>If You're Thinking of Living In column on New Rochelle, NY; photos; map; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Peter Ackerman, a lawyer in private practice in White Plains, and his wife, Mindy, a jewelry designer, were looking for their first home 17 years ago, Mr. Ackerman said he had strong opinions that helped guide him toward the multicultural Westchester city of New Rochelle.</p>
        <p>''I spent my teenage years in a homogeneous place that I would never want for my 11-year-old daughter,'' he said. ''From personal experience, I can tell you that spending time in an environment like that, kids don't have to work as hard at learning about other people in the larger world who are not like them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Peter Ackerman, a lawyer in private practice in White Plains, and his wife, Mindy, a jewelry designer, were looking for their first home 17 years ago, Mr. Ackerman said he had strong opinions that helped guide him toward the multicultural Westchester city of New Rochelle.</p>
        <p>''I spent my teenage years in a homogeneous place that I would never want for my 11-year-old daughter,'' he said. ''From personal experience, I can tell you that spending time in an environment like that, kids don't have to work as hard at learning about other people in the larger world who are not like them.</p>
        <p>''When you're forced into an environment where you really have to interact with kids from different socioeconomic and ethnic backgrounds,'' he said, ''you're forced to realize that the world is a more complex place than your own personal, rather insular environment. We believe there are no losses here in New Rochelle as the result of its diverse population. It's part of its strength.''</p>
        <p>Vijay Kumar and his wife, Subha Sundaram, feel the same way about New Rochelle. ''As immigrants from India, we believe in having our two children not only tolerate diversity, but really embrace and celebrate it like they can here,'' said Mr. Kumar, a regional manager of Citrix Systems, a software company in New York City. ''Our primary driver for moving here was really space. But it's comforting to know that in a suburban setting you can still find a balanced, cosmopolitan place where you don't have to give up anything.''</p>
        <p>New Rochelle's eclectic mix of people, homes and neighborhoods has inspired artists to try to recreate the feeling in television scripts, paintings, books and songs.  Carl Reiner wrote ''The Dick Van Dyke Show'' around the memories of his life in New Rochelle, Norman Rockwell painted his visions of American life during his 25 years there and E.L. Doctorow's novel, ''Ragtime,'' was inspired by his fireplace musings in his 1908 home in the city. Today New Rochelle is still a haven for artists from Hollywood to Broadway and Carnegie Hall, including Ossie Davis and Ruby Dee, Andrea McArdle, Frances Sternhagen and Robert Merrill.</p>
        <p>And its nine miles of shoreline, ethnic restaurants and neighborhoods and proximity to major highways and New York City continue to attract homebuyers.</p>
        <p>''There is no place like us,'' said Lucille Ritacco, of Lucille Ritacco Realty in New Rochelle. ''Even our high-end buyers in the $900,000 range keep losing homes because houses are getting multiple bids by buyers willing to pay $50,000 to $75,000 over asking to live here in magnificent Tudors and large, old colonials.''</p>
        <p>The city has a widely varied housing stock. ''This is one of the few places in Westchester where you can still find a small, starter home on a small corner lot or near the railroad for between $155,000 to $225,000,'' said Beryl Zawatsky of Beryl Z. Realty in New Rochelle,</p>
        <p>From there, homes can range up to $350,000 for larger, three-bedroom, two-bath older colonials in more residential areas on 75-foot-by-100-foot lots. Newer split-levels and ranches, as well as some colonials on one-third-acre parcels, range from $360,000 to $500,000. More stately homes, such as English Tudors with stained-glass windows and Georgian colonials with pillars, in Wykagyl Park, Bonnie Crest and Forest Heights range from $600,000 to $1 million. There are a relatively high 27 homes on the market in this price range, although 12 are in contract, she said. Homes along the shoreline in Premium Point Park and Sans Souci can sell for more than $1 million.</p>
        <p>BESIDES the many single-family homes on the market in New Rochelle, there are many other housing options. These include 41 co-op complexes, 8 condominiums, 268 multiple-family homes and 70 apartment buildings, said Louis Perone, the city assessor. In addition, 400 luxury rental units are planned for the downtown area.</p>
        <p>A two-bedroom co-op ranges from $60,000 to $150,000, and a two-bedroom condominium from $135,000 to $255,000. A two-bedroom apartment rents for approximately $1,100 a month.</p>
        <p>Timothy C. Idoni, New Rochelle's mayor, called the city, which was founded in the 1680's by the French Huguenots, a ''sophisticated suburb able to handle urban issues and suburban issues at the same time.''</p>
        <p>Recently, Ikea proposed a store along I-95 on 16 acres of property that includes 34 residences in a so-called blighted area. ''This area was designated for redevelopment years ago,'' Mayor Idoni said. ''One of the requirements that the city has placed on Ikea is to come up with an excellent relocation program for the residents down there.''</p>
        <p>Another issue that New Rochelle is tackling is whether the Young Israel of New Rochelle, which just bought property next to the Wykagyl Country Club to build a larger synagogue and catering facility, should get a zoning variance. ''The use of the synagogue itself is not illegal,'' Mayor Idoni said. ''It's the size of the building that's creating an issue. There's significant opposition to it from the neighborhood. But people have the right to buy property. When the synagogue completes their environmental impact study, we'll have more answers.''</p>
        <p>Carla Price, a substitute teacher at Horace Mann in Riverdale and an assistant to the director of the New Rochelle Opera Company, cited ''the unpretentiousness of the community and the fact that my son has become colorblind living here,'' as part of its attraction, and said that the city's school system has nurtured his endeavors.</p>
        <p>Her son, Aaron Kushner, 16, is a member of one of the few teenage Klezmer bands in the country, The Klezminors. Ms. Price said, ''Being able to send Aaron to a magnet elementary school that had a humanities-based curriculum was very important to me and Aaron's father, who is a professional musician.''</p>
        <p>The 10,165-student City School District of New Rochelle is unusual in many ways. ''What's special about New Rochelle is that we're diverse without division.'' said School Superintendent Linda E. Kelly. ''Almost half the student body is minority, representing 57 nations. We have students on welfare assistance, ones who are recent immigrants and wealthy students. We not only savor their differences, we cherish and nurture them.''</p>
        <p>The district's students can specialize in particular areas of interest in three of the district's magnet schools for art and humanities, math and technology or communication arts.</p>
        <p>EARLIER this year, a student in the high school's science research program was named a semifinalist in the Intel Science Talent Search. The high school also produced a semifinalist in 1999 and 1997. Several of New Rochelle's public schools have also earned the National Blue Ribbon School of Excellence by the New York State Education Department.</p>
        <p>Of the district's 496 high school graduates last June, 62 percent were accepted to four-year colleges, including Harvard , the University of Pennsylvania, Brown and Georgetown. Twenty-seven percent went on to two-year colleges. Students averaged 500 in verbal and 510 in math on the College Board tests this year, compared with statewide averages of 495 in verbal and 502 in math.</p>
        <p>Nineteen percent of the students in the district attend parochial and Jewish day schools in neighboring communities. Students can continue their college education without leaving home at three private colleges in the city: Iona College, the College of New Rochelle and Monroe College.</p>
        <p>After school and on weekends for recreation, children can play in the city's 35 parks, playgrounds and sports fields. Five Islands Park and Hudson Park are two of the largest active parks in New Rochelle. Residents can also volley on the city's 38 tennis courts; launch a boat from its public marina, which has 400 slips and 300 moorings; or bicycle or hike through the 67-acre Ward Acres.</p>
        <p>Carol Ann Samela, chairwoman of the New Rochelle Council on the Arts, said that the many artists living in New Rochelle frequently lent their talents to local productions. ''We bring top-notch entertainment into the city and nurture the arts in every way,'' she said.</p>
        <p>For a different kind of entertainment, residents can visit the new, downtown, $194 million entertainment complex, New Roc City. It has 18 movie screens, two IMAX theaters, two ice-skating rinks and a family entertainment center.</p>
        <p>The Siwanoy Indians occupied the city before the French came there seeking religious freedom. They named it after the French port of La Rochelle. It prospered as a farming community, but in 1849, after it became more accessible when the New York and New Haven Railroad opened a station, it began to grow as a resort town and eventually into a commuters' suburb.</p>
        <p>One of its most famous residents was Thomas Paine, who got a cottage and 274 acres of farmland from the New York State Legislature for his service to the American cause. His cottage, a landmark on the National Register of Historic Places, is open Friday, Saturday and Sunday afternoons from April through October.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
