<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Migrants, Hard Work in Hostile Suburbs</title>
    <meta content="24IMMI$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/nyregion/24IMMI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Migrant Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mexican-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Farmingdale (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leduff, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Migrant Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mexican-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E0DC173AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2404" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Migrants, Hard Work in Hostile Suburbs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE LeDUFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leduff, Charlie</byline>
      <dateline>FARMINGVILLE, N.Y., Sept. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Attack on two Mexican immigrants seeking work in Farmingdale, NY, underscores dangers faced by unwanted strangers in sometimes hostile suburbs; estimated 1 in 15 of village's summertime residents is migrant worker, who have come in great numbers over past four years to take jobs locals are unwilling or unable to do; most are illegal immigrants, and it is their illegal status that irritates most local residents; violence has shocked some whites, and even prompted formation of community group by politicians and church leaders looking for ways to ease tensions; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When dusk comes, the streets empty and the esquineros hurry to the homes they share with 15, 20 and sometimes 30 others to drink beer and eat supper.</p>
        <p>The esquineros -- the men of the corner -- used to walk home alone from the corners where they gather each morning to be hired out for yardwork or other day jobs. Now they walk in groups. At one house, where the Guatemalans live, the door is punctured with bullet holes; a white man recently drove by and unloaded a pistol.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When dusk comes, the streets empty and the esquineros hurry to the homes they share with 15, 20 and sometimes 30 others to drink beer and eat supper.</p>
        <p>The esquineros -- the men of the corner -- used to walk home alone from the corners where they gather each morning to be hired out for yardwork or other day jobs. Now they walk in groups. At one house, where the Guatemalans live, the door is punctured with bullet holes; a white man recently drove by and unloaded a pistol.</p>
        <p>The next block over, there is a white man who put his house up for sale after 20 Mexicans moved in next door. As he pulled into his driveway, he stared at his unwanted neighbors. He is a tough-looking guy, and he did not turn his eyes away. One of the Mexicans wore a secondhand shirt that read, ''We don't like you either.''</p>
        <p>Up until now, the culture divide of the suburbs has been more a cold war than a hot one, an uneasy peace with periodic clashes over public issues like limits on the number of boarders allowed in a house or a proposal in Suffolk County to sue the Immigration and Naturalization Service to more stringently enforce immigration laws.</p>
        <p>But when two Hispanic immigrants seeking work were lured to an abandoned building on Sunday and attacked by two white men wielding a knife, a crowbar and a shovel, the assault was a sobering reminder of the lives of the unwanted strangers. The divide plays out in towns like Brewster, Mount Kisco and Yonkers, N.Y., and Freehold, N.J.</p>
        <p>But the emotions are rawest in Farmingville, where it is estimated that in the summertime, one in 15 residents is a migrant worker. When October comes, a few men stay, but most follow their money home.</p>
        <p>The violence last Sunday shocked some whites and even prompted the formation of a community group by politicians and church leaders looking for ways to ease the tensions. But if the violence was a revelation to many whites, the hostility behind it was hardly news to the brown men in the Goodwill T-shirts and muddy jeans who come to the corner each morning looking for work.</p>
        <p>Anger on Both Sides</p>
        <p>Dionicio Urbina walked quickly through the white neighborhoods. He is 20 years old and was shocked when some white teenagers just a few years younger than he  hurled an ethnic slur and squealed with cracking voices, ''Speak English,'' and ''What are you doing here, Mexican?''</p>
        <p>In the safety of his worn-down house, Mr. Urbina lay on his bedroll and listened to a light rain pelt his window -- a bad omen for work in the morning.</p>
        <p>''You don't know what it's like to be in a town where they hate you,'' he said in nearly perfect English. ''The place is so weird to me. The suburbs. I never knew that word. In other parts of the country the Mexicans fight the Mexicans. Here, it's the white people who don't want us. It's not the country and it's not the city. It's strange, but, man, the money is here. I never dreamed about $100 a day.''</p>
        <p>There are plenty of jobs in this tree-lined hamlet in central Long Island that is home to 15,000 residents and acres of blacktop and strip malls. Mostly they are menial jobs like cleaning pools and landscaping, and like a quarter of all jobs in the United States, they pay about $8 an hour.</p>
        <p>The Latinos have come in great numbers over the past four years to take the jobs locals are unwilling or unable to do. Most are here illegally, and it is their illegal status that most irritates local residents.</p>
        <p>The people taunt each other. Some Americans picket the Latinos every Saturday as they stand on the corners waiting for work. The esquineros have become schooled in the ways of America. They picket back. And after the ambush of the two workers, more than 500 of the illegal immigrants took to the streets demanding their civil rights.</p>
        <p>Every morning a throng of Latinos stand on a small mound denuded of grass but choked with poison ivy. It is known as the esquina, or corner, and it is the best, most visible corner around. Some men walk two hours to get to this spot at Horseblock Road and North Ocean Avenue to be picked up for some work. It is an hour if you run.</p>
        <p>Farther back from the mound are some trees where men go in the sweltering mornings to relieve themselves or smoke a little marijuana. Next to it is the 7-Eleven, and even though there is a sign in front of the store that says ''Welcome to Farmingville,'' the esquineros know that they are not welcome.</p>
        <p>Here, 300 brown men on the corner are as obvious as a herd of ostriches.</p>
        <p>Before, they accepted their lot as unwanted outsiders. But the beating of the two men has made the esquineros angry. ''Man, they want you here in the mornings to do their animal work and then at night they want you to disappear,'' said Carlos Antonio, 19. ''If they want war, if they want Pancho Villa, then I can be Pancho Villa.''</p>
        <p>The American dream for the esquineros is to find a way off this corner. They tell the legend of the two brothers from Hidalgo who found their way to Farmingville 20 years ago. The brothers worked as stone masons and returned to Mexico with a fortune. Others followed, and now the esquineros come from all corners of Mexico and Central America.</p>
        <p>Lalo Cervantes, 37, comes. He is from Mexico City. He has gold in his teeth, and when he has no money in his pocket, he looks for a little work. Carlos Antonio comes too. And Gabriel Jimenez. Mr. Cervantes and Mr. Antonio speak good English. Mr. Jimenez, 23, comes from the mountains. He is a peasant and understands little English beyond push, pull, lift, over there, how much? and, do you buy lunch?</p>
        <p>Often a carful of young white women drive by and whistle at the men. Sometimes they give the men the finger. Either way, the men shout back with dull agitation. They have grown used to it. White people have complained to the police about the men harassing American women.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't let my woman walk by here either,'' Mr. Cervantes said. ''To tell you the truth, the whole scene does look bad. But it all gets mixed up in racism. It's not because we're Mexicans. It's because we're construction workers, because we are men.''</p>
        <p>The morning traffic must make a right turn out of the 7-Eleven. And when the Americans make the turn, they look left and avoid looking right at the esquineros.</p>
        <p>When they do look, their cars are swarmed with workers. One American woman looked with purpose and lowered her power window. ''I only need one,'' she said. She had some yardwork. When a man jumped in, the ribaldry began.</p>
        <p>''Big gringa in a big car,'' said Armando Perez, rubbing his palms together. ''Thick and soft. That's your American girls. Their husbands go to work and I think they are lonely just like us.''</p>
        <p>The esquineros would like a woman of any kind. There are few Mexican women out here, and the only companionship for them arrives in vans on Friday and Saturday evenings from Queens. The price is $20.</p>
        <p>A Day's Labor for $100</p>
        <p>A white man pulled up in a big white truck. He was new to the corner and had never hired esquineros before. Messrs. Jimenez, Antonio and Cervantes piled in. The patron spoke loudly, as if the sheer volume of his voice would increase their understanding of English. ''Boy, that's a zoo, huh? A free for all? You do that every day?''</p>
        <p>He took the men to a chic neighborhood in Port Jefferson. You could smell the saltwater first, then you could see the boats. Then, over a slight hill was the patron's dream house. It had a pool, and it cost $25,000 just to clear the trees. Where the trees used to be were 24,000 square feet of bald earth where the men were to lay the sod. Lalo Cervantes, with his nice English, became the crew chief. The boss's wife was very particular about her grass. But Mr. Cervantes was assiduous. He calmed the woman.</p>
        <p>The day was hot. The boss kept saying it wasn't too hot. Mr. Cervantes kept asking how much money he would be paid.</p>
        <p>''I'll take care of you,'' the boss kept answering. The workers grew suspicious that they would not be paid.</p>
        <p>Most workers will return with $100 in their pockets after long, dirty hours. A few will get nothing. They will get stiffed, and when they return home, all they will carry is malice in their hearts and a vague promise to get even with that gringo boss.</p>
        <p>This boss had nice cars and two grown sons with Adonis-like bodies. They like to go to the gym, the woman kept saying. One son drove a Mercedes, the other a Porsche, and they lifted no sod.</p>
        <p>''It's strange,'' Mr. Antonio said in Spanish. ''These guys don't know the value of what they've got. Big bodies and no work. This must make the old man sad.''</p>
        <p>When the work was done, the boss handed two new $50 bills to each man and said: ''You boys know anything about air-conditioning? I fired my whole crew because they're lazy. You guys like to work hard. I'll give you that.''</p>
        <p>He handed out his card and dropped the workers on the corner.</p>
        <p>''Oh man,'' said Mr. Antonio, tapping the card with his nails. ''It's my dream to get off the corner. Here's my ticket.'' He never did call the man.</p>
        <p>Thirty Men, One House</p>
        <p>The men walked down Horseblock Road to the Brewery, a cantina with gray walls that is one of the few places the cultures overlap: the American war veterans, the Portuguese-American contractors and the esquineros.</p>
        <p>A man named Alex Martinez held his head in his hands, his elbows on the bar. He stared into his plate. He had problems with his American girlfriend, he said.</p>
        <p>''She just doesn't understand,'' he told any stranger willing to listen. ''All the things. The car. She wants more. I tell her, 'I work for these things. Do you know the value of work?' I don't think she does. We come from different places.''</p>
        <p>There is a ranch house off Horseblock Road. In the house are 9 bicycles, 13 toothbrushes, 30 men, a big bottle of bleach, a pot of boiling chicken and five lingerie catalogs. The rain began to fall again. Some men sat around the dirty kitchen drinking beer and complaining about work.</p>
        <p>''The boss, he tells me he's going to pay me only $50 because he says I don't work.''</p>
        <p>''Fifty dollars? The garbage. So what did you do?''</p>
        <p>''What could I do? I took the fifty.''</p>
        <p>In the morning, more rain fell, and work was scarce. Across the street, white people picketed, as they do every Saturday, with signs that read ''Go Home'' and ''Stop the Crime.'' A man drove back and forth taking photographs of the esquineros.</p>
        <p>''I've got nothing against immigrants. Immigrants built this country,'' said the photographer, David Drew, 48. ''But these aren't immigrants. They're criminals taking advantage of a good thing. It's like putting bread out for the birds and the rats eat it.''</p>
        <p>The Mexicans understood his English. ''This guy, he's not stable,'' Cesar Perez said.</p>
        <p>The esquineros have learned to stick up for themselves. Encouraged by men like Carlos Canales, an outreach worker for the Work Place Project, the esquineros have staged demonstrations at the County Legislature when it considered passing laws aimed at them. They hold news conferences and picket the homes of contractors who do not pay their employees.</p>
        <p>During one of these vigils, among taunts of ''You make me sick,'' and ''My father came here legally,'' a group of Latino men with varying shades of skin spoke with two white women, one old, the other young.</p>
        <p>''Listen to me, please.'' the older woman said. ''I've got nothing against you personally. But you are here illegally. There are too many of you. We're inundated. You take the money home and make no life here. You don't learn English.''</p>
        <p>A brown man responded in clumsy English, ''But Spanish is the second language of the world.''</p>
        <p>''And guess what the first is,'' the woman said. ''It's the language we speak in this country.''</p>
        <p>Pay the Rent or Else</p>
        <p>When the white people showed up at the corner with signs on a wet Saturday morning a few weeks before the attacks, the esquineros pulled out their own banners and signs. They crossed the street to confront the white people. The white people ran away to the taunts of ''fascistas!''</p>
        <p>By 10 a.m., the rain was still falling and the men went home. At the ranch house on Horseblock Road, the landlord arrived wearing a dime-store badge. He had a siren in the window of his car. He was fond of telling the esquineros that he was a federal agent. He told them that if there was any trouble, if any man moved in without paying the $250 rent, then he had the power to arrest him, even to shoot him.</p>
        <p>This made the Mexicans laugh. ''It's really unbelievable the life here,'' Mr. Urbina said. ''These are the things the men go home to tell their families about America.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
