<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 9-24-00: On Language; -- Or Shut Up</title>
    <meta content="WLN123618" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233062"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Hadassah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1DA143BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1087" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 9-24-00: On Language; -- Or Shut Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire On Language column on Al Gore's modified use of phrase 'put up or shut up' and Dick Cheney's use of word squandered; corrects error in stating that first name of Sen Joe Lieberman's wife, Hadassah, is Hebrew equivalent of Esther (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'The time for generalities without specifics,'' said candidate Al Gore, ''I think is just about over. . . . It's kind of put up or shut up time.''</p>
        <p>His opponent promptly complained about the ''tone'' of this remark. Amid the general fear of being counterpunched with a charge of negativity, politicians shy from any locution that can be construed as harsh. Evidently Gore was concerned about his use of the directly challenging put up or shut up, because he preceded it with the ameliorating kind of and followed it with time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'The time for generalities without specifics,'' said candidate Al Gore, ''I think is just about over. . . . It's kind of put up or shut up time.''</p>
        <p>His opponent promptly complained about the ''tone'' of this remark. Amid the general fear of being counterpunched with a charge of negativity, politicians shy from any locution that can be construed as harsh. Evidently Gore was concerned about his use of the directly challenging put up or shut up, because he preceded it with the ameliorating kind of and followed it with time.</p>
        <p>The time combining form was pioneered in party time and was popularized by TV's Bob Smith in the late 1940's with ''Hi, kids -- it's Howdy Doody time!'' The time turns the preceding word or phrase into a modifier, thereby weakening put up or shut up.</p>
        <p>The substance of the charge has no place in this resolutely nonpolitical column. To philologists, however, the use of the Americanism put up or shut up poses a question: from what metaphor is it derived?</p>
        <p>The earliest recorded use is in Fred H. Hart's 1878 collection of stories, ''The Sazerac Lying Club.'' (This may have been a dialectical source of the poet Mary Karr's recent memoir of her childhood, ''The Liar's Club''; that best seller is soon to be followed by the avidly awaited memoir of her adolescence, ''Cherry,'' a slang reference to virginity. I enjoy digressions.) In a Hart story, the initialese P.U. or S.U. appears, explained by a character saying, ''P.U. or S.U. means put up or shut up, doesn't it?'' The caption to a cartoon in an 1884 Police Gazette was ''Put up, shut up or get!'' (presumably, ''get out'' or ''git''), and the Americanism was locked into language by Mark Twain in his 1889 ''Connecticut Yankee in King Arthur's Court'' with ''This was a plain case of 'put up, or shut up.' ''</p>
        <p>Put up what? If the metaphor is from fisticuffs, the figure of speech is one of a fighter putting up his dukes, or fists, and telling his opponent to be quiet or prepare to put up his own dukes to defend himself.</p>
        <p>A different possibility: the phrase could come from card playing, a rich source of phrases used in politics. Samples: F.D.R.'s New Deal, Truman's the buck stops here, with the buck, often a silver dollar, used to mark the position of the dealer, and stand pat, a poker locution used once by Richard Nixon as ''America cannot stand pat,'' and stricken by his speechwriter from subsequent speeches after it drew a sharp glance from the candidate's wife.</p>
        <p>Card playing is a strong possibility for the root because of the first verb, put, which is also used in put your money where your mouth is. To put up is synonymous with ante up, a call to place money in the ante, or ''pot.'' (The pot is called an ante, which means ''before,'' and could allude to the stake that must be placed ''before the draw.'' In 1882, Charles Welsh wrote in his poker guide about the ''eldest hand'' in the game: ''Before the dealer begins to deal the cards, the player next to his left, who is called the ante-man, or age, must deposit in the pool an ante not exceeding one-half the limit previously agreed upon.'')</p>
        <p>Did dealer Gore obliquely demand that the ante-man put up or quietly fold? Or did he make a veiled dialect reference to the stance of a pugilist? It's a down-and-dirty dialectical mystery that leads us to an etymological mystery:</p>
        <p>Squander</p>
        <p>''When I look at the administration now in Washington,'' Dick Cheney told the G.O.P. convention, ''I am dismayed by opportunities squandered.'' Next night, George W. Bush added, ''The current administration hasn't seized the moment -- they [sic] 've squandered the moment.'' Democrat Joe Lieberman came right back with ''the same people who let this nation drift are trying to convince us that the past eight years have been squandered.'' To Republican Jennifer Dunn's charge that ''Al Gore has squandered opportunities to improve America's future,'' Hillary Clinton showed the popular verb could be used by Democrats too: ''Let's not squander our children's future.''</p>
        <p>Not since pander entered the political lexicon has an obscure verb so suddenly come into vogue. The article that may have started it all was ''The Squandered Presidency,'' by the Brookings foreign policy expert Richard Haass, in the Spring 2000 issue of Foreign Affairs. Count its usages in coming debates.</p>
        <p>In its sense of ''scatter, dissipate,'' it first appeared in Shakespeare's 1596 ''Merchant of Venice,'' in which Shylock says of Antonio, ''other ventures he hath, squand'red abroad.''</p>
        <p>In its predominant sense of ''to spend extravagantly and wastefully,'' it appeared in Thomas Nashe's 1593 religious tract: ''Fooles shall squander in an houre, all the auarice of their ambitious wise Auncesters.''</p>
        <p>But what's the root? Where did Shakespeare or Nashe get it from? Nobody knows; the best dictionaries say ''origin obscure.'' A century ago, the 10-volume Century Dictionary etymologists took a speculative crack at it: perhaps squander grew out of a nasalized form of swadder, from the Swedish dialect skvadra, ''gush out, as water,'' or the Danish skvatte, ''squirt, splash,'' or the German ver-schwenden, which means ''squander, waste.''</p>
        <p>If you don't buy this speculation, and have your own, put up or shut up.</p>
        <p>Hadassah</p>
        <p>I erred in writing that the first name of Senator Lieberman's wife, Hadassah, was ''the Hebrew equivalent of Esther.'' I was misled by every translation I can find of the Old Testament passage Esther 2:7, which reads, ''And he brought up Hadassah, that is, Esther.'' In that passage, that is is confusing.</p>
        <p>The Hebrew word hadas means ''myrtle.'' It does not mean, nor is it the equivalent of, Esther, which may be the Hebraized form of Ishtar, a Persian</p>
        <p>goddess. In the Bible, the beautiful Jewish girl Hadassah took the name of Esther to better fit in Persian society, where she became the queen of Xerxes and was able to save her people from annihilation.</p>
        <p>Whoever next translates the Bible would do political pundits a favor by changing ''Hadassah, that is, Esther'' to ''Hadassah, also known as Esther.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
