<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Makes Further Moves To Lower Cost Of Heating Oil</title>
    <meta content="24OIL.$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/national/24OIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heating Oil</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Health and Human Services Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E3DA173AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Makes Further Moves To Lower Cost Of Heating Oil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clinton administration takes additional steps to cushion oil market against shortages this winter and to soften shock of higher prices on consumers; environmental regulators will explore ways to permit more varieties of heating oil to be burned, government will try to smooth out effects of its own fuel purchases, and administration will ask state utility regulators to keep sharp eye on fuel inventories at power plants and factories; Pres Clinton has directed Dept of Health and Human Services to release $400 million in aid to poor families to help them buy fuel, record allocation for this annual disbursement (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Clinton administration took several additional steps today to cushion the oil market against shortages this winter and to soften the shock of higher prices on consumers. Like the temporary release of oil from the Strategic Petroleum Reserve, announced on Friday, the new measures are intended mainly to ease tight supplies of heating oil, President Clinton said.</p>
        <p>Environmental regulators are to explore ways to permit more varieties of heating oil to be burned, the government will try to smooth out the effects of its own fuel purchases, and the administration will ask state utility regulators to keep a sharp eye on fuel inventories at power plants and factories, he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Clinton administration took several additional steps today to cushion the oil market against shortages this winter and to soften the shock of higher prices on consumers. Like the temporary release of oil from the Strategic Petroleum Reserve, announced on Friday, the new measures are intended mainly to ease tight supplies of heating oil, President Clinton said.</p>
        <p>Environmental regulators are to explore ways to permit more varieties of heating oil to be burned, the government will try to smooth out the effects of its own fuel purchases, and the administration will ask state utility regulators to keep a sharp eye on fuel inventories at power plants and factories, he said.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Clinton directed the Department of Health and Human Services to release $400 million in aid to poor families to help them buy fuel, a record allocation for this annual disbursement.</p>
        <p>''The overriding purpose for our action is to increase supply and help consumers make it through the cold winter,'' Mr. Clinton said. He defended as ''plainly a prudent thing to do'' his decision to release crude oil from the reserve, which had been recommended by Vice President Al Gore but was denounced by Gov. George W. Bush as a political ploy.</p>
        <p>But despite the avowed focus on home heating oil, the broader effects of the intervention in energy markets will be felt by consumers whenever they fill up at a gas station, pay for an airline ticket, or even pay the family's bills for electricity or natural gas, according to energy experts.</p>
        <p>Of the 30 million barrels that the government will lend to refineries in the next several weeks from the Strategic Petroleum Reserve, 85 to 90 percent will be turned into products other than home heating oil, Energy Department officials said. Fixing a shortage of heating oil is like confronting a shortage of brisket, they said; you have to kill the whole steer, which will also produce hamburger and sirloin, along with leather.</p>
        <p>Refineries will vary the proportions slightly, depending on market prices for products, but in general half of each barrel of crude oil becomes gasoline, a quarter becomes heating oil or diesel fuel (which are nearly identical) and a tenth becomes jet fuel. The rest goes to everything from lubricating oils to asphalt to floor wax.</p>
        <p>Because of futures markets, which send price signals faster than oil can flow physically through pipelines, consumers can expect to see prices declining across the spectrum fairly soon. But because the oil that will be released must be paid back later by oil companies, prices may rebound later, experts say.</p>
        <p>Even before the announcement on Friday, which came after futures markets closed, heating oil for delivery in October fell by 4.41 cents a gallon, to 95.48 cents.</p>
        <p>But only about 10 percent of households use heating oil or kerosene as their primary fuel, according to the Energy Department's most recent survey, in 1997. (That is down from 22 percent in 1978.)</p>
        <p>Philip K. Verleger Jr., of the Brattle Group, an economic consulting firm in Cambridge, Mass., said that the gush of oil onto the market would probably push the price of crude down by $5 to $7 a barrel, which comes to 10 to 15 cents a gallon.</p>
        <p>That could be enough, depending on such factors as the weather, to save a typical oil-heated household up to $100 over the winter, and a family might well experience similar savings for gasoline over several months of driving.</p>
        <p>The price of goods transported by trucks would also be held down. And because oil and gas are sometimes substituted for each other -- in electricity generation and various other industrial uses -- a decline in the price of one fuel would hold down the price of the other, experts said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
