<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; Cut Down on Out-of-Wedlock Births, Win Cash</title>
    <meta content="24LEWI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/weekinreview/24LEWI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegitimacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alabama</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arizona</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Illinois</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Michigan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Health and Human Services Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewin, Tamar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shalala, Donna E (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4DB1F3BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; Cut Down on Out-of-Wedlock Births, Win Cash</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TAMAR LEWIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewin, Tamar</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Health and Human Services Sec Donna E Shalala announces that Washington, DC, Alabama, Arizona, Illinois and Michigan will each get $20 million for showing largest decrease in out-of-wedlock births with no increase in abortion rates; $400 million 'illegitimacy bonus' program is part of welfare reform act; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOUR years ago, as the whole debate over ''family values,'' single mothers and welfare dependency reached its peak, Congress plopped a $400 million ''illegitimacy bonus'' program into the welfare reform act.</p>
        <p>The program, financed for four years, gives an annual award of $100 million, to be split among the five states that show the largest decrease in out-of-wedlock births with no increase in abortion rates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOUR years ago, as the whole debate over ''family values,'' single mothers and welfare dependency reached its peak, Congress plopped a $400 million ''illegitimacy bonus'' program into the welfare reform act.</p>
        <p>The program, financed for four years, gives an annual award of $100 million, to be split among the five states that show the largest decrease in out-of-wedlock births with no increase in abortion rates.</p>
        <p>Last week, Donna E. Shalala, the secretary of Health and Human Services, announced the second round of winners: the District of Columbia (which Congress regards as a state for this program), Alabama, Arizona, Illinois and Michigan will each get $20 million.</p>
        <p>''Reducing out-of-wedlock births is a significant way to reduce the risk of welfare dependency,'' said Olivia A. Golden, an assistant secretary at the department. ''We look forward to continued results of state efforts to use the flexibility and resources provided by welfare reform.''</p>
        <p>But what the bonus really rewards, whether it has anything to do with welfare -- and what, if anything, it accomplishes -- remains murky, said Cory Richards,  vice president for policy at the Alan Guttmacher Institute, a nonprofit research organization focusing on reproductive health and rights.</p>
        <p>''About the best you can say for the bonus is that it advertises the issue,'' Mr. Richards said. ''There's no requirement that the states tell the government what they're doing to bring down the rates, or even that they do anything at all, so there's no way states can learn from each other's successes. The federal government gives no guidance to the states as to what they should or shouldn't do to bring down the rates. And much of the period covered was before the welfare act even went into effect.''</p>
        <p>Others, however, defend the program.</p>
        <p>''Research has demonstrated over and over again that single-parent families live in poverty, so asking states to try to reduce illegitimacy rates is clearly a way of addressing the welfare issue,'' said Susan Orr of the Family Research Council, a conservative policy group in Washington. ''The extra money will let the states that are doing a good job help more women and children. It's a way to encourage responsible behavior.''</p>
        <p>Nationally, about a third of all births in the United States are to unmarried mothers -- a ratio that has been nearly constant for the last six years. But that leveling off comes after decades of rapid increases and growing concerns that children raised in single-parent households do not fare as well as those who live with both parents.</p>
        <p>The National Center for Health Statistics says births to unwed mothers accounted for only 5.3 percent of the nation's newborns in 1960, rising to 10.7 percent in 1970, 18.4 percent in 1980 and 28 percent in 1990.</p>
        <p>The bonuses awarded this month are based on statistics from 1995-1996 to 1997-1998. And most of the winners showed only tiny decreases in births to unmarried mothers: a 0.02 percent drop in Illinois, 0.29 percent in Alabama, 1.34 percent in Michigan, and 1.38 percent in Arizona. (Only one other state, Oregon, showed any decline.)</p>
        <p>The only large decline was in Washington, D.C., where out-of-wedlock births dropped 4.13 percent. The District of Columbia, along with Alabama and Michigan, also won bonuses last year in the first round of the program.</p>
        <p>The District has long had the highest out-of-wedlock birthrate in the nation, running above 60 percent. But that, like the recent declines, probably reflects its racial mix: the capital's population is mostly black, and while black women have traditionally had the highest rate of unmarried births, their rates are declining, while unmarried births to white women are on the rise.</p>
        <p>Michael Kharfen, a spokesman for the Department of Health and Human Services, does not dispute the idea that the bonus, so far, is rewarding demographic changes rather than effective state programs.</p>
        <p>''Most of what this is based on precedes the welfare reform act, and most of it is demographics,'' Mr. Kharfen said. ''And it's true that it doesn't target welfare recipients, since it's based on all out-of-wedlock births, and doesn't distinguish among economic background, or the age group, of the unmarried mothers.''</p>
        <p>As to why the program wasn't more targeted to welfare recipients, he said, ''you have to remember this was part of that whole welfare reform exchange with the states, that we give you the money and you have to achieve the goals, but we won't tell you what to do.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
