<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's Entertainment? That Depends...</title>
    <meta content="24OVER$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233192"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bureau of Labor Statistics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuehl, Claudia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04EFD8103BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2362" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's Entertainment? That Depends...</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA KUEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kuehl, Claudia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article, taking Bureau of Labor Statistics annual survey as classification baseline, explores that entertainment is and means to people in New York metropolitan statistical area; experts comment; drawings (Special Issue: Entertainment) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>REMEMBER what fun it was rushing Snowball to the vet after he gulped down a badminton birdie? Hey, you protest, that was not fun. Nevertheless, that's entertainment, according to the United States government.</p>
        <p>The Bureau of Labor Statistics, which annually surveys Americans about their spending habits, includes veterinary expenses in its ''entertainment'' category. Not classified as entertainment: reading, dining out and using a home computer, omissions that might give the bibliophile, the gourmand and the chat-room addict pause. The bureau also leaves out gambling, which some experts say is the most popular form of outside-the-home recreation in America.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>REMEMBER what fun it was rushing Snowball to the vet after he gulped down a badminton birdie? Hey, you protest, that was not fun. Nevertheless, that's entertainment, according to the United States government.</p>
        <p>The Bureau of Labor Statistics, which annually surveys Americans about their spending habits, includes veterinary expenses in its ''entertainment'' category. Not classified as entertainment: reading, dining out and using a home computer, omissions that might give the bibliophile, the gourmand and the chat-room addict pause. The bureau also leaves out gambling, which some experts say is the most popular form of outside-the-home recreation in America.</p>
        <p>The bureau's sometimes curious choices prompt the question: What is entertainment, anyway? And what factors -- genetic, geographic, chronologic, socioeconomic -- determine that some people, like Beth Henderson of Ashford, Conn., meet their entertainment needs through contemplative pursuits like reading and gardening, while others, like Rina Isaac of White Plains, embrace pulse-pounding activities like mountain biking and archery? What impels Dr. Alfred Scherzer of Hampton Bays, N.Y., to travel to Somalia to gaze at maribou storks, or Donald Wayne of Piscataway, N.J., to amass  100,000 postcards, including one made out of kangaroo skin?</p>
        <p>Social scientists say the human hunger for entertainment may be as old as society itself. ''I don't know that we have any sort of archaeological evidence of entertainment, per se,'' said Daniel Fessler, an assistant professor of anthropology at the University of California at Los Angeles, whose research fields include evolutionary psychology and psychological anthropology. ''But what we do have is the observation that all known human societies have entertainment of some fashion, and that suggests that it's very old indeed.''</p>
        <p>A society without entertainment ''would be a pretty frightening thing,'' said Frank A. Salamone, a professor of sociology at Iona College in New Rochelle, N.Y., and the author of ''Society, Culture, Leisure and Play: An Anthropological Reference'' (University Press of America, 2000).</p>
        <p>Entertainment ''lets us dream,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''It's imagination,'' he added. ''Play at its best gives us a million options.''</p>
        <p>As a noun, ''play'' commonly refers to the games of children. Adults, too old to zip into playsuits, instead put on ''leisure wear'' to ''recreate.''  But whether it's called leisure, recreation or entertainment, when an activity is ''nonproductive, in other words, the aim is not a product, the aim is the experience,'' that's play, and adults need to do it, said John R. Kelly, a sociologist and the author of 11 books about leisure.</p>
        <p>''We are working creatures, we are bonding creatures,'' he said, ''and we are playing creatures.''</p>
        <p>In the New York metropolitan statistical area -- which includes New York City, Westchester, Long Island, most of northern and central New Jersey, and southwestern Connecticut -- households spent an average of $1,835 annually on entertainment in 1997-98, according to the Consumer Expenditure Survey conducted by the Bureau of Labor Statistics.</p>
        <p>That number, though, is misleadingly low. Besides pet care, the bureau's list of entertainments includes movies and sporting events; hobbies, toys and games; television sets, videos and stereos; and sporting and exercise equipment. But add items like dining out, alcoholic beverages and reading, and the amount jumps to almost $5,200 a year, or more than 10 percent of the average household's pretax income. Add still more -- lottery tickets, Internet access, the incalculable costs of recreational shopping, and major investments, like the room Mr. Wayne added onto his New Jersey home to accommodate his collections -- and entertainment costs can soar.</p>
        <p>In some years, Dr. Scherzer, 71, spends more than $5,000 to watch birds in exotic locales. A practicing pediatrician and emeritus professor of pediatrics at Cornell Medical College, he is a co-president of the Moriches Bay Audubon Society, which has more than 750 members and covers a territory extending from Patchogue to the tip of the South Fork.</p>
        <p>In 35 years as a birder, Dr. Scherzer said, he has logged 1,500 to 2,000 species, many in his backyard, figuratively speaking. ''Eastern Long Island is very unusual, because the land mass involves the Atlantic Ocean on the east and the bays on the west, and it's right on the flyway of the eastern migration of birds that come down virtually from the North Pole on their way to South America,'' he said.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Kelly, who is a co-author with Rodney B. Warnick of ''Recreation Trends and Markets: The 21st Century'' (Sagamore, 1999), bird-watching is increasingly popular, especially among older adults, a population that grows with each aging baby boomer. In New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, membership in National Audubon Society chapters has climbed almost 17 percent in the last decade, to nearly 72,000, an Audubon Society spokesman said.</p>
        <p>At the Morton National Wildlife Refuge, a slender peninsula west of Sag Harbor, N.Y., that includes both upland and shore habitats, naturalists have documented roughly 280 species, and last year people flocked to see them. Attendance for 1998-99 reached almost 82,000, more than double the number of a decade ago, said Bob Parris, the deputy project leader for the Long Island National Wildlife Refuge Complex, which includes Morton and eight other sites.</p>
        <p>Dr. Scherzer said he liked to visit Morton in the off-season, when the crowds are sparser. There, he holds out his hand to the black-capped chickadees, which, secure in their protected area, boldly peck sunflower seeds from a human palm. ''It's just a nice experience,'' Dr. Scherzer said, ''that little furry thing on your finger.''</p>
        <p>Variety of Influences</p>
        <p>Economics, education, sex, religion, family background and age all influence entertainment choices. Up to 20 percent of Americans have no discretionary income for entertainment, while 10 percent can afford to spend ''significant amounts'' on fun, according to ''Recreation Trends and Markets.'' Further, some Americans have little discretionary time, Dr.  Kelly said, citing people who hold two jobs to support a family, mothers who shoulder a full-time job and take care of their families, too, and workers who may lose hours of recreation time to commuting.</p>
        <p>Choices also spring from living in a particular time and place. ''What was incredibly amusing in 1890 is now seen to be no longer funny, for the most part,'' said Dr. Salamone, the Iona professor. ''See two minutes of a German film, and you know it's German. Broadly speaking, English jokes aren't funny in the United States, no matter what background people have. Why do the French like Jerry Lewis? I never understood that.''</p>
        <p>People also choose activities that balance their lives. ''If you work in a steel mill all day, you don't rush out to play tennis when you leave the job,'' Dr. Kelly said. And for reasons that are still little understood, he said, some people are risk takers who like to play on the edge, others are intensely self-protective and need a comfort zone, and the majority fall between the two extremes.</p>
        <p>Ms. Isaac, 38, who teaches first graders in Manhattan, said that skiing, hiking, biking and archery help keep her balanced. ''When I leave the city, I need to revive my soul,'' she said. ''I make sure I am with nature.''</p>
        <p>The bow and arrow, which she took up three years ago, require a concentration and focus that send her deep into herself. ''You only hear your pulse, your heartbeat -- you can feel your sweat,'' she said. ''It's a competition between my physical self and my mind.''</p>
        <p>Games generally fall into one of two categories: those that combine physical skill and strategy, and those that combine strategy and chance, said Garry Chick, an associate professor of leisure studies at Pennsylvania State University. Players who excel in the first category reap more prestige, he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Isaac said one benefit from her archery is a new identity. ''People call me Rina the Archer, Pocahontas,'' she said. ''They say, 'The wild woman is here.' People see you on another level: 'Hey, that person shoots, and that's awesome.' ''</p>
        <p>The Couch Potato</p>
        <p>If archers inspire awe, couch potatoes draw sneers. But watching television remains Americans' prime pastime at night, a Gallup Poll reported in March 1999. Results of another Gallup Poll in January show that 57 percent of Americans watch three or more hours of television a day.</p>
        <p>Television delivers story after story, feeding the human need for narrative, which, along with dance, is a universal form of entertainment, said Dr. Fessler of U.C.L.A. Some theorists say that entertainment, like cooking, may be a tradition passed down from ancestral societies. But Dr. Fessler said it may instead be an evolved psychology, a desire that became embedded in the human mind through evolution.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, Dr. Fessler said, evolved psychologies can become insatiable. ''If you could afford it, and I guess some people can,'' he said, ''you can just plug yourself into entertainment all of your waking hours and never leave the house.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, more narratives await at the local multiplex. Between 1989 and 1999, the number of movie screens in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut rose 60 percent, to 3,470, according to the National Association of Theater Owners. Box offices nationwide took in $7.49 billion in 1999, and Americans spent an additional $17.36 billion renting and buying movies, according to the Video Software Dealers Association.</p>
        <p>Luckily for literacy, the stories on library shelves still beckon. According to ''Recreation Trends and Markets,'' more than 90 million adult Americans read books, and the number is rising. In early September, Ms. Henderson, 57, said she was reading six: a memoir, a biography, a travelogue, two local histories and a Harry Potter. A former teacher and school administrator who is now a sculptor, Ms. Henderson said that she spent $75 to $100 a month on newspapers, magazines and books, and combed the library stacks in Ashford and Mansfield, Conn., for free riches.  ''One of the things I like about reading is that it really promotes the use of your imagination, a lot more than watching a movie, for example,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In contrast, gambling, which Professors Kelly and Warnick describe as ''the largest single 'recreation' activity outside the home,'' doesn't so much promote imagination as feed off it, as gamblers imagine themselves rich.</p>
        <p>Their imaginations were working overtime in 1999 as Americans wagered more than $742 billion, according to an industry analyst, Christiansen Capital Advisors. That's 99 times last year's national movie box-office receipts, and almost triple the amount people wagered in 1989.</p>
        <p>In New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, dreamers spent $6.2 billion on lottery tickets in 1998-99, 73 percent more than a decade ago, according to figures provided by state lottery officials. And gamblers wagered $43.5 billion in Atlantic City casinos in 1999, about twice what  they spent in 1989, according to New Jersey Casino Control Commission figures.</p>
        <p>Gambling, which falls into the strategy-and-chance category of games, creates ''a kind of an artificial excitement,'' Dr. Kelly said.</p>
        <p>''You don't have to gain any skill to pull levers and push buttons,'' he said, ''but something is happening and you're involved in it and you have a certain stake in it.'' Gambling choices and styles vary. Some play bingo for fun, others buy lottery tickets out of financial desperation. ''That isn't play,'' he said. ''That's waiting to be struck by lightning.''</p>
        <p>Hooked On Collecting</p>
        <p>Gamblers and collectors are both treasure seekers, but collectors rarely go home empty-handed.</p>
        <p>There are four clubs in New Jersey for postcard collectors, known as deltiologists, and Mr. Wayne belongs to three of them, including the Central Jersey Deltiological Society, of which he is president. A serious collector since the mid-1960's, Mr. Wayne, 65, said he went ''a little berserk'' over novelty cards. Besides the kangaroo-skin oddity, he owns cards made of Irish peat, celluloid, aluminum, leather, macerated money and woven silk.</p>
        <p>But his acquisitive days are winding down, Mr. Wayne said, because even with the extra room, ''the house is full.'' Still, a collector can dream. At a recent postcard show in Clark, N.J., Mr. Wayne pointed out a man who claimed to own a million cards. ''People revere him as one of the icons of the postcard world,'' Mr. Wayne said. ''At least, I do.''</p>
        <p>Somewhere in the United States is someone who collects just about every kind of object, Dr. Kelly said. Add up all the collections -- stamps, coins, rocks, bones, thimbles, Hummel figurines, comic books, ice cream scoops, barbed wire and everything else -- and ''you probably have a fairly significant part of the adult population,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Collectors form groups, attend meetings and publish journals. ''The social aspects become very important,'' Dr. Kelly said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wayne, a retired math teacher who also collects slide rules and books about space, said he couldn't expect people to appreciate the thrill of postcards unless they saw his treasures. Even then they might not understand. Such passions develop over time, and the impulses behind them are often complex.</p>
        <p>Although it is easy simply to mock somebody else's idea of fun, the Bureau of Labor Statistics contends that it has valid reasons for each  omission from the Consumer Expenditure Survey's entertainment category. For example, the bureau deems reading more informational than entertaining, said Bill Passero, a senior economist. Dining out is a subcategory under food, and gambling is a miscellaneous expenditure, Mr. Passero said, noting that many  regard it not as entertainment but as an investment with a possible return.</p>
        <p>As for pet care, it's been part of entertainment (formerly ''recreation'') since at least 1950, according to bureau records. Where else would you put it? Mr. Passero wondered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wayne, for one, said the notion of pets as entertainment made sense.  He and his wife have two Shetland sheepdogs. ''They're a riot,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
