<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</title>
    <meta content="T22BAL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233167"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E1DA103BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anita Gates</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DON'T you just hate George Bush (pere) for turning ''a kinder, gentler America'' into a political joke? Henry Koster's HARVEY (1950) couldn't be kinder or gentler, even though it's about an alcoholic with mental problems James Stewart plays Elwood P. Dowd, of course, best friend of the title character, an invisible, martini-drinking 6-foot-3 1/2-inch-tall rabbit. (Harvey is seen by audiences only once, with is arm draped around Stewart in an oil portrait over the fireplace.) Josephine Hull won the best supporting actress Oscar for her role as Veta, Elwood's nervous older sister who tries to have him committed. Anyone who can sit through Stewart's alley-behind-the-bar speech and not feel a surge of warmth toward human kind in general is too cynical to live - Wednesday at 10:15 p.m. and Wednesday/Early Thursday at 4:45 a.m. on AMC.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DON'T you just hate George Bush (pere) for turning ''a kinder, gentler America'' into a political joke? Henry Koster's HARVEY (1950) couldn't be kinder or gentler, even though it's about an alcoholic with mental problems James Stewart plays Elwood P. Dowd, of course, best friend of the title character, an invisible, martini-drinking 6-foot-3 1/2-inch-tall rabbit. (Harvey is seen by audiences only once, with is arm draped around Stewart in an oil portrait over the fireplace.) Josephine Hull won the best supporting actress Oscar for her role as Veta, Elwood's nervous older sister who tries to have him committed. Anyone who can sit through Stewart's alley-behind-the-bar speech and not feel a surge of warmth toward human kind in general is too cynical to live - Wednesday at 10:15 p.m. and Wednesday/Early Thursday at 4:45 a.m. on AMC.</p>
        <p>George Bernard Shaw's name doesn't turn up in screenwriting credits often, but he was one of the five writers of PYGMALION (1938), based on his 1913 London play. The film - the original, nonmusical story of Henry Higgin's transformation of Eliza Doolittle from Cockney flower girl to beautifully spoken lady - has other revelations too. Lots of movie goers know Dame Wendy Hiller only from her Lady Bracknell and Mrs. Micawber days, but she was a dewy-faced newcomer, hailed as a young acting discovery, when she played Eliza. She's more convincingly low and more subtly changed than other interpreters of the role. And it's a joy to see Leslie Howard, a truly sexy Higgins ( in a Niles Crane sort of way), in an age-appropriate role. (Two years before, at 43, he'd played Romeo; and at 46 he was the supposedly young object of Scarlett O'Hara's affections, Ashley Wilkes.) Howard and Anthony Asquith directed - Saturday at 9 p.m. on CUNY.</p>
        <p>You could watch Alan Resnais's LAST YEAR AT MARIENBAD (1962) without reading the subtitles or knowing a word of French and much of it would still be fascinating. Sacha Vierny's cinematography alone is worth a New Wave fan's time, as this odd, hypnotic film's three characters glide slowly through a glamorous French hotel. But the film has a great deal to say, mostly about memory and reality. Delphine Seyrig plays a woman on holiday approached by a man (Giorgio Albertazzi) who says they met the year before and had an affair. She says she's never seen him before. Sacha Pitoeff is the woman's escort, who may or may not be her husband. It's sometimes baffling, sometimes stunning and a classic - Friday at 9 p.m. on TCM.</p>
        <p>Every writer who has ever dreamed of getting away from it all to work in complete isolation can appreciate Martin Ritts's sincere if improbably idyllic CROSS CREEK (1983). Mary Steenburgen plays Marjorie Kinnan Rawlings, before she wrote ''The Yearling,'' starting life anew, alone in a Florida swamp. Alfred Woodard earned a best supporting actress nomination for her role as the young woman Rawlings hires and inspires. Malcolm McDowell, Ms. Steenburgen's husband at the time, has a memorable cameo as Maxwell Perkins, the editor every good writer deserves - Sunday at 9 p.m., Sunday/Early Monday at 1 a.m. and Monday at 1 p.m. on Bravo.</p>
        <p>It may forever be known as the film on which Warren Beatty and Annette Bening (now married for eight years, with four children) met. BUGSY (1991), directed by Barry Levinson, is captivating and has a bevy of Oscar nominations to prove it. It's the story of Bugsy Siegel, the gangster who went to Hollywood, met his romantic match and ended up inventing Las Vegas - Thursday at 8 p.m. on Channel 55.</p>
        <p>Anita Gates</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
