<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 9-24-00: The Ethicist; Conference Call</title>
    <meta content="WLN123637" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Health; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233063"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Guarantees and Warranties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/The Ethicist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E1DA143BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="865" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 9-24-00: The Ethicist; Conference Call</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Randy Cohen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Randy Cohen The Ethicist column answers questions about whether it is wrong for doctors to accept lavish trips to weekend conferences subsidized by drug companies touting new products, buying new fan and using receipt to return broken one whose 90-day guarantee had passed, bidding up price at annual charity quilt auction and using no-longer-valid employee photo ID to get into museums for free (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A drug company invited me, a physician, to a weekend conference on one of their expensive new products. They flew my wife and me to a lovely resort where they fed and entertained us lavishly. I attended scientific meetings for a few hours; the rest of the time we were free to amuse ourselves. No quid pro quo was requested. To circumvent government regulations that limit such gifts, they made us doctors nominal ''consultants'' and paid us each $1,000. Everyone I spoke with felt a bit guilty about it (including me), but the inducements were too good to pass up. Do you see an ethical problem here? -- Anonymous, Kansas</p>
        <p>I do see a problem, and so does the American Medical Association -- it's called conflict of interest. To avoid it, the A.M.A.'s code of professional conduct says that an industry should not subsidize the cost of travel, lodging or personal expenses of conference-attending physicians.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A drug company invited me, a physician, to a weekend conference on one of their expensive new products. They flew my wife and me to a lovely resort where they fed and entertained us lavishly. I attended scientific meetings for a few hours; the rest of the time we were free to amuse ourselves. No quid pro quo was requested. To circumvent government regulations that limit such gifts, they made us doctors nominal ''consultants'' and paid us each $1,000. Everyone I spoke with felt a bit guilty about it (including me), but the inducements were too good to pass up. Do you see an ethical problem here? -- Anonymous, Kansas</p>
        <p>I do see a problem, and so does the American Medical Association -- it's called conflict of interest. To avoid it, the A.M.A.'s code of professional conduct says that an industry should not subsidize the cost of travel, lodging or personal expenses of conference-attending physicians.</p>
        <p>Accepting a drug company's largess might bias you in its favor -- if only subtly -- when you're deciding what medication to prescribe to your patients or order for your hospital. You and your colleagues may fancy yourselves beyond such partiality, but if it were so, that would practically make you unique human beings. Certainly your susceptibility to influence is presumed by the pharmaceutical companies: that's why they ladle out the money for lavish dinners.</p>
        <p>Signing on as a ''consultant'' heightens the ethical lapse. You yourself regard it as deceitful, and it is expressly forbidden by the A.M.A., which proscribes ''token consulting'' to justify the compensation of physicians by pharmaceutical companies.</p>
        <p>What slightly ameliorates your experience is the extent to which it is shared by your colleagues, despite the A.M.A.'s code. One definition of ethics is to conform to the conduct of one's profession. By this standard, you've done nothing wrong. However, by this standard a bookie does no wrong when he breaks the legs of a guy who is tardy paying his gambling debts. We may, perhaps, make more rigorous ethical demands upon you. If the conference was important, you should have bought your own ticket and attended with a clear conscience.</p>
        <p>One spring, I bought a window fan with a 90-day guarantee. I used it briefly then didn't use it at all for months. When I used it again after Labor Day, a blade broke off. I couldn't return it because 90 days had passed, so I bought an identical fan and used that receipt to return the older broken one. I believe the guarantee should cover 90 days of actual use, and so I say I did nothing wrong. Do you agree? -- A. K., Brooklyn</p>
        <p>I do not. That you can imagine a more flexible returns policy is neither here nor there. (I can envision my rent being $35 dollars a month, but my landlord remains committed to the amount actually stipulated in the lease.) However inadequate the guarantee, its terms were clearly spelled out when you bought the fan. While it is lamentable that your fan broke after the guarantee's expiration, that does not justify this petty deceit.</p>
        <p>At an annual charity quilt auction for a Mennonite camping association, prices were running lower than usual, so I bid up the price on a quilt I didn't want but could see that another guy really wanted. Eventually he got his quilt and the camp got some extra money. But was I wrong to cause him to spend more than he otherwise would have? -- Anonymous, Copenhagen, N.Y.</p>
        <p>You did nothing wrong. Indeed, you abetted the mission of the event, which was to attract charitable contributions, not just bargain hunters. Unlike auction scams in which a dealer's shills bid up a price, you'd have had to pay for the quilt had your bid prevailed. That is, you would have had to take responsibility for your actions, one aspect of ethical behavior. In addition, the other guy was free to drop out at any time. While your motives were different from his -- philanthropic rather than acquisitive -- there was no deceit, no compulsion and no impropriety.</p>
        <p>One of the perks I enjoyed on a recent job was free admission to museums with my employee photo ID card. Although I am no longer connected to the company, they never took back my ID, and I continue using it in my visits to the museums. Am I cheating?</p>
        <p>-- Anonymous, New York</p>
        <p>Let me ask you a question: if they'd neglected to collect your ignition key, would you still be cruising around in the company car?</p>
        <p>You are cheating the museum if you use a fake ID, i.e., one that falsely lists you as holding your old job. (Nor is it entirely proper to gain entry by paying with a counterfeit 20, by crouching down and saying you're under 5 or by wearing a smock, a straw hat and a look of genius while claiming to be the ghost of Claude Monet.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
