<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Restaurants Offer Music as an Entree</title>
    <meta content="24DINE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233097"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E3DB123BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Restaurants Offer Music as an Entree</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Long Island restaurants that offer live entertainment, including singers and dancers; photos; list (Special Issue: Entertainment) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GUACAMOLE has more zip and a margarita more tang when accompanied by a mariachi band; veal Marsala and spaghetti Arabiata more savor when they are enjoyed in tandem with a Verdi aria; swordfish kebab and shrimp Marmaris seem more exotic when a belly dancer is also working her magic; even a quiet dinner takes on a new identity when there is more to come: a movie or show as part of the price.</p>
        <p>Scores of restaurants provide harp or keyboard music as an accompaniment, but often patrons want more: a show, a full band, an extravaganza.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GUACAMOLE has more zip and a margarita more tang when accompanied by a mariachi band; veal Marsala and spaghetti Arabiata more savor when they are enjoyed in tandem with a Verdi aria; swordfish kebab and shrimp Marmaris seem more exotic when a belly dancer is also working her magic; even a quiet dinner takes on a new identity when there is more to come: a movie or show as part of the price.</p>
        <p>Scores of restaurants provide harp or keyboard music as an accompaniment, but often patrons want more: a show, a full band, an extravaganza.</p>
        <p>Several Long Island spots offer the best of both worlds: food that could make it on its own, plus a night of fun.  Southern-style restaurants, especially those with ties to New Orleans, frequently feature jazz and blues bands. Good dining spots like Cooking With Jazz, Too in Malvern, Cornbread and Caviar in Baldwin, Catfish Cafe in Lynbrook, Bayou in North Bellmore, Elk Street Grille in Port Jefferson, Duo in Hauppauge and Tupelo Honey in Sea Cliff come to mind. (See accompanying box for details.)</p>
        <p>Paula Jean's Supper Club in East Setauket has one of the most ambitious menus of live blues, zydeco and jazz around. Paula Jean's looks like a vintage nightclub with tables topped with 1930's-style shaded lanterns. There is a small stage with a backdrop of mirrors. Other walls hold pictures of legendary blues musicians.</p>
        <p>On a recent Wednesday there was an open blues jam. The host band that night was led by Willie Steele.  The trio played not only blues, but also delighted the crowd with jazz, swing and other rhythms. After an hour or so they took a break and turned the mike over to a jeans-clad fellow from the audience who played guitar and sang blues.</p>
        <p>Although the food is not as impressive as it was a few years ago, there's still plenty of good eating here. Head for the Cajun-Creole specialties, especially the Louisiana sampler ($27.50), a huge platter that serves four as an appetizer or two for a full meal. It has some of the restaurant's best dishes: New Friends gumbo, Cajun jambalaya, chicken Creole, red beans and rice and seafood-stuffed eggplant. The menu states, ''To keep music alive and menu prices reasonable we charge a nominal music fee.'' It was $5 a person that night.</p>
        <p>Another spot offering live music Thursday through Saturday nights is Bridges in Bridgehampton. But it is this restaurant's gospel brunches on  Sundays that offer something special on the Island. The music starts at 2 p.m. and goes for an hour. The men's chorus of the First Baptist Church of Southampton had diners clapping in rhythm and tapping their toes one recent Sunday afternoon. Churches from Greenport, Riverhead and Southampton participate other weeks. This is a spirited, lively experience complemented by soul-satisfying food.</p>
        <p>The $24.95 brunch starts with a complimentary drink and a selection of homemade quick breads. It ends with delightful homemade desserts.  High marks were earned by the warm bread pudding and the moist brownie sundae with vanilla ice cream and fudge sauce.</p>
        <p>Our favorite entree was the bourbon-glazed sliced ham accompanied by tasty collard greens, whipped sweet potatoes and rice. Blackened salmon, with the same plate mates, was moist and flaky. More traditional brunch fare, like omelets and eggs Benedict, arrive with asparagus, crisp potato pancakes and a fresh fruit garnish. Southern-fried chicken is another option.</p>
        <p>More typical of the Hamptons are the top-notch East End spots that serve special dinners that include a ticket to the movies as part of the price: Nick &amp; Toni's in East Hampton, the Paradise Cafe in Sag Harbor and the Maidstone Arms in East Hampton. The Maidstone also has a dinner-theater offering: a meal at a first-rate restaurant followed by a play down the street at the Guild Hall. In Nassau County, the Carltun's Palm Court in East Meadow has a similar deal, a four-course fixed-price dinner and a ticket to the show at the Westbury Music Fair.</p>
        <p>The Island's ethnic restaurants provide many opportunities for fun-filled nights. On Fridays and Saturdays, diners at Tequila Sunrise in Roslyn Heights are serenaded by a strolling mariachi band. Piri's Grill, a Turkish fish house in Great Neck, goes even further. Every Saturday night beginning at 8:30, there is Turkish music, followed by a belly dancer at 9:30.</p>
        <p>Large tables are set up on Saturday night, for this is the place to come for a celebration. We heard three or four ''Happy Birthdays'' and one ''Happy Anniversary'' sung one recent Saturday.</p>
        <p>When the waiters are not belting out those tunes, a duo is playing Turkish music and a talented young woman named April Grace is dancing between the tables. Sometimes she balances a curved sword on her head, at other times she captures diners with her shawl, encouraging them to dance with her.</p>
        <p>The music makes Piri's festive on Saturdays, but the food brings diners back. A large basket filled with warm pita triangles, squares of focaccia and slices of French bread is the perfect partner for the marvelous Turkish appetizers (mezes).</p>
        <p>The smoky babaganouj (eggplant salad), mild, creamy tarama (red caviar dip) and cacik (yogurt sauce flecked with dill) are standouts. Other pleasing openers are the melt-in-the-mouth stuffed eggplant, the garlicky grilled calamari brushed with a slick of lemon, oil and herbs, and the coban salad, a platter of cubed glistening jewels: tomatoes, cucumbers, onions, peppers and parsley in a nicely balanced vinaigrette.</p>
        <p>Most entrees are around $15, with the superb grilled calamari $12.95 when ordered as a main course. Fish are lovingly prepared here. Both the whole grilled St. Peter's fish and the grilled halibut were treats.</p>
        <p>Also earning high marks were the shrimp Marmaris, a ramekin holding a tasty broth chock-full of vegetables and firm shrimp glazed with a whisper of melted cheese, and the adana yogurtlu kebab, two cylinders of deftly spiced chopped lamb presented atop a bed of diced pita and yogurt sauce.</p>
        <p>The Italians excel at hospitality.  The good times at Pappagallo in Glen Head, La Cisterna in Mineola and La Viola in Cedarhurst often take the form of opera nights. On a recent Friday at La Viola, we experienced a near-perfect evening: an enthusiastic welcome, terrific food and wonderful music.</p>
        <p>Our waiter pegged us as first-timers and offered to answer any questions. He did a good job explaining the meal and previewing the musical entertainment. The $40 four-course dinner included unlimited wine (freely poured) or soft drinks.</p>
        <p>It began with a memorable pasta:  rigatoni in a fresh-tasting tomato sauce full of shrimp and chicken.  Diners had a choice of Caesar or mixed salad, followed by crisp veal Milanese under a mantle of chopped, ruby red tomatoes, onions, basil and garlic; juicy chicken breasts topped with asparagus and shiitake mushrooms, or sole francese. All were accompanied by a tasty potato croquette and creamed spinach. Portions were so large that doggie bags were de rigueur. Dessert was a yummy Napoleon oozing pastry cream.</p>
        <p>The sweetest part of the evening, though, was the music, which began at 8. That night, Carol Welker, Lee Roisum and Efren Puig were the singers, ably accompanied by Randy White at the piano. The eight selections from Verdi's ''Traviata,'' ''Don Carlo'' and ''Otello'' drew bravos and bravas from the appreciative audience. The cheers were sometimes led by the No. 1 music lover in the room, La Viola's owner, Lino Viola.</p>
        <p>Opera nights at La Viola are held in an upstairs party room that is spacious but still small enough to give a feeling of intimacy. The evening ended with the talented, personable performers changing the pace and singing songs from Broadway shows. A medley from ''The Sound of Music'' provided a chance for the audience to join in ''Climb Every Mountain'' and ''Edelweiss.''  There is no better night of restaurant entertainment than opera night at La Viola.</p>
        <p>A sampling of restaurants that offer more than food:</p>
        <p>Bayou, Omni Plaza -- 2823 Jerusalem Ave, North Bellmore, (516) 785-9263. Jazz or blues band every Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Bridges -- 964 Bridgehampton-Sag Harbor Turnpike, Bridgehampton, (631) 537-9105. Bands Thursday, Friday and Saturday nights. Gospel brunch 12:30 to 3 p.m. Sundays ($24.95). Music begins at 2 p.m.</p>
        <p>Carltun's Palm Court -- Eisenhower Park, East Measow, (516) 542-0700. Live jazz and late night menu every Friday and Saturday 8:30 p.m. to 1 a.m. Dinner and a show (Westbury Music Fair) $70. Call for schedule.</p>
        <p>Catfish Cafe -- 172 Merrick Road, Lynbrook, (516) 599-0137.  Blues Wednesdays and Fridays.</p>
        <p>Cooking With Jazz, Too -- 47 Church Street, Malverne, (516) 599-9589. Live music every night but Saturday. Closed Mondays.</p>
        <p>Cornbread and Caviar -- 590 Sunrise Highway, Baldwin, (516) 223-9575. Jazz band Fridays 6 to 10 p.m.</p>
        <p>Duo -- 661 Old Willets Path, Hauppauge, (631) 851-1507. Dance band Fridays 9 p.m. to 1 a.m. and a jazz duo Saturdays from 7:30 to 11 p.m.</p>
        <p>Elk Street Grille -- 201 Main Street, Port Jefferson, (631) 331 0960. Jazz band every Friday 8:30 to 11 p.m.</p>
        <p>La Cisterna -- 109 Mineola Boulevard, Mineola, (516) 746-9474.  Opera night the last Wednesday of the month beginning Oct. 25 ($65).  Before that date, the restaurant will offer a series of Neopolitan nights, with the next one scheduled Thursday. The regular menu is offered with a 10 percent music charge.</p>
        <p>La Viola -- 99 Chestnut Street, Cedarhurst, (516) 569-6020. Opera night is usually the first Friday of every month ($40). The next is scheduled for Nov. 3.</p>
        <p>The Maidstone Arms -- 207 Main Street, East Hampton, (631) 324-5006. Dinner and a movie special $28.50 for a three-course prix fixe dinner offered Monday through Friday from 6 to 7 p.m.  Dinner theater in conjunction with plays at the Guild Hall, $32 on Fridays, $36 on Saturdays for three-course dinner and a show.  Last seating at 6:15 for 8 p.m. curtain.</p>
        <p>Nick and Toni's, 136 North Main Street, East Hampton, (631) 324-3550. Special $24.95 dinner includes a UA movie ticket. Available Fridays and Sundays from 6 to 7 p.m. from late October to Memorial Day.</p>
        <p>Pappagallo -- 716 Glen Cove Avenue, Glen Head, (516) 676-3400.  Opera night the third Wednesday of the month. Five-course dinner at 7, music at 8 p.m. ($40).</p>
        <p>The Paradise Cafe -- 126 Main Street, Sag Harbor, (631) 725-6080.  Dinner and a movie in association with the Sag Harbor Cinema. The two-course meal is $28.50 and is offered Sunday through Thursday.  Movie tickets are good for the 5 or 7 p.m. show on Sunday and Monday and for the 7 p.m. show Tuesday through Thursday.</p>
        <p>Paula Jean's Supper Club -- 130 Old Town Road, East Setauket, (631) 751 5483. Music begins at 9 p.m. Wednesdays, open blues jams; some Thursdays, the concert of the month; Fridays, dance bands; Saturdays, blues bands. Sundays, open mike.</p>
        <p>Piri's Grill, 4 Welwyn Road, Great Neck, (516) 487-1070. Every Saturday Turkish music at 8:30 p.m., belly dancer at 9:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Tequila Sunrise, 388 Willis Avenue, Roslyn Heights, (516) 484-3341. Strolling mariachi band every Friday and Saturday night.</p>
        <p>Tupelo Honey -- 39 Roslyn Avenue, Sea Cliff, (516) 671-8300. Jazz Sunday brunch and Monday nights.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
