<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where All the Town's a Stage</title>
    <meta content="STRAW.$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Portsmouth (Nh)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marker, Sherry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire/Portsmouth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D6163BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where All the Town's a Stage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERRY MARKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marker, Sherry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sherry Marker travel article on historic neighborhood of Strawbery Banke in Portsmouth, NH, populated by costumed role players and interpreters; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT Strawbery Banke in Portsmouth, N.H., costumed role players and interpreters encourage visitors to eavesdrop on three  centuries of daily life, from the first settlement here in 1630 to the museum's foundation in 1958. The 1630 settlement took its name from the wild berries that grew along the banks of the Piscataqua River, but the settlers were less interested in the site's sylvan pleasures than in its economic possibilities. In 1653 Strawbery Banke changed its name to Portsmouth,  trumpeting that ''We are at the river's mouth and our port is as good as any in the land.'' Today's Strawbery Banke, which calls itself an outdoor history museum, preserves the original spelling of the first settlement's name.</p>
        <p>Throughout the 17th and 18th centuries, Portsmouth's sea captains sped cargos of lumber and cod across the Atlantic and throughout the Caribbean. Local carpenters made everything from the clipper ships to the boxes that held the cod. Prosperous sea captains and merchants built themselves handsome homes overlooking the waters that lapped the busy docks. But, when shipping declined in the 19th century, so did Portsmouth. As waterways silted up, and finally were filled in altogether, Portsmouth's oldest neighborhood was dismissively nicknamed Puddle Dock.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT Strawbery Banke in Portsmouth, N.H., costumed role players and interpreters encourage visitors to eavesdrop on three  centuries of daily life, from the first settlement here in 1630 to the museum's foundation in 1958. The 1630 settlement took its name from the wild berries that grew along the banks of the Piscataqua River, but the settlers were less interested in the site's sylvan pleasures than in its economic possibilities. In 1653 Strawbery Banke changed its name to Portsmouth,  trumpeting that ''We are at the river's mouth and our port is as good as any in the land.'' Today's Strawbery Banke, which calls itself an outdoor history museum, preserves the original spelling of the first settlement's name.</p>
        <p>Throughout the 17th and 18th centuries, Portsmouth's sea captains sped cargos of lumber and cod across the Atlantic and throughout the Caribbean. Local carpenters made everything from the clipper ships to the boxes that held the cod. Prosperous sea captains and merchants built themselves handsome homes overlooking the waters that lapped the busy docks. But, when shipping declined in the 19th century, so did Portsmouth. As waterways silted up, and finally were filled in altogether, Portsmouth's oldest neighborhood was dismissively nicknamed Puddle Dock.</p>
        <p>After World War II, greater Portsmouth  perceived the proliferating junkyards and tenaments of Puddle Dock as unwelcome eyesores. By the late 1950's, the entire 30-acre neighborhood was scheduled for the wholesale destruction then euphemistically called urban renewal. Fortunately, some local citizens were incensed at the thought that the Revolutionary War-era houses visited by George Washington, Lafayette and John Paul Jones might be razed. The preservationists bought the 10 central acres of Puddle Dock, and Strawbery Banke was reborn as a history museum. Now, Strawbery Banke draws some 60,000 visitors a year, and has been an important factor in the revitalization of Portsmouth.</p>
        <p>Strawbery Banke's 50 guides and six to eight costumed role players use everything from the leaded diamond-paned windows in the 17th-century Sherburne House to the gas chandelier in the elegant 19th-century Goodwin Mansion and the ration books in the World War II mom-and-pop Abbott Store to create ''a neighborhood where the past is forever present.'' The 40 mostly wood frame buildings that line Strawbery Banke's unpaved streets range in color from white to deep green, red and slate blue, with a variety of yellows and browns. Nine buildings are furnished as 18th-  and 19th-century homes; others contain crafts, architectural and archaeological displays, while yet others await restoration.</p>
        <p>Gardens with 18th-century medicinal herbs, Victorian flower beds, and the Kentucky Wonder pole beans of a World War II Victory garden grow where archaeological evidence, family letters and memories say they originally grew. Gardens and buildings, ranging from the 17th-century timber frame Sherburne House to a 20th-century cinder block garage, flank the central green that was a deep cove lined with docks until the early 1900's.</p>
        <p>When I visited Strawbery Banke last May, I particularly wanted to see two new exhibits: the Shapiro and Aldrich Houses. The Shapiro House, which opened in 1997, looks at the immigrant experience by focusing on the Shapiro family, which lived here in a late 18th-century house from 1909 to 1928.  The Aldrich House, which reopened in May after two years of extensive restoration,  recreates the atmosphere of the boyhood home of the writer Thomas Bailey Aldrich (1836-1907). I also wanted to revisit some of my favorite Strawbery Banke spots, so I allowed myself to wander the streets lined with flowering pear trees, stopping to watch a cooper making barrel staves at the Dinsmore shop, ogling the handsome slip-decorated stoneware made and sold at the museum pottery, and buying a copy of Aldrich's 1869 novel ''The Story of a Bad Boy'' at the excellent museum shop.</p>
        <p>I couldn't resist stopping at the house that for me encapsulates Strawbery Banke: the Drisco House on Puddle Lane. Step through the front door of this 18th-century frame house and turn right and you find yourself in the 1790's Shapley Shop. Cross the hall, and you'll be in a 1950's parlor that recreates a home from the period when Puddle Dock became the Strawbery Banke Museum.</p>
        <p>When I entered Mr. Shapley's shop, the costumed (and pigtailed) role player portraying the retired sea captain turned shopkeeper inquired where I had journeyed from that day. When I replied ''Massachusetts,'' Mr. Shapley wanted to know whether I had sailed over from Boston. After we worked out the details of my journey, I expressed surprise at the lemons and limes for sale.  Mr. Shapley asked whether I had not heard that a clipper had just put in from the Antilles.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Shapley spoke, I realized that I could faintly hear the voices of my childhood idols Dale Evans and Roy Rogers. Sure enough, when I said good-bye to Mr. Shapley and stepped across the Drisco House front hall, I found myself in a 1950's living room, with Roy, Dale and Trigger on the screen of a substantial black and white television console. From the linoleum floor covering and huge ash trays on floor stands, every detail precisely evoked the era of antimacassars. When I told an interpreter that I could almost smell my grandfather's Old Gold cigarettes, she told me that the living room had been arranged so that everyone could see the television -- and have an ash tray within easy reach.</p>
        <p>That 1950's living room gave me a severe case of nostalgia, so I headed along the dirt road to the World War II-era Abbott Store.  There, I was greeted by a dead ringer for Rosie the Riveter, who told me that she was waiting for the bus to the Naval Yard. ''My husband's not too happy about my working there,'' she confided, fiddling with her welder's goggles, ''but there's four of us ladies there now with so many men away.'' When she saw me eyeing the Chiclets in a glass display case she said, ''Guess that's the last we'll see of them. Now that the Philippines have fallen to the Japanese there's no more gum coming out to make Chiclets.''</p>
        <p>From the Abbott Store it was an easy stroll along Jefferson Street to the substantial 18th-century Thomas Bailey Aldrich House, which became Portsmouth's first museum house when the writer's widow created the Thomas Bailey Aldrich Memorial here in 1908. When the house had to be closed for structural repairs in 1998, Strawbery Banke made the decision to undertake a complete reinstallation. At present, the dining room and kitchen are complete, with the rest of the house to follow over the next few years. The undertaking is enormous: more than 600 items in the dining room and kitchen alone had to be removed, cataloged, cleaned and often repaired.</p>
        <p>Before all those items could be  returned to their original places, an important decision had to be made: should Mrs. Aldrich's original vision of the house be honored or should the reinstallation convey a more historically accurate version of the Aldrich House?</p>
        <p>By all accounts (including her own) Mrs. Aldrich, a quintessential literary widow, tried in 1908 to recreate every detail of her husband's boyhood home, drawing on her own memory of the house and on Aldrich's heavily autobiographical  ''Story of a Bad Boy.'' And therein lies the problem, since much that Mrs. Aldrich restored may originally have existed only in the world Aldrich created for his scalawag hero.  For example, the curator John Mayer suspects that the widow Aldrich may have allowed the strong forces of Colonial revivalism to persuade her to furnish a 19th-century kitchen with venerable Colonial cooking ware, including old-fashioned tin hearth ovens.</p>
        <p>After much soul-searching, Strawbery Banke decided to honor and recreate the 1908 vision of the Aldrich House as an example of how people then saw, and wished to see, the past.</p>
        <p>Already in 1908, Portsmouth was experiencing a wave of immigrants from southern and eastern Europe, and many long-time residents feared that the old ways were threatened. In short, not everyone would have been delighted at the news in 1909 that the Shapiros, a Jewish immigrant family from Russia, had moved into a late 18th-century white frame house virtually across the street from the Aldrich House.</p>
        <p>The costumed role player who portrays Mrs. Shapiro looked up from grating horseradish and greeted me with a ''Shalom'' as I stepped into her kitchen. As she set her glass of tea aside and smoothed the apron that covered her house dress, she told me that she had just finished planting her lettuces and peas, soon to be followed by beets for borscht.  She took a moment to show me her meat and her milk dishes, and to explain how she kept kosher, before turning to her massive cast-iron Beauty Hub coal stove.</p>
        <p>''I must be careful making the applesauce not to leave it too long on a too-hot burner,'' she said. ''If  you're not careful, applesauce becomes apple butter -- not a problem unless you're making latkes and need applesauce.''</p>
        <p>As mothers will, Mrs. Shapiro told me about her daughter, Mollie, who was worrying her parents by objecting to speaking Yiddish at home.  ''My Italian neighbors have the same problem,'' she said. ''Their children want only to be American and not learn the old languages that were good enough for us.''</p>
        <p>As other visitors entered the Shapiro House, I wandered off into the dining room, and listened to the audio recreation of the family's weekly Sabbath meal, and browsed upstairs, where I saw Mollie's collection of thumb-size china penny dolls, her toy coal stove and books for her Hebrew school lessons.</p>
        <p>When I came back downstairs, Mrs. Shapiro was telling a group of schoolchildren about Mollie's household chores. ''When my Mollie comes home from school,'' she said, ''she'll take the pan of melted water from under the icebox outside for water for the chickens.''</p>
        <p>I was almost out the door, when I thought of one more question. ''Those chickens,'' I said. ''I haven't seen them or even heard a peep out of them.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Shapiro was ready. ''On a day like this when it's still a bit chilly, the chickens like to huddle under the porch. When it's hot, they go there to get out of the sun. One day a little boy asked the question you just asked, and when I told him about the chickens, he ran outside and crawled under the porch. When he came back in, he said, 'I saw them, I saw the chickens under the porch.' ''</p>
        <p>That ability to make the invisible visible, the past present, is what Strawbery Banke is all about.</p>
        <p>Three centuries: barrel staves to ration books</p>
        <p>Getting There</p>
        <p>Strawbery Banke, (603) 433-1100, www.strawberybanke.org, in Portsmouth, N.H., is a five-hour drive from New York and an hour north of Boston. It is best reached by taking Exit 7 off Route I-95 and following the green Strawbery Banke signs.</p>
        <p>Planning a Trip</p>
        <p>The museum is open daily 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. through October. For the first time this year, from Nov. 1 to April 23, there will be guided walking tours beginning at the Dunaway Museum Shop; call the museum shop, (603) 433-1114, or the main number for times. Admission is $12 (off-season tours $7); seniors $11 (off season $6); ages 7 to 17 $8 (off season $4); family (two adults and two children under 17) $28. Tickets valid for two consecutive days.</p>
        <p>Coming events include Decorating the Sukkah, Oct. 12; Grand Old Portsmouth Brewer's Festival, Oct. 14 and 15; Hogwart's Halloween, Oct. 30; Annual Candlelight Stroll, Dec. 2 and 3 and 9 and 10; and an American Girl's Christmas, Dec. 16 and 17 and 27 to 30. Next year's theme will be Parlors, Pantries and Parties featuring furniture and ceramics and their use in the social life of Portsmouth.</p>
        <p>Visitors who find that Strawbery Banke whets their appetite for local history may want to buy the Portsmouth Harbour Trail guide, a historical walking tour of the town, and the Portsmouth Black Heritage Trail,  each $2 at the Greater Portsmouth Chamber of Commerce, 500 Market Street, (603) 436-1118; open Monday to Friday, 8:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>The 202-room Sheraton Harborside Portsmouth, (603) 431-2300, (800) 325-3535, fax (603) 431-7805, is a 10-minute walk from Strawbery Banke. There's an indoor pool and some rooms have harbor views, while others overlook an interior courtyard or the parking lot and town. Doubles: $129 to $179.</p>
        <p>Portsmouth has a number of pleasant bed-and-breakfast inns within easy walking distance of Strawbery Banke. The three-bedroom Oracle House Inn and Gardens, 38 Marcy Street, (603) 433-8827, is furnished with family heirlooms (the family has been here for 12 generations) and overlooks Strawbery Banke itself. Doubles $150.</p>
        <p>The nine-bedroom Bow Street Inn, 121 Bow Street, (603) 431-7760, fax (603) 433-1680, is on the second floor of a restored 19th-century brewery that now houses the Seacoast Repertory Theater. Rooms overlook the harbor or the 19th-century St. John's Church. Doubles $119 to $155.</p>
        <p>The Sise Inn, 40 Court Street, telephone and fax (603) 433-1200, is a Queen Anne mansion with marvelous oak woodwork, a Victorian parlor, fireplaces in most rooms, private bathrooms -- and Jacuzzi baths in several suites. Doubles $145 to $220.</p>
        <p>There are several motels just outside Portsmouth, at the Interstate Traffic Circle at Exit 5 off I-95. The Wynwood Hotel and Suites, telephone and fax (603) 436-7600, has indoor and outdoor pools. Doubles from $89 through October and during the holidays; winter rates from $59. You will have to use your car to get in and out of Portsmouth, and may want to use the High-Hanover Parking Facility (50 cents an hour).</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Dinner prices are for an entree and a glass of wine or beer.</p>
        <p>You can start eating right on the Strawbery Banke grounds, at The Cafe on the Banke, 61 Washington Street, (603) 436-8803, open daily 10 a.m. to 4 p.m., when the museum is open. The menu features sandwiches ($4.95), salads ($4.25) and snacks (pie or cake $2.95) that can be eaten indoors or at picnic tables.</p>
        <p>Open daily from 11 a.m. to 11:30 p.m., the perpetually crowded Stock Pot, 53 Bow Street, (603) 431-1851, has great harbor views and serves pastas, fish and vegetarian dishes; fish and chips, with a draft Sam Adams, costs $13.65.</p>
        <p>Roxanne's, formerly Karen's, 105 Daniel Street, (603) 431-1948, is open for breakfast and lunch Monday to Friday; brunch 8 a.m. to 2:30 p.m., Saturday and Sunday; and dinner 5:30 to 9:30 p.m. Thursday to Saturday. Terrific eggs Benedict; inventive pasta, fish and vegetarian dishes; indulgent desserts. There's an outdoor patio. Dinner for one with a glass of wine, from $20; reservations recommended for dinner.</p>
        <p>The upstairs wine bar at Lindbergh's Crossing, 29 Ceres Street, (603) 431-0887, opens daily at 4 p.m.  and the restaurant is open daily from 5:30 p.m. There's a harbor view upstairs, handsome brick and stone walls upstairs and down, and the entrees range from couscous with fruits de mer and seared duck breast to the somewhat eclectic free-range Southern fried rabbit with egg noodles and country gravy. Dinner for one with a glass of wine, from $25; reservations recommended.</p>
        <p>Wherever you eat, save room for a vanilla and ginger ice cream cone ($2.20) at Annabelle's, 49 Ceres Street, (603) 436-3400, open 10 a.m. until about 10 p.m. to mid-November.</p>
        <p>SHERRY MARKER lives in New England.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">SHERRY MARKER lives in New England.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
