<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Melissa Felsher, Mark Jaffe</title>
    <meta content="24FELS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FELSHER, MELISSA AMY (MELISSA AMY JAFFE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JAFFE, MARK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3DE113BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="403" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Melissa Felsher, Mark Jaffe</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Melissa Amy Felsher and Mark Jaffe, lawyers in the abuse and neglect division of the New York City Administration for Children's Services, were married last evening by Cantor Richard Botton at the Metropolitan Club in New York.</p>
        <p>The bride, 33, graduated cum laude from Syracuse University and received a master's degree in early childhood education from Columbia University and a law degree from Yeshiva University. Her father, Gary Felsher of New York, is the president of FGH Investments, a real estate development and investment company based in New York. Her mother, Alex Levitt of White Plains, is an interior designer there. The bride's stepfather, Albert Levitt, owns Nova Lighting, with retail stores in Nanuet, N.Y., and White Plains.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Melissa Amy Felsher and Mark Jaffe, lawyers in the abuse and neglect division of the New York City Administration for Children's Services, were married last evening by Cantor Richard Botton at the Metropolitan Club in New York.</p>
        <p>The bride, 33, graduated cum laude from Syracuse University and received a master's degree in early childhood education from Columbia University and a law degree from Yeshiva University. Her father, Gary Felsher of New York, is the president of FGH Investments, a real estate development and investment company based in New York. Her mother, Alex Levitt of White Plains, is an interior designer there. The bride's stepfather, Albert Levitt, owns Nova Lighting, with retail stores in Nanuet, N.Y., and White Plains.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 37, graduated from Syracuse and received a law degree from Tulane University. He is the son of Patricia and Murray Jaffe of Boca Raton, Fla., who are retired. His mother taught English and Latin at Oyster Bay High School on Long Island, and his father was the president of the Glaser-Jaffe Wool Stock Company, a fiber processing company in New York.</p>
        <p>The couple's romance developed in a measured manner because both worked in the same office at Children's Services.</p>
        <p>''I liked his interview style,'' Ms. Felsher said, remembering that Mr. Jaffe was one of her first interviewers when she applied for the job in October 1997. ''He had a good sense of humor and a confident, laid-back style, which helped relax me.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Jaffe was not the bride's direct supervisor, he would sometimes help her brainstorm through a problem. By the following May, the couple's friendship had evolved into romance.</p>
        <p>''Nothing is worse than a failed office romance,'' Mr. Jaffe said. ''But anytime you fall in love you take a risk.'' When they started dating, he immediately told his supervisor.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Jaffe proposed last Christmas Eve, the two continued to work in the same office, with similarly stressful jobs.</p>
        <p>For the bride, it has proven a balm. ''It is comforting knowing that he is there, and sharing in the work we do, which I think is very important.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
