<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Houston, Smarting Economically From Smog, Searches for Remedies</title>
    <meta content="24TEXA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/science/24TEXA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233392"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Petrochemistry and Petrochemicals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Houston (Tex)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yardley, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Houston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Petrochemistry and Petrochemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EED9163AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1349" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Houston, Smarting Economically From Smog, Searches for Remedies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM YARDLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yardley, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, Sept. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Economic self-interest that fueled Houston's growth is shaping its response to air quality problems that give it narrow lead over Los Angeles for unwanted title of nation's smog capital; city, at competitive disadvantage in attracting 'clean' industries prized in new economy, weighs controversial plan to comply with federal Clean Air Act by 2007; heaviest burden of plan falls on petrochemical companies that once dominated local economy and are responsible for bulk of pollution; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For decades, the stench of the nearby refineries never seemed to concern city leaders here. The hot summer breezes often carried a brown haze over the downtown skyline and, with it, an odor that the business elite regarded as the sweet smell of money.</p>
        <p>''Smell that,'' went a popular local refrain during the 1960's. ''That's prosperity.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For decades, the stench of the nearby refineries never seemed to concern city leaders here. The hot summer breezes often carried a brown haze over the downtown skyline and, with it, an odor that the business elite regarded as the sweet smell of money.</p>
        <p>''Smell that,'' went a popular local refrain during the 1960's. ''That's prosperity.''</p>
        <p>But no one is bragging about the city's bad air anymore. This year, Houston is narrowly leading Los Angeles for the unwanted title of the nation's smog capital. It had 38 days in which smog levels exceeded federal standards. The Environmental Protection Agency is threatening sanctions if something is not done. On Monday, readings of ozone, a primary ingredient in smog, were so high that residents in some neighborhoods were advised to stay indoors.</p>
        <p>So, for Houston, famous for its lack of zoning and its pursuit of free-wheeling capitalism, the polluted skies are forcing the city to do something that once seemed almost blasphemous here -- submit to government regulation. Even more, the proposed remedy calls for self-restraint that represents a major philosophical shift in this city.</p>
        <p>Yet, ultimately, the same economic self-interest that fueled Houston's unchecked growth is shaping its response to its air quality problems. In a new economy that prizes ''clean'' industries over polluting manufacturers, Houston is at a competitive disadvantage. Local technology companies are finding it harder to recruit employees, while business leaders fear that the city's image as the ''pollution capital'' is hurting its efforts to recruit companies and industries.</p>
        <p>''It's absolutely necessary that we solve this problem if we want to continue having economic growth and the lifestyle to which we are accustomed,'' said George Beatty Jr., an official with the Greater Houston Partnership, the region's chamber of commerce.</p>
        <p>Despite broad agreement on the severity of the problem, there is plenty of opposition to the proposed solution. This week, state officials held public hearings on a 19-point proposal to bring Houston into compliance with the federal Clean Air Act by 2007. The plan mandates a 90 percent reduction of industrial emissions, bans the use of heavy construction equipment and lawn mowers in the morning, reduces speed limits on highways and calls for coating new air-conditioning condensers with an experimental spray that supposedly eats ozone.</p>
        <p>On Monday, 800 furious people in suburban Brazoria County threatened to sue. They said they should be exempted because most of the pollution is generated elsewhere. On Tuesday, the air-conditioning industry argued that the condenser spray is unproven and would double prices. Landscape architects and contractors blanched at restricting work hours, and leaders of the petrochemical industry suggested that a 90 percent reduction in emissions might be impossible.</p>
        <p>''It's going to be tough on a lot of people,'' Commissioner Ralph Marquez of the Texas Natural Resources Conservation Commission said at a hearing Tuesday in downtown Houston. ''But the consequences of not doing it are greater.''</p>
        <p>The heaviest burden falls on the petrochemical companies that dominated the local economy until the collapse of the oil economy during the 1980's. The companies are responsible for the bulk of the pollution. Even today, nearly half of the petrochemical capacity in the United States remains on the eastern side of Harris County, which includes Houston.</p>
        <p>''Clean air is important and has to be achieved, but at the same time we have to maintain a strong economy,'' said Paula McLemore, a chemical company executive speaking for the East Harris County Manufacturers Association, which represents 120 plants and refineries.</p>
        <p>Ms. McLemore said her group was encouraging its members to do everything possible to meet the proposed goals, but she added that technology might not exist to enable every industry to reduce emissions 90 percent. ''Technology exists to get us to the 70 or 75 percent level,'' she said. ''Beyond that, it remains to be seen.'' She added, ''We're going to support this to the best of our ability.''</p>
        <p>For decades, the same men who ran the city's refineries also ran the city, and did so with the attitude that government should stay out of the way of business and development. As a result, Houston has perhaps the worst urban sprawl in the nation; its borders encompass 617 square miles, enough space to contain Chicago, Philadelphia, Baltimore and Detroit.</p>
        <p>''It was a place where you could make a lot of money, a place where the entrepreneurial spirit was unmolested,'' said Stephen Klineberg, a Rice University sociologist.</p>
        <p>But public criticism of the refineries is becoming increasingly acute. At Tuesday's hearing, one man called for a moratorium on new petrochemical plants, an unthinkable proposition in the past. Another woman criticized state officials for approving plans to expand the Port of Houston and to build a chemical plant near the suburb of Clear Lake.</p>
        <p>''My first recommendation is simple, and it falls under what is called common sense,'' said Tamara Maschino of Clear Lake. ''You clean up what you got before you add any more pollution.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Klineberg, who conducts an annual survey of attitudes in Houston, said the changing attitudes partly reflect the fact that the city's economy is no longer dominated by the petrochemical industry. He described the willingness of groups like the Greater Houston Partnership to embrace pollution reduction as ''a sudden 180-degree turn in the business leadership,'' even if the motives remain largely unchanged.</p>
        <p>''The goal has always been the same -- exploit whatever advantages you have to maximize profits,'' he said. ''That's exactly what's happening now. Suddenly, in the new world, our location next to the East Texas oil fields is no longer enough to get people to move here.''</p>
        <p>The deadline for completing a plan is approaching. The last of 14 public hearings is scheduled for next week, and state officials will accept written comments through September. The conservation commission must make a recommendation to the Environmental Protection Agency by December. The agency will spend about a year negotiating with state officials before implementation begins in 2002.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists note that much of this could have been avoided had state officials heeded warnings more than five years ago to seek reductions in emissions of nitrogen oxide, a primary raw material in the creation of ozone. Ground-level ozone is formed in hot, sunny climates when nitrous oxides from smokestacks, automobiles and other sources react in the air with hydrocarbons such as unburned gasoline. Unlike Houston, Los Angeles began fighting nitrous oxides roughly a decade ago, and its ozone levels have dropped significantly.</p>
        <p>About 55 percent of Houston's nitrogen oxide is generated by industry, 25 percent comes from cars and trucks and 20 percent can be traced to airplanes, trains, ships, lawn mowers and construction equipment.</p>
        <p>In the end, the home of NASA and the first indoor baseball stadium, the Astrodome, must find creative ways to clean up the air without killing the golden egg of its economy. Jim Marston, head of the Environmental Defense Fund, which is part of a task force working on the ozone plan, said Houston's businesses must consider an array of ideas: paying employees the value of a monthly parking spot as an incentive for them to car-pool; encouraging more telecommuting; charging lower registration fees and insurance rates for people who buy gas-efficient cars; and other strategies.</p>
        <p>None is a panacea, but Houston must consider just about anything. At the Tuesday hearing, for example, one woman recommended using robotic emission-free lawn mowers. It was an interesting concept with a familiar angle -- her company makes them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
