<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hannan's Two-Way Effort Leads Way for Garden City</title>
    <meta content="24SKOL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233576"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HIGH SCHOOL FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EFD8143AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hannan's Two-Way Effort Leads Way for Garden City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NYC metropolitan area high school football results noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bill Hannan rushed for three touchdowns and returned an interception 55 yards for another score to help Garden City defeat Hewlett, 24-12.</p>
        <p>Garden City managed to win without its starting quarterback, Dave Kang, who has an injured ankle. The junior quarterback Steve DeGrazia, who was 7 of 11 in passing for 93 yards and a touchdown, filled in admirably for Kang.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bill Hannan rushed for three touchdowns and returned an interception 55 yards for another score to help Garden City defeat Hewlett, 24-12.</p>
        <p>Garden City managed to win without its starting quarterback, Dave Kang, who has an injured ankle. The junior quarterback Steve DeGrazia, who was 7 of 11 in passing for 93 yards and a touchdown, filled in admirably for Kang.</p>
        <p>''It was a very good performance for a kid who had never been in there at crunch time,'' Garden City Coach Tom Flatley said of DeGrazia. ''He made some real good plays and called some good audibles at the line.''</p>
        <p>Hannan, a senior, gained 173 yards on 17 carries for Garden City (2-0). Hewlett is 0-2.</p>
        <p>In Bethpage's 35-6 victory over Glen Cove, Matt Rewkowski, the senior quarterback, rushed for two touchdowns and passed for two more. Rewkowski, who had 9 carries for 159 yards, completed 8 of 16 passes for 151 yards. Bethpage is 2-0; Glen Cove falls to 1-1.</p>
        <p>Baldwin's Sean Treasure had more than 200 total yards in a 22-0 victory over Long Beach (0-2). Treasure scored twice and gained 209 yards to lead Baldwin (1-1).</p>
        <p>Jarret Mizzi scored a touchdown, and Brendan Rooney had two touchdowns to power Floral Park (2-0) in a 21-0 victory over Plainedge (1-1).</p>
        <p>Elroy Lewis (14 carries, 134 yards) scored twice in the first half for Great Neck North (2-0) in a 12-6 victory over Lynbrook (0-2).</p>
        <p>Commack (2-0) rallied in the fourth quarter to defeat Ward Melville, 6-3.</p>
        <p>The senior quarterback Mike Prahalis tossed a 20-yard scoring strike to Bryan Tornee for the game-winner with less than a minute to play. Ward Melville is 0-2.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>Kaliym Hazel rushed nine times for 194 yards and 4 touchdowns in the first half to lead Hackensack (3-0), the top-rated school in the state, to a 38-0 victory over Passaic (0-2). The Comets' defense, which has not allowed a point in three games, limited Passaic to minus-9 yards in the first half.</p>
        <p>The sophomore quarterback Mike Loree, who was 11 of 12 for 223 yards, connected with Jarrett Schreck for three touchdown passes as Delbarton pounded West Orange, 44-6. Schreck had four receptions for 118 yards for Delbarton, 3-0. Mike DeFazio, the junior running back, scored 2 touchdowns and gained 113 yards on 14 carries. He also kicked three extra points and a 19-yard field goal. West Orange is 1-2.</p>
        <p>Quarterback Scott Stephen was 10 of 17 for 144 yards and 4 touchdowns as Glen Rock overpowered Hawthorne, 48-7. Mark Hannon and Craig Agnello each had two touchdown catches for Glen Rock (3-0). Hawthorne fell to 0-3.</p>
        <p>PREPS</p>
        <p>Poly Prep (4-0) routed Blair Academy, 46-12. The Brooklyn prep school was led by Marcus Wilson, who had 11 carries for 135 yards and 2 touchdowns. Chris Legree, who was 9 of 12 for 215 yards, hooked up with Jahkeen Gilmore on an 80-yard touchdown pass. Blair Academy is 2-1.</p>
        <p>Barry Mahabee caught a 30-yard pass from Matt Ryan in overtime to catapult Penn Charter of Pennsylvania (1-2) over Peddie (1-1), 21-15.</p>
        <p>Hotchkiss opened its season with a convincing 41-7 victory over Trinity Pawling. Rob Schaffer, the senior tailback, carried the offensive load for Hotchkiss, rushing 22 times for 179 yards and 3 touchdowns. Trinity Pawling is 0-1.</p>
        <p>Joe Bernard rushed for 4 touchdowns and 150 yards and Ben Schory picked off three passes in Riverdale's 50-6 drubbing over New York Military Academy (0-2). Riverdale improved its record to 2-0.</p>
        <p>Dennis Hicks rushed 14 times for 318 yards and scored on runs of 70, 42 and 30 yards, as Canterbury (1-0) defeated Cheshire Academy, 44-16. Cheshire Academy is 0-1.</p>
        <p>P.S.A.L.</p>
        <p>James Madison beat John Adams, 20-0, thanks to the defensive efforts of the senior Steven Boffo, who had eight tackles, and the junior Devale Ellis, who returned an interception 20 yards.</p>
        <p>Sheepshead Bay (2-0) defeated Midwood, 14-0. On Sheepshead Bay's fourth play from scrimmage, the junior running back Adeboyedo Akingba ran 29 yards for a touchdown.</p>
        <p>WESTCHESTER</p>
        <p>Matt Bernstein rushed nine times for 170 yards and 3 touchdowns and his brother Alex, a junior linebacker, recorded two sacks as Edgemont (3-0) dismantled Pleasantville, 55-0. Pleasantville is 2-1.</p>
        <p>HIGH SCHOOL FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
