<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playing Bumper Cars, With Real Cars</title>
    <meta content="24DEMO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233177"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wall Speedway (Wall Township, Nj)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kent, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E3D9103BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1063" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playing Bumper Cars, With Real Cars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL KENT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kent, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>WALL TOWNSHIP</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene at demolition derby at Wall Speedway in Wall Township, NJ, described (Special Issue: Entertainment) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR the last nine years, Joe Reilly fixed cars instead of crashing them. And then, last month, his son, Joe Jr., found the car, a 1978 Cadillac Seville in slightly less than mint condition.</p>
        <p>''The minute I saw it, I knew I had to drive it in a derby,'' said Mr. Reilly. ''My son had always wanted me to make a comeback, so we decided to go for it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR the last nine years, Joe Reilly fixed cars instead of crashing them. And then, last month, his son, Joe Jr., found the car, a 1978 Cadillac Seville in slightly less than mint condition.</p>
        <p>''The minute I saw it, I knew I had to drive it in a derby,'' said Mr. Reilly. ''My son had always wanted me to make a comeback, so we decided to go for it.''</p>
        <p>Until he hung up his helmet in 1991, Mr. Reilly, an Edison Township automobile mechanic who drove under the nickname of Ghetto Cruiser, had crunched, bashed and smashed his way to become a ''world champion'' demolition derby driver at Wall Speedway in Monmouth County.</p>
        <p>For nearly 30 years, Wall Speedway has been the state capital of the flamboyantly wasteful get-together known as the demolition derby, in which ordinary drivers in stripped-down cars crash into one another until the last car that can move, wins.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly was so popular that fans would give him their old cars, he said, ''just so they could watch them go out with a bang.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly and his son took a total of about 20 hours to remove the Cadillac's lights, glass and chrome, chain the doors shut, move the gas tank to the back seat and paint the car black, with Ghetto Cruiser in screaming yellow letters on each side.</p>
        <p>Then, on a cool Sunday night in August, Mr. Reilly towed the Caddie to Wall Speedway. They were surrounded by similar vehicles with such nom-de-booms as Nasty Habit, Voodoo Cadillac, Suicide Steve and Sudden Impact. Competing in the final of five heats, Mr. Reilly finished tied for first, his car locked in a death grip with Dennis (American Made) Draheim's Chevrolet.</p>
        <p>Crawling out of the steaming wreckage, Mr. Reilly slapped palms with Mr. Draheim, and shouted, ''I'm back.''</p>
        <p>Though the state's seven other speedways and a few county fairs will play host to an occasional derby, Wall Speedway has held five derbies this year, and a ''world championship'' match next Sunday. This match is open to any previous derby winner who, though it's rare when the winner of the $1,000 grand prize doesn't live within 30 miles of Wall Speedway.</p>
        <p>Jeff Gravatt, Wall Speedway's announcer, said that, as a sport, ''the derby is in something of a lull right now. We still get the crowds, but back in the 80's, we used to have more drivers so we could have more derbies here, sometimes as often as twice a month. The problem is, it's getting harder for the drivers to find the right cars. The rules specify that the cars must be American-made stock hardtops, like those big steel boats from the 60's and the 70s that your father used to drive.''</p>
        <p>The rules, enforced by the State Police (whose troopers inspect every car before a derby), also specify that drivers cannot hit one another head-on, cannot crash into the driver's side door and that every driver must wear a seat belt.</p>
        <p>''New Jersey's regulations regarding demolition derbies are the toughest in the country,'' said Sgt. Eric Mutter, one of three officers in the Jersey State Police Motor Vehicle Racing Control Unit, based in West Trenton. ''I am not aware of any deaths, or serious injuries in a derby held in New Jersey, in the history of the sport.''</p>
        <p>Richard Kercher, a driver from Fleetwood, Pa., who has won several ''world championships'' at Wall Speedway, said, ''If you're going to destroy a car, New Jersey's the safest place to do it.''</p>
        <p>Beyond an occasional bout of whiplash, ''Suicide'' Steve Rossics said, ''the worst that happened to me was that I almost got my thumb pulled off. I was holding on to the steering wheel and my front wheel got hit on an angle, which spun my steering wheel around and caught my thumb. Now I don't hold the wheel the same way.''</p>
        <p>The sport has had its share of legendary cars, like the Commode Car, with a portable toilet mounted on the roof, and such legendary drivers as Debbie McCabe of Dunnellen, who, as Madame X, was one of the first woman derby drivers in the country. ''You have anything to say about women drivers, I'm the one to say it to,'' Ms. McCabe said.</p>
        <p>The sport also lacks television coverage and big-money sponsorships. ''The drivers pay their own way,'' Mr. Gravatt said. ''They might get a local pizza parlor to kick in $20, but that's about it. For some reason, the idea of seeing a bunch of cars slamming into each other doesn't attract the kind of national sponsors that other kinds of racing does. There just isn't any money in crashing cars. You have to do it because you love it.''</p>
        <p>Bruce van Norde, a foreman of the motor pool that transports Monmouth County elderly citizens, stopped driving his red-white-and-blue ''Mr. America'' Buicks and Cadillacs in derbies in 1996, ''when I moved to a neighborhood where I can't have a bunch of torn-apart cars sitting out in the front yard.'' Mr. van Norde loves looking at his trophies. ''How many times do you get to be a world champion of anything?''</p>
        <p>Dennis Draheim of Brick Township drives cars painted with the ''Buy American'' logo used by his father, Morris, and brother Morris Jr. ''This is my only hobby. It costs me about $100 for the car, and the work I do myself or with my friends and family. We're in it for the satisfaction.''</p>
        <p>Satisfaction?</p>
        <p>''I drive a beer truck,'' Mr. Draheim said, ''and sometimes there'll be a problem with a delivery and I have to take it back. I also drive a limo and I'll get cut off at a toll booth, or stuck behind somebody going 30 miles per hour in a no-passing zone, and there'll be nothing I can do about it.</p>
        <p>''But when I get into my car at a derby, I can let out all my frustrations. I can bang my car into somebody else's, and the people in the stands will cheer, and it'll feel good. I tell you, a derby is the cure for every bad day you've ever had.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
