<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Armstead Leads Revitalized Defense</title>
    <meta content="Y24GIA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233556"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Redskins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Washington Redskins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6D8143AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="894" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Armstead Leads Revitalized Defense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New York Giants preparing for game against Washington Redskins (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jessie Armstead and Giants Coach Jim Fassel agreed to leave Armstead's outburst last November behind them by the time Armstead reported for the team's off-season conditioning program in March. He was there as much to rehabilitate his surgically repaired left knee as to prove he was still a leader.</p>
        <p>When Armstead arrived at Giants Stadium on March 20, he met with Fassel for 15 minutes, and each left the meeting convinced they could again lead the Giants. Both wanted desperately to win, and each needed the other.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jessie Armstead and Giants Coach Jim Fassel agreed to leave Armstead's outburst last November behind them by the time Armstead reported for the team's off-season conditioning program in March. He was there as much to rehabilitate his surgically repaired left knee as to prove he was still a leader.</p>
        <p>When Armstead arrived at Giants Stadium on March 20, he met with Fassel for 15 minutes, and each left the meeting convinced they could again lead the Giants. Both wanted desperately to win, and each needed the other.</p>
        <p>''He appreciated it,'' Armstead, an eighth-year linebacker, said last week. ''I was a man about the situation. I wasn't just sitting there and coming into the season holding any grudges, because I want to win. The only thing anybody ever has negative to say about me in the papers is maybe I want to win too much. The only time I got in trouble was because I was complaining that I wanted to win.''</p>
        <p>Armstead's play has been a key factor in a revitalized defense, although the Giants' offense has deservedly received much of the credit for their 3-0 record entering tonight's game against Washington. The defense has held opponents to a league-low 49 yards rushing a game. Washington (1-2) is averaging 124.3 yards a game rushing this year, and Redskins running back Stephen Davis ran for 309 yards in two games against the Giants last season.</p>
        <p>The Redskins bring back more painful memories for the Giants. Following their second loss to Washington last year, by 23-13, Armstead ripped the offense, saying it was inept and lacked fight. He openly wondered if the front office needed to make a changes with coaches or players. The Giants had lost to the Redskins earlier, 50-21, but this one was more costly internally.</p>
        <p>Fassel told Armstead not to criticize the offense, and defensive end Michael Strahan criticized Fassel for silencing a team leader. All three parties recently said that the situation was overblown publicly, but it was a tense few weeks.</p>
        <p>Armstead's words may have hurt, but they rang true. And changes have followed, with Kerry Collins becoming the starting quarterback; the offensive line being rebuilt; and Sean Payton being promoted to offensive coordinator.</p>
        <p>This season, Armstead has not been afraid to praise the offense, saying he is more proud of its desire than its performance. He said he told Fassel he made a mistake in airing his concerns publicly last year.</p>
        <p>''Everybody said we had a problem but the problem got solved, whatever way you look at it,'' Armstead said. ''Maybe I should have went about it a better way. I should've said I'm not speaking no more about the situation. That's the only thing I regret, that I let it carry on.''</p>
        <p>Armstead does not mind speaking his mind. That's why his friend Mike Barrow, a linebacker who was a free agent in the off-season, called him to ask about the Giants' defense and their chances of winning this season before signing with them.</p>
        <p>''I feel like everybody trusts me around here,'' said Armstead, who noted that the players voted him and Strahan defensive captains before the season. ''Guys realize that. They know I speak the truth, straight from the heart.''</p>
        <p>His teammates said Armstead did not change in the locker room following Fassel's scolding, perhaps only quieting himself around reporters. ''To us, there was no difference,'' cornerback Jason Sehorn said.</p>
        <p>Still, Armstead felt strongly enough to call Fassel and notify him that he would attend the off-season conditioning program, which he skipped the previous year. He also offered whatever help Fassel wanted. Armstead said their March meeting helped tremendously.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure a lot of guys were wondering what was going on,'' Armstead said. ''Jim's the head coach. He carries a lot of weight. As being one of the leaders around here, I carry some weight, too. There only can be one chief and he's the chief. We have to be on the same page.''</p>
        <p>Fassel called Armstead one of his favorite players. ''It showed me a lot of class,'' Fassel said. ''That meant a lot to me but I know Jessie Armstead and he's a great guy.''</p>
        <p>Armstead has proved much so far this year. He played last season's final three games with a knee injury, and his third Pro Bowl selection pushed back arthroscopic surgery until February, five months before training camp. He limited himself to one practice a day and did not dominate in the preseason. Fassel criticized the entire defense for its lack of a pass rush, and Strahan said the unit was not nearly as comfortable as in its commanding season of 1997.</p>
        <p>Armstead and the defense are again forces. He is tied for second on the team with 14 tackles and is tied with Barrow with a team-high two sacks.</p>
        <p>''What more can I do for people?'' Armstead said. ''I'm back.''</p>
        <p>Fassel said: ''To me the strongest form of getting this team going is those players in that locker room, on each other and together. They've got that going right now, and Jessie's a main part of that.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
