<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Preparing The Pool For Winter</title>
    <meta content="24HOME$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233163"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Swimming Pools</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romano, Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DA103BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1120" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Preparing The Pool For Winter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romano, Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Experts offer advice on preparing backyard swimming pools for winter; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE best thing about having a swimming pool in your backyard is that it's there whenever you want to use it.</p>
        <p>The worst thing is that it's still there even when you don't.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE best thing about having a swimming pool in your backyard is that it's there whenever you want to use it.</p>
        <p>The worst thing is that it's still there even when you don't.</p>
        <p>''Some people like to keep their pools open as long as possible,'' said Steven Mundree, president of H2O Pools, a pool maintenance company in Irvington, N.Y. ''But right about now is when I'm getting the most calls from customers who want to close them up.''</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Mundree and other pool experts said, while most customers use pool maintenance professionals to shut down their pools for the winter -- at a cost that can range anywhere from $100 to $500 -- it is a fairly simple procedure that a handy homeowner can accomplish in an afternoon.</p>
        <p>Richard Keane, the owner of Ultimate Pool Covers in Mastic, N.Y., said the first thing a homeowner should do when closing an in-ground pool is to drain the filter by disconnecting the line that runs from the filter to the pool and opening any drain plugs on the filter itself. Then, Mr. Keane said, the water level in the pool should be lowered using a submersible pump attached to a garden hose.</p>
        <p>''You want to drop the water down below the jets,'' Mr. Keane said, referring to the outlets through which filtered water is returned to the pool.</p>
        <p>He explained that this allows any water in the lines between the filter and the pool to drain back into the pool. The lines need to be drained, Mr. Keane said, to prevent them from freezing and breaking during the winter. In fact, he said, it is usually wise to ''blow out the lines'' by connecting a hose attached to an air compressor to the line leading to the pool at the point where it was connected to the filter. (Homeowners who do not have an air compressor, Mr. Keane said, can use a shop vacuum or even a leaf blower to blow out the lines. The fittings necessary to attach the vacuum or blower to the pool line can be improvised using common plastic fittings found in most home centers.)</p>
        <p>Once all water has been removed from the filter and the lines to the pool, Mr. Keane said, the homeowner should plug the jets and skimmer holes (the holes where water exits the pool on its way to the filter) so that no water can get back into the lines. (Some homeowners also put a special pool antifreeze into the skimmers.)</p>
        <p>''Most pool manufacturers and supply stores sell winterizing kits that include the plugs for the jets and skimmers,'' he said, adding that homeowners should also purchase winterizing chemicals -- basically, chlorine and an algicide -- in appropriate quantities for their pool size.</p>
        <p>''Once the jets and skimmers have been plugged, I like to raise the level of the water to just below the tile line and then add the winterizing chemicals,'' Mr. Keane said. If the water level in the pool is above the bottom of tiles installed along the top foot or two of the pool wall, he explained, there is a good chance the tiles will be damaged if the water in the pool freezes.</p>
        <p>The next step is to install the pool cover.</p>
        <p>''Now is the perfect time to decide whether you should be in the market for a new cover,'' said Phil Del Negro, general manager of Specialty Pool Products, a pool maintenance and supply company in Broad Brook, Conn.</p>
        <p>Mr. Del Negro saidthere are various styles of pool covers that range in price from as little as $150 to $8,000.</p>
        <p>The most basic and least expensive cover, he said, is a plastic sheet that extends a couple of feet onto the surface of the deck around the pool. The sheet generally lies on top of the water (which is why Mr. Keane likes to raise the level after plugging the jets) and is kept in place using water-filled plastic bags to weigh it down.</p>
        <p>''The problem with traditional covers is that they usually end up at the bottom of the pool by springtime,'' Mr. Del Negro said, explaining that freezing weather can damage the water-filled plastic anchoring bags and that accumulated leaves, rain or snow can pull the cover from under the anchors. More important, however, is the fact that traditional pool covers offer no safety features; anyone who ventures out onto such a cover will almost certainly end up underwater.</p>
        <p>''That's why your best bet is a safety cover,'' Mr. Del Negro said, referring to a woven mesh-type cover that is stretched tautly over the pool and held in place with springs attached to anchors embedded in the pool deck.</p>
        <p>''Having a safety cover is basically like having a trampoline over your pool,'' Mr. Del Negro said. In addition to their potentially life-saving advantages, mesh covers allow rain and melting snow to pass through the cover and into the pool, making it unnecessary to pump water off the cover when the pool is opened.</p>
        <p>Such covers, he said, cost about $800 for a 20 by 40 foot pool and can be installed by a homeowner with a drill and an afternoon to spare.</p>
        <p>For those who want the ultimate in convenience, nothing beats a fully automatic solid vinyl cover.</p>
        <p>''With an automatic cover, you turn a key, hold it for about 45 seconds, and your pool is open or closed,'' said Corinne Zemla, president of Poolsaver, a cover manufacturer in Walnut, Calif., who recently opened a distribution center in East Brunswick, N.J.</p>
        <p>With an automatic cover -- which costs about $6,500 installed for a 20 by 40 foot pool -- the sides of a solid vinyl cover are attached to tracks that run along the side of the pool. An electric motor -- usually mounted at the deep end of the pool -- turns a pulley that draws the cover along the surface of the water from one end of the pool to the other. Since the cover is supported at its sides by the track and in the middle by the water, it is considered a safety cover and will support the weight of at least two adults and a child.</p>
        <p>''It's like having a big water bed in your backyard,'' Ms. Zemla said.</p>
        <p>Additional information about covers can be found on Poolsaver's Internet site, www.poolsaver.com, and at Specialty Pool Products' site, www.wintercover.com. Another useful site is www.powertrackcovers  .com, the site of Pool Cover Specialists, a company in West Jordan, Utah.</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
