<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Using Music to Topple Walls for Jailed Youths</title>
    <meta content="24COLM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233307"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COPING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Felicia R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2D71E3BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Using Music to Topple Walls for Jailed Youths</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICIA R. LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Felicia R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Felicia Lee Coping column on Paul Thompson, who, twice a week, travels with his mobile music studio to juvenile detention centers in Bronx and Brooklyn in effort to help jailed teens improve their lives; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PAUL THOMPSON does not envision himself as a hip-hop version of a catcher in the rye. Rather, he just hopes to help create the epiphanies and sense of possibilities that saved his own skin, when he was a troubled boy running the streets of Harlem and the pregentrified Upper West Side.</p>
        <p>So twice a week, Mr. Thompson packs his car with what is essentially a mobile music studio and heads for a juvenile detention center. On Mondays he goes to the Horizon Juvenile Center in the Mott Haven section of the Bronx. On Fridays you can find him at the Crossroads Center in the Brownsville section of Brooklyn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PAUL THOMPSON does not envision himself as a hip-hop version of a catcher in the rye. Rather, he just hopes to help create the epiphanies and sense of possibilities that saved his own skin, when he was a troubled boy running the streets of Harlem and the pregentrified Upper West Side.</p>
        <p>So twice a week, Mr. Thompson packs his car with what is essentially a mobile music studio and heads for a juvenile detention center. On Mondays he goes to the Horizon Juvenile Center in the Mott Haven section of the Bronx. On Fridays you can find him at the Crossroads Center in the Brownsville section of Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>In both places, Mr. Thompson, a professional musician, meets with a small group of young people. He helps them put together songs, and they talk about the music industry, music theory and engineering.</p>
        <p>The goal is bigger than making melodies, though. Mr. Thompson wants these children, who are mostly 14 and 15 years old, to think about who they are and how they ended up where they are. His hope is that they can create better lives by connecting to something outside themselves.</p>
        <p>''I tell them that the most important thing you can do is struggle to come to terms with yourself, to be honest with yourself,'' said Mr. Thompson, who is 30 and grew up in the Riverdale section of the Bronx. ''Then find a way to express it. Honesty will set you free is my motto.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson is the first music director of War Child USA, the domestic part of an international nonprofit organization that tries to help young people who suffer from the violence of war. When Mr. Thompson sat done with War Child patrons last year to figure out how to help children in this country, he came up with the idea that incarcerated children are the victims of a domestic war. So, with the cooperation of the city's Department of Justice, he developed the program that he brings to the juvenile centers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson cultivates a relationship with the children by talking about himself. It helps that he looks young and hip, that he's black, and that he's in the music world.</p>
        <p>In the three months he has run the music program, he has worked with only two girls; one had a baby at 14 and one was pregnant. All the other children are Latin and African-American boys without much in the way of material things, and who also lack emotionally mature adults in their lives. When he asks them how they ended up in such bad shape, they give a bald recitation of the facts of their crime and punishment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson knows he has started to get through to them when they start talking about their feelings.</p>
        <p>Many have gone through hell. Mr. Thompson tells them they still have to find a way to pay the rent. And although music is the newest hustle in the ghetto, the way to big money, Mr. Thompson breaks down just who is getting rich from rapping and what it takes. It is sobering stuff for kids who believe that a sum like $50,000 can last forever.</p>
        <p>As for himself, Mr. Thompson says he grew up with some nice things, materially, as the son of a dentist and a nurse. But things were not happy at home, so he sold and used drugs. His four closest friends from that period in his life are dead. They died at 18 or 19, the victims of drug deals gone awry.</p>
        <p>He was saved by listening to John Coltrane, he said, and discovering his affinity for music. He was also lucky enough, he said, not to be arrested during that crazy time. He graduated from Bard College, bought a trumpet and went on to earn a master's degree in music composition and improvisation from the California Institute of the Arts.</p>
        <p>Since then, Mr. Thompson has made a name for himself in hip-hop and other categories, touring this country and Europe.</p>
        <p>His first work for orchestra, ''Purple, Black and Green,'' was performed by the American Symphony Orchestra, conducted by Leon Botstein. He started his own production company, and has had a long collaboration with MeShell Ndegeocello.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Thompson said he never forgot how it felt to feel alone and misunderstood. So he jumped at the chance to work with War Child.</p>
        <p>''He's actually connected with a few of the kids,'' said Sarina Roffe, the department's director of public affairs. ''He's very, very popular.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson is doing his thing while the city and the nation debate the right course for juvenile justice. In the last 10 years, the number of teenagers in adult prisons has doubled. Notably, only two years ago, the city opened the two detention centers that participate in Mr. Thompson's program. Ms. Roffe said the average daily population in the centers (there are now three in the city) has increased 10 percent each year for the last three years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson would rather discuss the importance of values and human connections than the politics, which are always shifting.</p>
        <p>''You go into these places and you see all these kids and it could leave you paralyzed,'' he said. ''I'm just trying to do my effort to build on the population of emotionally mature people who can help. It's like trying to build an army.''</p>
        <p>COPING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
