<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GOING OUT</title>
    <meta content="24TOWN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233202"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE TOWNS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDF113BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="19391" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GOING OUT</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An opinionated guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. Items may be submitted by mail to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036; by fax to (212) 556-7219, or by e-mail to njtowns@nytimes.com.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
        <p>BLAIR ACADEMY The Lyric Orchestra. Friday at 1 p.m. Tickets: $25 or $60; $15 for students and older people. DuBois Theater, Blairtown. (908) 362-6121, extension 5612 or (201) 217-2628.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An opinionated guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. Items may be submitted by mail to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036; by fax to (212) 556-7219, or by e-mail to njtowns@nytimes.com.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
        <p>BLAIR ACADEMY The Lyric Orchestra. Friday at 1 p.m. Tickets: $25 or $60; $15 for students and older people. DuBois Theater, Blairtown. (908) 362-6121, extension 5612 or (201) 217-2628.</p>
        <p>BURGDORFF CULTURAL CENTER Maplewood Jazz Festival, featuring performances by Maplewood Youth Jazz Ensembles. Today at 3 p.m. Tickets: $5. 10 Durand Road, Maplewood. (973) 378-2133.</p>
        <p>CALVARY EPISCOPAL CHURCH Calvary Chorale featuring Eugene Roan, harpsichordist, and John Burkhalter on recorder. Today at 4 p.m. Free will offering. 31 Woodland Avenue, Summit. (908) 277-1547.</p>
        <p>CHURCH OF THE HOLY SPIRIT The Mainstreet Brass Quintet. Saturday at 7:30 p.m. Tickets:  $10. 3 Haytown Road, Lebanon. (908) 236-6980.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY THEATER OF MORRISTOWN Michael Feinstein. Oct. 6 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $40 to $60. Joan Baez. Oct. 17 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $30 and $37.50. Philharmonia of the Nations. Oct. 21 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $33. Carter Brey, cellist, and Christopher O'Riley, pianist, in recital. Nov. 19 at 7 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $33.  ''Brazil Night,'' featuring Ivan Lins, Leila Pinheiro and Ed Motta, joined by Batacoto. Oct. 26 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $35. Lou Rawls.  Nov. 3 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $30 to $45. Al Di Meola. Nov. 4 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $32. The W. C. Handy All Stars. Nov. 10 at 8 p.m. Tickets: 25 to $35. Les Tambours Du Bronz. Nov. 17 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $35. Maynard Ferguson and his Big Bop Nouveau Band. Nov. 25 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $32. The Four Tops.  Nov. 30 at 8 p.m. Tickets: 30 to $45. A Judy Collins Christmas. Dec. 1 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $30 to $45. The Klezmatics. Dec. 7 at 8 p.m. Tickets:  $25 and $32. The Letterman Holiday Show.  Dec. 15 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $35. 100 South Street, Morristown. (973) 539-8008.</p>
        <p>ENGLEWOOD PUBLIC LIBRARY ''Triple Play'' will present ''Songs from Carl Sandburg's American Songbag, and More. . .Plus!'' Today at 6 p.m. Free. 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215, extension 244.</p>
        <p>ETHICAL CULTURE SOCIETY Black Tie, presented by the Teaneck Cultural Arts Coalition.  Today at 4 p.m. Tickets: $10, $7 for students and older people. 687 Larch Avenue, Teaneck. (201) 287-9730.836-5187.</p>
        <p>FIRST REFORMED CHURCH Lunchtime Recital Series, featuring Mark Trautman, organist. Wednesday, 12:15 p.m. to 12:45 p.m. Free; free luncheon to follow. 9 Bayard Street, New Brunswick. (732) 545-6262.</p>
        <p>FORT LEE PUBLIC LIBRARY Michelle Vargas, soprano, will perform opera and classical art song favorites at the American Association of University Women season opener. Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. Free. 320 Main Street, Fort Lee. (201) 592-3615.</p>
        <p>FREE PUBLIC LIBRARY OF ELIZABETH Michael Grill, concert organist of Munich, Germany, performs selections from Bach and recent favorites. Saturday at 2:15 p.m. 11 South Broad Street, Elizabeth. (908) 354-6060.</p>
        <p>JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS Herbie Hancock and Wayne Shorter. Oct. 12 at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $20 to $40. Opening Night Gala, starring Ray Charles, with Andy Bey. Oct. 13 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $30 to $65. Paul Anka. Oct. 24 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $30 to $60. Carnegie Hall Jazz Band: Harlem Renaissance. Oct. 25 at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $18 to $38. Michael Feinstein and Maynard Ferguson and his Big Bop Noveau Band. Oct. 29 at 3 and 7 p.m. Tickets: $24 to $42. Sonny Rollins. Nov. 4 at 8 p.m. Tickets:  $16 to $40. Dracula: The Music and Film With Original Music by Philip Glass, performed by Philip Glass and Kronos Quartet. Nov. 11 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $45. Chava Alberstein. Nov. 12 at 3 p.m. Tickets: $18 to $32. Carnegie Hall Jazz Band: Jerome Kern: All the Things You Are. Nov. 15 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $18 to $38.  Les Tambours du Bronx. Nov. 16 at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $20 to $35. Arlo Guthrie. Nov. 19 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $18 to $36. Judy Collins. Dec. 2 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $44. B. B. King. Dec. 6 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $30 to $60. Leon Redbone and Dr. John. Dec. 15 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $18 to $32. Moscow Boys Choir. Dec. 17 at 3 p.m. Tickets:  $20 to $36. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600.</p>
        <p>KEAN UNIVERSITY ''The Unknown Piazzolla'' featuring Allison Brewster, pianist, with Ted Hoyle, professor of cello. Tomorrow at 8 p.m.  Free. Wilkins Auditorium, 1000 Morris Avenue, Union. (908) 527-2337.</p>
        <p>McCARTER THEATER ''Chanticleer.'' Oct. 3 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $30 to $41. Dianne Reeves Quintet, with Brad Mehldau. Oct. 6 at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $28 to $36. ''Bernadette Peters. . .Gala Fundraiser for The McCarter Theater,'' with 30-piece orchestra. Oct. 7 at 8:30 p.m. Tickets: $60. Academy of Ancient Music, Andrew Manze, conductor and violinist. Oct. 30 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $35 to $46. 91 University Place, Princeton. (609) 258-2787.</p>
        <p>MINSTREL COFFEEHOUSE Modern Man, Liz Queler and Seth Farber. Friday at 8:30 p.m.  Tickets: $5. Morris County Park Commission's Cultural Center, 300 Mendham Road, Morristown. (973) 335-9489.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY PERFORMING ARTS CENTER New Jersey Symphony Orchestra, featuring ''Josefowicz Performs Prokofiev;'' Leila Josefowicz, violinist; Christopher Seaman, conductor. Today at 3 p.m. Tickets: $13 to $54.  New Jersey Symphony Orchestra's Young People's Concerts. Tuesday at 10 a.m. and 11:30 a.m.; Oct. 20 and 24 at 10 a.m. and 11:30 a.m. (973) 624-3713, ext. 253. India Bamboleo.  Oct. 8 at 5 p.m. Tickets: $13 to $45. Prudential Hall. Tito Paris. Oct. 14 at 7:30 p.m. Tickets:  $21 and $25. Victoria Theater. Dianne Reeves Quintet and Regina Carter Sextet. Oct. 14 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $10 to $42. Prudential Hall. NDR Symphony Orchestra of Hamburg, Christoph Eschenbach, conductor. Oct. 15 at 3 p.m. Tickets: $12 to $32. Evgeny Kissin, pianist. Oct. 18 at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $12 to $42. Buena Vista Social Club presents: Omara Portunondo with Barbarito Torres. Oct. 27 at 8 p.m. Tickets:  $14 to $48. Ravi Shankar with Anoushka Shankar. Nov. 21 at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $9 to $46.  The Canadian Brass with the New York Brass. Nov. 24 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $10 to $48.  Keith Jarrett Trio. Nov. 25 at 8 p.m. Tickets  $10 to $42. Andre Watts, pianist. Nov. 26 at 3 p.m. Tickets: $12 to $52. Emanuel Ax, pianist, and Yo-Yo Ma, cellist. Dec. 6 at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $13 to $40. Boston Symphony Orchestra.  Dec. 8 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $16.20 to $58. David Rudder. Dec. 15 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $13 to $45.  Vienna Boys Choir. Dec. 16 at 8 p.m. Tickets:  $10 to $48. Boston Pops, Keith Lockhart, conductor. Dec. 17 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $16.20 to $48.  Handel's ''Messiah,'' Musica Sacra Chorus and Orchestra of New York. Dec. 23 at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $10 to $48. Prudential Hall. 1 Center Street, Newark. (888) 466-5722.</p>
        <p>OUTPOST IN THE BURBS Karen Davis, Mike Kelly and TRMT (That Robert Matarazzo Thing). Friday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $8. 40 South Fullerton Avenue, Montclair. (973) 744-6560.</p>
        <p>PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE Debbie Friedman.  Oct. 10 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $30 and $40. Jackie Mason, ''Much Ado About Everything.'' Oct. 17, 18 and 20 at 8 p.m.; Oct. 19 and 21 at 2 p.m.  Tickets: $40 to $75. Barbara Cook. Dec. 5 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $40 and $50. Kathy Mattea. Dec. 19 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $40 and $50. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (973) 376-4343.</p>
        <p>PARAMUS PUBLIC LIBRARY Steve Cohn Trio jazz concert. Today at 2 p.m. Emily Howland meeting room. Route 116 East Century Road, Paramus. (201) 599-1300.</p>
        <p>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY RICHARDSON AUDITORIUM ''Revelry of Sound'' concert featuring the Princeton Symphony Orchestra, Mark Laycock, music director, with Ilya Itin, pianist. Today at 4 p.m. Tickets: $28, $25; $24, $22 for older people; $8, $6 for students. Pre-concert lecture at 3 p.m. Alexander Hall, Princeton. (609) 258-5000.</p>
        <p>PRIORY JAZZ SERIES Richard Reiter. Today, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m. Spirit of Life Ensemble. Friday, 7 p.m. to 11 p.m. No Cover. St. Joseph's Plaza, 233 West Market Street, Newark. (973) 242-8012.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY - CAMDEN Martin Dillon, tenor and assistant professor of fine arts, will give a concert featuring works by Handel, Scarlatti, Brahms, Rachmaninoff and Bernstein. Today at 1 p.m. From 2 p.m. to 4 p.m., the Stedman gallery will hold a reception for its exhibition, ''Every Picture Tells a Story.'' Gordon Theater, Third Street between Cooper Street and the Benjamin Franklin Bridge, Camden. (856) 225-6176.</p>
        <p>ST. JOHN'S EPISCOPAL CHURCH The Kreismer Family concert. Today at 7 p.m.  Free will offering. Intersection of Main Street and Franklin Turnpike, Ramsey (one block west of the Lake Street Exit on Route 17). (201) 327-0703.</p>
        <p>ST. MICHAEL'S CHURCH Special Memorial Concert for the Rev. Hugh Fitzgerald performed by the Schola Cantorum on Hudson choral group. Today at 4 p.m. Free will offering. 252 Ninth Street, Jersey City. (201) 798-6137 extension 3.</p>
        <p>SHANGHAI JAZZ Wooster St. Trolley (Dixieland). Tuesday. Wallace Roney Quintet, featuring Geri Allen, pianist. Wednesday at 7 p.m. Derek Smith, pianist. Thursday at 7 p.m.  Eric Olsen (pianist) Trio. Friday at 6:45 p.m. and 8:30 p.m. Roy Meriweather (pianist) Trio.  Saturday at 6:30 p.m. and 8:45 p.m. Shanghai Jazz debut of Rene Marie, vocalist. Next Sunday at 6 p.m. No cover. 24 Main Street, Madison. (973) 822-2899.</p>
        <p>STANHOPE HOUSE Zen Tricksters. Thursday at 9 p.m. Tickets: $12. Billy Hector and the Fairlanes. Friday at 10 p.m. Tickets: $6. Studebaker John and the Hawks. Saturday at 10 p.m. Tickets: $8. Oktoberfest, featuring Billy Hector Band, Fat Mama, Addison Grove Project and Devine Afflatus. Next Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $10. 45 Main Street, Stanhope. (973) 347-0458.</p>
        <p>STATE THEATER Iceland Symphony Orchestra. Oct. 7 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $45. Philharmonia of the Nations. Oct. 20 at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $25 to $45. Paul Anka. Oct. 22 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 and $40. Ray Charles. Oct. 25 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25. Linda Eder. Nov. 17 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $40. Peter, Paul and Mary: 40th Anniversary Tour. Nov. 18 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $50. Orpheus with James Galway. Nov. 30 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $45.  Irish Christmas with John McDermott. Dec. 1 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $38. Kenny Rogers in ''Christmas from the Heart.'' Dec. 13 at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $25 to $75. Chicago Brass Quintet with Princeton Pro Musica. Dec. 14 at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $20 to $32. Vienna Choir Boys. Dec. 15 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $38. George Winston.  Dec. 16 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $38. New Year's Eve Opera House Party, featuring the Rutgers University Orchestra and Chorus.  Dec. 31, 8 to 10:30 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $45. 15 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 246-7469.</p>
        <p>STOCKTON PERFORMING ARTS CENTER ''Ode to Joy'' performance by the Bay Atlantic Symphony. Today at 4 p.m. A pre-concert conversation with the maestro is scheduled for 3 p.m. Tickets: $20; $18 for older people; $9 for students; $5 for children. The Richard Stockton College of New Jersey, Jim Leeds Road, Pomona. (609) 652-9000.</p>
        <p>TIERNEY'S TAVERN Diane Moser's Composers Big Band. Wednesday, 8 p.m. to 11 p.m. Cover: $7. 136 Valley Road, Montclair. (973) 744-9785.</p>
        <p>TRUMPETS Carrie Jackson. Today, 7 p.m. to 11 p.m. Cover: $5. 6 Depot Square at Walnut Street, Montclair. (973) 744-2600.</p>
        <p>WATERLOO VILLAGE Cadek Trio. Friday at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $12; $6 for children. 525 Waterloo Road, off Interstate 80, Exit 25, Stanhope. (973) 347-0900.</p>
        <p>WESTMINSTER CHOIR COLLEGE OF RIDER UNIVERSITY ''Voices of Spring'': Compositions by Stefan Young. Today at 4 p.m. Tickets: $20; $12 for students and older people. Bristol Chapel, 101 Walnut Lane, Princeton. (609) 921-2663, ext. 308.</p>
        <p>WILLIAM PATERSON UNIVERSITY Midday Artists Series jazz concert. Thursday at 12:30 p.m. Tickets: $3. Shea Center for Performing Arts, 300 Pompton Road, Wayne. (973) 720-2371.</p>
        <p>Museums and Galleries</p>
        <p>ABC GALLERY ''The Fruits of My Labor, Oil Paintings and Pastels by Fern Blumberg.'' Through Friday. Hours: Monday and Thursday, 1 to 9 p.m.; Tuesday and Wednesday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Friday, 1 p.m. to 5 p.m. Lambertville Public Library, 6 Lilly Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-0275.</p>
        <p>AFRICAN ART MUSEUM OF THE S.M.A. FATHERS ''Eloquent Threads: The Language of African Costumes and Textiles.'' Through Dec. 31. Hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. 23 Bliss Avenue, Tenafly. (201) 894-8611.</p>
        <p>ALBA VINEYARD ''Realistic Portrayals'' of scenic landscapes, floral settings and man-made structures by Jean Olliver. Through Nov. 30. Hours: Wednesdays, Thursdays, Fridays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Musconetcong Gallery, 269 Route 627, Village of Finesville, Milford.  (908) 995-7800.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN LABOR MUSEUM ''Workers' Portraits,'' photodocumentary exhibit by Robert Gumpert. Through Dec. 31. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; other times by appointment. Botto House National Landmark, 83 Norwood Street, Haledon. (973) 595-7953.</p>
        <p>APPEL ART GALLERY ''Artists of Roosevelt, N.J.'' Through October. Hours: Sundays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Mondays through Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 9:30 p.m.; Fridays, 9 a.m. to 3 p.m. Katz Jewish Community Center, Springdale and Kresson Roads, Cherry Hill. (856) 751-9500, extension 203.</p>
        <p>ARTBUILDERS, INC. Roy M. Luciana, ''Internal Self-Portraits.'' Through Thursday. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 2 p.m. to 7 p.m. or by appointment. 193 Montgomery Street, Jersey City. (201) 433-2682.</p>
        <p>ARTISTS' GALLERY Bernard Ungerleider, paintings, and Bernard Mangiaracina, sculptures. Through next Sunday. Hours: Friday through Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. 32 Coryell Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-4588.</p>
        <p>ARTS GUILD OF RAHWAY ''Stolen Glances.'' Through Oct. 6. Hours: Wednesdays and Fridays and Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m.; Thursdays, 1 to 3 p.m. and 5 to 7 p.m.; other times by appointment. 1670 Irving Street, Rahway. (732) 381-7511.</p>
        <p>ATELIER FINE ART GALLERY ''Mike Filipiak, Recent Works of Maine and Hunterdon County.'' Saturday through Oct. 30. Opening reception: Saturday, 7 p.m. to 10 p.m. Hours: Thursdays to Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. 108 Harrison Street, Frenchtown. (908) 996-9992.</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC CAPE COMMUNITY COLLEGE Artworks of Faculty and Staff. Through Friday. Call for gallery times. Art Gallery, 5100 Black Horse Pike, May Landing. (609) 343-5040.</p>
        <p>ATRIUM GALLERY ''Fanciful Visions,'' exhibition featuring a collection of paintings by Andrea Baruffi. Through Oct. 31. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. Chubb, 15 Mountain View Road, Warren. (908) 903-2608.</p>
        <p>BARRON ARTS CENTER The Camera Arts Group exhibit. Through next Sunday. Hours: Monday through Friday, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sunday, 2 to 4 p.m. 582 Rahway Avenue, Woodbridge. (732) 634-0413.</p>
        <p>BERLEX LABORATORIES CORPORATE HEADQUARTERS ''Parallel Visions: A Compilation of G.J. Cloninger and Co. Gallery Artists.''  Through Nov. 15. By appointment. 340 Changebridge Road, Montville. (973) 276-2000.</p>
        <p>BERNARDSVILLE PUBLIC LIBRARY Nona Rutter and Debbie Seymour, pastel paintings. Through Saturday. Monday through Thursday, 10 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. 1 Anderson Hill Road, Bernardsville. (908) 766-0118.</p>
        <p>CAMDEN COUNTY CULTURAL AND HERITAGE COMMISSION ''Artists of Roosevelt, New Jersey''; Deborah Gross-Zuchman, watercolors, prints and collages; and historic photographs of Roosevelt, New Jersey. Through Nov. 17. Opening reception today, 2 p.m. to 5 p.m. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 1 p.m. and 2 to 4 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 4 p.m. Hopkins House, 250 South Park Drive, Haddon Township. (609) 858-0040.</p>
        <p>CHALFONTE HOTEL ''Drawn to the Sea,'' watercolors by Alice Steer Wilson. Through Oct. 15. Solarium and Magnolia Rooms, 301 Howard Street, Cape May. (609) 884-8409.</p>
        <p>CHAMOT GALLERY ''From Pop to the Millennium: 40 Years of Bill Barrell.'' Through Saturday. Hours: Tuesday through Sunday, noon to 6 p.m. 111 First Street, Jersey City. (201) 610-1468.</p>
        <p>CHAPIN SCHOOL Roxanne Weidele exhibit of drawings, paintings and three-dimensional paper construction. Through Oct. 6. By appointment. Gallery at Chapin, 4101 Princeton Pike, Princeton. (609) 924-7206.</p>
        <p>CLIFTON ARTS CENTER ''Open Shutters,'' group show by the Clifton Camera Club.  Through Oct. 15. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, 1 p.m. to 4 p.m. Clifton and Van Houten Avenues, Clifton. (973) 472-5499.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE OF NEW JERSEY Art Faculty Exhibition. Through Oct. 4. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, noon to 3 p.m.; Thursdays, 7 to 9 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 3 p.m. College Art Gallery, Holman Hall, Ewing. (609) 771-2368.</p>
        <p>DREW UNIVERSITY ''Siochan Hughes: Transport,'' an exhibit of photographs. Through Oct. 6. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 12:30 to 4 p.m. and by appointment. Korn Gallery, Madison. (973) 408-3439.</p>
        <p>DRUE CHRYST GALLERY Elaine Kurie, oil still lifes and landscapes. Through Saturday.  Hours: Monday, Thursday, Friday and Saturday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; or by appointment. 21 White Deer Plaza, Lake Mohawk, Sparta.  (973) 729-0609.</p>
        <p>EXTENSION GALLERY Atelier Members' Exhibit, ''Sculptures Created in or Incorporating Stone.'' Through Oct. 5. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; other times by appointment. 60 Ward Avenue Extension, Mercerville. (609) 890-7777.</p>
        <p>FAIRLEIGH DICKINSON UNIVERSITY ''Laid by Liberty'' acrylic paintings by Alex Lombardo. Through Oct. 6. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 2 p.m. Edward Williams Gallery, 150 Kotte Place, Hackensack. (201) 692-2449.</p>
        <p>FAIRLEIGH DICKINSON UNIVERSITY ''A Florham Sketchbook,'' exhibit of pen and ink drawings by Floyd R. Gellerman. Through Oct. 20. Opening reception: today, 3:30 p.m. to 5:30 p.m. Hours: Sundays, 2 to 10 p.m.; Mondays through Thursdays, 8:30 a.m. to 11 p.m.; Fridays, 8:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. The library, 285 Madison Avenue, Madison. (973) 443-8515.</p>
        <p>GABRIELE ART GALLERY James C. Christensen, art prints, poster, hand-painted porcelains and books; on display. Mr. Christensen will make a personal appearance. Friday, 6 p.m. to 9 p.m. Hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. 57 Bridge Street, Frenchtown. (908) 996-6011.</p>
        <p>GALLERY OF SOUTH ORANGE ''Essex Exposed 2; a juried exhibition of Essex County Artists.'' Through Oct. 22. Hours: Wednesdays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 2 p.m. and 4 to 6 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Baird Center, 5 Mead Street, South Orange. (973) 378-7754, extension 2.</p>
        <p>GALLERY ONE MAIN ''People's Choice Awards'' art show. Through Oct. 8. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Route 513, Highbridge. (908) 638-3838.</p>
        <p>GALLERY 214 ''Dreamscapes/Landscapes,'' paintings, prints, photographs and sculptures by 130 artists. Through Oct. 7. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m. 214 Glenridge Avenue, Montclair. (973) 744-8280.</p>
        <p>GROUNDS FOR SCULPTURE ''James Dinerstein: New Sculpture,'' works in cast bronze. Through April 8, 2001. Hours: Thursdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Tuesday and Wednesday by appointment. 18 Fairgrounds Road, Hamilton Township. (609) 586-0616.</p>
        <p>GUILD OF CREATIVE ART ''8th Annual Juried Open Show.'' Through Oct. 9. Hours: daily, noon to 4:30 p.m. 620 Broad Street, Shrewsbury. (732) 741-1441.</p>
        <p>HUNTERDON MUSEUM OF ART ''Runway:  Photographs by Larry Fink,'' an exhibit of behind-the-scenes photos from the world of fashion and haute couture. Through Nov. 26. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. 7 Lower Center Street, Clinton. (908) 735-8415.</p>
        <p>IN RARE FORM GALLERY ''All Chairs: Designs for 2001 and Beyond,'' works by the architect Matthew Hoey. Through Oct. 30. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. 14 Church Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-1006.</p>
        <p>J. C. C. METROWEST ''Reflections on Kiddush Sets: Sterling Silver Judaica,'' by Leo Contini.  Through Dec. 24. Marantz Art Gallery, J.C.C. of Metropolitan, 760 Northfield Avenue, West Orange. ''Life in Art: From the Gallery of Stan Kase Featuring Works by Scott Hanson, Marie Bobela and Jenny Stewart.'' Through Oct. 22. Gaelen Art Gallery, Lautenberg Family JCC of Greater Morris, 910 Route 10 East, Whippany. (973) 736-3200, ext. 330.</p>
        <p>J.C.C. ON THE PALISADES ''Yemenite Jews:  The Last Generation'' photographic exhibition. Through Friday. Hours: Monday through Thursday, 9 a.m to 10 p.m.; Friday, 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. 411 East Clinton Avenue, Tenafly. (201) 569-7900, extension 433.</p>
        <p>JERSEY CITY MUSEUM ''The Prints of a Sculptor,'' by Melvin Edwards. Through Oct. 7. Hours: Tuesdays, Thursdays, and Fridays, 10:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Wednesdays, 10:30 a.m.to 8 p.m. 472 Jersey Avenue, Jersey City. (201) 547-4514.</p>
        <p>JOHNSON &amp; JOHNSON HEADQUARTERS GALLERY Barbara Weissberger, drawings.  Through Oct. 13. New Jersey Photography Forum. Through Nov. 16. Call for appointment only. 1 Johnson and Johnson Plaza, New Brunswick. (732) 524-6957.</p>
        <p>KENT PLACE GALLERY ''Fantasy Mania,'' prints and sculptures by Florence Wint.  Through Oct. 6. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. 42 Norwood Avenue, Summit. (908) 273-0900.</p>
        <p>KERYGMA GALLERY ''Paintings,'' one-person show by Frank Trefny. Through Oct. 7. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. 38 Oak Street, Ridgewood. (201) 444-5510.</p>
        <p>LAWRENCEVILLE SCHOOL ''Myself, My Camera, My World: The Ennis Beley Project,'' photographs by 11 formerly homeless Trenton adolescents. Created by Young Audiences of New Jersey. Through Friday. Hours: Monday, Tuesday, Thursday and Friday, 9 a.m. to noon and 1 to 4:30 p.m.; Wednesday, 9 a.m. to noon. Gruss Center of Visual Arts, the Rotunda Gallery and the Marguerite and James Hutchins Gallery, Lawrenceville. (609) 620-6026.</p>
        <p>LONG BEACH ISLAND FOUNDATION OF THE ARTS AND SCIENCES ''2000 Craft Gallery.'' Through Oct. 15. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. 120 Long Beach Boulevard, Loveladies. (609) 494-1241, extension 300.</p>
        <p>MACCULLOCH HALL HISTORICAL MUSEUM ''Lasting Impressions,'' an exhibit on the history and techniques of printmaking. Through Jan. 14, 2001. Admission: $4; $3 for older people and students. Hours: Wednesdays, Thursdays and Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. 45 Macculloch Avenue, Morristown. (973) 538-2404.</p>
        <p>MERCER COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE ''Narrative Stance,'' exhibition of two Mercer County artists, Loring Hughes of Lawrenceville and Thomas Kelly of Trenton. Through Thursday. Hours: Monday, 12:30 to 3 p.m.; Tuesday, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Wednesday and Thursday, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m. and 6 to 8 p.m. The Gallery, Communications Center, 1200 Old Trenton Road, Trenton. (609) 586-4800, extension 3588.</p>
        <p>MONMOUTH COUNTY HISTORICAL ASSOCIATION ''The Karagheusian Rug Mill: A Story of Immigration and Industry.'' Tuesday through July 31, 2001. Opening reception: today, 4 p.m. to 6 p.m. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Admission: $2; $1.50 for older people; $1 for those ages 6 to 18; free for children under 6. 70 Court Street, Freehold. (732) 462-1466.</p>
        <p>MONMOUTH MUSEUM New Jersey Water Color Society: ''58th Annual Open Exhibition.'' Through Nov. 5. Opening reception: today, 3 p.m. to 5 p.m.; awards ceremony, 4 p.m.  Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Admission: $4. 761 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (732) 747-2266.</p>
        <p>MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM ''Lyrical Visions:  Music and Dance in American and Native American Art.'' ''Georgia O'Keeffe: The Artist's Landscape, Photographs by Todd Webb.''  Robin Lane, actress, will present a one-woman portrayal of O'Keeffe, today at 3 p.m.  Through Jan. 7, 2001. ''Croquet: The Art of Play.' Through Oct. 15 (course will be open Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m.) Admission: $7; $4 for children. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays and Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Admission: $5; $4 for older people and students; free for members and children under 12. 3 South Mountain Avenue, Montclair. (973) 746-5555.</p>
        <p>MONTCLAIR STATE UNIVERSITY ''Survey of Contemporary African Art,'' more than 50 works by artists from Algeria, Ghana, Mali, Nigeria and Senegal. Through Oct. 20. Opening reception: Thursday, 4 p.m. to 6 p.m. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. University Gallery, Life Hall, Valley Road and Normal Avenue, Upper Montclair. (973) 655-7640.</p>
        <p>MORRIS COUNTY HISTORICAL SOCIETY ''Women's Work is Never Done,'' an exhibition on the history and impact of the women's suffrage movement in New Jersey. Today through Jan. 28, 2001. ''1900,'' exhibit of photos, products and objects. Through September. Hours: Mondays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Admission: $4; $2 for students. Acorn Hall, 68 Morris Avenue, Morristown. (973) 267-3465.</p>
        <p>MORRIS MUSEUM New Jersey Arts Annual:  ''Everything for the Home'' juried exhibition.  Through Nov. 17. ''Art and Nature: The Hudson River School'' exhibition. Through Nov. 19. Hours: Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays to 8 p.m. Admission: $5; $3 for older people and children under age 3. 6 Normandy Heights Road, Morristown. (973) 538-0454.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF EARLY TRADES AND CRAFTS ''Time Made Visible: An Exhibit on Time and Timepieces.'' Through Dec. 30. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Admission: $3.50; $2 for students, children over 5 and older people.  Main Street at Green Village Road, Madison. (973) 377-2982.</p>
        <p>CASE MUSEUM OF CONTEMPORARY RUSSIAN ART ''20th Anniversary Exhibit,'' featuring many artists from the inaugural exhibition. Through Oct. 8. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 2 to 7 p.m. 80 Grand Street, Jersey City. (201) 332-5200.</p>
        <p>NABISCO GALLERY ''Preserving the Garden:  Saving New Jersey Landscape.'' Through Oct. 18. Hours: daily, noon to 4 p.m. 100 DeForest Avenue, East Hanover. (973) 503-2000.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS ''As If Alive: Animate Sculpture.'' Through Oct. 29. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, noon to 4 p.m.; Thursdays, 7 to 9 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 2 to 4 p.m. Palmer Gallery, 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY CITY UNIVERSITY ''Recent Paintings and Drawings by Jose Morales.'' Through Oct. 3. Lemmerman Gallery.  ''Roma: Partire, Comminare, Andare'' by Giuseppe Satta. Through Nov. 10. Courtney Gallery. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; other times by appointment. 2039 Kennedy Boulevard, Jersey City. (201) 200-3246.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY HISTORICAL SOCIETY ''Resource-Full New Jersey,'' an exhibition on natural resources, past and present, and land-use consequences. Through 2002. ''Dining In, Dining Out,'' featuring photographs, video clips, rare silverware, period furniture and 18th-century cookbooks. Through summer 2001. ''Pride of Newark: Baseball's Bears and Eagles,'' about the history of baseball in Newark. Through summer 2001. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. 52 Park Place, Newark. (973) 596-8500.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM ''Leonard Baskin, Clarence Carter, Jacob Lawrence and George Segal: New Jersey Remembers.''  Through Oct. 22. ''Woven by Tradition and Design: A Selection of American Indian Weavings, Textiles and Baskets.'' Through Jan. 27, 2001. ''Click! The Marvelous in American Vernacular Photography.'' Through Jan. 27, 2001. ''Dinosaurs, Ammonites and Asteroids.'' Saturday through Jan. 21, 2001. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 4:45 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Free. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6464.</p>
        <p>NEWARK MUSEUM ''Katherine Choy: A Promise Unfulfilled'' ceramic showcase. Through Jan. 21, 2001. ''Treasures of 19th-Century American Art.'' Through Dec. 3. ''The Luminous Image, V,'' and exhibition of illuminated photography. Through Oct. 8. ''Year of the Dragon: The Calligraphy of Wang Fangyu.'' Through Nov. 12. ''Needless Necessity: Jewelry, Silver and Personal Meaning.'' Through December. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m.; Thursdays (after hours) until 8:30 p.m. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (973) 596-6550.</p>
        <p>NEWARK PUBLIC LIBRARY ''Spared Lives:  The Actions of Three Portuguese Diplomats During World War II.'' Through Oct. 7 at the Van Buren branch. Hours: Mondays, Tuesdays, Thursdays and Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Wednesdays, 1 p.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays, 9:30 a.m. to 1:30 p.m. 140 Van Buren Street, Newark. (973) 733-7750. ''Diamond of Hope and Glory: The Life and Times of Latin Americans in the Negro Leagues.'' Through Dec. 2. Hours: Mondays, Fridays and Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Tuesdays, Wednesdays and Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 8:30 p.m. 2nd floor gallery, 5 Washington Street, Newark. (973) 733-7798.</p>
        <p>NOYES MUSEUM OF ART ''Art in Boxes: Hers and His Stories.'' Through Jan. 7, 2001. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. Admission: $3; $2 for older people and students. Lily Lake Road, Oceanville. (609) 652-8848.</p>
        <p>OAKLAND STREET GALLERY ''Perspectives in Color,'' featuring the paintings of Paul Briskey and Norman Perlmutter. Through Oct. 28. Green Apple Studio, 145 Oakland Street, Red Bank. (732) 450-2050.</p>
        <p>OCEAN COUNTY HISTORICAL SOCIETY ''Ocean County From the Explorers to 1950,'' featuring photographs, documents, paintings and objects illustrating the county's history. Through Oct. 31. Hours: Tuesdays and Thursdays, 1 to 3 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. 26 Hadley Avenue, Toms River. (732) 341-1880.</p>
        <p>OLD CHURCH CULTURAL CENTER Faculty Show. Through Friday. Hours: Monday through Friday, 9:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. 561 Piermont Road, Demarest. (201) 767-7160.</p>
        <p>WILLIAM PATERSON UNIVERSITY ''Brian Peterson: Earth, Light and Form,'' nature photographs. Through Oct. 13. ''Interior Views,'' artist's books and journals as art forms. Through Oct. 13. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Ben Shahn Galleries, Hobart Manor, 300 Pompton Road, Wayne. (973) 720-26542825.</p>
        <p>PETERS VALLEY CRAFT EDUCATION CENTER ''30th Annual Craft Fair.'' Today, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $5; free for children under 12. ''Art in the Open: The Peters Valley Gallery Without Walls'' exhibition featuring seven craft artists from New Jersey. Through Saturday. 19 Kuhn Road, Layton. (973) 948-5200.</p>
        <p>PRINCETON THEOLOGICAL SEMINARY ''Niches,'' works of Thomas McAnulty, sculptor. Through Nov. 3. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 8:30 a.m. to 9:30 p.m.; Saturdays, 8:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 2 to 9 p.m. Erdman Gallery, 20 Library Place, Princeton. (609) 497-7990.</p>
        <p>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY ART MUSEUM ''What Photographs Look Like.'' Through Oct. 15. ''Dutch Prints in the Golden Age.''  Through Nov. 5. ''Life in the Fin de Siecle:  Lithographs of Toulouse-Lautree.'' Tuesday through Oct. 29. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Princeton campus. (609) 258-3788.</p>
        <p>PRINGLE INTERNATIONAL ART GALLERY ''Alchemy and Magical Landscapes,'' an exhibition featuring original watercolors by Simon Palmer and etchings and collagraphs by Brenda Hartill. Through Oct. 14. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; other times by appointment. 8 Chambers Street, Princeton. (609) 921-9292.</p>
        <p>PRINTMAKING COUNCIL OF NEW JERSEY ''Dust Shaped Hearts'' by Don Camp -- A Collection of Casein and Earth Pigment Monoprints.'' ''Ulysses Suite'' by Julyen Norman -- woodcuts, and linoleum cuts depicting scenes from the classic novel by James Joyce.  Through Oct. 14. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m. 440 River Road, North Branch. (908) 725-2110.</p>
        <p>PUFFIN CULTURAL FORUM ''Sex, Lies and Politics: Cartoonists Shooting From the Hip,'' current and historic political cartoons. Through Oct. 29. Hours: Monday through Friday, 1 to 5 p.m.; or by appointment. 20 East Oakdene Avenue, Teaneck. (201) 836-8923.</p>
        <p>RAMAPO COLLEGE ''Distinctions,'' exhibit explores how people identify with and conform to a group. Thursday through Oct. 20. Opening reception: Thursday, 5 p.m. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 1 to 5 p.m. Kresge and Pascal Galleries, Berrie Center for the Performing Arts, 505 Ramapo Valley Road, Mahwah. (201) 684-7147.</p>
        <p>RARITAN VALLEY COMMUNITY COLLEGE ''The Portrait in the New Millenium,'' portraits by 15 artists in various media. Through Thursday. Hours: Monday, 3 to 8 p.m.; Tuesday and Thursday, noon to 3 p.m.; Wednesday, 1 to 8 p.m. Art Gallery, Route 28 and Lamington Road, North Branch. (908) 218-8876.</p>
        <p>J. RICHARDS GALLERY Dominique Dorie, landscapes of Europe. Through Oct. 5. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. 64 East Palisade Avenue, Englewood. (201) 871-1050.</p>
        <p>RIDER UNIVERSITY Marge Chavooshian, ''Paintings and Drawings.'' Thursday through Oct. 22. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 2 to 8 p.m.; Fridays through Sundays, 2 to 5 p.m. University Gallery, Route 206, Lawrenceville. (609) 896-5168.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY - CAMDEN ''Every Picture Tells a Story,'' an exhibit that explores storytelling through narrative art.  Through Nov. 11. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m. Free. Stedman Gallery, Third Street between Cooper Street and Benjamin Franklin Bridge, Camden. (856) 225-6350.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY MABEL SMITH DOUGLASS LIBRARY ''2000-01 Mary H. Dana Women Artists Series.'' Through Nov. 1. Mondays through Thursdays, 8 a.m. to 1 a.m.; Fridays, 8 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 1 a.m. George Street and Nichol Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 932-9407, ext. 26.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY - NEWARK ''Carrie Yamaoka: New Paintings.'' Through Oct. 13.  Robeson Center Art Gallery, 350 Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Boulevard, Newark. Hours:  Mondays, Wednesdays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 4 p.m. (973) 353-5119, ext. 32. Prints and Drawings by Anaida Hernandez, 1989-1999. Through September. Hours: Monday through Thursday, 8 a.m. to midnight; Friday, 8 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Saturday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sunday, noon to 10 p.m. Dana Library, 185 University Avenue, Newark. (973) 353-5900.</p>
        <p>SETON HALL UNIVERSITY ''A Response to Emotionalism: Recent Works by Eastern European Artists.'' Through Oct. 27. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. Walsh Library Gallery, 400 South Orange Avenue, South Orange. (973) 275-2033.</p>
        <p>SIMON GALLERY Larry Deyab and Katherine Parker, paintings. Through Oct. 7. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 5 p.m.; other times by appointment. 48 Bank Street, Morristown. (973) 538-5456.</p>
        <p>SOMERSET ART ASSOCIATION ''Adolf Konrad: A Tribute, Paintings and Drawings, 1970-1995.'' Through Nov. 17. Hours: Monday through Thursday, 9:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 2 p.m.; Saturdays, 9:30 a.m. to 1:30 p.m. Johnson Gallery, 2020 Burnt Mills Road, Bedminster. (908) 234-2345.</p>
        <p>SUMEI MULTIDISCIPLINARY ARTS CENTER ''Cuba: The Illusive Island.'' Through Oct. 14.  Hours: Wednesdays, 1 p.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; or call for appointment. 19 Liberty Street, at the corner of Lafayette Street, Newark. (973) 643-7883.</p>
        <p>SWAIN GALLERIES ''People, Places and Things'' pastels by Frank Zuccarelli. Through Saturday. Hours: Tuesday through Friday, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Saturday, 9:30 a.m. to 4 p.m. 703 Watchung Avenue, Plainfield. (908) 756-1707.</p>
        <p>TRENTON CITY MUSEUM ''Eleanor A. Magid:  Improvisational Bridges.'' Saturday through Nov. 5. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Sundays, 2 to 4 p.m. Ellarslie, Cadwalader Park, Trenton. (609) 989-3632.</p>
        <p>UNION COUNTY COLLEGE ''Hella Bailin: Retrospective,'' works by a world-travelling Union resident. Through Oct. 26. Hours: Mondays and Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m.; Tuesdays through Thursdays, 1 to 4 p.m. and 6 to 9 p.m. Tomasulo Art Gallery, Mackay Library, 1033 Springfield Avenue, Cranford. (908) 709-7155.</p>
        <p>WHEATON VILLAGE ''American Glass: 1900-2000,'' featuring more than 100 industrial and decorative pieces. Through Oct. 22. Hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $7; $6 for older people; $3.50 for students. No admission charge to the Gallery of American Craft. Exit 26, Route 55, Millville. (800) 998-4552, extension 2756.</p>
        <p>WHIPPANY RAILWAY MUSEUM ''Celebrate the Century Express,'' a U.S. Postal Service-sponsored rolling museum train full of commemorative stamps, video displays and other historical recreation. Today, noon to 6 p.m. Museum admission: $1 adults; $.50 for children. Route 10 West and Whippany Road, Whippany. (973) 887-8177.</p>
        <p>WILLIAMS GALLERY ''L'Afrique Peripherique Atlas'' or ''Journey Around Africa,'' exhibition featuring selected etchings by Rolf Weijburg, Dutch artist. Through Oct. 14. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; other times by appointment. 8 Chambers Street, Princeton. (609) 921-1142.</p>
        <p>YOGI BERRA MUSEUM ''El Beisbol Latino:  From Clemente to El Duque,'' an exhibition of baseball art, celebrating the greatest Latin American players and their influence.  Through Nov. 3. ''Championship,'' New York Yankee world championship trophies from 1996, 1998, 1999. Through September. Artifacts from the life of the baseball player and exhibits on the history of the Yankees, baseball in New Jersey, Negro Leagues, evolution of equipment, and baseball during World War II. Ongoing. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Tickets: $4; $2 for children. Montclair State University, 8 Quarry Road, Little Falls. (973) 655-2377.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>ATTIC ENSEMBLE ''Fifth of July'' by Lanford Wilson. Through next Sunday. Friday and Saturday at 8 p.m.; today and next Sunday at 3 p.m. Special ''early riser'' performance Thursday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $15; $10 for students and older people. Barrow Mansion, 83 Wayne Street, Jersey City. (201) 413-9200.</p>
        <p>BANANAS COMEDY CLUB Gary De Lena from Showtime's ''Comedy Club Allstars'' and HBO's ''National Lampoon's Movie Madness.'' Laurie Kilmartin, from Lifetime's ''Girls Night Out'' and Amanda Grumet, from Atlantic City's Tropicana, will join De Lena. Friday at 9:30 p.m.; Saturday at 8:30 p.m. and 10:45 p.m. Tickets: $10 on Friday; $12 on Saturday. Holiday Inn, 283 Route 17 South, Hasbrouck Heights. (201) 727-1090.</p>
        <p>BERGEN COUNTY PLAYERS ''Oliver!'' Through Oct. 7. Fridays and Saturdays at 8:30 p.m.; Sundays at 2 p.m. Tickets: $18. The Little Firehouse Theater, 298 Kinderkamack Road, Oradell. (201) 261-4200.</p>
        <p>CIRCLE PLAYERS ''The Complete Works of William Shakespeare, Abridged.'' Through Oct. 7. Fridays and Saturdays at 8 p.m.; special matinee performance today at 2 p.m.  Tickets: $12 (Fridays and Saturdays); $11 (today). 416 Victoria Avenue, Piscataway. (732) 968-7555.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY THEATER OF MORRISTOWN Paula Poundstone. Oct. 13 at 8 p.m. Tickets:  $25 to $35. Veriovka Ukrainian National Dance Company. Oct. 25 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $35. Weird Al Yancovic. Oct. 29 at 7 p.m.  Tickets: $25 to $35. 100 South Street, Morristown. (973) 539-8008.</p>
        <p>EATONTOWN PLAYHOUSE ''Wait Until Dark.'' Through Oct. 8. Fridays at 8:30 p.m.; Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 p.m. Tickets: $10 to $17 on Fridays and Saturdays; $16 on Sundays; $15 on Fridays and Saturdays for students and older people; $10 on Sundays for students and older people. 37 Highway 35 North, Tower Shopping Center, Eatontown. (732) 460-0100.</p>
        <p>ELIZABETH PLAYHOUSE ''The Youngest'' by Philip Barry. Through Oct. 15. Fridays and Saturdays at 7:30 p.m.; and Sundays at 2 p.m.  Tickets: $8; $6 for students and older people; $5 on Fridays. 1100 East Jersey Street, Elizabeth. (908) 355-0077.</p>
        <p>FORUM THEATER COMPANY ''Memorial Park.'' Today at 2 p.m. Tickets: $18; $12 for students and older people. 314 Main Street, Metuchen. (732) 548-0582.</p>
        <p>JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS Liam Harney's ''Celticfusion.'' Oct. 7 at 8 p.m. ''Capitol Steps.'' Oct. 19 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $16 to $28. Laughter Arts Festival. Oct. 26 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $35. ''Love Letters,'' starring Robert Wagner and Jill St. John. Oct. 27 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $24 to $42. George Carlin.  Oct. 28 at 7 and 10 p.m. Tickets: $24 to $36.  Squonk. Nov. 3 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 and $30.  ''The Snow Queen.'' Dec. 3 at 1 and 4 p.m.  Tickets: $12. New Jersey Ballet's ''Nutcracker.'' Dec. 9 at 1 and 4 p.m.; Dec. 10 at 1 and 4 p.m. Tickets: $15 to $26. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600.</p>
        <p>HUNTERDON HILLS PLAYHOUSE ''The Whole Town's Talking'' Dinner Theater. Through Oct. 28. Mondays through Saturdays at 11 a.m.; Sundays at 3:30 p.m.; Saturdays at 6:30 p.m. Tickets: $35.50 to $39.50 (lunch); $41.50 to $45.50 (Sundays); $43 to $47 (Saturday evenings). Exit 12 off Routes 78 and 22, Perryville. (800) 447-7313.</p>
        <p>KELSEY THEATER ''Arsenic and Old Lace.''  Fridays and Saturdays through Oct. 7 at 8 p.m.; next Sunday and Oct. 8 at 3 p.m. Tickets: $10 and $12. ''Little Shop of Horrors.'' Oct. 13 through 22. Fridays and Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Oct. 21 at 1 p.m.; Sundays at 3 p.m. Tickets: $10 and $12. ''The Tamburitzans.'' Nov. 11 at 8 p.m.; Nov. 12 at 3 p.m. Tickets: $16 and $18. Mercer County Community College, 1200 Trenton Road, Trenton. (609) 584-9444.</p>
        <p>LUMIA THEATER -- STAGE II ''Improper Attention,'' by Diane Bairamian. Today and tomorrow at 8 p.m. Tickets: $12; $10 for students and older people. 179 Broadway, Long Branch. (732) 229-3166.</p>
        <p>McCARTER THEATER ''The Odyssey.'' Through next Sunday. Tickets: $29 to $42. Call for show times. Julio Bocca and Ballet Argentino. Oct. 4 and 5 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $33 to $44.  Hubbard Street Dance Chicago. Bale Folclorico da Bahia: Carnival 2000. Oct. 8 at 3 p.m.  Tickets: $27 to $38. Nov. 8 and 9 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $33 to $44. ''A Christmas Carol.'' Dec. 5 to 24. Tickets: $32 to $40. American Repertory Ballet's ''The Nutcracker.'' Nov. 24 to 26; Dec. 28 to 31. Tickets: $26 to $38. Center for the Performing Arts, 91 University Place, Princeton. (609) 258-2787.</p>
        <p>MURDER TO GO THEATER ''Killing Mr. Withers.'' Ongoing. Fridays and Saturdays at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $45 on Fridays; $48 on Saturdays, includes four-course dinner. Il Giardino, Cedar Knolls. (973) 301-0562.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY PERFORMING ARTS CENTER Julio Bocca and Ballet Argentino. Oct. 6 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $10 to $42. Carnival 2000: Bale Folclorico Da Bahia. Oct. 13 and 8 p.m. Tickets: $10 to $48. NDR Symphony Orchestra of Hamburg. Oct. 15 at 3 p.m. Tickets: $12 to $32.  Ballet Folklorico de Mexico. Oct. 21 at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $10 to $48. Prudential Hall. The Flying Karamazov Brothers in ''L'Universe.''  Oct. 25 at 7:30 p.m., Oct. 26 at 7:30 p.m., Oct. 28 at 2:30 p.m. and 7:30 p.m. and Oct. 29 at 2:30 p.m. Tickets: $34 and $40. Victoria Theater.  Cloud Gate Dance Theater of Taiwan. Oct. 29 at 5 p.m. Tickets: $10 to $48. Hubbard Street Dance Chicago. Nov. 3 and 4 at 7:30 p.m.; Nov. 5 at 2:30 p.m. Victoria Theater. Veriovka Ukrainian National Song and Dance Ensemble. Nov. 3 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $10 to $48. Black Watch Drums, Pipes and Highland Dancers  and The Band/Choir of the Prince of Wales' Division. Nov. 4 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $12 to $52.  The Shaolin Warriors. Nov. 5 at 3 p.m. Tickets: $9 to $42. ''Peter Pan.'' Nov. 8 at 7:30 p.m.; Nov. 9 at 1:30 p.m. and 7:30 p.m.; Nov. 10 at 8 p.m.; Nov. 11 at 2 p.m. and 8 p.m.; Nov. 12 at 3 p.m. Tickets: $11 to $60. Taipei Folk Dance Theater. Nov. 11 at 7:30 p.m. Tickets:  $21 and $25. ''From the Mississippi Delta.''  Nov. 21 to Nov. 26. Tickets: $41 and $45. Victoria Theater. Savion Glover in ''Foot Notes,'' the concert with Jimmy Slyde, Dianne Walker and Cartier Williams. Dec. 21 at 7:30 p.m.; Dec. 22 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $10 to $48. Prudential Hall. ''It Ain't Nothin' but the Blues.'' Dec. 26 to Dec. 31. Tickets: $50 and $55. ''The Nutcracker on Ice,'' St. Petersburg State Ballet on Ice. Dec. 27 at 7:30 p.m.; Dec. 28 at 1:30 p.m. and 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $10 to $48. ''Cinderella on Ice,'' St. Peterburg State Ballet on Ice. Dec. 29 at 7:30 p.m.; Dec. 30 at 1:30 p.m. and 7:30 p.m.; Dec. 31 at 1:30 p.m. 1 Center Street, Newark. (888) 466-5722.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY SHAKESPEARE FESTIVAL ''Antony and Cleopatra.'' Through Saturday. Tickets: $25 to $38. Call for show times. F. M. Kirby Shakespeare Theater, 36 Madison Avenue, Madison. (973) 408-5600.</p>
        <p>PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE ''Anything Goes'' starring Chita Rivera and Lee Roy Reams. Through Oct. 15. Wednesdays through Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 7:30 p.m.; Thursday and Sunday matinees at 2 p.m.; and Saturday matinees at 2:30 p.m. ''Victor/Victoria.'' Nov. 1 to Dec. 10. Tchaikovsky's ''Nutcracker.'' Dec. 15 to 27. Tickets: $37 to $60. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (973) 376-4343.</p>
        <p>PARSIPPANY PLAYHOUSE ''Mack and Mabel.'' Friday through Oct. 21. Fridays and Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sunday, Oct. 15 at 2 p.m.  Tickets: $22; $17 for students; $15 for older people. 1130 Knoll Road, Parsippany. (973) 263-7020.</p>
        <p>PLAYHOUSE 22 ''Once Upon a Mattress.''  Through Oct. 7. Fridays and Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sunday matinees at 3 p.m. Tickets: $16; $12 for students and older people. 210 Dunhams Corner Road, East Brunswick. (732) 254-3939.</p>
        <p>RITZ THEATER ''Vaudeville Villains,'' comedy by Alex Wilkie. Through Oct. 7. Performances are Fridays and Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 2 p.m.; Wednesday, Oct. 4 at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $16 (Fridays and Saturdays); $12.50 (Sundays); $15 (Wednesdays). 915 White Horse Pike, Oaklyn. (609) 858-5230.</p>
        <p>STATE THEATER Travis Tritt. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $28 to $100. ''Celticfusion.'' Oct. 6 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $34. Ballet Nacional de Caracas. Oct. 19 at 8 p.m. Tickets:  $20 to $32. Peter Pan. Oct. 21 at 3 p.m. and 7 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $40. ''Veriovka: Ukrainian National Song and Dance Company.'' Oct. 24 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $38. ''Die Fledermaus,'' Western Opera Theater. Oct. 26 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $45. Mark Russell. Oct. 28 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $34. Wayne Shorter and Herbie Hancock: ''1+1.'' Nov. 9 at 8 p.m.  Tickets: $20 to $38. Trinity Irish Dance Company. Nov. 10 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $32.  ''Footloose.'' Dec. 2 at 3 p.m. and 8 p.m. Tickets: $21 to $47. ''Cinderella,'' Landis and Company. Dec. 3 at 1 p.m. and 4 p.m. Tickets: $12 to $14. American Repertory Ballet's ''Nutcracker.'' Dec. 9 at 1 p.m. and 4:30 p.m.; Dec. 10 at 1 p.m. and 4:30 p.m. Tickets: $16 to $32.  15 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 246-7469.</p>
        <p>TWELVE MILES WEST THEATRE COMPANY ''Shakespeare's R+J,'' adapted by Joe Calarco. Through Saturday Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8 p.m.; today at 3 p.m. Tickets: $20; $15 for students and older people.  (973) 746-7181.</p>
        <p>TWO RIVER THEATER COMPANY ''Arms and the Man.'' Today at 3 p.m. Tickets: $28. Algonquin Arts Theater, 171 Main Street, Manasquan. (732) 345-1400.</p>
        <p>VAGABOND PLAYERS ''Broadway's Best,'' a musical revue of some of the best songs Broadway has to offer this year. Today at 2 p.m. Tickets: $10; $8 for children under 12 and older people. Shore Hills Country Club, Morse Place, Landing. (973) 398-3565.</p>
        <p>WESTMINSTER CHOIR COLLEGE OF RIDER UNIVERSITY ''Weill: Down in the Valley'' and ''Copland: The Tender Land.'' Friday at 8 p.m.; Saturday at 3 p.m. and 8 p.m. Tickets:  $15; $10 for students and older people. The Playhouse, 101 Walnut Lane, Princeton. (609) 921-2663, ext. 308.</p>
        <p>For Children</p>
        <p>BERGEN COUNTY Y JEWISH COMMUNITY CENTER ''Club Y-J.C.C. Kids'' is sponsoring ''Bubblemania,'' which includes program, dinner and dessert for children in kindergarten and grade 1. Tuesday, 5:30 p.m. to 7 p.m.  Tickets: $12 for members; $18 for guests.605 Pascack Road, Washington Township. (201) 666-6610, extension 210.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY THEATER OF MORRISTOWN ''A Christmas Carol.'' Nov. 25 at 10 a.m. and noon.  Tickets: $12. Lazer Vaudeville. Dec. 3 at 1 p.m. and 4 p.m. Tickets: $12, $15 and $18. Tom Chapin. Dec. 17 at 1 p.m. and 4 p.m. Tickets:  $12, $15 and $18. ''Joyful Traditions: A Celebration of the Kwanzaa Spirit.'' Dec. 27 at 7 p.m. Tickets: $12. ''Sleeping Beauty.'' Dec. 28 at 1 p.m. and 4 p.m. Tickets: $12 and $15. 100 South Street, Morristown. (973) 539-8008.</p>
        <p>DORBROOK ACTIVITY CENTER ''Fun With French.'' For children 5 to 6 years old. Begins Thursdays at 1 p.m., through October 26. Pre-registration is required. (732) 842-4000.</p>
        <p>EATONTOWN PLAYHOUSE ''Granny's Puppet Cottage Show,'' sing-along with puppets. Tomorrow at 10 a.m. ''The Mother Goose Show,'' sing-alongs, nursery rhymes and ''go on a bear hunt.'' Friday at 10 a.m. ''Cowboy Vince and Comedy Magic.'' Friday at 11 a.m.'' Sing Along With Yosi.'' Saturday at 4:30 p.m. The youth theater group presents: ''Laff-In School; Our Time at Tony's and Brotherhood of Immortals.'' Saturdays at 2 p.m. and Sundays at 12:30 p.m. Through Oct. 8. Tickets at all events: $7.50. 37 Highway 35 North, Tower Shopping Center, Eatontown. (732) 460-0100.</p>
        <p>FORUM THEATER COMPANY ''The Legend of Sleepy Hollow.'' Saturday through Nov. 4. Performances are every Saturday at 11 a.m.  Tickets: $9. 314 Main Street, Metuchen. (732) 548-0582.</p>
        <p>KELSEY THEATER ''Otherwise Known as Sheila the Great.'' Oct. 14 at 2 p.m. and 4 p.m  Tickets: $7. ''Heidi.'' Nov. 4 at 2 p.m. and 4 p.m. Tickets: $7. ''Peter Pan.'' Nov. 24, Dec. 1 and 8 at 8 p.m.; Nov. 25, Dec. 2 and 9 at 1 p.m. and 8 p.m.; Nov. 26 and Dec. 3 and 10 at 3 p.m.  Tickets: $18; $16 for students and older people; $10 for children. '' 'Twas the Night Before Christmas. . ..'' Dec. 15 at 7 p.m.; Dec. 16 at 11 a.m., 2 p.m and 4 p.m. Tickets: $7. The Nutcraker Ballet. Dec. 23 at 1 p.m. and 4 p.m. Tickets: $10 and $12. Mercer County Community College, 1200 Trenton Road, Trenton. (609) 921-9444.</p>
        <p>MORRIS COUNTY PARK COMMISSION ''Bugs'' preschooler walk. Tomorrow at 9:30 a.m.  Fee: $5. ''Mother/Infant Walk: Patriot's Path.'' Tuesday at 9:30 a.m. Free. Pre-registration is required. Great Swamp Outdoor Education Center, 247 Southern Boulevard, Chatham Township. (973) 635-6629.</p>
        <p>NEWARK MUSEUM ''Where in the Universe Is Carmen Sandiego?'' at the Alice and Leonard Dreyfuss Planetarium. Through October. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays at 2:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 p.m. and 3 p.m. Tickets: $3; $2 for members; $1 for children and older people. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (973) 596-6355.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY CHILDREN'S MUSEUM Daily programs: ''Fairy Tale Play'' at 10:30 a.m.; ''Storytime'' at noon; ''Special Craft Project'' at 2:30 p.m. Permanent exhibits: child-size grocery store, pizzeria and castle, prehistoric cave, computers and more. Tickets: $8. 599 Industrial Avenue, Paramus. (201) 262-5151.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY PERFORMING ARTS CENTER ''Ragamala Music and Dance.'' For ages 8 and up. Next Sunday at 2 p.m. Bobby Sanabria and Ascension. Oct. 7 at 2 p.m. For ages 12 and up. ''Psyche.'' Oct. 21 at 2 p.m. For ages 12 and up. Tickets: $18; $9 for children. All-State Jazz Concert. Nov. 17 at 7 p.m. For ages 8 and up. Tickets: $16; $8 for children. ''Paper Bag Players.'' Nov. 18 at 2 p.m. For ages 3 to 8.  Tickets: $18; $9 for children. All-State Orchestra and Chorus Concert. Nov. 19 at 3 p.m. Tickets: $8 to $18; $8 for children. Mufaro's Beautiful Daughters. Dec. 2 at 2 p.m. For ages 5 to 12. Tickets: $18; $9 for children. ''Songs of the Season.'' Dec. 3 at 2 p.m. Tickets: $12; &amp; for children. ''Hans Brinker's Christmas.'' Dec. 9 and Dec. 10 at 2 p.m. Tickets: $18; $9 for children. ''A Joyous Gospel Holiday.'' Dec. 13 and 14 at 7 p.m. For ages 10 and up. Tickets: $25; $12 for children. 2000 Kwanzaa Festival Opening Celebration. Dec. 15 at 7 p.m. For ages 5 and up. Tickets: $18; $9 for children. ''The Spirit of Kwanzaa.'' Dec. 16 at 2 p.m. and 5 p.m. Tickets: $18; $9 for children. ''Kids and Yiddish.'' Dec. 17 at 3 p.m. Tickets: $18; $9 for children. 1 Center Street, Newark. (888) 466-5722.</p>
        <p>STATE THEATER ''Franklin's Big Adventure.'' Oct. 15 at 1 p.m. and 4 p.m. Tickets: 14. 15 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 246-7469.</p>
        <p>STONY BROOK-MILLSTONE WATERSHED ''Crickets and Grasshoppers'' for preschool children, ages 3 to 5. Tuesday, 10 a.m. to 11:30 a.m. and Wednesday, 1 p.m. to 2:30 p.m.  ''Crickets and Grasshoppers'' for school age children, 6 to 12. Thursday, 4 p.m. to 5:30 p.m.  Fee: $8; $5 for members. Pre-registration is required for all events. Buttinger Nature Center, 31 Titus Mill Road, Pennington. (609) 737-7592.</p>
        <p>Spoken Word</p>
        <p>ANSHE EMETH MEMORIAL TEMPLE Nat Bodian, author of ''The Joy of Publishing'' -- among other books, will discuss the Jewish family heritage of the 19th-century pirate Jean Lafitte; sponsored by the Jewish Historical Society of Central New Jersey. Today at 1:30 p.m. Free. 222 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 249-4894.</p>
        <p>BARNES &amp; NOBLE Brendan P. Tobin, author, will discuss and sign his book ''Yes, You Can!  Extraordinary Results from Ordinary People.'' Thursday at 7:30 p.m. Free. 1180 Raritan Road, Clark. (732) 574-1818.</p>
        <p>BARNES &amp; NOBLE Dr. Michael Kasten, a certified hypnotherapist and author, will discuss and sign copies of his book ''Mastering the Game of Life.'' Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. Free. 753 Route 18, Brunswick Square, East Brunswick. (732) 432-0100.</p>
        <p>BARNES &amp; NOBLE Caryl Stern-LaRosa, author, will discuss and sign copies of her book ''Hate Hurts: How Children Learn and Unlearn Prejudice.'' Today, 7:30 p.m. to 8:30 p.m. Free. 518 West Mount Pleasant Avenue, Livingston. (973) 535-9087.</p>
        <p>BARNES &amp; NOBLE Marcia Rosen, author, will discuss and sign copies of her book ''The Woman's Business Therapist.'' Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. Pre-registration is required by tomorrow. 160 Route 17 North, Paramus. (201) 261-6995.</p>
        <p>BERNARDS TOWNSHIP LIBRARY Dr. Barbara Tomlinson, retired course coordinator of the humanities component of Kean University's General Education program, will present five sessions on ''Let's Visit the Met,'' a slide-lecture series on highlights at the Metropolitan Museum of Art. The first session, ''Shining Light on Classical Greece and Rome: The Brilliant New Galleries'' will take place on Wednesday, 1 p.m. to 2 p.m. Registration is required; fee: $25. ''Friday Night at the Opera,'' after-hours series with Prof. Robert W. Butts, founder and director of the Baroque Orchestra of Boonton. Friday, 7:30 p.m. to 9 p.m.  Fee: $25 for six sessions. 32 South Maple Avenue, Basking Ridge. (908) 204-3038.</p>
        <p>BORDERS BOOKS AND MUSIC Betty Bonham Lies, author of ''My Ticket to Tomorrow,'' will lead a discussion of ''Earth's Daughters:  Stories of Women in Classical Mythology.''  Thursday at 7:30 p.m. Free. 601 Nassau Park Boulevard, Building G, Princeton. (609) 514-0040.</p>
        <p>ENGLEWOOD PUBLIC LIBRARY Jeff Perry, author and labor leader from Westwood, will discuss Herbert Harrison, ''The Father of Harlem Radicalism,'' to mark ''Banned Books Week'' -- Sept. 23 to 30. Tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. Free. 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215, ext. 227.</p>
        <p>ETHICAL CULTURE SOCIETY Arthur Dobrin, leader of the Ethical Humanist Society of Long Island, will discuss a humanist's appreciation of Christianity. Today at 11 a.m. 687 Larch Avenue, Teaneck. (201) 836-5187.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY HISTORICAL SOCIETY Thomas Guy, producer and director of a documentary about Newark's jazz tradition called ''I Heard Tell: A Portrait of Newark's Jazz Legacy 1920's to 1950's,'' will discuss the personal interviews he conducted. Wednesday, 12:15 p.m. to 1 p.m. Free. 52 Park Place, Newark. (973) 596-8500, extension 234.</p>
        <p>RAMAPO COLLEGE Daniel C. Barsen, vice president of the American International Automobile Dealers Association, will moderate a forum about dramatic changes occurring in the automobile industry. Representatives from Jaguar, Mercedes-Benz, Volvo and BMW will attend. Thursday at 6 p.m.; reception at 5 p.m. Student Center Alumni Lounge, 505 Ramapo Valley Road, Mahwah. (201) 684-7287.</p>
        <p>Etc.</p>
        <p>CRAFTSMAN FARMS FOUNDATION ''Living the Arts and Crafts Lifestyle V,'' a weekend symposium dedicated to the ideals and influences of Gustav Stickley, with lectures, artisan fair, silent auction, tours of the Stickley family home and more. Today, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. Admission: $10 adults, $3 children 6 to 12 for the craft fair; $12 for lectures. 2352 Route 10 West, at Manor Lane, Parsippany. (973) 540-1165.</p>
        <p>DEEP CUT ORCHID SOCIETY Annual Auction, with more than 425 orchid plants to be auctioned. Today, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; preview at 9:30 a.m. Free. Fire House No. 2, Conover Road, Colts Neck. (732) 531-5058.</p>
        <p>DREW UNIVERSITY ''The Downward Spiral: Truth, Lies, and the Ultimate Complicity in Holocaust/Genocide,'' a film and lecture series. ''A Visitor From the Living.'' Tuesday, 7 to 9:30 p.m. Admission: $5; free to Drew community. University Center 107, 36 Madison Avenue, Madison. (973) 408-3600.</p>
        <p>FLAT ROCK BROOK NATURE CENTER Sunset Hikes. Tuesday at 6:30 p.m. Fall strolls.  Wednesday mornings through November, 10 a.m. to 11 a.m. Fee: $3 for non-members; free for members. Pre-registration required. 443 Van Nostrand Avenue, Englewood. (201) 567-1265.</p>
        <p>HOBOKEN ARTS AND MUSIC FESTIVAL Today, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Washington Street (from Newark to 7th Street) will be closed to traffic from 8 a.m. to 7:30 p.m. More than 300 artists, photographers and craftspeople, including food vendors and musical performances by NRBQ, the Duprees, and more. (201) 420-2207.</p>
        <p>MONTCLAIR PUBLIC LIBRARY ''Booktoberfest,'' with book sale, games and rides, writing workshops for kids, storytelling and more. Today, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Free. Clary Anderson Arena, 41 Chestnut Street, Montclair address: 50 South Fullerton Street, Montclair. (973) 744-0500, ext. 225.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY CONVENTION/EXPO CENTER ''12th Annual New Jersey Fall Boat Show.'' Friday through next Sunday. Friday, 1 p.m. to 10 p.m.; Saturday, 11 a.m to 10 p.m.; next Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Tickets: $7; $5 for children, 12 to 17; free for children under 11. 97 Sunfield Avenue, Edison. (800) 332-3976.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY FILM FESTIVAL FALL 2000  ''East West.'' Today at 7 p.m. ''Benjamin Smoke.'' Friday, Saturday and next Sunday at 7 p.m. Scott Hall, 123. Rutgers University, College Avenue and Hamilton Street, New Brunswick. ''Eyes Without a Face.'' Thursday at 7 p.m. Loree Hall, 24. Rutgers University, Nichol Avenue and George Street, Douglass College campus, New Brunswick. Tickets: $5; $4 for members.(732) 932-8482.</p>
        <p>SIX FLAGS GREAT ADVENTURE ''9th Annual Fright Fest.'' Friday evenings, Saturdays and Sundays through Oct. 29. Includes Halloween-themed rides, attractions, shows and a ''Hallowedding'' ceremony on Oct. 13. Free with admission, $43.96 (adult); $21.98 (child). Northern Star Arena, exit 7A off the New Jersey Turnpike. (732) 928-1821.</p>
        <p>SOMERSET COUNTY PARK COMMISSION ''Brooklyn Botanical Garden'' daylong trip.  Thursday, 8 a.m. to 6 p.m. Fee: $30; $20 for students and older people. ''1770's Living History Festival,'' including working crafts, live music, tours and hay rides. Next Sunday, 10:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. Fee: $2 donation (optional). Visitor Center, 190 Lord Stirling Road, Basking Ridge. (908) 766-2489.</p>
        <p>TRAILSIDE NATURE AND SCIENCE CENTER ''Harvest Festival,'' including demonstrations, storytelling; planetarium shows; crafts; petting zoo, and more. Today, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $3; free for children 7 and under. ''Native American Skylore'' planetarium show. Today at 11:15 a.m., 12:30 p.m., 1:45 p.m., 3 p.m. and 3:45 p.m. Free. 452 New Providence Road, Mountainside. (908) 789-3670.</p>
        <p>WHEATON VILLAGE ''2nd Annual Festival of Fine Craft,'' featuring music, craft demonstrations, children's activities, food and more.  Saturday and next Sunday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $7; $6 for older people; $3.50 for students; includes admission to all Wheaton Village attractions. Exit 26, Route 55, Millville. (800) 998-4552.</p>
        <p>WHIPPANY RAILWAY MUSEUM ''Pumpkin Festival.'' Next Sunday, 12:30 p.m. to 5:30 p.m. Admission: $7; $4 for children under 12.  Route 10 West and Whippany Road, Whippany. (973) 887-8177.</p>
        <p>At the Casios</p>
        <p>All tickets are available through Ticketmaster, (800) 736-1420.</p>
        <p>BALLY'S PARK PLACE ''Legends in Concert.'' impersonations of Stevie Wonder, Little Richard, Elvis Presley, Linda Ronstadt and Barbra Streisand. Mondays through Thursdays at 3:30 and 7:30 p.m.; Saturdays at 8 and 10:30 p.m.; Sundays at 7:30 and 10 p.m. Tickets: $15 to $25. Park Cabaret, Boardwalk and Park Place. (800) 225-5977.</p>
        <p>CLARIDGE HOTEL ''Pump Boys and Dinettes,'' national tour of the Broadway musical. Today, 3 and 7 p.m. Tickets: $15. ''Jeff McBride's Abracadazzle.'' Wednesday through Nov. 16. Mondays through Thursdays at 8 p.m.; Saturdays at 8 p.m. and 11 p.m.; Sundays at 7 p.m. Tickets: $15, Sundays through Thursdays; $19, Saturdays. Palace Theater, Boardwalk and Park Place. (609) 340-3700.</p>
        <p>TROPICANA Travis Tritt with Montgomery Gentry, special guest. Friday at 9 p.m. Tickets: $47.50. ''I.F.C. Ultimate Fighting.'' Saturday at 9 p.m. Tickets: $150 and $100 (orchestra); $50 (mezzanine); $35 (bleachers); $25 (balcony). ''Dresses of Diana, Princess of Wales Exhibit.'' Wednesday through Dec. 28.  Hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 10 p.m. Tickets:  $13.95; $11.95 for older people; $6.95 for children, aged 5 to 11. Boardwalk and Brighton Avenue. (609) 340-3020.</p>
        <p>ON THE TOWNS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
