<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Model Festival for London. But for New York?</title>
    <meta content="24OEST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/arts/24OEST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000924T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233082"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Masur, Kurt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oestreich, James R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EEDC153BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2333" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Model Festival for London. But for New York?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES R. OESTREICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Oestreich, James R</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on BBC Proms, summer music festival now at Royal Albert Hall, which began in 1895 at old Queen's Hall; New York Philharmonic music director Kurt Masur is exploring possibility of bringing Proms-like event or modern music festival to Seventh Regiment Armony in New York City; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is the very model of a modern music festival,'' the conductor Andrew Davis pattered during the 72nd and last concert of the BBC Proms festival at the Royal Albert Hall here this month, offering no apologies to Gilbert and Sullivan and filling out the famous song with more doggerel celebrating the Proms. It was a parting tribute, for Sir Andrew was relinquishing the post he had held for 11 years, as chief conductor of the BBC Symphony Orchestra, the mainstay of the festival, to become music director of the Lyric Opera of Chicago. (Leonard Slatkin succeeds him at the BBC.)</p>
        <p>The Proms, which began in 1895 and are still going strong, to judge from the last four concerts this year, are surely the model of a summer music festival for London. And it is a model that some have eyed longingly from afar, finding it attractive for, say, New York. Kurt Masur, even as he enters his penultimate season as music director of the New York Philharmonic, continues to broach the possibility of a Proms-like event in the Seventh Regiment Armory across Central Park from Lincoln Center. But how well might the Proms translate to New York? And if not the Proms, then what is the model of a modern music festival for New York?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is the very model of a modern music festival,'' the conductor Andrew Davis pattered during the 72nd and last concert of the BBC Proms festival at the Royal Albert Hall here this month, offering no apologies to Gilbert and Sullivan and filling out the famous song with more doggerel celebrating the Proms. It was a parting tribute, for Sir Andrew was relinquishing the post he had held for 11 years, as chief conductor of the BBC Symphony Orchestra, the mainstay of the festival, to become music director of the Lyric Opera of Chicago. (Leonard Slatkin succeeds him at the BBC.)</p>
        <p>The Proms, which began in 1895 and are still going strong, to judge from the last four concerts this year, are surely the model of a summer music festival for London. And it is a model that some have eyed longingly from afar, finding it attractive for, say, New York. Kurt Masur, even as he enters his penultimate season as music director of the New York Philharmonic, continues to broach the possibility of a Proms-like event in the Seventh Regiment Armory across Central Park from Lincoln Center. But how well might the Proms translate to New York? And if not the Proms, then what is the model of a modern music festival for New York?</p>
        <p>The Henry Wood Promenade Concerts, to use the formal title, were founded by Wood, a conductor, organist and pianist, in the old Queen's Hall, with a capacity of 2,500. They take their character from the Promenaders, or Prommers: the devoted listeners who buy standing room on the arena floor directly in front of the stage and,  since the festival moved to the vast Royal Albert Hall in 1941, high aloft in the gallery. This hall, a study in faded elegance on the grand scale, holds almost 6,000 people, including 900 Prommers in the arena and 500 more in the gallery. Lines of Prommers form outside on the day of a concert, often extending for blocks. Some wait to buy tickets, for $:3, less than $5; others hold season tickets at a sizable discount.</p>
        <p>What I remember best from an earlier visit to the Proms, 12 years ago, was the byplay among Prommers, with chants, posters and props commenting drolly or nonsensically on the music or on politics. But here there was little of that. Oh, the arena challenged the gallery to a phantom tennis match at one point, and the grunts of serves from on high were answered by shouts of 'Fault!'' below. But for the most part, the Prommers spent the time before concerts collecting money for charities and engaging in polite conversation.</p>
        <p>And once performances began, an American could only be stunned by the intense silence among so many listeners, with scarcely a cough heard through at least two entire evenings.</p>
        <p>''In any hall, those paying the least amount of money are among the most avid listeners, but they're usually far from the action,'' said Nicholas Kenyon, who has been director of the Proms since 1996. ''But here the atmosphere of the hall is based on the people paying the least. The concentration is incredible, and it radiates outward.''</p>
        <p>Outward from those standing in the arena, that is. ''The gallery is a law unto itself,'' Mr. Kenyon added. ''We hear strange stories about what goes on. We even believe that babies have been born up there, or if not born, at least conceived.''</p>
        <p>Oddly, there were flurries of coughs, American style, at the best of those four late concerts, with Valery Gergiev conducting the World Orchestra for Peace in a blazing performance of Shostakovich's ''Leningrad'' Symphony on the next to last night. And the Last Night of the Proms, as the capstone is called, is something else again.</p>
        <p>There, national sentiment and general lunacy prevail, and the audience becomes part of the show, waving flags and banners and singing along to Elgar (''Land of Hope and Glory''), Arne (''Rule, Britannia'') and Parry (''Jerusalem''), producing sound effects in Wood's ''Fantasia on British Sea Songs'' and, on this occasion, serenading the departing maestro. The soberest critics stay away and dismiss the affair as a nationalistic display co-opted by right-wing elements. Others in the cultural world more given to ambivalence tend to sound some variation on the words of a radio producer who called the event ''utterly offensive but quite wonderful.''</p>
        <p>Even that judgment was too harsh for Mr. Kenyon, himself a former music critic at The New Yorker and at several London newspapers. ''It's utterly eccentric and very difficult to explain but totally inoffensive,'' Mr. Kenyon said, pointing out that audience members wave flags of many countries. ''It's really not a political event of any kind. If we saw any danger of its being taken over that way, we would do something about it. It's a totally innocent outpouring of British spirit, with people singing tunes that everyone likes to sing.''</p>
        <p>At that, half of the concert is ''serious.'' On that recent Saturday, Sir Andrew led the BBC Symphony in Elgar's orchestration of Bach's Fantasia and Fugue in C minor (BWV 537); the young American violinist Hilary Hahn played Mozart's Violin Concerto in D (K. 218) brilliantly; and the English soprano Jane Eaglen gave a powerful account of the final scene from Strauss's ''Salome.''</p>
        <p>And the rest of the Proms season can be more than serious. The Wednesday before, Bernard Haitink led the BBC Symphony Orchestra and Chorus in Beethoven's Ninth Symphony with unusually substantial company: Stravinsky's ''Symphony of Psalms.'' The Stravinsky completed a seasonlong survey of psalm settings, no less, and unfortunately it (or Mr. Haitink) set a tone of coolness and abstraction that more or less carried through the Beethoven. The Shostakovich symphony, that Friday, was also set off substantially, by ''La Mer'' of Debussy, sounding in Mr. Gergiev's hands like the Baltic Sea.</p>
        <p>And on the Thursday, H. K. Gruber conducted the BBC Philharmonic and the BBC Singers in a concert version of Weill's ''Aufstieg und Fall der Stadt Mahagonny'' (''Rise and Fall of the City of Mahagonny''), completing another seasonlong concentration, on the music of Kurt Weill in his centenary. (Other featured composers were Bach, Copland, Shostakovich and Sullivan.) With the singers heavily amplified and ''staging'' applied in dribs and drabs, the performance made an uneven effect. (Or worse: Rodney Milnes wrote in The Times of London, ''It's been a good season, and if it was time for an absolute turkey, here it was.'')</p>
        <p>For whatever reasons, this was the only concert that did not come close to filling the house, and there was room on the arena floor for some to sit. But most evidently take it as a point of honor to stand, and what terrors could the three hours (with intermission) hold here after the six hours (with intermissions) of Simon Rattle's concert performance of Wagner's ''Parsifal'' four days before?</p>
        <p>Yet for all the seriousness of much of the enterprise, including goodly doses of contemporary music, the atmosphere remains festive. Wood, who died in 1944, still presides in the form of a bust imported from the Royal Academy of Music and placed on a pedestal at the rear of the stage. On the last night, he is crowned with a wreath. He was also brought into action in ''Mahagonny,'' spotlighted as if he were delivering the English commentary on Bertolt Brecht's deeply cynical text; in fact, the commentary was piped in, recorded by Jeremy Paxman, an acerbic and hard-hitting television interviewer.</p>
        <p>And all of this largess is shared with the city and the nation through the good offices of the BBC, which took over the Proms in 1927, rescuing them from insolvency. (The annual budget now approaches $8 million, with more than half covered by ticket sales and the BBC supplying the rest.) Every concert is broadcast on radio, and many, including the last night, are televised. The second, ''pops'' half of the final concert is shown in nearby Hyde Park, as part of a larger program attended by tens of thousands; this year, it was also shown in parks in Liverpool and Birmingham.</p>
        <p>So much a part of the public consciousness are the Proms, it seemed only natural that Sir Andrew's last concert should be the occasion for a television profile of him on ''This Is Your Life,'' the British equivalent of an old American show, in which the subject is taken by surprise. Sir Andrew was ambushed on camera at the end of the rehearsal on Saturday and whisked off to a studio to record the rest of the show for future broadcast.</p>
        <p>HOW does all of this apply to New York? Not whole cloth, for sure; not even with all the Britishisms translated into American. As with so many traditions, institutions and circumstances that have evolved over the years -- as with that incomparably rich, warm sound of Carnegie Hall partly lost in the 1986 renovation, for example -- the Proms have grown organically and taken on a life of their own, a product of seeming defects as well as obvious virtues, of inadvertency as well as careful design. (In Carnegie, read: hole in the stage ceiling, curtain to hide the hole and the like.)</p>
        <p>''It has taken 106 years of continuous tradition to build this,'' Mr. Kenyon said. ''You can't create something like that overnight.'' But you have to start somewhere. And the multidisciplinary Lincoln Center Festival represents a notable beginning over its first five years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kenyon, who finds the great value of the Proms in its ability to attract new listeners from outside the field, remains skeptical. ''There is a genuine need for a new venue in New York,'' he said. ''I wouldn't have thought of Lincoln Center, which feels stuffy and conventional. I would have thought that the crowds for Central Park concerts should be the basis of a constituency. How do you get those people indoors?''</p>
        <p>Nigel Redden, the director of the Lincoln Center Festival since 1998 and of the Spoleto Festival U.S.A. in Charleston, S.C., begs to differ. ''We've gotten an audience that is anything but stuffy,'' he said of the New York festival. ''Audiences come to where the programs are exciting, and it happened this summer with our presentations of Caribbean music and electronic music.''</p>
        <p>Those events, it should be noted, moved to sites outside Lincoln Center, as have others not well served by its buildings, like the Chinese opera ''The Peony Pavilion.'' On the other hand, the concerts of the New York Philharmonic at Avery Fisher Hall have been hard put to separate themselves from the humdrum of the regular season.</p>
        <p>Last spring at Spoleto, Mr. Redden showed what might be missing so far in New York: the way a festival can capture the imagination of a city, as the Proms regularly do in London. The festival concert at Spoleto was a performance of ''Surrogate Cities,'' a big, brash bear of a piece by Heiner Goebbels, a German. It could not in itself have held much interest for nonmusical Charlestonians, but Mr. Redden presented it in the Memminger Auditorium, a building nearly destroyed by Hurricane Hugo in 1989 and reopened for the occasion. All of Charleston wanted to get in, and musical and municipal concerns tumbled together to create an event far larger than the sum of its parts. It was a delight.</p>
        <p>Charleston, of course, is not New York in its diversity and its distractions. Nor, even, is London. And the Lincoln Center Festival, multidisciplinary as it is, cannot be all things to the music world.</p>
        <p>''I think aspects of the festival have caught the imagination of the city in certain ways,'' Mr. Redden said. ''It hasn't happened to the entire city, and it can't.'' Mr. Redden plans to offer music of Mr. Goebbels at Lincoln Center next summer, though nothing that would require the huge forces of ''Surrogate Cities.''</p>
        <p>The Philharmonic has announced that it will not take part in the festival next year. Might there at some point be room alongside the Lincoln Center Festival for a separate summer venture by the Philharmonic?</p>
        <p>It may be more edifying to contemplate the possibilities for different kinds of collaboration between the Lincoln Center Festival and the orchestra. And that seems to be a direction in which Zarin Mehta, the orchestra's new executive director, is inclined to move.</p>
        <p>''It's a little unclear to me, after talking to the architects, how the armory would work,'' Mr. Mehta said. ''Some people say the capacity could be 4,000 to 5,000, and the architects say 2,700 to 2,800. Well, if it's 2,800, indoors, why are we moving from Avery Fisher Hall?''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Mehta sees exciting possibilities for various kinds of activities there, not just in the summer but year-round; not just for the Philharmonic but in collaboration with other constituents of Lincoln Center or even Carnegie Hall, which is also under new leadership, in Franz Xaver Ohnesorg.</p>
        <p>What might come of all these new personalities and ideas in combination and conflict? And how will the Mostly Mozart Festival, which is run by Lincoln Center in the Philharmonic's hall and has recently regained some of its original Promsian spirit, fit in? What is needed is some amalgam to engage the hearts and minds of New Yorkers beyond the music ghetto and beyond the culture crowd. It won't be the Proms, nor should it be. For them, there will always be an England.</p>
        <p>MUSIC  Correction:  September 24, 2000, Sunday  A picture caption on Page 37 of Arts &amp; Leisure today about a recital planned on Tuesday by the violinist Viviane Hagner misidentifies her musical mentor. He is Pinchas Zuk erman, not Itzhak Perlman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 24, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Page 37 of Arts &amp; Leisure today about a recital planned on Tuesday by the violinist Viviane Hagner misidentifies her musical mentor. He is Pinchas Zuk erman, not Itzhak Perlman.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
