<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Indexes Fall, Some Musings on the Downside</title>
    <meta content="24PORT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/business/24PORT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PORTFOLIOS, ETC."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Portfolios Etc</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E1D71E3BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Indexes Fall, Some Musings on the Downside</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jonathan Fuerbringer Portfolios etc column on speculates about whether downturn in all three major stock indexes is indication that baby boomers, as they retire, are moving money from stocks to bonds; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS the last week of the third quarter begins, the three major stock indexes are down for the year. And if they finish the quarter this way, it will be the first time since 1990 that all three have been down at this time of the year. So let's think some bearish thoughts.</p>
        <p>One of the threats to the stock market is the retirement of the baby boomers. As they leave the work force, will they also choose less risk, moving money from stocks into bonds?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS the last week of the third quarter begins, the three major stock indexes are down for the year. And if they finish the quarter this way, it will be the first time since 1990 that all three have been down at this time of the year. So let's think some bearish thoughts.</p>
        <p>One of the threats to the stock market is the retirement of the baby boomers. As they leave the work force, will they also choose less risk, moving money from stocks into bonds?</p>
        <p>Paddy Jilek, the director of United States economics at Credit Suisse First Boston, thinks so.</p>
        <p>He acknowledges that the life-expectancy data shows that people who are retiring at 65 can now expect to live to 75 or 80. That makes it difficult to say when retirees' investment horizons will shorten enough to make them demand investments that are less risky than stocks. Still, he said, ''eventually the baby boomers will become risk averse like every retiree, and that means, other things being equal, the stock market could struggle over a 10-year period.''</p>
        <p>For the first baby boomers, the age of 65 doesn't come for 10 years. So what's the worry? Mr. Jilek thinks that the previous generation, which is reaching 65 now, is ready to begin making the portfolio shift to less risky assets like bonds. And he argues that this group, which dates from 1935 -- 10 years before the beginning of the baby boom generation -- was the pace setter at two other crucial points for markets.</p>
        <p>One was the surge in home buying that he believes reached its inflection point around 1965, while many baby boomers were still in grade school. Before then, housing prices had been falling, relative to the Consumer Price Index. Afterward, housing prices began to rise in real terms.</p>
        <p>The second key point was at the beginning of the 1980's. That, Mr. Jilek argued, was when this older group began the accumulation of financial assets to help pay for college educations for their children and eventual retirement for themselves.</p>
        <p>If this group is leading the way again, investors may have more to worry about now than they are aware of. ''A sprinkle now, a drizzle soon, and a torrent in 15 year's time,'' Mr. Jilek wrote in a recent report on this issue. ''It's the sprinkle that marks the inflection point relative to asset prices.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jilek thinks that there is another threat to the stock market -- one that means it may not be able to match the wonderful returns of the last half of the 1990's. And if it coincides with the shift of risk preference by those born in 1935 who are now retiring, it could aggravate the portfolio shift away from equities, putting downward pressure on stocks.</p>
        <p>That threat, he says, is from abroad.</p>
        <p>In his report, Mr. Jilek argued that foreign demand for American stocks played a crucial role in the second half of the 1990's -- and that a switch in sentiment could hurt. In 1999, according to Federal Reserve data, foreign investment funds bought a net $98.1 billion of American stocks. And that number has taken off this year, despite the poor performance of the major stock indexes. Net purchases surged to $176.4 billion in the first half.</p>
        <p>American stock has also been gobbled up in the form of foreign acquisitions of United States companies. There were about $153 billion in cross-border deals in 1999, almost double the $78 billion in 1998.</p>
        <p>So with the stock market in a position it has not seen for a decade, think of influences that go beyond corporate earnings, whose growth appears to be slowing, and whether the Federal Reserve is finished raising interest rates for this cycle.</p>
        <p>Even if it is not a factor tomorrow, Mr. Jilek said, it would be wise to be a little more cautious about the potential for stocks in the years ahead. ''I think it is an issue you really need to keep in mind,'' he added. ''It's there all the time and can be a pretty powerful force.''</p>
        <p>PORTFOLIOS, ETC.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
