<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro-North Adds More Service</title>
    <meta content="24TRAI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metro-North Commuter Railroad Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herszenhorn, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E6DD133BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro-North Adds More Service</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID HERSZENHORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herszenhorn, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Metro-North Commuter Railroad, responding to increased ridership, plans to add more than dozen trains between Connecticut and New York; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN one of its largest service expansions in recent history, the Metro-North Commuter Railroad's new fall schedule will add more than a dozen trains between Connecticut and New York in response to increased ridership throughout the New Haven line.</p>
        <p>Metro-North officials said overall ridership has risen 4.6 percent and on weekends 3.1 percent from comparable periods last year. Officials estimated that 55,000 people use the trains each weekday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN one of its largest service expansions in recent history, the Metro-North Commuter Railroad's new fall schedule will add more than a dozen trains between Connecticut and New York in response to increased ridership throughout the New Haven line.</p>
        <p>Metro-North officials said overall ridership has risen 4.6 percent and on weekends 3.1 percent from comparable periods last year. Officials estimated that 55,000 people use the trains each weekday.</p>
        <p>The railroad will add one morning rush-hour express train from New Haven to New York, three evening rush-hour express departures from Grand Central Terminal, two evening rush-hour trains from Stamford to New York and 10 new trains between Stamford and New York on Saturdays.</p>
        <p>The increased Saturday service with four new departures from Stamford to New York and six new departures from New York to Stamford will create half-hourly service in both directions throughout most of the day. The service changes will take effect on Oct. 29.</p>
        <p>The new morning express train will depart New Haven at 6:44, leave Stamford at 7:30 and arrive in Grand Central at 8:18. The new departure makes a total of nine express or semi-express trains arriving in New York from Stamford between 8 and 9 a.m. The new evening express departures from Grand Central will be at 4:41, 5:18 and 6:58. The new evening express departures from Stamford will be at 4:20 and 4:46.</p>
        <p>Officials said they hoped the added weekday express service in both directions would help alleviate some of the traffic on Interstate 95, particularly among intrastate commuters -- those traveling within Connecticut or Westchester. Some passengers traveling to Greenwich from stations farther east in Connecticut may save as much as 12 minutes in travel time, railroad officials said. Passengers headed to Westchester or New York City from Stamford could save up to 11 minutes on the new express trains.</p>
        <p>But in some cases, the speedier trip will come with an inconvenience: the need to switch trains in Stamford. And headed back east in the evenings, some passengers boarding in Greenwich or in Westchester may actually have slightly longer rides in addition to the transfer in Stamford.</p>
        <p>In addition to the added service, some existing routes will be changed in response to passenger requests. These include the addition of a stop at Fordham in the Bronx, on the 4:52 p.m. and 5:53 p.m. trains from New Haven and the extension of the 7:41 a.m. train from Grand Central to Bridgeport, to include stops in Stratford, Milford and New Haven. This train will leave New York at 7:34 a.m.</p>
        <p>The service additions were made possible, and to some extent necessary, by several developments, including the construction of a 950-car parking lot at the Bridgeport station and the completion of a new platform in the Stamford station. Also, the expansion of Amtrak's high-speed Acela service will require departure times of nearly all trains on the New Haven line to shift slightly on the fall schedule.</p>
        <p>''We are providing better and more service to a growing market,'' said Howard Permut, Metro-North's vice president for planning and development. ''With respect to the intrastate service, we are providing much better service for people who live on the east end who are working in Stamford and to a little bit lesser extent in Greenwich.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
