<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POSTINGS: Community Board Opposes Adding to Height; A Plan to Renovate an East Side Landmark</title>
    <meta content="24APOS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233183"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lowe House (Nyc)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Landmarks Preservation Commission (NYC)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD9103BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="490" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POSTINGS: Community Board Opposes Adding to Height; A Plan to Renovate an East Side Landmark</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Community Board 8 votes against recommending major parts of plan by new owner, Spence School, to renovate 22-bedroom Lowe House on East 93d Street to New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission; drawing; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the last mansions built in Manhattan -- the 22-bedroom Loew House at 56 East 93rd Street, constructed in 1932 -- would receive an expanded fifth floor, a new sixth floor and a below-ground gymnasium under a renovation plan proposed by its new owner, the Spence School.</p>
        <p>But not without opposition from Community Board 8, which voted Wednesday against recommending major parts of the plan to the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission. The board's vote is not binding.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the last mansions built in Manhattan -- the 22-bedroom Loew House at 56 East 93rd Street, constructed in 1932 -- would receive an expanded fifth floor, a new sixth floor and a below-ground gymnasium under a renovation plan proposed by its new owner, the Spence School.</p>
        <p>But not without opposition from Community Board 8, which voted Wednesday against recommending major parts of the plan to the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission. The board's vote is not binding.</p>
        <p>The Spence School, whose present building at 22 East 91st Street serves 600 girls in kindergarten through high school, bought the mansion for $15.9 million in May 1999 with the intention of creating a new site for classes up to the fourth grade. The mansion, once owned by the showman Billy Rose, was purchased from the Smithers Alcoholism Treatment and Training Center of Roosevelt Hospital.</p>
        <p>With its arched windows, scooped facade and slate mansard roof, the landmarked 24,000-square-foot building is a combination of the Regency and Adamesque styles that characterized English architecture between 1760 and 1810. The Spence School proposal would add 12,000 square feet to the building, half of that below ground.</p>
        <p>''It's four and a half stories now,'' said Samuel G. White of Buttrick White &amp; Burtis, the architectural firm that designed the renovation. ''We're proposing to make it five and a half stories by building out the fifth floor and adding a partial sixth floor.''</p>
        <p>The fifth floor would contain homerooms and the sixth floor would be a science laboratory. ''To keep the rooftop addition out of the sightline, we are setting the enlarged fifth floor and the sixth-floor penthouse back from the property line,'' Mr. White said.</p>
        <p>The plan also calls for excavating 21 feet below grade to create a 47-by-78-foot gymnasium. Construction would take about 18 months.</p>
        <p>Arlene Gibson, the head of school, said the renovation could cost $24 million. ''We don't want to change the character of the building,'' Ms. Gibson said. ''I think we're going to breathe new life into it.''</p>
        <p>Community Board 8, however, was not convinced. Its chairman, M. Barry Schneider, said the board particularly opposed raising the roof. ''Half the plan is below grade and not visible, and that passed,'' Mr. Schneider said. ''But we rejected the in-fill on the fifth floor and the additional sixth floor.'' The plan is scheduled to go before the Landmarks Preservation Commission on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
