<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Listeners Help Keep Public Radio Alive</title>
    <meta content="24RADI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233119"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Public Radio</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kolb, Elzy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE6DF133BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Listeners Help Keep Public Radio Alive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELZY KOLB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kolb, Elzy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on support from universities and listeners that is keeping public radio stations on Long Island thriving (Special Issue: Entertainment) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHATEVER the vagaries of Congressional financing, public radio stations on Long Island are thriving, thanks to support from universities and listeners attracted to their niche programming.</p>
        <p>''Things are going pretty good these days,'' said Wallace Smith, general manager of WPBX-FM, set on the Southampton College campus of Long Island University. ''Two or three years ago, this was the least developed station in the market. Since then, the university has made a significant financial investment in the station. The university president and the chairman of the board want the station to compete in the public radio market. It's a major public service for Long Island, and it's major public relations for the university.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHATEVER the vagaries of Congressional financing, public radio stations on Long Island are thriving, thanks to support from universities and listeners attracted to their niche programming.</p>
        <p>''Things are going pretty good these days,'' said Wallace Smith, general manager of WPBX-FM, set on the Southampton College campus of Long Island University. ''Two or three years ago, this was the least developed station in the market. Since then, the university has made a significant financial investment in the station. The university president and the chairman of the board want the station to compete in the public radio market. It's a major public service for Long Island, and it's major public relations for the university.''</p>
        <p>Listener support for WPBX, whose programming consists of jazz and public-radio news programs, has increased in recent years, so the station does fewer days of on-air fund-raising. ''Subscribers have gone up significantly in two or three years,'' Mr. Smith said. ''We used to do three long beg-athons annually. This year, we have plans for six drives, of four days each.''</p>
        <p>So far, only 6 to 8 percent of the station's revenue comes from underwriting from foundations and local businesses, but Mr. Smith expects that to change. ''We plan to aggressively pursue underwriting. I see this as a major growth area.''</p>
        <p>WCWP-FM, based on the C. W. Post campus of L.I.U., also receives substantial university support. The station simulcasts WPBX's programming, except from 7 p.m. to 3 a.m., when locally originated programming airs. Much of what is played in this time slot is produced by students. The mixed format includes alternative, heavy metal, hip-hop, blues, ethnic and gospel music. ''The heavy metal program, in particular, has a very, very loyal following,'' said the station director, Judy Kramer. ''The station offers artists and genres not heard very often on commercial radio. I view college radio as kind of a farm system; you learn about music and develop an appreciation for artists from college radio. College radio launches a lot of artists' careers, too.''</p>
        <p>The station has a continuing relationship with one foundation, but there are no plans to press for more.</p>
        <p>''We don't have the infrastructure to try for more local underwriting,'' Ms. Kramer said. ''Since we're part of the L.I.U. network, additional underwriting would have to be for the network as a whole.''</p>
        <p>Bruce Avery, general manager of Hofstra University's WRHU-FM, said: ''If you produce a good product, listeners will find you through word of mouth. The audience is very loyal, very supportive. We build donations one listener at a time. If you do a good job, they're as appreciative, if they can be'' at fund-raising time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Avery described the station as having ''an educational mission. The station's priorities are helping students grow, and serving the community audience.''</p>
        <p>WRHU, which broadcasts a mixed format that includes jazz, classical, hip-hop and ethnic music, is staffed mainly by volunteers. Of the approximately 150 volunteers, more than two-thirds are students. Mr. Avery would like to explore new ways to generate revenue, such as Webcasting, producing programs locally for syndication, sponsorships and licensing.</p>
        <p>For WUSB-FM, part of the State University of New York at Stony Brook, ''Pressure to raise money doesn't exist,'' said Norm Prusslin, general manager and director of student media.</p>
        <p>A part-time consulting engineer is the station's only paid employee. The rest of the staff is made up of volunteers, some of whom are there as part of training programs or academic internships.</p>
        <p>''Our operational costs are budgeted from year to year, and the university or fund-raising covers our expenses,'' Mr. Prusslin said. WUSB features a varied format, with everything from rock to polka to science fiction programming.</p>
        <p>During fund-raising, the station tries to stick to the regular schedule, but to create special programs within that framework. For example, ''The special programming might consist of listener favorites, or long sets by a single artist, like the Grateful Dead, Tom Waits or Frank Zappa,'' Mr. Prusslin said. ''The mission behind it is not to hit people over the head, it is to have fun. This is what we have to do to reach our goals.''</p>
        <p>While the station receives some underwriting from local businesses, on-air mention is limited to 10 seconds.</p>
        <p>''Our listeners feel underwriting messages sound too much like commercials, so we only give the phone number and a generic description,'' Mr. Prusslin said. ''There's no call to action, no qualitative announcement.''</p>
        <p>WRLI-FM differs from the other Long Island stations in that it is not associated with a university; it is part of the Connecticut Public Broadcasting system. Its format is classical music, news and entertainment programs like ''Car Talk'' and ''The Faith Middleton Show.''</p>
        <p>John Berky, vice president and director of radio for Connecticut Public Broadcasting said: ''Radio has to become more formatted to succeed. A mixed format makes it tough for people to find what they want. Most people listen to three or four stations, the ones they preset in their cars. They want to hear what they expect when they press that button. If they don't, you don't rate a button.''</p>
        <p>Members provide about 65 percent of WRLI's money. ''If you give the listeners what they want, they'll support you,'' Mr. Berky said. However, ''Whenever Congress gets angry, our funding from members goes up. The listeners respond and come to our rescue.'' Underwriting accounts for about 25 percent of WRLI's annual budget.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
