<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Move Over, Shecky</title>
    <meta content="24CASI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlantic County (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Trump Taj Mahal Casino Resort</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spears, Britney</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFD9103BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1203" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Move Over, Shecky</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTIC CITY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on movement in Atlantic City, NJ, to develop new entertainment markets and target younger crowds; recent Britney Spears concert at Trump Taj Mahal attracted much younger crowd but casino executives admit taking loss; photos (Special Issue: Entertainment) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A WELL-MUSCLED young man, carried by guide wires, does five flips 10 feet up in the air before landing on the stage as fireworks spurt off around him. Stage left and right at the Trump Taj Mahal' s Mark Etess Arena, hard-bodied dancers of both sexes slither to the center in orange pod suits, reminiscent of characters in alien movies.</p>
        <p>While firework flames start shooting Tiki-like at each side of the stage, high atop a staircase above the squirming orange pod dancers rises a young woman in a cleavage-exposing black top and flowing black pants with yellow flames at the ankle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A WELL-MUSCLED young man, carried by guide wires, does five flips 10 feet up in the air before landing on the stage as fireworks spurt off around him. Stage left and right at the Trump Taj Mahal' s Mark Etess Arena, hard-bodied dancers of both sexes slither to the center in orange pod suits, reminiscent of characters in alien movies.</p>
        <p>While firework flames start shooting Tiki-like at each side of the stage, high atop a staircase above the squirming orange pod dancers rises a young woman in a cleavage-exposing black top and flowing black pants with yellow flames at the ankle.</p>
        <p>Drumbeats pulsate from 25-foot-high curved speakers astride the stage, as the young woman, the pop star Britney Spears, breathily intones her hit song, ''Oops, I Did It Again.''</p>
        <p>This is clearly not your grandfather's let's-go-see-Jerry-Vale casino town anymore.</p>
        <p>While there is a certain incongruity in the fact that half the members of a casino-show audience will not be old enough to bet legally until the 2010's, it is clear that Ms. Spears' first visit to Atlantic City is part of a trend away from the diet of tried-and-true entertainment at the Shore resort.</p>
        <p>This fall, for instance, the casinos will present Luciano Pavarotti and Gladys Knight; LeAnn Rimes, the country teen star, and Alice Cooper, the hard rocker; the singer Ani DiFranco and the folkies Leo Kottke and Tuck and Patti.</p>
        <p>Sure, there are still traditional casino acts like Tom Jones and Paul Anka and Don Rickles and Kenny Rogers. But casino entertaiment chiefs are beginning to look to folk, rock and country to provide a wider swath of options for casinogoers.</p>
        <p>The movement is underway all over town to develop new markets and target slightly younger demographics, said Bob Chambers, entertainment director at the Sands Hotel-Casino, which will have Ms. DiFranco and the country singer Kathy Mattea in its fall showroom line-up. ''It probably started two or three years ago when the Trump Marina embarked on a younger entertainment program,'' Mr. Chambers said. ''Everyone laughed at it, but they carved out a niche. Now everyone wants at least some small part of it.''</p>
        <p>Steve Gietka was the entertainment coordinator at the Trump Marina who brought in 70's and 80's rockers like Foreigner, Steppenwolf and Ted Nugent after a deal to create a Hard Rock Casino fell through. Now Mr. Gietka also programs the larger 5,000-seat Etess Arena at the Taj Mahal, where Ms. Spears appeared.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gietka said that though the Taj Mahal took a loss on the Spears concert, the idea was to show that the casino was the place the big act plays.</p>
        <p>''She's the hottest star of the moment,'' said Mr. Gietka. ''All the big players want tickets for their kids.  They may not be able to come to the casino that night because they are with their kids, but we're betting that they remember that we allowed them to do something nice for their children.''</p>
        <p>Michelle Robb, the entertainment director at the Atlantic City Hilton, said her hotel casino had ceded that far younger part of the market to Mr. Gietka.</p>
        <p>''We used to have more production shows that catered to the bus-down market,'' said Ms. Robb. ''Then we decided to go younger and had acts like Andrew Dice Clay and Toto, but it didn't work out well for us.''</p>
        <p>''I think your property has to have that feel for it to work,'' she said. ''Go to the Marina and you will hear Van Halen over the speakers in the lobbies. We can't do that. Our demographic is older and if you start introducing Van Halen, you drive away your base.''</p>
        <p>Still, Ms. Robb is tweaking that demographic a bit.  Hall and Oates, the Philadelphia-native rockers, do well at the Hilton, and Judy Collins will be playing there this fall. The country star Trisha Yearwood sold out the 1,400-seat showroom at the Hilton this summer.</p>
        <p>''We thought that Trisha and Judy Collins would fit in well with both the older group and baby boomers,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Rick Gallagher, who programs entertainment at the Hilton's sister hotel casino up the Boardwalk, Caesars Atlantic City (they are both owned by the Park Place Entertainment), is an advocate of a more varied entertainment schedule. For the older audience, he has Mr. Rickles, Tony Bennett and Bill Cosby this fall; for boomers, he is bringing in the Temptations and Isaac Hayes, and for the somewhat younger set, there are Howie Mandel and Ms. Rimes.</p>
        <p>''Country music has moved toward the center of the appeal line,'' said Mr. Gallagher. ''Travis Tritt and the Dixie Chicks sound like rock. And when I listen to LeAnn Rimes, she certainly sounds like pop. They have moved away from that twangy sound and the costuming, the presentation and the videos now have some sex appeal. So it is more appropriate for the casinos than it used to be.''</p>
        <p>Caesars is also bucking a trend away from comedy headliners at the casinos. Ms. Robb, at the Hilton, said that it was harder to book comics these days. ''Either they don't need the work or they are too young for the casino crowd,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But at Caesars, where Mr. Mandel, Mr. Cosby and Mr. Rickles are scheduled this fall, Mr. Gallagher said:</p>
        <p>''We have more entertainment than the other casinos, so naturally we want to vary it,'' said Mr. Gallagher. Caesars has six headline acts for the fall, while most other casinos have three or four. Bally's has but one scheduled, Natalie Cole, going with its Legends in Concert lookalike stage show most of the fall.</p>
        <p>Most of the Atlantic City casino hotels book entertainment only on weekends when they would otherwise not draw customers, not on a holiday or Miss America weekend or when there is a big boxing card or large convention. One mini-trend is to have a few headline acts during midweek. Susan Anton, for instance, will play the week following Thanksgiving at the Atlantic City Hilton.</p>
        <p>''Debbie Reynolds sold well during the week for us in July, so we will try it here and there,'' said Ms. Robb.</p>
        <p>Atlantic City casinos are also likely to offer more variety in a shorter time than in Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>''There are few bidding wars,'' said Bill Gaydos, the director of entertainment and special events at the Tropicana Casino-Hotel. ''We all have to have different people, since we get a lot of repeat business.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gallagher, from Caesar's, concurred: ''In Vegas, since customers don't come in for the day, acts can repeat and repeat. We're finally getting more sophisticated about entertainment here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
