<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Bologna, A Grand Plaza Defines the City</title>
    <meta content="BOLOGN$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233059"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bologna (Italy)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Povoledo, Elisabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Bologna</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DC173BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Bologna, A Grand Plaza Defines the City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETTA POVOLEDO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Povoledo, Elisabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elisabetta Povoledo travel article on Bologna, Italy; photos; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FEW Italian cities still live in their main squares as intensely as Bologna does. Since the 13th century, the Piazza Maggiore has served as the city's social, administrative, political and commercial heart. Milestone events that have marked Bologna's history -- from the celebrations for the coronation of Charles V as Holy Roman Emperor in 1530, to the city's collective rage after a bomb killed 85 people at the train station in 1980 -- have been commemorated there.</p>
        <p>From morning to night, the sounds of Bologna overlap and merge in the square. Mornings bring the soft prayers of the devout in the Basilica of San Petronio at early Mass, the clamor of the nearby food market and the shuffle of briefcase-carrying civil servants on their way to the Palazzo d'Accursio, the original part of Bologna's immense city hall, the Palazzo Communale.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FEW Italian cities still live in their main squares as intensely as Bologna does. Since the 13th century, the Piazza Maggiore has served as the city's social, administrative, political and commercial heart. Milestone events that have marked Bologna's history -- from the celebrations for the coronation of Charles V as Holy Roman Emperor in 1530, to the city's collective rage after a bomb killed 85 people at the train station in 1980 -- have been commemorated there.</p>
        <p>From morning to night, the sounds of Bologna overlap and merge in the square. Mornings bring the soft prayers of the devout in the Basilica of San Petronio at early Mass, the clamor of the nearby food market and the shuffle of briefcase-carrying civil servants on their way to the Palazzo d'Accursio, the original part of Bologna's immense city hall, the Palazzo Communale.</p>
        <p>As the day progresses, the shouts of schoolchildren visiting the Municipal Collections of Art or the Morandi Museum become more boisterous, and eventually the piazza becomes an after-school playground where passers-by duck flying soccer balls.</p>
        <p>Around sunset, the square fills with clusters of older Bolognesi -- mostly men -- animatedly discussing the latest soccer match, and cafe-lounging people-watchers savoring aperitifs at tables in front of the Palazzo del Podesta. At night, students from Bologna's renowned university -- dating back to the 11th century, it is one of the oldest in the Western world -- gather for concerts, street performances or just hanging out.</p>
        <p>The square was built by the commune, or town council, so that Bologna's citizens -- at the time 50,000, more than Rome, Paris or London -- had a place to meet. Over the centuries, the Piazza Maggiore has reflected the changing city. Today, another transformation is under way, sparked by Bologna's selection as one of nine European Capitals of Culture for the year 2000. The designation has enriched the city's cultural offerings, with dozens of important exhibitions, hundreds of concerts, theater and ballet performances, as well as special tourist itineraries throughout the year.</p>
        <p>Bologna has many nicknames. It is known as la grassa (the fat), for its love of food and physical pleasures. It is known as la rossa (the red), not because of its political inclinations (from the end of World War II until last year it was governed by Communist or post-Communist administrations), but because of the distinctive russet red brick that has shaped much of its architecture. And it is known as la dotta (the learned), because of its university.</p>
        <p>Although it has the lowest birth rate in Italy, Bologna is a city of young people. The presence of the students is felt everywhere, from the profusion of funky clubs and well-stocked bookstores, to the enormous outdoor market selling used just-about-everything that takes over the central Via dell'Indipendenza every Friday and Saturday.</p>
        <p>Bologna takes its role as a center of education seriously. Of the many projects associated with Bologna 2000, one in particular is intended to encourage the Bolognesi to remain dotti, and that is the transformation of the so-called Ex Sala Borsa, or Former Stock Exchange, into Italy's largest multimedia library.</p>
        <p>Part of Pallazzo d'Accursio, the Stock Exchange, just off the square, was built in the late 19th century, when the city administration decided it would be more dignified for farmers to do their haggling inside rather than on the streets. The farmers snubbed the offer (they were too attached to their beloved piazza) and after various incarnations, the building has been restored.</p>
        <p>The enormous central hall has retained its 19th-century look, ringed by arcades on three levels, but early next year it will be fitted with 900 work stations and some 300 computer terminals.</p>
        <p>The restoration brought to light Bologna's distant past. Traces of Etruscan wells and of the Roman forum and basilica were found, leading archaeologists to conclude that this spot was once the heart of the ancient city. The remains of these foundations are visible through the glass floor in the main hall of the Stock Exchange, and will be accessible for tours when the library opens in January.</p>
        <p>The building just reopened this month with an exhibition on Charles M. Schulz and ''Peanuts'' (Italians love Snoopy).</p>
        <p>If you ask a Bolognese to meet you somewhere downtown, he is likely to  suggest the enormous 16th-century fountain of Neptune, just outside the front door of the Sala Borsa. Certainly, the gigantic bronze sculpture of the god of the sea, by the Flemish sculptor Giambologna (the fountain itself was designed by Tommaso Laureti) is hard to miss and there are steps to sit on and people to watch should your date be late.</p>
        <p>The statue is a symbol of the city, as are two imposing early 12th-century towers in the nearby Piazza di Porta Ravegnana, the Garisenda and Asinelli. These Due Torri lean at an ominous, Pisa-like angle, but unlike the one in Pisa, their stability does not seem in question.</p>
        <p>Eight hundred years ago, there were more than 100 such towers peppering the Bologna skyline, like so many clunky red-brick reeds growing skyward. A few others still exist, scattered throughout the center, but only Asinelli, at 318 feet the tallest remaining one, can be climbed -- on rickety, well-worn wooden steps --  for a spectacular view of the city.</p>
        <p>Many of the buildings of the Piazza Maggiore look medieval, with pointed gothic arches and crenelated parapets. How odd, then, that one of the most authentic medieval buildings -- the 13th-century Palazzo di Re Enzo -- was essentially reconstructed in the early 20th century. Its transformation into a fairy tale castle was based on turn-of-the-century notions about the Middle Ages.</p>
        <p>Attached to it is the Palazzo del Podesta, a 15th-century reconstruction of the 13th-century original. After a lengthy restoration, its high Renaissance arches again provide a fitting backdrop for the piazza's better cafes.</p>
        <p>Along with the Palazzo di Re Enzo, also restored for Bologna 2000, it is used for exhibitions, conferences and congresses (Bologna is an important city for trade fairs -- showcasing everything from light gardening tools to antiterrorism devices).</p>
        <p>In the Middle Ages, security was handled differently, as a look at the impenetrably fortresslike Palazzo d'Accursio, will attest. One of the largest building complexes in Italy -- almost a small city within the city -- it has been since the 13th century a seat of power, both secular and papal.</p>
        <p>Today, the municipal government is gradually moving out of the palazzo, making room for new exhibition halls and expanded art galleries. The restored Sala d'Ercole -- so called for a gigantic statue of Hercules by Alfonso Lombardi (1519) that dominates the room -- is used for photography exhibitions and this month and next, a show on Pina Bausch, the contemporary German choreographer, by Francesco Carbone, is expected to draw large crowds.</p>
        <p>The impressive municipal art collections on the second floor of Palazzo d'Accursio have been reorganized and restored, and the last rooms will open by the end of the year. In June 1999, the Rusconi rooms -- named for the Marchesi Rusconi family, donors of the art displayed there -- were opened after a 10-year restoration.</p>
        <p>Paintings, sculptures and furniture are arranged to suggest an 18th-century private mansion, and the apartment includes a charming room entirely frescoed to give the illusion of standing in an outdoor garden. Bird songs from the piazza complete the fantasy.</p>
        <p>Since 1993, the palazzo has also housed works by Giorgio Morandi, one of Italy's modern masters.</p>
        <p>On the Piazza Maggiore, the comune built an immense gothic basilica to commemorate Bologna's independence and dedicated it to San Petronio, a fifth-century bishop of Bologna who is the city's patron saint. Statues of the Virgin Mary and child and of two saints, and pilasters with scenes from the Old and New Testaments, sculptured by Jacopo della Quercia, decorate the main portal.</p>
        <p>It is easy to see why the young Michelangelo was impressed by the portal's dramatic intensity and technical virtuosity. The 15th-century masterpiece lightens San Petronio's massive facade, which was left unfinished -- a foretaste of heaven perhaps.</p>
        <p>Already one of the largest churches in the world, legend has it that San Petronio was to be even bigger than St Peter's. But the city's ambitious plans were thwarted by Pope Pius IV, who in 1562 ordered the building of the Palazzo Archiginnasio to the east of the basilica, effectively blocking further development.</p>
        <p>The interior walls of the Archiginnasio, once the principal seat of the university, are entirely covered with the coats of arms of cardinal legates,  rectors, priors and students, artfully arranged in frescoed commemorative memorials. The theater where doctors held anatomy lessons (only in winter because in summer the corpses would smell), was bombed during World War II, but faithfully reconstructed with as many original pieces as were salvageable.</p>
        <p>Covering the intricately carved wood ceiling are astrological figures; in the 16th century, doctors used astrological calendars to decide which days were best for operating. Happily for the advancement of science, the medical school in Bologna was the first to question this widely held practice.</p>
        <p>For a city that isn't particularly rainy, Bologna is well endowed with arcades. There are an astonishing 23.6 miles of these portici, tall passageways that originated in the Middle Ages as do-it-yourself home-expansion projects to house students pouring into the city. The longest is the Portico di San Luca, whose 666 arches extend nearly two and a half miles .</p>
        <p>THE portico that flanks the Archiginnasio is a mere 456 feet long, so the walk isn't strenuous. Still, it is nice to know that at its end, one can stop at Zanarini, a fashionable bar that has not renounced its 1950's feel. Bustling at the hour of the aperitif, a Bolognese tradition, it offers snacks of quail eggs, cheese puffs and canapes with spinach and shrimp and sun-dried tomatoes, nearly a meal in themselves.</p>
        <p>Attached to the Archiginnasio is a former Renaissance hospital, about the last place one would expect to find a 3,300-year-old Egyptian bas relief. But Bologna's exceptional archaeological museum, housed in the Ospedale Santa Maria della Morte, has the largest collection of Egyptian art in Italy after Turin.</p>
        <p>The original 19th-century wood-and-glass display cabinets give you the feeling that Howard Carter could saunter through the door at any minute bearing a statuette from Tutankhamen's tomb. Beginning in October, the museum will put on an important Bologna 2000 exhibition, ''Etruscan Princes Between the Mediterranean and Europe,'' including reconstructions of life-size monuments, palaces and tombs dating between the late eighth and early sixth centuries B.C. and 600-odd artifacts.</p>
        <p>They don't call Bologna la grassa for nothing. One of its principal attractions is food, and the city is renowned for delicate meat-filled tortellini; plumper, ricotta-filled tortelloni; passatelli (pasta made with bread crumbs, eggs and Parmesan); and mortadella, the scrumptious sausage that bears little resemblance to American baloney.</p>
        <p>Behind the 16th-century Palazzo dei Banchi, dominating the eastern end of the Piazza Maggiore, is a picturesque cluster of narrow streets, packed with opulent small shops bursting with a fantastic variety of fruits, vegetables, cheeses and cured meats. You may have to fight for walking space, but a stroll through the market's fresh produce is key to understanding why the Bolognesi eat so well.</p>
        <p>Tucked inside the market -- and eerily silent compared with the cacophony outside -- is the recently restored church of Santa Maria della Vita. In a dimly lighted chapel on the right is one of Bologna's greatest art works, a 15th-century life-size terra-cotta group sculpture, ''Lamentation Over the Dead Christ,'' by Niccolo dell'Arca (Nicholas of the Tomb), -- one of the most touching and horrifying depictions of raw grief imaginable.</p>
        <p>The artist was known by his somber name because of his other masterpiece: the upper sections of the tomb of St. Dominic, who is buried in a church dedicated to him just a few blocks south of Piazza Maggiore. Three youthful works by Michelangelo are also part of the monument.</p>
        <p>Another Michelangelo work, a bronze sculpture of Pope Julius II, had a short life on the facade of San Petronio. After three years there, it was destroyed in 1511, when the pope lost control of Bologna, ousted by the French, who reinstated the Bentivoglio family to power.</p>
        <p>The Piazza Maggiore was a principal stage where that power struggle was acted out, just another chapter in its 800-year history as the city's vital heart.</p>
        <p>A city of culture, history and food</p>
        <p>Tickets and Information</p>
        <p>Bologna is offering a rich cultural agenda this year, with hundreds of exhibitions, performances and conferences. The best place to find up-to-date information on these events is www.bologna2000.it. Tickets and information are also available at the Palazzo del Podesta in Piazza Maggiore.</p>
        <p>Tourist information is available at the tourist office on the ground floor of the Palazzo d'Accursio, Piazza Maggiore 6, (39-051) 246-541, or by calling the Municipal Public Relations number, (39-051) 203-040.</p>
        <p>What to See</p>
        <p>''Etruscan Princes Between the Mediterranean and Europe,'' Museo Civico Archeologico, Via dell'Archiginnasio 2; (39-051) 233-849; Oct. 1 to April 1. Open daily except Monday, 9 a.m. to 7 p.m. Admission, $5.35.</p>
        <p>''Linus Loves Bologna: 50 Years of Peanuts,'' through Nov. 26 at the Former Stock Exchange in the Palazzo d'Accursio, provides an opportunity to check out the building before it reopens fully in January. Information: (39-02) 54913 (Italian only). Hours: 10 a.m. to 10 p.m.; closed Monday. Admission, $2.25.</p>
        <p>Sala d'Ercole, on the second floor of the Palazzo d'Accursio, is the site of ''Pina Bausch: The Dream Is,'' an exhibition of photographs by Francesco Carbone, through Oct. 23. Open Monday, Thursday and Saturday from 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. and till 10 p.m. Tuesday, Friday and Sunday. Closed Monday.</p>
        <p>In the same building are the Municipal Collections of Art, open daily except Monday 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; (39-051) 203-526. Admission $3.55. Upstairs is the Morandi Museum, which will show works by Paul Klee Nov. 25 to Feb. 28. Admission $3.55; (39-051) 203-629.</p>
        <p>The theater in the Archiginnasio can be visited free Monday through Friday, 9 a.m. to 6:45 p.m. and Saturday till 1:45 p.m. Free.</p>
        <p>The Asinelli tower is open daily 9 a..m to 5 p.m. Admission, $2.25.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Ristorante Silverio, 19 Via Mirasole, (39-051) 585-857, with unique variations on traditional cooking in a cozy upscale setting, is well worth the 15-minute walk from Piazza Maggiore. The starters include fresh asparagus tips in a parmesan cream, passatelli (a pasta made of bread crumbs, parmesan cheese and eggs that is a staple Bolognese dish) in a creamy spinach sauce. Second courses include a creative selection of meats or a ricotta and semolina cake seasoned with broccoli, sage and other fresh herbs. A meal for two with wine is about $55, at 2,250 lire to the dollar. Closed Sunday.</p>
        <p>La Pernice e La Gallina, 4 Via dell 'Abbadia, (39-051) 269-922, a 10-minute walk from the piazza, is one of the best of a new crop of restaurants, proposing a nouvelle twist on traditional cuisine along with a varied seafood menu. An unusual dessert is a biscuit filled with rum cream and accompanied by a sauce made from chopped-up cigar leaves.  Dinner for two with wine, from $70. Closed Sunday; open for lunch by request.</p>
        <p>Annamaria, 17A Via Bellearti, (39-051) 266-894, is popular with students and music buffs -- the university and opera house are nearby. Its reputation is based on its homemade pasta, particularly the tagliatelle, tortellini and tortelloni. Meal for two with wine, $55. Closed Monday.</p>
        <p>Rrose Selavy, Via Marsala 3C, (39-051) 271961, just off the Via dell'Indipendenza, is stylishly decorated with leopard skin settees and arty bronze chandeliers. The lunch menu proposes unusual salads for those who wish to take a break from Bologna's heavy cuisine (which the restaurant serves at dinner time). The dessert selection is sinfully long. Lunch for two with wine, $40.</p>
        <p>Lazzarini, 1 Via Clavature, (39-051) 229-798, in the heart of the central market, offers the local take on fast food: stuffed piadine (the pita-like bread of the region), crochette (deep-fried rice or potato croquettes) with vegetables, Gorgonzola or mushrooms, vegetarian strudels and sandwiches. Meal for two with wine, from $13.</p>
        <p>A predinner aperitif is a Bolognese tradition. Two of the more fashionable bars are Zanarini, Loggia del Pavaglione, Piazza Galvani 1, (39-051) 222-717, with its funny 50's decor (closed Monday), and the Caffe Martini, Piazza della Mercanzia 6 (39-051) 226-318, in the shadow of the two towers. A fruity aperitif at either is around $4 at the counter.</p>
        <p>The best ice cream in Bologna, and, some argue, in Italy, can be had at La Sorbetteria, 44 Via Castiglione (south of Piazza di Porta Ravegnana), (39-051) 233-257.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>Grand Hotel Baglioni, 8 Via Indipendenza, (39-051) 225-445, fax (39-051) 232-4840, was built in the 18th century as a seminary and converted into a first-class hotel in 1911. Standard doubles, some of which are decorated in Empire style, are $238 to $302, including breakfast.</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Hotel, 6 Via dell 'Orso, (39-051) 229-393, fax (39-051) 224-602, has been tastefully restored and provides modern comfort at a reasonable price. Doubles, including an impressive breakfast buffet, $98 to $150.</p>
        <p>Hotel Commercianti, 11 Via De' Pignattari, (39-051) 233-052, fax (39-051) 224-733, is next to the Basilica of San Petronio in a building that dates to the 12th century that's been made 21st-century comfortable. There's a memorable breakfast buffet included in the rates, $125 to $222.</p>
        <p>ELISABETTA POVOLEDO</p>
        <p>ELISABETTA POVOLEDO is a researcher in the Rome bureau of The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">ELISABETTA POVOLEDO is a researcher in the Rome bureau of The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
