<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World: Putin and the Press; An Invitation You Can't Refuse: Be on My Team</title>
    <meta content="24BOHL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/weekinreview/24BOHL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233326"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bohlen, Celestine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dorenko, Sergei</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DE1F3BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1252" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World: Putin and the Press; An Invitation You Can't Refuse: Be on My Team</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELESTINE BOHLEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bohlen, Celestine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Russian Pres Vladimir V Putin's dealings with media notes that controversial TV journalist Sergei Dorenko's regular Saturday night program was recently taken off air, on what he is certain were orders from Kremlin; Dorenko photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN Russia, rulers don't just fight to take or keep power. They also fight to make sure they don't have to share it. This was true for the czars, it was true for the Communist Party and, so far, it seems to be true for President Vladimir V. Putin, who came to the Kremlin by way of the K.G.B. and its successor agency, the F.S.B., where he learned to look on people as either  patriots or traitors.</p>
        <p>This trait has been most apparent in his dealings with the media, where Mr. Putin more than his predecessor, Boris N. Yeltsin, seems determined to bring wayward journalists and media barons onto his team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN Russia, rulers don't just fight to take or keep power. They also fight to make sure they don't have to share it. This was true for the czars, it was true for the Communist Party and, so far, it seems to be true for President Vladimir V. Putin, who came to the Kremlin by way of the K.G.B. and its successor agency, the F.S.B., where he learned to look on people as either  patriots or traitors.</p>
        <p>This trait has been most apparent in his dealings with the media, where Mr. Putin more than his predecessor, Boris N. Yeltsin, seems determined to bring wayward journalists and media barons onto his team.</p>
        <p>Sergei Dorenko, arguably Russia's most famous and most controversial television journalist, is no stranger to the power games that pass for politics in Russia. A one-time anchorman and board member at ORT, the country's largest channel, he has been on both sides: a victim when he was summarily tossed off the air two years ago by Yevgeny M. Primakov, who was then prime minister, and a victimizer who has used his prime-time weekly program to mock, condemn, expose and generally excoriate members of the anti-Kremlin opposition (who happen to include Mr. Primakov).</p>
        <p>But since early summer, Mr. Dorenko has put distance between himself and the Putin Kremlin. He criticized the arrest of the media baron Vladimir Gusinsky in June, and in August he broadcast interviews with angry relatives of the sailors who died when the submarine Kursk sank. Two weeks ago, his regular Saturday night program was suddenly yanked from the air, on what he is certain were orders from the Kremlin.</p>
        <p>At a press conference a few days later, Mr. Dorenko gave an account of his firing, and of his dealings with Mr. Putin over the last year, that was extraordinary in its detail. The account was one-sided, to be sure, and the world may never know Mr. Putin's version. But Mr. Dorenko's account was accepted in Russia as entirely believable, which speaks volumes about the skewed relationship between power and the press in Russia today, less than 10 years after Communism's collapse.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dorenko's account almost evokes St. Peter. He was asked three times to prove his loyalty and three times he ducked, saying he is too ''cantankerous'' to be on anyone's team. After that, he got no more chances.</p>
        <p>At the press conference, which was held Sept. 11, Mr. Dorenko first recounted a conversation with Konstantin Ernst, general director of ORT, on the night before the program was canceled.</p>
        <p>''He found me, summoned me and said that my previous program caused strong indignation in the Kremlin and that it threatened the ORT channel,'' Mr. Dorenko said. ''And that I had to be a patriot of the channel and I had to make a program which they would like.'' He said Mr. Ernst suggested a pro-Putin show, rather than repeating his criticism. ''It could even be interesting from a dramatic point of view,'' he recalled Mr. Ernst as saying.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dorenko refused, comparing the strategy to strangling oneself in order to protect oneself from being strangled. The next day, Mr. Dorenko said, Mr. Ernst told him the program would not be broadcast. ''His last words were . . . 'As they say in the American movies: Nothing personal.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dorenko, asked if he thought Mr. Ernst had acted on instructions from the Kremlin, warmed to the theme of how power is exercised in Russia. He went back over his encounters with Mr. Putin, who became president in August after having been  named acting president in January and then winning a March election. ''The first time  Putin invited me to just have a talk with him was in September last year. I said: 'Is it an interview? I am ready' . . . He said: 'No, I wanted only to have a talk.' ''</p>
        <p>The two met a second time that month for an interview, and again on Jan. 15. At that meeting, Acting President Putin told Mr. Dorenko he considered him a member of his team. Mr. Dorenko demurred, noting that team play was not in his nature.</p>
        <p>Then, in June, when Mr. Gusinsky was put in prison for four days, Mr. Dorenko responded with a dramatic appearance on Mr. Gusinsky's NTV, ORT's rival. He warned that the old ghosts of Russia's authoritarian past were being called back to life, revived by secret signals coming from on high.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin, according to Mr. Dorenko, summoned him soon afterward. ''He said: 'Something's wrong? . . . Something is going on, I understood, something is going on with you.' I said: 'Nothing is going on, I am still the same.' He said that he thought that we were people from the same team.''</p>
        <p>''We met one-to-one, it was in the back room, behind his office, we had tea,'' Mr. Dorenko said. '' 'We should not sort out relations like this,' '' Mr. Dorenko recalled Mr. Putin as saying.</p>
        <p>And then, on Aug. 29, after the Kursk sank, Mr. Dorenko was again called to the Kremlin and wound up in Mr. Putin's office.  During this conversation, Mr. Dorenko said, he spoke of his admiration of the president's ability to fit in with different audiences. '' 'But looking at you I see two people,'' he recalled saying. '' 'One of them has a Patek Philippe watch, and the other one has epaulettes of the F.S.B.' He said, 'We have the kind of country where it is always good to have epaulettes.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin urged Mr. Dorenko to stay on at ORT despite recent changes in ownership. Mr. Dorenko, puzzled, asked, ''Am I leaving  or did I tell anybody that I am leaving?'' The president then clarified his point. ''No, to stay and work as a member of the team.''</p>
        <p>I  SAY: 'Vladimir Vladimirovich, I am saying it for the third time . . . I am not a member of the team, no matter how offensive it may sound, of anybody's team. I work for my viewer and for the guy I see in the mirror when I shave and for those who scream at me demanding to free the bathroom when I am shaving. This is all, here is my team, it's a small team, a very compact one.' And he said: 'I see you have not made a decision.' . . .</p>
        <p>''I thought that my arguments were in vain, because he either did not understand or pretended that he didn't. His last words were: 'Think, don't rush.'</p>
        <p>''If you know the bureaucrats' logic in general and bureaucrats' logic in Russia in particular, you have a clear understanding that after the president says, 'Think, don't rush,' no one will dare to make a decision to take off the air or fire me or do something against me until he has at least waved his hand. . . .''</p>
        <p>On Sept. 9, it became clear to Mr. Dorenko, who knows better than most how power works in Russia, that its latest czar had indeed waved his hand. After his program was canceled, Mr. Dorenko desperately tried to reach the president but could not get through, and no one called him back.</p>
        <p>''There was no answer,'' he said. ''Which is why I think that it was a serious answer.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
