<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Advance? No, Thanks, He'll Publish It Himself</title>
    <meta content="24BENN$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/technology/24BENN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaplan, Benjamin R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tabor, Mary B W</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">How to Go to College Almost For Free (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E2D71E3BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1209" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Advance? No, Thanks, He'll Publish It Himself</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARY B.W. TABOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tabor, Mary B W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Benjamin R Kaplan, 23, whose self-published book, How to Go to College Almost for Free: The Secrets of Winning Scholarship Money, has sold 25,000 copies since February and who is starting 25-city book tour; increase in number of self-published books discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BIG publishers dream about first-time authors like Benjamin R. Kaplan.</p>
        <p>Since February, Mr. Kaplan, 23, has sold an impressive 25,000 copies of his book, ''How to Go to College Almost for Free: The Secrets of Winning Scholarship Money.'' He has become a talk-show and bookstore favorite and is starting a 25-city book tour. And he has basically done it all himself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BIG publishers dream about first-time authors like Benjamin R. Kaplan.</p>
        <p>Since February, Mr. Kaplan, 23, has sold an impressive 25,000 copies of his book, ''How to Go to College Almost for Free: The Secrets of Winning Scholarship Money.'' He has become a talk-show and bookstore favorite and is starting a 25-city book tour. And he has basically done it all himself.</p>
        <p>The traditional publishers will have to keep dreaming, at least for now. Despite lucrative offers for book deals, Mr. Kaplan, who received an economics degree from Harvard in 1999, bypassed them last year to start his own company, Waggle Dancer Books, so he can publish more books and expand into audio and video tapes and electronic reports.</p>
        <p>''What I like about self-publishing is that if you succeed, you succeed on your own merits,'' said Mr. Kaplan, who wrote his 316-page book after receiving almost $90,000 in scholarship money. ''If you fail, you fail on your own merits as well.''</p>
        <p>Self-publishing of successful books is nothing new. Many best sellers, like ''The Celestine Prophecy'' and ''The Christmas Box,'' ended up with major publishers but were first published without book deals. But Mr. Kaplan's bold approach demonstrates  what some people in the industry say is a growing challenge to traditional publishing houses.</p>
        <p>Over the summer, Stephen King sidestepped his longtime publisher, Simon &amp; Schuster, and began putting his new book, ''The Plant,'' up for sale on the Internet. New ventures like Versaware, iUniverse.com, eNovel.com and iVillage also draw large numbers of self-publishing writers. And with help from companies like Amazon.com, unknown authors with shoestring budgets can share virtual shelf space with the blockbusters.</p>
        <p>''More and more people are turning to self-publishing,'' said Marilyn Ross, executive director of the Small Publishers Association of North America, which represents 1,300 independent presses, self-publishers and authors.</p>
        <p>Debbie Pressnell, an assistant vice president at the Ingram Book Group, a leading wholesaler, said her company had seen a slight increase in the number of self-published titles. ''It's so easy now,'' she said. ''People can practically publish from their desks.''</p>
        <p>WRITERS have been seeking new outlets for various reasons. As publishing houses consolidate, fewer new writers can get in the door; media-wise authors, meanwhile, are able to mount their own promotional campaigns. And while e-publishing sites typically offer no advance, they give more generous royalties -- often about 40 percent. (Major publishers typically offer 10 to 15 percent.)</p>
        <p>The large houses say the self-publishers  pose no threat. ''It's no secret that if you publish yourself, you can make more than a 15 percent royalty,'' said David Rosenthal, publisher of Simon &amp; Schuster trade books, a division of Viacom. ''But everything has its price.'' He said major publishing houses could offer authors more sophisticated design, editing, promotion and distribution.</p>
        <p>During a telephone interview, Mr. Rosenthal began tapping at his computer to check out Mr. Kaplan's sales. (Late Friday afternoon, the book ranked No. 191 on Amazon.) ''Clearly, he's doing something right,'' he said. ''But I think a traditional publisher could do as well if not better for him.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''It sounds like the kind of book we should think of buying.''</p>
        <p>HarperCollins, a unit of the News Corporation, has already tried.</p>
        <p>During the spring, after his mother-in-law sent him a news clipping about Mr. Kaplan, Adrian Zackheim, an associate publisher at HarperCollins, invited him to his New York office to talk deals.</p>
        <p>''I just listened,'' Mr. Kaplan said. ''But I felt it was more important for me to follow through with my plans to self-publish.'' HarperCollins said he turned down two six-figure offers.</p>
        <p>For a busy young man like Mr. Kaplan -- a former star tennis player in high school and an overachiever who has been known to stay awake 60 hours to finish a project -- the writing, publishing and promotion of his book have required the same kind of zeal he showed in applying for scholarships. (He won more than 20.)</p>
        <p>Having turned down publishers' queries because he felt they ''didn't get what the book was about,'' Mr. Kaplan finished writing ''How to Go to College'' in the summer of 1999 while living with his parents in Gleneden Beach, Ore.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaplan hired a friend from Harvard to draw the book's cartoons, but he and his parents did everything else. Mr. Kaplan taught himself how to format the entire book on his computer. His mother, Patana, and his father, Gary, helped with the editing. And his parents, who once published a small computer magazine, also contracted with a local printer for 5,000 copies, paying the bill with money from the family's unused college savings.</p>
        <p>With the books stacked in the garage, the family began the slow process of distributing copies two by two. Then four by four. Mr. Kaplan's relentless promotion ran from high school appearances to bookstore signings to television and radio appearances. Citing the early sales of his book, priced at a relatively high $23.95, he convinced Ingram, the wholesaler, as well as other distributors including Amazon.com and Baker &amp; Taylor, of Charlotte, N.C., to pick up his book.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaplan still lives at home, pouring all his earnings back into publishing. ''I don't own a car,'' he said. ''And quite frankly, I've been too busy and haven't had a chance to figure out how much money we have or have not made so far.''</p>
        <p>Will he ever sign with a major publisher? Mr. Kaplan has not ruled out such a move, but he is looking for partnerships that are in tune with his mission of providing books to help families through milestones, like college and high school.</p>
        <p>Known on the Internet as ''the Scholarship Coach,'' he maintains several Web sites, including www.waggledancer.com. (A waggle dancer is a kind of scout bee that performs an informative dance that helps other bees find new food sources.)</p>
        <p>To finance his tour, a cross-country trek in a 40-foot-long bus, Mr. Kaplan received backing from Sallie Mae, the student-loan giant, which has introduced a free financial aid Web site, Wiredscholar.com. He also hired a publicity firm.</p>
        <p>ON Monday night, the irrepressible Mr. Kaplan spent an hour in a Borders bookstore cafe in Mount Kisco, N.Y., bouncing around a stage discussing his book.</p>
        <p>Mondays usually yield tiny audiences at signings. But Mr. Kaplan's talk drew 35 people, who sat crowded at little tables. The book has 12 chapters, with titles like ''Acing the Interview'' and ''Show Me the Money'' and includes samples of winning scholarship essays as well as a listing of scholarships. But Mr. Kaplan says the most important factor is to be willing to work hard, whether in shaping a letter or preparing book shipments with foam filler.</p>
        <p>''Stephen King, Michael Crichton and John Grisham are all great authors,'' he said. ''But I can pack books in peanuts better than anyone.''</p>
        <p>BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
