<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Double Identity For Bucs</title>
    <meta content="24BUCS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/sports/24BUCS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EEDC173AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1403" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Double Identity For Bucs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, Fla., Sept. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you locked Keyshawn Johnson and Warren Sapp in a room together with only one microphone, who would get the first word and who would have the last one? When both are in the same locker room, both as Tampa Bay Buccaneers, Johnson holds court on one side, Sapp on the other. They often meet in the center, offering playful jabs, pushing buttons, creating a fun ruckus.</p>
        <p>Put both on the same field -- Johnson as a receiver and the team's offensive identity, Sapp as a tackle and the team's defensive identity -- and, thus far, winning has ensued. Tampa Bay is 3-0 and has outscored its opponents, 93-26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you locked Keyshawn Johnson and Warren Sapp in a room together with only one microphone, who would get the first word and who would have the last one? When both are in the same locker room, both as Tampa Bay Buccaneers, Johnson holds court on one side, Sapp on the other. They often meet in the center, offering playful jabs, pushing buttons, creating a fun ruckus.</p>
        <p>Put both on the same field -- Johnson as a receiver and the team's offensive identity, Sapp as a tackle and the team's defensive identity -- and, thus far, winning has ensued. Tampa Bay is 3-0 and has outscored its opponents, 93-26.</p>
        <p>When the Buccaneers play the 3-0 Jets here Sunday at Raymond James Stadium, Johnson and Sapp will be easy to find. Johnson is the new Buccaneer who has a score to settle with his old team. Sapp is the nucleus of a defense that can be ferocious and frightening.</p>
        <p>Sapp understands Johnson's emotions entering this battle against the team that traded him to Tampa Bay back in April.</p>
        <p>''Keyshawn loves the game,'' Sapp said this week. ''I have no doubt that he loved playing for the Jets and considered that team his home. It's still fresh for him. All I know is if the Bucs traded me, I'd torture them. And if I ever got to play against them, I'd make them regret it. We want to win this game to be 4-0. We don't want anyone coming in here and beating us in our own stadium. Those are the reasons we as a team want to win this game.</p>
        <p>''But we'd like for Keyshawn to have his day and if that happens, it's a bonus. A nice bonus.''</p>
        <p>Johnson and Sapp. Two Pro Bowl players. Two loquacious, outrageous, outspoken Buccaneers.</p>
        <p>Two of a kind.</p>
        <p>The Little Kid Kept His Word</p>
        <p>Marcus Allen, a former Pro Bowl running back, was recently remembering practices at the University of Southern California, where he played in the late 70's and early 80's, and how this little kid with a big mouth kept running around saying how great he was and how great he would be. Allen said Keyshawn Johnson then was the same as Keyshawn Johnson today. So full of confidence and prepared to say so.</p>
        <p>Johnson, who is 28, said he is in part a product of his environment. He said he grew up in South Central Los Angeles ''in poverty and with anything you could associate with poverty, including drugs, crime and murder.'' There was a hustle on every street.</p>
        <p>''You'd hear guys talking, challenging you all of the time,'' Johnson said. ''A guy would say, 'I'm going to get me a Benz!' and you'd look up and the next day and he'd be driving a new Mercedes. Back there you talked, you did it.''</p>
        <p>And that is what Johnson does in football. He talks. He does it. The ''does it'' part is why Tampa Bay traded for Johnson and gave him a six-year, $52 million contract that included a $13 million signing bonus.</p>
        <p>The Jets certainly did not trade Johnson because he was not a productive and elite football player (he had 305 receptions and 31 touchdown catches in 4 seasons). They traded him for two first-round draft picks with one eye on the future and with the other on the present in an attempt to create a more controlled climate for their new coach, Al Groh.</p>
        <p>All this week Johnson answered questions about Groh and the Jets, about Jets receiver Wayne Chrebet. Johnson says Chrebet is not a problem; the problem, Johnson says, is when others try to compare him to Chrebet.</p>
        <p>''To me, it's like comparing Allen Iverson to Michael Jordan,'' Johnson said. ''I'm really good friends with Allen Iverson, but I just don't think you can or should do that. When people try doing that with us, I just look at him as the Rudy guy from that Notre Dame movie and it's no comparison. Hey, what's the big deal? The Jets had a player, traded him, and now they are playing against that player. I really don't know exactly what to expect or what I'm going to do in this game. I could have a quiet game or I could get like 400 yards.</p>
        <p>''I know I want to be 4-0 when it's over. I know I play well in big games. And I know the Jets are going to try to take me out. They say they aren't going to scheme for me, but that's just posturing. They think they know me because I played there for four years, but really, they only know me in the scheme of how they used me. There are things I can do that they didn't ask or let me do on the football field. Tampa Bay is going to let me do those things, like go vertical more. They will see.''</p>
        <p>Johnson is asked why he simply does not keep quiet.</p>
        <p>''Jordan did it his way, Magic did it his way and I do it my way,'' he said. ''I get along with teammates. I've never been in a bar fight or embarrassed an organization with public conduct that was illegal. I say what I've got to say, regardless; but when you do it like people don't want you to do it, it's a problem. Plus I speak well, I look good, I'm successful and I'm black and some people just have a problem with that combination. And people might say, 'There he goes with the race card,' but I'm not. That's just the truth.''</p>
        <p>A Rebirth Under Dungy</p>
        <p>Sapp has been a Buccaneer since 1995. After his first season, in which Tampa Bay went 7-9, he wanted out.</p>
        <p>''It was the Sam Wyche days here, he ran a three-ring circus, and I have often told people that his franchise back then was like a third world country,'' Sapp said. ''The facilities were horrible and the team was terrible on the field and off. There was jealousy and envy in the locker room over me; they used to call me Super Rookie, the guy that was going to take the team to the Super Bowl all by himself, and they didn't say it in a complimentary fashion. Nobody in here cared after a loss. I was miserable.''</p>
        <p>But Tony Dungy arrived as coach before Sapp's second season. Sapp, who is 27, said he had heard so much about Dungy that he considered him ''the messiah, the chosen one.'' Dungy told Sapp he needed him.</p>
        <p>''He said there would be a new stadium and that he was going to take the shackles off me and let me go after the ball,'' Sapp said. ''He said he was going to build his defense around me and asked me if I could handle that. I said, 'Let's go.' ''</p>
        <p>And Dungy's words proved true.</p>
        <p>The Buccaneers kept getting better and finished last season one victory short of the Super Bowl after winning the National Football Conference Central Division at 11-5.  Through this season's first three weeks, only Tampa Bay players have been named the N.F.C. defensive players of the week: cornerback Ronde Barber, linebacker Derrick Brooks and then Sapp.</p>
        <p>Sapp believed his weight rose and his play dropped two seasons ago, when he had only seven sacks. He rededicated himself to reaching top form, and last season (12.5 sacks) and this season (5.5 sacks) he has. He talks about himself and Johnson ''autographing their performances'' against the Jets and beyond, a favorite phrase of Tampa Bay's assistant head coach, Herman Edwards.</p>
        <p>''I walked into this game some 75 years after it started,'' Sapp said. ''I've got a long list to climb. I want in the year 2020 for someone to say, 'Hey, that kid reminds me of Warren Sapp and how dominating he was.' I want to leave the game in better shape than I found it.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
