<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Alfonzo Ignores Pain and Powers Mets' Drive</title>
    <meta content="24METS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E7D8143AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1065" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Alfonzo Ignores Pain and Powers Mets' Drive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Sept. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Philadelphia Phillies, 7-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Edgardo Alfonzo was worn down by the end of last season. Alfonzo, the Mets' second baseman, had taken only five games off, and after the playoffs he sat out the winter ball season at home in Venezuela. He resolved to ask for a few more days off this season, and he has gotten them -- 12, in all.</p>
        <p>But Alfonzo is still banged up, with a sore hip and groin, and games on artificial turf are never kind. None of that has mattered on this road trip, however. After their 7-3 victory over the Philadelphia Phillies tonight, the Mets had split the 10 games on the trip. Whenever they have won, Alfonzo has played a major role.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Edgardo Alfonzo was worn down by the end of last season. Alfonzo, the Mets' second baseman, had taken only five games off, and after the playoffs he sat out the winter ball season at home in Venezuela. He resolved to ask for a few more days off this season, and he has gotten them -- 12, in all.</p>
        <p>But Alfonzo is still banged up, with a sore hip and groin, and games on artificial turf are never kind. None of that has mattered on this road trip, however. After their 7-3 victory over the Philadelphia Phillies tonight, the Mets had split the 10 games on the trip. Whenever they have won, Alfonzo has played a major role.</p>
        <p>Now the Mets, having won three of their last four games, are closing in on a playoff berth. After their game tonight and before the finish of West Coast games involving their competitors, the Mets' clinching number for the wild-card playoff spot was three.</p>
        <p>Alfonzo had a home run and a double, scoring three runs, and he has hit .361 on the trip, most of which has been played on artificial turf. Tonight he was plunked in the back by a pitch, though he said he felt fine. ''I'm tough, man,'' Alfonzo said, but he also played down the effects of the grind.</p>
        <p>''All the players should be a little tired,'' he said. ''It's been a long season -- all the travel, all the plays, all the stress that you have. But that's what spring training's all about. You have to prepare, you have to keep working, keep yourself in shape.''</p>
        <p>Alfonzo is having another sensational season, with 106 runs scored and one more extra-base hit than Mike Piazza, who had a double and a run-scoring bloop single tonight. Those efforts helped lift Mike Hampton (14-10) to his first victory this month. The Phillies did their share, too.</p>
        <p>The Mets scored two runs on wild pitches, one on an error and one on a bloop single. They took eight walks and one hit batter from six Phillies pitchers. It has been a forgettable year for the last-place Phillies, and Mets supporters were the most vocal among the 22,570 fans at Veterans Stadium.</p>
        <p>Most of their replica jerseys were Piazza models, and he rewarded them with his two hits. But while Piazza is just now emerging from three weeks in offensive hibernation, Alfonzo has stayed steady throughout September. He is batting .311 this month after slumping to a .232 average after Aug. 31 last year.</p>
        <p>Alfonzo said he had been trying to be more aggressive at the plate, but he would still take pitches, depending on the situation. Really, he said, he is just keeping things simple. ''Don't think too much,'' he said. ''I've figured that out.''</p>
        <p>Hampton said: ''He's a very consistent player. He's able to adjust each at-bat. If they're getting him out with certain pitches, it seems like he's able to make that adjustment and hit that pitch. He's one of the guys you know you can count on.''</p>
        <p>Except last Monday, when he had his worst performance in months in a loss at Atlanta, Hampton has been just as dependable. He did not have his signature pitch, the sinker, working for him tonight, but he said his hard cutter was the sharpest it had been all year.</p>
        <p>Hampton used that pitch effectively over six innings before coming out in the seventh, after a seemingly interminable top of the inning in which the Mets scored four runs off three relievers.</p>
        <p>Not that Hampton minded waiting out a rally. When the Mets scored in the first, it was the first run they had scored in almost 27 innings while he was pitching, since his start at St. Louis on Sept. 2. Hampton was 0-3 this month, despite pitching well in three of his four starts.</p>
        <p>For the second game in a row, the Mets' leadoff hitter doubled and scored. On Friday, it was Benny Agbayani, who later strained his hamstring and could be out several days. Tonight it was Timo Perez, this year's version of Melvin Mora, right down to his uniform number, 6. Like Mora, Perez had never played in the majors before this season but earned a promotion with a strong showing in the minors. Also like Mora, Perez has proven his usefulness to Manager Bobby Valentine and seems likely to earn a postseason roster spot.</p>
        <p>Mora, who was traded to Baltimore in July, is more versatile, because he can play the infield. But Perez has more speed and bats left-handed, and has made a better early showing as a hitter.</p>
        <p>Perez punched a ball to left field to open the game, and it kept carrying as the left fielder, Pat Burrell, twisted one way, then the other. It landed over Burrell's head, and Perez pulled into second with his seventh major league hit (Mora had five last year).</p>
        <p>The next hitter, Derek Bell, stung a pitch to first base, where it took one hop on the slick artificial turf and went between first baseman Brian Hunter's legs for an error. Perez scored, made a fine grab in the bottom of the first and ignited the seventh-inning rally, as well, bunting for a single and scoring.</p>
        <p>''I think he's going to be a good player,'' Valentine said. ''I thought that after seeing a couple of games. The catch he made in the first inning wasn't a walk at the beach. He's a leadoff hitter, he scores and he's able to make all the plays -- he can hit, bunt, run the bases, play defense, throw. He has a feel for it. I like what I've seen.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Shea Stadium will be sold out for the first two home games of the National League division series, should the Mets qualify. All 7,000 tickets available for each game were sold today.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
