<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abstracting The Meaning</title>
    <meta content="24ART.$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233086"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">College of New Rochelle</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lombardi, D Dominick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E7DF123BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abstracting The Meaning</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By D. DOMINICK LOMBARDI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lombardi, D Dominick</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ROCHELLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>D Dominick Lombardi reviews works by contemporary abstract artists on view at College of New Rochelle's Castle Gallery; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the late 1950's, the Abstract Expressionist Adolph Gottlieb said, ''We are going to have perhaps a thousand years of nonrepresentational painting. . . . Abstraction is not a limitation but a liberation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gottlieb was teaching at the Pratt Institute at that time, and he was probably responding to the opposing views of the Social Realist artists who stressed representation in their art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the late 1950's, the Abstract Expressionist Adolph Gottlieb said, ''We are going to have perhaps a thousand years of nonrepresentational painting. . . . Abstraction is not a limitation but a liberation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gottlieb was teaching at the Pratt Institute at that time, and he was probably responding to the opposing views of the Social Realist artists who stressed representation in their art.</p>
        <p>A new exhibit at the Castle Gallery, titled ''Another Story Altogether: Abstraction in Painting Today,'' provides support for Mr. Gottlieb's viewpoint. Here, the curators Katherine Gass and Wennie Huang, who is the Castle Gallery's director, select 12 artists that show Abstract Art as diverse and experimental.</p>
        <p>When the term abstraction is used to describe art, it implies that the artist has taken something concrete, something from the physical world, and changed it in some way. Objects or concepts are distilled or distorted, becoming less recognizable.</p>
        <p>Emily Cheng's work is the clearest example of this process. In ''Tempering the Will'' (2000), Ms. Cheng convulses reality. A blue dinner plate, its contents, and the table cloth beneath it are transformed as if gravity is being compressed. The pattern on the plate runs outward; the food on the plate reforms on a molecular level, and the pattern of the tablecloth wanders into some parallel dimension as the fabric twists, pulling free from the table top.</p>
        <p>Melissa Gwyn's inspiration is also relatively easy to trace back to its source. In ''Untitled'' (2000), a winter cabbage-like form erupts, spewing pure, unblended paint through bursting, dull-green skin. Here, one sees how abstraction can easily lead to a Surrealistic vision.</p>
        <p>Another Surrealistic result can be seen in Augusto Arbizo's ''Motif'' (1999). ''Motif'' reminded me of Pavel Tchelitchew's interior landscapes, whereby a body part -- in Mr. Tchelitchew's case a head; in Mr. Arbizo's case a heart-like form -- becomes transparent amid a growing energy field.</p>
        <p>Creighton Michael, too, does a variation of the internal landscape; his paintings, however, are more visceral. Probing deeper, he is attracted to the otherwise imperceptible patterns and systems of his innermost reaches. Some patterns are more surface oriented like fingerprints. Some are reminiscent of sea coral. Most are like those garnered by feel, or theory, or electron microscope. When combined, these patterns evoke life's subconscious, a powerful system of impulses, which changes everything from reason to instinct.</p>
        <p>Under the blanket term Abstraction, can be found Non-Representational, or Non-Objective Art.</p>
        <p>This is when the artist creates a painting without any conscious, real world reference. This type of art is more of a reflective  visualization than an abstraction.</p>
        <p>Despite the reference to Op Art, Maureen McQuillan's two nonobjective works appear fresh and alive. Using printer's ink and resin on paper, she too, probes her unconscious mind, though here the results are more about the process than they are about the meaning. When you look at the subtly changing sinuous lines in Ms. McQuillan's work, you can almost feel her heart beating. Her art-making process is extremely intimate.</p>
        <p>Another nonobjective artist is Erin Parish. Her ''Ohne Titel'' (2000) reminds me of Ad Reinhardt's subterranean colored, blue-green paintings, though Ms. Parish creates her illusion through transparency, texture and detail. Where Mr. Reinhardt looked not to represent an actual object or thing, Ms. Parish adds layer upon layer of effects, which evoke some very nonspecific, amorphous gas-like veils containing undefinable particles frozen beneath and atop the surface of the painting.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Cooper's candy-colored abstractions are mostly about paint's properties. How it froths, foams, cracks, drips, dries, smears and slides. At first her work appears free and loose; but one quickly notices a technique or approach that could only evolve after controlled and varied periods of drying and manipulation. It is easiest to say that her paintings are orchestrated without premeditation. She reacts to the paint, as much as it is affected by what she decides to do with it.</p>
        <p>Another somewhat witty artist is Lisa Stefanelli. It is important to note that Ms. Stefanelli's source of information for her sinuous, seemingly never-ending lines is her experience as a figure skater. Apparently, she is reprocessing the lines that she once etched into the ice. Before I knew of her background, I thought she might be mixing Art Nouveau with crazy, exaggerated hairstyles -- like the Pop-Surrealist hair stylist Ruth Marten. But knowing the skating reference makes her expressions in paint more compelling.</p>
        <p>''Another Story Altogether: Abstraction in Painting Today'' runs through Oct. 15. The Castle Gallery is on the campus of the College of New Rochelle. Information: (914) 654-5423.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
