<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rock Dreams, as Latte Steams</title>
    <meta content="24STAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233188"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brindley, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Estes, Lelan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jennings, Dana</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E6D8103BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rock Dreams, as Latte Steams</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANA JENNINGS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jennings, Dana</byline>
      <dateline>UPPER MONTCLAIR</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Daniel Brindley and Lelan Estes, two young rock musicians who dream of making it big as they work at Starbucks in Upper Montclair, NJ; photo (Special Issue: Entertainment) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOMETIMES, the true rebels are the quiet rebels.</p>
        <p>Consider Daniel Brindley and Lelan Estes, two young musicians who work at the Starbucks on Valley Road here. In a hypercaffeinated climate of Frappuccinos and Tiazzis, macchiatos and double espresso shots -- ''I'd like a grande-iced-skim-latte, please'' -- Mr. Brindley and Mr. Estes wear Starbucks green, sling coffee (tall, grande or venti?), grind glossy sacks of Guatemala and Sumatra, make change and, most important, dream music, drink music, talk music.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOMETIMES, the true rebels are the quiet rebels.</p>
        <p>Consider Daniel Brindley and Lelan Estes, two young musicians who work at the Starbucks on Valley Road here. In a hypercaffeinated climate of Frappuccinos and Tiazzis, macchiatos and double espresso shots -- ''I'd like a grande-iced-skim-latte, please'' -- Mr. Brindley and Mr. Estes wear Starbucks green, sling coffee (tall, grande or venti?), grind glossy sacks of Guatemala and Sumatra, make change and, most important, dream music, drink music, talk music.</p>
        <p>''Today's music is all so corporate driven; a song is just a commodity,'' says Mr. Brindley, 21, an instrumentalist and songwriter imbued with a self-effacing 1960's intensity. ''What matters to me is who's really making music, who cares more about the music than the money.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Estes, 22, who plays bass in the North Jersey punk (with a hint of country) band Cropduster, says: ''We want to go into the music business and make change. We want to affect people. If we can deal with one person in a kind and honest way, it's worth it.''</p>
        <p>Theirs is a timeless suburban tale; it's easy to imagine it as a midseason replacement on Fox: Three or four young, idealistic musicians (budding rock 'n' rollers do tend to rotate in and out of this particular Starbucks) making mochas and struggling toward their big -- or, at least, medium-size -- break.</p>
        <p>Parents, blame it on Elvis, that patron saint of all garage bands.</p>
        <p>Ever since Elvis Aron Presley ducked his head and shyly creeped into Sun Records of Memphis, Tenn., back in August 1953, thousands of young musicians have embraced the great American myth that a kid with pluck, a hook and a few chords can become a rock 'n' roll star.</p>
        <p>But stardom isn't necessarily what Mr. Brindley and Mr. Estes want -- though they wouldn't sneer at a record deal. They see their challenges as more spiritual, more artistic. Thrashing through the wilderness of corporate bands ('N Sync, the Backstreet Boys, the Spice Girls) and the MTV-endorsed rebellion of Kid Rock, Eminem and Limp Bizkit, they're seeking something different.</p>
        <p>''We're after the other definition of success,'' says Mr. Brindley, whose singer-songwriter heroes include Bruce Cockburn, Nick Drake and Bob Dylan (''of course''). ''Folk music is against the grain. It doesn't have the stamp of approval of MTV.''</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Brindley and Mr. Estes, friends since childhood, carry a pledge-of-allegiance reverence for Bill Mallonee and the Vigilantes of Love, an Athens, Ga., alternative-country band whose music, they say, ''is built on honesty, humility and kindness.''</p>
        <p>Which isn't quite how Kid Rock and the other MTV avatars of calculated rage built their careers. ''It doesn't take many brains to do what they're doing,'' Mr. Estes says.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Brindley and Mr. Estes should know. They are unknown, but they are already professional musicians, the same way that minor leaguers are pro baseball players. They're all just waiting for that summons to the big leagues.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brindley, of Montclair, plays local clubs and coffeehouses and has gigged in Hoboken and New York City. He also helps his Luke, his older brother (he co-produced Luke's new compact disc, ''Spring Song'') and works with the Montclair acoustic group Vesper.</p>
        <p>With Cropduster, whose music has been called ''energetic, disillusioned country punk,'' Mr. Estes, of West Orange, has traveled to North Carolina, Pennsylvania, Upstate New York, Manhattan and throughout New Jersey.</p>
        <p>The Internet also plays a vital role in their music. Mr. Brindley can be heard performing with his brother at lukebrindley.com, while Cropduster holds forth at cropdustermusic.com.</p>
        <p>But, when the music stops there's other music to face, like the job at Starbucks.</p>
        <p>''Actually, Starbucks has been great, giving me the time to pursue this,'' says Mr. Estes, who has worked there four years and who is the store's assistant manager. ''Of course, I only get five hours of sleep, and I have a constant twitch in my eyelid.'' He laughs.</p>
        <p>But the coffee beat can be wearing. ''Some people feel they can be rude to you just because you work at Starbucks,'' Mr. Estes says.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brindley, who works there part time and who is a senior music major at Rutgers-Newark, says, ''If I'm tired, it's hard for me to hold back when customers are rude.''</p>
        <p>As young suburban men, they've both run into the typical suburban attitudes, and platitudes. Parents and grandparents don't want their babies to grow up to be musicians for the same reason they keep their lawns edged stiffer than Johnny Unitas's old crewcut: What will the neighbors think?</p>
        <p>As Mr. Estes says, ''My folks are dubiously optimistic.''</p>
        <p>But the good-college-good-job-good-pay formula doesn't appeal to either man.</p>
        <p>''The choice to play music goes against the dominant culture,'' Mr. Brindley said. ''For a long time, I even hesitated to call myself a musician.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Estes adds: ''We don't think we have everything figured out. But we're not jaded. I went to Montclair State for a while, and one night I went to see the Vigilantes of Love, and I realized I was trapping myself in this box, in the ABC's of life. I realized what I really wanted to do was pursue music and writing.''</p>
        <p>He pauses, that quiet rebellion in his eyes. ''I'm getting married in nine months,'' Mr. Estes says. ''The things that I'm doing are long shots. But I'd be a miserable person if I didn't do them. Money is not what is going to make us happy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
