<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marcela Sanchez, James Grover</title>
    <meta content="24SANC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233274"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SANCHEZ, MARCELA MARIE (MARCELA MARIE GROVER)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GROVER, JAMES ARTHUR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E6DA1E3BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="483" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marcela Sanchez, James Grover</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marcela Marie Sanchez, a daughter of Dr. Bonnie Z. Sanchez of Clearwater Beach, Fla., and Dr. Rolando Sanchez of Tampa, Fla., was married on Friday to James Arthur Grover, the son of Judith and James R. Grover of Old Saybrook, Conn. Diane L. Seemann, a retired clerk of Washington County Superior Court, officiated at Rosecliff, a Stanford White house-museum in Newport, R.I.</p>
        <p>The bride, 29, is the general counsel at Apogee Networks, an Internet software company in Saddle Brook, N.J. She graduated from Hamilton College and New York Law School. Her father, a vascular surgeon, practices in Tampa. Her mother, a podiatrist, practices in Clearwater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Marcela Marie Sanchez, a daughter of Dr. Bonnie Z. Sanchez of Clearwater Beach, Fla., and Dr. Rolando Sanchez of Tampa, Fla., was married on Friday to James Arthur Grover, the son of Judith and James R. Grover of Old Saybrook, Conn. Diane L. Seemann, a retired clerk of Washington County Superior Court, officiated at Rosecliff, a Stanford White house-museum in Newport, R.I.</p>
        <p>The bride, 29, is the general counsel at Apogee Networks, an Internet software company in Saddle Brook, N.J. She graduated from Hamilton College and New York Law School. Her father, a vascular surgeon, practices in Tampa. Her mother, a podiatrist, practices in Clearwater.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 28, is a vice president of First Atlantic Capital, an investment firm in New York. He evaluates and oversees leveraged buyout transactions. Mr. Grover graduated from Duke University. His father retired as a salesman in Westport, Conn., for I.B.M.</p>
        <p>Ms. Sanchez and Mr. Grover met on a ferry from Athens to Santorini while on vacation in Greece six years ago. He was traveling with three friends and was reading ''The Bonfire of the Vanities'' by Tom Wolfe.</p>
        <p>''I told him it was one of the worst books I had ever read,'' remembered Ms. Sanchez, who was with a girlfriend. Discussion turned into conversation. Mr. Grover said he and his friends did not have hotel reservations on Santorini. Ms. Sanchez said she had contacts, and got a hotel room for the four men.</p>
        <p>''I just felt so comfortable with him,'' Ms. Sanchez said.</p>
        <p>They had a four-day romance, which ended when Mr. Grover returned to the United States and Ms. Sanchez continued her travels, to Southeast Asia.</p>
        <p>She wrote him in Newport. He was working there as an engineer. ''As I was traveling, I found myself thinking about him over and over,'' Ms. Sanchez said. ''When I went hiking in the north of Thailand, I remember looking around and thinking James would have absolutely loved this trip.''</p>
        <p>They met again later that year, when she returned to the United States. Romance followed, although she was preoccupied with law school in New York and he lived in Newport. In the summer of 1996, he joined her in New York, where he had taken a job.</p>
        <p>Ms. Sanchez said she was drawn to him in part ''because he was sweet and soft-spoken, and I had never encountered anybody else like that.'' Mr. Grover said, ''She was energetic and driven, qualities which are very compatible with mine.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
