<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; The Night Belongs to Greene, but the Future Belongs to Jones</title>
    <meta content="24ARAT$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233572"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Marion</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greene, Maurice</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E0D8143AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="891" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; The Night Belongs to Greene, but the Future Belongs to Jones</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times column discusses Olympic gold medal performances of US sprinters Marion Jones and Maurice Greene; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Off the track and into his new and long-awaited life as an Olympic gold medalist, Maurice Greene made the rounds, hammed it up with the men who had finished in his dust and then happened to glance at the television, mounted high on the back stage wall. There, was a scene that is likely to be repeated several times over the following week. There, was a face that Madison Avenue will undoubtedly soon come to love.</p>
        <p>There, Marion Jones was beating him to the medal stand, on her way to becoming a transcendent American star. On the night of dueling sprinters and sexes, Greene did all he could, with his flamboyant swagger, with no way to surprise people unless he failed, which he most certainly did not.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Off the track and into his new and long-awaited life as an Olympic gold medalist, Maurice Greene made the rounds, hammed it up with the men who had finished in his dust and then happened to glance at the television, mounted high on the back stage wall. There, was a scene that is likely to be repeated several times over the following week. There, was a face that Madison Avenue will undoubtedly soon come to love.</p>
        <p>There, Marion Jones was beating him to the medal stand, on her way to becoming a transcendent American star. On the night of dueling sprinters and sexes, Greene did all he could, with his flamboyant swagger, with no way to surprise people unless he failed, which he most certainly did not.</p>
        <p>''We got destroyed,'' said Ato Boldon, silver medalist, after Greene powered out of the blocks, shifted into warp drive the last 50 meters and won the men's 100 meters in 9.87 seconds tonight at the beautiful Olympic Stadium that holds 110,000 spectators and accommodates a fair amount of oversized moths. The moths were circling but Greene was flying. No doubt was left regarding the identity of the world's fastest human, unless you were in lane eight, and trying to claim that title yourself.</p>
        <p>''I actually thought we were even, until I saw the replay,'' Boldon said. ''But that's what peripheral vision does to you.''</p>
        <p>By the time Boldon hit the interview area, he had come to grips with the realization that his training partner, the 26-year-old first-time Olympian he had taken under his wing, had ascended to that place in time when the moon, the stars and the moths are perfectly aligned. Too bad Greene had to stoop to all the trash-talking and tongue-wagging. Performance is the greatest form of intimidation, and his world-record 9.79 and his 30 sub-10-second times coming into Sydney were enough to remind the others, at least subliminally, that they were racing for second.</p>
        <p>''Definitely a down year for mere mortals in the 100,'' Boldon said, a club in which Greene was not being counted as a member.</p>
        <p>''A lot of this stuff is day by day, moment by moment,'' said the bronze medalist, Obadele Thompson. ''He puts things together very well, day by day, moment by moment. Ergo, we don't beat him very often.''</p>
        <p>Boldon, of Trinidad and Tobago, told Thompson, of Barbados, ''Two hundred, let's do it,'' referring to a race that will be free of Greene and Michael Johnson, open to them and other mere mortals. They gratefully took their silver and bronze and left Greene to his just rewards, including a victory lap that included a stop to sit, remove his shoes and hurl them into the stands.</p>
        <p>Ergo, Nike executives were cheering wildly somewhere, or merely applauding the flawless execution of a prearranged plan. While Greene maintained, ''I'm not into sport for fame and fortune,'' let's be serious. Cashing in on gold has become almost a corporate Olympics in itself, witness the silver shoes that Jones, another soldier of the swoosh, high-stepped in to the finish, as her face transformed from a mask of determination to a smile that in a power failure could light up the stadium.</p>
        <p>If Michael Johnson proved one thing after Atlanta four years ago, it is that extending Olympic celebrity beyond those welcome-home nights on the couch next to Letterman or Leno is getting harder and harder. Greene could have thrown Imelda Marcos's entire collection into the stands along with his, but he'll soon find out that only Jones, five golds or not, will step up to the next level of stardom from these Games.</p>
        <p>She's got that unique and magnetic aura. Or as she said when asked to describe what a gold medal feels like, ''No rough edges, very smooth.''</p>
        <p>Her mother is a native of Belize, where young Marion spent summers and even her honeymoon, and why she carried two flags on her victory lap. Fred Evans, the coach of two Belize runners here, said the country doesn't have a single track and his athletes train on a soccer pitch. He hoped Jones would help raise the money to build a small stadium, so that a Belize runner could someday go for the gold, like Maurice Greene, or golds, like Jones.</p>
        <p>Greene, naturally, was asked his opinion of Jones's attempt to do the unfathomable, as many American track stars undoubtedly will in the coming days.</p>
        <p>''I wish her the best because I wouldn't try it,'' he said. ''I was very tired last year after Seville after running all the rounds of the 100 and 200 and all the relays. I just hope her body doesn't break down.''</p>
        <p>At the trials last summer, both Greene and Johnson pulled up lame, trying to outdo each other in the 200 meters. Everyone here is in awe of what Marion Jones is trying to do, and that includes the world's fastest human, still a title of renown, even when Marion Jones was on the program, too.</p>
        <p>It was Greene's night, but it was also a one-night stand. With all due respect to Cathy Freeman and Johnson, the Olympics, from hereon out, belong to Jones.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
