<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parents and Children Wait, But Not Exactly Patiently</title>
    <meta content="24SIDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Stamford (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bailer, Darice</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E5DD133BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parents and Children Wait, But Not Exactly Patiently</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DARICE BAILER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bailer, Darice</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Parents in Samford, Conn, pick up slack by driving groups of children back and forth to school when school bus service becomes sporadic as result of driver shortage (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE bus had been late before, and Millie Ho of Stamford expected the problems to continue. So instead of her son, Norman, 8, standing around waiting every morning, she began driving him to Davenport Ridge Elementary School.</p>
        <p>''You never know what's going on, so I just bring him,'' Ms. Ho said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE bus had been late before, and Millie Ho of Stamford expected the problems to continue. So instead of her son, Norman, 8, standing around waiting every morning, she began driving him to Davenport Ridge Elementary School.</p>
        <p>''You never know what's going on, so I just bring him,'' Ms. Ho said.</p>
        <p>Then she ran into her neighbor, Debbie Merberg, during the second week of school, who told Ms. Ho that the buses were now pretty much on time. Sure, the bus didn't reach school until 9:15 the first couple of mornings, with school starting at 9, but parents discovered that the route was too long and adjustments were made. Now the bus was picking up the neighborhood children closer to their route's 8:40 scheduled time. So Norman was back on the bus again.</p>
        <p>There had been problems last year, too. Their school bus driver left in the middle of the year and parents said their children didn't have a regular morning or afternoon driver. Ms. Merberg, whose son, Alex, 7, attends Davenport, said sometimes the bus wouldn't even come. So parents took over, helping each other out. When the morning bus didn't show up, they picked up the neighborhood children and drove them to school. When the bus failed to bring their children home in the afternoon, they drove back to school and drove them home.</p>
        <p>''It was very frustrating,'' Ms. Merberg said. ''I gave up after awhile and didn't even bother.''</p>
        <p>She also almost gave up on this year's afternoon run. Her child's afternoon driver would change from day to day, and the bus wasn't as timely as the morning one. Ms. Merberg picked up Alex at 4:15 p.m. on the first day, after she called the school and learned that the bus was running late. If she hadn't retrieved him, he wouldn't have arrived home until 5:30 p.m., she said.</p>
        <p>Also, Alex's bus number changed as bus officials scrambled to reorganize the route and compensate for an inadequate number of drivers. So four other Davenport parents in the neighborhood also began driving their children to and from school.</p>
        <p>On this morning, the bus was on time, flashing its red warning lights by the watermelon-colored mailbox at the corner of Quarry and New England Drive. Actually, it was five minutes early.</p>
        <p>''The bus! The bus!'' shouted Liah Luvice, 5, skipping toward the door.</p>
        <p>''I just started putting her on the bus because it's coming regular now,'' said Liah's father, Isabelo Luvice.</p>
        <p>Alex Merberg almost missed the bus. The driver waited patiently, seeing the boy hurrying down the street, holding his mother's hand. Ms. Merberg didn't mind that the bus was early.</p>
        <p>''We like that,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But in Wilton that morning, two parents gave up on the bus and drove their children to school.</p>
        <p>The Salem Road bus had only been late once before, parents said, but on this day it didn't show up until 8:50 a.m., about 20 minutes late and only 5 minutes before school started. That was enough for Ann Sullivan.</p>
        <p>''I've had it,'' said Ms. Sullivan, who was waiting with David, her kindergartener, at the top of Salem Road. She had also been waiting with Robin House and her daughter, Gabrielle, 7. So, Ms. House and Ms. Sullivan decided they would carpool and drive to the Ina E. Driscoll School in Wilton instead.</p>
        <p>Ms. Sullivan knew that her town wasn't the only one with too few bus drivers.</p>
        <p>''You can understand the problems that they're having,'' Ms. Sullivan said, ''but still. The kids are late for school.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
