<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fusaichi Pegasus Sharp In His Return to Racing</title>
    <meta content="24RACI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/sports/24RACI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EEDC173AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fusaichi Pegasus Sharp In His Return to Racing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fusaichi Pegasus made a triumphant return to racing yesterday after a four-month absence, and he did it regally and professionally, sweeping into the lead in the homestretch and winning the Jerome Handicap over El Corredor and Albert the Great.</p>
        <p>He did it despite carrying the high weight of 124 pounds, despite a light rain at Belmont Park and despite having sustained a foot injury after winning the Kentucky Derby last spring and running second two weeks later in the Preakness. And he did it with the same Olympian bearing that had made the son of Mr. Prospector and the grandson of Danzig the ranking candidate for Horse of the Year and the buzz of the racing world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fusaichi Pegasus made a triumphant return to racing yesterday after a four-month absence, and he did it regally and professionally, sweeping into the lead in the homestretch and winning the Jerome Handicap over El Corredor and Albert the Great.</p>
        <p>He did it despite carrying the high weight of 124 pounds, despite a light rain at Belmont Park and despite having sustained a foot injury after winning the Kentucky Derby last spring and running second two weeks later in the Preakness. And he did it with the same Olympian bearing that had made the son of Mr. Prospector and the grandson of Danzig the ranking candidate for Horse of the Year and the buzz of the racing world.</p>
        <p>Fusaichi Pegasus ran the mile in 1:34, which equaled the fourth-fastest time in the 131 runnings of the Jerome. And he joined three other colts -- Aristides in 1875, Carry Back in 1961 and Chateaugay in 1963 -- who won the Kentucky Derby and the Jerome in the same year.</p>
        <p>In the second half of Belmont's doubleheader, the trainer Todd Pletcher saw the 61st running of the Vosburgh swept by his 3-year-old speed horses, Trippi, who won by half a length, and More Than Ready, who finished second. Both horses will not race again until they try another sweep in the Breeders' Cup Sprint in six weeks.</p>
        <p>But this was a day dominated by the return of Fusaichi Pegasus.</p>
        <p>''He's the champion,'' said Kent Desormeaux, the West Coast jockey who has been aboard the 3-year-old  for every race except the first in his career of six victories and two seconds. ''He's the best horse I've ever ridden. I'm just so excited that he's back.''</p>
        <p>But Neil Drysdale, who trains Fusaichi Pegasus for his Japanese owners, was still guarded about when his star would race again. If Fusaichi Pegasus stays sound, he may run in the $1 million Jockey Club Gold Cup on Oct. 14 at Belmont Park en route to the ultimate target, the $4 million Breeders' Cup Classic at Churchill Downs on Nov. 4. After that, he will head for Kentucky and a career as a stallion.</p>
        <p>''It's far too early to discuss where he'll go next,'' Drysdale said. ''But the Jockey Club Gold Cup is certainly one of our options. It was important to get this race today. There was never a major concern about the weather. The track stayed wet-fast, but had the rain gotten into the bottom, it would have been a major concern.''</p>
        <p>Then he remembered that his talented colt had apparently outgrown his headstrong behavior before races and said: ''He's much more mature than he was this spring. I think he handled everything very well.''</p>
        <p>Fusaichi Pegasus, who was purchased for $4 million as a yearling and is now valued at $60 million, handled everything well from the paddock to the starting gate. He broke from the rail alertly, saved his strength while Albert the Great took an early and unwelcome lead and then moved to the outside when they were leaving the backstretch. Once headed for home, he cruised to the front under a hand ride by Desormeaux, who looked back once to see who was getting close.</p>
        <p>''In the stretch, it looked like Kent stopped riding,'' Drysdale said. ''Then when he looked back and saw El Corredor, he started riding again.''</p>
        <p>At the finish, Fusaichi Pegasus had three-quarters of a length on El Corredor, who had won his last four starts for Bob Baffert in California. Nick Zito's Albert the Great was nearly four lengths back in third. The winner paid $4.40 for a $2 bet as the 6-5 favorite, and earned $90,000, raising his career bankroll close to $2 million.</p>
        <p>In the Vosburgh, Trippi held the lead almost from the start while More Than Ready ran ninth for half a mile. The two then dueled down the stretch, but Trippi held onto his lead by half a length over his stablemate.  One Way Love was two lengths back in third.</p>
        <p>The winner ran the seven furlongs under Jerry Bailey in 1:213/5  and returned $9.20 for a $2 bet and earned $180,000.</p>
        <p>Bailey, who heard footsteps in the final yards, remembered, ''I knew a horse was coming on the outside, but I didn't know it was More Than Ready.''</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
