<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Dance Vivaldi, Just Ask Vivaldi</title>
    <meta content="24FANG$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/arts/24FANG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Ballet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vivaldi, Antonio (1675-1741)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fanger, Iris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wheeldon, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3DC153BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Dance Vivaldi, Just Ask Vivaldi</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRIS FANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fanger, Iris</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iris Fanger article on Boston Ballet guest choreographer Christopher Wheeldon, who is working on ballet set to Antonio Vivaldi's Four Seasons, which will have its world premiere at Wang Theater; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHRISTOPHER WHEELDON had no intention of making a ballet of Antonio Vivaldi's ''Four Seasons,'' even though he thinks the music is wonderful. When he saw James Kudelka's ballet to the same score, he recalls, he thought: ''Wow, this is long. I love the music but I would never do this.'' He couldn't see how to stretch enough inventive steps over the length of such a familiar work.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, he agreed to take it on because the Boston Ballet, where he has been appointed principal guest choreographer through 2003, wanted the ''The Four Seasons'' for its repertory. And while studying the music for clues to where he should start, he found inspiration in the composer's own words, inserted in the score. ''In the winter,'' Vivaldi wrote in one note, ''our feet chatter with cold. We shiver in the snow.'' With that, Mr. Wheeldon's imagination took off, and the ballet started to take shape.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHRISTOPHER WHEELDON had no intention of making a ballet of Antonio Vivaldi's ''Four Seasons,'' even though he thinks the music is wonderful. When he saw James Kudelka's ballet to the same score, he recalls, he thought: ''Wow, this is long. I love the music but I would never do this.'' He couldn't see how to stretch enough inventive steps over the length of such a familiar work.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, he agreed to take it on because the Boston Ballet, where he has been appointed principal guest choreographer through 2003, wanted the ''The Four Seasons'' for its repertory. And while studying the music for clues to where he should start, he found inspiration in the composer's own words, inserted in the score. ''In the winter,'' Vivaldi wrote in one note, ''our feet chatter with cold. We shiver in the snow.'' With that, Mr. Wheeldon's imagination took off, and the ballet started to take shape.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wheeldon, who retired as a soloist with the New York City Ballet last spring, says he has been working from ''noon to dusk every day'' to finish the 48-minute ballet, which will have its world premiere on Thursday at the Wang Theater, where the company's season runs through Oct. 8. Collaborating with Santo Loquasto, who has designed the scenery and costumes, Mr. Wheeldon was emphatic about ''wanting to escape the rather typical idea of the changing of the seasons.''</p>
        <p>''I asked Santo to create for me a space that evoked a sense of period in a way,'' he recalls. ''It has a hint of traveling performers who come upon a space. We have four very different seasons choreographically.''</p>
        <p>To watch Mr. Wheeldon rehearsing in the top-floor studio of the South End building that is home to the Boston Ballet is to note the self-confidence and easy manner of a choreographer who works comfortably with the dancers. A slow, backward slide for Lyn Tally down a ramp from a heavy, gold-colored wagon was hard to achieve until Mr. Wheeldon demonstrated the body pose he had in mind.</p>
        <p>''I came into the studio fairly unprepared for the ballet,'' he says later. ''I'm not a big preparer anyway. I don't spend hours in the studio alone, forming combinations. It's much more interesting for me to create something for a personality. I'm interested in learning the craft of building roles for dancers. After all, the great choreographers of the past whom I admire -- Balanchine, Robbins, Ashton, MacMillan, Kylian, Tudor and Taylor -- worked in this way.''</p>
        <p>Just 27 years old, Mr. Wheeldon has choreographed works for many companies over the last five years, beginning with a full-evening production of ''A Midsummer Night's Dream'' for the Colorado Ballet. But it's a mistake to make too much of his age. The major choreographers whom he reveres were also early bloomers: think of Balanchine at age 21 in Monte Carlo, creating works for the Diaghilev Ballets Russes, and Robbins making ''Fancy Free'' for Ballet Theater when he was 26.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wheeldon's Boston assignment, his third new work for the company since the 1999 productions of ''The Firebird'' and ''Corybantic Ecstasies,'' shares the program with Daniel Pelzig's ''Resurrection,'' a new work set to Samuel Barber's Concerto for Cello and Orchestra. ''The Four Seasons'' is one of many premieres on Mr. Wheeldon's dance card this year. Since last spring, when he announced he was retiring from performing to concentrate on making ballets, he has created works for his home company, the City Ballet, as well as for the San Francisco Ballet, the Royal Ballet of London and a workshop presentation of a Marvin Hamlisch-John Guare musical, ''The Sweet Smell of Success,'' directed by Nicholas Hytner. The musical, based on the film of the same name, is to have its preview in Chicago in December 2001 and to open in New York in 2002. Mr. Wheeldon shared the choreography credit with Susan Stroman in the recent film ''Center Stage,'' also directed by Mr. Hytner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wheeldon's 10-year dancing career started when he joined the Royal Ballet of England in 1991. Two years later, after recovering from an injury that sidelined him in London, he arrived in New York, where he knew practically no one. He showed up at City Ballet to take a guest class and within two days was invited into its corps de ballet. ''It was fate,'' he says. ''I hadn't even seen the Statue of Liberty yet.''  It was also fateful, perhaps, that Peter Martins, the company's ballet master in chief, happened to be watching class that day to audition a different young man.</p>
        <p>While a corps de ballet member of City Ballet, Mr. Wheeldon created his first work for the School of American Ballet, which won him the Mae L. Wien Award for choreography in 1996.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Ringer, a principal dancer with the company, stepped into the leading role of another Wheeldon work, ''Mercurial Manuevers,'' last spring. She remembers when Mr. Wheeldon joined the company: ''All of a sudden this new boy was here. He looked 12. He was so open and friendly. And then he started dancing, and we were amazed at what a beautiful dancer he was. Any time there was a five-minute break, if he had any energy, he would get up and do some choreography. He'd bring a girl over and say, 'Try this.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wheeldon did not come to America unprepared. Born in Yeovil, Somerset, in southwest England, he was enrolled at the East Coker Ballet School at the age of 7 after having seen -- and been enchanted by -- a Royal Ballet touring performance of ''La Fille Mal Gardee.'' As he remembers his early classes, he was ''the only boy in what seemed like a forest of girls in pink.''</p>
        <p>Within a year he was accepted at the Royal Ballet School in the junior division, progressing to residential status at age 11. He had a banner year when he graduated from the school into the company at 17, won the gold medal at the Prix de Lausanne and received the school's Ursula Moreton Prize for Choreography. His interest in making dances had been fostered at the school from the start. Anthony Dowell, the artistic director of the Royal Ballet, keeps framed above his desk a program that Mr. Wheeldon designed at 11 to accompany one of his early choreography projects.</p>
        <p>Despite the gold medal, his two years dancing with the Royal Ballet were not easy; he suffered many injuries. ''I had weak ankles,'' he explains.</p>
        <p>But Kenneth MacMillan had been observing his progress and encouraged him as both performer and fledgling choreographer. Cast in MacMillan's controversial last work,  ''The Judas Tree,'' about the gang rape of a young woman on an industrial site, Mr. Wheeldon remembers it as ''a strange experience for a 17-year-old, watching this old, very bizarre, rather sickly Kenneth creating this twisted story.''</p>
        <p>''I'd literally just graduated from the Royal Ballet School, having just danced Balanchine's 'Valse Fantaisie' there,'' he says. ''That's when I first knew I wanted to explore American dance more.''</p>
        <p>MacMillan's death at the theater  during a performance of his ''Mayerling,'' while Mr. Wheeldon was onstage in its cast, was a blow to the young dancer. ''I was disheartened.'' he says. ''Not to say that my move to America might not have happened without it.'' In a similar way, Robbins's death after Mr. Wheeldon had worked with him often at City Ballet was another barrier, he says: ''I learned quite a lot from watching him choreograph.''</p>
        <p>The decision to concentrate on choreography came for many reasons. ''I had wanted to be a super dancer,'' he explains. ''I wanted it quite badly until I was promoted to soloist at New York City Ballet in 1999. Then it seemed to me I had reached the point that there was no looking back. As a dancer I had quite a lot of problems partnering. I wanted to be able to turn, to jump, but there comes a time in your career when you have to assess the situation. You grow up.''</p>
        <p>His choreography has gained wide attention; as early as 1996 he was on the cover of Dance Magazine. Anna Kisselgoff wrote in The New York Times in May: ''No ballet choreographer of his generation can match his imaginative use of the classical vocabulary.'' Anna-Marie Holmes, the artistic director of the Boston Ballet, says: ''I'll help him his whole career, any way I can. I'm thrilled that I got him here.''</p>
        <p>Still, there are dissenting voices. Jann Parry, a British dance critic, commented on Mr. Wheeldon's progress in a review of his ballet ''There Where She Loves'': ''He rarely seems to deliver more, or other than required -- and if he doesn't overreach himself in his 20's, how will he dare to do so later?'' She went on to say of the ballet that ''as an examination of how things are between men and women in love, it barely skims the surface.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wheeldon admits he has much to learn. ''I can go to City Ballet every night now that I'm not a dancer and study those fantastic works,'' he says. ''I know how it feels to be dancing, to be riding on top of the music, underneath the music, dancing through the music. There's nothing like dancing in a Balanchine ballet because you really just become the music. But you can't stand back from it when you're amongst a corps of 38 or 40 dancers at the back of the stage, concentrating on your counts. I'm looking forward to learning the repertoire from an audience and choreographic point of view.''</p>
        <p>After he finishes ''The Four Seasons'' in Boston, Mr. Wheeldon will take a monthlong break to settle into a newly purchased one-bedroom condominium in the Chelsea section of Manhattan, which he shares with his partner, Jock Soto, a principal dancer with City Ballet. Then, after spending November and December rehearsing a new work for a January premiere for City Ballet, where he has been appointed artist in residence, he travels to Calgary, Alberta, to choreograph ''A Midsummer Night's Dream'' for the Alberta Ballet. From there, it's on to Hamburg to make a work for John Neumeier's company, before returning to City Ballet to choreograph still another ballet for the spring season.</p>
        <p>He is booked to work on ''The Sweet Smell of Success,'' with a ballet due on his contract with Boston for 2001-2002 season.</p>
        <p>It's no wonder he says ''a year doesn't seem like a very long time.''</p>
        <p>DANCE Iris Fanger, director of the Harvard Summer Dance Center from 1977 to 1995, writes frequently about dance and theater for The Christian Science Monitor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Iris Fanger, director of the Harvard Summer Dance Center from 1977 to 1995, writes frequently about dance and theater for The Christian Science Monitor.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
