<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jets Gird For Battle With Bucs' Defence</title>
    <meta content="Y24JET$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/sports/24JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233395"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E6D8163AF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jets Gird For Battle With Bucs' Defence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was facetiously suggested at some point during the cacophonous past week that the real fun would be if Keyshawn Johnson played defense, too, so that he could spend today trying to jam Wayne Chrebet all the way into the grass of Raymond James Stadium in Tampa, Fla.</p>
        <p>As if Tampa Bay's defense was not scary enough. The dirty little secret of today's game between the undefeated Jets and Buccaneers is that while Johnson may present a huge challenge to audio technicians everywhere, he is not, by far, the greatest threat to the Jets' chances of going 4-0. Johnson may have provided the oratorical background dissonance, but it is the Tampa Bay defense, which Jets Coach Al Groh compared last week to Pittsburgh's Steel Curtain of the 1970's, that will surely decide this game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was facetiously suggested at some point during the cacophonous past week that the real fun would be if Keyshawn Johnson played defense, too, so that he could spend today trying to jam Wayne Chrebet all the way into the grass of Raymond James Stadium in Tampa, Fla.</p>
        <p>As if Tampa Bay's defense was not scary enough. The dirty little secret of today's game between the undefeated Jets and Buccaneers is that while Johnson may present a huge challenge to audio technicians everywhere, he is not, by far, the greatest threat to the Jets' chances of going 4-0. Johnson may have provided the oratorical background dissonance, but it is the Tampa Bay defense, which Jets Coach Al Groh compared last week to Pittsburgh's Steel Curtain of the 1970's, that will surely decide this game.</p>
        <p>''It has been tough to score against Tampa Bay,'' Groh said. ''There has been only one true offensive touchdown scored against them.''</p>
        <p>That came in the game against New England. Two other touchdowns scored against the Bucs this season came on a punt return by New England and a desperation pass by Detroit.</p>
        <p>The Buccaneers' defense will swarm to the ball today with all of the ferocity of the microphones encircling Johnson. Though ranked third in the league, it is the most feared unit in the game. The Bucs have the defending defensive player of the year in lineman Warren Sapp, who has a league-leading five-and-a-half sacks, and they have cornered the market on the league's defensive player of the week award, winning it all three weeks this season.</p>
        <p>The unit has 18 sacks in three games, putting it on pace for 96 this season; that would obliterate the record of 72, set by the 1984 Chicago Bears. And the defense has allowed the Bucs' offense, considered the weak link of the team, to outscore opponents by 93-26, the second-fewest points allowed in the league.</p>
        <p>The Tampa Bay defense says that if the offense scores just 17 points a game, it can do the rest. Seventeen points is 11 fewer than the 1985 Bears gave their vaunted defense to work with. It is 8 fewer than the Steel Curtain got in the 1970's, as the Steelers won four Super Bowls.</p>
        <p>Jets center Kevin Mawae said Tampa Bay had the best defense in the league. Groh went further.</p>
        <p>''This team certainly has the look of a Super Bowl team,'' Groh said. ''The team looks in style similar to the Pittsburgh teams when they were on their championship runs. The cornerstone of the team is defense built on speed and explosiveness and disruption. You see some of the same type of players, whether it was Jack Ham playing outside linebacker and now it's Derrick Brooks. Whether it was Mean Joe Greene disrupting things in the middle and now it's Warren Sapp. Whether it was the hard-hitting guys in the secondary, be it Mel Blount and now it's John Lynch and Ronde Barber as the blitzer.''</p>
        <p>This all comes at a time when the Jets' offense continues to start and stall like a balky car. Fourteen of the Jets' points against Buffalo -- the best defense the Jets have faced this season -- were a result of a desperation pass at the end of the first half and a kickoff return by Kevin Williams. And quarterback Vinny Testaverde admitted last week that he was having trouble reading some defenses, particularly corner and safety blitz packages that are being disguised in ways different from what he was used to seeing in 1998. That could play right into the Bucs' plans: Barber, a cornerback, has three and a half sacks.</p>
        <p>The Jets discovered the formula for facing a great defense last week, when they played Buffalo, which finished last season ranked No. 1. The secret: do not fall far behind and establish the run. That means blocking Sapp, who has exceptional mobility for someone so large.</p>
        <p>Jets running back Curtis Martin, the league's second-leading rusher, carved out 84 yards against the Bills' defense, which had been giving up just 46.5 rushing yards a game. Martin said he would prefer to run right at Sapp, rather than around him.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if that's better or not,'' Martin said. ''He can disrupt the entire offense. They run around and they all get to the ball. You need just one guy making the tackle. There's always two, three, four, five, six guys on one tackle.''</p>
        <p>If Tampa Bay gets a quick lead, it will force the Jets to start throwing the ball more and relying on Martin less. That would give the Bucs the freedom to rush the passer continually. Ask the Lions' Charlie Batch what that was like. The Bucs led Detroit by 11 points in the second half, so he was forced to throw on all but two second-half plays. The result: he was sacked six times in the second half. The Jets have given up only two sacks so far this season.</p>
        <p>''We're not a line that's going to back down from anyone,'' Jets guard Randy Thomas said. ''We work too hard to go out there and make guys look real good.''</p>
        <p>Tampa Bay's defense looks just fine on its own.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
