<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Automotive Ecosystem Proves Fragile</title>
    <meta content="24TIRE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/24/business/24TIRE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233319"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone/firestone Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maynard, Micheline</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD61E3BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1117" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Automotive Ecosystem Proves Fragile</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELINE MAYNARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maynard, Micheline</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article assesses adverse impact on major automotive parts suppliers as result of Firestone tire recall; photo; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE fallout from the Firestone tire recall is rattling many of the biggest automotive parts suppliers, who are already dealing with weaker sales, cost-cutting demands and other pressures.</p>
        <p>The sector was beset by earnings warnings last week from several major players, all of which count Ford Motor, which had many of the recalled tires on its sport utility vehicles, as a major customer. Dana, TRW, Visteon, Tower Automotive, Eaton, Lear, ArvinMeritor and Dura Automotive all said third-quarter profits would be reduced from earlier estimates, partly because Ford halted production for three weeks in August and September at three truck plants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE fallout from the Firestone tire recall is rattling many of the biggest automotive parts suppliers, who are already dealing with weaker sales, cost-cutting demands and other pressures.</p>
        <p>The sector was beset by earnings warnings last week from several major players, all of which count Ford Motor, which had many of the recalled tires on its sport utility vehicles, as a major customer. Dana, TRW, Visteon, Tower Automotive, Eaton, Lear, ArvinMeritor and Dura Automotive all said third-quarter profits would be reduced from earlier estimates, partly because Ford halted production for three weeks in August and September at three truck plants.</p>
        <p>Ford took the action to divert tires that would have been installed on S.U.V.'s and pickup trucks built at the plants to dealers for use as replacements for some of the 6.5 million tires Firestone recalled on Aug. 9 for possible defective tread.</p>
        <p>The automaker collected 100,000 tires by shutting plants in Edison, N.J., Hazelwood, Ky., and St. Paul. Operations at the factories resumed last Monday. Ford expects to make up production of the 23,500 Ford Ranger pickups lost to the shutdown but will not recover production of 15,000 Explorers and Mercury Mountaineers.</p>
        <p>The production cuts, although hardly severe in themselves, were enough to hurt many parts suppliers, forcing them to trim their output in turn.</p>
        <p>Summer is always costly for parts makers and auto companies because they make big investments in changeovers for the new model year, which begins in October.</p>
        <p>But this year, there have been other complications. Companies with European operations, like Dana and TRW, have been hurt by the weak euro and currency fluctuations. Companies that supply manufacturers of heavy-duty trucks, like ArvinMeritor and Borg-Warner, have seen a drop in business  as the market softened. Federal Mogul, which makes engine parts, has felt the heat in both areas. Last week, it announced that its chief executive, Richard Snell, had resigned and that third-quarter earnings would fall below expectations.</p>
        <p>And all the companies are facing pressure from the major automakers to keep a lid on prices. General Motors and DaimlerChrysler, in particular, have started extensive cost-cutting drives in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>Ford's move only heightened suppliers' misery, said Joseph Phillippi, an analyst at PaineWebber. ''It's a horrific confluence of economic events,'' he said. Gary Corrigan, a Dana spokesman, added: ''Generally bad news comes in threes. This time it didn't come in three, it came in four.''</p>
        <p>In many cases, the Ford situation will probably have only minor effects on suppliers' stock prices. But it highlights how dependent those companies still are on their key customers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Phillippi said the Ford cutback magnified the pitfalls of the industry's shift in the 1990's to just-in-time delivery systems.</p>
        <p>For most of the 20th century, parts makers generally kept plants humming year-round, filling orders from the automakers that were placed before the start of each model year. Deliveries were made daily or weekly. Any parts not needed immediately were kept in auto company warehouses or at the parts makers' own depots.</p>
        <p>But following the lead of Japanese rivals, American automakers changed their factories over the last 10 years to align production more closely with sales. They now depend on frequent supplies of parts -- like seats, steering wheels and engines -- which often arrive at factories only hours before they are to be installed.</p>
        <p>Automakers have saved billions of dollars over the years by not having excess inventory. But if production stops at an auto plant, parts shipments stop, too, and parts production ceases almost automatically.</p>
        <p>The brief Ford shutdown forced Dana to curtail production at plants in Fort Wayne, Ind., Cape Girardeau, Mo., and Pottstown, Pa., resulting in the layoff of 2,000 workers. Dana does not keep its parts plants running for more than a week after a closing at an auto factory it supplies, Mr. Corrigan said.</p>
        <p>Analysts are watching the Firestone recall to see if Ford plans more closures, which could then affect fourth-quarter earnings. But Darren Kimball, an analyst at Lehman Brothers, said he was not expecting the company to take further action, now that tire companies like Goodyear Tire and Rubber and Michelin have stepped up production of replacements for Firestone tires.</p>
        <p>''People are speculating as to where the next piece of bad news will come from,'' Mr. Kimball said. But he said he thought most of the announcements had already been made.</p>
        <p>Indeed, some company executives privately attribute the flood of warnings last week to the idea of safety in numbers. They theorize that investors are less likely to punish any one company for acknowledging that its results will fall short if many companies in the sector are affected.</p>
        <p>''Once the storm clouds pass, you'll see some companies trading at extremely cheap valuations,'' Mr. Kimball said. His top pick is Delphi Automotive Systems, which  was part of G.M. until its spinoff in 1999.</p>
        <p>ABOUT 70 percent of Delphi's business came from G.M. this year, versus 76 percent in 1999, said Steve Gaut, a Delphi spokesman. He said Delphi was diversifying beyond G.M. and the auto industry in general. It now sells cellular phone components to Ericsson of Sweden, speedometers to Harley-Davidson and wiring harnesses to Boeing. Delphi has said it expects to meet analysts' third-quarter projections.</p>
        <p>Kenneth Blaschke, an analyst at Deutsche Bank Alex. Brown, said he sees strong growth potential for Johnson Controls, a maker of seats and auto interiors, which said last week that its fiscal fourth-quarter earnings, to be reported in October, would exceed analysts' estimates by 16 percent.</p>
        <p>Johnson Controls' business is divided almost evenly among Ford, G.M. and DaimlerChrysler. Mr. Phillippi of PaineWebber sees that as a strong selling point for the stock.</p>
        <p>With the Ford situation seemingly past, Mr. Phillippi said he expected to see many parts makers bounce back later this year. ''This is very much of a short-term issue,'' he said. ''Generally, we think we're through the worst of that.''</p>
        <p>INVESTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
