<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Gardeners, Learning Season</title>
    <meta content="24PLAN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ginsburg, Elisabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7D6103BF937A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1235" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Gardeners, Learning Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH GINSBURG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ginsburg, Elisabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sampling of local horticulture events as growing season comes to end in New Jersey (Special Issue: Entertainment) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DAVID gardeners know that fall is a time to get back out into the beds and borders after the dog days of summer.  The weeds grow, rain or shine, and all those garden center bargains have to be planted before the nights begin to get frosty. Then there are the bulbs. If you ordered in bulk in July, you can count on spending September and October digging holes.  And even after the bulbs and the perennials have been safely put to bed, there is the fall cleanup to be done.</p>
        <p>Inevitably though, there will come a time when even the most fanatical gardener decides to hang up the tools and take a well-deserved rest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DAVID gardeners know that fall is a time to get back out into the beds and borders after the dog days of summer.  The weeds grow, rain or shine, and all those garden center bargains have to be planted before the nights begin to get frosty. Then there are the bulbs. If you ordered in bulk in July, you can count on spending September and October digging holes.  And even after the bulbs and the perennials have been safely put to bed, there is the fall cleanup to be done.</p>
        <p>Inevitably though, there will come a time when even the most fanatical gardener decides to hang up the tools and take a well-deserved rest.</p>
        <p>October, November and December are great months for meeting other gardeners, learning and savoring the harvest. Specialized plant societies, botanical gardens and arboreta in the region put on a variety of events, lectures, classes and shows open to the public. Attending is a great way to stay in touch with the garden without getting your fingernails dirty.</p>
        <p>Here is a sampling of what is going on in local horticulture as the growing season winds to a close.</p>
        <p>African Violets And Gesneriads</p>
        <p>Many gardeners keep the horticultural flame burning during the winter with African violets and other members of the gesneriad family.  The Long Island Chapter of the American Gloxinia and Gesneriad Society will present a session on creating floral designs with gesneriads at their free monthly meeting, Oct. 14. The chapter's meetings take place the second Saturday of each month at Clark Botanic Gardens, 193 I. U. Willets Road, Albertson, N.Y., and start at noon with a plant sale.  For further information, contact Paul Susi at starz@worldnet.att.net, or Marcia Degner at bdegner@redconnect.net, or call the Botanic Gardens, (516) 484-2208.</p>
        <p>Violets, gloxinias and other gesneriads will also be in the spotlight this fall at the Frelinghuysen Arboretum, in Morristown, next Sunday from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. the Frelinghuysen Arboretum Gesneriad Show will showcase plants in this family, with exhibits, crafts, and a plant sale.  On Saturday Nov. 4, from 1:30 p.m. to 5 p.m., and on Sunday Nov. 5 from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m., the arboretum will be the site of the Tristate African Violet Council Judges' Show, including horticulture, design and special exhibits divisions. For information on either show, call the arboretum, (973) 326-7600.</p>
        <p>Violets, gloxinias and other gesneriads will also be in the spotlight twice this fall at the Frelinghuysen  Arboretum in Morristown; On Oct. 1, from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m., the Frelinghuysen Arboretum Gesneriad Society will be holding its annual show and plant sale, ''Gesneriads Get My Vote.'' The show will feature plants in this family, with exhibits, crafts and a plant sale. Information: Jeanne Katzenstein, (973) 627-2755 or jkatzenste@aol.com.</p>
        <p>Chrysanthemums</p>
        <p>Chrysanthemums are the longtime stars of the fall garden. See them in their glory when the Planting Fields Arboretum in Oyster Bay, N.Y., plays host to the Chrysanthemum Show on Oct. 7 and 8 from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. The show will feature exhibits and demonstrations on all aspects of chrysanthemum culture and arrangement, with plants available for sale. For information, call the arboretum, (516) 922-9201.</p>
        <p>Garden State mum fanciers will want to mark their calendars for Oct. 7 and 8, the dates of the New Jersey State Chrysanthemum Show at the Frelinghuysen Arboretum in Morristown. Mums of all types and colors will be exhibited, judged, discussed and sold both days from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. For information, call the Frelinghuysen Arboretum at (973) 326-7600.</p>
        <p>Herbs</p>
        <p>New Jersey herb aficionados can indulge their love of useful plants at monthly meetings of the Northern New Jersey Unit of the Herb Society of America; meetings are held on Thursdays from 10:30 a.m. to 1 p.m. at the Frelinghuysen Arboretum in  Morristown. On Oct. 12, the topic will be ''Making Dried Wreaths Extraordinaire.'' November will find members considering ''Herbal Lotions, Creams and Tinctures.'' For information, contact Betty Robrecht at (908) 769-5640.</p>
        <p>Orchids</p>
        <p>The love of orchids knows no season. Celebrate it at the American Orchid Society's Joint Presidents Council Orchid Speakers Day, an event for orchid fanciers from all over the tristate area on Nov. 4, from 8:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. The conference, presented by affiliated societies in the tristate area, is designed to bring together orchid authorities to discuss specific aspects of orchid culture and scholarship, according to a spokesman, Joe Reider. Speakers scheduled to appear include Pedro J. Martinez (''Indigenous Orchids of Venezuela''), H. P. Norton (''Phaleonopsis Hybrids''), Karsten Woodrich (''Indigenous Orchids of South Africa'') and Dr. Kim Wing Yam (''Orchids of the Singapore Botanical Garden''). Advance registration is required. To register send $30 per person, plus name, address, telephone number and e-mail address (if applicable) to Joe Reider Jr., 94-62 217th Street, Queens Village, N.Y., 11428. For information, call Mr. Reider at (718) 776-0929.</p>
        <p>Rhododendrons</p>
        <p>Rhododendron enthusiasts are almost as numerous as the plants that they admire, and so are rhododendron-related events this fall.</p>
        <p>The New York chapter of the American Rhododendron Society meets on the third Thursday of each month at 8 p.m. at Planting Fields Arboretum in Oyster Bay. Dr. Steve Krebs, an Ohio-based rhododendron expert, will speak Oct. 19 about ''Rhododendron Research at the Holden Arboretum.'' On Nov. 16, the speaker will be Bud Gehnrich. His topic, after a recent horticulture-related trip to North Carolina, will be ''Seeking Our Native American Azaleas.'' For information on the New York chapter and its activities, contact Jim Fry, (631) 754-2412.</p>
        <p>Dr. Krebs is also speaking in New Jersey at the First Presbyterian Church of Hightstown, 320 North Main Street, Hightstown, on Oct. 18 at 8 p.m. in an appearance sponsored jointly by the Princeton and New York chapters of the American Rhododendron Society. For information on either event, contact Henry Schannen, (732) 833-1439.</p>
        <p>Arboretums</p>
        <p>Fall is Harvest Festival time at Reeves Reed Arboretum in Summit.  The family-friendly affair will be  Oct. 14 from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Many of the activities will be geared to children, with a pumpkin patch where little ones can select their own pumpkins and a hay maze to get (temporarily) lost in. Pony rides, face painting and a petting zoo will also be featured. Adults can enjoy the fall blooms and foliage on the arboretum property. Admission to the festival is $5 a person, with children under 5 admitted free.</p>
        <p>The arboretum will also offer two trips for adults this fall. The first, an excursion to the Staten Island Arboretum and Chinese Scholar's Garden will take place Thursday. Participants will leave from the arboretum at 8:15 a.m. and return about 4:30 p.m. A second trip, to Grounds for Sculpture, the J. Seward Johnson sculpture collection in Princeton, is scheduled for Nov. 7. Departure will take place at 8:30 a.m., with an estimated return at 5:15 p.m.</p>
        <p>To make reservations for either of the two trips, or to find out more  about the Reeves-Reed's schedule of fall classes for children and adults, call (908) 273-8787.</p>
        <p>The Freylinghusen Aboretum in Morristown has already had its big fall harvest show. But it still has a full schedule of classes. Information: (973) 326-7600.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
