<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Battleground to ATM, Such Is New Jersey's Fate</title>
    <meta content="15POL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238851"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peterson, Iver</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5DE163FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Battleground to ATM, Such Is New Jersey's Fate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Iver Peterson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Peterson, Iver</byline>
      <dateline>PRINCETON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iver Peterson On Politics column explores reasons for New Jersey's decline as important state in presidential politics (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was a time when New Jersey mattered in presidential politics.</p>
        <p>Last year about this time, this state was on the list of battlegrounds, up there with Michigan and Pennsylvania and Ohio and the other states where no vote could be taken for granted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was a time when New Jersey mattered in presidential politics.</p>
        <p>Last year about this time, this state was on the list of battlegrounds, up there with Michigan and Pennsylvania and Ohio and the other states where no vote could be taken for granted.</p>
        <p>It was good to be wanted -- while it lasted -- and a lot of people were looking forward to a fight for the heart of New Jersey: newspapers and cable television stations hungry for advertising, politicians hoping for a moment in the limelight, everyone thinking of some generous act Congress might use to swing our votes.</p>
        <p>No longer.</p>
        <p>The campaign of Gov. George W. Bush of Texas has all but conceded New Jersey to the Democrats, just the way it gave up on New York and Massachusetts at the beginning of the game, and that means that the Democrats take New Jersey's 15 electoral votes for granted. Mr. Bush has not pleaded for votes in New Jersey since attending a fund-raising event during the summer, and the same goes for the rest of the party heavyweights, who use the state as an ATM but not as a hunting ground for votes.</p>
        <p>Dick Cheney, Mr. Bush's vice presidential running mate, was in the state for an appearance recently, of course, and thousands of commuters to the seashore will no doubt go to the polls next month with the memory of Vice President Al Gore shutting down the Garden State Parkway in rush hour so he could get to Jon Bon Jovi's $850,000 fund raiser for him.</p>
        <p>''That's all we are,'' said Ross K. Baker, a political scientist at Rutgers, ''an extractive colony for political fund raising.''</p>
        <p>How did we go from being loved for our votes to just being hit up for cash? And how can the Republicans ignore a state that has voted for the winner in every election but three in this century? Even when its popular vote went with the loser, it was a Republican loser: Charles Evans Hughes in 1916, Thomas E. Dewey in 1948 and Gerald R. Ford in 1976.</p>
        <p>There seem to be plenty of answers for why a state that errs on the side of Republicanism should be ignored by that very same party this year.</p>
        <p>David Rebovich, a political scientist at Rider University, says that New Jersey Republicanism may be in bad odor with the rest of the party. Although it has a Republican governor and a Republican-controlled statehouse, the state's Republican Party is distinctly liberal by, say, Texas standards, and it got a black eye in the Iowa Republican debates last year when the conservative Gary L. Bauer, otherwise forgotten, demanded that Mr. Bush promise to never, ever pick Governor Whitman as a running mate.</p>
        <p>It makes sense that if a state's voters are pushing its conservative party increasingly to the left, Democrats will eventually be the beneficiary. Mr. Baker says Mrs. Whitman's narrow re-election victory in 1997 over a virtually unknown Democratic opponent -- Mayor James E. McGreevey of Woodbridge, and Robert G. Torricelli's defeat of Richard A. Zimmer, a Republican, in their hotly contested Senate race in 1996, indicates a state that is slowly drifting leftward toward New York and the rest of the Northeast, and away from the central Atlantic states' more conservative traditions.</p>
        <p>''I think this may portend a longer-term trend in which New Jersey has become more like New York,'' Mr. Baker said. ''This election could mark the final colonization of New Jersey by New York.''</p>
        <p>Roger A. Bodman, a Republican strategist who ran two successful Republican presidential campaigns in New Jersey in 1984 and 1988, also blames the neighbor, although he does not think the state has been fatally infected by liberal tendencies.</p>
        <p>''George Bush didn't write off New Jersey,'' Mr. Bodman said. ''He wrote off New York and the New York media market. When you have a limited amount of money, $68 million or whatever it is, it comes down to a fiscal decision.''</p>
        <p>And any decision to buy expensive New York television advertising to reach New Jerseyans alone went out the window when Mr. Gore chose Senator Joe Lieberman of Connecticut, thereby undercutting the Bush's ancestral ties to Connecticut and making any media campaigns there pointless.</p>
        <p>As for New Jersey swinging to the Democrats, Mr. Bodman pointed out that Ross Perot's inroads among conservative voters in the state in 1992 probably had as much to do with Bill Clinton winning New Jersey in 1992 as the President's appeal, noting in previous years the state went with the Republican winner in three straight Presidential elections.</p>
        <p>So will the politicians come back some day. Will New Jersey matter again?</p>
        <p>''I certainly hope so,'' Mr. Bodman  said.</p>
        <p>ON POLITICS Iver Peterson reports from New Jersey for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Iver Peterson reports from New Jersey for The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
