<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Diverse Italian Fare, Highlighted by Calamari</title>
    <meta content="15DINE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238845"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Amalfi Grille (New Haven, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Patricia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E7DF163FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Diverse Italian Fare, Highlighted by Calamari</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooks, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia Brooks reviews Amalfi Grille in New Haven, Conn (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AROUND the corner from the Shubert theater and within a few blocks of the Yale University campus, art museums and Yale Repertory Theater, is the Amalfi Grille, one of New Haven's newest Italian restaurants.</p>
        <p>Now that the northern Italian food craze seems to have run its course, southern Italian cooking may be in again. As in Capri, and now Amalfi. Actually, many Italian restaurateurs have learned that diners enjoy mixing and matching regions. Thus risotto, gnocchi, beef carpaccio and polenta are as prevalent on southern Italian menus today as on those of the north. Gone are the days when a request for pesto elicited a ''Say what?'' at many of Connecticut's old Neapolitan restaurants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AROUND the corner from the Shubert theater and within a few blocks of the Yale University campus, art museums and Yale Repertory Theater, is the Amalfi Grille, one of New Haven's newest Italian restaurants.</p>
        <p>Now that the northern Italian food craze seems to have run its course, southern Italian cooking may be in again. As in Capri, and now Amalfi. Actually, many Italian restaurateurs have learned that diners enjoy mixing and matching regions. Thus risotto, gnocchi, beef carpaccio and polenta are as prevalent on southern Italian menus today as on those of the north. Gone are the days when a request for pesto elicited a ''Say what?'' at many of Connecticut's old Neapolitan restaurants.</p>
        <p>The Amalfi Grille menu reflects this recent north-south diversity. But if one thing stands out when perusing the menu it is the chef's penchant for calamari. Three squid dishes highlight the appetizer list, with two more as entrees.</p>
        <p>In fact, one of our best starters was New York style calamari, a mammoth mound of ever-so-lightly floured-and-fried squid rings, enveloped by a jaunty, well-spiced fra diavolo sauce. Tender and flavorful, the squid in their compatible sauce were a welcome change from the deep-fried ones (on the menu as D'Orati, also good).</p>
        <p>Other appetizers we savored were two versions of meaty grilled portobello mushrooms: Gorgonzola (piqued by the tangy melted cheese) and Amalfi (in an anchovy sauce sparked with tomato and onion).</p>
        <p>Polenta Valrellina consisted of a large plateful of soupy polenta, cooked soft as cornmeal mush, with a barely perceptible hint of goat cheese and a few shrimp bits on top. The dish was as bland as nursery food, but appealing in its way.</p>
        <p>Our most winning entree was gnocchi pesto. Tiny dumpling-pillows, light and delicate, were enshrouded by a voluptuously creamy pesto sauce, garnished with fresh basil leaves. Another dish, gnocchi Sorrentino, with mozzarella and basil in a marinara sauce, was tasty too, but definitely second-string to the excellent gnocchi pesto.</p>
        <p>Veal selvatici and chicken breast selvatici were both enlivened by a succulent cognac, shallot cream sauce. The chicken had the edge for us because of added wild mushrooms.</p>
        <p>Grilled pork chop, a special, was sizable (a characteristic of Amalfi entrees), but its dry, chewy, fibrous texture really needed a sauce. This should have been a given, as saucing seems to be an Amalfi Grille forte. The dish was helped only marginally by the accompaniment of flavorful roasted potato boats. A better entree choice was New York strip pizzaiola, tender beef in a lusty, garlicky marinara sauce.</p>
        <p>All entrees came with a house salad with fresh, crisp greens, a choice of several zippy dressings, a starch (potato or pasta) and fresh seasonal vegetables.</p>
        <p>We found tour desserts, especially the dense carrot cake and chocolate truffle cake, to be commercial-tasting and skippable.</p>
        <p>For $62.80, two of us dined on three courses apiece, before tax, tip or drinks. This represents considerable value, with only one entree -- filet mignon -- as much as $19.95, most of the others in the mid-teens. The medium-small, well-chosen, affordable wine list (from $19) is strong on Italian vintages, with various French and California choices as well.</p>
        <p>For a pleasant, highly civilized dining experience, Amalfi Grille is an elegant change from some of the highly charged hot spots that have been opening lately. And the price is certainly right.</p>
        <p>Comings and Goings</p>
        <p>Le Bistro des Amis in Westport has gone, but in its place is another French restaurant, Tartine, whose chef was formerly at Chez Noue in Ridgefield. . . . White Oak Bistro in New Canaan has new ownership, a new chef and new name, 62 Main (which is also its location). . . . Also in New Canaan, Tandoori, which opened last spring, has already changed its menu from Indian-Malaysian back to regular Indian.</p>
        <p>Amalfi Grille  196 Crown Street, New Haven.  (203) 777-4745</p>
        <p>Good</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Wall sconces and chandeliers, ivory-colored walls, stately chairs and dark wood room dividers. Noise level: Well-spaced tables and carpeting help keep level low.  SERVICE -- Warm and professional.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Beef carpaccio Toscano, New York style calamari,  polenta Valrellina, portobello Amalfi, portobello Valvellina, gnocchi pesto, New York strip pizzaiola, veal selvatici, chicken breast funghi selvatici.  PRICE RANGE -- Lunch entrees $7.95 to  $10.95, dinner entrees $12.95 to $21.95.  CREDIT CARDS -- Most accepted.  HOURS -- 11:30-2 p.m. Tues.-Fri., 5 to 9:15 (last order taken) Mon.-Sat.  RESERVATIONS -- Accepted.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY -- Street level with restrooms at same level.</p>
        <p>THE RATINGS Extraordinary, Excellent, Very Good, Good, Poor to Satisfactory.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambiance and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
