<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Skintight Clothes in a Skintight Shop</title>
    <meta content="15STAR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/living/15STAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Leather and Leather Goods</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Three Star Leather (Nyc Shop)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hayt, Elizabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leather and Leather Goods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E4DE123FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Skintight Clothes in a Skintight Shop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH HAYT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hayt, Elizabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Three Star Leather, Upper East Side tailor, which specializes in made-to-measure skintight leather pants; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT could have been a scene right out of a Candace Bushnell story. Three 30-something blondes were trying on leather pants, crowding in front of a mirror. Although they didn't know each other, the women had arrived simultaneously at Three Star Leather, an Upper East Side tailor, and were now bonding over the buttery hides.</p>
        <p>''Do I look fat?'' a woman in brown pants asked, turning to study her behind.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT could have been a scene right out of a Candace Bushnell story. Three 30-something blondes were trying on leather pants, crowding in front of a mirror. Although they didn't know each other, the women had arrived simultaneously at Three Star Leather, an Upper East Side tailor, and were now bonding over the buttery hides.</p>
        <p>''Do I look fat?'' a woman in brown pants asked, turning to study her behind.</p>
        <p>''Would these be better with a lower waist and a little flare at the bottom?'' asked another, in black pants.</p>
        <p>''I'm embarrassed to say at my age, I don't own any leather pants,'' confessed the third, in an olive pair. ''There's this pressure because there's all this leather nowadays and you feel like you have to own it. But I didn't like what was out there in terms of the quality and the fit.''</p>
        <p>Three Star Leather has been bursting at the seams among style connoisseurs since it opened three years ago, riding the crest of the leather craze of recent seasons. Once reserved for high-end fashion and western wear, leather is now so common that it's in every store window from Gucci to the Gap.</p>
        <p>As a result, for discerning fashionistas, wearing mainstream leather has become as desirable as taking mass transit to a black-tie affair. They are seeking more upscale leather alternatives at places like Three Star, which specializes in made-to-measure leather pants that fit like a second skin.</p>
        <p>''With so much money out there, everyone knows the latest Gucci or Prada,'' said Katherine Keeney Taveras, manager of Sulka, a luxury men's shop a few blocks up Madison Avenue, which uses Three Star Leather for alterations. ''There's the type of woman who wants something above and beyond what everyone else has. They're the ones going to Three Star.''</p>
        <p>As little known as the whereabouts of the next Fendi sample sale, Three Star Leather is tucked away on the fifth floor of a nondescript office building on Madison Avenue near 67th Street. The 350-square-foot shop is divided into a back workroom, where six Eastern European tailors sit elbow to elbow snipping and hand-stitching swaths of leather, and a front showroom decorated with tear sheets from fashion magazines and jammed with racks of clothing samples, as well as bolts of ostrich and python skins, suede and cowhide. The front room also doubles as a makeshift dressing room, with customers ducking into a curtained corner to try on copies of the latest designer styles.</p>
        <p>The bare-bones interior does not discourage fashion insiders who have learned about the craftsmanship by word of mouth. Throughout the day, personal shoppers appear with their clients for knockoffs of a Ralph Lauren leather jean-style jacket or a Chanel shearling coat with exposed seams, at 30 percent less than the originals. Messengers from boutiques on Madison and Fifth Avenues like Valentino, Yves Saint Laurent and Gucci drop off their most expensive leather coats for alterations. Style slaves who wouldn't be caught dead carrying anything as passe as last season's Prada bowling bag stop by for snug pants to show off perfectly sculptured seats.</p>
        <p>Three Star Leather opened in 1997, four years after Steven Frank, a former store manager for North Beach Leather, a chain, teamed up with one of his company's tailors, Mikhail Payziyev, an immigrant from Uzbekistan. The two men, co-owners of the shop, make an odd pair. With his graying ponytail, Mr. Frank looks like a guest on VH1's ''Behind the Music,'' while Mr. Payziyev, who has a dark mustache, could pass for a physics professor.</p>
        <p>To drum up business when they opened, Mr. Frank walked up and down Madison Avenue, introducing himself to store managers and promising same-day alterations of leather clothing. Joan &amp; David was the first boutique to take him up on his offer. Although Three Star Leather now serves 25 stores and some 200 individual customers, the tailors still offer speedy alterations.</p>
        <p>''Our store is very busy, and our clients want something as soon as possible,'' said Stephanie Leonard, general manager for the Joseph boutiques. ''Three Star can take something apart and put it back in a day or two.''</p>
        <p>Keeping up with fashion trends by browsing the wares of nearby boutiques and studying the patterns of clothing brought to them for alterations, Mr. Frank and Mr. Payziyev are able to make reproductions that could fool even a savvy designer-label hound.</p>
        <p>In early September, Corey Gelman, who owns a dog-wear company, saw a picture of Vogue's editor at large, Andre Leon Talley, in a red ankle-length alligator coat and gave it to Three Star Leather to copy in black leather embossed to look like crocodile. ''It's the height of fashion,'' she said happily of the coat, which cost $1,895, a fraction of what Mr. Talley's alligator coat cost.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frank said he has never seen the demand for leather designs so high since he started working at North Beach Leather in 1984. In 1997, Three Star Leather put together about 25 pairs of custom-made leather pants, which sold for $595 to $895, depending on the style and type of skin.</p>
        <p>This year, it expects to make as many as 300 pairs of pants. In addition, with leather being so popular, more customers are bringing in pants that have stretched and sagged, requiring a nip and tuck after a season of wear and tear.</p>
        <p>''All this leather is being shown, but what happens when you get out of a cab and you rip or gouge your pants?'' Mr. Frank asked. ''That's what we do.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
