<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Year That Was</title>
    <meta content="15SALAMOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salamon, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koppel, Ted</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Off Camera: Private Thoughts Made Public (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E5DB1E3DF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Year That Was</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Julie Salamon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salamon, Julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Julie Salamon reviews book Off Camera: Private Thoughts Made Public by Ted Koppel (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OFF CAMERA</p>
        <p>Private Thoughts Made Public.</p>
        <p>By Ted Koppel.</p>
        <p>320 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OFF CAMERA</p>
        <p>Private Thoughts Made Public.</p>
        <p>By Ted Koppel.</p>
        <p>320 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>FOR 20 years, ''Nightline'' has been a rare achievement in network news -- consistently willing to probe complex stories at length, regardless of how they'll twitch the Nielsen meter. Provocative yet responsible, this idiosyncratic program occasionally behaves as an arbiter as well as reporter of events. Its mainstay has always been Ted Koppel, whose intelligence and piquant interviewing style have set the program's course. His slight aloofness only enhances his credibility. But what works on the tube doesn't necessarily translate into print, as Koppel proves in ''Off Camera,'' his daily diary for 1999, which Alfred A. Knopf is marketing in the shape of a book.</p>
        <p>As he reduces his role at ''Nightline,'' Koppel has decided to get personal, to tell us things he ''would never express on the air'' -- though there's far more mundane detail and pontificating here than insight or revelation. This is a circumspect journal, which seems to have been aimed at publication from the outset. Either that, or Koppel has a peculiar tendency to speak from the mountaintop inside his own head.</p>
        <p>By using the diary form, Koppel apparently felt absolved of any responsibility to connect one entry to the next, or sometimes even one paragraph to the next. Kindly, this could be called an impressionistic approach. Someone less kind (or more rigorous) might call it lazy -- a surprising trait in an obviously industrious man. But what else can explain cutting and pasting a platitudinous speech, as he does on Sept. 16?</p>
        <p>If the book doesn't exactly have a theme, it does have a recurring topic: how the proliferation of news and pseudo-news has affected the nation's increasingly short attention span and vice versa. On Jan. 24, he writes: ''Now, satellite technology and 24-hour cable networks inundate us with every latest development, even as it unfolds. We chew them up and spit them out and, almost immediately, reach for the next morsel.''</p>
        <p>He despairs of this phenomenon, but his book mirrors it. Koppel chews and spits with alarming speed. These dutiful daily minutes of his life tend to run a few paragraphs, and cover a remarkable range, from having his driveway plowed, the Clinton impeachment trial, fishing, Kosovo and a boxing match to ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire'' (he's a fan).</p>
        <p>To be fair (as Koppel might say), he devotes several astute and passionate entries to the Balkan wars and the two trips he took to the region in 1999 for ''Nightline.'' He gives equal time, however, to recalling the touristic glories of a Mediterranean vacation with his wife, Grace Anne, about whom he writes with admirable tenderness. On Nov. 3, in Jerusalem, mixing business and pleasure, they have lunch with Suha Arafat, who is ''smart, hospitable and charming.''</p>
        <p>After much bemoaning of the news industry's deplorable state, the Koppels set off for Ireland, for a luxe biking trip organized by Michael Eisner, chairman of Disney, which owns ABC. Koppel worries about the melding of entertainment and news, writing, on Sept. 20, that he is eager for a ''longer, relaxed conversation'' about this with his boss. Then, for six days, he comments on the wonders of Galway Bay and Ballynahinch, but not on talks with Eisner (though we learn that another media mogul, Barry Diller, the trip's co-host, befriended a Jack Russell terrier).</p>
        <p>Koppel throws a few darts, but at odd targets, scolding Jimmy Carter for publicly criticizing President Clinton's Kosovo strategy. Koppel actually agreed, but thought it was ''tacky'' to ''second-guess'' a fellow member of a ''very distinguished but tiny club.''</p>
        <p>The book's pithy swatches of commentary often read like a series of ''Nightline'' introductions, which may suit television-trained readers. And some people may find it satisfying to learn that even the famous can't crack the bureaucratic indolence of the telephone company. The most revealing thing to emerge from this busy whir, however, is an aging newsman's strangely nave, but also poignant, bewilderment at how swiftly time eradicates the importance of today's events and those who report on them.</p>
        <p>Julie Salamon is a television critic for The Times. Her books include ''The Devil's Candy'' and ''The Net of Dreams.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Julie Salamon is a television critic for The Times. Her books include ''The Devil's Candy'' and ''The Net of Dreams.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
