<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Raising Crops, and Self-Esteem, on a Special Farm</title>
    <meta content="15MAP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238899"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE MAP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">High Point Farm (High Point, Ny)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fountain House (Nyc)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saggese, Charlie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Demasters, Karen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E0DF143FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Raising Crops, and Self-Esteem, on a Special Farm</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN DeMASTERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Demasters, Karen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charlie Saggese, social worker and program coordinator, answers questions about High Point Farm, working farm and retreat staffed by members of Fountain House, nonresidential center in New York City for adults with persistent mental illnesses; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>High Point Farm is a working farm in the extreme northwestern corner of the state next to High Point State Park. But unlike other farms, this 477-acre tract is a retreat that is staffed by members of Fountain House in New York City, a treatment center for adults with persistent mental illnesses. The farm will be open to the public to tour the grounds and view the fall foliage from 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. Oct. 21 and 22 and Oct. 28 and 29. Charlie Saggese, a social worker and program coordinator for High Point Farm, recently talked about Fountain House.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>High Point Farm is a working farm in the extreme northwestern corner of the state next to High Point State Park. But unlike other farms, this 477-acre tract is a retreat that is staffed by members of Fountain House in New York City, a treatment center for adults with persistent mental illnesses. The farm will be open to the public to tour the grounds and view the fall foliage from 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. Oct. 21 and 22 and Oct. 28 and 29. Charlie Saggese, a social worker and program coordinator for High Point Farm, recently talked about Fountain House.</p>
        <p>Q. What is Fountain House?</p>
        <p>A. Fountain House is a nonresidential program for people with persistent mental illnesses. It was the original club house model for psychiatric treatment, which has now been copied by many other treatment centers. Everyone who receives treatment at Fountain House is a member of the club and the staff work for the club members, just like the staff at the Harvard Club work for the members. The members are involved in every aspect of running the house as part of their treatment. The same principle applies at the farm. The members who come here for a day or a week run the farm. Everyone does what he or she is best at, from running the house, to taking care of the animals, to taking care of the orchards, to planting and harvesting the produce from the garden.  Q. How did the program start?</p>
        <p>A. The farm was bequeathed to Fountain House, a not-for-profit organization, by the wealthy parents of one of the club members. The parents of the member saw how much good it did their son to be at their farm and they wanted others at Fountain House to be able to have the same advantage. That was in 1978. The operation was expanded over the last five years. The buildings were renovated and the working part of the farm was re-established.  Q. What do you grow on the farm?</p>
        <p>A. We have four llamas, four alpacas, four cashmere goats and chickens. The fleece is sold or spun. We want to buy a loom and renovate one of the buildings to house it so we can use the thread. Twelve acres is in orchards, mostly apples and a few pears and plums, and in a garden. All of our farming is organic, which is more difficult because you can't just grab a bottle of chemicals if you have a bug problem. We have a chef in New York City who wants to buy organic produce next summer.  Q. What else is on the farm?</p>
        <p>A. Most of the land is woodlands and we have received awards for timber management. Over the years we have had three thinnings and the timber was sold. This brought back the balance to the woodlands. A complete woodshop was donated to us, so now we can make and repair furniture. We have trails through the woods where you can hike. We have the farmhouse and the other buildings that are Adironack-style and a Swiss-style chalet that sleeps 18.</p>
        <p>Q. How does it help club members to stay at the farm?</p>
        <p>A. The farm is a great leveler. The pitfalls of any treatment program is the pedestal effect in which some people are seen as higher or better than others. Here, we work as a team and everyone contributes. It also allows people a wide variety of opportunities to see what they can do. It teaches members to have the wherewithal to overcome the challenges of trying new things.</p>
        <p>Q. Why the open house?</p>
        <p>A. We want to engage the community. The stigma associated with mental illness is the biggest battle we have to face. People are afraid of what they don't know, and they are afraid of people suffering from mental illness. We just want to be another part of the community here.</p>
        <p>KAREN DeMASTERS</p>
        <p>ON THE MAP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
