<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chances Are, You're a Barbarian</title>
    <meta content="15STARLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Star, Alexander</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berman, Morris</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Twilight of American Culture, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E5DB1E3DF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chances Are, You're a Barbarian</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alexander Star</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Star, Alexander</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alexander Star reviews book The Twilight of American Culture by Morris Berman (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Twilight of American Culture</p>
        <p>By Morris Berman.</p>
        <p>205 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $23.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Twilight of American Culture</p>
        <p>By Morris Berman.</p>
        <p>205 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $23.95.</p>
        <p>Morris Berman is best known as the author of a trilogy on human consciousness. He has now devoted a book to a society -- our own -- that he believes is lacking in both humanity and consciousness. Indeed, ''The Twilight of American Culture'' is an impassioned indictment of contemporary life: the ''toxicity'' of corporate capitalism, the ''nakedly sick'' enterprise of deconstruction, the poor spelling of public signs and the ''incomprehensible'' conversation overheard on a Greyhound bus. If you'd like to combine the anti-multinational rage of a black-clad Seattle protester with the mordant cultural despair of a Hilton Kramer or Jacques Barzun, here is your man.</p>
        <p>Relying on the writings of the great pessimist Oswald Spengler as well as on a drawerful of articles from Harper's and other magazines, Berman compares the predicament of contemporary America with that of the Roman Empire in its final days. Just like Rome, the United States suffers from an increasing gap between rich and poor, a teeming bazaar of eccentric faiths and a general dumbing-down of the collective intelligence. Today, democracy means ''the right to shop, or to choose between Wendy's and Burger King,'' while the ''corporate takeover of intellectual property'' has resulted in ''the replacement of intelligent citizens by mindless consumers.'' Despite all of America's entrepreneurial ''dynamism,'' a new dark age is falling. ''For those seduced by noise, toys and technology, the current transformation to a global economy is nothing less than cultural efflorescence. For those who place their values elsewhere . . . the very transformation . . . is ultimately every bit as dark as the early Middle Ages.'' Since he believes that during the Dark Ages ''most people forgot how to read or think,'' this is bad news indeed.</p>
        <p>While Berman asserts that it is futile to battle the corporate oligarchy, he does recommend an alternative way of life that he labels ''the monastic option.'' Like the medieval monks who preserved brittle classical manuscripts on their wind-swept Atlantic retreats, certain new monastic individuals (N.M.I.'s for short) are preparing civilization's eventual revival. In the most interesting portions of his book, Berman cites a number of men and women who ''resist'' the ''global corporate world order'' by boycotting Starbucks and recognizing the difference between ''hype'' and ''reality.'' He admires the Vancouver-based Adbusters magazine and the filmmaker Michael Moore for ''exposing the emptiness of the corporate/commercial way of life''; he admires Earl Shorris's Clemente course for teaching the Great Books to the poor, and The Concord Review for encouraging high school students to produce rigorously researched history papers.</p>
        <p>But does Berman really wish these endeavors success? After all, he champions new monastic individuals for knowing that they ''need to stay out of the public eye,'' and that they are ''likely to be more significant for being marginal.'' Therefore, he questions Shorris's decision to accept federal funding for the Clemente course, and worries that Moore may become merely ''a commodity of an 'alternative' sort.'' Then again, Berman's advocacy of renunciation only goes so far. He sees nothing wrong with his favorite (federally funded) National Public Radio program or with Moore's expose of Nike's C.E.O., Phil Knight: ''From a 'monastic' point of view, it is important for American audiences to see such people close up.'' Visibility is to be avoided, except when it isn't.</p>
        <p>In general, Berman's broad-brush approach to social criticism makes Spengler look like Seurat. Writing about the Dark Ages, he tells us that ''the intellectual disciplines of distinction, definition and dialectic'' were lost. Perhaps Berman should try to find them. It's hard to credit a complaint about the decline of literacy from a writer who speaks of ''a parade of mental theme parks,'' or whose idea of qualifying an argument is to maintain that ''a descent into real barbarism'' is ''certainly possible, and may even occur to some degree toward the end of the 21st century, perhaps for a short period of time.'' With tongue partly in cheek, Berman likes to pronounce impressive-sounding numbers: ''In terms of what's made available via the world of commercial publishing, 96 percent of it is pretty much the same stuff''; ''millions of Americans already don't know the difference between fiction and nonfiction.'' Apparently, the author is among those Americans who see little reason to provide any evidence for their most sweeping statements of fact.</p>
        <p>Alexander Star is the editor of Lingua Franca.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Alexander Star is the editor of Lingua Franca.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
