<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inciting Intellect as Well as Passion</title>
    <meta content="15REAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/arts/15REAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238827"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Petronio, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reardon, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1D61E3CF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1585" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inciting Intellect as Well as Passion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER REARDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reardon, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on dancer/choreographer Stephen Petronio, whose new work, Strange Attractors, will premiere at Joyce Theater; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the final scene of ''Not Garden,'' his 1998 treatment of Dante's ''Inferno,'' the dancer and choreographer Stephen Petronio leaned so far forward that with the help of a harness, he appeared to hover just above the stage in a radiant column of light. In the context of the dance, the image served as a metaphor for redemption and enlightenment, as if he were falling into something deeper. To viewers familiar with Mr. Petronio's blistering brand of expressionism, it also signaled a more profound level of creative prowess.</p>
        <p>A chorus of critics hailed ''Not Garden'' as a turning point for Mr. Petronio, if not an overdue mark of maturity. As his first evening-length dance, it dispensed with his usual gender-bending antics to reveal a capacity for sustained movement exploration and a firm grasp of his compositional tools. Clive Barnes, writing in</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the final scene of ''Not Garden,'' his 1998 treatment of Dante's ''Inferno,'' the dancer and choreographer Stephen Petronio leaned so far forward that with the help of a harness, he appeared to hover just above the stage in a radiant column of light. In the context of the dance, the image served as a metaphor for redemption and enlightenment, as if he were falling into something deeper. To viewers familiar with Mr. Petronio's blistering brand of expressionism, it also signaled a more profound level of creative prowess.</p>
        <p>A chorus of critics hailed ''Not Garden'' as a turning point for Mr. Petronio, if not an overdue mark of maturity. As his first evening-length dance, it dispensed with his usual gender-bending antics to reveal a capacity for sustained movement exploration and a firm grasp of his compositional tools. Clive Barnes, writing in</p>
        <p>Dance Magazine, called it ''the most artistically satisfying and aesthetically integrated work of his that I've seen.''</p>
        <p>Now, despite a rocky spell that left him with a broken foot and a new roster of dancers, Mr. Petronio, 44, is setting his sights even higher. On Tuesday he will return to the Joyce Theater for the premiere of ''Strange Attractors,'' an hourlong dance that deftly shifts between order and chaos. When his company completes its season on Sunday, it will embark on a nine-city American tour.</p>
        <p>A few weeks ago, Mr. Petronio sat in his rooftop garden, six stories above the clamor of the East Village, and expounded on his penchant for coupling formal abstraction with emotional heat.</p>
        <p>''I try to hit the brain center and the pelvic center at the same time,'' he said, flashing a smile. ''The animal and the evolved. Those are the two sides of me in constant battle. I don't believe, as many high structuralists do, that to have a formal aesthetic experience you have to drain yourself of passion.''</p>
        <p>That hybrid sensibility has played especially well in Europe, where he has found his largest and most loyal audience.</p>
        <p>''Stephen is very ambitious, and I mean that in the best way,'' said Val Bourne, the artistic director of Dance Umbrella in London, which has championed Mr. Petronio's work since the mid-1980's. ''Talent is not enough; you need to be tenacious, too. Lots of people flare up and then just burn out. I'm interested in longevity, and Stephen has really hung in there.''</p>
        <p>The son of a truck driver from Nutley, N.J., Mr. Petronio came late to dance, but he brought with him the devotion of a religious convert. In the span of just five years, he saw his first dance performance (Rudolf Nureyev in ''The Sleeping Beauty''), took his first dance class (at Hampshire College in Amherst, Mass.) and became the first man to join the influential troupe led by Trisha Brown (in 1979). After seven years he left to run his own company, but he is still widely considered one of the keenest interpreters of her work.</p>
        <p>Out on his own, though, Mr. Petronio took a few liberties with Ms. Brown's cerebral technique, tarting it up with corsets, speeding up the tempo and pushing the extensions farther out into space. He quickly solidified his reputation for dense, turbulent dances with ''Walk-In,'' a 1986 collage of contrapuntal movement, electronic music by David Linton and photographs found on the street. The piece earned him a New York Dance and Performance Award, known as a Bessie.</p>
        <p>''People often call my work 'violent,' '' said Mr. Petronio, whose swashbuckling look (shaved head, pierced ears) belies his mirthful charisma. ''But the way I see it, crashing out into space is an incredibly affirming experience for a dancer, and it should be for a viewer, too.''</p>
        <p>For ''Strange Attractors,'' his new piece for eight dancers, he enlisted a cadre of artistic collaborators from London. The sculptor Anish Kapoor, who won Britain's Turner Prize in 1991, created a polished aluminum set piece that has been likened to a huge pair of contact lenses. Ghost, the fashion house that outfitted the dancers in ''Not Garden,'' designed most of the costumes. The dance, which consists of a short prelude and two longer acts, also features music by the rock trio Placebo, the minimalist composer Michael Nyman and the hip-hop wunderkind James Lavelle.</p>
        <p>The title ''Strange Attractors'' comes from chaos theory, a branch of math and mechanics that tries to explain how apparently random behavior can occur in a system governed by deterministic laws. The classic example, called the butterfly effect, asks whether a butterfly flapping its wings in Brazil could cause a tornado in Texas. The answer hinges partly on the concept of a strange attractor, which the troupe's program notes define as ''a moving and magnetic focal point in a seemingly chaotic field.''</p>
        <p>''I used the concept of strange attractors in the broadest sense,'' said Mr. Petronio. ''I would establish a focal point -- a dancer, a phrase of movement, an event -- and build more dancing around it. Then I would erase the focal point, or I would shift it across the stage so it's elusive and almost unidentifiable.''</p>
        <p>He also chose the name for its poetic resonance, which evoked the peculiar logic of the human heart. In the first act of ''Strange Attractors,'' however, the emphasis is on formal abstraction, as two lines of dancers weave through the same space but seldom touch. Whirling off-kilter, they trace long, looping lines reminiscent of a drip painting by Jackson Pollock. The lush lyricism finds its counterpart in the music, a composition for piano and strings by Mr. Nyman, who is best known for his haunting score for the 1993 film ''The Piano.''</p>
        <p>When the troupe performed the first act last fall in San Francisco, the critic Rita Felciano said it ''confirms Petronio as one of the most thoughtful and lyrically inventive choreographers of his generation.''</p>
        <p>Then misfortune struck. On vacation in Hawaii in December, Mr. Petronio was gazing up at a full moon, leaning backward while videotaping it, when he lost his footing on the side of a road. An X-ray of his right foot showed a spiral fracture, a thin crack coiled around one of his metatarsals. He has not performed since.</p>
        <p>''That little thing, slipping off the edge of a molecule, has changed my life radically for almost a year,'' he said. ''I'm a hyperactive person, and it stopped me. It was like a little death.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Petronio has been rolling with the punches of late. His trusted assistant, Kristen Borg, retired from dancing last year after 15 years with the troupe. Her successor, Todd Williams, formerly of the New York City Ballet, was sidelined last month by a hernia sustained during rehearsal. Several other dancers have moved to other companies since ''Not Garden'' was seen at the Joyce two years ago, leaving Mr. Petronio with a new lineup for ''Strange Attractors.''</p>
        <p>WARY of reinjuring his foot, he will limit himself to a brief line dance that he choreographed last winter to Placebo's ''Without You I'm Nothing,'' a pop song with vocals by David Bowie. Leaning on one another for support, eight glassy-eyed figures stagger and grope while the lyrics tell of a ''strange infatuation.'' The four-minute piece, which calls to mind a close-knit dance troupe after several weeks on the road, will serve as a prelude to ''Strange Attractors.''</p>
        <p>As he set to work on the second act, Mr. Petronio looked for ways to create a movement vocabulary that would be distinct from the bold extensions of the first: ''I was thinking, 'If my work is about inventing ways to direct energy out into space, what would I do if I stopped doing that?' '' The answer came from Crunch, the gym where he used to train with a boxing instructor.</p>
        <p>''When I began to blunt the ends of my lines, the boxing moves just started coming out of my body,'' Mr. Petronio said. ''I don't want to make a fight. That would be 'West Side Story.' What I want to do is use the syntax of sparring, the focused energy and the blunt lines, to make another kind of construction.''</p>
        <p>In rehearsal, with their balled fists and curled gestures, the dancers looked strong and sensual -- more as though they were having fun than venting aggression. In fact, the second act includes a great deal more touching and partnering than the first. With quicksilver precision, clusters of dancers form and dissolve, revealing momentary symmetries and flourishes of affection. Other dancers ride invisible whorls of energy in their wake.</p>
        <p>''Order and chaos have always been the defining poles for me,'' Mr. Petronio said shortly before completing the piece. ''As people, we like to understand and orient ourselves. But as an artist, I also like to disorient myself and my audience. For me, that's what makes good art. That's why chaos, confusion and disorganization are an important part of what we need to see on the stage.''</p>
        <p>DANCE Christopher Reardon's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the German choreographer Susanne Linke.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Christopher Reardon's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the German choreographer Susanne Linke.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
