<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Break New Jersey To the Kids</title>
    <meta content="15COLU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238849"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="JERSEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Galant, Debra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E5DE163FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Break New Jersey To the Kids</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBRA GALANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Galant, Debra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Debra Galant Jersey column on trying to explain to her children why New Jersey is often butt of jokes; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE experts say that you shouldn't listen to the news in front of small children, because you never know when a truly disturbing story will come on.</p>
        <p>They're thinking about the normal gory schoolyard shootings or the Jon-Benet Ramsey case, but my children were recently exposed to something even more unsettling: the Jersey joke.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE experts say that you shouldn't listen to the news in front of small children, because you never know when a truly disturbing story will come on.</p>
        <p>They're thinking about the normal gory schoolyard shootings or the Jon-Benet Ramsey case, but my children were recently exposed to something even more unsettling: the Jersey joke.</p>
        <p>It was one of those classic cases. Yet another company -- this time, Time Warner Cable -- had mocked New Jersey in an advertisement, implying we were technologically challenged. Governor Whitman charged in on her white horse. The ad was pulled, apologies made, the honor of the Garden State defended.</p>
        <p>Just another day in the life of the most derided state on the Eastern Seaboard (except, perhaps, for North Carolina, South Carolina, Georgia and Florida). But for my little New Jerseyans -- or should I say Joiseyans? -- it was like a whiff of toxic waste. If there is one thing that children care about, it is not being a laughing stock. There are 50 states and they live in the one that is the butt of all the jokes? It's like discovering you have toilet paper stuck to your shoe.</p>
        <p>I tried to explain it to my 8-year-old son like this: ''You know the New Jersey Turnpike? The road that we take when we go to Washington? Well, lots of people drive on that road, and they pass oil refineries and things, and they think it's kind of ugly. And that's all they know about New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>''You mean,'' he said, lip trembling, ''they come here just to tease us?''</p>
        <p>My 12-year-old daughter didn't even try to figure it out. ''Let's move,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Which made me wonder: Is discovering that your state is a national embarrassment a rite of passage?</p>
        <p>In the quest for the answer, I decided to interview Miss New Jersey, Jill Horner, who -- after all -- has to defend the honor of the state in a bathing suit. Jill called me collect from Atlantic City, where the preliminary competitions had been going on. It turned out that other contestants, particularly the Southern women, had been teasing her mercilessly about being from ''Joisey.''</p>
        <p>Did it wipe the smile from her face? Never. ''I found myself saying Joisey,'' she said with a laugh. ''And I've never said it in my life.''</p>
        <p>I also talked to John Gorka, a folk singer whose song, ''I'm From New Jersey,'' is to me the state anthem. Mr. Gorka grew up in Colonia and didn't discover the hilarity of this until he went to college in Pennsylvania. His song describes New Jersey as ''like Ohio/only more so'' and makes fun of our low expectations. ''If the world ended today/ I would adjust.''</p>
        <p>The idea was to disarm critics by ''bringing it up first,'' said Mr. Gorka, who now lives in Minnesota but uses ''I'm From New Jersey'' as a signature piece.</p>
        <p>''Whether it's deserved or not is besides the point,'' he said. ''It just depends what you do with that.''</p>
        <p>Which is pretty much the attitude of John Bendel, whose Web site -- New Jersey Uber Alles -- asks whether you would fight and die for New Jersey. Mr. Bendel, who grew up in Belleville and used to write for National Lampoon, now lives in Island Heights. His  site suggests several new state slogans, like ''New Jersey: We Kick Delaware's Butt'' and ''New Jersey . . . Please Take Someone With You When You Leave.''</p>
        <p>''The point of the site is not to poke fun at New Jersey,'' Mr. Bendel said. Then he paused. ''Well, I guess it does.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bendel's first conscious memory of New Jersey being a joke was watching ''Saturday Night Live,'' but he added, ''I think in my heart I knew it all along.''</p>
        <p>As an experiment, I asked my husband, who was in Sydney covering the Olympics, to find out if the Jersey joke had spread there. It hadn't. Not one person laughed when he mentioned his state. But when he explained the reputation New Jersey has Stateside, they all had the same reaction: ''Oh. Like Tasmania.'' Then they laughed.</p>
        <p>Finally, I talked to that short-haired defender of big-haired girls, Christie Whitman. ''Everybody trashes us all the time,'' she said. ''You've got to stand up to it.''</p>
        <p>She remembers being teased about being from ''Joisey'' when she was 10 or 12 and took a trip out of the state. She was perplexed, like my children, and had to ask her parents what it meant.</p>
        <p>Which is one reason she finds it important to stand up to bullies. ''You don't have to promote yourself at the expense of someone else,'' the governor said. ''That's not good for kids. And that's not good for New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>JERSEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
