<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Adventurer's Map to a World of Information</title>
    <meta content="15KAST$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/arts/15KAST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238819"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kastner, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ritchie, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7D91E3CF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1237" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Adventurer's Map to a World of Information</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFFREY KASTNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kastner, Jeffrey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeffrey Kastner interviews artist Matthew Ritchie, whose major exhibitions since 1995 have focused on adventurous story lines and whose latest, Parents and Children, is set to open at Andrea Rosen Gallery in New York City; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S all made up,'' Matthew Ritchie says with a characteristically inscrutable grin as he settles into a chair in his Chelsea studio. ''Except for all the parts that are true.''</p>
        <p>It's a late summer afternoon, and Mr. Ritchie is taking a break from preparations for his forthcoming show at the nearby Andrea Rosen Gallery, helping a visitor unravel fact from fiction in his sprawling artistic program. At first glance, Mr. Ritchie's ambitious paintings, drawings and installations seem to illustrate an impenetrable personal cosmology. Yet they're built on a rigorous system of real-world information, ranging from theoretical physics and molecular biology to medieval alchemy and classical philosophy. According to the artist, it's just the beginning of a continuing project designed to function as nothing less than ''a map of everything.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S all made up,'' Matthew Ritchie says with a characteristically inscrutable grin as he settles into a chair in his Chelsea studio. ''Except for all the parts that are true.''</p>
        <p>It's a late summer afternoon, and Mr. Ritchie is taking a break from preparations for his forthcoming show at the nearby Andrea Rosen Gallery, helping a visitor unravel fact from fiction in his sprawling artistic program. At first glance, Mr. Ritchie's ambitious paintings, drawings and installations seem to illustrate an impenetrable personal cosmology. Yet they're built on a rigorous system of real-world information, ranging from theoretical physics and molecular biology to medieval alchemy and classical philosophy. According to the artist, it's just the beginning of a continuing project designed to function as nothing less than ''a map of everything.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ritchie first introduced his scheme in a 1995 show, ''Working Model,'' which centered on a color-coded chart that proposed a virtually inexhaustible range of potential interactions between 49 characters. Collectively, this gang of comic book-style superheroes symbolized the artist's view of the multiplicitous connections between art, religion, politics and science; individually, they embodied everything from the speed of light to the human limbic system to the biological classification protista (simple organisms like protozoa and algae).</p>
        <p>''Basically, I wanted to say, 'Here's a map, now let's go on a journey,'' says the 36-year-old Mr. Ritchie, whose voice still bears traces of his native England. ''It was meant to be a generative structure, designed to produce adventures inside itself, adventures in information.''</p>
        <p>Each of his subsequent major exhibitions has focused on such an adventure, presented in the form of an unconventional story elaborated through paintings, drawings, installations and writing. In a 1996 show, ''The Hard Way,'' Mr. Ritchie drew on the legend of the Watchers, the fallen angels described in the Old Testament book of Enoch, to evoke the emergence of human consciousness. In ''The Gamblers,'' the artist imagined the Big Bang as a noirish casino night involving seven entities representing the quantum mechanical forces, gathered in a Holiday Inn outside Boston. For ''The Fast Set,'' mounted earlier this year at the Museum of Contemporary Art in Miami, he explored the laws of thermodynamics through a tragic love triangle involving the Golem, a movie star and an astronaut about to depart on a fictional seventh Mercury space mission.</p>
        <p>''Parents and Children,'' the show opening at Andrea Rosen on Saturday, is a continuation of the story, begun in Miami, focusing on what the artist describes as ''the transformation of energy into matter.'' (The last part will be shown at the Dallas Museum of Art in January.)</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Ritchie considers himself a painter, he's equally adept in each of the mediums he uses to tell his tales. His colorful, large-scale works on canvas and wall drawings incorporate figurative and abstract elements. Highly detailed in oil and marker pen, they include quasi-organic abstract shapes whose forms and colors refer back to the characters and attributes of his original scheme. Mr. Ritchie uses a flat vinyl material called Sintra for his sculptural wall and floor pieces; these are formal echoes of the paintings, says the artist, designed to allow viewers ''to walk inside the pictures.'' Most of the major exhibitions have also included stories, either in the catalog or displayed directly on the walls, written in a style that recalls hard-boiled fiction. ''I spent way too much time thinking about this,'' Mr. Ritchie says with a trademark touch of self-deprecation, referring to his dauntingly complex conceptual program.</p>
        <p>Born and reared in suburban London, he was an indifferent student through his years at the city's Camberwell School of Art. Following graduation, he left England and arrived in New York in 1988 with what he recalls as ''no sense of direction whatsoever.'' Without working papers or job prospects, Mr. Ritchie remembers being ''literally down to my last quarter'' when an acquaintance from art school, whom he bumped into one day on a street in SoHo, helped him find work painting buildings.</p>
        <p>Back on his feet financially, he began making art again. He converted a basement room into a studio in the Mercer Street building where his friend lived -- the same building where he eventually found work as a superintendent and met his wife, the actress Garland Hunter, and where the couple still lives today. It was also there that he began to develop the theoretical concepts on which he has built his career.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't call myself a scholar,'' Mr. Ritchie says, ''but I did as much research as an ordinary person who's a building superintendent can manage in his spare time -- into the history of color, into competing religious systems in the West and their relationship to philosophical and political structures, how those in turn were related to the evolution of early scientific practices and how that evolved into contemporary scientific practice. I looked at things like high-temperature physics and biology and the relationships between them that, collectively, form what we would like to believe is an objective truth about the nature of our lives. All that was cooking away in my brain and then, bizarrely enough, I decided to try and force it into the brightly colored waistcoat of contemporary painting.''</p>
        <p>ALTHOUGH his work is considered among the most ''difficult'' in all of contemporary art, Mr. Ritchie disputes the notion that it is intentionally cryptic. ''I'm trying to create a landscape where different kinds of information can coexist,'' he says. ''I haven't generated that information to be obscure -- that information actually exists, and when you overlap it, it produces new intersections of information. Basically, I dreamed the whole thing up as a way to express just how much fun you can have thinking, to convey my personal sense of how incredibly rich and complicated the world is.</p>
        <p>''I have real resistance to the idea of art being difficult because there is some sort of integrity in being difficult,'' he continues. ''It's more that the world is difficult, it is complicated. Quantum mechanics is difficult, but it's also real.'' As for the idea that many people don't ''get'' it, Mr. Ritchie laughs and says, ''You know, you don't really 'get' a tree either.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Ritchie continues to explore the potential of his cosmological system, his decision to work within such a particularized framework has proved to be energizing rather than limiting, he says. ''This is a machine designed to produce insights for me,'' he explains, ''but also to produce for people the exhilaration of connecting with knowledge. What's liberating about the idea of paintings being full of information is that it helps you remember that everything is full of information.'' The challenge, he says, is finding the right balance between form and content. ''I'm trying to say you can have both. You can have something that's both beautiful and meaningful -- and that the meaning enhances the beauty and the beauty enhances the meaning.''</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE Jeffrey Kastner's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the photographer Bill Owens.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jeffrey Kastner's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the photographer Bill Owens.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
