<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Father's Triumph Over Cancer</title>
    <meta content="15MILE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238901"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MILESTONES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Testes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ames, Lynne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drysdale, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Testicular Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DE143FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Father's Triumph Over Cancer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNE AMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ames, Lynne</byline>
      <dateline>YORKTOWN</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Bill Drysdale of Yorktown, NY, who, in June of 1999, at age 36, was diagnosed with advanced seminoma, virulent form of testicular cancer, which had metastisized throughout his body; he comments on treatment and remission; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BILL DRYSDALE and his wife, Laura, are putting up their Halloween decorations this week -- ghoulish purple lights strung from the trees, glowing pumpkins on the doorstep of their raised ranch house here. That doesn't sound like a big deal, but a year ago, Mr. Drysdale didn't know if he would see another Halloween.</p>
        <p>In June of 1999, the genial 36-year-old, a marketing director for Fuji, was found to have cancer. Last October, he was in the middle of chemotherapy, which caused violent vomiting, diarrhea and weakness. This year he is in remission, talking happily about Halloween costumes with his wife, a teacher, and their daughters, Taylor, 3, and Samantha, 1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BILL DRYSDALE and his wife, Laura, are putting up their Halloween decorations this week -- ghoulish purple lights strung from the trees, glowing pumpkins on the doorstep of their raised ranch house here. That doesn't sound like a big deal, but a year ago, Mr. Drysdale didn't know if he would see another Halloween.</p>
        <p>In June of 1999, the genial 36-year-old, a marketing director for Fuji, was found to have cancer. Last October, he was in the middle of chemotherapy, which caused violent vomiting, diarrhea and weakness. This year he is in remission, talking happily about Halloween costumes with his wife, a teacher, and their daughters, Taylor, 3, and Samantha, 1.</p>
        <p>''It was the thought of my family, my wife and daughters, that kept me going,'' he said. ''When I was first diagnosed, my doctor told me I had a 70 percent chance of making it. I never even asked what about the other 30 percent. I only focused on staying alive.''</p>
        <p>Like many other cancer sufferers, Mr. Drysdale's journey through devastating illness began with ambiguous symptoms.</p>
        <p>In August 1997, he had a bad bout of vertigo accompanied by vomiting and nausea; doctors did CAT scans to rule out brain tumors and found nothing. Tests for ''markers,'' biochemical substances sometimes found in the blood of people with certain cancers, also proved negative. Neurologists performed their own inquiries and came up empty.</p>
        <p>Eventually, doctors diagnosed labyrinthitis, an inner ear problem, and sinusitis. Mr. Drysdale had five sinus operations, but even with antibiotics, the infections recurred.</p>
        <p>Then one night in June 1999, he had excruciating stomach pains. He went to the emergency room at White Plains Hospital Center and was given a CAT scan of the abdomen. At last he had an answer. ''They told me they thought I had a large mass near the pancreas. As scary as that was, I figured at least there was something concrete now to go on.''</p>
        <p>He was admitted to the hospital's special cancer unit. In the radiology department, Dr. John Train did needle biopsies of the stomach tumor. The pathology report came back: Mr. Drysdale had advanced seminoma, a virulent form of testicular cancer, which had metastasized throughout his body.</p>
        <p>There were no palpable lumps in the testicle; it was only through the cells in the tumor that the nature of his disease was found. As for the sinusitis, his immune system had been working so hard fighting the cancer, it had left him susceptible to infections, doctors explained.</p>
        <p>At this point, Dr. Mark Fialk, an oncologist with a practice in Scarsdale and medical director of the White Plains Hospital Dickstein Cancer Treatment Center, became the lead doctor in the case. Mr. Drysdale recalled: ''He told me I had one of the best types of cancer to have -- that it was curable in 70 percent of cases. But he also said it was one of the worst in terms of treatment. He warned me that the treatment would be devastating.''</p>
        <p>And so began an odyssey that Mr. Drysdale recorded in a spiral notebook.</p>
        <p>For four months, he was on a cycle: two days in the hospital for tests, five days in the hospital for intravenous administration of the drugs and one to five days in the hospital afterward, depending on the severity of the side effects. Then he would go home, only to return 10 days later and start the process over again.</p>
        <p>His particular ''cocktail'' consisted of cisplatin, a form of platinum, and something called etoposide. While the etoposine made his hair fall out, the cistplatin wreaked havoc with his system, producing raging fevers, chills, vomiting, dysentery, blurred vision, ringing in the ears and loss of taste.</p>
        <p>''Everything tasted like metal to me,'' he said. ''The only thing I could keep down, strangely, were cherry Slurpees. I have no idea why.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Drysdale at times became more upset than her husband did.</p>
        <p>''It was just so hard to watch him,'' she said. ''With cancer the treatment seems worse than the disease at times. It can be so terrible, so hard, but you know it's necessary.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Drysdale, meanwhile, persevered. ''I wasn't running around, obviously,'' he said. ''I wasn't clapping my hands and saying, 'This is great.' I'd be curled up in a fetal position, moaning. But I did tell myself -- and I tell others as well -- that the more positive your outlook, the better your chances for a good outcome. I really believe that a positive outlook helps the chemo to work.''</p>
        <p>He paused. ''At the time, Taylor was 2; we'd tried for four years to have her. Samantha was still in the womb. I knew I had to stay alive for them and for my wife.''</p>
        <p>The chemotherapy worked. It shrank the abdominal tumor sufficiently so it could be surgically removed. Three metastases in his lungs also disappeared. Doctors removed his right testicle, where the cancer had originated. When he looks at his notebook entries today -- ''fever continuous, burning up my veins,'' he experiences a horrifying sensory recall. But he is more than willing to talk to anyone about his battle, to relive it mentally if that will help someone else.</p>
        <p>Today, 15 months after the diagnosis, he is considered to be in complete remission. He sees Dr. Fialk monthly. The fear of recurrence is ever present, but he tries to eclipse it with hope. So far, he has succeeded.</p>
        <p>''This summer, I went on trips to the beach to the Jersey Shore,'' Mr. Drysdale said. ''I'm back at work. I'm doing well. Cancer-wise, everything is fine. If there's going to be a relapse, it's usually within the first two years, I was told. So June 2001 is my big date.</p>
        <p>''But I look at it this way: I've made it this far, I'm going to go the distance.'' He smiled. ''Right now, I'm just looking forward to spending Halloween with my kids.''</p>
        <p>MILESTONES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
