<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Star Volleyball Player Who Happens to Be Deaf</title>
    <meta content="15SPOR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FOR THE RECORD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volleyball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deafness</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York School for the Deaf</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Palazzo, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slater, Chuck</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Deafness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volleyball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deafness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E0D6173FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="980" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Star Volleyball Player Who Happens to Be Deaf</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHUCK SLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slater, Chuck</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Jennifer Palazzo, star of New York School for the Deaf volleyball team who was chosen last year to play in Fairchester League's all-star volleyball game; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT happened a year ago. It was an honor, but a daunting one for a pre-freshman.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Palazzo, an eighth grader, had been chosen to play in the Fairchester League's all-star volleyball game -- not with her teammates from the New York School for the Deaf but with hearing girls who communicated with quick vocal directions in a fast-paced game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT happened a year ago. It was an honor, but a daunting one for a pre-freshman.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Palazzo, an eighth grader, had been chosen to play in the Fairchester League's all-star volleyball game -- not with her teammates from the New York School for the Deaf but with hearing girls who communicated with quick vocal directions in a fast-paced game.</p>
        <p>''I'm nervous,'' Jennifer told her coach, John Cleary, with rapid hand signs, questioning whether she should take part. ''Go ahead,'' he signed back. ''So you make a mistake, so what? You learn from it.''</p>
        <p>''And,'' Cleary said recently through an American Sign Language interpreter, ''she played and she did a great job.''</p>
        <p>Prinne Eberle, the School for the Deaf's athletic director, nodded in agreement.</p>
        <p>''The important thing is she played,'' Ms. Eberle said. ''We've had seniors in the past who refused to go. 'I'm not playing -- a deaf kid with all those others!' But Jennifer had the confidence in herself to do it.</p>
        <p>''When she came here in the seventh grade, she wouldn't have.</p>
        <p>''It's not the win-loss record that matters,'' Ms. Eberle continued. ''It's helping to build the character of the kids.''</p>
        <p>In that sense, sports have served Jennifer well, just as she has served the School for the Deaf's teams well.</p>
        <p>From its small pool of 30 boys and 25 girls at the eighth grade and high school levels, the School for the Deaf fields six varsity teams: boys' soccer, girls' volleyball and basketball and track for both boys and girls. Plus a cheerleading squad. Jennifer, of Nanuet, plays key roles on all three girls' teams.</p>
        <p>''She's one of the top athletes in our school,'' Mrs. Eberle said. ''She has the potential to be good at any level.''</p>
        <p>A star in volleyball, Jennifer is a starter in basketball, though only 5- foot-3 and 105 pounds. In track, she competes in diverse events like the triple jump, the high jump, the mile and the 4 by 100 relay. She has high jumped 4 feet 6 inches, only 9 inches less than her own height.</p>
        <p>But those are not the performances that matter.</p>
        <p>''When Jennifer came to our school,'' Mrs. Eberle said, ''she was a very quiet and shy kind of girl. A very bright girl, but shy by nature, and when she started organized sports, she was very hesitant.</p>
        <p>''She came to realize she had some talent. She wasn't afraid to make mistakes, so she was easy to coach. As her skills improved, you could see her confidence improve, and it spilled over into her everyday school life and her social life. By the eighth grade last year, she had enough confidence to work toward and become a representative in the student body government.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Eberle is also in charge of the dormitories, so she had a widened perspective on the transformation.</p>
        <p>''Sports played a big part in that change,'' she said. ''Sports enables kids to shine in several ways, and once Jennifer found a place to shine, she had the courage to try other things. She learned from sports that even if you don't know how to do something this time, the next minute you can do it.''</p>
        <p>For a deaf youngster, it can mean coming out of a shell.</p>
        <p>''I've learned so much here,'' Jennifer said, walking on campus with the easy grace of the natural athlete. ''I knew I was good in sports even when I came here, but I didn't know I had these skills. But here I am, and I kind of surprised myself.</p>
        <p>''I used to be shy and afraid of trying new things. Now I'm very confident.''</p>
        <p>And very willing to help others. Mr. Cleary called Jennifer ''the most unselfish athlete I have ever had.''</p>
        <p>''In running, the mile is not her best event,'' he explained. ''She usually runs the mile when another player can't or doesn't want to run. She willingly runs just to earn points for the team.''</p>
        <p>Her positions -- point guard in basketball and setter in volleyball -- are both leadership roles, the coach said.</p>
        <p>As a setter, Jennifer retrieves the other team's slams and serves them up to taller teammates for kills. ''I can save anything,'' she said.</p>
        <p>No lack of confidence there. ''She's changed so much,'' Mr. Cleary said.</p>
        <p>Her brother Nick, 13 and also deaf, has noticed. ''Oh yes,'' he signs when asked if his sister has gained in confidence. ''It even seems as if she communicates more now. Even her sign language has improved.''</p>
        <p>Their shared challenges have brought the Palazzo siblings -- who moved from the Bronx two years ago -- closer together. They have not, however, dimmed sibling rivalry.</p>
        <p>Jennifer said: ''I beat him in a race every time. Every time.''</p>
        <p>Nick said: ''Usually. Usually she wins, but sometimes I do.''</p>
        <p>Their mother, Yvonne, recognizes the value of sports in their development. A single parent who works full time, she nevertheless manages to get to all their late-ending events since the Rockland County school district provides transportation back to Nanuet only up to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>With the volleyball season winding down, Jennifer will be turning her attention to basketball. Cleary is sure of one thing.</p>
        <p>''Last year we had a senior who was very good,'' the coach said, ''and Jennifer was never able to stop her in practice. She was almost too polite. That will not happen this season.''</p>
        <p>FOR THE RECORD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
