<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Exchange Rate Behind Bars</title>
    <meta content="15PRISONT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="76" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238744"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Barter</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leduff, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Barter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE0DD1E3DF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Exchange Rate Behind Bars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Charlie LeDuff</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leduff, Charlie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes barter system used by inmates at Suffolk County (NY) Jail; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The buildings that make up the Suffolk County Jail resemble a Moscow government complex. They are gray with staggered green windows and slab walls of cement, all ringed in high hurricane fencing and razor wire. Visitors are prohibited from bringing gum, candy or food. No medications. No hats or belts. No sweaters, jackets or coats. No jewelry. No hair curlers. No paper of any kind. No cigarettes or cigars. No alcohol.</p>
        <p>And definitely no money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The buildings that make up the Suffolk County Jail resemble a Moscow government complex. They are gray with staggered green windows and slab walls of cement, all ringed in high hurricane fencing and razor wire. Visitors are prohibited from bringing gum, candy or food. No medications. No hats or belts. No sweaters, jackets or coats. No jewelry. No hair curlers. No paper of any kind. No cigarettes or cigars. No alcohol.</p>
        <p>And definitely no money.</p>
        <p>Without cash of their own, inmates are forced to improvise. Having recently lived in legitimate society, they are used to a certain standard of living. So the black market flourishes, based on a barter system. Inside jail, there are six ways to obtain tradable commodities.</p>
        <p>1) Charity: Your family or well-wishers may drop money in your commissary account, which allows you to purchase up to $25 worth of merchandise twice a week from the jail. (Prisoners fill out order forms, and the goods are delivered to them on Tuesdays and Fridays.) Among the more popular items are Devil Dogs snack cakes going for 60 cents a pack and baby lotion to soften the skin at $1.25 a bottle. Prepackaged tuna has become a big success since it was introduced to the commissary earlier this year for $1.50 per bag. (A side of mayonnaise is $1.) Dictionaries go for $5.50, but few of those are sold, correction officers report. And at the ''Monday Night Football'' wine and cheese fetes, the p2/3te is sliced beef jerky (55 cents a stick) and the cheese is processed cheese spread ($1.60) smeared on the slices of bread provided at mealtimes. The wine is local, made from fermented fruit cups, with yeast coming from scraps of bread.</p>
        <p>2) Contrabanditry: An inmate can have dope and tobacco -- which was outlawed in the facility during the mid-90's -- smuggled in at the risk of jail time to himself and his confederate.</p>
        <p>3) Conniving: An inmate can trade whatever he has been given by the authorities or whatever he has managed to scam from them. This goes for everything from morning coffee to clean socks to prescribed medications from the psychiatric unit that an inmate hides under his tongue.</p>
        <p>4) Corporeal: Some inmates trade the only thing they bring in: their bodies.</p>
        <p>5) Cards: Everything from commissary goods to promissory notes are gambled in the housing tiers. You can easily tell who's rich by Suffolk County Jail standards; they have soft skin and a shelf full of food. The mopes and card punks walk around in dirty socks or no socks at all.</p>
        <p>6) Cribbing: This is out-and-out theft. It stems from the inability or unwillingness to pay your bills, and it is rare. It's not so much the adage ''honor among thieves'' that holds here, but more like ''fear among thieves,'' says Correction Officer Lori McKeough of the Suffolk County Sheriff's Department, who works in the commissary unit. It may result in the sharpened end of a toothbrush being jabbed into the neck of the inmate in arrears. Cribbing is usually the work of men scheduled for release in the morning.</p>
        <p>When officers believe contraband has permeated their walls, they will shake down and inspect the suspect's cell. Then they check his commissary account. It's a good method for tracking the black market within the jail. Consider the inmate, for instance, who has no money in his account and hasn't had money in his account for a very long time. But when the authorities come to inspect his cell, it is filled with so many items from the commissary that it looks like a cross between a party store and a beauty shop. This means one of three things: 1) He's winning at cards. 2) He's trading away his breakfast. 3) He's dealing dope.</p>
        <p>''The rule is very simple,'' says Lt. Lloyd Manseau, the 49-year-old commanding officer of security. ''Everything is worth something in here. Nothing goes to waste. Except, of course, lives.''</p>
        <p>One economic postulate of the incarcerated is that if there is a buck to be made, there is a boob to be played. There is no better example of this than the skinny kid who recently visited his friend in lockup. The visiting area contains steel stools, yellow walls and a Plexiglas barrier long enough for 40 inmates and visitors to chat at a time. Since the New York State Department of Corrections mandates that all inmates must have the opportunity to touch their loved ones, they are allowed a kiss when their visitors arrive, a kiss when they depart and for the duration of the 45-minute visit they may hold hands above the Plexiglas divider.</p>
        <p>This is when the contraband is exchanged. There are only two officers guarding the proceedings, and though each inmate must submit to a strip-search following a visit, a full rectal search requires a court order. ''A lot gets in, there's no way around it,'' says Manseau, a silver-haired pragmatist whose youth was lost patrolling the halls of this hole.</p>
        <p>The visitors bring the contraband wrapped tightly in rubber balloons, and the savvy inmate will have his pant leg split and his rectum greased. The goods are squirreled away in seconds.</p>
        <p>The skinny kid was from Pennsylvania and not so nimble. A guard spotted him, and before the exchange was made, he was snared with three balloons of marijuana, one balloon of pharmaceuticals and two balloons of tobacco. There was laughter among the guards looking through the one-way glass. ''He must be new at this,'' said one of them. ''He just earned himself a bed in here.''</p>
        <p>Three balloons may seem to the law-abiding citizen not worth the risk to one's freedom, but you must consider what the market will bear in the Suffolk County Jail. A balloon may hold 10 tablets and enough tobacco or marijuana for 10 skinny smokes. Each pill may fetch $5, a cigarette as much as $15 and a reefer $25. The money in these situations is usually exchanged by girlfriends on visiting days.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, we had a guy in here who was waiting on $25 bail,'' said one correction officer. ''He was a real pain, if you know what I mean. A real operator. Finally, he got to the point where he was causing so much trouble that the C.O.'s took up a collection to bail him out just to get him out of here. He refused it. You know why? He said he was making more money in here in a week than he could make out on the streets.''</p>
        <p>Located in the crotch of Long Island where the east end splits into the North and South Forks, the Suffolk County Jail is home to 1,200 people. But when summer ebbs and vacationers go away, there is little to do but crime and the jail population generally balloons to 150 percent of capacity.</p>
        <p>An inmate named Peaches says he comes here to convalesce. He is male by gender, but female by occupation, he says. His full name is Charles Wayne Cameron. He is 43 and has been arrested 145 times and convicted 80 times, mostly for prostitution and petty larceny. He is currently doing time for taking a car because his trick did not understand that he was simply borrowing it, Peaches explains.</p>
        <p>''You can get anything in here that you get in the Hamptons: condoms, heroin, you name it,'' says the frail, coffee-skinned, blue-eyed hustler who should know, since he works the Hamptons streets when not in jail. The tony vacation towns are, after all, only 10 miles away from the jailhouse.</p>
        <p>''A girl like me is a commodity in here since there's so many guys going to state penitentiary who aren't going to have a loving relationship for a very long while.''</p>
        <p>Peaches lives in the first-floor-east block -- protective custody -- home to the rapists, child molesters and the insane. (Those considered suicidal must wear paper clothes so they can't hang themselves.) Anyone may ask to be moved to protective custody if he feels threatened, and when he does, he meets Peaches. The price? Twenty-five dollars in snack cakes and a $5 I.O.U.</p>
        <p>''A little bit of weed is always a nice tip,'' says Peaches, winking. ''And if you can't pay, there's always some kind of way to work it off.''</p>
        <p>There is a card game in fourth-floor-east block. It smells powerfully of urine there. The ceilings are peeling. The floors are wet. There are barnyard noises. Four men gamble for batteries and shampoo and aloe vera gel. Chips are playing cards torn into quarters, and each one represents 5 cents. Commissary goods are cashed in with the house at face value. At the end of the game, every man is allowed to cash out and take back those products he can still afford. The winner has first pick of whatever is left over.</p>
        <p>''Weed, smokes, what have you,'' says Tito Velez, 30, who is holding two arms full of snack cakes and hair-care products. ''Sometimes the game gets so amped up, you got to call your girl to have her drop $100 in somebody's commissary 'cause you lost so bad,'' he says. Then he cuddles his cakes like an infant. ''But that don't happen to me.''</p>
        <p>The most popular trade inside is in batteries. Used for tape players ($25), the batteries will usually wear down in a matter of hours because they are not the alkaline type but the paper-jacket type (three for $2.25). The authorities found that when they allowed the inmates to have alkaline batteries, the men peeled the metal jackets off and made shanks to stab one another. Because the paper batteries run down so quickly, inmates will go heavily into debt to be able to listen to some music. The trade is usually something like one pack of batteries on Saturday for three packs on Tuesday, when the commissary reopens.</p>
        <p>''It's like a reflection of society as a whole,'' says Lieutenant Manseau, who has watched the bartering game for more than 20 years. ''It's 'Live for today.' Why do people buy S.U.V.'s and go into debt to do it? The same reason people trade three packs of batteries to listen to music. Because it's all about 'I want what I want, and I want it now.' That's America. People will go in debt because they don't want to want. Of course, one person is honest and the other is dishonest, but the premise is the same.''</p>
        <p>The card game breaks up, and a man goes back to his cell to study a picture of his naked girlfriend. She is bent over, facing away from the camera. The photo has more value than your run-of-the-mill pornography because she is real in the sense that she is known to somebody on the cellblock. ''How much for that?'' someone asks him.</p>
        <p>''A whole balloon,'' he answers. It is an unreasonable sum, and there are no takers.</p>
        <p>It is 4 p.m. when Eddie B. walks out of jail. There is no one to pick him up, and his shoes are untied. For anyone who is destitute and in need of a hand, jail officials will gladly buy him a seat on the first bus out of town. But Eddie came in with $6 in his pocket, and he gets it back in a manila envelope. He's not about to spend it on a bus ticket. Eddie is free now. Free to express himself and make choices with his money, real money. ''I'm gonna buy me a pack a smokes and a Budweiser, 'cause that's all I drink Budweiser,'' he says. ''I deserve it. I just paid my debt to society.''</p>
        <p>Charlie LeDuff is a reporter for the Metro Section of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Charlie LeDuff is a reporter for the Metro Section of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
