<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="15GUID$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238858"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DC163FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1399" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Barbara Delatiner</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>The North Carolina Dance Theater, a company directed by Patricia McBride and Jean-Pierre Bonnefoux, pulls into the Van Nostrand Theater on the Brentwood campus of Suffolk Community College today at 3 p.m. with ballets by Balanchine, Forsyth and Paul Taylor (631) 665-4350. The weekend brings dance, too, but an entirely different genre, as Noche Flamenca, a troupe of dancers, singers and guitarists, perform Andalusian gypsy music at 5 and 9 p.m. Saturday at the Westhampton Beach performing Arts Center on Main Street (631) 288-1500, and the Ballet Folklorica de Mexico appears at 7 p.m. next Sunday at Tilles Center In Brookville (516) 299-3100.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>The North Carolina Dance Theater, a company directed by Patricia McBride and Jean-Pierre Bonnefoux, pulls into the Van Nostrand Theater on the Brentwood campus of Suffolk Community College today at 3 p.m. with ballets by Balanchine, Forsyth and Paul Taylor (631) 665-4350. The weekend brings dance, too, but an entirely different genre, as Noche Flamenca, a troupe of dancers, singers and guitarists, perform Andalusian gypsy music at 5 and 9 p.m. Saturday at the Westhampton Beach performing Arts Center on Main Street (631) 288-1500, and the Ballet Folklorica de Mexico appears at 7 p.m. next Sunday at Tilles Center In Brookville (516) 299-3100.</p>
        <p>Korean War Exhibition</p>
        <p>Curators at Guild Hall in East Hampton mark the 50th anniversary of the start of the ''forgotten war'' with ''The Korean War in American Art and Culture: 50 Years Later.'' Opening Saturday with a reception at 5 p.m., the exhibition, said to be the first of its type mounted in the United States, includes a section with photojournalism by David Douglas Duncan, Margaret Bourke-White and others, and combat art by painters like Hugh Cabot and John DeGrasse. Another gallery at the cultural center on Main Street features works by contemporary Korean-American artists. The exhibition, running through Jan. 7, will be accompanied by a series of films including ''Steel Helmet,'' Nov. 2; and ''M*A*S*H,'' Nov. 30; and a ''Hot Topics'' panel discussion, ''Korea: A Forgotten War,'' Nov. 12 (631) 324-0806.</p>
        <p>Jewish Art</p>
        <p>In Southampton, at the Parrish Art Museum where the exhibition, ''The Perpetual Well: Contemporary Art from the Collection of the Jewish Museum'' remains through Nov. 12, today there is a gallery talk by Donna Harkavy, a curator, at 2 p.m. and the first of a series of pertinent films, ''The Chosen'' at 6 p.m., and, on Saturday at 8 p.m., a performance by the Pharoah's Daughters, a band that performs Middle Eastern music (631) 283-2118.</p>
        <p>Day for the Organ</p>
        <p>Today more than 200 chapters of the American Guild of Organists will offer ''Pipes Spectacular'' concerts throughout the country. On Long Island, there will be three. In Garden City, at the Cathedral of the Incarnation on Cathedral Avenue, members of the Nassau guild will put the largest pipe organ on the Island to work for an ''Evening in Paris: Organists Favorites of the French Romantic Period'' at 4 p.m. (516) 764-9578. The Suffolk chapter, joined by the Northport Chorale, offer Handel, Bach and theater music, at 2 p.m. at Trinity Episcopal Church on Main Street in Northport (631) 544-4147. Finally, organists from the East End who belong to the Sunrise chapter perform on a newly restored Hook and Hastings Pipe Organ at 6 p.m. at the First Parish Church on Sound Avenue in Jamesport (631) 298-9427.</p>
        <p>Orchestra Anniversary</p>
        <p>The North Shore Symphony Orchestra opens its 40th Anniversary season today at 2 p.m. by avoiding tradition. Its first concert, featuring Gary Levinson, a violinist with the New York Philharmonic, in a program of Mozart, Schubert, Saint-Saens and Sindling, is at St. Joseph's College in Patchogue, not at North Shore High School, and instead of being free as performances have been in the past, this one will cost $8, or $5 for the elderly (631) 447-3200.</p>
        <p>From the Chambers</p>
        <p>Chamber music dominates the concert stage this week with seven events in the offing. Today there are three. Chamber Players International opens its season of Champagne brunches, ''Musical Cuisine,'' with ''The Russian Golden Age'' at noon at the Brookville Country Club on Chicken Valley Road in Glen Head featuring Russian food and music by Prokofiev, Rachmaninoff and Shostakovich (877) 444-4488. The Hofstra String Quartet performs works by Carter, Dvorak, Hayden and Turnia at 3 p.m. at the Monroe Lecture Center Theater on the university's Hempstead campus (516) 463-6644. And in Oyster Bay, Friends of the Arts opens its Concerts at Coe Hall with the Rossetti String Quartet playing music by Beethoven, Dvorak and Ravel at 2:30 p.m. at Planting Fields (516) 922-0061.</p>
        <p>In a break from the familiar repertory, at 8 p.m. Wednesday at the Staller Center, the Contemporary Chamber Players at the State University at Stony Brook open their new season with a program devoted to new works by Stony Brook composers (631) 632-2787. Saturday brings three more concerts as the Wynsum Piano Trio plays music by Brahms at 8 p.m. in the Music at Greenlawn Series at the Presbyterian Church on Pulaski Road (631) 262-3306; ''Music for Montauk'' begins its 10th free season with the St. Luke's Chamber Ensemble joined by Max Barros, pianist, in an all-Mozart concert at 7 p.m. at the Montauk School on South Dorset Road (631) 668-2481, and in the Islip Arts Council's Silver Anniversary Chamber Music Series, the Juilliard String Quartet plays works by Haydn, Mendelssohn and Ruth Crawford-Seeger at 8 p.m. in the Sayville Middle School on Johnson Avenue (631) 224-5420.</p>
        <p>American Music</p>
        <p>To set the stage for its major exhibition on ''Aaron Copeland's America,'' which opens Nov. 4, the Heckscher Museum of Art on Prime Avenue in Huntington starts a seven-part, monthly series of concerts devoted to American music. First up at 8 p.m. Saturday are David Sear and Peter Pickow in ''An Evening of American Folk Songs'' (631) 351-3250.</p>
        <p>College Thespians</p>
        <p>With the new term now some six weeks old, thespians at local colleges and universities have had enough time to learn their lines. Hence six productions on six different campuses. In Brookville, the Post Theater Company ends its run of ''The Rocky Horror Picture Show'' at 3 p.m. today at the Little Theater on the C. W. Post campus of Long Island University (516) 299-2356. Student actors at Nassau Comunity College in Garden City offer ''A Pocketful of Rhymes,'' a children's musical based on traditional Mother Goose works, through next Sunday at the Little Theater (516) 572-7676, while also in Garden City, a all-female cast ends its version of Neil Simon's ''Odd Couple'' at 2 p.m. at the Olmsted Theater at Adelphi University (516) 877-4010.</p>
        <p>At Hofstra University, ''The Fantasticks'' reign through next Sunday in the West End Theater on the Hempstead campus (516) 463-6644.  Neil Simon is in the spotlight again in Selden where Suffolk Community College students offer his ''Biloxi Blues'' at Stage 119 from Wednesday through Oct. 29 (631) 451-4163. Finally, in Stony Brook on Thursday ''Six Degrees of Separation'' opens a run through Oct. 29 at Staller Center's Theater II on the State University campus (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>Free Choices</p>
        <p>TODAY -- The Long Island Maritime Museum in West Sayville holds ''Celebrate the Bay,'' a maritime folklife festival with local fishermen, baymen and folk artists like decoy carvers and clamshell artists sharing their history and traditions; music by folksingers like David Sear, Stuart Markus and Judith Zweiman; storytelling from Reggie Jones, the veteran Jones Beach lifeguard, and Max Wheat, poet; and tours of bay houses that will cost $10 or $5 for children. The fest is from 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. at the museum on West Avenue (631) 447-8679.</p>
        <p>''Highlights from Zarzuelas and Spanish Classical Music'' will be performed at 3 p.m. at Salten Hall of New York Institute of Technology in Old Westbury (516) 686-7640.</p>
        <p>In ''Fit for a King,'' Christopher Bezuidenhout, flutist, and Andrus Madsen, harpsichordist, perform music heard in the court of Frederick the Great of Prussia in the first ''Barogue Sundays at Three'' concert at Staller Center at the State University at Stony Brook (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>TOMORROW -- Celebrating ''Italian Heritage Day,'' Nassau Community College in Garden City offers ''Glimpses into Italian and Jewish Relationships,'' with panel discussions of topics like ''The Italian-American -- Jewish-American Connection: the Intermarriage Experience,'' starting at 1 p.m., and the screening of ''The Garden of the Finzi-Contini'' at 6:15 p.m. It all takes place in the College Center (516) 572-7170.</p>
        <p>THURSDAY -- The United States Air Force Concert Band and Singing Sergeants perform at 8 p.m. Thursday at Tilles Center on the C. W. Post campus of Long Island University in Brookville (516) 299-3100.</p>
        <p>SATURDAY -- The Blessed Women's Singing Homeless Choir, a group made up of present and past homeless women from the New York area, appears at 7:30 p.m. at the Sayville Community Church on Middle Road. Free will offerings will be accepted (516) 797-4863.</p>
        <p>Compiled by Barbara Delatiner</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
