<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Multiple Personalities? Yes, on the Radio</title>
    <meta content="15JOUR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238866"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wgbb-Am (Merrick, Ny)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Protestant Churches</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Council of Churches</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brannigan, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koski, Hope</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E6D9163FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Multiple Personalities? Yes, on the Radio</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Journal column: Jim Brannigan is host and Kevin Thompson is his sidekick on fast-paced, old-fashioned comedy show on WGBB-AM radio in Merrick; Hope Koski, 60, first woman in Episcopal Diocese of Long Island to be appointed rector of parish, has become first female president of Long Island Council of Churches; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AND now, broadcasting live at 9:30 p.m. Tuesdays from WGBB-AM in Merrick, it's old-fashioned, chuckle-a-minute radio.</p>
        <p>''For the past six months we've had the pleasure of coming into your homes,'' Jim Brannigan, host of  ''What Else Ya Got'' on WGBB (1240), was saying. ''The police may call it breaking and entering, but we like to call it entertainment.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AND now, broadcasting live at 9:30 p.m. Tuesdays from WGBB-AM in Merrick, it's old-fashioned, chuckle-a-minute radio.</p>
        <p>''For the past six months we've had the pleasure of coming into your homes,'' Jim Brannigan, host of  ''What Else Ya Got'' on WGBB (1240), was saying. ''The police may call it breaking and entering, but we like to call it entertainment.''</p>
        <p>Welcome to Bedford Corners, the small, fictional town Mr. Brannigan created for the half-hour weekly audio show. Just how small? The ice cream parlor has only one flavor. And the 15 characters who live there -- including the know-it-all Bavarian professor, Heinscheveye VanDerNoggin; Angus MacDougal, a Scottish owner of the local tavern, the Breezy Kilt; Crazy Calhoone, a lovable looney; Father Time, depended on for historical perspective; and Problem Man, who answers listeners' solutions by giving them the problem -- are Mr. Brannigan's different voices.</p>
        <p>''What else ya' got?'' asks Kevin Thompson, 44, in a deep, booming voice at the end of each fast-moving segment. Mr. Thompson, a life-insurance salesman from West Hempstead, is a humorist, magician, amateur actor and Mr. Brannigan's sidekick and friend of 10 years.</p>
        <p>Try a medical soap opera, Morgue Manner. Where the patients check in -- ba da boom -- after they've checked out. Mr. Brannigan, 30, plays the doctor; his fiancee, Stephanie Turner, 31, an actress, portrays the nurse.</p>
        <p>''Anesthesia, doctor?'' Ms. Turner asks.</p>
        <p>''None for me thanks, I'm driving,'' Mr. Brannigan replies, pressing the button on a coffee grinder to mimic the sound of sawing.</p>
        <p>Then the soap opera music, orchestrated by a keyboard player, Martha Pramnieks, 38, of Garden City, fades in. And Liz Follett, 36, of Islip, who works in the accounting department at Vytra Health Plans by day and does local theater by night, starts to sing.</p>
        <p>''Sketch comedy, the way that we're doing it, is good for those who like to click the remote,'' Mr. Brannigan said. ''It moves along at a pace where your finger wouldn't get to the button before something new or interesting is happening. If you were in your car, it's perfect for the preset scanning generation or those with attention deficit disorder. For today's audiences, it's like deja vu. It moves very fast.''</p>
        <p>For a living, Mr. Brannigan, a lifelong Wantagh resident, works in public relations in Huntington. Weekends and evenings, he does stand-up comedy at Governors, the Brokerage and McGuire's comedy clubs.</p>
        <p>Last November, acquaintances doing a late-night radio show on WGBB asked Mr. Brannigan to do a character. He called in as Sean Connery. Ms. Turner pretended to be Katharine Hepburn. Joey Alcarese, the station manager, happened to be listening -- and she wanted to hear more.</p>
        <p>Forget modern drive-time, happy-talk, zoo-crew radio. Each week since January, Mr. Brannigan has written and performed a 23- to 25-page sketch character comedy-variety show, squeaky clean but loaded with innuendoes, straight out of the Golden Age of Radio.</p>
        <p>''When I was a kid, I listened to a lot of the old rebroadcasts on radio and tapes of Bob Hope and Jack Benny and Burns and Allen,'' he said. ''I just was enthralled. It really allows you to create the images in your mind. I just thought this is the greatest thing.''</p>
        <p>He also watched television, homing in on rebroadcasts of ''The Carol Burnett Show'' and ''I Love Lucy.''</p>
        <p>'' It just looked like they were having so much fun and I just wanted to be a part of that very badly,'' he said. ''When this show came around, it was kind of a culmination of everything I had been working on.''</p>
        <p>While a student at Nassau Community College, Mr. Brannigan worked as a disc jockey at WHPC. Upon transferring to Hofstra University, he shifted to writing and journalism. A theater minor, he performed at the Broadhollow Theater in Bethpage and with the Arena Players in Farmingdale. Later he did a six-month East Coast tour with a production of ''Around the World in 80 Days.'' His role included multiple character parts, quick changes and different accents.</p>
        <p>Back in New York, Mr. Brannigan played eccentric characters and used different voices at the Jekyll and Hyde Club, a theme restaurant.  And he spent nearly two years as a series regular on ''USA Up All Night, with Gilbert Gottfried.''</p>
        <p>''My future is in entertainment,'' Mr. Brannigan said. ''Radio is a wonderful medium that lets the imagination open up. Radio is a little more intimate and allows creativity.''</p>
        <p>As the show winds down, the news comes on. As ''Flash'' Brannigan, he spoofs it, Jay Leno style, with co-anchor ''Scoop'' Thompson. With neither budget nor sponsor, the call-in segment ''Who Wants to Win Some Free Cash?'' gives away one dollar, a scratch-and-win ticket or a Lotto ticket.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, Mr. Brannigan finds writing a weekly script grueling. Then he remembers his father's words after hearing his first broadcast.</p>
        <p>''I've seen you on the stage,'' James Brannigan told his son. ''I've seen you on TV. You have a great face for radio.''</p>
        <p>Heeding the Call</p>
        <p>When Hope Koski was about 7 years old, she told her mother that she wanted to be an Episcopalian priest. ''Oh honey,'' the Very Rev. Hope Koski recalled her mother saying. ''Little girls can't be priests.''  ''Mommy, I don't want to be a priest when I'm a little girl,'' Ms. Koski replied. ''I want to be a priest when I grow up.''</p>
        <p>But when she got to Union Theological Seminary in Manhattan in 1963, women weren't allowed to prepare for the priesthood. Ms. Koski studied liturgical music instead, receiving her master's degree in sacred music. She went to work as a church organist and choir director and was a lay chaplain at the University of Wisconsin for 10 years.</p>
        <p>''I really knew in my heart that if I were male instead of female, I would have gone for ordination,'' said Ms. Koski, 60. Her calling to the priesthood, she said, came from God.</p>
        <p>So in 1977, when the Episcopal Church voted to ordain women, Ms.  Koski headed back to seminary and studied for three more years. She was among the first 100 women to be ordained nationwide She took the pulpit at St. Lawrence of Canterbury Episcopal Church in Dix Hills 11 years ago. She was the first woman in the Episcopal Diocese of Long Island to be appointed rector of a parish and is still the only female rector in Suffolk County. She is also dean of the region, overseeing 10 churches.</p>
        <p>St. Lawrence, she said, is a racially and ethnically diverse, liberal, social-action-oriented congregation. Parishioners come from as far east as Selden, south from Patchogue, north to Lloyd Harbor and west from Mineola.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes I'm a draw and sometimes I'm a stay-away,'' said the priest, known to her congregants as Mother Koski. ''Some people just don't want a woman as their priest. You have to be very careful about sacraments. You wouldn't want them to have any chance of the magic not working. You want to make sure that baby is really baptized when it's baptized and that marriage is really going to stick,'' said Ms. Koski, who is divorced and has three grown children.</p>
        <p>In May, Ms. Koski became the first female president of the Long Island Council of Churches, an ecumenical organization representing 750 local Protestant churches. It also has nonvoting representatives from the Catholic, Greek Orthodox and Jewish communities.</p>
        <p>''It's a way for the small and normally separated Protestant churches that range from congregations of 20 to 30 people to congregations of thousands to come together with a unified voice,'' she said. ''It lets small congregations have some strength from larger congregations and larger congregations gain the strength of smaller congregations.'' One of her goals is to use technology to bring churches together through the Internet.</p>
        <p>The council runs food pantries, leads initiatives to secure grant money to end sweatshops and unfair labor practices, runs the Protestant chaplaincies for Nassau County, and supports the Multi-Faith Forum, an outreach group promoting understanding of the 12 major faiths practiced on Long Island -- Jainism, Islam, Baha'i, Hinduism, Sikhism, Zen Buddhism, Brahma Kumaris, American Indian, Unitarian Universalism, Yoga, Christianity and Judaism.</p>
        <p>''We work very hard for the social integration of all Long Islanders with each other so that people aren't afraid of each other,'' Ms. Koski said.</p>
        <p>''Anything we can do to lessen the fear of neighbors for each other and of communities for people they don't know is well within our range of interest,'' she said, ''To make sure that peace reigns and make sure we have no religious wars on Long Island. Lord knows, we don't need that.''</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
