<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All Things O'Neill in New London</title>
    <meta content="15OPOP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238860"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monte Cristo Cottage (New London, Conn)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">O'neill, Eugene, Theater Center</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Neill, Eugene (1888-1953)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Eugene O'Neill</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E2DC163FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1049" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All Things O'Neill in New London</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLYN BATTISTA</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on upcoming Eugene O'Neill Conference at Eugene O'Neill Theater Center in Waterford, Conn; readings of scenes from O'Neill plays will take place at his boyhood home, Monte Cristo Cottage, in New London; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON Friday and Saturday, the Eugene O'Neill Conference at Monte Cristo Cottage will explore the life, work and influence of the playwright. It will also focus on Monte Cristo itself, the modest house in New London where O'Neill spent his boyhood summers -- and found so much material for his plays.</p>
        <p>The conference, which celebrates O'Neill's birth on Oct. 16, 1888, is open to the public and will include a round-table discussion led by Arthur and Barbara Gelb, O'Neill biographers who have recently updated their original work, as well as workshops by theater professionals. The director of the conference, J Ranelli, said he hoped that it would become ''an annual dialogue for people working in the theater or interested in it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON Friday and Saturday, the Eugene O'Neill Conference at Monte Cristo Cottage will explore the life, work and influence of the playwright. It will also focus on Monte Cristo itself, the modest house in New London where O'Neill spent his boyhood summers -- and found so much material for his plays.</p>
        <p>The conference, which celebrates O'Neill's birth on Oct. 16, 1888, is open to the public and will include a round-table discussion led by Arthur and Barbara Gelb, O'Neill biographers who have recently updated their original work, as well as workshops by theater professionals. The director of the conference, J Ranelli, said he hoped that it would become ''an annual dialogue for people working in the theater or interested in it.''</p>
        <p>Even more, Mr. Ranelli and other supporters hope it will support efforts to do needed work on the 19-century cottage and to create a new center devoted to O'Neill that could become the repository for a collection of O'Neill papers.</p>
        <p>The conference is a project of the Eugene O'Neill Theater Center in Waterford, which runs the annual National Playwrights Conference and other theater programs. The center owns the cottage, now a theater museum, but will hold the conference at roomier sites nearby.</p>
        <p>Romulus Linney (whose work ''A Lesson Before Dying'' is playing Off Broadway) will open the conference with a Friday night talk on O'Neill at Connecticut College in New London. Saturday's events will be at the O'Neill Center.</p>
        <p>During the round-table discussion, Mr. Gelb said, ''We'll talk about the new material.'' He and Mrs. Gelb did extensive research for their recently published ''O'Neill: Life with Monte Cristo,'' the first volume in what is to be a three-volume rewrite of their 1962 work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ranelli predicted lively conversation. ''This is not a formal deal,'' he said. ''People can come, fuss, fight and fume.''</p>
        <p>Other participants will include Jackson Bryer, co-editor of ''The Selected Letters of Eugene O'Neill,'' and Judith Barlow, author of ''Final Acts: The Creation of Three Late O'Neill Plays.''</p>
        <p>O'Neill's innovations will be seen in the afternoon workshops, which Mr. Ranelli, a theater director who lives in Old Lyme, said would demonstrate ''performance and production, how we do things, how plays are dealt with in rehearsal.'' Among the participants will be Douglas Hughes, artistic director of the Long Wharf Theater in New Haven, and Mr. Ranelli, who will note Chekhov's influence on O'Neill. An evening reception will honor the actor Jason Robards, recipient of the first annual Monte Cristo Award.</p>
        <p>The weekend will draw attention to the history, problems and potential of the Monte Cristo Cottage, named after the Count of Monte Cristo role played by James O'Neill, the playwright's father. The cottage played a big role in the playwright's life and work, work that earned a Nobel Prize and four Pulitzer Prizes as well as setting a new course.</p>
        <p>''Eugene O'Neill changed the American theater,'' said Mr. Gelb. ''It was a very old-fashioned, melodramatic theater before he came on the scene. He helped raise it to the level of art. He forced Broadway to meet him and his new ideas on his own terms; he paved the way for people like Tennessee Williams.''</p>
        <p>O'Neill used the cottage as a setting not only for ''Long Day's Journey'' but also for his only comedy, ''Ah Wilderness!'' and parts of other plays. He used other local material as well, as he made his lasting mark. ''So much of the theater has sprung from what O'Neill represented,'' said the associate curator of the cottage, Lois McDonald, ''and so many of his plays reflect the time he spent in New London. He used settings, people he knew here.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. McDonald and the curator Sally Pavetti have worked at the cottage since the mid-70's. That was when George White, founder of the O'Neill Center, led efforts to buy the cottage, find money to renovate it and open it as a museum.</p>
        <p>The living room is furnished according to the stage directions for ''Long Day's Journey.'' Other rooms are filled with memorabilia.</p>
        <p>''People are fascinated by O'Neill's life,'' said Mrs. Pavetti, who has greeted visitors from all over. There been readings, seminars and other events at the cottage. But the budget has always been limited, and there has been no fully organized programming. ''We've been hopping from burner to burner,'' said Mrs. Pavetti, who like Mrs. McDonald is employed part-time.</p>
        <p>Now, said Howard Sherman, director-designate of the O'Neill Center, ''It's time to reinvigorate the facility.'' For starters, there's great need for foundation repairs and some fresh paint. Also planned is an addition that will provide easier access to the cottage, along with space for a bookshop. What's greatly hoped for is the construction of a barn-like building that would have climate-controlled archival space, elbow room for scholars doing research, and areas for classes, seminars and small-scale performances.</p>
        <p>Planning and fund raising lie ahead. ''The conference,'' said Mr. Sherman, ''is the first step in showing people what the Monte Cristo Cottage can be.''</p>
        <p>Conference events are free, but reservations are suggested for the Saturday events at the Eugene O'Neill Theater Center (305 Great Neck Road, Waterford). On the schedule are a round-table discussion of influences on O'Neill (10 a.m.-12:30 p.m.), workshops and discussions on rehearsal and performance of modern plays (1:30-4:30 p.m.) and a reception for Jason Robards (5-7 p.m.).</p>
        <p>Flock Theater performances of ''The Hairy Ape'' at Connecticut College are at 7:30 p.m. on Thursday, at 9:30 p.m. on Friday and at 7:30 p.m. on Saturday. Tickets are $12, $10 for older people and students.</p>
        <p>Readings of scenes from O'Neill plays take place at 7:30 p.m. at the Monte Cristo Cottage (325 Pequot Avenue; 860-443-0051) on Wednesday as well as again on Nov. 8 and Nov. 15. (No admission charge.)</p>
        <p>Call (860) 439-2787 for more information or reservations.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
