<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Down the Alley With a Stranger</title>
    <meta content="15SOAP$15" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238984"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FIRST PERSON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ross, Patricia Lahrmer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E1DF123FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1108" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Down the Alley With a Stranger</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA LAHRMER ROSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ross, Patricia Lahrmer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia Lahrmer Ross essay recounts experience when her car window was smashed, bag containing personal belongings was stolen and stranger on East Village street, who might have been perpetrator, helped her find her things; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DINNER was delicious. So was the Sunday evening in  the East Village. One of those you want to hold on to, summer lingering, the cold nights just around the corner.</p>
        <p>Walking in warm, light rain past vendors decorating a full block of Second Avenue with their wares, I noticed a tote bag, persimmon with blue and gold flowers. It stood out from the other drab garments, like a  lemon yellow taxi in a sea of gray traffic. The bag was exactly like the one I'd packed to take to the beach the next day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DINNER was delicious. So was the Sunday evening in  the East Village. One of those you want to hold on to, summer lingering, the cold nights just around the corner.</p>
        <p>Walking in warm, light rain past vendors decorating a full block of Second Avenue with their wares, I noticed a tote bag, persimmon with blue and gold flowers. It stood out from the other drab garments, like a  lemon yellow taxi in a sea of gray traffic. The bag was exactly like the one I'd packed to take to the beach the next day.</p>
        <p>''Oh, but it's a lot tattier than mine,'' I thought. We walked on, and I reflected on the coincidence. Mine was such an unusual bag.</p>
        <p>When my husband and I returned to our BMW wagon, parked on Cooper Square, we saw a man stooping to look into the back seat. Our car's back windows had been smashed.</p>
        <p>We knew better. Never leave bags in a car to tempt burglars. Park in a garage. But we were seduced by late summer; we discarded our cloak of urban mistrust.</p>
        <p>All I could think about was my address book, containing the whereabouts of every person I care for in this world. And also my weekly calendar for the year, the book that lets me feel I have a hold on life. Everything -- business and personal -- is in two black books. They mean nothing to anyone but me. Gone.</p>
        <p>I felt helpless, then violated, at the same time working to dispel both feelings, to steady myself.</p>
        <p>Finally, my husband spoke: ''Let's go straight to the police station.''</p>
        <p>''Drop me on Second Avenue,'' I replied. ''Someone in that sidewalk sale has all my clothes and books.''</p>
        <p>We hurried; the vendors might be packing up soon. It was Sunday night. I darted out of the car and determination seized me.</p>
        <p>Standing on the southeast corner of Seventh Street, I saw, coming toward me my persimmon bag, swinging in the left arm of a man with a carefree demeanor. He was a young man on a Sunday stroll, waving a paperback in his right hand.</p>
        <p>I walked up to him. ''Excuse me, this is important. I think that may be my bag.''</p>
        <p>He handed the bag to me, or I took it. The heaviness was a giveaway -- it was mine. I always pack too much. The other clue was the book in his hand, ''High Fidelity,'' the novel I had packed that morning.</p>
        <p>''Some of the stuff in here is mine,'' he said. ''Someone gave me this bag.'' We unzipped it together. Some items of clothing were familiar to me; others not.</p>
        <p>I looked him in the eye. This was a neighborhood I trusted, even though I knew drug dealers and users were nearby, in the alphabet streets to the east. I often came to the restaurants here for the comfort foods my grandmother made -- pirogis and cabbage soup. He was not posed for flight or conflict. I thought I saw contrition on his face. And surprise. I decided he was not the one who had smashed our car. A dealer in contraband or an accomplice to thieves? Maybe.</p>
        <p>''Look,'' I said. ''There was nothing in the bag I cared about except two small black books which are very important to me. I'll give you a reward if you can help me find them.''</p>
        <p>''Does one of the books say Mats. . . . something on the cover?''</p>
        <p>''Yes.''</p>
        <p>''I know where they are. Follow me.'' His eyes lit up.</p>
        <p>I felt strangely safe, even though I was alone with a stranger. He took the heavy bag from me, in what felt like a kind gesture. I was wearing high heels. He could move more quickly, so I told him to go ahead. I didn't want the two black books to have any extra minutes in which to fall into another's hands.</p>
        <p>We turned into an alley lit up bright as a football field, quiet as the countryside. Ahead of me, he was standing on a curb, smiling the triumph of a conqueror, waving two black books in the air. Surrounding him were puddles strewn with soggy debris -- my white leggings, beige lace underwear, a red silk pullover.</p>
        <p>''This is where they throw the stuff they don't want,'' he said. ''They mostly want cameras and stuff like that.''</p>
        <p>My companion assisted me, lifting a sandal here, a toiletry item there, as I signaled ''keep'' or ''discard.'' He gave me a plastic bag for the wet and soiled items. All the while he muttered a kind of mantra, ''Why do they do these things, why do they do these things?''</p>
        <p>Working in the damp night, I wondered, was this the first time he had seen the face of a burglary victim. Had he ever been able to associate a real person with the items he sold on the street? Could he be the thief after all? And a fine actor?</p>
        <p>I had lost all sense of time and place. The light was so bright, as if the moon had descended to give us a hand. I became aware that no one else in the world knew my whereabouts.</p>
        <p>''Oh, my medication!'' I cried. 'Do you see anything that looks like a medicine bottle?''</p>
        <p>I wanted to arouse his sympathy; the medication was only estrogen, easily replaceable.</p>
        <p>I noticed the coating of the small green estrogen tablets dissolving, giving the water an oil-slicked look. Smashed lipstick and mascara were partners in the puddles.</p>
        <p>Normal was returning. The work was done. I gave him a twenty.</p>
        <p>''Can I walk you back?'' he asked. Then he hugged me. ''I'm so sorry this happened to you.''</p>
        <p>There we were, wrapped in an embrace, a man who had to sell stolen clothing in the street to earn a living, and a woman who has enough clothing to keep a Salvation Army resale store in business.</p>
        <p>My walk back alone did not take long. A glimpse of a police car, two officers in the front seat and my husband in the back, brought me nearer to the real world.</p>
        <p>Later, I would remark that the only beloved garment missing was a T-shirt with a head shot of Elvis, captioned: ''Are You Lonesome Tonight?''</p>
        <p>''You mean he gave you the bag?''  the cops demanded. ''Where is he? You let him get away!''</p>
        <p>''You went with him?'' my husband exclaimed.</p>
        <p>What else could I have done?</p>
        <p>FIRST PERSON Patricia Lahrmer Ross was the original Passionate Shopper for New York magazine. She lives in Scarsdale, N.Y.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Patricia Lahrmer Ross was the original Passionate Shopper for New York magazine. She lives in Scarsdale, N.Y.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
