<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Helping Businesswomen Network</title>
    <meta content="15SING" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pace University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hudson Valley Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Singer, Cecile</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brenner, Elsa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E5DE173FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Helping Businesswomen Network</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELSA BRENNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brenner, Elsa</byline>
      <dateline>TUCKAHOE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Cecile Singer, 70, one of first women to serve in New York State Assembly and first and only woman on Hudson Valley Bank board in Tuckahoe; she is moderator of Second Annual Networking Roundtable for Women in Business and Professions at Pace University's Lubin Graduate Center; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT drives Cecile Singer after all these years?</p>
        <p>As a pioneer who opened doors for other women -- she was one of the first  women to serve in the New York State Assembly -- she's not satisfied with the progress that has been made since the women's movement began.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT drives Cecile Singer after all these years?</p>
        <p>As a pioneer who opened doors for other women -- she was one of the first  women to serve in the New York State Assembly -- she's not satisfied with the progress that has been made since the women's movement began.</p>
        <p>In the Assembly, Ms. Singer was -- among other things -- the ranking member of the Committee on Children and Families and the Subcommittee on Family Law. She has described herself as part of ''a bridge generation that sandwiched politics in between the children and the chicken soup.''</p>
        <p>It's not that the 70-year-old Ms. Singer points a finger at men or glass ceilings or any other outside force for the fact that women ''still aren't in the board rooms or back rooms where the real decisions are made,'' as she described the problem.</p>
        <p>''It's no one else's fault anymore,'' said Ms. Singer who is the first and only woman on the board of the Hudson Valley Bank here. ''The doors are open now for women in many professions, but we still have to move more of them through and get them to their goals.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Singer will be moderating the Second Annual Networking Roundtable for Women in Business and the Professions on Oct. 25 at Pace University's Lubin Graduate Center in White Plains. She organized the first round table a year ago, thinking at the time that it would be a one-time event.</p>
        <p>''Instead,'' she said, ''I found that there was an absolute hunger for women to talk to each other, to do business with each other.''</p>
        <p>Thirty years ago, when Ms. Singer was the assemblywoman from Yonkers, Bronxville, Tuckahoe and Scarsdale, women were so rare in government that people who saw her in the halls of the Capitol often mistook her for a secretary.</p>
        <p>But that's not the case these days. Three of Westchester's seven state representatives are women, although statistics show that women are markedly underrepresented in government. (In Congress and in most state legislatures, only 10 percent of the lawmakers are women; in the New York State Legislature, that number is about 18 percent.)</p>
        <p>Today, in government and business, the biggest problem for women, Ms. Singer said, is their inability ''to deal with the bottom line and make the cash registers ring.''</p>
        <p>''By and large,'' she said, ''we don't go to the golf courses to do business, and we don't have the networking in place to bring the dollars in the door with us.''</p>
        <p>The Networking Round Table is intended to foster discussion among women who are the decision makers in companies.</p>
        <p>Speakers will include Dr. Karen Berger, chairwoman of the marketing program at Pace, who will discuss marketing fundamentals; Shari Aaron, president of Fresh Marketing, who will talk about improving consumer perceptions of a company; Michael D. Feinstein, a senior vice president of Hudson Valley Bank, who will talk about financing business development with Small Business Administration Loans; and Marge Loverson, president of It's Strictly Business, who will focus on strategies to gain visibility.</p>
        <p>Abigail Kirsch, the Tarrytown caterer, will give the luncheon address, a case history of her business.</p>
        <p>Women who attend will have an opportunity to display their promotional literature and should bring their business cards to distribute. The cost of the conference is $35 a person in advance or $40 at the door. It begins at 8 a.m. and runs until 1 p.m.</p>
        <p>For further information, call Beth Willensky at (914) 576-5874 or mail a check payable to Women in Business and the Professions: Second Annual Round Table to C. Singer, 117 Cliffside Drive, Yonkers, N.Y. 10710.</p>
        <p>The conference is sponsored by the State Division for Women, Lower Hudson Advisory Council, of which Ms. Singer is the chairwoman; the Rockland-based Partnership of Women Entrepreneurs, a nonprofit group; the Westchester Association of Women Business Owners, another nonprofit organization; the Westchester Women's Bar Association; and Pace University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
