<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</title>
    <meta content="12ONLINE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001022T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238843"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E3D61F3CF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANITA GATES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S easy to forget what a skillful work Robert Zemeckis's FORREST GUMP (1994) is. Six years later, the special effects (from the hero, chatting with presidents to Gary Sinise's amputated legs) don't seem so amazing, but Tom Hanks's gut-level sincerity in the title role does. This is the story of a simple man's life, his love for one woman (Robin Wright, who is lovely as the emotionally bruised Jenny) and his encounters with Elivs, J.F.K., Bear Bryant, Dick Cavett, the Black Panthers, Vietnam, shrimp boats, Apple Computer stock and long-distance running. ''Forrest Gump'' won six Oscars, including best picture, best actor and best director, and it proved that an I.Q. of 75 and a good heart can get big cosmic free-for-all. You decide -- Saturday at 8 p.m. on Channel 7.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S easy to forget what a skillful work Robert Zemeckis's FORREST GUMP (1994) is. Six years later, the special effects (from the hero, chatting with presidents to Gary Sinise's amputated legs) don't seem so amazing, but Tom Hanks's gut-level sincerity in the title role does. This is the story of a simple man's life, his love for one woman (Robin Wright, who is lovely as the emotionally bruised Jenny) and his encounters with Elivs, J.F.K., Bear Bryant, Dick Cavett, the Black Panthers, Vietnam, shrimp boats, Apple Computer stock and long-distance running. ''Forrest Gump'' won six Oscars, including best picture, best actor and best director, and it proved that an I.Q. of 75 and a good heart can get big cosmic free-for-all. You decide -- Saturday at 8 p.m. on Channel 7.</p>
        <p>Clint Eastwood did a masterly job of turning Robert James Waller's soap opera of a novel into a film: THE BRIDGES OF MADISON COUNTY (1995). And probably only Mr. Eastwood, directing himself, could get away with a line like ''I embrace the mystery'' without sounding tritely New Age. He's the craggy National Georgraphic photographer on assignment to shoot covered bridges in the heartland. Meryl Streep is the vaguely dissatisfied Iowa housewife and mother he asks for directions. The rest is romantic history, four days that shook their world. The film's greatest achievement may be that it manages to celebrate the grand passion and family responsibility equally - Saturday at 8 p.m. on Channel 4.</p>
        <p>When Jean Renoir's GRAND ILLUSION (1937) opened in this country in 1938, the New York Times film critic Frank S. Nugent called it ''a strange and interesting film.'' That's the sort of understatement this masterpiece does so well. Pierre Fresnay, Jean Gabinand Dalio star as french officers (aristocrat, exmachinist and heir to a new-money banking fortune) in a World War I German prison camp. Erich von Stroheim is their courtly commandant. The film is quietly articulate about social class and definitions of escape, but it has moments of literal patriotism too. Just try to resist the impromptu ''marseillaise'' in the middle of the prisoners revue -- Thursday at 10 p.m. on TCM.</p>
        <p>George Stevens was in career transition, from comedy to drama, when he directed I REMEMBER MAMA (1948), and the result is enough to give sentimentality a good name. Irene Dunne stars as the emotional core of a struggling, loving Norwegian immigrant family in early-20th-century San Francisco. Barbara Bel Geddes is the aspiring-writer daughter who narrates. The plot is the stuff of everyday life: financial worries, relatives' visits, a timid suitor, a rapid passage of time. Oscar Homolka's death scene may not be the most realistic in cinema history, but it makes a good argument for everyone's last word being a toast: ''Skol'' -- Saturday at 9 p.m. on Channel 13.</p>
        <p>Henry James, like many great authors, is tricky to translate for the screen, so Peter Bogdanovich can be forgiven if DAISY MILLER (1974) is imperfect. The story -- of a headstrong young American beauty, making enemies and conquests on the grand Tour -- is still intriguing. And the film is lovely to look at, beginning in the lake-side gardens of Montreux, Switzerland, and ending in the ancient glamour of Rome. As Daisy, the 24-year-old Cybill Shepard plays insipid self-absorption to the hilt. It is strange, though, that Mr. Bogdanovich seems to have directed her never to take a breath - Wednesday at 10:15 p.m. and Wednesday/Early Thursday at 5 a.m. on AMC.</p>
        <p>Anita Gates</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 22, 2000, Sunday  A picture caption on the Critic's Choice movie page of the Television section last Sunday misidentified the actor standing beside Erich von Stroheim in the film ''Grand Illusion.'' He was Pierre Fresnay, not Jean Gabin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 22, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on the Critic's Choice movie page of the Television section last Sunday misidentified the actor standing beside Erich von Stroheim in the film ''Grand Illusion.'' He was Pierre Fresnay, not Jean Gabin.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
