<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Echoes From a Dark Past</title>
    <meta content="15KENN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/arts/15KENN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238833"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wahlberg, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Dana</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Yards, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E6DF1F3CF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2181" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Echoes From a Dark Past</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANA KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Dana</byline>
      <dateline>SANTA MONICA, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dana Kennedy interviews actor Mark Wahlberg, who comments on preparation for his role in new movie The Yards and time he spent as 17-year-old convict in Deer Island prison near Boston; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE REV. JAMES FLAVIN still remembers what it was like to visit 17-year-old Mark Wahlberg in the Deer Island prison near Boston where the future rapper, underwear model and movie star was serving time for attacking a man with a hooked stick that took out his eye during a robbery.</p>
        <p>''It was such a horrendous place, they've closed it down,'' said Father Flavin, a Roman Catholic priest who has been both friend and counselor to Mr. Wahlberg since he was 13. ''It was filthy and there were rats everywhere. Mark was really scared. He was such a little guy. But he always put on a tough face.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE REV. JAMES FLAVIN still remembers what it was like to visit 17-year-old Mark Wahlberg in the Deer Island prison near Boston where the future rapper, underwear model and movie star was serving time for attacking a man with a hooked stick that took out his eye during a robbery.</p>
        <p>''It was such a horrendous place, they've closed it down,'' said Father Flavin, a Roman Catholic priest who has been both friend and counselor to Mr. Wahlberg since he was 13. ''It was filthy and there were rats everywhere. Mark was really scared. He was such a little guy. But he always put on a tough face.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahlberg, now 29, served 45 days for what police said was the racially motivated beating of a Vietnamese man in 1988. Mr. Wahlberg later said that he and his friends were under the influence of alcohol and PCP during the attack and denied that race was a factor. But the reality of prison shocked him into turning his life around, he says. For years he has had nightmares about going back.</p>
        <p>Last year he did go back, but on his own terms. For his role as Leo Handler, a troubled young man just released from prison in the new film ''The Yards'' (opening on Friday), Mr. Wahlberg arranged to be incarcerated at Rikers Island in New York for a day. ''They took all my stuff, gave me an ID and put me in the cage,'' Mr. Wahlberg said during a lunch interview at an elegant Italian restaurant here. ''I went through the whole place, even the Bing, where they house the really violent inmates. I lifted some weights in the yard. It was very helpful. It refreshed my memory.''</p>
        <p>Immersing himself in roles is nothing new for Mr. Wahlberg, who moved to Gloucester, Mass., weeks before filming started on his last movie, ''The Perfect Storm,'' and lived above a waterside bar, mingling and drinking with the locals. He spent six months working with a vocal coach for his part as a rock star in the 2001 release ''So You Wanna Be a Rock Star'' (formerly ''Metal God''), with Jennifer Aniston, and he's about to go ''hang with test pilots,'' he said, for his role in Tim Burton's planned remake of ''The Planet of the Apes,'' the part Charlton Heston originally played.</p>
        <p>But when it came to ''The Yards,'' a drama about family and corruption set in the vast New York subway yards, it would seem that Mr. Wahlberg had already done sufficient research. In fact, he was originally hired to play Willie, Leo's treacherous best friend, but switched roles with the actor Joaquin Phoenix. ''Willie was the flashier part, but I felt I knew Leo and I should play him,'' Mr. Wahlberg said. ''I spoke to Joaquin and he felt for the other part, so it worked out.''</p>
        <p>Leo's prison term comes about largely because he took the fall for friends, and he spends most of the movie terrified he will slip up and be sent back. In real life, Mr. Wahlberg had frequent brushes with the law before he went to jail and several more even after he shot to fame as the rapper Marky Mark, in the early 1990's.</p>
        <p>But unlike Leo, Mr. Wahlberg was not isolated in jail. ''I was in there with these 30- to 34-year-old guys from my neighborhood who I'd really looked up to,'' Mr. Wahlberg said. ''When I saw what they were about, I decided I wanted something better. A lot of them had a problem with that. It forced them to look at themselves.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahlberg went to Rikers to research his role for ''The Yards'' because his own experience had been so different. ''Leo wasn't the kind of guy who would go to prison and see guys he knew like I did,'' he said. ''He got thrown into Rikers, a white guy who didn't know anybody. That's a lot tougher. I only saw three white guys in the yard when I was there. One white guy was in for some white collar crime, and he kept getting beat up every day because he wanted to get up and watch the Bloomberg Report.''</p>
        <p>That Mr. Wahlberg would return to prison -- this time as a movie star -- testifies to a life story that itself would make a riveting film. But while his journey from Boston street thug to washed-up rap sensation to respected Hollywood player seems unlikely at best, Mr. Wahlberg says he has been an actor of sorts all his life. ''Whether I was doing a scam on somebody in a store or on the street or whether I was telling the judge it wasn't me and putting on the tears, it was all acting,'' he said. ''I could always get over the judge, the cops, my mother. If the cameras had been rolling when I was in court all those times, I'd have a couple Oscars already.''</p>
        <p>Father Flavin is one of many friends, relatives and Hollywood heavyweights who have taken a liking to Mr. Wahlberg and have often helped advance his career.</p>
        <p>Others include his brother Donnie, the entertainment mogul David Geffen, the director Penny Marshall and, most recently, the actor George Clooney. They seem to regard him with affection, respect -- and some wariness. Father Flavin, who remains so close to Mr. Wahlberg that the actor flew him out to Los Angeles last month so they could spend a few days golfing together, sums him up this way: ''He's the best con artist I've ever met, but he's worked really hard to change.''</p>
        <p>JAMES GRAY, 31, the director and co-writer of ''The Yards,'' says that he and Mr. Wahlberg spoke often of Mr. Wahlberg's jail experience and became friends during the shoot. ''But I don't really feel that I know him,'' Mr. Gray said. ''He's very hard to read, a very complex character. There's something mysterious about him. I will say this: he's incredibly shrewd, incredibly street smart. Nobody can outfox him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahlberg grew up in working-class Dorchester, Mass., the youngest of nine children. His father, a hard-drinking truck driver, and his mother, a nurse, split up when he was 11. Mr. Wahlberg's life unraveled soon after.</p>
        <p>He dropped out of school after the eighth grade and began a life of crime with friends from his neighborhood, robbing and beating up people and sometimes selling drugs.</p>
        <p>During this time, his brother, Donnie Wahlberg, became the front man for New Kids on the Block, the 1980's teenage heartthrob singing group. At one point Donnie let Mr. Wahlberg open for the group as Marky Mark and his career took off. At that point Mr. Wahlberg's only previous performing experience had been in elementary school talent shows, in which he had achieved some notoriety for break-dancing and rapping. But Mark disliked the canned choreography and commercial sound of the New Kids and dropped out within a few months, returning to his criminal life on the streets.</p>
        <p>After he was released from prison, Donnie Wahlberg came to the rescue again. He urged his brother to move to Los Angeles, got a friend to watch out for him and helped him get a recording contract. Two years after leaving jail, Mr. Wahlberg's first album, ''Marky Mark and the Funky Bunch,'' went platinum.</p>
        <p>Not long after, David Geffen, who was producing records at the time, sized up Mr. Wahlberg's popularity among young girls and suggested to his friend Calvin Klein that he use him in a modeling campaign. The Calvin Klein contract led, in 1993, to  revelations about Mr. Wahlberg's past when reporters found out about his arrest and prison term as well as two earlier incidents in which the police said he had chased and yelled racial epithets at African-American school children.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahlberg's rap career faded and he got involved in more scandals, most involving fights in clubs and accusations of homophobia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahlberg, who is soft-spoken and genial in person, is resigned to questions about his past. The only time he becomes uncomfortable during the interview is when he is asked if he has ever sought out Tranh Lam, the man who lost his eye in the attack and apologized to him. (The Boston police say Mr. Lam apparently moved out of Dorchester and his current whereabouts are unknown.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahlberg says he apologized to Mr. Lam in court but has not had contact with him since. ''It would be unfair to all the other people that I messed up if I only singled him out,'' he said. ''I'm certainly sorry for what I did. I did this every day until I was sent to prison.''</p>
        <p>His past may cause Mr. Wahlberg genuine pain, but it has sometimes proved useful in Hollywood. ''Certain people in this town love it,'' he said. ''They think it's sexy, they think it's great.''</p>
        <p>But while Mr. Wahlberg may have been aggressive and violent as a youth, he is, by all accounts, almost docile on movie sets. Mr. Gray's directing style, he says, is so detailed that he often positions the actors' heads just so. ''Joaquin threatened me with bodily harm if I ever touched his head,'' Mr. Gray recalled. ''It didn't bother Mark at all.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahlberg says he is happiest when directors, like David Russell of ''Three Kings,'' give him precise line readings before each take. ''I figure, why not give them what they want?'' Mr. Wahlberg said.</p>
        <p>That attitude runs counter to the bad-boy street reputation that got Mr. Wahlberg started as an actor. Though he reportedly had a falling out with Mr. Klein during his modeling contract, he admits the sneering, hard-bodied images of him shot by Herb Ritts got him his first big acting job as a tough Southern soldier in ''Renaissance Man'' (1994).</p>
        <p>''Penny Marshall saw me in my underwear on the billboard and called me up to audition,'' Mr. Wahlberg said. ''I got the part, and I was on my way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahlberg won good reviews for ''Renaissance Man'' and even better ones the following year in ''Basketball Diaries,'' opposite Leonardo DiCaprio. But it was his breakout performance as the extremely well-endowed porn star Dirk Diggler in ''Boogie Nights'' (1997) that earned him respect in Hollywood.</p>
        <p>His role in ''Three Kings'' last year, which co-starred George Clooney, led to a lasting bond between the two men. Mr. Wahlberg co-starred with Mr. Clooney as a doomed swordfisherman in ''The Perfect Storm,'' and Mr. Clooney's company is producing ''So You Wanna Be a Rock Star.''</p>
        <p>A LL I'm trying to do is create a body of work I can be proud of,'' Mr. Wahlberg said. ''I'm doing things people think I can't pull off, but I'm not doing things I don't think I can pull off.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Wahlberg said, he has embarked on an effort to improve himself and to help young people in his old neighborhood. He returns occasionally to speak at the local Boys Club that banned him, supposedly for life, at age 12. He is also close to his nine nieces and nephews, for whom he has already set aside money for college tuition. He is about to earn his high school equivalency degree after studying for several years.</p>
        <p>''It's embarrassing for me when they ask where I went to school because they look up to me,'' Mr. Wahlberg said. ''They think if I didn't graduate from high school, why should they? I tell them I'm still going to school and so should they.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahlberg is based in Los Angeles but lives in sublets and carts his possessions around in boxes. He considers his mother's Braintree, Mass., house his real home. He is involved with the actress Jordana Brewster (''The Faculty'') but says serious relationships are difficult for him. He is more enthusiastic talking about how many of his friends from his old neighborhood are now working for him in Los Angeles. Unlike Leo Handler and his associates in ''The Yards,'' said Mr. Wahlberg, ''they stay out of trouble now, and so do I.''</p>
        <p>Father Flavin said: ''Having some of his old friends around and helping them change is his way of staying sane himself. Just because he's out in Hollywood doesn't mean his life is perfect. His new life has as many challenges as the old one. You can get lost out there as easily as you can back home.''</p>
        <p>FILM Dana Kennedy is an entertainment reporter for MSNBC.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dana Kennedy is an entertainment reporter for MSNBC.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
