<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Grades 4 and 8 Fared on Tests</title>
    <meta content="15REPORT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E4DB113FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Grades 4 and 8 Fared on Tests</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tables show results of New York City fourth- and eighth-grade statewide math tests (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York State Education Department released the results of statewide tests in reading and mathematics last week, and the news was mixed. Students across the state, especially in New York City and other urban areas, failed to meet new higher standards and graduation requirements set by the state.</p>
        <p>Overall scores climbed slightly on the eighth-grade math test, but dropped on the fourth-grade math and eighth-grade reading tests. In the city, the results were particularly poor in the eighth grade for the second year in a row, raising questions about whether middle schools are meeting students' needs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York State Education Department released the results of statewide tests in reading and mathematics last week, and the news was mixed. Students across the state, especially in New York City and other urban areas, failed to meet new higher standards and graduation requirements set by the state.</p>
        <p>Overall scores climbed slightly on the eighth-grade math test, but dropped on the fourth-grade math and eighth-grade reading tests. In the city, the results were particularly poor in the eighth grade for the second year in a row, raising questions about whether middle schools are meeting students' needs.</p>
        <p>Among the city's eighth-grade students who took the state tests, 68 percent failed to meet standards on the English Language Arts test, compared with 65 percent in 1999. In math, 77 percent failed to meet standards, the same number as last year. Nearly half of the city's eighth-grade test-takers scored in the lowest possible category on the math exam.</p>
        <p>Of all the city students who took the fourth-grade math test, 54 percent failed to meet state standards, compared with 50 percent in 1999. Results of a fourth-grade English Language Arts test were released last spring.</p>
        <p>What follows are the scores for city public schools that have a fourth or eighth grade.</p>
        <p>ABBY GOODNOUGH</p>
        <p>INCOME -- Percentage of students who did not qualify for free school lunch, based on Federal income guidelines. The higher the number, the higher the income.</p>
        <p>NUMBER TESTED -- Total number of students who took each test.</p>
        <p>PERFORMANCE LEVELS -- Percentage of students in each category. Levels are ranked from 1 to 4, lowest to highest. Students at Levels 1 and 2 fall below standards, with those at Level 1 having serious deficiencies, and those at Level 2 needing extra help.</p>
        <p>Students at Levels 3 and 4 meet the standards. Those at Level 3 are on track to meet the state's high school graduation requirements, and those at Level 4 perform at consistently high levels.</p>
        <p>PERCENTAGE MEETING STANDARDS -- Total percentage of students scoring at Levels 3 or 4 this year and last. Change indicates increase or decrease in the percentage.</p>
        <p>NOTES -- Blanks indicate missing data. District summaries were calculated from individual school data provided by the state. Tables include all schools for which the state provided data. Data for some schools were not available.</p>
        <p>District 85 schools have been taken over by the Chancellor for poor performance.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
