<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>We're No. 1, and Paying for It</title>
    <meta content="15STEE$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/opinion/15STEE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steel, Ronald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E5D7133FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1123" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>We're No. 1, and Paying for It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ronald Steel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steel, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ronald Steel Op-Ed article on foreign policy issue that Al Gore and George W Bush will not discuss: US is a great imperial power; says great powers may be admired or emulated, but they are rarely loved; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was an eerie coincidence. On Wednesday night, Al Gore and George W. Bush debated foreign policy for some 40 minutes. The next day, the tense confrontation between Israelis and Palestinians erupted into virtual open warfare, and in Yemen, the American Navy destroyer Cole was bombed in a terrorist attack that took the lives of 17 sailors.</p>
        <p>In retrospect, the debate last week didn't come close to touching on the real repercussions of an interventionist foreign policy. It's not that such a policy is wrong. But the terrorist attack on Thursday does demonstrate that in foreign policy, as in domestic policy, there is no free lunch; every policy exacts a price.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was an eerie coincidence. On Wednesday night, Al Gore and George W. Bush debated foreign policy for some 40 minutes. The next day, the tense confrontation between Israelis and Palestinians erupted into virtual open warfare, and in Yemen, the American Navy destroyer Cole was bombed in a terrorist attack that took the lives of 17 sailors.</p>
        <p>In retrospect, the debate last week didn't come close to touching on the real repercussions of an interventionist foreign policy. It's not that such a policy is wrong. But the terrorist attack on Thursday does demonstrate that in foreign policy, as in domestic policy, there is no free lunch; every policy exacts a price.</p>
        <p>Terrorist attacks are not capricious, nor are they even irrational. They have happened with regularity over the years. In 1998, the American embassies in Kenya and Tanzania were bombed and 224 people were killed. In 1996, a truck bomb exploded outside an American military compound in Saudi Arabia, killing and injuring more than 500 people. In 1993, the World Trade Center in Manhattan was bombed by foreign terrorists.</p>
        <p>All these acts were directly related to the active role the United States plays in the world, and they were intended to punish and change that role.</p>
        <p>Neither George Bush nor Al Gore wants to change that role in any kind of real way -- but they, and we as a country, have failed to address its repercussions. Instead, in this presidential campaign, we have focused on essentially rhetorical differences.</p>
        <p>In the debate, Mr. Gore presented himself as a committed liberal interventionist in the Woodrow Wilson tradition. He defended the American intervention in Bosnia on humanitarian grounds, and also went on to argue that ''genocide or ethnic cleansing . . . can bring into play a fundamental American strategic interest, because I think it's based on our values.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the promotion of American values throughout the world seemed to be the centerpiece of his foreign policy. The United States should ''have a sense of mission in the world'' and use its ''values'' and its strength to ''project the power for good that American can represent,'' he proclaimed.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, he defended the administration's decision not to intervene in the Rwanda genocide, in which an estimated 600,000 people were murdered. He did so on the grounds that our ''national security interest'' was not involved.</p>
        <p>This explanation hardy differed from that of Mr. Bush, who also opposed humanitarian intervention in Rwanda and supported the intervention in Bosnia (because of our interests in NATO). Although he opposed sending troops to Haiti to promote democracy, he supported interventions in Lebanon, Grenada, Panama and the Persian Gulf.</p>
        <p>''We can't be all things to all people in the world,'' Mr. Bush declared, nor should we ''walk into a country and say, we do it this way, so should you.''</p>
        <p>For all their supposed differences, Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush agree more than they disagree. They both believe in a powerful military, in strong alliances held together by America's armed forces, direct economic and political intervention where it serves American interests and the active discouragement of any potential rival power.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush may have spoken gently during the debate about the virtues of displaying ''humility.'' But what he meant was the humility of the strong, not of the weak. Moreover, both men labored to portray their vision of American foreign policy as good not only for the United States but for the world.</p>
        <p>The attack in Yemen serves as a  reality check. It reminds us that the very ''values'' in which we take pride can be viewed by others as hypocritical or corrupt or even evil. And it reminds us that our power to project our values can been seen as a mortal threat to the values of others, however objectionable we may regard those values.</p>
        <p>Those we describe as terrorists do not see themselves in such terms. They are, in their own eyes, what Ronald Reagan once called the Nicaraguan contras: ''the moral equivalent of our Founding Fathers.''</p>
        <p>Even among our friends, admiration for our values is not unbounded. The attack on a McDonald's store in France by a disgruntled citizen was widely applauded there as an act of cultural resistance. For most of the world, America is the 800-pound gorilla that they must appease as they lie down with it uneasily every night.</p>
        <p>It can hardly be otherwise. If the United States is to play a powerful role in the world -- and both candidates, along with virtually all Americans, want this -- it must do things that will annoy and even infuriate others.</p>
        <p>This is true no matter what we do. It is particularly true if the United States more actively pursues what Mr. Gore has referred to as the policy of ''forward engagement'' --  of ''addressing problems early in their development before they become crises.''</p>
        <p>This is another way of describing an activist, interventionist foreign policy of the sort that a great imperial power pursues to protect its interests and nip opposition in the bud.</p>
        <p>But such policies exact a price. One of them is involvement in wars and crises over issues that we hardly understand; another is being subjected to the feverish contempt of those who scorn what we are and hate us for what we do.</p>
        <p>This is the way the world works, and it does little good, except perhaps for our self-esteem, to proclaim, as Mr. Gore did in the debate that, ''this nation is now looked on by peoples on every other continent and the peoples from every part of this earth as a kind of model for what the future could be.''</p>
        <p>Nor can we realistically be a ''humble nation,'' in Mr. Bush's phrase, in anything but rhetoric if we expect to retain our full power and influence. The suicide bombers in Yemen help remind us that virtue is not its own reward.</p>
        <p>Great powers may be admired or emulated, but they are rarely loved. Both George Bush and Al Gore know this, even though they think that voters' tender sensibilities may be offended to hear it. But we and they have to recognize our nation as the great imperial power it has become.</p>
        <p>And as Edmund Burke observed during the high tide of British power and influence, ''A great empire and little minds go ill together.''</p>
        <p>Ronald Steel teaches international relations at the University of Southern California and is the author of ''Temptations of a Superpower'' and ''In Love with Night: The American Romance with Robert Kennedy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ronald Steel teaches international relations at the University of Southern California and is the author of ''Temptations of a Superpower'' and ''In Love with Night: The American Romance with Robert Kennedy.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
