<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lazio Reasserts His Support for the Israelis</title>
    <meta content="15LAZI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/nyregion/15LAZI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239158"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DE113FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lazio Reasserts His Support for the Israelis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <dateline>POUGHKEEPSIE, N.Y., Oct. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Repr Rick A Lazio, campaigning through New York's Hudson Valley, urges staunch support for Israel; takes hard-line stance against Palestinians and criticizes Clinton Administration for abstaining from United Nations Security Council vote last week instead of casting veto; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the White House announced today that President Clinton would head to the Mideast to mediate peace talks, Representative Rick A. Lazio continued his criticism of the administration, saying: ''What Israel needs right now is not a broker. It needs an ally.''</p>
        <p>The comments put some distance not only between Mr. Lazio, the Republican candidate for United States Senate from New York, and Mr. Clinton, but also between Mr. Lazio and the Republican presidential nominee, George W. Bush, who has expressed support for the president's mediation efforts in the Mideast and said that the United States must ''speak with one voice.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the White House announced today that President Clinton would head to the Mideast to mediate peace talks, Representative Rick A. Lazio continued his criticism of the administration, saying: ''What Israel needs right now is not a broker. It needs an ally.''</p>
        <p>The comments put some distance not only between Mr. Lazio, the Republican candidate for United States Senate from New York, and Mr. Clinton, but also between Mr. Lazio and the Republican presidential nominee, George W. Bush, who has expressed support for the president's mediation efforts in the Mideast and said that the United States must ''speak with one voice.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio and his Democratic opponent, Hillary Rodham Clinton, have been courting Jewish voters in a race that polls indicate is tight.</p>
        <p>Both have taken a hard-line stance against the Palestinians and have criticized the Clinton administration for abstaining from a United Nations Security Council vote last week instead of casting a veto. The vote condemned Israel for a spate of violence that has left nearly 100 dead -- mostly Palestinians -- in the past two weeks. Mrs. Clinton, though, has generally backed her husband's efforts to resolve the crisis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio made his remarks as he departed from his stump speech to comment on the explosion on the U.S.S. Cole in Yemen. He said the incident, which Navy officials say was apparently caused by a terrorist bomb, was evidence that the United States needed to stand tough toward the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>''It is important now not to equivocate,'' Mr. Lazio said. ''Not to show weakness. Not to create openings where others can exploit that. And so our hearts go out to the men in uniform who lost their lives in the last few days. It once again points up the fact that we live in a very dangerous world.''</p>
        <p>Later, at a news conference, Mr. Lazio tempered his remarks about the United States' role in the peace talks, which are scheduled for Monday in Egypt.</p>
        <p>''I think that to the extent that people can continue to discuss ways in which we can bring peace, that's a good thing,'' Mr. Lazio said. ''I think it's fine that Egypt has agreed to be a partner in trying to resolve the latest violence. I think we should be a partner to that. But I think that that should not suggest or indicate that there is any ambivalence or there is any equivocation about where our security concerns lie, that we stand shoulder to shoulder with Israel.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio began his day of campaigning with a speech to the Board of Realtors in Tuxedo. Then he visited a center for the elderly and a deli in Goshen, a pumpkin festival in Kingston, and downtown Poughkeepsie before winding up tonight at a ''Rigatoni with Rick'' dinner in White Plains.</p>
        <p>At the same time, his campaign released two new commercials that went on the air today and criticized Mrs. Clinton's record and move to New York. ''Can you name three things Hillary Clinton has done for New York?'' an announcer asks, followed by a procession of people answering ''no'' in various ways.</p>
        <p>At the pumpkin festival, amid the usual assortment of backers decked out in Lazio T-shirts and the like, he encountered a band of supporters wearing a devil costume, a Hillary Clinton mask and a hockey mask similar to the one worn by the character from the ''Friday the 13th'' movies. The devil held a sign that read, ''I sold my soul to Bill Clinton.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio, who has expressed some ambivalence about negative campaigning, made an effort to avoid them.</p>
        <p>''They mean well,'' Mr. Lazio told a supporter who inquired about the costumed supporters as people began photographing them. ''I just don't want to get in the photo, though.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
