<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gazing Up Third Avenue and Seeing the Future</title>
    <meta content="15DREA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239014"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: THE HUB"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">City College of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EFDC123FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gazing Up Third Avenue and Seeing the Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Architects from City College seek input from local residents over development of new business district planned around the Hub, corner of 149th Street and Third Avenue in the Bronx; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Commissioned to create the look of the major new business district planned around the Hub, the corner of 149th Street and Third Avenue, architects from City College roamed the area with cameras last week, craning their necks over a steady stream of traffic heading north to Yonkers and trying to see the future.</p>
        <p>The architects were working with local residents, who had given their ideas for the redevelopment in a series of public meetings called dream sessions and held by Community Board 1. Though the project encompasses 156th to 145th Streets, from Park to St. Ann's Avenues, it focuses on the center of the Hub, a patch of land wedged into the heart of three smoldering arteries of through traffic, hemmed in by nine bus stops and two subway stations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Commissioned to create the look of the major new business district planned around the Hub, the corner of 149th Street and Third Avenue, architects from City College roamed the area with cameras last week, craning their necks over a steady stream of traffic heading north to Yonkers and trying to see the future.</p>
        <p>The architects were working with local residents, who had given their ideas for the redevelopment in a series of public meetings called dream sessions and held by Community Board 1. Though the project encompasses 156th to 145th Streets, from Park to St. Ann's Avenues, it focuses on the center of the Hub, a patch of land wedged into the heart of three smoldering arteries of through traffic, hemmed in by nine bus stops and two subway stations.</p>
        <p>The residents had envisioned fountains springing from concrete, streets closed for public parks, and new stores flinging open their doors to recapture the vitality that radiated half a century ago from the area, once called the Times Square of the Bronx.</p>
        <p>The faded Hearns department store sign on a tall building still shone brilliantly back then, and the grand old 1910 opera house, now occupied by a church, swung with the rhythms of New York's most renowned Puerto Rican bandleaders as the Bronx Casino and the Caravana Club.</p>
        <p>Though the realization of dreams for the area is still a long way off, the architects are to deliver a progress report to the community on Nov. 1. In January, they will submit their final recommendations, likely to include specifications for everything from street vending to building heights, or possibly even bringing musical events back into the old opera house.</p>
        <p>Today a bus dispatcher's hut made of blue and white concrete blocks and a simple bus overhang are the centerpiece of the Hub. But the way the architects see it, this triangle of concrete is the one major slab of public space in the area, and it should be beautiful, accessible, memorable and comfortable.</p>
        <p>''That has got to go,'' said Marilyn Gallagher, a landscape architect who is the project manager from City University's Architectural Center, motioning toward the dispatcher's office. ''It doesn't need to be that large. The rest of the triangle should be public space.''</p>
        <p>''It'd be nice if it were covered,'' she added. ''A fountain, perhaps. Trees, if possible. It should be a place to sit, with good signs, where you can stop. One idea would be to refer to the past, an event, industry or maybe even transportation itself, the fact that the El was here.''</p>
        <p>On the street, as a barreling van honked loud and long at a woman crossing with a baby carriage, Zeev Raz surveyed the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>''It's good to improve things, said Mr. Raz, outside the Sound Buys music store where he works. ''It raises up the spirit of the people.''</p>
        <p>ANDREW FRIEDMAN</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: THE HUB</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
