<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Baseball Tradition Thriving in St. Louis</title>
    <meta content="15DAVE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/sports/15ANDE-EARLY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239220"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4DA113FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="955" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Baseball Tradition Thriving in St. Louis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Anderson Sports of The Times Column discusses winning tradition of St Louis Cardinals franchise; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN October, baseball is more than just games between teams that represent a city. It's often one area of America against another.</p>
        <p>If a Subway Series were to develop between the Yankees and the Mets, it would create a civil war within New York's five boroughs and the surrounding suburbs on Long Island, Westchester, northern New Jersey and southern Connecticut. But the two current League Championship Series are much more than New York against St. Louis and New York against Seattle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN October, baseball is more than just games between teams that represent a city. It's often one area of America against another.</p>
        <p>If a Subway Series were to develop between the Yankees and the Mets, it would create a civil war within New York's five boroughs and the surrounding suburbs on Long Island, Westchester, northern New Jersey and southern Connecticut. But the two current League Championship Series are much more than New York against St. Louis and New York against Seattle.</p>
        <p>They are really New York against Middle America in one series and New York against the Pacific Northwest in the other.</p>
        <p>''In St. Louis, they're not talking about a Subway Series, they're talking about St. Louis,'' Tony La Russa, the Cardinals' manager, said after yesterday's 8-2 victory at Shea cut the Mets' lead to 2-1 in their National League pennant playoff. ''We come from the Midwest. That's not what they're hoping for there.''</p>
        <p>If everybody out there beyond the Hudson River always seems to be rooting against the Big City, everybody out there is rooting even harder for their own geographical area. And no team, including the Yankees, has deeper roots for its rooters than the St. Louis Cardinals, a franchise with a long proud tradition.</p>
        <p>''There is a great tradition here, a great organization,'' said second baseman Fernando Vina, who was with the Mets and the Milwaukee Brewers before being traded to the Cardinals late last year. ''After losing two, we had to go out there and battle. That's the qualities of this organization -- battling, playing hard.''</p>
        <p>If the Yankee tradition goes back to Babe Ruth and Lou Gehrig, the Cardinal tradition goes back just as far, to when second baseman Rogers Hornsby hit .424 in the 1924 season and 39-year-old Grover Cleveland Alexander struck out Tony Lazzeri to quench the Yankees in the 1926 World Series.</p>
        <p>All those baseball fans in Middle America know that Cardinal tradition also goes back to when Dizzy Dean and the Gashouse Gang reigned, when Stan Musial drilled holes in the right-field screen at Ebbets Field, when Bob Gibson drilled holes in batters' ribs, when Lou Brock stole all those bases, when Ozzie Smith somersaulted to shortstop.</p>
        <p>Will Clark has been a Cardinal for less than three months since being acquired to play first base while Mark McGwire is reduced to being a pinch-hitter on a damaged right knee, but he appreciates that tradition.</p>
        <p>''You see guys like Bob Gibson, Lou Brock and Red Schoendienst around the clubhouse,'' Clark said. ''Even Stan Musial from time to time. They have some awesome stories to tell, and I'm all ears.''</p>
        <p>Joe McEwing, the Mets' handyman infielder-outfielder, toiled in the Cardinals' farm system for seven season before earning the nickname Super Joe as a rookie last year. He joined the Mets during spring training in a March trade for the left-hander Jesse Orosco, but he learned his baseball in the Cardinal system.</p>
        <p>''In the Cardinal clubhouse there are pictures and plaques all over the place of the famous players,'' McEwing said. ''I remember Lou Brock talking about base-stealing and saying, 'When you turn to steal, move your right elbow hard to clear your path.' ''</p>
        <p>Gibson and Brock are on the payroll as special instructors. Schoendienst, a former Cardinal manager, is a special assistant to the general manager. Musial is still ''Stan the Man,'' a seven-time National League batting champion with a statue outside Busch Stadium. Once upon a time, he would offer advice on hitting.</p>
        <p>''Stan would start by saying, 'Just hang back and . . ,' '' Keith Hernandez recalled, ''then he'd stop and say, 'Oh, just see the ball and hit it.' ''</p>
        <p>Hernandez, the Mets' former first baseman who arrived in a 1983 trade with the Cardinals, threw out the first ball yesterday. As a visitor at Friday's workouts, he wore his two World Series rings -- his 1986 Mets ring on his right ring finger, his 1982 Cardinals ring on his left ring finger.</p>
        <p>Long before cable television turned the Atlanta Braves and the Chicago Cubs into teams with national followings, the Cardinals were as much America's team as the Yankees or the Brooklyn / Los Angeles Dodgers.</p>
        <p>More than half a century ago, when St. Louis was the westernmost city in the major leagues, the Cardinals' radio station, KMOX, reached listeners all over the Deep South, the Southwest and the Rocky Mountains. That network built a fan following that still exists. People drive hours to attend games at Busch Stadium.  When an Illinois woman once mentioned her three-hour drive to St. Louis, a young man smiled and said, ''How about 14 from Denver?''</p>
        <p>The Cardinals are considered to be ''the Yankees of the National League,'' the N.L. franchise with the most pennants, 15, and the most World Series championships, 9. The Cardinals are the only N.L. team to hold an edge on the Yankees in the World Series.</p>
        <p>Of their five Series against the Yankees, the Cardinals won three, in 1926, 1942 and 1964.</p>
        <p>But in what is known now as the postseason, that Cardinal tradition is on a losing streak.</p>
        <p>Since their last World Series victory in 1982 over the Milwaukee Brewers, who were then in the American League, the Cardinals have lost their two World Series (to the Kansas City Royals in 1985 and to the Minnesota Twins in 1987).</p>
        <p>They also lost the 1996 N.L.C.S. to the Atlanta Braves after having held a 3-1 lead.</p>
        <p>All those Cardinal fans in Middle America don't want that losing streak to continue.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
