<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Retail Space Grows and Spending Wanes, Some Stores Feel Pinch</title>
    <meta content="15RETA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/nyregion/15RETA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239123"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Warner Brothers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bagli, Charles V</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EFDA103FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Retail Space Grows and Spending Wanes, Some Stores Feel Pinch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES V. BAGLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bagli, Charles V</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ecomomists and retail analysts discuss how as retail space grows and consumer spending wanes, many stores will begin to feel financial pinch; recent closure of Warner Brothers store on Fifth Avenue in midtown Manhattan discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Warner Brothers seemed to have a hit on its hands in 1993, when an astounding 20,000 people a day began streaming through its newly opened studio store at the northeast corner of Fifth Avenue and 57th Street, plucking Bugs Bunny T-shirts, Batman dolls and action figures from the shelves.</p>
        <p>Business was so brisk that Warner Brothers took over 6 floors, for a total of 11, at the Fifth Avenue store three years later, as retailers, restaurants and movie theaters scrambled to open amid a seemingly ever-expanding shopping boom in New York City.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Warner Brothers seemed to have a hit on its hands in 1993, when an astounding 20,000 people a day began streaming through its newly opened studio store at the northeast corner of Fifth Avenue and 57th Street, plucking Bugs Bunny T-shirts, Batman dolls and action figures from the shelves.</p>
        <p>Business was so brisk that Warner Brothers took over 6 floors, for a total of 11, at the Fifth Avenue store three years later, as retailers, restaurants and movie theaters scrambled to open amid a seemingly ever-expanding shopping boom in New York City.</p>
        <p>But Thursday afternoon, Warner Brothers executives told employees that the giant Fifth Avenue flagship would shut its doors for good in January. The store is not only a casualty of declining sales at Warner studio stores in New York and nationwide, economists and retail analysts say, but also a yellow light warning of a softening in what is acknowledged as the strongest retail environment in decades.</p>
        <p>Consumer spending is still solid, said Mark M. Zandi, the chief economist for Economy.com, a consulting firm whose clients include the federal government and major banks, but it is not growing as rapidly this year as it did in the late 1990's.</p>
        <p>Despite this slowdown, work has begun on four of five projects that call for a total of  one million square feet of new retail space  in Manhattan within the next three years. The four are the Time Warner Center at Columbus Circle; a mixed-use tower on the site of the old Alexander's flagship department store on the Upper East Side; and two on 125th Street, Harlem USA and Harlem Center. The fifth, still in the planning stages, calls for 200,000 square feet of retail space in the blocklong Farley Post Office Building just west of Pennsylvania Station.</p>
        <p>''The tremendous boomlike growth in retail space was not a problem when you had boomlike growth in consumer spending,'' Mr. Zandi said. ''But there's been a definitive slowdown in consumer spending. And by next year we may see more problems for retailers and higher vacancy rates.''</p>
        <p>These trends will become more apparent, Mr. Zandi added, when economic indicators like year-over-year retail construction, retail sales and consumer spending figures are released early in 2001.</p>
        <p>But signs of trouble are already visible in New York. Stern's has announced it will close its eight-story department store in Herald Square next spring, and the Official All Star Cafe just shut its doors in Times Square. Sales are down for the once seemingly invincible Gap Inc., which has five dozen Gap, Old Navy and Banana Republic stores in Manhattan alone, and the chain does not plan to renew leases for at least four small stores on the East Side, said Robert K. Futterman, a major retail broker who worked with Gap.</p>
        <p>Home Depot, which has plans to open a superstore in East Harlem, saw its stock plunge last week after analysts expressed fears that shoppers might be cutting back on home improvement projects.</p>
        <p>The big HMV record store at Broadway and 72nd Street closed recently, admitting defeat in a battle with Tower Records several blocks away at Lincoln Square, much the same way Tower closed its store on East 86th Street a couple of years ago, ceding the territory to HMV. Taking over the HMV space on the Upper West Side is Urban Outfitters.</p>
        <p>Despite the thousands of visitors  and office workers who throng a revitalized Times Square every day, real estate brokers say that many owners of the new stores along 42nd Street complain that sales are not as strong as they had hoped. The brokers also say that the major theater chains that opened large multiplexes in many large apartment areas in Manhattan are now trying to pull out of similar projects in Brooklyn and Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''It's not only New York,'' said Kurt Barnard, publisher of Barnard's Retail Trend Report, a trade journal. ''America is overstored.  Competition is rampant. Too many stores look alike.''</p>
        <p>Many brokers dispute that a slowdown exists, however. Shoppers are still clogging the streets, they say, and retailers are still jostling for  space. They contend that the store closings are nothing more than the results of the usual battles that separate winners from losers in retailing.</p>
        <p>''A lot of the boom businesses of the 90's, like the Gap, have lost their luster,'' said C. Bradley Mendelson, a retail broker at Insignia/ESG who put together many deals in Times Square in the last few years. ''And they are starting to be replaced by better or new concepts like Hennes &amp; Mauritz, which features hip European fashions at low prices.''</p>
        <p>It is hard to find vacant retail space in Manhattan and rents are at an all-time high, brokers say. Ground-floor space can cost as much as $300 a square foot in Times Square and up to $500 on the premier shopping blocks like those along Fifth and Madison Avenues north of 55th Street.</p>
        <p>Alan Victor, the executive vice president of Lansco Corporation, a broker that has represented J. Crew, Warner Brothers and other national retailers, said the Gap still planned to open new stores, despite a decline in sales at existing stores. High-end chains including Hugo Boss, Escada, Burberry and Hermes have also leased large new spaces or expanded existing stores on Fifth and Madison Avenues.</p>
        <p>While brokers acknowledge that these high-rent stores cannot generate a profitable sales volume, they make sense from a marketing standpoint because they provide the prestige of an address in some of the most recognizable shopping areas in the world.</p>
        <p>''Retailing is better than ever,'' Mr. Futterman said. ''I've never seen more tenants ready to expand and pay top dollar.''</p>
        <p>That attitude is part of the problem, said Emme P. Kozloff, a retail analyst with Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, a money management company. Many retailers are still acting as if consumer spending is growing at a rapid rate. The Gap chain, for instance, cannibalized its own market in New York and other places, Ms. Kozloff said, by opening stores within blocks of one another  while facing stiff competition from discount stores also selling khakis, blue jeans and T-shirts.</p>
        <p>Often the same retail chain is opening stores at several of the city's currently desirable shopping areas: the newly renovated 510,000 square feet of retail space at Rockefeller Center, the recently refurbished 300,000 square feet at the World Trade Center, and the newly expanded 170,000 square feet at Grand Central Terminal, as well as in SoHo and along Columbus Avenue. Again and again, Banana Republic, Sephora, J. Crew, Warner and Disney Stores have shown up at two or more of these hot spots.</p>
        <p>''Whether it's New York City or the United States, overexpansion is one of the biggest fears among investors in the retail sector,'' Ms. Kozloff said. ''The retail pie only grows but so fast. Somebody's going to get burned.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Kozloff and Mr. Zandi said they expected consumer spending to continue to slacken because of rising interest rates, higher home heating prices, an uncertain stock market and an increase in online shopping.</p>
        <p>Some of the city's many new retail projects will undoubtedly succeed, analysts and economists say, but economists say there are not enough shoppers to justify all the retail space coming on the market, just as there were not enough moviegoers to justify the number of screens put up  in the late 1990's.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, the major theater chains put up huge megaplexes with stadium seating in Manhattan, Queens, Brooklyn and elsewhere. Loews and AMC opened a total of 38 screens at two theaters on opposite sides of 42nd Street, near Eighth Avenue. Neither has lived up to expectations. Regal built a multiplex in Battery Park City that the company admits is doing poorly.</p>
        <p>First, filmgoers abandoned existing theaters, and then attendance fell off altogether when the movie studios failed to produce any blockbusters. Now the theater chains are suffering financially.</p>
        <p>Disney and Warner Brothers, as well as Viacom and Coca-Cola, began opening stores in the early 1990's to generate new revenue and increase  awareness of their brand names. Warner Brothers opened the first of three stores in New York in 1993. Its chief rival, Disney, opened the first of six New York stores in newly resurgent Times Square in 1996. A month later, Warner signed a deal for a new store across Seventh Avenue, and doubled the size of the Fifth Avenue store.</p>
        <p>But it was not long before those companies and others exhausted much of the public's appetite for theme merchandise. Two years ago, Viacom closed 15 Nickelodeon stores nationally. More recently, Coca-Cola closed its store on Fifth Avenue. Disney has announced that it expects to shed 140 of its 740 studio stores, and several brokers say the company is trying to sell the lease on its store on 34th Street between Fifth Avenue and the Avenue of the Americas.</p>
        <p>In recent years, both Warner and Disney suffered from competition with discount stores that sold studio-licensed T-shirts emblazoned with the same cartoon characters for far less money than the studio stores. Brokers and executives familiar with Warner Brothers' sales figures also said that the Times Square studio store undercut its sister store on Fifth Avenue. ''They're dying over there,'' said one executive, referring to the Fifth Avenue location.</p>
        <p>Warner Brothers executives declined to discuss sales. They would say only that the company would continue to operate its stores in Times Square and the World Trade Center, and that it expected to be part of a large store showcasing Time Warner's entire line of products when the company's headquarters opens at Columbus Circle in three years.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kozloff, for one, was doubtful. ''Character merchandise has saturated the market,'' she said. ''How many Mickey Mouse or Tazmanian Devil T-shirts can you sell? Not as many as they'd hoped.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
