<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends; A Shot Seen 'Round the World</title>
    <meta content="15SCHW$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/weekinreview/15SCHW.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001022T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239036"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cincinnati Reds</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisk, Carlton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwarz, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cincinnati Reds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E3DA123FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="934" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends; A Shot Seen 'Round the World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN SCHWARZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schwarz, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cameraman who captured Carlton Fisk's home run in bottom of 12th inning in Game Six of 1975 World Series between Boston Red Sox and Cincinnati Reds kept camera on Fisk largely because he saw a rat coming near camera; never had camera captured an athlete's emotions so immediately; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LOU GERARD didn't smell a rat. Instead, he was staring one straight in the eye. Little did either one know how that rodent would change sports television forever.</p>
        <p>It was 25 years ago next Saturday, Game Six of the 1975 World Series between the Boston Red Sox and the Cincinnati Reds. As Boston's Carlton Fisk led off the bottom of the 12th inning with the score tied 6-6, Gerard, the NBC cameraman stationed inside Fenway Park's famous Green Monster left-field wall, was directed by his producer, Harry Coyle, to follow the ball wherever Fisk might hit it. Gerard responded, ''Harry, there's a rat right here next to me the size of a cat, and it's moving closer.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LOU GERARD didn't smell a rat. Instead, he was staring one straight in the eye. Little did either one know how that rodent would change sports television forever.</p>
        <p>It was 25 years ago next Saturday, Game Six of the 1975 World Series between the Boston Red Sox and the Cincinnati Reds. As Boston's Carlton Fisk led off the bottom of the 12th inning with the score tied 6-6, Gerard, the NBC cameraman stationed inside Fenway Park's famous Green Monster left-field wall, was directed by his producer, Harry Coyle, to follow the ball wherever Fisk might hit it. Gerard responded, ''Harry, there's a rat right here next to me the size of a cat, and it's moving closer.''</p>
        <p>''What are you gonna do?'' Coyle replied.</p>
        <p>''Maybe . . . I ought to just stay on Fisk and see what happens.''</p>
        <p>What happened was one of the most thrilling moments in sports history: Fisk launched a fly ball high into the night that barely caromed off the left field foul pole, sending the Red Sox to riotous victory in what many regard as the best game ever played. But soon 100 million television viewers were treated to a historic instant replay. Because Gerard had kept his lens fixed on the batter, he caught Fisk as he dropped his bat and frantically motioned for the ball to land fair, bouncing on his toes while throwing his hands to his right, as if directing a jumbo jet on a runway. Never before had a camera captured an athlete's emotions so immediately.</p>
        <p>''They didn't even know they had that shot at first,'' said John Filippelli, an associate director that night for NBC and now an executive producer for ABC. ''It was a wonderful aberration that changed television. No one had ever thought of isolating on an individual.''</p>
        <p>Sports television, for most of its history to that point, had consisted of a few cameras following the ball, whether hit, shot or thrown for a touchdown. Baseball games were originally broadcast with just one camera high behind home plate or down the first-base line. CBS introduced instant replay in the early 1960's, and ABC's ''Wide World of Sports'' soon after ventured into the human drama of sports, but live game broadcasts still did little more than allow the viewer into the stadium.</p>
        <p>Televised so crudely, baseball's most significant moments -- from Bobby Thomson's ''Shot Heard 'Round the World'' in 1951, to Don Larsen's 1956 World Series perfect game, to Roger Maris's 61st home run in 1961 -- became legendary not for what they looked like but for what they felt like. Whether fans watched such feats on television, listened on the radio or simply heard stories passed on through the years, their memories were more visceral than visual.</p>
        <p>Fisk's mad dance showed what TV had been missing. After the game, Gerard stopped by the production truck, where a colleague giddily congratulated him: ''Nobody's ever had anything like that! You're going to see what happens after this.''</p>
        <p>Capturing emotion became television's new toy. Cameras sprouted like dandelions around stadiums, and faster instant-replay technology allowed viewers far more intimate portraits of athletes and games. Magic Johnson became as known for his smile as his skills. When Kirk Gibson hit his game-winning home run in the 1988 World Series despite having two injured legs, fans instantly saw close-up replays not only of Gibson jubilantly limping around the bases but of the stupefied pitcher, Dennis Eckersley.</p>
        <p>Every innovation, of course, has its downside. NBC's recent coverage of the Sydney Olympics surfeited viewers with so many features about athletes' emotional state that one had to wonder if the true competition was not for the fastest time or best performance but for the most gut-wrenching personal drama. First in professional sports and then in college, the focus on individuals begat graceless end-zone dances and preening for the cameras after monster dunks; for the modern athlete, anonymity is anathema.</p>
        <p>''To me, television is at its best when it's simply eavesdropping on events that would have been essentially the same had there been no television,'' said Bob Costas, NBC's Olympic host and primary baseball voice. ''These days, every athlete who crosses the finish line in the Olympics, when they celebrate it's genuine but they are all aware they are players in a movie. They are putting on a performance for the cameras.''</p>
        <p>As legendary as Fisk's home run has become, it has, paradoxically, led to the demise of the true sports legend. As fans are spoon-fed every angle, their imagination withers. The controversy surrounding Jack Dempsey's ''Long Count'' boxing victory over Gene Tunney in 1927 would have been settled in a matter of seconds by instant replay. Even Wilt Chamberlain's record 100-point game in 1962 has no visual record; one can only fathom how dominating he must have been. Satchel Paige's mastery is a mystery. Today there are no secrets, nothing left unseen or unexplained.</p>
        <p>FANS only thirst for greater access, and the Internet is delivering it. During the recent United States Tennis Open, the event's official Web site allowed people to choose between three matches rather than the single broadcast shown on CBS, and even use their computers to zoom the cameras in on the action.</p>
        <p>Future Webcasts of sporting events will allow viewers to choose from dozens of camera angles and unlimited replays. Video libraries will allow people to relive historic sports moments at will. Many fans will choose Fisk's home run. As they click the mouse, they should thank the rat.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 22, 2000, Sunday  An article last Sunday about the impact of television coverage on sporting events misidentified the winner of the 1927 ''Long Count'' boxing bout. It was Gene Tunney, not Jack Dempsey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 22, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about the impact of television coverage on sporting events misidentified the winner of the 1927 ''Long Count'' boxing bout. It was Gene Tunney, not Jack Dempsey.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
