<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Premier Of Singapore Sees Pitfalls In Debt Relief</title>
    <meta content="15SING$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/world/15SING.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239125"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harvard University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee Kuan Yew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EEDA103FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Premier Of Singapore Sees Pitfalls In Debt Relief</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Oct. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former Singapore Prime Min Lee Kuan Yew is warning leaders of developing nations against viewing debt relief as panacea for faltering economies and urging them to avoid development theories that are more ideological than practical; warns writing off debt may make nations look perennially uncreditworthy and unattractive to investors; is set to open series of lectures by world leaders at Harvard (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lee Kuan Yew, who turned a pestilential port called Singapore into a country with living standards to rival those of Europe, is warning leaders of developing nations against viewing debt relief as a panacea for faltering economies and also urging them to avoid the trap of development theories that are more ideological than practical.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lee, who now bears the title of senior minister for his country and next week opens a series of lectures by world leaders at Harvard, said that writing off or reducing the debt of developing nations -- a policy now supported by rich nations like the United States, Japan and many in Europe -- may only make nations look perennially uncreditworthy and unattractive to investors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lee Kuan Yew, who turned a pestilential port called Singapore into a country with living standards to rival those of Europe, is warning leaders of developing nations against viewing debt relief as a panacea for faltering economies and also urging them to avoid the trap of development theories that are more ideological than practical.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lee, who now bears the title of senior minister for his country and next week opens a series of lectures by world leaders at Harvard, said that writing off or reducing the debt of developing nations -- a policy now supported by rich nations like the United States, Japan and many in Europe -- may only make nations look perennially uncreditworthy and unattractive to investors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lee, who was Singapore's prime minister from independence in 1965 until his retirement in 1990, has been criticized, particularly in the United States, for his tight control of politics and the social engineering he employed, complete with myriad rules about public behavior, as he developed his small city-state.</p>
        <p>Economically, however, development experts acknowledge that his tropical island without resources has become a high-technology and banking center with one of the world's best airlines, high health and education standards, and decent housing for all. Singapore, with a highly educated work force, is also considered one of the least corrupt countries in the world, in part because of the strength of its civil service.</p>
        <p>Too many third-world leaders, Mr. Lee said, had bought into fashionable theories of development that were more political than pragmatic. It happened, he said, in the first round of the post-colonial age, and it seems to be happening again.</p>
        <p>''Third-world leaders become prisoners of contemporary ideas of the time,'' he said in the interview Wednesday, sitting beside his wife, Kwa Geok Choo, whom he met and married while they were students at Cambridge University in England in the 1950's. They are both lawyers.</p>
        <p>''The first generation were greatly influenced by Nehru, Nasser, Tito, Sukarno -- and at that time they believed that the way to industrialize, the way to catch up with the West was to concentrate on heavy industry, state enterprises -- shortcut the whole process,'' Mr. Lee said. ''This was the result of the myth that the Soviet Union did it that way.''</p>
        <p>''It also fitted in with their natural desire to be in charge,'' he said. ''If you leave it to the market, you're not in charge. If you're in charge, it means that you get the benefits of a percentage and your friends are favored and so on. And so they just drifted into this course of action, which has been most unproductive. ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lee's message is reflected in a new book, ''From Third World to First: The Singapore Story, 1965-2000,'' (HarperCollins). The statesman, now 76, recounts how he saw trouble coming among new nations in the 1950's and 1960's as patterns of dependency on richer nations and corruption and ostentation took hold in post-colonial administrations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lee said he read and heard out all the arguments made by writers like the Argentine economist Raul Prebisch, who recommended state planning and import substitution to shield countries against market forces, as well as other development economists at the London School of Economics. ''I said, this is rubbish!'' said Mr. Lee, a free marketeer who preached competition and cooperation with economic giants. ''But they believed it because it was also emotionally satisfying.''</p>
        <p>''Now, they are in a different stage,'' he said. ''Their economies are really malfunctioning, they've missed opportunities of growth, their infrastructure is inadequate, education has not been as thorough as it could have been, literacy -- poor, technical skills -- poor.''</p>
        <p>This puts many nations at a disadvantage in the face of a digital revolution and a global economy, he added. The fear of being exploited by the economically powerful is thus real, he said. ''But if you are left out, the world will just pass you by, and the catch-up would be even more difficult.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
