<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Baby Steps</title>
    <meta content="15FEAT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Felicia R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E5DB123FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Baby Steps</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICIA R. LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Felicia R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Maria, recovering crack addict living with her infant daughter in therapeutic community town house on Manhattan's Upper West Side; Maria has just started $8-an-hour clerical job, opened savings account and entered last phases of her therapy; she hopes to eventually have her own apartment and regain custody of her other three children; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE night before starting her new job, Maria nervously spread potential outfits for the big day across her narrow single bed. Choosing between pants and dresses and between a sassy lavender and a sedate beige, she sought a look that reflected the hope she invested in every detail of starting over.</p>
        <p>Maria is a recovering crack addict. She lives with her infant daughter in a ''therapeutic community'' town house on the Upper West Side for addicted mothers and their babies. Just minutes away are the park benches where she once slept, the addicts and dealers she once knew, and the corners where she once bought crack, sometimes with her body. Every day, as she takes three subway lines to work, cares for her daughter and negotiates therapy groups and training programs, the crack world hovers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE night before starting her new job, Maria nervously spread potential outfits for the big day across her narrow single bed. Choosing between pants and dresses and between a sassy lavender and a sedate beige, she sought a look that reflected the hope she invested in every detail of starting over.</p>
        <p>Maria is a recovering crack addict. She lives with her infant daughter in a ''therapeutic community'' town house on the Upper West Side for addicted mothers and their babies. Just minutes away are the park benches where she once slept, the addicts and dealers she once knew, and the corners where she once bought crack, sometimes with her body. Every day, as she takes three subway lines to work, cares for her daughter and negotiates therapy groups and training programs, the crack world hovers.</p>
        <p>But this fall, when so much in the city feels new and full of promise, Maria, 38, is poised to begin a new life. She began an $8-an-hour clerical job, opened a savings account and entered the last phases of her therapy. By December or January she hopes to complete the drug program, which is part of a court-ordered judgment after her arrest on drug charges last year.</p>
        <p>She hopes that one day soon she will have her own apartment and perhaps even leave the city. Most important, she hopes to regain custody of her other three children. They are all under 11 and have lived with Maria's mother and sister for most of their lives because Maria was beholden to crack.</p>
        <p>''I have struggled a lot,'' Maria said one recent night, sitting in the empty nursery of the town house. Her baby was tucked in for the night in the room they share with another recovering addict and her toddler son. The room, brightened by photographs and Halloween decorations, resembles a college dormitory except for the cribs.</p>
        <p>''I did a lot of dirt,'' she said, ''but I felt I had to survive to be in the streets, chasing this drug. Sometimes I get sad now. The thought of all the waste of my life. I look at the clear picture, at all those years I wasted doing nothing.''</p>
        <p>Crack ravaged scores of poor neighborhoods in the city in the 1980's. Even as the epidemic has subsided and receives far less attention, women like Maria are testament to its long reach and tenacious hold. And for Maria, not using crack is just one of many steps in reclaiming her life. Her struggle is constant. It is as small as trying to open a bank account and as large as trying to get a job, especially with a prison record. It is as small as relearning how to dress and wear makeup and as large as regaining the trust of the embittered mother and sister who raised her children.</p>
        <p>Each day brings drama, because so much is at stake. One sultry summer day Maria received the job offer. A few days later she was in a hospital's emergency room because of a bad reaction to a test for tuberculosis exposure. Some days her older son is glad to see her in spite of her years of absence and neglect. Other days he barely speaks to her.</p>
        <p>Maria's life is both full and regimented as she catches up. She has to sign in and out of the town house, do household chores and apply for a pass to stay overnight with her mother. As she completes more therapy, she wins more privileges. Maria will leave the program when the court is satisfied that she is drug free, responsible and self-supporting.</p>
        <p>''You can do to yourself with crack in one year what it can take alcohol 20 years to do,'' said Diane M. Churchill, a Manhattan psychotherapist who specializes in substance abuse treatment. ''It'll take a long time to realize all the ramifications of the epidemic: the crack-addicted kids, the kids with crack-addicted parents, the boarder babies, the H.I.V. transmission. It caused people to grow up without really being reared.''</p>
        <p>Even among substance abusers, a crack addict, especially a woman, is at the bottom of the social hierarchy and is particularly stigmatized. For that reason, Maria has not shared her history with anyone at work and goes by her first name only in this article.</p>
        <p>Nothing in Maria's appearance these days would give her story away. Fluent in English and Spanish, she is poised and precise in her speech, although she sometimes lapses into the bubbly shibboleths of self-help programs, perhaps because she is reinventing herself and taking it, as she says,  ''minute by minute.''</p>
        <p>Every day, she talks about what she has missed, especially in her children's lives. In addition to the three children who live with her mother, she has a son who was adopted at birth.</p>
        <p>''I cry a lot, just at the thought that my younger sister played a big part in their lives, in the absence of me,'' she said of the sister who helped raise Maria's children. ''In school, the parent-teacher meetings. Sometimes when I have to attend a meeting, they look at me like, 'Who are you?' That's hurtful.''</p>
        <p>Although she sometimes gives in to the blues, keeping busy helps. In addition to a 40-hour work week, Maria's time is consumed by job training, parent training, individual therapy, a trauma therapy group. She has a vocational counselor and a work-readiness group. Before falling off to sleep at night, she studies for her G.E.D., the high-school equivalency diploma.</p>
        <p>''I need to keep busy,'' she said. ''Boredom is my enemy.''</p>
        <p>Last weekend, on a clear, chilly Saturday, Maria went to a Dime Savings Bank on the Upper West Side and opened a savings account, the first bank account she has ever had.</p>
        <p>''They said I could have an A.T.M. card, but I don't know,'' she said, leaving the bank with a smile of accomplishment.''You can just go and get the money anytime. I need to save.''</p>
        <p>Maria works hard getting the small things right. She can tell you, for instance, exactly how she budgets the $39.50 a week she gets in public assistance (the rest goes directly to her drug program), down to car fare, lunch, cigarettes. She has timed her morning routine with the baby to the minute, including the baby's braids, her own makeup, a cigarette, a prayer. She keeps a worn copy of the Bible in her room.</p>
        <p>It is up by 6 and not home again until at least 12 hours later. If she is five minutes late for work, she stays at least five minutes later.</p>
        <p>''They treat me like a regular human being,'' Maria said of her colleagues. ''They're not looking at me or judging me. It's just the opportunity to do something for myself and earn my own money.</p>
        <p>''I've come this far and it's almost over,'' she said. ''Sometimes, I get a little low confidence in myself at work, so I triple-check to make sure I don't make any errors.''</p>
        <p>''The struggle isn't as hard anymore for me, but it hurts to think of relapsing,'' said Maria, who has two older brothers and two younger sisters. ''I want my sisters to look up to me again. I don't give up the faith that one day they will look up to me as their big sister.''</p>
        <p>She continued: ''And my mom has been through so much. In prison, visiting through snow, sleet, heat. My kids are a handful, and my mother has raised them all this time.</p>
        <p>''It's a do-or-die situation,'' she said. ''I'm almost 39 years old, with five kids with five different men. I can't take it one day at a time. I take it one minute at a time.''</p>
        <p>MARIA'S drug ordeal began with smoking marijuana as a 15-year-old high school student on the Upper West Side. Then, she thought she smoked to fit in with her friends. Now she says it reflected a deep feeling of worthlessness.</p>
        <p>Maria and her siblings grew up in a one-bedroom walk-up. Her parents separated decades ago. Maria grew up mostly without her father, an alcoholic and heroin addict whom she has not seen in years. Her mother relied on welfare, cleaned offices and did whatever was needed to support the family. Maria remembers her suffering physical abuse at the hands of Maria's father and other men.</p>
        <p>Maria was never especially good in school, she recalled. She went as far as 10th grade and began shoplifting. She hung out with older men who introduced her to powdered cocaine. Her mother beat her and threw her out in an effort to stop her drug use. Nothing worked.</p>
        <p>At 17, she was married for two weeks to a man from Colombia who, she now believes, married her to stay in the country. They went to City Hall and had a ''short little wedding cake'' to celebrate. Then he disappeared. Maria said she went ''a little crazy'' after he left.</p>
        <p>After selling cocaine for a drug-dealer boyfriend, Maria decided to try a purer, rock-hard form of cocaine.</p>
        <p>Soon, she was addicted to crack. She was 22, smoking as much as an ''eight ball,'' or three grams, every day. What she did not get from her boyfriend she got by working as a prostitute.</p>
        <p>''I never planned anything,'' Maria said the other day, sitting in Riverside Park. ''I never had the thought of really struggling hard to become something. Everything went to crack.</p>
        <p>''I know these streets like the back of my hand,'' she said. ''I've slept on plenty of these benches. I was a walking zombie. The longest period I stayed high, straight and nonstop, was 14 days without sleeping or eating.''</p>
        <p>At 28, she became pregnant with her first son by another crack addict. She was six months pregnant when she went to Rikers Island for possessing cocaine and attempting to sell it.</p>
        <p>The boy was born without drugs in his system. He went straight to Maria's mother, and Maria went back to crack, smoking it up to the time her second son was born in 1992. He had cocaine in his system and had to withdraw from the drug in his hospital crib before also being turned over to his grandmother.</p>
        <p>Arrested again just months later and unable to make the $1,500 bail, Maria went through a militarylike drug-treatment program in Buffalo. For nearly four years she was drug free. She worked as a receptionist and bookkeeper and lived with a companion, with whom she had a daughter.</p>
        <p>But then, after the relationship faltered, Maria became depressed and fell back into the crack world. In the summer of 1997, she had her fourth child and he was born addicted to the drug. She said she was told by city officials that she had 10 days to find a relative to take him or she would lose him to foster care.</p>
        <p>That son was eventually adopted by a relative.</p>
        <p>''I thought that was a rock bottom, right there,'' Maria said. ''But they've been very happy with that kid. I've never had that inner regret feeling for having done that. I just don't want him to hate me.''</p>
        <p>Then it was back to crack. And another pregnancy. And back to Rikers. Finally, Maria came to the therapeutic community in a move arranged by her Legal Aid lawyer and her mother.</p>
        <p>Maria has no single answer for why she used drugs. Part of it was the sadness of not really having had a father and the fear and anger of watching her mother struggle for money and be abused by men.</p>
        <p>Part of it was the feeling that she was not smart enough to finish high school, not special or talented. Clothes made her happy, but she never had the opportunity to analyze her feelings until she started therapy.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to be something other than what I was. My mom struggled a lot to give us what we had, but it wasn't enough. And I'd see girls with their dads pick them up at school and give them allowances. Daddy never took us nowhere.''</p>
        <p>''Clothes were so important,'' she continued. ''A nice silk shirt. I felt like it was gold, like something that made me shine. I used to change three times a day. But I still used to give up on myself.''</p>
        <p>With crack, there were no bad feelings. Except for the times she wondered about her children. Maria would then walk to the family church where she received her First Communion. She prayed for salvation. Then she hoped she would not run into her mother as she searched the streets for more crack.</p>
        <p>THE other day, Maria and the children attended a program that aimed to strengthen the relationship between recovering addicts and their families. Everyone used Play-Doh to create a sculpture representing how they would like the family to be together.</p>
        <p>Maria and her children made stick figures, which sat in a Play-Doh living room. Maria cooed over the figures and seemed almost radiant. Her older son complained that he wanted to leave and play basketball.</p>
        <p>The day was busy with shuttling the children back and forth between her mother's apartment and various appointments and outings.</p>
        <p>After the parent-child group, Maria dropped her sons at a basketball game in a neighborhood center. She picked up her younger daughter back at the town house where they live, and then took both daughters to her mother's place.</p>
        <p>She fetched the boys at basketball, only to be greeted mostly with silence at her efforts to make conversation. Maria then took one child to his psychotherapist, sitting almost an hour in the overcrowded waiting room until his appointment. Maria and the other boy then went around the corner to have a slice of pizza. His mood brightened as he debated the merits of Coke versus Pepsi.</p>
        <p>That evening she planned to take the children to a movie and then go to her Narcotics Anonymous meeting in a nearby church.</p>
        <p>The touchstone is always family, Maria said. Even in the throes of addiction she made it to her mother's apartment every New Year's Eve to celebrate.</p>
        <p>The mother's three-room apartment, where Maria grew up, has four beds in the bedroom and a sleep sofa in the living room. Her mother, sister and the three children live there. The floors are covered with worn linoleum, the rooms separated by curtains. The living room is full of religious icons and a hulking television set.</p>
        <p>Her mother, who is now 61, watched both Maria and one of Maria's brothers become crack addicts. Two of her other children are firmly entrenched in the middle class; a 44-year-old son is a certified public accountant, married and a father, while a 35-year-old daughter is married, a mother and an administrative assistant.</p>
        <p>The youngest child, Maria's 31-year-old sister, works in a bank and lives at home to help her mother raise Maria's children.</p>
        <p>''You put yourself on hold,'' that sister said one day while Maria visited.</p>
        <p>The sister remembered comforting their mother as she visited Maria and her brother in prison or passed them on the corner, knowing they were high. She said she was angry that she could never look up to either sibling.</p>
        <p>She and her mother cried when they talked about Maria. They love her, they said, but for all her talk about setting goals and being strong, they were the ones who nursed the children through colds and attended school meetings. They saw Maria relapse, and they know her as a woman who did not listen.</p>
        <p>''I would love for one day for her to have her kids back,'' Maria's sister said. ''And I hope she never goes back to drugs. But whatever happens, she'll always be my sister. When Maria was in the streets, I told people, 'That's my sister.' ''</p>
        <p>Maria's eyes filled with tears.</p>
        <p>The sister then translated her mother's Spanish.</p>
        <p>''For Maria to prove to me she can have a life, she has to do it for a while, beyond five years,'' the mother said. ''She quit using drugs before.''</p>
        <p>Maria's sons have been terribly wounded by their ordeal, their grandmother said. The little girl's father visits and sends money, but neither boy has a father in his life.</p>
        <p>''I'm very upset,'' Maria's mother said. ''I don't understand why it happened. I never taught them that. I never gave them a reason to go into the drug life, to leave their kids.''</p>
        <p>Tears ran down her face.</p>
        <p>''I had a lump in my throat,'' Maria said when she walked a visitor outside the apartment. ''It hurts me, to hear them talk that way. I understand. I have to prove myself.''</p>
        <p>Later that day, on the bus with her sons, the younger one asked Maria about the meaning of the word ''desire,'' which he had seen in a movie poster.</p>
        <p>''It means when you really want something,'' Maria said in her calm, precise way. ''It is a very strong feeling inside to make something happen.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
