<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Asks Black Ministers to Help Bring Voters to the Polls</title>
    <meta content="15DEMS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/politics/15DEMS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239145"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ELECTORATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5DF113FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="598" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Asks Black Ministers to Help Bring Voters to the Polls</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore urges get-out-the vote effort on his behalf, telephone conference call with black ministers; also seeks to spur loyalists in second conference call with Hispanic officials and volunteers in his campaign offices around nation (M)o</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the presidential election in a dead heat, Vice President Al Gore sought to mobilize his campaign's ''get out the vote'' drive today by imploring black preachers to push for his election from their pulpits.</p>
        <p>''I'm asking you in your sermons to do the work of the Lord here on earth,'' Mr. Gore declared in seeking vocal advocates for his candidacy. ''I ask for your help in getting that message out urgently tomorrow.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the presidential election in a dead heat, Vice President Al Gore sought to mobilize his campaign's ''get out the vote'' drive today by imploring black preachers to push for his election from their pulpits.</p>
        <p>''I'm asking you in your sermons to do the work of the Lord here on earth,'' Mr. Gore declared in seeking vocal advocates for his candidacy. ''I ask for your help in getting that message out urgently tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>The vice president spoke to the black ministers in a telephone conference call from Air Force Two as he flew from Detroit to Washington. He also participated in a second conference call with Hispanic officials and volunteers in Gore campaign offices around the country, including Texas, Florida, California and New York.</p>
        <p>Analysts have predicted an especially low turnout in the Nov. 7 elections, and the Gore campaign has already begun to ''activate the base,'' political jargon for firing up its most loyal backers to make sure they vote and get others to the polls.</p>
        <p>As Election Day nears, Democrats typically appear in black churches, while conservative causes are promoted in fundamentalist and Roman Catholic churches. But church officials have to be careful not to cross the line into campaigning for a specific candidate, which could threaten their tax-exempt status.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore spoke first with black ministers, including Dr. Benjamin L. Hooks, former executive director of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Dr. Hooks said that some African-Americans did not know Mr. Gore's record. By way of explaining it, Dr. Hooks, who said he had known the vice president since ''his daddy had him clean out pigsties,'' said, ''His heart is right, his mind is fixed, his spirit is on fire.''</p>
        <p>In a closing prayer, the Rev. Ronald Williams of Portland, Ore., asked God, on behalf of Mr. Gore, to ''strengthen him against those who would attempt to weaken him.'' And he asked God for ''success in voter registration and success in voter turnout and success and victory on Election Day.''</p>
        <p>In his second phone call, which he laced with Spanish phrases, Mr. Gore turned his attention to the ''colonias,'' the poor settlements along the Texas border. Hispanic leaders have criticized Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, Mr. Gore's Republican rival, for never having visited a colonia, and Mr. Gore highlighted that today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore referred to remarks made Friday by Mr. Bush's secretary of state, Elton Bomer, defending the governor. ''You don't have to go to Alaska to know it's cold,'' Mr. Bomer said, ''and I don't think you have to go to colonias to know what it's like.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said today, ''That is a cold comment in itself,'' and said ''it speaks volumes'' about Texas and the Bush administration. He added that when Texas had the largest budget surpluses, ''instead of devoting resources to improving the colonias, he made his priority a tax cut for wealthy interests.''</p>
        <p>As if speaking at a rally, Mr. Gore enumerated his priorities: health care and education, protecting Social Security and Medicare, offering middle-class tax cuts, protecting the environment and enforcing civil-rights laws. ''This is time for leadership,'' he said. ''This is time for passion.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ELECTORATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
