<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Not-Quite Landmark Languishes in Limbo</title>
    <meta content="15LAND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239012"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: FLUSHNG"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">College Point Little League</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Castro, Jerry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Day, Sherri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E6DC123FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="448" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Not-Quite Landmark Languishes in Limbo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERRI DAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Day, Sherri</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>College Point Little League president Jerry Castro says group plans to apply for money to restore historic Angelo Petromelis College Point Senior Center in Queens, built in 1906 as firehouse; senior center officials are looking for new home; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last year, a ceiling in the Angelo Petromelis College Point Senior Center nearly caved in under the weight of pigeon droppings. The birds had nested in the roof, and their droppings were eating through the ceiling.</p>
        <p>The city, which runs the center, repaired the roof. However, Sabina Cardali, president of the College Point Civic and Taxpayers Association, says the building is still unsafe and wants the center to relocate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last year, a ceiling in the Angelo Petromelis College Point Senior Center nearly caved in under the weight of pigeon droppings. The birds had nested in the roof, and their droppings were eating through the ceiling.</p>
        <p>The city, which runs the center, repaired the roof. However, Sabina Cardali, president of the College Point Civic and Taxpayers Association, says the building is still unsafe and wants the center to relocate.</p>
        <p>''It's falling apart,'' Ms. Cardali said. ''These quarters are just not suitable for seniors.''</p>
        <p>The College Point Little League owns the building, a three-story structure on 123rd Street between 13th and 14th Avenues. It was built in 1906 as a firehouse for the private community of College Point; the center for the elderly has occupied it for the past quarter century.</p>
        <p>In June, the building was listed on the State Register of Historic Places. Last month, it received the federal designation. Although the exterior is undistinguished, the interior features such decorative touches as embossed paneling.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cardali said the designations created a problem because now the building's owner cannot make repairs on the site quickly.</p>
        <p>But the old firehouse is not actually a landmark. In fact, only three percent of the 71,000 properties on the National Register of Historic Places are official landmarks. Most are simply places with historic interest. And being listed on the federal and state rosters does not automatically prevent an owner from making improvements.</p>
        <p>Jerry Castro, president of the College Point Little League, said his group did not apply for landmark designation because of the restrictions it brought with it. He plans to apply for money available to restore buildings listed as historic places, since his group, a volunteer organization, cannot afford to make repairs on its own.</p>
        <p>Although the firehouse needs repairs, Suzanne Metaxas, the center's director, said it was safe. It is, however, too small for the senior program, which is growing. She has been looking for new quarters for more than a year but has not found anything the city is willing to pay for.</p>
        <p>''It's just unfortunate that things have not worked out,'' Ms. Metaxas said.</p>
        <p>SHERRI DAY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: FLUSHNG</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
