<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Embargo Seen as Aid To Castro; Canada, Too</title>
    <meta content="15CANA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/world/15CANA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239119"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cuba-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Canada-International Relations-Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sherritt International Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Axworthy, Lloyd (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Castro, Fidel (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE5DA103FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="708" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Embargo Seen as Aid To Castro; Canada, Too</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <dateline>CHURCHILL, Manitoba, Oct. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Canadian Min Lloyd Axworthy holds United States economic embargo has given nationalist aura to Fidel Castro's regime, while helping Canada become largest foreign investor in Cuba, interview; cites key role played by Canada's Sherritt International Corp, which has nearly $1 billion invested in Cuba (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The long-running United States economic embargo of Cuba has played neatly into the hands of both the Havana government and Canada, which has become the largest foreign investor in Cuba, Canada's foreign minister, Lloyd Axworthy, said in an interview here today.</p>
        <p>''It's the one thing that keeps them in power, keeping up their police state,'' Mr. Axworthy said, explaining that American economic sanctions give a nationalistic aura to Fidel Castro's 41-year-old rule in Cuba. ''If the U.S. announced tomorrow that the embargo was going off, Castro would have to find something else to replace it. Otherwise, the whole place would go like wildfire.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The long-running United States economic embargo of Cuba has played neatly into the hands of both the Havana government and Canada, which has become the largest foreign investor in Cuba, Canada's foreign minister, Lloyd Axworthy, said in an interview here today.</p>
        <p>''It's the one thing that keeps them in power, keeping up their police state,'' Mr. Axworthy said, explaining that American economic sanctions give a nationalistic aura to Fidel Castro's 41-year-old rule in Cuba. ''If the U.S. announced tomorrow that the embargo was going off, Castro would have to find something else to replace it. Otherwise, the whole place would go like wildfire.''</p>
        <p>Sherritt International Corporation, a Toronto company, has nearly $1 billion invested in Cuban oil production, nickel mining, power generation, cell phones, tourism and agriculture. Hundreds of thousands of Canadians travel to Cuba each winter for discount beach vacations.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the House of Representatives overwhelmingly approved an agricultural financing bill today that would slightly ease the embargo on Cuba, allowing food and medicine sales.</p>
        <p>''If the U.S. Congress were to allow American companies to make certain investments, it would make our prime minister very unhappy,'' Mr. Axworthy said. ''The more Congress keeps U.S. companies out, the more it allows Sherritt to control the island.''</p>
        <p>Relations between Canada and Cuba cooled in the late 1990's because of Mr. Castro's continued crackdowns on dissident journalists and human rights activists. But this month, in a clear effort to repair ties, Mr. Castro attended the funeral of former Prime Minister Pierre Trudeau in Montreal.</p>
        <p>This week the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation broadcast extracts from a two-hour interview it had with Mr. Castro.</p>
        <p>In the interview, Mr. Castro said  no prisoner had been tortured since he took power in 1959 and indirectly confirmed that his jails hold about 300 political prisoners, telling the Canadian interviewer, ''Listen, if we jailed all of those who receive a salary from the United States to fight against the revolution, there would be a lot more than those 300.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Castro, who has nearly outlasted nine American presidents, has shown no indication that he will get along with the 10th. In August, he remarked that George W. Bush and Al Gore were ''the most boring and insipid'' candidates in American history. On Canadian television, he said: ''I'm against both of them, I'd like another candidate. But there are only these two and my position is this: I don't like either of them.''</p>
        <p>Recognizing that the seizure of American properties by Cuba's revolutionary government four decades ago is a sore point for some Americans, Mr. Axworthy predicted that Americans would have as much luck getting compensation from Cuba as  British refugees did from the United States after the American Revolution.</p>
        <p>Turning to other issues in the Americas, Mr. Axworthy, who plans to retire by the end of this year to head an international affairs institute in British Columbia, said that the ''power of the street'' dictated recent decisions to abandon power by Presidents Alberto K. Fujimori of Peru and by Slobodan Milosevic of Yugoslavia. Last June, Mr. Axworthy led a mission by the Organization of the American States to Lima to ask Mr. Fujimori to make democratic changes in Peru after his tainted re-election in May.</p>
        <p>''Those guys were scared when I was there,'' Mr. Axworthy said, recalling that 4,000 policemen guarded the streets during his visit with Cesar Gaviria, the Organization of American States' secretary general. Reflecting on Mr. Fujimori's decision in September to cut short his term and hold new elections, Mr. Axworthy said that even back in June, ''the ruling class, the smoothies, knew it was over.''</p>
        <p>Turning to relations with the United States, with whom Canada conducts 86 percent of its foreign trade, Mr. Axworthy said he saw no need for the two nations to adopt a European-style customs union, a proposal that could mean adopting common immigration policies, common external tariffs and free movement of goods and people inside the two-nation zone.</p>
        <p>''We don't need a footprint like the European Union, we don't need a superstructure,'' he said. Instead, he advocated the gradual ''harmonization'' of relations and extension of free-trade pacts into Central and South America.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
