<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mugabe's Foes in Zimbabwe, Stymied, Talk of Violence</title>
    <meta content="Y15ZIM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/world/15ZIMB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239111"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zimbabwe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swarns, Rachel L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mugabe, Robert (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E7DE103FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1576" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mugabe's Foes in Zimbabwe, Stymied, Talk of Violence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL L. SWARNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swarns, Rachel L</byline>
      <dateline>CHITUNGWIZA, Zimbabwe, Oct. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Opposition joy over their sweep in June of over third of parliamentary seats in Zimbabwe has quickly dissolved into discontent as opposition legislators repeatedly find selves outnumbered and ignored; opposition is warning for first time that its supporters may turn to violence if Pres Robert Mugabe's government continues to block their efforts at change; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The opposition legislators now speak the language of ayes and nays, motions and resolutions and their names appear in neat black type on white government doors. But the jubilation over their sweep in June elections of more than a third of parliamentary seats has quickly dissolved into discontent.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, the opposition has watched helplessly as the government has pardoned the perpetrators of political violence, drafted governing party militants into a militia and allocated millions of dollars more to the costly war in Congo while shabby hospitals here run short of syringes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The opposition legislators now speak the language of ayes and nays, motions and resolutions and their names appear in neat black type on white government doors. But the jubilation over their sweep in June elections of more than a third of parliamentary seats has quickly dissolved into discontent.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, the opposition has watched helplessly as the government has pardoned the perpetrators of political violence, drafted governing party militants into a militia and allocated millions of dollars more to the costly war in Congo while shabby hospitals here run short of syringes.</p>
        <p>Over and over the legislators have found themselves outnumbered and ignored. And as frustration rises, the opposition is warning for the first time that its supporters may turn to violence if the government of President Robert Mugabe continues to block their efforts at change.</p>
        <p>Three months after Zimbabwe embarked on its uneasy journey into this new era of multiparty democracy, disillusioned members of the opposition party, the Movement for Democratic Change, have begun calling for mass protests to force Mr. Mugabe to leave power before the presidential election in 2002.</p>
        <p>The new message is already simmering in the urban townships. On Wednesday, as scores of people danced at a rally here with drums pounding and feet stomping, there was little celebration of the power of the ballot box. ''You are going to see violence,'' the opposition supporters sang in a warning to the government. ''We are going to fight you violently this year.''</p>
        <p>''In that Parliament, we are not going to achieve anything,'' said Job Sikhala, an opposition legislator here, as he folded his frame into a faded sofa in his three-room house. ''The people of this country must be prepared to rise against this dictatorship.''</p>
        <p>''We will have casualties,'' he said.  ''We don't dispute this. But we have been frustrated enough. Politics must be taken out of that Parliament building.''</p>
        <p>It is a striking shift in rhetoric and strategy for the opposition, which  loosened Mr. Mugabe's grip on Parliament by offering an alternative to the governing party. After controlling all but three parliamentary seats for more than a decade, the governing party had become increasingly identified with the problems of official arrogance, corruption, violence and economic decline.</p>
        <p>Senior opposition officials emphasize that the party remains committed to nonviolence and to the parliamentary system. And some party members are privately urging their colleagues to abandon the inflammatory language and confrontational approach increasingly favored by some legislators and the party leader, Morgan Tsvangirai.</p>
        <p>But even those officials with misgivings about the new strategy say the party cannot afford to accept its role as a popular but toothless political movement.</p>
        <p>In this community of crumbling cement houses, where sewage spills into dusty streets and rolling blackouts leave families dining by candlelight, the people have begun to grumble. The cities voted overwhelmingly for the opposition, pinning their hopes on promises of economic revival and a return to law and order.</p>
        <p>But the opposition Movement for Democratic Change controls only 57 of 150 parliamentary seats. That is  enough to prevent Mr. Mugabe from changing the Constitution, but  not enough to give the party a majority in Parliament or any real influence on economic policy or on a government that continues to disregard the courts and harass its critics.</p>
        <p>Frustrated supporters of the movement have loudly bemoaned the lack of progress, firing off a  stream of letters like one in this week's Financial Gazette in which John Moyo complained, ''Sadly, Morgan Tsvangirai has gone to sleep and let the fire go out.''</p>
        <p>Responding to the complaints, the party leadership recently agreed to pursue a peaceful mass-action campaign that would most likely include a combination of strikes, marches and work stoppages. On Monday the plan will be presented to the party's national executive committee, who will debate tactics and timing.</p>
        <p>There are few regional models that offer inspiration. The countries at the foot of the continent are often celebrated for their tranquillity and commitment to multiparty democracy. But they are mostly stable states  dominated by one party, with small and ineffective oppositions.</p>
        <p>Lately, radicals in the opposition have been looking to the recent revolt in Yugoslavia as a model, championing the idea of a huge uprising that would flood the streets with protesters, shutter vital industries and ultimately topple the government.</p>
        <p>But others are strongly advocating a postponement or even cancellation of the mass-action campaign, given the violence that erupted this week.</p>
        <p>Around midnight on Monday, the police arrested and jailed Mr. Sikhala and two other opposition legislators on charges of inciting violence. Later that morning the officers converged on the airport vowing to arrest Mr. Tsvangirai on his return from South Africa for warning Mr. Mugabe in a recent speech, ''If you don't want to go peacefully, we will remove you violently.''</p>
        <p>That afternoon, hundreds of members of the Movement for Democratic Change gathered outside the courthouse to protest the arrests, hurling bottles and stones after riot police descended on the peaceful protest with tear gas and swinging batons.</p>
        <p>The authorities ultimately released Mr. Sikhala and the others and backed away from their threats to arrest Mr. Tsvangirai. But for some the incidents confirmed the dangers.</p>
        <p>''We old men are trying to control tempers and emotions,'' Fidelis Mhashu, a retired college professor and newly elected member of Parliament, said of the efforts to calm younger politicians like Mr. Sikhala. ''But even some of us old people are fed up.''</p>
        <p>''Our constituents are already saying we are wasting time in Parliament,'' Mr. Mhashu said. ''I tell them we must wait until the elections in 2002 for real change. They tell me, ''We can't wait that long.' They suggest, 'Let's go to the streets.' ''</p>
        <p>''We may not be able to ignore the high temperature among our people,'' he said quietly. ''But we must be careful. A hungry man is an angry man. And when we go on the march, there is no guarantee that we're going to be able to control our people from going on a rampage.''</p>
        <p>The numbers of the hungry are growing.</p>
        <p>International donors have shunned Mr. Mugabe's government, which misled bankers about the cost of its war in Congo and condoned the pre-election violence that left nearly 30 opposition supporters dead.</p>
        <p>As a result, this country's mismanaged economy is expected to shrink by 5 percent this year. Factories are laying off workers. Unemployment is soaring. And this week, the state-controlled newspaper, The Herald, reported that the prices of sugar and bread had surged by 34 percent this month.</p>
        <p>In the open-air market here, where women sell vegetables and men sell kerosene, Stella Masawi said she drank tea now for lunch because she could not afford to waste her cornmeal, the staple food here.</p>
        <p>Petros Eliya, 28, a kerosene salesman, said bread and sugar had become luxuries, items he could buy only once a month instead of once a week.</p>
        <p>''What Tsvangirai said is right,''  Mr. Eliya said, referring to the opposition leader's remarks about forcing Mr. Mugabe from power. ''Things are too difficult. We cannot wait until the elections of 2002.''</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Masawi disagreed. ''If people march in the streets,'' she said, ''I'm afraid there might be war in this country.''</p>
        <p>David Coltart, a lawyer and opposition legislator, said he thought  most opposition members would support a peaceful, meticulously planned mass-action strategy that would persuade Mr. Mugabe to resign without damaging the economy or provoking violent clashes. But his constituents in the poor black townships of Bulawayo want something radical, like a long general strike.</p>
        <p>''It's all very well to call for a stayaway, but are people prepared to stay away for months on end?'' Mr. Coltart asked of the work stoppages. ''And you've got to understand the nature of this regime. They control the army. They control the police. They've got the guns. Violence is a very viable option for them. Are we ready for that?''</p>
        <p>It was a question that Victor Kunaka asked himself outside the courthouse on Monday when it seemed as if the swirling clouds of tear gas were blinding his eyes and bursting his lungs. And then he thought about Tafadzwa, his 2-year-old son.</p>
        <p>''I thought, 'If I die here, who will take care of my child?' '' remembered Mr. Kunaka, a 26-year-old machine operator.</p>
        <p>''But when I thought of him, that made me want to fight so he can have a better life than his father,'' he said. ''We want to send a message to this government. We cannot bear this kind of life anymore. And then we started looking for stones and bottles to throw at the police.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
