<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Torre Looks to a Met for Strategic Inspiration, and Is Glad He Did</title>
    <meta content="15NOTE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/sports/15NOTE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="2000 PLAYOFFS: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torre, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E7DA113FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Torre Looks to a Met for Strategic Inspiration, and Is Glad He Did</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, Oct. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees manager Joe Torre discusses American League Championship Series against Seattle Mariners (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Todd Zeile of the Mets helped Manager Joe Torre of the Yankees learn a lesson that paid off, in a roundabout way, in Game 3 of the American League Championship Series on Friday night.</p>
        <p>When Zeile played with St. Louis and Torre was his manager, Zeile led off in an extra-inning game and worked the count to three balls and no strikes. Torre gave him the take sign, following conventional wisdom. Zeile took a meaty fastball right down the middle before drawing a walk, but did not score.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Todd Zeile of the Mets helped Manager Joe Torre of the Yankees learn a lesson that paid off, in a roundabout way, in Game 3 of the American League Championship Series on Friday night.</p>
        <p>When Zeile played with St. Louis and Torre was his manager, Zeile led off in an extra-inning game and worked the count to three balls and no strikes. Torre gave him the take sign, following conventional wisdom. Zeile took a meaty fastball right down the middle before drawing a walk, but did not score.</p>
        <p>Later, as Torre reflected upon that move, he thought it was silly. Zeile was one of his biggest home run threats, and why not give him a chance to drive a fastball?</p>
        <p>Torre changed his strategy, deciding to take it case by case. The Yankees' cleanup hitter, Bernie Williams, led off the second inning on Friday, got ahead in the count, three balls and no strikes, against Seattle's Aaron Sele. Through Willie Randolph, the third-base coach, Torre gave Williams the go-ahead to swing.</p>
        <p>Sele fired a thigh-high fastball and Williams clubbed it for his first homer of the postseason, the first of eight runs the Yankees scored.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to give a green light to everybody in that situation,'' Torre said. ''It's got to be someone who can hit a home run.''</p>
        <p>Torre also took into account that Sele consistently pitches within the strike zone, reducing the chances that Williams would swing at a bad pitch, and Williams's experience at swinging on 3-0. According to Torre, Williams has gotten much better at being selective in these situations.</p>
        <p>Another factor probably was Torre's sense that his team's offense was coming together. A couple of the Yankees mentioned that it was incredible that one at-bat in one inning -- David Justice's leadoff double in the eighth inning of Game 2 -- had turned around their entire attack. The Yankees scored seven runs in that inning, taking Justice's cue: being more patient and forcing the pitcher to throw strikes, an approach that has won championships for them the last two years.</p>
        <p>''I felt good about the club going in,'' Torre said. ''I just sensed a less tense ballclub. Maybe it was the day off, I don't know. But they just came out and played the game yesterday.''</p>
        <p>Seattle Manager Lou Piniella said: ''Look, they are not the world champions for nothing. They know how to play. They have been there before, and they have played in so many big games that you have to go out and beat them. They're not going to beat themselves.''</p>
        <p>Neagle to Start Game 5</p>
        <p>Knowing that Seattle cannot clinch this series in Game 5, Joe Torre settled on Denny Neagle as the Yankees' starter for that game. Torre had held off deciding until after the Yankees won Game 3, because if Seattle led, three games to one, he wanted the option of pitching Orlando Hernandez, the team's best postseason pitcher, in Game 5.</p>
        <p>Neagle pitched effectively in Game 1, allowing two runs in five and two-thirds innings. ''I knew there was a possibility that they might want to bring El Duque back on three days' rest if we were down in the series, but I can't worry about that,'' Neagle said. ''All I can think is that I did a good enough job the other night to warrant another start.''</p>
        <p>If the Yankees can wrap up the series here on Sunday, Torre will have a full array of choices when he aligns his pitching rotation for the World Series; he can pitch Hernandez in Game 1, Roger Clemens in Game 2, Andy Pettitte in Game 3 and Neagle in Game 4. By doing that, Torre would ensure that Clemens would not have to pitch in Shea Stadium, where he has fared poorly during his career, and where he would be a target of the Mets' fans, who will probably never let him forget the beaning of catcher Mike Piazza; if Clemens pitches Game 2 in Yankee Stadium, he will be in line to pitch Game 6 in Yankee Stadium, if necessary.</p>
        <p>Neagle played with Atlanta earlier in his career and today he said that he felt the Braves were affected by the pressure that was on them to win the World Series more often.</p>
        <p>''You don't have that feeling whatsoever with this team,'' Neagle said. ''There are a lot of professionals going about their business in the right way. And I always said that is a reflection of your manager and the guys in the clubhouse, and that's why they have been able to overcome the tough five-game series in Oakland, right out of the chute. It's a combination of the personalities we have in the clubhouse.''</p>
        <p>2000 PLAYOFFS: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
