<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INVESTING WITH -- Andrew C. Stephens; Artisan Mid-Cap Fund</title>
    <meta content="15INVO$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/business/15INVO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Artisan Mid-Cap Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stamler, Bernard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Investing With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D6123FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="930" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INVESTING WITH -- Andrew C. Stephens; Artisan Mid-Cap Fund</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD STAMLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stamler, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bernard Stamler Investing With column describes Artisan Mid-Cap Fund, managed by Andrew C Stephens; photo; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HE may not exactly be a farm boy, but he did grow up in the Wisconsin countryside. And he is not a carpenter, either, although he and his wife are restoring the old, lakefront house they bought recently.</p>
        <p>But Andrew C. Stephens, 36, the manager of the three-year-old Artisan Mid-Cap fund, says his investment philosophy is influenced both by his memories of those who till the soil and by his newfound appreciation of what it takes to survive a renovation. With investing, as with an old house, ''You have to have a little bit of vision and a little bit of patience,'' he said. And, like a farmer with diverse plantings, you have to have a ''broad exposure'' to the market, he said, and to think of your portfolio as having three distinct pieces: ''the garden, the crop and the harvest.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HE may not exactly be a farm boy, but he did grow up in the Wisconsin countryside. And he is not a carpenter, either, although he and his wife are restoring the old, lakefront house they bought recently.</p>
        <p>But Andrew C. Stephens, 36, the manager of the three-year-old Artisan Mid-Cap fund, says his investment philosophy is influenced both by his memories of those who till the soil and by his newfound appreciation of what it takes to survive a renovation. With investing, as with an old house, ''You have to have a little bit of vision and a little bit of patience,'' he said. And, like a farmer with diverse plantings, you have to have a ''broad exposure'' to the market, he said, and to think of your portfolio as having three distinct pieces: ''the garden, the crop and the harvest.''</p>
        <p>In the garden -- 20 percent of his fund's holdings -- are the ''things you've planted'' about which ''you think you're right, but it's too early to know for sure.'' The crop -- 60 to 70 percent of the fund's assets -- are those stocks that are ''happening now.'' And the harvest -- those stocks that go above his valuation targets or whose profits start going down -- well, those are the ''ripe'' assets, the ones whose time to be sold has come.</p>
        <p>It is a homespun approach, to be sure. Nevertheless, the fund, which opened for business in June 1997 and has $202.7 million in assets, has had a return of 49.7 percent, annualized, over the three years through August, according to Morningstar Inc. That compares with 32.1 percent for the mid-cap growth fund category and 25.3 percent for the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index.</p>
        <p>That record has earned considerable praise for Mr. Stephens, who has run the fund since its inception, and who previously was a co-manager of the Strong Asset Allocation fund at Strong Capital. Mr. Stephens' work for Artisan this year recently won him the No. 1 spot in the Barron's/Value Line annual ranking of mutual fund managers.</p>
        <p>SO how does a company plant its stock in Mr. Stephens' garden? It is a three-step process, he said.</p>
        <p>First, he looks for companies that have at least two of four characteristics: dominant market share, low production costs, a proprietary asset and ownership of a ''defensible'' brand name. Next, he makes his own assessment of a stock's value, based upon the company's present and estimated future cash flow. Finally, he looks for something special -- an indication that the company is heading for an ''accelerating profit cycle.''</p>
        <p>''It could be from some kind of change that's in the wind, like a technological breakthrough,'' Mr. Stephens said. ''Or it could be from some kind of internal change, like new management.''</p>
        <p>In picking stocks, Mr. Stephens generally avoids formulas like price-to-earnings ratios. Instead, as long as they fulfill his other criteria, he chooses companies whose shares are trading at less than 60 percent of his own assessment of their value. His portfolio, with a median market capitalization of $3.8 billion as of Sept. 30, contains the stocks of about 60 companies that ''are every bit as dominant in their markets as big caps,'' but cheaper, he said.</p>
        <p>And in contrast to the situation at many small caps, he said, ''you don't have to put up with unseasoned management or illiquid stock'' with his companies.</p>
        <p>Companies that meet Mr. Stephens' requirements include Ace Ltd., a writer of multiline property and casualty insurance in the United States. Mr. Stephens sees Ace as a miniature version of the American International Group, one of the world's largest insurers; it is run by former A.I.G. executives.</p>
        <p>Just as a ''mostly uninterrupted negative pricing cycle'' -- widespread cuts in premiums --  seems to be ending among competing insurers, Mr. Stephens said, those executives have bought a number of operations, including the United States casualty business of the Cigna Corporation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stephens began buying Ace shares in May at about $26. They now trade at $34.38, or 12.5  times his earnings estimate of $2.75 a share for the 12 months ending May 2001. His 12-  to 18-month price target for the stock is $45 to $50.</p>
        <p>Then there is Citizens Communications, previously known as Citizens Utilities, a company that dominates local telephone service in many rural areas across the country.</p>
        <p>''People in these markets have as much need -- if not more -- to get on the Internet as anyone,'' Mr. Stephens said. But the big telephone companies are divesting themselves of their rural assets. And so Citizens -- with new management, like so many of Mr. Stephens' other favorites -- is buying them and upgrading them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stephens started acquiring shares of Citizens in August 1999, at about $12. They now trade at $13.81; his 12-  to 18-month price target is $30.</p>
        <p>But he is patient in his investing.  ''It's like scraping wallpaper,'' he said. ''You steam and you steam and you steam, and finally, you get what you want.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
