<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Venture Capitalists, Venturing Beyond Capital</title>
    <meta content="15VENT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/technology/15VENT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239032"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Charles River Ventures</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">browning, lynnley</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Startup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E5DA123FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Venture Capitalists, Venturing Beyond Capital</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNLEY BROWNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">browning, lynnley</byline>
      <dateline>WALTHAM, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles River Ventures funds its own multi-million dollar program to provide the high-tech start-ups it finances with an ambitious set of business development services to ease rocky passage from idea to profitable concern; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST March, Charles River Ventures, a prominent venture capital firm in New England, offered spare office space in its headquarters here to a promising Internet company in which it had a stake. But the gesture was far more than just an informal helping hand to a fledgling business.</p>
        <p>The aid, furnished to a digital security company called Guardent, is part of a multimillion-dollar program through which Charles River wants to give the high-tech start-ups it finances a leg up in the race for riches. Called CRVelocity, the five-month-old project offers these companies an ambitious set of business development services, from computers to consultants, to ease the rocky passage from idea to going concern.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST March, Charles River Ventures, a prominent venture capital firm in New England, offered spare office space in its headquarters here to a promising Internet company in which it had a stake. But the gesture was far more than just an informal helping hand to a fledgling business.</p>
        <p>The aid, furnished to a digital security company called Guardent, is part of a multimillion-dollar program through which Charles River wants to give the high-tech start-ups it finances a leg up in the race for riches. Called CRVelocity, the five-month-old project offers these companies an ambitious set of business development services, from computers to consultants, to ease the rocky passage from idea to going concern.</p>
        <p>Some people say the approach is risky, but Charles River is not the only venture capitalist to start dispensing much more than capital. To different degrees, a number of other firms -- Greylock of Boston, Battery Ventures of Wellesley, Mass., and Mohr, Davidow Ventures of Menlo Park, Calif., to name a few -- are also signing on to the strategy for their high-tech start-ups.</p>
        <p>''We're definitely seeing a growth in services -- if not across the board, then very predominantly,'' said George Moriarty, chief editor of Venture Economics, a trade publication.</p>
        <p>The services take many forms. Venture capital firms may provide furnished office space, hire recruiters and consultants in marketing and product development, hold job fairs and splashy corporate retreats to foster strategic alliances among new companies and sign up partners to serve as the start-ups' interim chief executives. The firms are also creating limited-access Web sites where young companies can soak up shop talk.</p>
        <p>The new assistance reflects growing competition among venture capital firms and the plausible notion that sizable investments -- Charles River has $11.7 million riding on Guardent -- merit added support. For many dot-com start-ups and their financial backers, the help may be more valuable than ever, as the tumble of technology stocks this year has made life more perilous.</p>
        <p>Of course, venture capitalists have always helped the high-risk companies they finance -- serving on their boards, recruiting their executives, offering advice. But the new aid goes much further.</p>
        <p>It is also true that incubators, which are specialized venture capital shops, have long offered their start-ups a full range of business development services. But while the traditional venture capital firms usually do not dominate the companies they help, incubators often treat their start-ups as subsidiaries, expecting them to use the services and products of other entities in the fold. They may write the start-ups' strategies, even fire their founders. And start-ups entering an incubator's nest give up big equity in their companies, often 50 percent -- two or three times what a traditional venture shop might typically take.</p>
        <p>Guardent, for one, seems to be growing nicely with the hands-off kind of help that Charles River is offering. The donated offices allowed the start-up to swell from 3 to 55 employees in just three months. That growth put new workers, some with pierced eyebrows, into cramped cubicles, cheek by jowl with boxes of such supplies as bowling-style company shirts that were given to employees. In June, Guardent decamped to an old bank building nearby.</p>
        <p>But the company, now 120 strong, still receives plenty of guidance, including two recent reports produced by Charles River on Guardent's market. Daniel R. McCall, a co-founder of Guardent, said the studies saved him three weeks of work -- an eon in Internet time. And the venture firm's debt-financing consultant helped Guardent arrange a loan quickly.</p>
        <p>Charles River, a 30-year-old firm  in the top tier of the industry, may be taking the boldest strides in this new field. The firm has $675 million invested in 75 start-ups, mostly in data communications and e-commerce; 55 of those companies are using CRVelocity in some way.</p>
        <p>One of them, Proficiency, is fashioning software that allows companies to work together online. It has used the program's free office space, legal counsel and executive recruiting services, among other help. Another start-up, Snowshore, makes hardware and software for Internet voice services; it has used CRVelocity for marketing and finance advice, middle-level staffing and free office space. There are the little things, too -- like the free lunches that employees of both Proficiency and Snowshore receive at the Waltham site.</p>
        <p>The pool of possible beneficiaries will grow as Charles River continues to raise a new venture fund -- now near the $1 billion mark -- for financing new companies. CRVelocity, on which the firm plans to spend $10 million this year, will also keep growing; the size of its staff should double to 30 by December.</p>
        <p>''It's going to be a huge payoff for us,'' predicted Ted R. Dintersmith, a general partner at the firm and the man behind CRVelocity. ''These companies are going to be a lot stronger.''</p>
        <p>Others seem less sure. For an industry traditionally composed of  small clubs of deal makers with Rolodexes, not expedition-sized staffs with complex business development tools, the foray into services faces uncertain prospects. As they proceed, venture capitalists must ensure that they maintain the nimbleness they need in their fast-paced marketplace.</p>
        <p>''In a competitive environment, it helps to have more to offer entrepreneurs,'' said Prof. Joshua Lerner of Harvard Business School, who calls the size of the Charles River plan ''audacious.'' But, he warned, ''scaling up makes it challenging to retain the lean organizational culture that made you successful in the first place.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Edward B. Roberts, chairman of the Entrepreneurship Center at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, agreed. ''I worry about having 15 people, let alone 30,'' he said about the Charles River program.</p>
        <p>Some skeptics go further, asserting that venture capital is the art of finding rough diamonds, not the trade of trying to polish stones into gems.</p>
        <p>Others point out that incubators, an important model for the strategy, have been floundering on Wall Street amid doubts about the ''build a company fast'' approach. With shares of public incubators like CMGI, Internet Capital Group and Softbank falling sharply this year, these skeptics say, mainstream venture capital firms should be wary of following in the incubators' footsteps.</p>
        <p>Some venture capital firms -- and even some start-ups that are in line for the new aid -- buy these and other criticisms.</p>
        <p>Benchmark Capital, of Menlo Park, refuses to hire an associate, let alone a staff recruiter or a product-development specialist, for its start-ups. (The firm, however, is starting a networking Web site for them.) Andy Rachleff, a general partner, said such services often appeared to be marketing ploys rather than strategies to give a real boost to new businesses.</p>
        <p>David Callan, chief executive of a Charles River start-up called RiverDelta Networks, a broadband services provider, said he preferred his own group of bankers, headhunters and lawyers to the services of CRVelocity. ''If you add help, it adds a layer of complexity that takes more time,'' said Mr. Callan, a veteran of three start-ups. ''I'm interested in my relationship to my general partner at Charles River, not to his firm.''</p>
        <p>But others contend that a helping hand makes sense. For one thing, they say, a start-up bogged down in a hunt for office space wastes time that could be spent developing its business, outdistancing competitors and moving toward such lucrative events as an initial public offering or a sale to another company.</p>
        <p>''Speed is critical'' in the venture capital world, said Izhar Armony, a general partner at Charles River.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dintersmith estimated that CRVelocity would shorten by two to four months the time needed to sell a start-up or to bring it public. Over all, said Joseph Tibbetts, who oversees CRVelocity, the project might make the difference between a start-up that raises, say, $800 million in an initial offering and a powerhouse that pulls in $2 billion. (No start-ups using CRVelocity have yet gone public or been sold -- not surprising, given the recent cooling in the initial-offering market and the newness of the project.)</p>
        <p>Proponents of the new aid also say it can help in a time of heightened competition among venture firms, corporate investing arms and the wealthy individuals known as angel investors. As the broad gains in technology stocks grew spotty this year, the race intensified to rope in the high-quality prospects -- the Amazon.coms of tomorrow. Offering more than just loads of cash can give investors an edge.</p>
        <p>FINALLY, the venture capital industry is flush with money to fuel these initiatives. It invested $59.9 billion in 1999; some experts expect the amount to double this year. With many of the new venture funds topping $1 billion as investors chase hot sectors like wireless communications, the firms have buckets of fund management fees to spend on  big organization-building moves.</p>
        <p>At Greylock in Boston, the new largess meant leasing several thousand square feet of office space near its Palo Alto branch to furnish free housing for up to three start-ups. The move is part of what Greylock calls its Fast Forward initiative to jump-start choice companies. The program also offers the services of three new specialists with backgrounds in finance, information technology, product development and recruiting.</p>
        <p>''We're saying, 'Hey, we've got to do more to help our companies,' '' said Henry McCance, Greylock's senior partner, who calls Fast Forward ''a necessary additional service that we need to stay competitive.''</p>
        <p>In August at the Sundance resort in Utah, Greylock even held a retreat -- its first ever -- for 85 start-up managers. The event, at which participants listened to a speech by Gen. Colin L. Powell and dined on buffalo steak, showed how even established  venture capital firms are seeing themselves not only as visionary financiers but also as businesses that must cater to their start-ups in a formal, organized way.</p>
        <p>Battery Ventures has added eight employees this year to help start-ups with business planning, bringing to 20 the number who are aiding portfolio companies. The firm, which recently raised a $1 billion fund, has also hired a recruiter and two partners who focus on start-up marketing issues.</p>
        <p>Mohr, Davidow Ventures has taken a different tack. It has five partners, two of them hired since December, whose full-time jobs are to serve as interim chief executives at its start-ups.</p>
        <p>''It really makes a difference to the entrepreneurs and helps us attract some of the best deals and get them at the earliest stage,'' said Donna Novitsky, the Mohr partner who  serves as the temporary chief executive of InLeague, an Internet payroll and benefits start-up in which Mohr has a stake.</p>
        <p>''Venture capital is no longer about the money,'' Ms. Novitsky said. ''It's about the resources you bring to companies.''</p>
        <p>Other firms are treading on narrower paths. For example, Kleiner Perkins Caulfield &amp; Byers, of Menlo Park, recently hired a leading headhunter to be used by its portfolio companies. Bessemer Venture Partners, also of Menlo Park, bought an entire executive-search boutique for the same purpose. And Matrix Partners, in Waltham, may hire someone to collect salary and bonus data that its portfolio companies can share.</p>
        <p>TO help its start-ups, Charles River recently hired no fewer than 12 specialists -- in executive recruiting, product marketing, subordinated debt financing, equipment leasing and contract law. Three employees of Everynetwork, an information technology firm that is a subcontractor for Charles River, work full time helping the start-ups install computer systems. By year-end, the firm will include 15 more consultants, some working in business development, investment banking and volume purchasing of computers and other needs.</p>
        <p>Many of these new Charles River specialists can help in areas like marketing in which most venture capitalists have little expertise. The consultants sometimes do the work themselves but generally offer detailed advice and refer start-ups to law firms, banks, recruiting agencies and others.</p>
        <p>Charles River has also leased an additional 12,000 square feet at its Waltham headquarters to temporarily house up to four start-ups. The firm has held all-day forums for start-up executives and runs a Web site for its portfolio companies that details office-space rates and stock-option trends and, soon, will offer live chat and message boards.</p>
        <p>In all, Mr. Dintersmith said, ''any of our companies might now have a dozen points of contact with us.''</p>
        <p>Guardent, whose other investors are Sequoia Capital and New Enterprise Associates, seems pleased with all the help. Maria A. Cirino, Guardent's chief executive, said the start-up used the CRVelocity program's  property specialist to learn how to negotiate a remodeling of its offices. (Guardent's current conference room is an old bank vault lined with safe-deposit boxes.)</p>
        <p>But all the assistance carries a price of sorts. As it puts more on its start-ups' table, Charles River is demanding more in return.</p>
        <p>''Our bar for what we want to fund has gone up,'' said Mr. Dintersmith,  who ran a leading division of a semiconductor company, Analog Devices, before plunging into venture capital 12 years ago. He said the higher standards meant more rigorous scrutiny of business models and company founders as well as a larger ownership stake -- at least 15 percent, up from 10 percent -- for its initial investments.</p>
        <p>AND there are limits to what Charles River will do to help. For example, problems arose when HighWired.com, a Web site about high school that features yearbooks, clips from student newspapers and the like, relied on CRVelocity for legal advice on routine business matters.</p>
        <p>''We had to reset their expectations,'' said Mr. Dintersmith, adding that in general CRVelocity would not become a Sherpa to companies. ''We're not going to review their documents.''</p>
        <p>Don Young, chief executive of HighWired.com, acknowledged that his company was an active user of CRVelocity. But, he added: ''CRVelocity will push back if it thinks it has to. They have a limited amount of resources.''</p>
        <p>Such growing pains may worry venture capitalists, some of whom see the risks in the changes even as  they adopt them. ''The whole thing is a little experimental,'' Mr. McCance of Greylock acknowledged.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, whatever the merits, this growth of services may mark a turning point in the industry, said Prof. Paul Gompers of Harvard Business School.</p>
        <p>''It's the evolution of venture capital,'' Professor Gompers said, ''from an art into a business.''</p>
        <p>And Free Lunch, Too</p>
        <p>To give start-ups a push in the race for riches, some venture capital firms are furnishing them with offices and legal advice - even temporary chief executives. Above, executives at Charles River Ventures share lunch at the firm's offices in Waltham, Mass., with presidents of two companies the firm is aiding - Scott Berkey, far left, of Proficiency and Joel Hughes, second from left, of Snowshore. Ted Dintersmith, second from right, a general partner, hatched Charles River's plan; Izhar Armony, center, a general partner, is on the board of Guardent, another company it is financing. Sarah Reed, right, works full time furnishing the start-ups with legal advice. Here are details of the help that four of the firm's companies receive:</p>
        <p>Start-up: Proficiency  Business: Software to help companies work together online  Charles River Ventures' stake: $4 million  Aid received: Free office space, legal advice, executive recruiting</p>
        <p>Start-up: Guardent  Business: Digital security  Charles River stake: $11.7 million  Aid received: Free office space, advice on loans and real estate</p>
        <p>Start-up: NextObjects  Business: Communications software  Charles River stake: $3.4 million  Aid received: Advice on marketing and debt financing, legal counsel</p>
        <p>Start-up: Snowshore  Business: Hardware and software for Internet voice services  Charles River stake: $4.6 million  Aid received: Marketing and financial advice, midlevel recruiting, free office space</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
