<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Opposites Meeting For Title In M.L.S.</title>
    <meta content="15MLSS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/sports/15MLSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Fire</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kansas City Wizards</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E6DD113FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Opposites Meeting For Title In M.L.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses outlook for Chicago Fire-Kansas City Wizards match for Majpr League Soccer championship (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It will be the best offense against the best defense in Sunday's Major League Soccer championship game.</p>
        <p>The Chicago Fire, the team with the most productive offense, also has one of the premier money players in the world in Hristo Stoitchkov, and a number of coaches and general managers think that his presence gives Chicago the edge over the Kansas City Wizards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It will be the best offense against the best defense in Sunday's Major League Soccer championship game.</p>
        <p>The Chicago Fire, the team with the most productive offense, also has one of the premier money players in the world in Hristo Stoitchkov, and a number of coaches and general managers think that his presence gives Chicago the edge over the Kansas City Wizards.</p>
        <p>Stoitchkov's leadership since he came to the United States at the beginning of the season has been more evident in the playoffs. After playing only 18 games with nine goals in the regular season because of injuries, Stoitchkov has four goals and five assists in six playoff games to put Chicago in position to win its second M.L.S. title in three years.</p>
        <p>Chicago reached the title game at Robert F. Kennedy Stadium by eliminating the New England Revolution and the MetroStars in the playoffs, while Kansas City defeated Colorado and Los Angeles. The Fire captured the league title as an expansion team in 1998, while the Wizards are making their first title-game appearance.</p>
        <p>Sunday's game, which will be broadcast live by ABC, provides an ideal matchup between teams that split regular-season one-goal games and tied for a league high with 57 points. Chicago's 67 goals were the most in the league, while Kansas City's 29 goals allowed were the fewest. Wizards goalkeeper Tony Meola, who was voted the league's most valuable player, set a league record with 16 shutouts. Meola has allowed only four goals in six playoff games.</p>
        <p>The experienced Meola in goal and Peter Vermes in the middle of the defense have made it difficult to score against the Wizards. But Meola and Vermes, both former members of the MetroStars, and the sensational rookie defender Nick Garcia could have their hands full in the championship game because Chicago has so much firepower.</p>
        <p>Along with Stoitchkov, who will play as a striker because Peter Nowak is healthy and will be the playmaker in midfield, Chicago has other dangerous scorers in Ante Razov, Josh Wolff and Dema Kovalenko, who grew up in Ukraine and communicates with Stoitchkov in Russian.</p>
        <p>Stoitchkov, 34, and the 23-year-old Kovalenko, who lived under the rule of the Soviet Union for years, are roommates on the road. Stoitchkov has taken a particular interest in Kovalenko, who helped Indiana University to two national titles.</p>
        <p>''I think God sent him to Chicago to make me a better player and person,'' Kovalenko said of Stoitchkov. ''I feel fortunate to be spending so much time with a player who was once considered the best player in the world.''</p>
        <p>Stoitchkov said that an M.L.S. title for Chicago was just as important to him as individual awards with several teams and collective success with clubs and the national team of Bulgaria. ''It's one more game for me that I have to win,'' Stoitchkov said after he stepped off the team bus for practice on Friday at George Mason University. ''We want to win this game and we want to win the double,'' he said, referring to M.L.S. Cup 2000 and Chicago's U.S. Cup final clash with Miami on Saturday.</p>
        <p>There was one television crew waiting for the teams to arrive on Friday, and it was from Spain. It wanted to interview Stoitchkov, who gained renown with Barcelona.</p>
        <p>''This is not a challenge for us,'' Stoitchkov said of Kansas City's efficiency on defense. ''They have to worry about how to stop our attack. They have to worry about how to defend against us.''</p>
        <p>While the Fire looks to several players for offensive production, Kansas City relies almost strictly on the scoring of Miklos Molnar of Denmark, who had 12 of Kansas City's 47 goals in the regular season. Molnar has added four goals in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>CORNER KICKS</p>
        <p>Two members of the MetroStars were honored by Major League Soccer at a black-tie awards gala Saturday night. General Manager NICK SAKIEWICZ was voted the league's executive of the year after he helped engineer the most dramatic turnaround in the history of the league. Sakiewicz, who won the same award last year as a member of the Tampa Bay Mutiny, helped the MetroStars capture their division title after finishing last in the league in 1999. . . . CLINT MATHIS, who finished second in the league in scoring with 46 points and was named the league's player of the month for June and September, was voted one of the league's best 11. The Chicago Fire and the Tampa Bay Mutiny led the list with three players each, followed by two from Kansas City and two from Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
