<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Detainees Begin Hunger Strike, Advocates for Immigrants Say</title>
    <meta content="15IMMI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="42" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/nyregion/15IMMI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239170"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hunger Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Elizabeth Detention Center (NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wong, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunger Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E6DC113FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Detainees Begin Hunger Strike, Advocates for Immigrants Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WONG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wong, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dozens of detainees at Federal immigrant detention center in Elizabeth, NJ, start hunger strike to protest conditions and what they call an unfair parole process (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dozens of detainees at a federal immigrant detention center in Elizabeth, N.J., have started a hunger strike to protest conditions and what they call an unfair parole process, friends and a lawyer who have spoken with detainees in the last two days said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The strike started in several men's dormitories of the Elizabeth Detention Center on Tuesday and was quickly joined by some of the female detainees, which is rare, said Joyce Antila Phipps, a lawyer for El Centro Hispanoamericano, an advocacy group for immigrants that is based in Plainfield, N.J. As many as two-thirds of the 300 or so detainees could be participating in the strike, said Ms. Phipps, who has four clients in the center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dozens of detainees at a federal immigrant detention center in Elizabeth, N.J., have started a hunger strike to protest conditions and what they call an unfair parole process, friends and a lawyer who have spoken with detainees in the last two days said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The strike started in several men's dormitories of the Elizabeth Detention Center on Tuesday and was quickly joined by some of the female detainees, which is rare, said Joyce Antila Phipps, a lawyer for El Centro Hispanoamericano, an advocacy group for immigrants that is based in Plainfield, N.J. As many as two-thirds of the 300 or so detainees could be participating in the strike, said Ms. Phipps, who has four clients in the center.</p>
        <p>The United States Immigration and Naturalization Service said it had received reports that some detainees were not eating, but was not sure whether a hunger strike was taking place.</p>
        <p>The center, which has been managed since 1997 by the Corrections Corporation of America, houses refugees who are applying for asylum in the United States. Many come from war-torn regions of Eastern Europe, West Africa and the Indian subcontinent, and are applying for asylum for reasons that include political persecution and fear of genital cutting. The center comprises more than 20 dormitories and about a dozen solitary confinement rooms, and more than 80 percent of the detainees are men.</p>
        <p>In 1998, nearly 100 detainees staged a hunger strike to protest what they considered tough criteria for getting parole. That strike ended on its third day, after immigration officials promised to review the parole requests of 50 detainees and study ways to increase the quantity of food and lower the prices of telephone cards used by detainees.</p>
        <p>Ms. Phipps said she received telephone calls on Thursday from two of her clients. They told her that a hunger strike had begun, she said, and that they were demanding reinstitution of canceled English classes, a more liberal parole policy, an end to abusive behavior by guards and other improvements to living conditions.</p>
        <p>''Over the last couple of months, there has been increasing frustration over several issues,'' Ms. Phipps said. ''People are really worked up.''</p>
        <p>Kerry Gill, an I.N.S. spokesman, said the agency received reports on Friday morning that ''some people had missed meals.'' But he said he was not sure how many people were involved or whether a hunger strike was actually taking place.</p>
        <p>''At that point, the managers were looking at it to see if this was in fact the case,'' he said. ''It is difficult to say this event is taking place.''</p>
        <p>There was no response to messages left for a spokesman for the center on Friday evening and last night.</p>
        <p>In addition to Ms. Phipps, several people said they had received frantic calls in the last few days from detainee friends telling them there was a strike. John Vanier, who has been visiting people at the center for two years on behalf of Riverside Church in Manhattan, said an Algerian man he sees every week left a message on his answering machine on Friday. Mr. Vanier played back the message to a reporter.</p>
        <p>''A lot of problems here,'' the Algerian detainee said. ''Last night, something happened. A lot of people on strike.''</p>
        <p>A former detainee from Ghana, Stella Asamaniwa, said she received a telephone call on Friday morning from a woman she had befriended at the center. The woman said the guards disconnected the telephones and television sets for several days after the strike began, Ms. Asamaniwa said.</p>
        <p>The same reports were received by Baaba Andoh, another former detainee from Ghana who won asylum in July based on a fear of genital cutting if she was deported to Ghana. Ms. Andoh said she received a call on Friday from a friend saying he was participating in the strike.</p>
        <p>Yesterday morning, Ms. Andoh and Mr. Vanier, who know each other from the center, took a bus to Elizabeth to see their friends. Visitors are allowed on weekends. The two said that when they arrived shortly after 9 a.m., guards told them they could not immediately go into the men's visiting area because ''something was happening back there.''</p>
        <p>After a half-hour wait, they said, they were allowed inside and spoke separately to more than a half-dozen detainees who confirmed that a hunger strike was taking place. Two men said none of the detainees in the two dormitories where they lived were eating, while Mr. Vanier's Algerian friend said only a handful in his dormitory were participating in the strike, Mr. Vanier and Ms. Andoh said.</p>
        <p>''I was really scared that they were going to starve to death,'' said Ms. Andoh of four women with whom she spoke. ''They told me they feel so dry and dehydrated. I told them they should try to eat.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
