<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Benes Makes His Playoff Return Worth the Wait</title>
    <meta content="15RAFE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/sports/15RAFE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239207"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Benes, Andy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EFDB113FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Benes Makes His Playoff Return Worth the Wait</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Performance of St Louis Cardinals pitcher Andy Benes in victory over New York Mets in third game of National League Championship Series discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The game is rerun occasionally on cable television late at night, and when Andy Benes sees himself giving up the home run to Don Mattingly, he smiles. Sure, his Mariners came back to win that division series in 1995, but Benes grew up a Mattingly fan in southern Indiana and appreciated the standing ovation his hero received that night.</p>
        <p>Benes also appreciated how long it took Mattingly to reach the playoffs and wondered when he would get another chance. Before last night, Benes's last appearance in the postseason was in relief in the seventh game of the 1996 National League Championship Series. He entered with a 6-0 deficit and knew the Cardinals were on their way toward squandering a three-games-to-one lead to the Atlanta Braves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The game is rerun occasionally on cable television late at night, and when Andy Benes sees himself giving up the home run to Don Mattingly, he smiles. Sure, his Mariners came back to win that division series in 1995, but Benes grew up a Mattingly fan in southern Indiana and appreciated the standing ovation his hero received that night.</p>
        <p>Benes also appreciated how long it took Mattingly to reach the playoffs and wondered when he would get another chance. Before last night, Benes's last appearance in the postseason was in relief in the seventh game of the 1996 National League Championship Series. He entered with a 6-0 deficit and knew the Cardinals were on their way toward squandering a three-games-to-one lead to the Atlanta Braves.</p>
        <p>Benes waited four years for another opportunity. Pitching on a gimpy right knee yesterday, Benes shut down the Mets for eight innings and the Cardinals won, 8-2, to pull back into this N.L.C.S. The Mets lead the four-of-seven-game series, two games to one, with Game 4 tonight.</p>
        <p>''You never know when you're going to have an opportunity, when your team's going to have an opportunity,'' Benes said by his locker, as he recalled Mattingly's home run. ''I never like giving up home runs, but when he hit a home run at Yankee Stadium, there was a delay in the game. That was one of the most awesome things that I've ever seen because of the respect that those people have for him. So you never take it for granted that you're going to be back there.''</p>
        <p>Benes, 33, has been back to the playoffs since 1996, but only as a spectator. He watched from the visitors' bullpen at Shea Stadium last year as Todd Pratt's home run cleared the center-field wall and beat the Diamondbacks in the division series. Benes was on Arizona's roster, but Manager Buck Showalter elected not to use him.</p>
        <p>Then, last week, Benes was passed over in the Cardinals' three-game sweep of the Braves in the division series. His start last night had as much to do with circumstances as trust. Cardinals starter Garret Stephenson sprained a ligament in his pitching elbow against the Braves and will miss the rest of the postseason.</p>
        <p>So the Cardinals turned to a hobbled Benes. His right knee is protected by a brace that bulges through his uniform pants. Benes tore cartilage, and landed on the disabled list in August; he was limited to two relief appearances and three starts in September.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's was his first start in 13 days, a span filled by throwing simulated games to his brother and teammate Alan. Benes had his knee drained on Friday night in his hotel room, with his wife watching so she would understand why he complained about the pain.</p>
        <p>''She's not good with needles,'' Benes said, ''so she was fanning herself.''</p>
        <p>Benes didn't give the Mets a chance to catch their breath. After the Cardinals scored twice in the top of the first inning, Timo Perez and Edgardo Alfonzo began the bottom of the inning with singles. But Benes got Mike Piazza to ground to third to start a double play. He knew he was lucky when Robin Ventura followed with a line drive at his head, which he gloved.</p>
        <p>In the fourth inning, the Cardinals took a 5-1 lead and knocked Rick Reed out of the game. Again, the Mets rallied in the bottom of the inning. Ventura walked and Todd Zeile and Benny Agbayani singled to load the bases and bring up Jay Payton.</p>
        <p>But luck was on Benes's side. Carlos Hernandez, his catcher, has had limited experience catching Benes since joining the team at the July 31 trading deadline. Hernandez knew Benes threw a fastball, slider, changeup and curveball, and called for all of them throughout the game, veering from Benes's usual hard-throwing style. Benes had also observed how the Mets' Bobby J. Jones threw a one-hit shutout by changing speeds against the Giants to clinch the division series.</p>
        <p>Benes threw a first-pitch slider that Payton grounded to the right side for a double play, allowing a harmless run to score.</p>
        <p>The next batter was Darryl Hamilton, a left-handed pinch-hitter. Benes fell behind two balls and one strike before Hamilton hit a sinking liner that center fielder Jim Edmonds caught a foot off the grass. The Cardinals led, 5-2, and Benes took a step toward redeeming himself for 1996.</p>
        <p>Ray Lankford was Benes's teammate on that Cardinals team and can understand the pitcher's burden. ''I know it was tough for me,'' Lankford said. ''I never thought it'd take this long to get back.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
