<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congress Pushes Ahead on Bill To Expand Medicare Benefits</title>
    <meta content="15HEAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/politics/15HEAL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D7103FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congress Pushes Ahead on Bill To Expand Medicare Benefits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bill sailing through Congress with bipartisan support would expand Medicare coverage for some preventive health services and reduce cost of hospital outpatient care for beneficiaries, while increasing payments to health maintenance organizations, hospitals and other health care providers; would cost $26 billion to $28 billion over five years, with two-thirds of money going to providers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Older people will receive several new Medicare benefits under legislation sailing through Congress with bipartisan support.</p>
        <p>The bill improves coverage of mammography, Pap smears and pelvic examinations for women; expands coverage of colonoscopies to detect colon cancer, and authorizes payment for tests for glaucoma.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Older people will receive several new Medicare benefits under legislation sailing through Congress with bipartisan support.</p>
        <p>The bill improves coverage of mammography, Pap smears and pelvic examinations for women; expands coverage of colonoscopies to detect colon cancer, and authorizes payment for tests for glaucoma.</p>
        <p>In addition, the bill promises to reduce the cost of outpatient care for beneficiaries, a goal long sought by AARP, formerly known as the American Association of Retired Persons.</p>
        <p>The new benefits are included in a bill that also increases Medicare payments to health maintenance organizations, hospitals, nursing homes and home care agencies.</p>
        <p>Republicans said they had decided to provide other new Medicare benefits for two reasons. First, they said, the benefits, especially coverage for preventive health services, can prolong the lives of older Americans. Second, they said, the benefits serve an important political purpose, showing that members of Congress care about older voters even as lawmakers respond to the pleas of lobbyists for the health care industry.</p>
        <p>Overall, the legislation will cost $26 billion to $28 billion over five years. Health care providers will receive two-thirds of the money.</p>
        <p>One of the most significant features of the bill is a provision limiting the amounts that can be charged to beneficiaries for outpatient care at hospitals. Because of a quirk in the Medicare law, patients in recent years have been forced to pay a rapidly growing share of the cost for outpatient services like cataract surgery and hernia operations. Patients sometimes pay more than 60 percent of what the hospital receives.</p>
        <p>Under the legislation, the patient's share of outpatient bills may not exceed 60 percent next year, 55 percent in 2002 and 2003, 50 percent in 2004, 45 percent in 2005 and 40 percent in 2006. The Congressional Budget Office estimated that these limits would save beneficiaries $1.8 billion in the next five years.</p>
        <p>Kirsten A. Sloan, a lobbyist at AARP, said, ''This will be a great help to beneficiaries, who have been paying astronomical amounts in co-payments for some hospital outpatient services.''</p>
        <p>Under another provision of the bill, Medicare would cover colonoscopies for all beneficiaries. Under current law, it covers such procedures only for people who have a high risk of developing colon cancer, because of their family history or other factors.</p>
        <p>Medicare does not cover routine screenings for glaucoma. But under the legislation, it would cover such examinations for people with a high risk of glaucoma, including people with a family history of the disease and people who have diabetes.</p>
        <p>The legislation would also expand coverage of Pap tests, to help detect cervical cancer. In most cases, Medicare now pays for a Pap smear and a pelvic examination once every three years. Under the legislation, it would pay for the test and the examination every two years.</p>
        <p>Under the bill, Medicare would, for the first time, cover ''medical nutrition therapy services'' for some patients. The benefit would become available next year to Medicare patients with diabetes or kidney disease. The government would study whether coverage should be extended to other groups.</p>
        <p>Congress has also decided to increase payments for certain types of mammography that use new computer technology to help detect breast cancer in women with no symptoms. The payment for such a test, which now averages $84, could be increased by 50 percent.</p>
        <p>Medicare now pays for some organ transplants and for the drugs needed to prevent rejection of the transplanted organs, but coverage of the drugs is generally limited to 44 months. The bill in Congress would eliminate the time limit on coverage of the drugs.</p>
        <p>Republicans have also agreed to increase payments to H.M.O.'s, in hopes of persuading them to stay in the Medicare program. The monthly payment on behalf of a Medicare beneficiary now ranges from a low of $402 in some rural areas to a high of $814 in parts of New York. The bill would establish a minimum payment of $525 a month for beneficiaries in any metropolitan area with a population of more than 250,000.</p>
        <p>This would help cities like Portland, Ore., where Medicare now pays $453 a month, and Albuquerque, where it pays $430.</p>
        <p>In rural areas, the minimum payment would be raised to $475.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
