<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campaigns and Global Crises</title>
    <meta content="15SUN1$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/opinion/15SUN1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1D8133FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campaigns and Global Crises</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial on different approaches presidential candidates Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush would take towards foreign policy; says Bush believes in team concept that would rely on seasoned advisers, while Gore would be more inclined to rely on his own instincts and experiences (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once again the United States has been jolted by foreign crises in the midst of a presidential campaign. Indeed, the turmoil in Israel, the deaths of American sailors in Yemen and the overthrow of Slobodan Milosevic in Serbia all serve as reminders that we are not just choosing a chief architect of domestic policy on Nov. 7. We are also choosing a commander in chief and the nation's principal diplomat. Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush expressed substantial agreement in their debate last week on the centrality of America's role in an unstable world. But recent events underscore that variations in approach can be very important in dealing with real-world events.</p>
        <p>To begin with, the candidates seem to envision different processes. Mr. Bush spoke of a team concept that would rely on seasoned advisers. Mr. Gore would be more inclined to rely on his own instincts and experience. In that context, he argued for a more muscular projection of American influence, including military intervention, in overseas trouble spots. He described himself as a ''hard-liner'' in favor of action during debates over the Balkans among advisers to President Clinton. By contrast, Mr. Bush argued for a more cautious approach, calling for the earliest possible withdrawal of American troops in the Balkans. He warned against using American troops for ''nation-building'' and said that any foreign involvement must be based on a strict definition of vital national interest. He argued quite properly for the importance of having an exit strategy from the outset.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Once again the United States has been jolted by foreign crises in the midst of a presidential campaign. Indeed, the turmoil in Israel, the deaths of American sailors in Yemen and the overthrow of Slobodan Milosevic in Serbia all serve as reminders that we are not just choosing a chief architect of domestic policy on Nov. 7. We are also choosing a commander in chief and the nation's principal diplomat. Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush expressed substantial agreement in their debate last week on the centrality of America's role in an unstable world. But recent events underscore that variations in approach can be very important in dealing with real-world events.</p>
        <p>To begin with, the candidates seem to envision different processes. Mr. Bush spoke of a team concept that would rely on seasoned advisers. Mr. Gore would be more inclined to rely on his own instincts and experience. In that context, he argued for a more muscular projection of American influence, including military intervention, in overseas trouble spots. He described himself as a ''hard-liner'' in favor of action during debates over the Balkans among advisers to President Clinton. By contrast, Mr. Bush argued for a more cautious approach, calling for the earliest possible withdrawal of American troops in the Balkans. He warned against using American troops for ''nation-building'' and said that any foreign involvement must be based on a strict definition of vital national interest. He argued quite properly for the importance of having an exit strategy from the outset.</p>
        <p>As a page that has generally been reluctant to endorse military intervention, we like Mr. Bush's cautious attitude. But presidents seldom get to confront neat, well-ordered foreign policy problems. Indeed, with the post-cold-war era, the world is getting messier. The difficulty in foreign policy is not enunciating home principles but applying them in complex situations. The governor said, for example, that the American hemisphere was a region of vital interest but declared without explanation that intervention to restore democracy in Haiti was inappropriate. Surely if America wants to exert leadership in the years ahead, it cannot automatically dismiss peacekeeping and nation-building missions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, in trying to draw distinctions between himself and the less-experienced governor, outlined a more aggressive response to America's role as the sole superpower. He called for engagement overseas to protect American values as well as interests, and to deal with humanitarian crises. He spoke of his views as in line with the Marshall Plan and the establishment of NATO after World War II. We think Mr. Gore is on the right track in trying to define a foreign policy that deals with the increasing prevalence of genocidal conflict. But he offered no assurances on what limits he might place on such involvements. Defining such limits is the essence of presidential leadership.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush was right, of course, that such decisions are taken in consultation with allies and advisers. But it is naive to think that presidential decision-making rests on the consensus of experts alone. Sometimes seasoned advisers disagree or err or get bad intelligence. All recent presidents have come to understand the need to cut through what their advisers say, and in some cases disagree with the best of them. Evan Thomas's new biography of Robert Kennedy reminds us of how Central Intelligence Agency officials and others led President  Kennedy and his brother astray on Cuba. President Reagan listened to the best of his cabinet, including Secretary of State George Shultz, who is now advising Mr. Bush, in keeping the marines in Lebanon in 1983, with disastrous consequences. Mr. Clinton has spoken ruefully of his failure to question his advisers vigorously in Somalia and Bosnia early in his term. That is why Americans, in choosing the next president, need to reflect on the temperament and experience of the man seeking the office and not simply on his assurances that he will bring the best advisers into the White House with him.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
