<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From a Summons to a Slap: How the Fight in Yugoslavia Was Won</title>
    <meta content="Y15YUG$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/world/15YUGO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239114"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Serbia-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Roger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pavkovic, Nebojsa (Col) (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DD103FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="3479" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From a Summons to a Slap: How the Fight in Yugoslavia Was Won</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER and ROGER COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven; Cohen, Roger</byline>
      <dateline>BELGRADE, Oct. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>More planning lay behind march on Belgrade that overthrew Yugoslav Pres Slobodan Milosevic than final tumult suggests; planners carefully chose targets, penetrated police's secret communications system, recruited some disaffected off-duty police officers and paratroopers and sent emissary to Budapest to inform United States government; were unsure how ready police officers and military would be to repel uprising, although Gen Nebojsa Pavkovic indicated military command remained loyal to Milosevic; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Early in the day of the uprising that overthrew Slobodan Milosevic, Ljubisav Djokic received a call requesting special assistance from organizers of the opposition. Mr. Djokic, a construction worker, drives a large bulldozer, and he was asked to bring it along to a mass demonstration in central Belgrade.</p>
        <p>Arriving in front of the federal Parliament shortly before 3 p.m. that Thursday, Oct. 5, he was confronted by riot police officers. ''I thought it was going to be peaceful,'' he said. ''But when the tear gas started and people fled, I came eye-to-eye with the police. Then I asked myself, 'Why did you come? What are you waiting for? Did you come to a parade or do you want to finish something?' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Early in the day of the uprising that overthrew Slobodan Milosevic, Ljubisav Djokic received a call requesting special assistance from organizers of the opposition. Mr. Djokic, a construction worker, drives a large bulldozer, and he was asked to bring it along to a mass demonstration in central Belgrade.</p>
        <p>Arriving in front of the federal Parliament shortly before 3 p.m. that Thursday, Oct. 5, he was confronted by riot police officers. ''I thought it was going to be peaceful,'' he said. ''But when the tear gas started and people fled, I came eye-to-eye with the police. Then I asked myself, 'Why did you come? What are you waiting for? Did you come to a parade or do you want to finish something?' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Djokic switched on his machine and lumbered forward, crushing two concrete flower boxes before raising his big shovel to smash windows of the Parliament. As some demonstrators threw bottles of flaming gasoline inside the Renaissance-style building, he used the shovel to hoist other demonstrators into the breach.</p>
        <p>After 13 increasingly desperate years under Mr. Milosevic, Serbia had risen. It looked chaotic. But as Mr. Djokic's summons suggests, more planning lay behind the march on Belgrade than the final tumult suggests. Still what no one could know was how ready the police officers and military would be to repel the uprising.</p>
        <p>A close look at the rebellion reveals planning that included a careful selection of targets, penetration of the police's secret communications system, recruiting some muscular -- but disaffected -- off-duty police officers and paratroopers and the dispatch of an emissary to Budapest to inform the United States government.</p>
        <p>''We had to have a combination of organization and spontaneity,'' said Vuk Obradovic, a former army general and now the leader of the small Social Democracy Party. ''Mass civil disobedience requires spontaneity to succeed. But we planned this carefully. It was organized disorder, and that is one reason that in the end the police could not cope.''</p>
        <p>Two days before the uprising, Mr. Obradovic, who quit the army over Mr. Milosevic's policies, had addressed a letter to Gen. Nebojsa Pavkovic, Yugoslavia's top military commander, urging him to show restraint. ''Take the right side!'' he pleaded. ''Take the people's side!''</p>
        <p>A Sharp Reply</p>
        <p>General Pavkovic chose to show him the courtesy of a reply, just one day before Mr. Milosevic fell. It was both sharp and telling. It accused Mr. Obradovic of ''prejudgment of the electoral results and disobedience of the electoral procedure.''</p>
        <p>The letter made clear that on the eve of the revolt, the army command remained loyal to Mr. Milosevic, rejecting the opposition's view that Vojislav Kostunica had won the Sept. 24 presidential election outright.</p>
        <p>As crowds poured into Belgrade the next day, Mr. Obradovic fired off a last letter to his old friend General Pavkovic, lamenting that his effort to ''open your eyes'' had failed. It concluded: ''Our communication is ended. God help you!''</p>
        <p>But blood was not shed in the end. This was no Leninist revolution. It paused, at a sort of Serbian halfway house, dislodging Mr. Milosevic, installing Mr. Kostunica as president of Yugoslavia, but leaving in place -- for now -- many of the regime's authorities, including General Pavkovic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic's end came in an overwhelming display of popular anger, prepared by the hard work that spread resistance through the provinces to create a Serbian grass roots movement schooled in passive resistance and propelled to its climax by a sense that, in the words of one important organizer, Cedomir Jovanovic, ''by Thursday, it was us or them.''</p>
        <p>Many feared that the malevolent magician of Serbia would conjure a route to survival yet again. He had denied Mr. Kostunica a first round victory and dictated a second round of voting that the opposition had vowed to boycott.</p>
        <p>''I was very worried early last week that the opposition seemed to be following a course that would prevent them running a second time, but was not active enough to make a difference,'' said William D. Montgomery, the United States ambassador who ran an embassy in exile in Budapest.</p>
        <p>But the concern proved misplaced. For once, it was not the opposition that had misplayed its hand; it was Mr. Milosevic.</p>
        <p>He had manipulated the Constitution last July to call the election in September, giving Serbs a chance to vote against him. But he misread the polls and failed to steal enough votes. When he manipulated the count to deny Mr. Kostunica his victory, for most Serbs it was too much. During the protests, one of the most popular slogans was: ''Take us out of this madhouse, Kostunica.''</p>
        <p>Courts offering no justice, jobs offering no money, police offering no protection, state television offering no truths and a form of rule offering no apparent purpose beyond the perpetuation of the regime had ended by convincing a majority of Serbs that somebody was crazy, and it wasn't them.</p>
        <p>But this diffuse anger needed channeling. A student movement, Otpor (Resistance), founded in 1998, provided some of it. The arrest in the last two years of more than 1,500 of its members had produced broad disgruntlement and encouraged parents to follow their children in shedding their fear.</p>
        <p>''We were the young of Serbia, the shield that accepted the kick and bite of the regime, allowing Mr. Kostunica to campaign calmly,'' said Srdja Popovic, an Otpor leader. ''And we told our members to never cease quoting Borges when they emerged from jail,'' referring to the late Jorge Luis Borges, the Argentine writer: '' 'Violence is the last refuge of the weak.' ''</p>
        <p>Otpor's message was simple -- ''Gotov je'' -- ''He's finished.'' Flush with funds from Western aid groups and governments, within three days of Mr. Milosevic's July 27 announcement of the presidential election Otpor had six tons of printed campaign material ready. The goal was clear: produce a conviction that the impossible could happen, that Mr. Milosevic could be ousted by systematically transferring fear from a long-cowed population into the very organizations that supported the regime.</p>
        <p>Inside the army and the police, a decade of conflict had taken its toll, people close to those institutions said. Defeats in Croatia and Bosnia were followed by the humiliation of Kosovo last year. While Mr. Milosevic used the opportunity to denounce a new enemy in NATO, many young Serbs saw mass evictions and killings up close for the first time. They were especially incensed when Mr. Milosevic proclaimed his capitulation in Kosovo as a victory.</p>
        <p>It was this sort of sentiment that helped turn old Milosevic strongholds in central and southern Serbia into centers of opposition. The disgruntlement also allowed men like Velimir Ilic, the mayor of the central Serbian town of Cacak and a particularly blunt opposition leader, to recruit successfully within the police and army and gain first-rate intelligence on police activities.</p>
        <p>''For years, we used to gather and criticize Milosevic and go home and he was still there,'' said Mr. Ilic, the leader of the New Serbia party. ''And this time we spat out that method because we feared it would drag out for 100 days of banging dishes with someone complaining we were keeping a baby awake. So we decided we are men, let's do it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ilic, who led 10,000 people, some of them armed, 90 miles north to Belgrade on the decisive Thursday, added that he had senior police agents from Belgrade and Cacak working for him, as well as off-duty paratroopers. ''We knew every order coming from the Interior Ministry,'' he said. ''We knew what they were planning. We saw their faxes.''</p>
        <p>The mayor is not disinclined to promote his role, and his bravura may on occasion make light with details. But his account is supported by other leaders who make clear that the intelligence available on police moves -- and hesitations -- was significant by the time a huge crowd converged on central Belgrade.</p>
        <p>A Secret Vote</p>
        <p>In Valjevo, 60 miles southwest of Belgrade, orders were received from the capital four days before the uprising to arrest four political leaders. But the police commander there, long sympathetic to the opposition, held a secret vote with his men. The vote went against the arrests.</p>
        <p>''Milosevic did not foresee those faces in Belgrade,'' said Slobodan Homen, an Otpor founder. ''They were not middle class faces. Those were faces with real anger in their eyes, the faces of workers and peasants who had come to the capital to finish the job.''</p>
        <p>But not everyone who could be there came. Mr. Obradovic, the former general turned opposition leader, who said his role had been to keep the army and police off balance, gave instructions that only one bus should come to Belgrade with workers from the striking Kolubara coal mine, 30 miles from the capital. The strike, which began five days after the election in September, was critical. It widened the opposition movement to the workers and frightened the regime, which needed coal from the mine to keep supplying electricity.</p>
        <p>A personal, predawn appeal from General Pavkovic, combining entreaty and threat, failed to break the rebellion at the mine, and when police moved in on Wednesday morning, Oct. 4, they backed off when faced with a growing, angry crowd of supporters of Mr. Kostunica and the strike.</p>
        <p>Then, on the eve of the huge demonstration in central Belgrade, Mr. Kostunica made his second visit to the Kolubara strike, and it had a triumphal feel. His prize was coming closer, and the next day, half a million people would come to Belgrade in his name. Some of them were ready and  prepared to fight and die for the prize, even as those who organized ''revolutionary violence'' insist they kept the details from Mr. Kostunica.</p>
        <p>The key was to keep the police from consolidating their forces. ''We wanted to keep the police preoccupied in different places,'' Mr. Obradovic said. ''That's why I said, 'One bus only from Kolubara.' Our last recourse would have been to bring all Serbia to Belgrade if Mr. Milosevic cracked down.''</p>
        <p>Such a crackdown could not be ruled out. Several opposition figures received death threats early in the week, they said. A woman working in a senior position in the armed forces said that everyone in the army had been reminded before the election that Mr. Kostunica had vowed to ''professionalize'' and slash the size of the army. ''The message was, 'Think about your job before you vote,' '' she said.</p>
        <p>After the first round of voting, she continued, the new message was that everything was under control, and Mr. Milosevic would prevail.</p>
        <p>As opposition leaders met at their headquarters on Oct. 4, the day before the march on Belgrade, the murkiness of the last 10 years in Serbia endured. But they repeated their resolve that the next day would be ''D-Day,'' as they called it. Mr. Milosevic was given a deadline of 3 p.m. that Thursday to accept the results of the election and resign.</p>
        <p>''We knew Thursday was the crucial day, because on Sunday, in the so-called second round, Milosevic would re-elect himself and it would all be over,'' said Zarko Korac, a leading opposition figure.</p>
        <p>Targets were set that were symbols of the regime: the federal Parliament, the Serbian television building that had drummed out Mr. Milosevic's propaganda for a decade, his Serbian Social Party headquarters, a main municipal police station and the retaking of the B-92 independent radio station that had been seized by the government.</p>
        <p>But there was nothing as precise as a battle plan.</p>
        <p>''What we needed was a symbolic act that would liberate the people,'' Mr. Jovanovic said. ''We knew we could not settle for less than that.''</p>
        <p>As the coordinated convoys of protesters started to roll toward Belgrade Thursday -- from north, south, east and west, in buses and trucks, tractors and cars -- one opposition leader absented himself, heading for Budapest.</p>
        <p>That was Mr. Homen, an Otpor founder, who went to the American embassy in Hungary where he met with Mr. Montgomery, the American diplomat in charge of dealing with Yugoslavia. ''I explained to the ambassador that this was the decisive day, that we needed to finish the story, and were ready to occupy the federal Parliament and the Serbian TV building,'' he said.</p>
        <p>No Offer of Help</p>
        <p>During the meeting, Mr. Homen also inquired as to what the American reaction would be if forces loyal to Mr. Milosevic fired on the demonstrators. ''I was told there was no possibility of military help,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Montgomery confirmed that the meeting had taken place. ''If ever anybody asked, I always discouraged any notion that there could be any kind of military intervention,'' he said. ''But I made clear that pressure had to be maintained, could not stop -- and they seemed to realize that themselves.''</p>
        <p>Certainly, the momentum was ferocious. As one long convoy of protesters rolled toward Belgrade from Kraljevo in central Serbia, it was confronted by a police roadblock that refused to move.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jovanovic, who was in radio contact with the leader of the protesters, heard him turn to the crowd and say that every veteran of the Serbian wars in Croatia, Bosnia and Kosovo should come to the front. About 1,000 men stepped forward.</p>
        <p>Then one of them approached the police chief at the roadblock and, without a word, slapped him twice across the face as he instructed him to move. In a telling illustration of how psychological power had shifted from the regime to the opposition, the police moved out of the way.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obradovic and Momcilo Perisic, the army chief of staff fired by Mr. Milosevic in 1998, had contacts inside the high command with whom they had been in contact for weeks, and they knew that Mr. Milosevic was ordering the army to stop the columns of protesters moving into Belgrade.</p>
        <p>By early afternoon on Thursday, as the crowds built in Belgrade, General Pavkovic, the top military commander, concluded that an order to fire would not be obeyed by his troops. ''Pavkovic told Milosevic that if he ordered out the tanks, the next picture he would see would be of protesters on top of the tanks giving a flower to a crying soldier,'' one official said.</p>
        <p>General Pavkovic, who had tied his career to political support for Mr. Milosevic, turned, realizing that it was better to risk being fired than hanged. The army remained in its barracks as the 3 p.m. deadline passed, and a huge crowd surged toward the federal Parliament.</p>
        <p>In a cloud of overwhelming tear gas, demonstrators heard the following over the police communications they had penetrated: ''Send us reinforcements! Send reinforcements!'' The reply came back: ''We are trying, wait while we try.''</p>
        <p>But soon afterward, the message from the outer ring of police around the crowd to those at the Parliament was more somber: ''We don't know what to do, some of our men are putting down their weapons.''</p>
        <p>Going for Broke</p>
        <p>Despite the tear gas, Mr. Djokic, with his bulldozer, was undeterred. ''I was sure I'd go to prison for the rest of my life, so I thought, let me go clean RTS, too,'' he said, referring to the headquarters of Radio Television Serbia, the hated state media known as Television Bastille.</p>
        <p>There were lines of police in the front of the building firing tear gas, and Mr. Djokic went forward three times, then stopped. Suddenly, he said, someone with a beard gave him a gas mask, ''and I went on attack.'' Shots were fired at him, making two holes in the back window.</p>
        <p>He crashed through the concrete of the main door of the building, and protesters rushed in.</p>
        <p>At the Parliament, Mr. Jovanovic, a leader among the demonstrators, was wearing a bulletproof vest and was among the first of about 200 people to enter. Police fired rubber bullets -- he has one as a souvenir -- but no live rounds. The police were firing stun grenades, more tear gas and some chemical with a choking effect.</p>
        <p>In the lower house assembly room, a police unit decided not to fight. They called their superior officer and asked permission to leave the building. ''They were told to use all possible means to fight back,'' Mr. Jovanovic said. ''But then the unit commander took off his side arm, and the others followed.'' They put down their weapons and riot gear and left the building.</p>
        <p>Demonstrators swarmed in past the growing flames, and some started looting, ripping off chairs, hat racks, leather briefcases and other souvenirs, while some protesters started tossing election ballots -- already marked in favor of Mr. Milosevic -- out of the second-story window of the building, which was begun in 1907 and finished in 1936.</p>
        <p>Zoran Djindjic, one of the top opposition leaders, was running a command headquarters from the party offices of the Democratic Alternative of Nebojsa Covic, a former mayor of Belgrade who broke with Mr. Milosevic. The office has a steel door and a television camera watching the outside. The staircase was full of beefy, short-haired Djindjic bodyguards, many of them wearing body armor, who went off on missions, some of them led by Mr. Jovanovic.</p>
        <p>Everyone understood that the Parliament was a symbol but storming it would not make Mr. Milosevic leave, opposition leaders said. That was why the taking of the state-run news media, especially Radio Television Serbia and Politika, the state-run daily newspaper, and the main police stations was crucial.</p>
        <p>''It was like a run on the Winter Palace,'' Mr. Jovanovic said. Teams moved from the building of B-92, the independent radio seized by the state, which Otpor helped liberate, to RTS, which was also set on fire, then to other state media and, perhaps most important, to the RTS studio and transmitter on a hill three miles south of the federal Parliament.</p>
        <p>The chief editor of Politika escaped up a fire stairs and over the roof, but the head of RTS and the chief news editor were severely beaten.</p>
        <p>A Swift Collapse</p>
        <p>With the army inactive, the Belgrade police collapsed. About 5:30 p.m., the commanders decided they could not fight the inevitable, and by 7 p.m., the order came over the police radio: ''Give up. He's finished.''</p>
        <p>Commanders made contact with Mr. Djindjic and Mr. Kostunica, promising they would only attack if attacked and would otherwise withdraw.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obradovic was dispatched to seal the bargain, finding a frightened police commander, Gen. Branko Djuric, in his office in the main police headquarters building on 29 November Street.</p>
        <p>At city hall, across a park from the burning federal Parliament, Mr. Kostunica swept through the huge crowd to give a speech of triumph and reconciliation from the balcony, a reluctant revolutionary who had been propelled into power. ''Good evening, dear liberated Serbia!'' he shouted.</p>
        <p>In the hallway, Belgrade's new mayor, Milan Protic, a historian, could barely control his emotions. ''We're living the revolution,'' he said, as hundreds of thousands cheered outside.</p>
        <p>''I've been a historian all my life,'' he said. ''I've studied the past to understand the essence of a nation's feelings and development. And this is really something else -- this is really living history.''</p>
        <p>One day later, about 11:30 at night, on Friday, Mr. Milosevic went on television to concede defeat in the election to Mr. Kostunica. The two men had met a few hours earlier, brought together by General Pavkovic, in a summer house in Tito's former residence on Uzicka Street in Belgrade.</p>
        <p>They spoke alone for about 20 minutes. One of their topics, Mr. Kostunica said later, was the transitory nature of power.''I talked about how power, once lost, is not power lost forever,'' Mr. Kostunica said. But Mr. Milosevic's long and bloody grip on the fractured state of Yugoslavia had been broken.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
