<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEHIND THE WHEEL/Acura MDX; Through the Woods in Comfort</title>
    <meta content="15AUTO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Honda Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jensen, Cheryl</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E7DD123FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1291" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEHIND THE WHEEL/Acura MDX; Through the Woods in Comfort</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHERYL JENSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jensen, Cheryl</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on 2001 Acura MDX; chart; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you come late to the party, you can make a grand entrance and be the center of attention, or you can find yourself so tardy that most of the guests have already gone home. There is no doubt that Acura has come very late to the luxury sport utility festivities.</p>
        <p>Its excuse is that its engineers were busy developing other vehicles, said Art St. Cyr, the project leader for the MDX team. So, instead of designing its own sport utility, Acura made due with a rebadged version of the Isuzu Trooper that it called the SLX. But the boxy SLX was out of sync with buyers looking for more luxurious S.U.V.'s. Mr. St. Cyr said that with only the SLX to offer, the company was losing 25 percent of its potential customers to the competition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you come late to the party, you can make a grand entrance and be the center of attention, or you can find yourself so tardy that most of the guests have already gone home. There is no doubt that Acura has come very late to the luxury sport utility festivities.</p>
        <p>Its excuse is that its engineers were busy developing other vehicles, said Art St. Cyr, the project leader for the MDX team. So, instead of designing its own sport utility, Acura made due with a rebadged version of the Isuzu Trooper that it called the SLX. But the boxy SLX was out of sync with buyers looking for more luxurious S.U.V.'s. Mr. St. Cyr said that with only the SLX to offer, the company was losing 25 percent of its potential customers to the competition.</p>
        <p>Now, with its 2001 MDX, Acura executives say they are ready to compete with the Lexus RX 300, Mercedes-Benz ML320 and BMW X5. The 2001 MDX went on sale this month with a base price of $34,850, including delivery charges. In keeping with Acura's recent policy of selling only vehicles with a high level of equipment, there are just two factory options, a touring package and a  $2,000 navigation system.</p>
        <p>Acura says its goal is to offer the best of two worlds by combining the features of truck-derived sport utilities, like a high seating position and all-wheel drive, with carlike handling and comfort. The handling and comfort come from the MDX's one-piece unit-body construction, the same approach taken with the RX 300 and X5. The ML320 uses a separate frame, like most trucks.</p>
        <p>The MDX's interior looks upscale, but not excessively luxurious; and while the driver and passengers sit high and have good visibility, minimal climbing is required.</p>
        <p>A third-row seat turns the MDX into an especially versatile and practical vehicle. You have the option of carrying a total of seven passengers when this seat is upright, or five passengers plus more luggage when it is folded flat. The third row is fine for two children but could carry two adults only in a pinch -- literally, because of its limited leg room and the difficulty of climbing into the back. The second and third rows both have split seats that fold down, making the MDX highly flexible in how many passengers, and what kinds of cargo, it can carry.</p>
        <p>With an overall length of 188.5 inches, the MDX is about 8 inches longer than the RX 300 and 4.8 inches wider. With the third seat folded flat, there are 49.6 cubic feet of cargo space. With the third seat in use, cargo capacity is rated at 14.8 cubic feet, which is about 2 cubic feet less than the trunk of a midsize sedan like the Ford Taurus.</p>
        <p>That beats the RX 300 for flexibility and cargo-carrying, even though the Lexus's second row can slide 4.7 inches toward the front or rear, allowing either maximum cargo space or maximum legroom.</p>
        <p>For those who worry about the safety of the third-row occupants, Acura says that in a rear-impact collision at 35 miles an hour, with a vehicle of similar size, the MDX's body stops crumpling before the third seat is disturbed.</p>
        <p>Other safety features include a front air bag on the passenger side that inflates at one of two speeds, depending on the severity of the crash. There are also door-mounted side-impact air bags up front for both driver and passenger. The one on the passenger side can tell if a child or small adult is leaning into its path and might be injured if it deploys. In that case, it disables the side-impact bag and reactivates it once the passenger is seated correctly.</p>
        <p>Acura officials say a big advantage of the MDX is its handling, and a 500-mile drive along interstates and two-lane mountain roads through Pennsylvania and Ohio backed up this assertion.</p>
        <p>The MDX is based on the front-wheel design of the Honda Odyssey minivan. But, despite its weight distribution of 58 percent up front and 42 percent in the rear, the MDX is surprisingly eager to change direction and manages to avoid feeling nose-heavy.</p>
        <p>The steering is on the light side, which is characteristic of most Honda and Acura vehicles. The fully independent suspension manages to keep moderately tight control over body lean and roll without sacrificing too much ride comfort. With the RX 300, there is more body lean but a more refined ride and a softer feel. The Lexus also seems quieter.</p>
        <p>Acura's 240-horsepower V-6 engine has variable valve timing for smooth and efficient performance. Combined with the five-speed automatic transmission, the engine gives good acceleration almost any time, despite a vehicle weight of 4,300 pounds unloaded. Ninety-five percent of its 245 foot-pounds of torque is available at only 2,000 r.p.m., Acura says, and it seems true. Need power to get up a hill? No problem.</p>
        <p>In normal dry-pavement cruising, the front wheels of the MDX get all the power, in contrast to the RX 300, which evenly splits torque between the front and rear. When wheel slippage occurs, the RX 300's all-wheel-drive system can switch up to 95 percent of torque to the front or rear depending on which wheels have the most traction. All of this is invisible to the driver. There are no levers to engage or knobs to turn.</p>
        <p>Acura engineers say the four-wheel-drive system in the MDX is unlike the system in the RX 300 and many other all-wheel-drive sport utility vehicles that react to wheel slippage only. They say the VTM-4 system (which stands for Variable Torque Management-4WD) can react before wheel spin occurs -- as well as direct more, and gradually increasing, torque to the rear wheels if wheel spin is detected in front. The system has three modes, only one of which requires the driver to push a button.</p>
        <p>The first distributes torque to all four wheels as the MDX accelerates from a stop to cruising speed. That means traction is available immediately to move the vehicle from a stop on wet or slippery surfaces before any wheel spin occurs. The operation of the second mode is similar to conventional all-wheel-drive systems that use wheel spin from the front wheels to send an increasing amount of torque to the rear wheels.</p>
        <p>If the MDX gets stuck, or is about to, help is available from the third, or lock mode. By pushing the dash-mounted VTM-4 button while in first, second or reverse gears, a maximum of 54 percent power is locked in to the rear wheels until the MDX gets moving.</p>
        <p>This lock mode is an advantage. On the other hand, all of the competition for 2001 has some form of skid control system intended to counter oversteer or understeer; the MDX does not.</p>
        <p>The MDX has a lot going for it. For a reasonably large vehicle it provides good handling, an impressive powertrain and a lot of versatility. It has taken Acura a long time to get serious about the sport utility market. Now that the MDX has arrived, even if fashionably late, it promises to add some life to the party.</p>
        <p>INSIDE TRACK: -- Plush but practical foul-weather friend.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
