<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Take-a-Kid-Fishing Trip: Not Just Children Get a Lift</title>
    <meta content="Y15OUT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/sports/15OUTD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BACKTALK: OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7DA103FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Take-a-Kid-Fishing Trip: Not Just Children Get a Lift</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Pete Bodo</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>My friend Chris von Strasser looked ready to go fishing. Dressed on this oppressive August day in safari shorts, sturdy brown shoes and a faded ochre shirt, he had slung over his shoulder the familiar, ratty old-world rucksack that appeared to have endured the Crimean campaign. However, as he was standing in the middle of Lexington Avenue, frantically flagging a cab, a cell phone pressed to his right ear, I knew this would be a fishing trip of a different kind.</p>
        <p>Forty-five minutes later, the swaying and clicking Q train deposited us at Sheepshead Bay. The quayside air smelled of salt, and gulls shrieked as we walked past the venerable Lundy's and Randazzo's Clam Bar -- the self-proclaimed Pride of Sheepshead Bay -- to a wooden dock beside a stout white fishing boat, the Sea Queen. Some 40 youngsters in Cub and Boy Scout regalia, and 6 adult chaperones, waited impatiently to board. The youngsters, filled with anticipation, were gazing at the oily water beside the dock.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>My friend Chris von Strasser looked ready to go fishing. Dressed on this oppressive August day in safari shorts, sturdy brown shoes and a faded ochre shirt, he had slung over his shoulder the familiar, ratty old-world rucksack that appeared to have endured the Crimean campaign. However, as he was standing in the middle of Lexington Avenue, frantically flagging a cab, a cell phone pressed to his right ear, I knew this would be a fishing trip of a different kind.</p>
        <p>Forty-five minutes later, the swaying and clicking Q train deposited us at Sheepshead Bay. The quayside air smelled of salt, and gulls shrieked as we walked past the venerable Lundy's and Randazzo's Clam Bar -- the self-proclaimed Pride of Sheepshead Bay -- to a wooden dock beside a stout white fishing boat, the Sea Queen. Some 40 youngsters in Cub and Boy Scout regalia, and 6 adult chaperones, waited impatiently to board. The youngsters, filled with anticipation, were gazing at the oily water beside the dock.</p>
        <p>''Some of these kids, they've grown up in Manhattan or the Bronx and they've never even seen the water,'' said the owner of the Sea Queen, George Aswad. ''I get a big kick out of this.''</p>
        <p>This trip was one of 12 sponsored by Take-a-Kid-Fishing Inc., a New York-based not-for-profit organization started by von Strasser and five other anglers in 1998. The organization develops and runs free environmental education and fishing programs, working with groups including the East Harlem School at Exodus House, the Flatbush Haitian Center and the New York City Mission Society.</p>
        <p>The group is a volunteer organization that relies on private and corporate financial sponsors -- in the case of this trip, Citibank. Even Aswad gives Take-a-Kid-Fishing a free trip each year.</p>
        <p>''We stress the educational aspect of this experience,'' said von Strasser, 43, a self-employed financier. ''And we also have prep and follow-up courses that help teach the kids -- mostly boys and girls between the ages of 8 and 12 -- that fish don't live in a supermarket. They're part of a larger, sometimes fragile chain of life. This also is a cross-cultural experience for a lot of kids, and a lesson in social cooperation.</p>
        <p>''But the bottom line from the start was our feeling that going fishing, whether a kid takes up the sport or not, is a traditional American rite of passage. Unfortunately, a lot of urban children, especially those without adequate support structure at home, never get to experience that magic.''</p>
        <p>The Sea Queen swung round, headed out to -- well, not exactly sea, but close enough for our purposes. As the deckmates demonstrated the fundamentals of bottom-fishing for our quarry, fluke, von Strasser told the youngsters not to cash in their chits for hot dogs and soft drinks until later, to prevent seasickness. Feeling salt spray for perhaps the first time, one child ran up and down the deck, shouting, ''It's raining, it's raining.''</p>
        <p>When the captain cut the engines 15 minutes later, we could still see bright yellow taxicabs crawling along the shoreline, jumbo jets headed for Kennedy International Airport crossed low above our bow, and the Ferris wheel at Coney Island stood out like a giant sunflower. In the distance, a delicate blue-and-pink haze cloaked the Statue of Liberty.</p>
        <p>But the youngsters could just as well have been in a remote reach of the Tortugas. They stared at the spot where their pink monofilament lines sliced the pea-green water, and they diligently jigged their blunt boat rods, making the spearing bait and five-ounce lead sinkers dance along the bottom.</p>
        <p>''I think I've got something here,'' Andrew, a 10-year-old, exclaimed. ''Hey, wow, it's a fish!''</p>
        <p>A chorus immediately rose from the youngsters lined up at the rail. ''It's a keeper, it's a keeper,'' they cried, hoping the fish would exceed the 15 1/2-inch conservation-based limit they had learned about earlier. The brown fish, flat as a placemat, was indeed large enough to keep and take home to eat.</p>
        <p>Soon another child hooked a fish. He reeled it up, swung it over the rail and promptly dropped the rod and ran the other way. Nothing would persuade him to touch it -- or even to stand beside the mate, Ira Brown, who volunteered to hold the fish for a photograph.</p>
        <p>''There's a long way to go with some of these kids,'' said Deborah Jain, a cubmaster who works at Chase Manhattan as a service representative. ''But we have to get them off the streets, let them know there's a whole wide, sometimes better world out there.''</p>
        <p>I was partnered with Daniel, a dreamy 8-year-old Filipino boy from Queens with enormous liquid brown eyes. His father was back in the Philippines; his mother worked long hours in a boutique. At first, he found handling the spearing ''yucky,'' and he misidentified a jellyfish drifting by as a doughnut.</p>
        <p>But he had the innate patience that makes for a good angler, and although we fished hard with no luck, he remained attentive until a final blast of the Sea Queen's horn late in the afternoon signaled us to reel up one last time for the short run home.</p>
        <p>Down below, some youngsters were already sound asleep, others sucked on the popular Baby Bottle Pops and some, flushed with success, were bragging and dispensing fishing tips.</p>
        <p>Out across the bay, golden light danced on the Statue of Liberty's tiara.</p>
        <p>BACKTALK: OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
