<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Japanese Press North Korea on Old Kidnappings</title>
    <meta content="15JAPA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/world/15JAPA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239128"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Japan-International Relations-North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North Korea-International Relations-South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North Korea-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">French, Howard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D9103FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1057" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Japanese Press North Korea on Old Kidnappings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">French, Howard W</byline>
      <dateline>NIIGATA, Japan, Oct. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Surge of new publicity about cold war era kidnappings of Japanese attributed to North Korea has made disappearances hot political issue in Japan as North Korea improves ties with South Korea, United States and other nations; critics question Japan's gift of rice to North Korea given lack of progress in kidnappings; North Korea denies role in disappearances; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the last day she was seen by her family, Megumi Yokota left the Yorii Middle School for home as usual around 6:30 p.m., after badminton practice with two teammates, and climbed the gentle hill for the short walk that led to their homes, and beyond, toward the sea.</p>
        <p>One after another, her junior high classmates waved goodbye and turned off the main road for home. With only a hundred yards or so left in her final stretch, Megumi, 13, never did make it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the last day she was seen by her family, Megumi Yokota left the Yorii Middle School for home as usual around 6:30 p.m., after badminton practice with two teammates, and climbed the gentle hill for the short walk that led to their homes, and beyond, toward the sea.</p>
        <p>One after another, her junior high classmates waved goodbye and turned off the main road for home. With only a hundred yards or so left in her final stretch, Megumi, 13, never did make it.</p>
        <p>Bloodhounds traced the girl's scent all the way to the final street corner where she should have turned for her house, but for years, despite a large manhunt, the 1977 disappearance never generated another clue.</p>
        <p>Until, that is, in 1997, when Japanese authorities cited accounts of kidnappings in Japan by arrested spies and defectors from North Korea and attributed the disappearance to kidnapping by North Korea -- one of 10 such cases of missing persons in which the prime suspect is the North Korean government.</p>
        <p>The recent dramatic improvement in North Korea's relations with South Korea, the United States and other nations has left the disappearance of Miss Yokota and the other Japanese one of the most delicate loose ends of a cold war that long kept the secluded Communist North Koreans estranged from their neighbors. The fates of these missing persons are unacknowledged and unsolved, meaning that efforts at more normal ties between Japan and North Korea are proceeding at a far slower pace than those between the two Koreas.</p>
        <p>A surge of new publicity has meant that the disappearances have once again become a hot political issue here. The government seemed embarrassed by the strong reaction this month to the news that it had given a half million tons of rice, worth roughly $1 billion, to famine-prone North Korea.</p>
        <p>Officials defended the costly donation, saying that it would help establish better ties, perhaps even securing cooperation on the disappearances. But editorial writers questioned Japan's generosity given the lack of progress in the cases. A citizens group that has long campaigned for the disappeared persons mounted noisy protests in front of the Foreign Ministry against what they called a ''sellout,'' and stepped up a petition drive that has already collected 1.3 million signatures for stronger government action.</p>
        <p>''The purpose of this aid is very ambiguous,'' said Shigeru Yokota,  Megumi's father, a 64-year-old retired banker. ''If it is humanitarian aid, why did they give so much more than the United Nations requested? If it is political aid, what are we getting in return?''</p>
        <p>Sadao Kobayashi, a retired detective who worked on the Megumi case, along with hundreds of other policemen, couched things in far starker terms as he showed a visitor around the waterfront and the port, which handles many freighters en route to nearby Korea.</p>
        <p>''We would like to ask if Mr. Mori's child disappeared like this whether he would treat this matter so lightly,'' he said, referring to Prime Minister Yoshiro Mori. ''Japan behaves as if, just by throwing money around, problems will be solved. We must be more decisive, and not so pathetic.''</p>
        <p>North Korea has scorned the notion that it has been involved in the Japanese disappearances, citing, among other incidents, the high-profile case in the Niigata area last year of a girl who was eventually found after being held prisoner and abused in a private home for nine years.</p>
        <p>''If the Japanese politicians truly hope for the improvement of the Democratic People's Republic of Korea-Japan relations and feel ashamed of their crime-woven past and present, they should stop talking about 'suspected kidnappings,' a by-product of their anti-Korean policies, and combat crime in their own country,'' the official North Korean news agency said.</p>
        <p>South Korea, too, has reported over 400 cases of suspected abductions by the North over the years. Moreover, South Korean officials say, it must be remembered that the disappearances from Japan occurred during a period in which several terrorist actions -- from bombing airliners to commando raids on the South Korean president in Seoul -- were attributed to North Korea.</p>
        <p>Megumi Yokota's disappearance on November 15, 1977 has taken on particular symbolic importance because it was the first of several mysterious abductions from coastal towns beginning in the late 1970's.</p>
        <p>During the next year, seven Japanese people, including three couples, disappeared from beaches spread widely along Japan's western coast. And in yet another case, which provided one of the first leads to the suspected North Korean connection, a couple escaped an attempted abduction after four men bound them with ropes in Toyama Prefecture, southwest of Niigata.</p>
        <p>The next breaks in the cases began to trickle in from North Koreans who had fled their country or been arrested as spies. Kim Hyun Hui, a North Korean woman who acknowledged her role in and was convicted of the 1987 mid-air bombing of a Korean Airlines Boeing 707 said that a woman who had been abducted from Japan had tutored her intensively for two years in the language and customs of Japan so that she could pass for Japanese.</p>
        <p>Similar stories have been told by defectors of having native Japanese as their tutors, in preparation for infiltration of this country, or other secret missions. Sightings of Megui, who would now be 36, have also been reported. Yet the question of how a young teenage girl could have fit into a country's espionage plans remains unanswered.</p>
        <p>''Perhaps the North Korean agents had very strict orders to complete their mission by a certain time. They may have rushed and decided to take whoever they could get," said Megumi's father, still struggling to understand. ''Really, we don't know why they took her.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
