<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Become An Instant Art Star</title>
    <meta content="17NYARTIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="61" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230968"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Rebecca</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Solomon, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EFDB1739F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3225" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Become An Instant Art Star</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Deborah Solomon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Solomon, Deborah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes artist Rebecca Smith's first year in New York City; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Name: Rebecca Smith  Age: 34  Coming from: New Haven  Looking for: Recognition</p>
        <p>What can happen in a year? Nothing. Everything.</p>
        <p>Rebecca Smith arrived in New York a little more than a year ago, a young artist with a master's degree from Yale. It might seem overly optimistic if not preposterous to assume that her life could be radically altered in the space of a single year. If you're an artist, you're lucky if anything happens in 10 years. You're lucky if anything happens in the course of your entire miserable life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Name: Rebecca Smith  Age: 34  Coming from: New Haven  Looking for: Recognition</p>
        <p>What can happen in a year? Nothing. Everything.</p>
        <p>Rebecca Smith arrived in New York a little more than a year ago, a young artist with a master's degree from Yale. It might seem overly optimistic if not preposterous to assume that her life could be radically altered in the space of a single year. If you're an artist, you're lucky if anything happens in 10 years. You're lucky if anything happens in the course of your entire miserable life.</p>
        <p>And yet, since she moved to New York, Smith's life has changed beyond recognition. Granted, she did not undergo a Schnabel-like apotheosis, did not have a sellout show or receive a surprise call from the likes of Mary Boone. No, this isn't a story about that kind of rocket-to-the-top success.</p>
        <p>Here are some of the things that happened to Becky Smith this year: She moved into her own place on Franklin Street in the Greenpoint section of Brooklyn, furnished it with stuff she found on the sidewalk and acquired a dog named Mr. President, a three-legged Chihuahua. ''I was dog-sitting him,'' she explains, ''and we fell in love, so the woman who owned him let me keep him.''</p>
        <p>It's a shining spring day, and Becky is sitting in a gallery, her own gallery, as it so happens. Surely her most ambitious undertaking this year was to start a place called Bellwether, a not-for-profit, artist-run space that occupies a storefront on Franklin Street. Her one-room apartment doubles as her painting studio, and when she heads out she can walk down empty streets to the sound of her footsteps. Unlike the Williamsburg section of Brooklyn, a famously cool art enclave, Greenpoint is relatively staid. As Becky says, ''You see fewer pairs of paint-encrusted pants here.''</p>
        <p>A charismatic, heavyset woman of 34, Becky grew up in a small town outside of Pittsburgh, the daughter of an Episcopal theologian. Last Thanksgiving, her parents came to Brooklyn for a visit. ''I made beds for them on the floor of the gallery,'' she recalls. ''At the end of the weekend, they said, 'It was great to see you, but we won't be back anytime soon.' ''</p>
        <p>She tells this story with a triumphant smile, as if taking pleasure in her new, all-improved identity as a New York artist. It has always been a dream: to leave the provinces for the privilege of being young and penniless in New York. To move to the city is to shed your past, to persuade your family, your friends and particularly yourself that you are an artist, nothing else. All you need is a New York address and already you are part of a grand tradition that goes back at least to the 50's, when Jackson Pollock and his cronies haunted Greenwich Village, punched each other out at the Cedar Tavern and made New York the world capital of art.</p>
        <p>Of course, most young artists can no longer afford to live in Manhattan, only in the outer boroughs. And bohemia might seem as distant in time as nickel cups of coffee. By now we're accustomed to the complaints: the museum blockbusters, insane auction prices and incessant marketing of culture have killed off any semblance of community or integrity in the art world.</p>
        <p>But this is unfair. To spend any time with Becky Smith is to discover a circle of dedicated, properly impoverished artists. True, it does make a difference that their friendships were forged in the cozy realm of grad school, which tends to breed cliquish behavior. There were days with Becky when I kept hoping to see scenes of creative angst; instead I felt as if I had stepped into an episode of the TV show ''Cheers.'' Becky's friends were always dropping by the gallery or checking in on the phone. One day I met Jeanne Lorenz, a young artist who specializes in lush watercolors of dewy-eyed cartoon animals. ''Greenpoint is a Yale ghetto,'' she told me, ''and Becky is the don of the Yale mafia.''</p>
        <p>Becky is indeed a magnetic personality, and when we initially met I suspected that she would ''get somewhere'' by the end of her first year in New York. Success in the art world is probably predicated on equal parts talent and enterprise, and Becky seemed to have the requisite ingredients. One day I asked her to talk about her formative experiences at Yale. I expected to hear about Painting 101, but instead she expounded on her job as a coordinator of the visiting artists program -- she had managed to meet a dozen or so art stars by picking them up at the New Haven train station when they came to lecture. ''I'm such a shuttler,'' she says. ''When I left school, one of my teachers asked me if I was going to start a taxi service for artists when I got to New York.''</p>
        <p>O.K., Act I.</p>
        <p>If you are a young artist newly arrived in New York, you need two things: an apartment and a job. Surely the most coveted job is that of artist's assistant, which promises instant entry into the orbit of the art world. Ideally, the artist you work for should be clinically sane, at least moderately famous and on amiable terms with the curators at the Whitney Museum of American Art.</p>
        <p>Becky quickly found such a job. She had been in New York for less than 48 hours when she started working for Lisa Yuskavage, a fellow Yale alumna who's one of the hotties of her generation, a central figure in the we-love-bimbos school of painting. ''Lisa's my favorite painter,'' Becky says, ''along with John Currin, who's a genius. I love paintings by art pirates who go into art history and raid it for sex, death and kitsch content.''</p>
        <p>The job turned out to be a small fiasco. Becky had imagined helping out around the studio, organizing an archive, taking calls from interesting people, but instead she ended up traipsing to the dry cleaners in the East Village to pick up Yuskavage's shirts. One afternoon, Becky asked Yuskavage if she could leave work three hours early to go to a friend's birthday party, and though Yuskavage said yes, Becky could tell she was seething.</p>
        <p>It took all of one week for her to get fired. As she recalls, ''Lisa told me I was too much of a diva, too much into my own deal, to be a good assistant.'' She went home and called her mother in Pittsburgh and wept into the phone.</p>
        <p>Yuskavage says: ''Young artists need to realize that studio assistants' jobs aren't glamorous. Working for me is not like working for Andy Warhol at the Factory. There's no party going on in my studio.''</p>
        <p>Of course, getting fired from your first job is probably a rite of passage for any serious New York artist. It certifies you as an unfettered, defiant spirit and bodes well for your future. Although Becky had every reason to feel shut out of the Manhattan art scene, she began thinking about starting a scene of her own. It sounded crazy, but she knew of other people who had done it, most notably Damien Hirst, who, before he became world-famous for slicing up cows, was organizing shows in abandoned warehouses in London. Becky hoped her gallery would be like that, the sort of adventure that awakened the money-petrified art establishment to the vigor of youth.</p>
        <p>She asked three of her friends to be partners: Simone DiLaura, Matthew Keegan and Daphne Fitzpatrick, only one of whom went to Yale and all of whom live in Brooklyn. No one was in any position to fork over start-up money for a gallery, though Simone's father, a bowling-supply manufacturer in Detroit, advanced them $4,000. Becky paid for the rest, some $12,000 in expenses, putting it all on her Visa platinum card. ''I'm not Little Miss Thrifty,'' she says, ''but I'm good at getting myself out of debt.''</p>
        <p>Bellwether formally opened on a crisp Sunday in November, and the debut show, a three-artist affair, included Becky's most recent work -- a series of imposing romantic landscapes. About 200 people jammed the gallery for the opening; many of them had only recently graduated from art school and appeared surprised to realize that in the same stretch of time in which they had done little more than unpack their belongings and gotten a cell-phone number Becky had done all this, opened this pristine, charming place. They oohed and aahed over everything -- the freshly Sheetrocked walls, the nicely designed orange sign in the window, the table stocked with bottles of wine, the striking professionalism of it all.</p>
        <p>When I arrived at the gallery, Becky wasn't there, but soon I saw her pull up to the curb in her blue Toyota minivan. Two shaggy-haired guys climbed out of the back and walked into the gallery. She spent the afternoon shuttling visitors from the Bedford Avenue subway stop to the gallery, a five-minute ride. I got into the van, and Elliott Smith's ''Waltz No. 2'' was on the tape deck. ''Easy listening for ex-punk rockers,'' she noted brightly as we sped off.</p>
        <p>A few days later, we met at Bellwether to talk about her work. The gallery was stone quiet -- it's open only on weekends -- and Becky was in an uncharacteristically anxious mood. She was wondering how her peers viewed the gallery. They could see it as an inspired gesture, but they could also see it in cynical terms; i.e., as a career move, a way to focus attention on herself. New York is like that: the capital of art, the capital of resentniks. Everyone in the art world is always accusing everyone else of being overly ambitious, as if the detractors were as pure as Buddhist monks.</p>
        <p>''Do you like my work?'' Becky asked with a straight face, seating herself in a tattered lavender chair in her studio. ''It's so feminine and girlie. I feel like it's non-Zeitgeist stuff.''</p>
        <p>Actually, at a time when painting is making a comeback, and when much of the new painting asserts the overlap between high and low, craft and kitsch, Becky's work is in sync with the moment. She specializes in fantasy landscapes whose pastel tones and frilly forms might be described as contemporary rococo. Most of her imagery is swiped from somewhere else: Victorian postcards, or curvy architectural ornaments, or reproductions of those overly grand, empty landscapes produced by the Hudson River School. Taken together, the references suggest a mood of romantic longing.</p>
        <p>Looking at her paintings, I was reminded that appropriation, which began as a gravely hip joke where everything coyly alludes to itself, has lately turned unironic. I asked her whether her generation is post-postmodernism, beyond cuteness, beyond cleverness, trying to rehabilitate art as a form of personal communication.</p>
        <p>''Definitely,'' she said, sipping a cup of tea. ''I think of my work as a suite of paintings for an unknown beloved. What do human beings long for? They long to be known, they long to possess, to have an affinity with one who can truly appreciate them. It struck me last year that I was longing for a soulmate.''</p>
        <p>Taking her comment perhaps too literally, I asked her whether she has a boyfriend. ''I've spent so much of my life chasing love,'' she said with a sigh. ''But now I think, let it chase me. My life changed when I stopped chasing love. In my mind, I picture myself as a Victorian spinster in some mansard house up on a cliff, living with my dogs.''</p>
        <p>In the end, the show wasn't reviewed in any art magazines or newspapers, except for WaterfrontWeek, a Brooklyn freebie memorable mainly for its restaurant ads. None of her paintings sold. Even so, she tried to be upbeat, to think of the show as a ''positive experience,'' as she says, and she felt consoled whenever she made a mental list of the many artists who had seen it: Amy Sillman, Rochelle Feinstein, Catherine Opie, Sam Messer and even Lisa Yuskavage, with whom she had reconciled.</p>
        <p>But in the months following the show, disappointments began piling up. She couldn't believe it when she was passed over for ''Greater New York,'' a much-discussed survey show at P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center that claimed to feature every young artist in the metropolis with any promise. ''I was praying I'd get in,'' she says. ''Artists are like racehorses. Collectors, dealers and critics aren't willing to bet on us until we've run a few races.''</p>
        <p>And then there was the Tiffany ordeal. Tiffany grants are given every other year to ''emerging artists,'' a euphemism for artists with no track record. If you are chosen you get $20,000 to spend however you wish. Becky was nominated by David Pease, a former dean of the Yale School of Art who is on the board of the Tiffany foundation. ''She's someone who's serious about what she's doing,'' Pease says. ''She's committed to pursuing a life in art.'' Becky knew the grant was a long shot, but isn't anything possible if you want it enough?</p>
        <p>One evening a few weeks before Christmas, Becky was making the rounds of the Williamsburg studios when she dropped in on Jeff Gauntt, a painter of stylish psychological landscapes. In the middle of the studio visit, he told her he had some good news. ''I just got a Tiffany,'' he said with a bashful smile.</p>
        <p>It was as if someone had slapped her. Jeff heard. Jeff heard. Jeff heard. It was all she could think about.</p>
        <p>She went home and, holding back the tears, called David Pease. ''Next time,'' he said in a soothing voice.</p>
        <p>By then she had no money in the bank and the proverbial rent was due. Unable to get a grant, she came up with a novel idea. ''I gave myself my own grant,'' she says. ''I gave myself a platinum-card grant'' -- in short, a loan of $6,000. She figured she would be able to repay it once she managed to sell a few paintings. But as the year wore on, no income came in, and Bellwether, despite its spirited monthly shows, never did turn a profit. With the arrival of summer, she owed Visa about $16,000. ''My card was maxed out,'' she says. She was fearful she would sink as fast as she rose.</p>
        <p>Amazingly enough, she managed to get herself out of the hole in the space of a single night -- a classic moment of Becky-ish ingenuity. One Sunday in June, she held a barbecue-raffle to benefit the gallery; tickets were sold for $100 a pop, and everyone was guaranteed to win a prize, a photograph or a drawing or even a not-awful painting donated by a young artist. On the night of the bash, the block of Franklin Street that is home to Bellwether was closed off to traffic. The raffle was one of those events that require tremendous planning and coordination, and I still recall my astonishment standing on the food line in the sweltering heat, music blasting, bodies swaying, grills blazing, and noticing a few hundred savory lentil burgers neatly arrayed in aluminum pans -- those, too, a donation. By the end of the evening, $24,000 had been raised.</p>
        <p>Becky is so proficient an organizer that at times I wondered whether she would end her first year in New York by deciding to give up painting. I had read somewhere that only 1 percent of art students actually become artists. The rest drift off into other fields, and I found it easy to imagine Becky 10 years down the road as some kind of impresario: the director of a major Chelsea gallery, perhaps, or the highly praised manager of a huge and unwieldy government arts program.</p>
        <p>Late one afternoon I mentioned this to her, but I regretted it as soon as the words came out, for she appeared a bit wounded. It was summer, and we were in her minivan, heading over the Williamsburg Bridge. In the distance, Manhattan shimmered like an island from a fairy tale.</p>
        <p>''If I thought that starting Bellwether was going to make me an art dealer, I never would have done it,'' Becky said. ''I don't want to be a dealer. I'm a painter.'' Her comment reminded me that I hadn't seen her work in a while and, feeling neglectful, I promptly made an appointment to drop by her studio.</p>
        <p>When I arrived a few days later, several large paintings were leaning against the far wall. Becky began talking about them freely and thoughtfully, but to my puzzlement, they were the same paintings I had seen on my previous studio visit seven months earlier.</p>
        <p>''I'd rather see your new work,'' I said.</p>
        <p>''I don't have any new work,'' Becky replied without apology. Curled up in her lavender chair, dressed in a striped tank top, black pants and sandals, she suddenly looked younger, almost like a willful adolescent.</p>
        <p>''What do you mean? You haven't made any paintings this year?''</p>
        <p>''No,'' she said, ''none, except for that tiny painting I made for the raffle. All the paintings in my studio were done before I moved to New York.''</p>
        <p>For nearly a year, I had imagined her ensconced in her studio, thinking hard about art, working feverishly, discarding false starts and struggling to create meaningful objects. But in fact she had done no such thing.</p>
        <p>What had the year brought? It was disturbing to contemplate: a hundred parties, a hundred new art-world connections. She had lived out the life of a New York artist with all the social trappings and trimmings -- with everything except for the difficult, solitary labor of making art. She could see the disappointment on my face.</p>
        <p>''It's weird with me and my work,'' she said calmly. ''There are periods when I work intensely, but I need to get into a dreamy-fantasy state to do my painting, and this year I was busy just moving to New York and trying to support myself.''</p>
        <p>In the days afterward, I wondered if I had been overly judgmental. It's certainly true that the hardships of city life can drain your resources and be a frustrating deterrent to creativity. Besides, what's one year? A life in art, with its inevitable setbacks and heartbreaks, counts only in the long run; the winners are the ones who sustain their passion and concentration over time. Surely it was way too soon to have any real sense of Becky's future, her plot, her destiny.</p>
        <p>A week or so later, I called her to apologize, but I never did reach her. Her answering machine picked up, and I was surprised to hear a new message. ''Hi. It's Becky,'' the taped voice said. ''I'm probably home but I can't come to the phone because I'm trying to paint.''</p>
        <p>Deborah Solomon, a regular contributor to the magazine, is at work on a biography of Norman Rockwell.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Deborah Solomon, a regular contributor to the magazine, is at work on a biography of Norman Rockwell.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
