<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Immigrants With an I.P.O.</title>
    <meta content="17NYISRAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="86" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230972"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Odigo (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">America Online Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ronen, Avner</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ronen, Maskit</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sella, Marshall</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EEDB1739F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2166" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Immigrants With an I.P.O.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marshall Sella</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sella, Marshall</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marshall Sella profiles Avner and Maskit Ronen, Israelis who moved to New York in January to form fledgling company, Odigo, and take on America Online; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Name: Avner and Maskit Ronen  Age: 24  Coming from: Israel  Looking for: Big bucks</p>
        <p>Avner Ronen was speeding in a cab from J.F.K. to Manhattan when he decided to move to the city. It was the middle of January. Until this day, the young Israeli's vision of New York had been a blur of Silicon Alley offices, a Holiday Inn on West 32nd Street and little else. Here he was, being swept along the same unfamiliar roads he had ridden so many times from the airport, this time to the meager temporary apartment his software company rented in the lower depths of Broadway. In all his life, it had never occurred to him that he would live in this place. ''I was in complete denial about it,'' he says. ''I still am.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Name: Avner and Maskit Ronen  Age: 24  Coming from: Israel  Looking for: Big bucks</p>
        <p>Avner Ronen was speeding in a cab from J.F.K. to Manhattan when he decided to move to the city. It was the middle of January. Until this day, the young Israeli's vision of New York had been a blur of Silicon Alley offices, a Holiday Inn on West 32nd Street and little else. Here he was, being swept along the same unfamiliar roads he had ridden so many times from the airport, this time to the meager temporary apartment his software company rented in the lower depths of Broadway. In all his life, it had never occurred to him that he would live in this place. ''I was in complete denial about it,'' he says. ''I still am.''</p>
        <p>Avner, 24, would soon find himself living like a student in a battered East Village loft. He would see his fledgling company, Odigo, laid siege to by America Online, the user-friendly Godzilla of the Internet world. He would be poised to earn fantastic amounts of wealth -- and would be equally poised to earn nothing. But having spent five years in the Israeli Defense Forces, he was not given to panic. ''Conflict with AOL is not so terrible,'' he once told me. ''Things are more difficult with Hezbollah.''</p>
        <p>Ronen has never quite shed his military appearance -- though having settled in Manhattan, that aesthetic is now supplied by Astor Place Barbers and Banana Republic. He is laconic and expresses his passions with equal minimalism: Yes, well. His year of patrolling the Territories as part of a combat unit has instilled in him an air of complete certainty.</p>
        <p>So when the idea of moving to New York struck him, Avner didn't waver. These runs to New York for meetings had become more and more frequent. The Jan. 25 start-up of Odigo, which specializes in instant-message technology, was fast approaching. ''It may sound absurd in this Internet age,'' he says, ''but sometimes you must physically be in an environment to feel what is happening. You need presence.'' Choosing Silicon Alley over Silicon Valley was a matter of pure logistics: Odigo had 70 employees back home, and Ronen believed that the extra time difference between Israel and California would be too burdensome.</p>
        <p>Still in the cab, Avner called Israel and casually informed his wife, Maskit, of his impulse to move. She agreed instantly. Maskit, who is also 24, met Avner in the military, where she had a senior rank and, significantly, was his computer instructor. (She is now one of Odigo's software engineers.) ''There was no time to digest this information for either of us,'' Avner recalls. ''Moving here was just a theory.''</p>
        <p>On Feb. 5, having never laid eyes on this city, Maskit arrived from Tel Aviv with four cats and Uma, the family boxer, in tow. She has scarcely any memory of the trip except, upon arrival, the repeated motion of dragging one pet crate forward and rushing back to fetch the next. And there was that first sting of bitter cold as she stepped outside the terminal. In Maskit's experience, winter meant 50 degrees; the bleakness of New York put her in a state of shock. ''In time, we regarded the sight of steam rising from streets as highly romantic,'' Avner says. ''But that did not happen the first week.''</p>
        <p>Despite the terrors of the climate, Maskit immediately set about looking for an apartment in the East Village. Avner always held that this was where young people live in Manhattan; it was the way of things. Maskit searched for three weeks before happening upon a rather stern edifice on East 10th Street near Fourth Avenue, stuck between the dueling canopies of the Galaxy Delicatessen and Green East Deli. The Ronens knew at first sight that the place was right for them. They had always admired wood floors -- who noticed a few scuffs? -- and there was even a small kitchen. ''So there it was,'' Avner says. ''From our house back in Modi'in, with five bedrooms and a garden, we upgraded to a one-bedroom apartment in the East Village. And all for only five times the money!''</p>
        <p>At $2,600 a month, it was artist housing without the artist rates. The walls were thin, so the Ronens heard every neighbor's sneeze and clatter. Despite having shipped Maskit's CD's from home, they put off buying a stereo because their new friend next door, a Swede called Balthazar, worked as a D.J. ''The music he plays is now our music,'' Avner told me. ''We quite like it.''</p>
        <p>For its American headquarters -- and given the 80-hour workweek, the Ronens' real home -- Odigo secured a few rooms in the Bowling Green Offices below Wall Street. The building was one of those places where high-tech start-ups rush in to fill a vacuum. Disused rooms, still chipped and gloomy, were suddenly inhabited by people with bright machines and visions of I.P.O.'s. The companies that surrounded Odigo went by hazy, ambitious-sounding names like Horizon Global Trading LLC and Media Technology Group. Week to week, you'd see their confidence grow. Hasty paper signs gave way to (still temporary) cardboard logos with color print. It was the same story with Odigo. By May, the company had grown from a fragile seedling into a going concern with nearly half a million users.</p>
        <p>Any internet start-up that arrives without a war has no reason to exist. Odigo did not suffer long for want of an adversary. In the spring, it collided head-on with America Online over the instant-message market. Unlike e-mail, instant messages pop up on a computer screen, allowing users to have real-time conversations without the tiresome ceremony of opening files. So-called I.M. technology is now used by 180 million people, and applications in the business world are expected to proliferate.</p>
        <p>In 1998, AOL acquired the Israeli company ICQ, the world's other major purveyor of instant messages. Back in Israel, entrepreneurs were electrified; one of their number had been bought up by an Internet colossus. Men like Avner began looking for a way to muscle in on the market. Odigo, named after the Greek word for ''guide,'' was born that December.</p>
        <p>Although Odigo was in direct competition with AOL, Avner's vision was that all I.M. users should be able to communicate with one another. He liked to say that ''creating barriers between Odigo and AOL users is as absurd as, say, denying telephone contact between people who use MCI and those who use Sprint.''</p>
        <p>America Online, which controlled 90 percent of the instant-message market, lacked this spirit of camaraderie. It saw companies like Odigo as parasites -- and wasn't bashful about trying to snuff them out. When Yahoo and the Microsoft Network tried to link up with AOL's instant-message network, AOL electronically blocked them within a matter of hours.</p>
        <p>That didn't stop Odigo from tapping into the AOL reservoir. It made its first contact with AOL's millions of I.M. users on May 31. Remarkably, a full week passed without incident. At a meeting of his New York staff on June 9, Avner felt bold enough to express his hope that perhaps AOL was going to leave his company alone, ''that it logically was not going to concern itself with a small start-up in New York.'' Recalling this day, he wryly holds up two fists in triumph.</p>
        <p>Optimism was premature. The very next night, as he and Maskit were walking to a late Saturday showing of ''Mission: Impossible 2,'' he received word that AOL had cut Odigo off. Avner rushed straight to the office, as did his chief software engineer back in Israel, to find a coding solution that would reconnect their I.M. network to AOL's. By Monday, they had succeeded.</p>
        <p>AOL bit back. Within 48 hours, they had disconnected Odigo again.</p>
        <p>The struggle continued for months. ''AOL became quite nasty about it,'' Avner says. ''We tried to speak to someone on the business level and sent letters, e-mails, FedEx. Not instant messages, though -- we didn't have access to Steve Case's screen name.''</p>
        <p>Neither side gave an inch. By midsummer, AOL had blocked Odigo 17 times -- and 17 times, Odigo's technicians had cracked the wall to re-establish contact. ''We insist,'' Avner said, paring his battle rhetoric to the bone. ''We have ability.''</p>
        <p>After recounting this history for an hour or so on a gray July afternoon, Avner told me in passing that, oh, yes, two hours ago Odigo had logged its one millionth user. I pointed out that this was a milestone for even the most jaded entrepreneur. ''Yes, well,'' he replied. ''It is a validation.''</p>
        <p>In adjacent offices, the staff was milling about in high spirits, but Avner took everything at his own quarter-pace. As it turned out, this was his version of party mode. Special Israeli-made keychains had been sent for; the momentous date, ''18-7-2000,'' had been engraved on each one. A few feet away there were boxes of Champagne and vodka. ''Everybody is going to drink the vodka and get drunk,'' he announced, as if winding up an agenda. ''Then we will sing into the night.''</p>
        <p>Living like specters in New York, floating through on business, the Ronens put down few roots their first year. They made no friends outside the office and had no taste at all for networking at Silicon Alley parties. They sought neither driver's licenses nor a local physician. Work never left time for planned visits to the Empire State Building, the Statue of Liberty or ''Blue Man Group,'' far less the day trips Avner read about in his new Getaways guidebook.</p>
        <p>Furnishing the apartment proved to be a particular nonpriority. In the living room, light was derived mainly from the glow of a large Sony television set (which was wired to a DirectTV satellite dish, in order to deny money to Time Warner/AOL). It took until late July for a halogen floor lamp to be installed. ''For four months, we simply didn't see in here,'' Avner told me the week of the big purchase. ''Light was a luxury.''</p>
        <p>But little by little, the place was coming together. Balthazar, the Swedish D.J., gave his friends a fine, if scuffed, dining table -- but only because he was being evicted. There was talk of buying a CD player.</p>
        <p>By the first cool day of August, ambling around the office on a Friday afternoon, Avner and Maskit seemed to have cracked all the codes they needed to flourish in their sliver of New York. Odigo was now growing by 10,000 users a day. The company's business plan had been designed to earn most of its revenues from licensing its technology -- and the Odigo client list now ran to 84 firms in 28 countries.</p>
        <p>Avner always looked slightly perplexed when I asked about the possibility of success, huge success, for the two of them. Even though it was not yet profitable, Odigo was a Silicon Alley start-up. How would wealth change their lives?</p>
        <p>''This will sound unreal,'' he said, sounding unreal, ''but that type of success never enters my mind.''</p>
        <p>I pressed the point, trying not to sound crass. But the issue was crass. What if this thing really hits? I was saying. What about the dough?</p>
        <p>Avner tilted his head right to left and back again, a real-world cubist trying to complete his view of everything. After an age, he replied, ''I'll start another company.''</p>
        <p>As for their living situation, the Ronens decided that, even if Odigo did become a mind-bending success, the place on 10th Street was fantastic. I asked Maskit if she ever had dreams of a spacious Park Avenue apartment; she crinkled her nose. Later, when we were alone, Avner said the only thing that would cause them to consider moving would be if they were going to have children here.</p>
        <p>The long shadow of AOL had become less fearsome, much as I knew Avner was utterly focused on the war. Casually as ever, he mentioned that, just this morning, AOL had blocked Odigo's access for the 18th time. It had been six weeks since the last assault. ''We were beginning to think they'd given up,'' Avner said dryly. ''We thought they'd come to their senses.''</p>
        <p>But these skirmishes now seemed almost reassuring. Odigo was still a sharp stone in AOL's boot. The fact that AOL had not responded to the company's offers of a dialogue now seemed laughable; plainly, the giant was not ignoring the upstart.</p>
        <p>''We get the message,'' Avner said, leaning his head back and smiling at the ceiling. ''We've all been in the courting-and-dating scene. When you call and she doesn't answer, that is the message.''</p>
        <p>By Monday morning, Odigo was back online again, with AOL and the world.</p>
        <p>Marshall Sella, a contributing writer for the magazine, last wrote about voyeuristic entertainment on television and the Internet.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Marshall Sella, a contributing writer for the magazine, last wrote about voyeuristic entertainment on television and the Internet.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
