<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turned Collar</title>
    <meta content="17DESILVT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Desilva, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonard, Elmore</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pagan Babies (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE4DA1539F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turned Collar</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bruce DeSilva</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Desilva, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce DeSilva reviews novel Pagan Babies by Elmore Leonard (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PAGAN BABIES</p>
        <p>By Elmore Leonard.</p>
        <p>263 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Delacorte Press. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PAGAN BABIES</p>
        <p>By Elmore Leonard.</p>
        <p>263 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Delacorte Press. $24.95.</p>
        <p>ELMORE LEONARD is one of our finest humorists, especially when he is not trying to be funny. The humor lies in his wickedly acute depictions of human nature: the greedy dreams of schemers like Harry Arno in ''Pronto'' (1993), the cool stupidity of psychopaths like Armand Degas in ''Killshot'' (1989) or the devious ways of women like Lucy Nichols in ''Bandits'' (1987). The humor works because Leonard is going not for laughs but for truth. We laugh because we recognize people we know and sometimes, though it can be hard to admit, something of ourselves in the flawed, very real people of his hard-boiled crime novels.</p>
        <p>But then there are the times, as with ''Pagan Babies,'' when Leonard seems to be self-consciously writing comedy. That is when we encounter someone like Father Terry Dunn, who did some work for the Detroit mob, skipped the country to avoid arrest, adopted the identity of a Roman Catholic priest, got himself a church in (of all places) Rwanda, stood idly by as machete-wielding Hutu villagers murdered his Tutsi flock, later shot down four of them in a strange act of contrition, fled Rwanda, returned to the United States and started scamming the top mobster in Detroit for a donation for the orphaned ''pagan babies.'' Does he sound anything like you or anyone you know?</p>
        <p>Father Dunn is an over-the-top character reminiscent of such Carl Hiaasen creations as the former Florida governor who lives in the Everglades and collects road kill for supper. This is fine for Hiaasen, who is better than Leonard at this sort of thing anyway; but for Leonard it is a dead-end descent into parody and a departure from his strength as a wry observer of humanity.</p>
        <p>The thing of it is, Leonard is such a marvelous writer that even his mistakes are worth reading. ''Pagan Babies'' has the same fast pace, crackling dialogue and dark ironies we've come to expect from every Elmore Leonard novel for the last 20 years. And there are some well-drawn characters, especially a small-time thug named Johnny Pajonny. When Father Dunn skipped town for Rwanda, he took Pajonny's dirty money with him and left him to take the fall for the crime they committed together. Pajonny is so dumb that Dunn later is able to persuade him that all of this was actually his fault. However, just as we have dismissed Pajonny as a comic loser, he demonstrates unexpected loyalty to an undeserving friend. In fact, the book as a whole is a sharp exploration of loyalty and disloyalty, trust and betrayal.</p>
        <p>Leonard's early crime novels, like ''Mr. Majestyk'' (1974) and ''City Primeval'' (1980), are grim crime stories peopled by enraged vigilantes and determined policemen. But as he gained confidence as a writer, he loosened up, got to know his characters better and discovered that, as with Chili Palmer of ''Get Shorty,'' (1990), they could be both serious and funny at the same time. In fact, it's the seriousness that makes the humor possible, and Leonard understands this. He once recounted his response to</p>
        <p>a script sent him by Bruce Willis. In the place where a bartender tossed off a hard-boiled line, the stage direction called for the character to grin and wink. Wrong, Leonard told Willis. The line may have</p>
        <p>been funny but the character was serious about what he was saying.</p>
        <p>The movie version of ''Get Shorty'' may be where the trouble started. Its director, Barry Sonnenfeld, played it strictly for laughs, casting Danny DeVito in the title role. Leonard loved the movie but was surprised by it. ''I didn't realize I had written such a funny book,'' he said at the time. Since then, with both ''Pagan Babies'' and ''Be Cool'' (1999) he sometimes has worked too hard for laughs. It's a mistake, like making a wrong turn down a one-way street. Leonard is so skillful that he avoids head-on collisions, but that doesn't mean the turn was a good idea.</p>
        <p>Bruce DeSilva, news/features editor of The Associated Press, is writing his first novel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Bruce DeSilva, news/features editor of The Associated Press, is writing his first novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
