<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Orthodox Angels Are Aiding Women in Childbirth</title>
    <meta content="17BIRT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BOROUGH PARK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Maimonides Medical Center (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siegal, Nina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E1D61038F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="477" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Orthodox Angels Are Aiding Women in Childbirth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NINA SIEGAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siegal, Nina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on work of group of 75 Orthodox Jewish women who volunteer at Maimonides Medical Center in Brooklyn, NY, as doulas, or labor coaches, for women giving birth; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mirrel Eissenberg, vice president of a real estate management firm,  was wearing a floppy blue smock with teddy bears printed on it at the Maimonides Medical Center in Borough Park.</p>
        <p>When she is not making property deals, she is a hand holder, a massage giver and a calming voice for women undergoing childbirth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mirrel Eissenberg, vice president of a real estate management firm,  was wearing a floppy blue smock with teddy bears printed on it at the Maimonides Medical Center in Borough Park.</p>
        <p>When she is not making property deals, she is a hand holder, a massage giver and a calming voice for women undergoing childbirth.</p>
        <p>She reached into the wide pockets of her smock and pulled out the tools of her craft.</p>
        <p>''Soothing tapes of all kinds of music, a little massager; sometimes I give that to the husbands,'' she said with a tender smile, then pulled a packet of papers from another pocket. On the pages were phrases like ''take a deep breath,'' ''push'' and ''relax,'' translated into Russian, Hindi, Polish and Spanish, then transliterated into Hebrew.</p>
        <p>Ms. Eissenberg has a steady gaze, straight brown hair that curls neatly under her chin, and remarkably blue eyes. She is one of 75 Orthodox Jewish women who volunteer at Maimonides as doulas, or labor coaches, for women giving birth.</p>
        <p>The doula program was created two years ago by N'Shei Cares, part of Agudath Women of America, an Orthodox Jewish women's group.</p>
        <p>''Doula'' is a Greek word meaning handmaiden. The tradition of guiding a woman through labor is ancient, with no specific ties to Orthodox Judaism. And although Maimonides is a Jewish hospital, only 40 percent of the patients are Jews, so often the bonds forged during childbirth between the doula and the mother cross cultural barriers.</p>
        <p>Each volunteer must take a four-day course, complete a probationary period of six months, then sign on for at least a year.</p>
        <p>Maimonides handled more than 5,000 births last year alone, making it  one of the busiest delivery rooms in the city. So hospital officials are glad to have the doulas.</p>
        <p>''It's a busy labor room,'' said Carol Kidney, the hospital's assistant director of obstetrics and gynecology. ''And this means someone can focus primarily on the well-being of the mom.''</p>
        <p>The organizers of the program were surprised to learn that scores of Orthodox women wanted to participate.</p>
        <p>''It's the 'in vogue' thing to do now in our community,'' said Laya Leshkowitz of N'Shei Cares.</p>
        <p>On a recent afternoon, as a baby's heartbeat ticked loudly on an electronic monitor in the delivery room, Ms. Eissenberg smoothed the mother's hair.</p>
        <p>''You meet so many different people,'' she said. ''This one is saying her prayers, this one is saying another kind of prayer. Every birth is a miracle, and each of these women gives me the honor of allowing me to share it with her.''</p>
        <p>NINA SIEGAL</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BOROUGH PARK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
