<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yonkers Judge Backed by Spencer Gets on Ballot</title>
    <meta content="17JUDG$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231167"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yonkers (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yonkers (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brenner, Elsa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Borrelli, Edward P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spencer, John D (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E3D61238F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="507" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yonkers Judge Backed by Spencer Gets on Ballot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELSA BRENNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brenner, Elsa</byline>
      <dateline>YONKERS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Edward P Borrelli, Yonkers city court judge supported by Mayor John Spencer, NY, wins spot on ballot (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THOUGH Mayor John D. Spencer wasn't on the ballot in Tuesday's primary, many in Yonkers see him as a big winner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spencer's candidate for city court judge, Edward P. Borrelli, won a spot on the ballot, edging out a candidate endorsed by the Republican hierarchy, led by John Jacono, the party chairman, and State Senator Nicholas A. Spano.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THOUGH Mayor John D. Spencer wasn't on the ballot in Tuesday's primary, many in Yonkers see him as a big winner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spencer's candidate for city court judge, Edward P. Borrelli, won a spot on the ballot, edging out a candidate endorsed by the Republican hierarchy, led by John Jacono, the party chairman, and State Senator Nicholas A. Spano.</p>
        <p>The mayor had appointed Mr. Borrelli earlier this year to fill a vacancy on the court, but Republicans who didn't agree with his choice, endorsed two other candidates for two vacancies on the court, Robert C. Cerrato and John J. Breslin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cerrato, who was supported by both Mr. Jacono and the mayor, received 1,915 votes, and Mr. Borrelli won 1,880. But Mr. Breslin received only 1,463 votes and was knocked off the ballot.</p>
        <p>Mayor Spencer, who before the primary denied there was any friction between himself and Senator Spano, on Wednesday described the Republican Party leadership as irresponsible and denounced the ''back-room political agendas'' that led to the nominations. He also referred to Mr. Jacono as ''a so-called city leader'' backed by Senator Spano.</p>
        <p>The mayor first alluded to his growing frustration with the party in a letter to constituents this summer.</p>
        <p>''This past spring, when the time came to formally nominate Judge Borrelli to run for one of two open seats on the court for a full term, I asked the Yonkers Republican Party to support him,'' Mr. Spencer said. ''Unfortunately, the party hierarchy does not share my commitment to support the best choice for the people of Yonkers.''</p>
        <p>He said the party was piqued because the mayor did not support their candidate. ''For far too long, Yonkers has suffered from such shortsighted and petty politics,'' the mayor said in the letter.</p>
        <p>In contrast, Mr. Jacono and Mr. Spano both struck a conciliatory note on Wednesday. Mr. Jacono, for example, said he was eager to put politics aside.</p>
        <p>''Yes, there's been a rift, certainly there has,'' he said. ''But all it amounted to was a difference of opinion. I'll have no problem working with the mayor.''</p>
        <p>Anthony Aurrichio, chairman of the Conservative Party, also wanted to move on and likened the primary to a ballgame. ''When it's over, it's over, and life goes on,'' said Mr. Aurrichio, whose party endorsed Mr. Borrelli.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano shared that view. ''Members of the Republican Party have spoken,'' he said. ''They chose two outstanding candidates, and now it's time for everyone to get together and set aside any differences.''</p>
        <p>The senator, who faces a re-election challenge from Thomas J. Abinanti, a Democrat, called the primary ''an overrated test of wills.''</p>
        <p>Given the outcome with victories by Mr. Spencer's candidate and another who was endorsed by the Republican party, Mr. Spano, said: ''It's a fair compromise. Now it's time to move ahead.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
