<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bills' Fierce Defense Limits Jets in Playing Catchup</title>
    <meta content="Y17JET$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/sports/17JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Buffalo Bills</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Buffalo Bills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EEDC1E38F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bills' Fierce Defense Limits Jets in Playing Catchup</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses upcoming game between New York Jets and Buffalo Bills; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Quarterback Brett Favre of the Green Bay Packers knew the truth about the fourth-quarter comeback last season. A boost for morale, a thrill for fans, but a flimsy construct on which to build a successful season.</p>
        <p>Favre knew the Packers were in trouble in 1999 when they won three of their first four games on fourth-quarter comebacks. His reputation as a big-play, guts-of-steel competitor had been burnished by that first month. But the season was ripe for a tailspin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Quarterback Brett Favre of the Green Bay Packers knew the truth about the fourth-quarter comeback last season. A boost for morale, a thrill for fans, but a flimsy construct on which to build a successful season.</p>
        <p>Favre knew the Packers were in trouble in 1999 when they won three of their first four games on fourth-quarter comebacks. His reputation as a big-play, guts-of-steel competitor had been burnished by that first month. But the season was ripe for a tailspin.</p>
        <p>''If you have to come from behind your first four games and win three of those on the last play, you've got to expect it's going to be a long year,'' Favre said.</p>
        <p>It was. The Packers finished 8-8 and their coach, Ray Rhodes, was fired.</p>
        <p>For every charming group of cardiac kids, there are many more teams that cause their coaches to reach for heart medication. After two victories in which a dysfunctional offense took three quarters to come to life, today the Jets (2-0) face in the Bills (2-0) a team with a defense so dominating that it is unlikely to let the Jets catch up if they fall behind. If the Jets have effectively peered over the cliff these last two weeks only to race all the way back to victory, the Bills are more likely, if given the chance, to shove the Jets into the abyss.</p>
        <p>The Bills had the best overall defense in the league last season, and, despite losing four starters, including defensive end Bruce Smith, have the third best this season. Whether the Jets' offense can be productive against such a defense has been at the heart of Jets practices this week.</p>
        <p>''We need to sharpen up consistency,'' Coach Al Groh said. ''Particularly against the Buffalo defense, they're going to make it hard enough on you to be consistent. The offensive efforts of their opponents have been start, stop, go, sputter. But there's no smoothness or sustaining of the ball. That's got to be our emphasis point: put good plays back to back, three, four, five.''</p>
        <p>That is not so easy. Much has been made of Vinny Testaverde's poor starts, only to be redeemed by brilliant fourth quarters. In the fourth quarters, Testaverde is 14 of 19 (73.7 percent) for 270 yards, 3 touchdowns and no interceptions, and he is, by far, the most productive fourth-quarter quarterback in the league. In the first three quarters, he is 25 of 62 (40.3 percent) for 272 yards, 1 touchdown and 2 interceptions.</p>
        <p>There is no common denominator to the poor offensive play. In the first game, the offense was undone by penalties. In the second, after a first-quarter touchdown drive, the offense was plagued with poor execution -- ill-conceived throws and dropped balls -- by several players.</p>
        <p>''We feel like the last two weeks we've made some mental errors,'' Testaverde said. ''If I had not missed the entire year last year, maybe I would have played a little bit better early on.''</p>
        <p>But Testaverde is not just out of practice. The defensive styles he is facing have changed, and the Jets' own offensive style has changed because Dan Henning is now the offensive coordinator. And, of course, Testaverde's targets have changed with the departure of Keyshawn Johnson. Testaverde has told people that he believes it will likely take him a few more games to get into a rhythm. Buffalo's defenders, who already have eight sacks this season, will try to make sure he doesn't get into the groove against them.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the Jets will try to establish Curtis Martin and the running game. It was something they failed to do against New England, a game in which Martin's play was slowed by a sprained knee. Martin said this week that his knee, sprained against Green Bay, is still not the same and the Bills have, historically, made Martin's life miserable. He has not gained more than 64 yards against the Bills in four games against them as a Jet and, other than in his rookie year, he has not had a 100-yard game against the Bills.</p>
        <p>And the Bills allow an average of just 46.5 yards rushing, second in the league. That is thanks, in part, to a defensive alignment the Bills have tagged ''the package.'' It is more like ''the mountain.''</p>
        <p>In it, the 330-pound nose tackle Ted Washington will slide over to the defensive end while the 310-pound Pat Williams plays nose tackle in running situations. Groh suggested that a fork lift might be best for moving them. Green Bay gained 40 yards rushing last week. Tennessee's Eddie George was held to 37 yards.</p>
        <p>''Ted Washington is probably the hardest guy I play against every year,'' said Jets center Kevin Mawae, who will face Washington and Williams. ''Add Pat Williams behind him or beside him and it makes it even worse. These guys against the run are probably the best in the league. It's critical we can get it going.</p>
        <p>''We can't wait around and wait around and hope to get something done in the last six minutes. This game is not going to be easy. We've got to win it on defense and win it on special teams and the offense has got to be able to hang on and score points when we can.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
