<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants' Offense Purring Under Payton</title>
    <meta content="Y17GIA$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/sports/17GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231388"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Payton, Sean</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EED81E38F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants' Offense Purring Under Payton</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giants offensive coordinator Sean Payton's play-calling puts Giants at third in NFC in offense; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sean Payton was a senior when he walked into Coach J. R. Bishop's office at Naperville Central High School outside Chicago. Bishop started to fume when Payton, his starting quarterback, told him the team had too many plays. Bishop relented, trimmed the playbook and the Redskins won their next game in a rout.</p>
        <p>''I learned to listen to him because he studied the game,'' Bishop said in an interview last week. ''When he said something, he knew what he was talking about.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sean Payton was a senior when he walked into Coach J. R. Bishop's office at Naperville Central High School outside Chicago. Bishop started to fume when Payton, his starting quarterback, told him the team had too many plays. Bishop relented, trimmed the playbook and the Redskins won their next game in a rout.</p>
        <p>''I learned to listen to him because he studied the game,'' Bishop said in an interview last week. ''When he said something, he knew what he was talking about.''</p>
        <p>Eighteen years later, Payton is calling the plays as the Giants' offensive coordinator. Now his expanded playbook has received at least some of the credit for the 2-0 record the Giants carry into today's game against the 0-2 Bears in Chicago.</p>
        <p>Payton does not turn 37 until December, and he is nine months younger than his left tackle, Lomas Brown, adding to his reputation as one of the game's bright young offensive minds.</p>
        <p>''Certainly I feel prepared to be a coordinator, but there's a lot of on-the-job training,'' Payton said.</p>
        <p>Payton deflects praise, preferring to credit improved personnel and his fellow assistants. He points to a rebuilt offensive line, quarterback Kerry Collins's maturity and the development of running backs Tiki Barber and the rookie Ron Dayne. The Giants are third in the National Football Conference in total offense, with the yardage divided almost exactly evenly between rushing (a league-high 195 a game) and passing (196).</p>
        <p>Under Payton, who became the coordinator in February, the Giants promise a diversified offense with multiple formations and personnel groups and lots of motion. Payton says his master playbook may be on the ''aggressive end'' of the league in terms of number of plays, although he will not reveal its size. He uses 150 to 200 plays each week.</p>
        <p>''I don't think we've reinvented the wheel,'' Payton said. ''You go around the league and the approach used by us is shared by many in the business. The playbooks look the same. They're the same size. Even last year's playbook was the same size going into training camp. Going into the game we may carry more, but I think that comes from the experience we have in the players that know the system well and are confident in that.''</p>
        <p>Coach Jim Fassel cannot help seeing a younger version of himself in Payton. Both men were fired from their first National Football League jobs and became offensive coordinators elsewhere. Fassel, who began as the Giants' quarterbacks coach under Ray Handley in 1991, was the offensive coordinator at Denver before returning to coach the Giants in 1997. Payton joined the Giants after losing his job as Philadelphia's quarterbacks coach when Ray Rhodes was fired after the 1998 season.</p>
        <p>''It's the same thing: He's got the boy wonder tag,'' Fassel said. ''He goes out there and lights it up on offense. The thing you got to learn is patience. And he's got that, but it looks like he's paralleling a lot of things.''</p>
        <p>Fassel canceled a Super Bowl trip in 1999 to interview Payton to be his quarterbacks coach. Fassel was considering eventually delegating the play-calling duties. He also wanted a coach who was not sensitive and unafraid to voice his opinion.</p>
        <p>Payton called the plays in the victory over the Jets last December, after Fassel left the team for two days the previous week after his mother died. The Giants amassed 490 yards, their most in 14 years. Fassel was praised for putting his ego aside, and the move was made permanent last winter, when Payton was named the coordinator.</p>
        <p>Now Payton's name is appearing elsewhere. He was stunned when he was named in a fan poll of possible replacements for Kansas City Coach Gunther Cunningham last week, and noted that it was premature since he had been a coordinator for just one game. But Payton wants to be a head coach one day and has a big supporter in Fassel. ''He definitely has all the qualities you want in a head coach,'' Fassel said.</p>
        <p>Today's game will serve as a sort of homecoming for Payton, who played for the Bears during the National Football League players' three-game strike in 1987. Being a replacement player has not hurt Payton, and the end of the strike actually kick-started his coaching career. He became a graduate assistant at San Diego State and quickly rose from job to job, eventually learning offensive schemes from the Philadelphia Eagles assistants Jon Gruden and Bill Callahan, now Oakland's head coach and offensive coordinator, respectively.</p>
        <p>Bishop, now the offensive coordinator at Wheaton College, saw a future coach in Payton, who went on to throw for 10,665 yards at Eastern Illinois, the third most in Division I-AA history. ''Now he coaches me,'' Bishop said.</p>
        <p>Payton told Bishop last winter that he planned to increase Barber's workload, even before the Giants drafted Dayne. Barber leads the league with 240 rushing yards and a 10-yard average a carry.</p>
        <p>Asked for the difference in the offense from last season, Barber said: ''I think it has been Sean Payton's offense without a doubt. He's put us in a lot of different formations, a lot of motion that is catching people off guard.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
