<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Tops South Korea; Holdsclaw Is Sidelined</title>
    <meta content="Y17BAS$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/olympics/17BASK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E7D71E38F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Tops South Korea; Holdsclaw Is Sidelined</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States defeats South Korea in women's Olympic basketball, 89-75; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Skittering across the floor, penetrating without regard for their bodies and kicking the basketball out for 22 3-pointers, the undersized players from South Korea entertained a near-sellout crowd on the opening night of the Olympic women's basketball tournament.</p>
        <p>If only they had had a center as big and as skilled as 6-foot-5-inch Lisa Leslie, who knows what shock and grief might have befallen the favored and powerful United States. As it is, Team USA will be without the services of Chamique Holdsclaw at least until the medal round.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Skittering across the floor, penetrating without regard for their bodies and kicking the basketball out for 22 3-pointers, the undersized players from South Korea entertained a near-sellout crowd on the opening night of the Olympic women's basketball tournament.</p>
        <p>If only they had had a center as big and as skilled as 6-foot-5-inch Lisa Leslie, who knows what shock and grief might have befallen the favored and powerful United States. As it is, Team USA will be without the services of Chamique Holdsclaw at least until the medal round.</p>
        <p>After the United States women held off the South Koreans, 89-75, at the Dome in Olympic Park, the team disclosed that the former Tennessee All-American and star of the Women's National Basketball Association's Washington Mystics will miss at least all the team's preliminary games with a pre-stress fracture condition in her right foot.</p>
        <p>Holdsclaw woke up Thursday morning sore and could not participate in the day's practice. A magnetic resonance imaging test on the 23-year-old forward's foot yesterday revealed the beginnings of a stress fracture.</p>
        <p>When United States basketball players are beset by injury in international play, coaches and teammates usually urge them to take their time recovering because the team has such incredible depth. But to win a third straight gold medal, the United States women may need to be at full strength.</p>
        <p>Leslie and Sheryl Swoopes eventually proved too strong and persevering for the South Koreans, whose average team height is 5-10. The two W.N.B.A. stars combined for 53 points in the victory.</p>
        <p>But not before South Korea frustrated the Americans with its break-neck, head-down style of play.</p>
        <p>Swinging the ball around and making themselves almost impossible to guard at times, Yang Jung Ok, Park Jung Eun and Jung Sun Min combined for 47 points. South Korea came within 72-64 with less than 7 minutes left and never trailed by more than 16.</p>
        <p>''We've always had trouble with that style of play,'' United States Coach Nell Fortner said. ''Japan did the same thing to us in Atlanta four years ago. It's very hard to guard. Where we're from, when someone like Nikki McCray drives and runs into somebody, she stops and passes. They don't stop. They just keep going and take you for the ride.''</p>
        <p>South Korean Coach Yoo Soo Jong said: ''The U.S. is the No. 1 team, so we are very happy. Our players played very unexpectedly well. We gave our best and gave our audience pleasure. I'm very happy about the result.''</p>
        <p>Just how fallible this United States women's team is is up for debate. When the players attacked defensively and got into their running game midway through the second half, Team USA looked untouchable. But then, these are many of the same players who won by 41 points against South Korea at the 1996 Games in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>The United States women had often said over the past few weeks that their road to another gold medal would be more difficult to negotiate than in the past.</p>
        <p>Never was that more clear than tonight, when they kept leaving their defensive assignments to help out inside and routinely got burned from the perimeter.</p>
        <p>''They try to move the ball around until you have some miscommunication,'' said Leslie, who added 11 rebounds. ''I found myself guarding a 5-foot-6 woman once. They've got an excellent style.''</p>
        <p>The Americans' greatest challenge will most likely come from the Russian Federation, Australia and Brazil. All three teams won their openers yesterday, with the Australians routing Canada, 78-46, Brazil knocking off Slovakia, 76-60, and Russia holding off Cuba, 72-62, in the most competitive game of the night.</p>
        <p>Lauren Jackson, the lanky, 6-5  19-year-old who will most likely be the No. 1 pick in the W.N.B.A. draft, scored 18 points and pulled down 8 rebounds for Australia.</p>
        <p>Team USA faces Cuba on Monday in what is regarded as its first genuine test.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the possibility of Holdsclaw returning to the lineup is up in the air. She attended last night's game in a walking boot, fitted to alleviate pain in the foot. Holdsclaw actually missed time during the Mystique's training camp because of a similar injury, but the same metatarsal bone was not involved, a team spokeswoman said.</p>
        <p>''I'm disappointed,'' Holdsclaw said. ''I've worked so hard to get to this level. I'm hoping to be able to still play. My family is coming over here. This is what I've worked for, to play in the Olympic Games.''</p>
        <p>She was averaging more than 15 minutes, almost 6 points and 3 rebounds a game during the team's select exhibitions.</p>
        <p>''I'm really going to try and keep her off of it until the medal-round games,'' Fortner said.</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
