<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Overcrowded Schools, Cold Shoulders</title>
    <meta content="17SCHO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: QUEENS UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Queens (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kulick, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shulman, Claire (Boro Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'grady, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E7DD1138F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Overcrowded Schools, Cold Shoulders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM O'GRADY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'grady, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Queens Borough Pres Claire Shulman and Flushing on Hill Taxpayers Assn chairman David Kulick, noting serious school overcrowding, call for action to assure that school construction projects stay on schedule; photo; list (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>School overcrowding has become so bad in Queens that Borough President Claire Shulman has called for a Marshall Plan of new school building. She also convenes what she calls War Room meetings each month to ensure that no school construction project has fallen behind schedule. And she has declared the boroughwide deficit of 27,688 school seats a state of emergency.</p>
        <p>But she is not the only one using martial metaphors on this subject. David Kulick, chairman of the Flushing on the Hill Taxpayers Association, was one among several at a public meeting in June who called a planned school at Queens College ''one more potential assault'' on their neighborhood. Mr. Kulick said the school would draw too much traffic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>School overcrowding has become so bad in Queens that Borough President Claire Shulman has called for a Marshall Plan of new school building. She also convenes what she calls War Room meetings each month to ensure that no school construction project has fallen behind schedule. And she has declared the boroughwide deficit of 27,688 school seats a state of emergency.</p>
        <p>But she is not the only one using martial metaphors on this subject. David Kulick, chairman of the Flushing on the Hill Taxpayers Association, was one among several at a public meeting in June who called a planned school at Queens College ''one more potential assault'' on their neighborhood. Mr. Kulick said the school would draw too much traffic.</p>
        <p>''No one questions the need for more schools in Queens,'' he said, ''but it is also clear that we don't need one in our area.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kulick's objections, which are shared by others, could soon be heard more frequently as the city Board of Education gears up to build 23 new schools in Queens by 2004. (Construction on five new schools is scheduled to begin by December.) Although the board is responsible for choosing the sites, Ms. Shulman has taken an active role in finding locations and said she was ''willing to take the heat'' for selecting them.</p>
        <p>''Whatever site you find, there are people who say, 'You shouldn't build it here,' '' she said. ''But I can't stand idly by when the kids are in trouble.''</p>
        <p>The school planned at Queens College was originally to be a math-and-science-oriented school in an underused portion of Public School 219, also in Flushing. Because of opposition, the plans shifted to the college campus.</p>
        <p>''If we keep this up,'' Ms. Shulman said, ''the school will never be built.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Shulman said some have objected to new schools for fear that immigrant students from overcrowded areas would be bused in. But she said that overcrowding was not limited to areas where immigrants live, and that five of the seven Queens school districts were at more than 100 percent capacity. She added that if current levels of immigration in Queens hold, there will still be overcrowding, even with new schools.</p>
        <p>The most tightly packed school in Queens is Newtown High School in Elmhurst, which is operating at 180 percent of capacity. The assistant principal, Michael Eisman, said that when the 4,800 students enter the hallways to change classes, there is gridlock.</p>
        <p>''It's so crowded that you're leaning on the person in front of you,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At Ms. Shulman's meetings, which are attended by Board of Education officials and the borough's seven school superintendents, the first order of business is to examine a chart that shows the status of each new school construction project. Ms. Shulman said it was important to track the progress of each school, because financing will be lost for any building that does not have a foundation by 2004.</p>
        <p>But Pat Dolan, president of the Kew Gardens Hills Civic Association, said site selection was not deliberate enough.</p>
        <p>''Because there is a hurry, there is very little professional city planning going on,'' she said.</p>
        <p>JIM O'GRADY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: QUEENS UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
