<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Streetscapes/7 East 96th Street; A French-Style 1913 Town House, in Limestone</title>
    <meta content="17SCAP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231111"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Manhattan Country School</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Codman, Ogden</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gray, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Streetscapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E0DB1538F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1291" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Streetscapes/7 East 96th Street; A French-Style 1913 Town House, in Limestone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER GRAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gray, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of architect Ogden Codman, whose 1913 French-style town house on Manattan's East 96th Street, now housing Manhattan Country School, is undergoing facade cleaning and repair work; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OGDEN CODMAN wanted to turn 96th Street between Fifth and Madison Avenues into an elegant Parisian ensemble, with wide, French-style town houses lining the wide block, almost like a European square. Codman, an architect and decorator who collaborated with Edith Wharton, achieved his goal only fractionally before moving to France in the 1920's, when apartment buildings took over the block.</p>
        <p>Now the Manhattan Country School is cleaning and repairing the facade of Codman's 1913 house at 7 East 96th Street, recapturing some of his unusual vision.</p>
        <p>Codman was born in 1863 to an old Boston family. He tried banking but quickly switched to studying architecture at M.I.T., demonstrating a lifelong interest in architectural history by making precise drawings of early American buildings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OGDEN CODMAN wanted to turn 96th Street between Fifth and Madison Avenues into an elegant Parisian ensemble, with wide, French-style town houses lining the wide block, almost like a European square. Codman, an architect and decorator who collaborated with Edith Wharton, achieved his goal only fractionally before moving to France in the 1920's, when apartment buildings took over the block.</p>
        <p>Now the Manhattan Country School is cleaning and repairing the facade of Codman's 1913 house at 7 East 96th Street, recapturing some of his unusual vision.</p>
        <p>Codman was born in 1863 to an old Boston family. He tried banking but quickly switched to studying architecture at M.I.T., demonstrating a lifelong interest in architectural history by making precise drawings of early American buildings.</p>
        <p>Later he apprenticed to several architects, just as the Colonial Revival was beginning to lighten the somber oak and mahogany palette of the Victorians. In 1891 Codman opened an office in Boston and was soon working on the Newport, R.I., and New York houses of Edith Wharton.</p>
        <p>A bigger break came in 1895 when he decorated the upper-floor interiors of the Breakers, the giant Newport mansion of Cornelius Vanderbilt II. According to research by Pauline C. Metcalf, a decorative-arts historian and an expert on Codman's work, one of Codman's draftsmen on this project was Emery Roth, who later designed the San Remo, Beresford and other notable New York apartment buildings.</p>
        <p>After Codman opened a New York office in the 1890's, his commissions included the interiors of the town houses at 16, 18 and 20 East 84th Street. Like his other designs, these were light and delicate. Codman rejected the overstuffed opulence of the gilded age, as did Wharton.</p>
        <p>In 1897 he and Wharton wrote a book,  ''The Decoration of Houses,'' published by Charles Scribner's Sons, advocating simpler, more refined designs. Among their maxims were ''proportion is the good breeding of architecture'' and ''the supreme excellence is simplicity.'' The tract established both authors as tastemakers for a new age.</p>
        <p>In 1904 Codman married Leila Webb, a rich widow, and in 1907, while living in her old house at 15 East 51st Street, they bought a 40-foot-wide lot at 7 East 96th Street.  Although Andrew Carnegie had built his mansion at Fifth Avenue and 91st Street in 1902, 96th Street was still somewhat too north as far as Upper East Side town houses were concerned.</p>
        <p>But it was a coveted, wide cross street, and property restrictions of 1901 limited the midblock to private houses. One town house had gone up at 10 East 96th Street in 1902 -- it was demolished in the 1920's -- but no others had followed.</p>
        <p>The Codmans did not build immediately, and Leila Codman died in 1910. In 1913, Ogden Codman finally built a French-style town house in limestone, with urbane detailing and a sheltered carriageway -- the main door is inside, two rooms back from the street.</p>
        <p>The interiors of the house are generally intact, with simple detailing. A curved stairway rises to the second floor, with a paneled library at the front and a circular dining room at the rear.</p>
        <p>IN 1915 the census taker recorded Codman in the house with a chauffeur and six servants. According to Ms. Metcalf, Codman intended 7 East 96th Street as one of a group of four similar houses, modeled after DePau Row, an 1830's group on Bleecker Street between Sullivan and Thompson Streets. Codman had drawn those houses years before.</p>
        <p>Elevation drawings for four of the 96th Street houses are reproduced in the 1988 book ''Ogden Codman and the Decoration of Houses,'' edited by Ms. Metcalf. They depict slightly varying designs for 9, 11 and 15 (there was no number 13) East 96th Street.</p>
        <p>Unlike the architect Frederick Sterner, who developed groups of row houses speculatively, Codman did not buy any of the land, hoping to stimulate interest by example alone. No. 9 was designed for Francis Wissman, a real estate investor who had bought the land; 11 East 96th Street was for Richard Trimble, the treasurer of U. S. Steel; and no. 15 was for Edward Shearson, also an officer at U.S. Steel until he left to found the brokerage firm once known as Shearson, Hammill, now absorbed by Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>But the flood tide of town house construction never washed over 96th Street, and none of Codman's original clients actually built. Shearson, for instance, moved from Greenwich, Conn., to the St. Regis Hotel. But he did sell his land to Lucy Drexel Dahlgren, a Philadelphia heiress, who built 15 East 96th Street from Codman's designs in 1916, the same year Robert L. Livingston built a less ambitious house at 12 East 96th Street, also designed by Codman. That house is now La Scuola d'Italia ''G. Marconi,'' which offers bilingual instruction for nursery through high school; the house at 15 East 96th is still a private residence.</p>
        <p>In the 1920's, apartment development filled the rest of the block, and the reconstruction of the Central Park transverses spilled traffic out onto 96th Street, spoiling the rest of Codman's dream. The 1925 census showed him still at 7 East 96th, but two years later he sold the house and moved to France, where he died in 1951.</p>
        <p>The new owners were Edith Moore, daughter of the publisher Joseph Pulitzer, and her husband, William S. Moore, great-great-grandson of Clement Clarke Moore, author of ''A Visit From St. Nicholas.'' The Moores' children sold the house in 1948, and their daughter-in-law, Katherine S. Moore, remembers finding many of Codman's books in the house; the books were donated to the Metropolitan Museum of Art.</p>
        <p>In 1965 the Codman house was bought by the Manhattan Country School. Now the school is almost finished with a facade-restoration program, replacing the slate roof and copper dormers, removing old paint and dirt from the facade and repainting Codman's elegant shutters.</p>
        <p>Michele Sola, the director, said that the exterior work would not directly help school operations but that there was great affection for the building. Inside, the 195 students from nursery to eighth grade work amid Codman's chaste, sophisticated interiors. Lunches are delivered in the old dumbwaiter, and Codman's original lyre-type window latches are still working. The outlines of the building's original automobile turntable -- a device for reversing a car's direction --  show through the linoleum in a classroom at the rear of the first floor.</p>
        <p>Dr. Sola said that the school had watched with interest the dramatic rise in property values for old single-family residences -- especially intact ones, like the Codman house. But she added that for her school, with its emphasis on diversity, ''there are strategic reasons for being right on 96th Street, midway between East Harlem and the East Side.''</p>
        <p>Any sale, she said, would evolve into ''a discussion of philosophy.'' In the meantime, pieces of the old Codman house are for sale.  The school has salvaged most of the original slates from the roof, and on Oct. 21, at its annual Farm Festival on the block, the school will auction off the pieces as a group.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
