<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Head-Spinning Evil Gets a New Twist</title>
    <meta content="17RAFF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/arts/17RAFF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231062"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rafferty, Terrence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedkin, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blatty, Peter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Exorcist, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E6D81738F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1224" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Head-Spinning Evil Gets a New Twist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRENCE RAFFERTY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rafferty, Terrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Terrence Rafferty article, recalling audience reaction to William Friedkin's 1973 movie The Exorcist, based on Peter Blatty's novel, on new, longer version about to be released in movie theaters (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN William Friedkin's ''Exorcist,'' based on William Peter Blatty's best-selling theological-horror novel, opened on Dec. 26, 1973, it was not only the movie event of the Christmas season that year; it also became the dominant pop-culture phenomenon of the final days of Richard M. Nixon's presidency. One wouldn't want to make too much of this: to suggest, for example, that Mr. Blatty's tale of the expulsion of a possessing demon from the body of a 12-year-old girl in any way enhanced the national will to eject rascals from the White House would be stretching a point. You could do that. But it would be wrong.</p>
        <p>It was, however, undeniably a fairly hysterical time, and audiences' reactions to ''The Exorcist'' at the very least reflected something of the era's high-strung personality. There were reports that preview audiences were so upset by the film's blasphemies, obscenities and graphic physicalshocks that several viewers fled the theater, fainted and/or vomited. (As it turns out, the scene that evoked the strongest flight response was a long sequence of medical testing.) And although such reactions are perfectly valid critical comments on many movies, in the case of ''The Exorcist'' audience revulsion became a kind of selling point: people lined up for hours, braving the winter cold, to see little possessed Regan (Linda Blair) swivel her head 360 degrees, hurl her well-meaning mother across the room, belch profanities at anyone within earshot, crush the genitals of a psychiatrist, masturbate with a crucifix, and spew green liquid in the faces of unsuspecting Jesuits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN William Friedkin's ''Exorcist,'' based on William Peter Blatty's best-selling theological-horror novel, opened on Dec. 26, 1973, it was not only the movie event of the Christmas season that year; it also became the dominant pop-culture phenomenon of the final days of Richard M. Nixon's presidency. One wouldn't want to make too much of this: to suggest, for example, that Mr. Blatty's tale of the expulsion of a possessing demon from the body of a 12-year-old girl in any way enhanced the national will to eject rascals from the White House would be stretching a point. You could do that. But it would be wrong.</p>
        <p>It was, however, undeniably a fairly hysterical time, and audiences' reactions to ''The Exorcist'' at the very least reflected something of the era's high-strung personality. There were reports that preview audiences were so upset by the film's blasphemies, obscenities and graphic physicalshocks that several viewers fled the theater, fainted and/or vomited. (As it turns out, the scene that evoked the strongest flight response was a long sequence of medical testing.) And although such reactions are perfectly valid critical comments on many movies, in the case of ''The Exorcist'' audience revulsion became a kind of selling point: people lined up for hours, braving the winter cold, to see little possessed Regan (Linda Blair) swivel her head 360 degrees, hurl her well-meaning mother across the room, belch profanities at anyone within earshot, crush the genitals of a psychiatrist, masturbate with a crucifix, and spew green liquid in the faces of unsuspecting Jesuits.</p>
        <p>I have to confess that I did not stand in line for ''The Exorcist'' that winter but caught up to it later, when the fuss had died down. Because I was at that time living in a university dormitory, I really didn't need to go to the movies to see people vomiting and passing out. And the spectacle of clever priests drinking Scotch and wrestling with their faith had less exotic allure for me than it had for many members of the audience: I'd known Jesuits all my life, because my father taught at Brooklyn Prep, a Jesuit high school of which, as it happens, Mr. Blatty is an alumnus. When I finally saw the picture, the audience was clearly shaken, but the screening was medically uneventful.</p>
        <p>Now ''The Exorcist'' is back, in a new, longer version that Warner Brothers is releasing in theaters on Friday. Since the advent of home video, more and more films have been turning up on cassette and DVD in altered states designated as ''director's cuts.'' This edition of ''The Exorcist,'' however, appears to be essentially a writer-producer's cut: many of the additional scenes are those that Mr. Blatty has, over the years, loudly criticized Mr. Friedkin for excising. (The director had banished Mr. Blatty from the editing room because he was being, in his words, ''a pain.'')</p>
        <p>As recently as two years ago, when Mr. Friedkin and Mr. Blatty were interviewed for a BBC documentary (which is included on the 25th-anniversary ''Special Edition'' DVD), the director still believed that his cut of ''The Exorcist'' was ''as close to a perfect film as you can make,'' while the writer continued to argue that the movie's current ending left his story dangerously vulnerable to theological misinterpretation: for all these years, Mr. Blatty has been bugged by the knowledge that some viewers thought  the Devil had won.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Blatty has apparently worn Mr. Friedkin down. This new ''Exorcist'' restores the writer's preferred ending (which is also the final scene of the novel), an exchange of excruciating jocularities between a middle-aged police detective and a young Jesuit, in which we are given to understand that the spirit of the story's martyred hero, Father Damien Karras (Jason Miller) lives on. On this issue, Mr. Friedkin was right the first time. The scene was an embarrassment in the book, and it is immeasurably worse on the screen: Lee J. Cobb's grotesque performance as the detective italicizes every inanity. The triumph of the Devil isn't any more depressing than the idea that grown men might actually talk to each other the way this priest and this cop do.</p>
        <p>Other changes are trivial. There's a brief shot of Georgetown in Washington -- where the heroine, Chris MacNeil (Ellen Burstyn) and her satanically challenged daughter live -- inserted before the film's original opening sequence, in which the title character, the elderly archaeologist-priest Lankester Merrin (Max von Sydow), digs for evil in northern Iraq. The new beginning is inoffensive but useless, as are a handful of superimposed images of scary-monster heads that have been added to later, more horrific scenes in the MacNeil household: they are coals to Newcastle, or, if you will, priests to Georgetown.</p>
        <p>The longest restored sequence, an additional (earlier, less grisly) diagnostic scene, slightly improves the structural clarity of the narrative. And for horror-movie aficionados, the main attraction of the expanded ''Exorcist'' is undoubtedly the inclusion of the legendary (well, to some) ''spider walk'' -- i.e., the scene in which Regan skitters down a staircase on all fours, hands first and her body facing upward. It's a good, unnerving shock effect: whether the picture needs another of those is, I guess, a matter of taste.</p>
        <p>BY far the best thing about this ''Exorcist'' is that it makes a bit more room for Max von Sydow, arguably the planet's greatest living actor. Father Merrin is just a routinely brilliant supporting turn for him, and in a way this character is to von Sydow what Obi-Wan Kenobi was to Sir Alec Guinness: the role that the general audience would forever identify him most closely with. But the movie wouldn't work at all without his enormous, mysterious authority and grace. Mr. von Sydow's terse readings suggest the let's-get-it-done manner of an old spiritual gunslinger wearily cleaning up one more rotten town: he appears to be the one person involved in the movie who understands that it's not a theological parable but an exceptionally perverse western. The revised ''Exorcist'' gives him a few more scenes, and, though they're brief, anything that increases the amount of Max von Sydow in the world has to be considered a force for good.</p>
        <p>Like every powerful horror movie, ''The Exorcist'' gains from being seen on a big screen, with an audience primed to scream and talk back. No one should expect vomiting and fainting this time, though. Horror is mainstream entertainment now, and our collective tolerance for gore, obscenity and even invasive medical procedures is exponentially greater than it was in the Trickster era. Our gross-out threshold has risen as fast and as high as the stock market -- thanks largely, it should be said, to ''The Exorcist'' itself. Twenty-seven years ago, moviegoers stood in line to get queasy. We must have acquired a taste for it, because we haven't stopped yet.</p>
        <p>FILM Terrence Rafferty is the critic at large for GQ magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Terrence Rafferty is the critic at large for GQ magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
