<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Memory Vault Rich in Lore of the Stage</title>
    <meta content="17NESM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/arts/17NESM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231038"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nesmith, Nathaniel G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bentley, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2D81F39F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1420" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Memory Vault Rich in Lore of the Stage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts of conversation between Columbia University President's Fellow in theater Nathaniel G Nesmith and theater critic, playwright and Brecht translator Eric Bentley, 84; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ERIC BENTLEY, the eminent theater critic, playwright and Brecht translator, has cause for celebration: his 84th birthday (which was last Thursday) and the recent publication of a volume of his theater criticism, ''What Is Theater? 1944-1967'' (Hill &amp; Wang). Most of the essays in this portrait of New York theater, drawn mainly from the 1950's, appeared in The New Republic.</p>
        <p>Recently, Mr. Bentley and Nathaniel G. Nesmith, a President's Fellow in theater at Columbia University's Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, talked in Mr. Bentley's Manhattan apartment. Here are excerpts from their conversation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ERIC BENTLEY, the eminent theater critic, playwright and Brecht translator, has cause for celebration: his 84th birthday (which was last Thursday) and the recent publication of a volume of his theater criticism, ''What Is Theater? 1944-1967'' (Hill &amp; Wang). Most of the essays in this portrait of New York theater, drawn mainly from the 1950's, appeared in The New Republic.</p>
        <p>Recently, Mr. Bentley and Nathaniel G. Nesmith, a President's Fellow in theater at Columbia University's Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, talked in Mr. Bentley's Manhattan apartment. Here are excerpts from their conversation.</p>
        <p>NATHANIEL G. NESMITH -- Nowadays it is common for people to bemoan the death of the theater. Is the theater dying?</p>
        <p>ERIC BENTLEY -- ''The theater is dying'' is something that has been said over and over. If it is put as a question, the real meaning is whether mass communication (movies, television and radio) has killed off live theater. Up to now, the answer is resoundingly no. But who knows? Everyone today is talking about the Internet, the latest threat. Nothing is eternal. The drama is an art that may end sometime.</p>
        <p>If we are going to discuss it from an artistic point of view, I think there is something to the live theater that I would certainly work to preserve. When you are in the theater with a living actor, a kind of electric current is established between you and the actor. It has to be his presence. And, psychologically, this makes for a different experience for the audience.</p>
        <p>For example, acrobats on a high wire: if you see it on television, you just watch it. But if you are in the theater audience, you are wondering if they are going to fall off! You don't know the future. Now, that is a psychological factor that is present all the time. You are in the living present with a not totally certain future.</p>
        <p>NESMITH -- You studied with C. S. Lewis. What influence did he have on you?</p>
        <p>BENTLEY -- I was a student of his and I was his assistant. When he was sick, I replaced him. I took over his students after I graduated. There was much more distance between the teacher and the pupil in England than in America. Although he did not put on airs, I always revered him as if he were a bishop.</p>
        <p>He was very important to me beyond anything academic in that he gave me confidence and self-esteem when I didn't have it. He did it in a particularly subtle way. It began by him criticizing me devastatingly. I felt even less self-respect. Then he talked some more and helped me very much.</p>
        <p>I wrote a very pretentious paper. (When you are young and ambitious, you get beyond yourself trying to sound profound and big.) At Oxford, you have the wonderfully privileged system of having the teacher's attention alone for an hour. You read your stuff to him. He takes notes or interrupts.</p>
        <p>He didn't interrupt on this particular occasion. When it was over, there was a pause. He said, ''It makes my head swim.'' I asked what was the main trouble. He mentioned one or two passages. And then he asked what one sentence meant. He picked one of the worst sentences. To show you how naive I was, I said: ''I lifted that from another critic. I didn't understand it, sir, but I thought you would.''</p>
        <p>He laughed and said, ''Well, I don't.''</p>
        <p>I asked if any passages were better. He said yes. Then I asked if any passages were really good. He said one or two. I asked if he would tell me which ones because I really didn't know. He got his notes and said the passage about so and so. I asked if that was really good. He said: ''Yes, that was interesting. I started to listen and wanted to argue with you.'' I said that was only me talking. He said to continue to talk and ignore those other voices.</p>
        <p>Lewis persuaded me that I was worth listening to. I asked him not to encourage or flatter me because it would do a great deal of harm. I said, ''If you are telling me that this is really good, I want to know if you really believe that.''</p>
        <p>Our aim at Oxford was to get First Class Honors in the degree, which is difficult to get. I was working hard on it. He said to me, ''If you don't get a First, I don't know who would.'' I asked if he really believed that. (I didn't feel that I would get it, though I did, as it turned out.) He said, ''Certainly I believe that.''</p>
        <p>NESMITH -- What is your fondest theater memory?</p>
        <p>BENTLEY -- Well, I don't have one. Among the fondest memories is the first Shakespeare I saw performed with top actors. That would be John Gielgud in ''Hamlet'' and ''Romeo and Juliet.'' Peggy Ashcroft was Juliet. It was somewhere in the middle 1930's, when I was a high school student. Those were revelations of what the theater is, what acting is and what Shakespeare is -- everything together in the simplest way.</p>
        <p>Gielgud was at that time an independent actor, with none of these fancy modern interpretations put on Shakespeare. I felt I was getting the pure Shakespearean article by a man who knew how to speak it and act it. It was so moving. Even though it was long ago, I can still see images of particular moments. For example: I was wondering how he was going to do ''To be or not to be.'' We had all read ''Hamlet.'' He did it so you had to lip-read. He did it without his voice. He knew all the high schools kids were out front waiting for it. I don't know if he did that every time, but he sure did it for us.</p>
        <p>Later on, it was going to Berlin and seeing ''Mother Courage'' in the ruins of Berlin, directed by Brecht. There can be no recapturing a moment like that because it wasn't just the play but the fact that it was done in Berlin, at that moment in time, for that audience. It was overpowering. For a dramatist who used to pretend that he didn't want to arouse emotions, it was an overwhelmingly emotional occasion.</p>
        <p>NESMITH -- Your worst memory?</p>
        <p>BENTLEY -- The worst is forgotten, I think. But when I see one of my own plays badly done or misunderstood, it is really painful. I would like to walk out but I can't because I am the guest or something. I have the helpless feeling that I am sitting at my own funeral. Sitting and seeing one of your own plays being done badly is one of the most unbearable things in life. Particularly if you think your play is pretty good.</p>
        <p>NESMITH -- Of all the roles you have achieved -- critic, scholar, educator, director, translator, actor, playwright -- is there one for which you would most like to be remembered?</p>
        <p>BENTLEY -- I have published a lot of things, many volumes. If you look at writers in the past, even some of the greatest -- Voltaire, for instance -- his collected works in the library fill several huge shelves. Yet all that is read is ''Candide'' and one or two other short things. A man who published thousands of influential pages, he survives by a couple of hundred pages.</p>
        <p>If I am to survive at all, if people read me when I am dead, I would like to be remembered by one of my plays -- though I don't know which one.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
