<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Detective Tale Involving a Town's Birth, the Clue Was Framed</title>
    <meta content="17MAP.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231170"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE MAP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlantic Highlands (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boyd, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nash, Margo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E0DF1338F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Detective Tale Involving a Town's Birth, the Clue Was Framed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGO NASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nash, Margo</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paul Boyd, historian and chairman of Atlantic Highlands Environmental Commission, answers questions about his quest to confirm site of original settlement of New Jersey town; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Dec. 14, 1667, the first Europeans to settle in what is today  Atlantic Highlands decided to lay out 10 lots in an area they called  Portland Poynt on the Navesink peninsula. They wrote their decision on a deed: ''The  Lotts on Portland Poynt being unto No. 10 are layed out and are in breadth twenty pls [poles] each Lott, and run up from the banck into the woods upon A strait line W. &amp; N. with corner as the land is good, about 60 to 70 poles.'' The deed also stated there was a swamp nearby.  But where had these lots been? Paul Boyd, a Ph.D. candidate in cultural geography at Rutgers University who is the historian of the Atlantic Highlands Historical Society and  chairman of the Atlantic Highlands Environmental Commission, worked on the problem for five years. He recently spoke about a breakthrough featuring an old painting.</p>
        <p>Q. Who were the first European settlers in the area?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Dec. 14, 1667, the first Europeans to settle in what is today  Atlantic Highlands decided to lay out 10 lots in an area they called  Portland Poynt on the Navesink peninsula. They wrote their decision on a deed: ''The  Lotts on Portland Poynt being unto No. 10 are layed out and are in breadth twenty pls [poles] each Lott, and run up from the banck into the woods upon A strait line W. &amp; N. with corner as the land is good, about 60 to 70 poles.'' The deed also stated there was a swamp nearby.  But where had these lots been? Paul Boyd, a Ph.D. candidate in cultural geography at Rutgers University who is the historian of the Atlantic Highlands Historical Society and  chairman of the Atlantic Highlands Environmental Commission, worked on the problem for five years. He recently spoke about a breakthrough featuring an old painting.</p>
        <p>Q. Who were the first European settlers in the area?</p>
        <p>A. They were English. They first came to scout out the area in December 1663. It was part of the Dutch empire, but the Dutch had done nothing to build or stay here. They were traders. The first English settlers  knew the English government was going to come and boot out the Dutch. So they began to realize there were opportunities here.</p>
        <p>Q. How did you try to find the location of the first lots?</p>
        <p>A. The literature I went to assumed the town grew like other towns, and that the commercial center that is here now was the heart of the original town. But this was just an assumption. I asked myself what's the proof? First I went back to the archive in Monmouth Country in Manalapan and looked at the deed, a manuscript hand-written on vellum. The text was faded and it was fuzzy. So I looked at the neighboring pages for documents made by the same hand with letters that were clearer. By the time I finished I had filled in the gaps. But it was written in Old English and used old measures like poles, not yards or feet or acres, and you have to interpret that. ''Into the woods'' -- what woods? ''Straight line west and north''-- how does a  straight line go west and north? All  those items I played with almost like a jigsaw puzzle until they fit.</p>
        <p>Q. Where was original settlement?</p>
        <p>A. I believed it was along the west bank of the Many Mind Creek, a creek that changes directions, which is why people called it that. The commercial center of today is two blocks east of the settlement.</p>
        <p>Q. But you were not absolutely sure until you saw it in a painting?</p>
        <p>A. Yes. In October of last year I had an epiphany. There is an 1879 painting in the Strauss Mansion Museum, our historical society headquarters in Atlantic Highlands, which shows the landscape looking north toward the central lowlands of today's town and the bay beyond. There are tree-bordered fields west of the Many Mind Creek which seem to echo the lots as I worked them out. The trees were obviously planted on the borders of the farm fields to mark  where the borders were. I had not looked that closely at it before, but then it clicked after I had written out my interpretations. There was also a swamp in the painting formed by the Many Mind Creek, a swamp that has since been filled. But at first it's hard to tell it was a swamp, because the painting had been done to promote the development of the town and the artist had tried to make the swamp look like a lake.</p>
        <p>Q. What does your discovery mean?</p>
        <p>A. If you know what you came from, you can figure out how we got there  and where we are going. So the people with wet basements now know: ''Oh, my house is where the swamp was.'' In other words, if you go from swamp to swank, you won't forget all about the swamp.</p>
        <p>MARGO NASH</p>
        <p>ON THE MAP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
