<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reeling In Syosset's Catch of the Day</title>
    <meta content="17DINE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001001T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coolfish (Syosset, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEEDE1538F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reeling In Syosset's Catch of the Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews Coolfish restaurant in Syosset, Long Island; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHALK up another success for Tom Schaudel. Both the sign at the door and the business cards of Coolfish, his new restaurant in Syosset, accurately proclaim ''It's hot.'' Mr. Schaudel, one of the Island's most enterprising chefs, currently owns Lemongrass in Roslyn, Maxwell's in Garden City and now Coolfish. This latest venture replaces 107 Ocean Bistro, his Locust Valley restaurant that closed earlier this year, and like its predecessor, it showcases seafood.</p>
        <p>Coolfish is hidden in an office complex off Jericho Turnpike. Still, crowds are finding it; it was virtually full every time I visited, no matter what night of the week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHALK up another success for Tom Schaudel. Both the sign at the door and the business cards of Coolfish, his new restaurant in Syosset, accurately proclaim ''It's hot.'' Mr. Schaudel, one of the Island's most enterprising chefs, currently owns Lemongrass in Roslyn, Maxwell's in Garden City and now Coolfish. This latest venture replaces 107 Ocean Bistro, his Locust Valley restaurant that closed earlier this year, and like its predecessor, it showcases seafood.</p>
        <p>Coolfish is hidden in an office complex off Jericho Turnpike. Still, crowds are finding it; it was virtually full every time I visited, no matter what night of the week.</p>
        <p>Coolfish is about twice the size of 107 Ocean Bistro, and patrons nod their approval as they are led into the striking room. There's lots of brick, along with burnt umber walls, skylights and enough hanging fish and fish sculptures to put across the restaurant's theme. There are also large black-and-white photographs of Long Island scenes, including one of Mr. Schaudel at an East End vineyard.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schaudel is a creative chef who molds his components -- top-quality meats and fish, precise cooking and exotic accompaniments -- into a menu filled with arresting flavors. Witness the Asian smoked ostrich salad: thin slices of rosy meat with mango, fresh soybeans and greens in a red ginger vinaigrette.  The watercress salad glossed with a sherry vinaigrette and ringed with seared diver scallops and black mission figs was equally good.</p>
        <p>Another appetizer, a special one night, that hit the mark was seared foie gras paired with a grilled peach and a peach-and-date conserve. Unfortunately, the two quarter-size medallions of liver were disappointingly skimpy.</p>
        <p>Other appetizers that create some excitement were the crisp barbecued pulled pork quesadilla, the Portuguese fish soup (reminiscent of a very tasty Manhattan clam chowder) and the steamed Prince Edward Island mussels. The last arrived in a covered bowl (the lid becomes a receptacle for shells) filled with a dynamite Thai red curry, lime and coconut milk broth.</p>
        <p>There were a couple of misses in the grilled pizza and pasta category.  Goat cheese tortelloni boasted a delicious roasted tomato sauce with basil and olives, but the melted cheese was grainy and unpleasant.  The duck prosciutto pizza with provolone, caramelized onions and asparagus got high marks for its toppings, but the crust lacked the chewy texture pizza lovers expect.</p>
        <p>Every fish and meat entree was an unqualified success. I loved the Chilean sea bass with lobster sauce, sauteed spinach and smoked tomato relish. Also receiving applause were the oven-roasted striped bass set over mashed potatoes with a lobster, corn and soybean succotash and the grilled salmon atop an arresting summer pesto risotto.</p>
        <p>Meats also boasted a trio of hits: a perfectly cooked sirloin crowned with crisp onion rings and served with pancetta and scallion-dotted mashed potatoes; a moist pork chop in a cinnamon and chipotle marinade; and terrific grilled chicken over a flavor-packed bed of farro, a grain the size and consistency of barley.</p>
        <p>Desserts are wonderful. Who could resist the chocolate bag, a banana split in chocolate molded in the shape of paper bag? This dish, originated at Dave's Grill, put Montauk on the culinary map. Other top choices are the warm upside-down apple tart with caramel sauce, ice cream and whipped cream; the maple bread pudding with buttermilk ice cream and walnut-maple crunch custard; and the airy Key lime pie with a a ginger-snap crust garnished with whipped creme fraiche and a ginger-blackberry compote.</p>
        <p>Noise is a problem when the restaurant is full (and it nearly always is). The volume rises as neighboring diners talk louder to be heard, causing a spiraling cacophony.</p>
        <p>The service staff at 107 Ocean Bistro displayed a winning combination of youthful enthusiasm and professional efficiency. Coolfish's staff has not attained that level of performance. One evening our elusive waiter was very hard to flag down. Runners delivering dishes were confused at every course. Another night those speedy fellows had everything down pat, and our waitress was attentive -- at first. But even she got bogged down when the restaurant filled.</p>
        <p>Coolfish  6800 Jericho Turnpike, Syosset, (516) 921-3250.  Very Good  ATMOSPHERE -- Attractive seafood spot.  SERVICE -- Erratic. Stumbles when restaurant is full.  SOUND LEVEL -- Loud when crowded.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Smoked ostrich salad, watercress salad with scallops and figs, pulled pork quesadilla, steamed mussels, Portuguese fish soup, Chilean sea bass, striped bass. Grilled salmon, chicken, sirloin and pork chop. All desserts.  WINE LIST -- A multinational selection of nearly 200 bottles, with prices from t $19 to nearly $700.  PRICE RANGE -- Lunch entrees $7 to $13. At dinner, appetizers $5 to $13, pizzas and pastas $12 to $18, entrees $16 to $24, desserts $6 to $8.  CREDIT CARDS -- All major cards.  HOURS -- 11:30 a.m. to 8 p.m. Monday through Thursday, to 10 p.m. Friday, 5:30 to 10 p.m. Saturday and 5:30 to 8:30 p.m. Sunday.  RESERVATIONS -- A must.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY -- Eight steps at entrance.</p>
        <p>THE RATINGS Extraordinary, Excellent, Very Good, Good, Poor to Satisfactory.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambiance and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT E-mail: lidining@nytimes.com</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 1, 2000, Sunday  The Dining Out column on Sept. 17, about Coolfish, a new restaurant in Syosset, misstated its hours. They are 11:30 a.m. to 10 p.m. Monday through Thursday; to 11 p.m. on Friday; 5 p.m. to 11 p.m. on Saturday;  and 5 p.m. to 9 p.m. on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 1, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Dining Out column on Sept. 17, about Coolfish, a new restaurant in Syosset, misstated its hours. They are 11:30 a.m. to 10 p.m. Monday through Thursday; to 11 p.m. on Friday; 5 p.m. to 11 p.m. on Saturday;  and 5 p.m. to 9 p.m. on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lidining@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
