<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Fashion Show to Chamber Music</title>
    <meta content="17JON.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231290"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anthony, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">La Ferla, Ruth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E6D71038F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1310" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Fashion Show to Chamber Music</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RUTH LA FERLA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">La Ferla, Ruth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elegant scene at John Anthony's haute couture show for fall and winter at Peggy Guggenheim's former town house in Manhattan, accompanied by chamber orchestra, described; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was the archetypal fashion show: guests perched on the edge of their white-lacquered chairs, craning to catch every nuance of the dresses about to drift into their midst. Seated front row center, Pauline Trigere peered intently at the procession of black cocktail dresses swaying to the accompaniment of ''Begin the Beguine.''</p>
        <p>The scene was John Anthony's haute couture show for fall and winter, a conspicuously genteel event staged last Wednesday afternoon at Peggy Guggenheim's former town house on East 61st Street. With its dove-gray walls, chandeliers and sconces, and a chamber orchestra discreetly tucked into one corner, the setting transported visitors to a time as distant in spirit as it was in location from the frenzy of Fashion Week in Midtown, where most American designers are now showing ready-to-wear collections for spring 2001.  Sounding a bit wistful, Pamela Fiori, the editor in chief of Town &amp; Country, said, ''I felt like I was back in the 50's.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was the archetypal fashion show: guests perched on the edge of their white-lacquered chairs, craning to catch every nuance of the dresses about to drift into their midst. Seated front row center, Pauline Trigere peered intently at the procession of black cocktail dresses swaying to the accompaniment of ''Begin the Beguine.''</p>
        <p>The scene was John Anthony's haute couture show for fall and winter, a conspicuously genteel event staged last Wednesday afternoon at Peggy Guggenheim's former town house on East 61st Street. With its dove-gray walls, chandeliers and sconces, and a chamber orchestra discreetly tucked into one corner, the setting transported visitors to a time as distant in spirit as it was in location from the frenzy of Fashion Week in Midtown, where most American designers are now showing ready-to-wear collections for spring 2001.  Sounding a bit wistful, Pamela Fiori, the editor in chief of Town &amp; Country, said, ''I felt like I was back in the 50's.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Anthony will doubtless love hearing that. Since abandoning Seventh Avenue in the mid-1980's to establish his couture house in a basement atelier on East 66th Street, the designer has strenuously cultivated the manner and the trappings of the Avenue Montaigne, the home of $50,000 handmade gowns in Paris. It is a posture that would be easy to mock, had fashion not so recently come back around to Mr. Anthony's point of view.</p>
        <p>Seated on a slipper chair the morning after the show, Mr. Anthony, who gives his age as 62, said in a voice like unguent, ''It's not me that's different; it's the times.''</p>
        <p>As he well knows, he is playing these days to an audience obsessed with the Stork Club set, the swells and debs of the 1940's and 50's. Fawningly portrayed in a spate of recent films, books and exhibitions, they have been represented on the runway by pointy shoes and tippets, pearls and fat fox stoles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Anthony has benefited from a flourishing economy. ''Women are dressing up -- some of my clients are out every night,'' he exulted. Others, he knows, are busily introducing their friends to the designer so that they too can indulge in the voluptuous ritual of having a dress made and fitted by hand.</p>
        <p>The day after the show, Mr. Anthony, who has built his business on  word of mouth and advertises primarily in Town &amp; Country, was startled by an unaccustomed flurry of attention. ''We must have had a dozen calls from clients, and it's not 12 o'clock,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In any given year Mr. Anthony sees about 150 clients, he said, some young mothers, others in their 80's, who visit once or several times a season, and drop from $5,000 for a suit to hundreds of thousands of dollars for a 25-piece wardrobe.</p>
        <p>Though his patrons have remained steadfast over the years, there were times, he confided, when he couldn't afford new fabrics to dress them.  After introducing a ready-to-wear label in the early 70's, and cementing a reputation as one of New York's premier fashion makers, Mr. Anthony abruptly left Seventh Avenue in 1984. ''The kind of work I was doing wasn't going anywhere,'' he said of his understated coats and suits, which were supplanted in the stores by racier fare. After a year, he opened his couture house, attracting a trickle of patrons, whose numbers have swollen over time.</p>
        <p>''Look, I'm still here,'' he said the other day, clearly relishing his role as a member of a vanishing breed.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fiori said, ''John may be America's last couturier.'' Placing him on a lofty plane with James Galanos and Ms. Trigere, she added, ''People say he's got an old-fashioned attitude, but every one of his looks, if you saw them on the runways of Saint Laurent, Dior or Badgley Mischka, people would be standing up and applauding.''</p>
        <p>That is probably an exaggeration; editors from the major fashion publications generally skip Mr. Anthony's shows. The fact that over the years he has kept to his own measured pace, showing hyperfastidious cashmere coats and luncheon suits when other designers were selling blatant sex, has cost him. ''He was overlooked,'' said Caroline H. Newhouse, the widow of Theodore Newhouse, a founder of Advance Publications, and at 90 a longtime client. ''I knew all the great designers,'' added Mrs. Newhouse, maintaining that Mr. Anthony is due for a reappraisal.</p>
        <p>As chance would have it, the designer's lavish get-ups are in sync with the current trend for luxury and flamboyant glamour. Especially for evening, Mr. Anthony doesn't stint on sumptuous fabrics and details. Dressed in his workday uniform of a black cashmere sweater the day after the show, he sauntered into his studio, making straight for a brown satin toggle coat. Its opulent fabric and incongruously sporty design make it an exemplar of the offhand luxury that has long defined great American sportswear.</p>
        <p>Talking a visitor through the collection -- 30 looks wrought in cashmere, wool, satin and tulle -- is something he has done so many times he seems to be spoofing himself. He paused, parting the folds of a moire evening coat to show off its magenta lining. ''I love magenta,'' he said. ''It's so Pentecost.''</p>
        <p>Tugging at the sleeve of a characteristically understated wool and cashmere topper, he noted puckishly, ''This is very John Anthony, don't you think?''</p>
        <p>Also very John Anthony are a profusion of coats and suits by other, better known designers splashed in the pages of this month's Vogue -- all conspicuous, if sometimes unwitting homages to the high-bred style of Mr. Anthony and his contemporaries, designers like Bill Blass, Geoffrey Beene and Ms. Trigere.</p>
        <p>One suspects that Michael Kors and John Bartlett, who have obviously studied the cuts, fabrics and proportions of these Seventh Avenue masters, might like to slip into the couturier's studio to pore over every meticulous dart and seam.</p>
        <p>Unlike most members of fashion's younger generation, Mr. Anthony dishes up his movie star confections without a trace of irony. Not that his clients mind. Just after the show, Catherine Wells-Debs, a San Francisco social figure, snapped up the most outrageously theatrical piece in the designer's collection, a pink satin coat with a big sable collar.</p>
        <p>Melissa McNair, a client in her early 30's from Fort Worth, Tex., was in town last week to be fitted for six pieces, including a backless black satin cocktail dress. She seems to get an erotic tingle out of personal fittings. ''Everything is sewn right on your body,'' she said. Her husband, an investment banker, ''finds these clothes very sexy,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''Sexy -- I don't like the word,'' Mr. Anthony demurred privately with a curl of the lip. ''Sex is for the bedroom. I prefer glamour. Between sex and glamour, there's a razor's edge.''</p>
        <p>''My clothes have those wonderful small shoulders; they're very tight, very close to the body,'' he added,  running his hands suggestively over his waist and hips.</p>
        <p>For the most part, though, Mr. Anthony's designs recall a more decorous era. Thrusting a microphone toward Mr. Anthony, Lauren Ezersky, who was covering the show for the Style Network, posed a demure question: ''Where do you find the length of a dress?''</p>
        <p>Afterward, Mr. Anthony all but snorted, ''Who asks questions today about hemlines?'' But he had to concede there was something sweet about that query. ''It comes from a time when there were rules,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
