<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fancy Fiddling</title>
    <meta content="17DINE$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231174"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Soho On George (New Brunswick, Nj, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Catherine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4DE1338F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1145" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fancy Fiddling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHERINE JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Catherine</byline>
      <dateline>NEW BRUNSWICK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Catherine Jones reviews Soho on George restaurant in New Brunswick, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GRILLED fare has always struck a chord with me. Hamburgers just aren't the same out of a pan -- and they're even tastier on a grilled rather than toasted bun.</p>
        <p>When it comes to grilling, some of us go far beyond the standard ingredients. Ever tried grilled whole scallions? Cornmeal pizza? How about making cooled chocolate chip cookies gooey again on a grill top? Grilled cheese can be downright elegant if the name is taken literally.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GRILLED fare has always struck a chord with me. Hamburgers just aren't the same out of a pan -- and they're even tastier on a grilled rather than toasted bun.</p>
        <p>When it comes to grilling, some of us go far beyond the standard ingredients. Ever tried grilled whole scallions? Cornmeal pizza? How about making cooled chocolate chip cookies gooey again on a grill top? Grilled cheese can be downright elegant if the name is taken literally.</p>
        <p>While I do love my grilled pound cake, I'm aware that there are limits. My wallet certainly remembers losing six perfectly good lobsters to the cause. But bite after rubbery bite, I knew I would find a kindred spirit one day, someone who would come up with a spectacular grilled item that even I had never considered.</p>
        <p>I think I have: Bruce Courtright and grilled watermelon.</p>
        <p>Both can be found at Soho on George in New Brunswick. Mr. Courtright, assisted by Doug Gough, has been creating masterpieces in the restaurant's open kitchen since it opened two years ago. His training, which includes La Varenne in France, Grove in Manhattan and Twenty Eight in Montclair, obviously gave him the confidence to experiment and let the winners emerge.</p>
        <p>The appetizer that incorporates grilled melon is certainly one. Tender Thai hanger steak, marinated in Omengang Belgian-style beer, fans one edge. Juicy triangles of red and yellow seedless watermelon, macerated in a sugar syrup redolent of red pepper flakes and mint, line the other. A scattering of red onion adds crunch, and a tiny scoop of spicy white peppercorn-infused vanilla ice cream gives each bite a final kick. Unusual? You bet. Tasty? That grill-marked melon disappeared quickly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Courtright is capable of working wonders without his trusty grill, too. Pan-seared gravlax-style salmon had a stiff seared edge encasing a luxuriously soft interior. Redolent of salt, sugar and aquavit, this classic Danish dish sat atop a roasted peach and basil compote accompanied by a cornbread pudding. Lobster, artichoke and potato pirogi surrounded a warm fingerling potato salad, studded with pancetta rather than bacon and garnished with a hearty dollop of lobster creme fraiche. A stuffed leg of rabbit towered above a cloudlike gathering of garlic and rosemary gnocchi. An encircling sauce, made from roasted corn and Pineau des Charentes (a white dessert wine), brought out the flavors of the chicken mousse, prosciutto and spinach filling. The chilled vegetable terrine, layered with summer's bounty and bound in a sunny tomato aspic, was utterly refreshing, especially when paired with warm Israeli couscous.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, the salads are equally endearing. I enjoyed the dressing on the spinach salad, made from tarragon clabber cream thinned with poached pear juices. The textural toppings were a further delight: slivered goat cheddar, sweet grilled red onions, toasted hazelnuts and tiny cubes of pear -- how many versions did it take to get to this level of perfection? The marinated tomato salad was equally memorable, served over baby arugula and a green scallion coulis, and surrounded by fried rounds of breaded Manchego cheese.</p>
        <p>My companion had never eaten ostrich, and Soho on George seemed like a good place for a first sampling. Chopped and sauteed wild mushrooms hugged the tender meat's exterior, bound by a thin, clear flavorful netting of caul fat. Mr. Court right's gnocchi made another appearance, this time flavored with mushrooms to go with the fresh summer truffles and black truffle butter. In all this woodland luxury, I was still able to notice the nectarine gastrique, a sauce loosely based on caramel but hit with a dose of citrus and star anise.</p>
        <p>The halibut special also succeeded at incorporating many flavors and ingredients. A ragout of baby vegetables (baby pattypan squash, carrots, pearl onions and shiitakes) tumbled down from a section of roasted butternut squash into a steaming mound of amaranth. Many steer clear of amaranth, the world's smallest grain, leery of overcooking. But Mr. Courtright proudly served it, simmered in a mixture of chicken stock and port, as the perfect foil to halibut in a saffron fumet beurre blanc.</p>
        <p>I have no worries that certain entrees will improve over time, given Mr. Courtright's penchance for fiddling. Pan-roasted rack of lamb, over a sweet potato and sour cherry compote and finely diced ''micro'' ratatouille, is either ahead of its season or is missing a needed texture or ingredient. Orange-braised lobster, served over a crispy spinach noodle cake, is set in a sauce so buttery that the fava beans, corn kernels and almonds lost their identities. Finally, the pan-seared breast and stewed leg of duck, both tender and succulent, were paired with sweet vegetables prepared with Moroccan seasonings and an even sweeter jus, resulting in the kind of combination that's immediately filling rather than tempting.</p>
        <p>EVERYONE seems to have fun with desserts, made by the equally inventive Duane Hendershot. Having spent most of my meal keenly focused on just my table, I looked up at the sleekly modern room to see servers sliding sugar sticks into butterscotch cappuccino mug handles and topping ice cream soda lattes with spirals of whipped cream. The ''soda fountain favorites'' were a favorite of mine: a miniature rendition of a root beer float in a little chocolate cup with a chocolate straw, an ice cream sandwich on a mint cookie and a banana split cake. Again, some combinations need further development; the rice pudding parfait, orange pound cake and the white chocolate raspberry-almond brownie are all a bit cluttered at present. ''Cookies on the go,'' which come in a box you can choose to take home, is a cute idea, but it might be more appealing if the cookies weren't so stiff from the start.</p>
        <p>But bring me as many peach cobblers as you'd like. It's the perfect dessert to end a meal started by the grill, as well as a fitting toast to the end of summer.</p>
        <p>Soho on George  335 George Street, New Brunswick  (732) 296-0533  VERY GOOD  SERVICE -- Helpful, attentive and friendly.  ATMOSPHERE -- Verging on futuristic.  SMOKING -- Allowed in the bar area.  WINE LIST -- Many expensive, small production wines.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Pan-seared salmon, potato pirogi, stuffed leg of rabbit, chilled vegetable terrine, Thai hanger steak, spinach salad, tomato salad, ostrich, halibut, peach cobbler, soda fountain favorites, ice cream soda latte, butterscotch and English toffee cappuccino.  PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers: $7 to $13; salads: $6 to $9; entrees: $18 to $26; desserts: $7.50 to $12.  CREDIT CARDS -- All major.  RESERVATIONS -- Recommended.  HOURS -- Lunch: Mondays through Fridays, 11:30 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Dinner nightly  5 to 11 p.m. Sundays 4 to 10 p.m.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Fully accessible.  RATINGS -- Poor, Fair, Satisfactory, Good, Very Good, Excellent, Extraordinary.  Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
