<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blurring Distinctions Between Real and Artificial</title>
    <meta content="17ART.$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231094"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Braff, Phyllis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sherman, Cindy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Black, Jappie King</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nolan, Janet</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Villiers, Jephan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6D61438F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blurring Distinctions Between Real and Artificial</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phyllis Braff</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Braff, Phyllis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Phyllis Braff reviews works by photographer Cindy Sherman at Glenn Horowitz Bookseller, East Hampton, Long Island, three-dimensional installations by Jappie King Black and Janet Nolan at Nese Alpan Gallery in Roslyn and works by Brussels-based artist Jephan de Villiers at Roseline Koener Gallery in Westhampton Beach; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cindy Sherman: Early Work  Glenn Horowitz Bookseller, 87 Newtown Lane, East Hampton. Through Oct. 1. (631) 324-5511.</p>
        <p>Over the past two decades, Cindy Sherman's photography and reputation have become familiar to museum and gallery visitors worldwide. Her fictional portraits, based on herself in disguise, refer to widely known subjects and blur distinctions between the real and the artificial. The work has triggered stimulating discussions about fluid definitions of identity and has been a major influence on the new wave of artists who stage themes for the camera.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cindy Sherman: Early Work  Glenn Horowitz Bookseller, 87 Newtown Lane, East Hampton. Through Oct. 1. (631) 324-5511.</p>
        <p>Over the past two decades, Cindy Sherman's photography and reputation have become familiar to museum and gallery visitors worldwide. Her fictional portraits, based on herself in disguise, refer to widely known subjects and blur distinctions between the real and the artificial. The work has triggered stimulating discussions about fluid definitions of identity and has been a major influence on the new wave of artists who stage themes for the camera.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, when the Museum of Modern Art exhibited its newly acquired series by Ms. Sherman, known as the ''Untitled Film Stills'' (1977-1980), the 69 images were widely studied as the first phase of an important career. The artist was 23 when she began photographing herself in appropriated female movie roles. There was a recognition of common things, as in Pop Art, but the subject was the issue of role playing at many levels.</p>
        <p>A major precedent for this body of work is being exhibited for the first time. The 32 examples on view date from 1976, just after Ms. Sherman finished art school. There are two series, ''Bus Riders'' and ''Murder Mystery People.''</p>
        <p>Unlike the ''Film Stills,'' which concentrate on the iconic nature of movie actresses and on a variety of dramatic settings, the earlier work shows Ms. Sherman adopting both male and female personas and isolating each against the same segment of empty wall. A light socket at left center remains constant and the line to the camera's shutter snakes across the same four horizontal floor boards in each composition.</p>
        <p>The repetition in backdrop immediately announces the artifice involved. The emphasis is always on the posturing, pretense and idea of fiction. The awareness that each figure is the same person raises questions about the authenticity of the implied narrative.</p>
        <p>There is a heightened awareness of devices, too, in this panorama of wigs, props and type-casting garments and poses.</p>
        <p>Black/Nolan  Nese Alpan Gallery, 1499 Northern Boulevard, Roslyn. Through Sept. 23. (516) 484-7238.</p>
        <p>Installation projects most often create three-dimensional situations. Both Jappie King Black and Janet Nolan, in independent projects, have taken the next step and have treated the entire gallery space, including the ceiling, as part of their orbit. While the two projects are quite different, and each artist has her own goals, the characteristics of vines contribute to the mood established in both instances.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nolan's assertive but fanciful ''Glove-Winged Blackbirds'' envelopes the visitor in cascades of soaring, transformed gloves with fingers that seem to flutter in a make-believe breeze. Most have been helped into their pseudo-magical role with a heavy, uniform coating of paint. A strong green tone predominates, but the highest flying clusters are black with gold tips. Each glove calls attention to its specific gesture.</p>
        <p>Like many of Ms. Nolan's sculpture installations in the past 25 years, this project is based on discarded objects. Using recognizable articles with a history minimizes tendencies to consider the work whimsical. More important, the gloves furnish an anchor to reality and make the stretch to the metaphor of a flying creature more resonant.</p>
        <p>Dried grapevines are a principal material for Ms. Black, who develops a range of effects in her varied articulations of wall, floor and window areas. There are comparatively mammoth configurations of twisted, occasionally brightly colored strands that could suggest imaginary cities and there are many rather minute forms that recall objects made for divination purposes.</p>
        <p>At times the emphasis is on the stringy, unraveling properties of vine clusters and the linear action they can invent. One large area seems to celebrate the rich density and complexity of wild, tangled streamers and threads.</p>
        <p>At other times, the fiber has been used to make individual, well-defined shapes that are arranged to look like collections of specimens. Some shapes have eye openings and seem anthropomorphic. There are hints of ritual and symbolism, too. The strongest associations are with earlier societies that make pieces from and about nature.</p>
        <p>Jephan de Villiers  Roseline Koener Gallery, 88 Main Street, Westhampton Beach. Through Oct. 9. (631) 288-1017.</p>
        <p>While visiting eastern Long Island last year, the Brussels-based artist Jephan de Villiers collected driftwood, seashells and horseshoe crabs to add to the collections of bird feathers and dried forest debris that have long been components of his sculpture and assemblages.</p>
        <p>The local shoreline material has a featured role in this new group of tightly patterned compositions that emphasize texture, contour and the harmony the artist imposes on rough, disparate elements. He builds in a certain tension between the innate freedom in nature and the precision of his schemes. Several examples pile and compress shell fragments with a density that produces flickering light reflections and abstract configurations. Less weighted with symbolism, they introduce a welcome freshness.</p>
        <p>When formal placements dominate, the work has links to ceremonial uses of natural materials. Where moonlike faces emerge, a bit of sorcery is implied.</p>
        <p>Mr. de Villiers augments his goal of finding energy in the debris of forest and sea with surface markings loosely related to hieroglyphics  These are strong visual additions and suit the mood of collective memory and universality. A number of the most effective examples build exclusively on the spirited, gestural strokes. They belong partly to the realm of communication, and partly to the realm of evocative design.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
