<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pleasant Surprise: Anemones in the Fall</title>
    <meta content="17WGARMT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231235"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DB1038F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pleasant Surprise: Anemones in the Fall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH GINSBURG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU don't see the fall-blooming Japanese anemones (Anemone Japonica) in every garden, but you do see them in a lot of interesting gardens. One such place is a little butterfly garden tucked beside an elementary school near my house. A local designer, who is noted for her lush layouts, sense of history and stellar plant selections designed the plot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU don't see the fall-blooming Japanese anemones (Anemone Japonica) in every garden, but you do see them in a lot of interesting gardens. One such place is a little butterfly garden tucked beside an elementary school near my house. A local designer, who is noted for her lush layouts, sense of history and stellar plant selections designed the plot.</p>
        <p>As I walked by the other day, I noticed a tall white anemon, its delicate single flowers standing high above a whorl of dark green leaves. As benfits a plant that grows to be 2 to 3 feet tall, the anemone was at the back of the bed of shorter specimens. It faced south, but I am sure at some times of the day it is shaded by the neighboring butterfly bushes. The anemone was a pleasant surprise, perfect there at this time of year.</p>
        <p>The most surprising thing about fall-blooming anemones is their color. At a time of year when the landscape is full of gold, burgundy and russet, anemones blossom in shades of pink or white. The petals are usually daisy-like, and a mass of golden stamens brightens the center of each flower head.</p>
        <p>The second most surprising thing about these anemones is that they don't mind partial shade. A few days ago I saw a flourishing clump that was sited on the east side of a house, partially shaded by the overhanging eves. The stalks were full of buds and the plant was obivously doing very nicely with little more that a few hours of morning sun.</p>
        <p>Anemones are members of the enormous Ranunculaceae or buttercup family. The Japanese types have been in Western gardens for at least 150 years. Robert Fortune, a Socttish botanist who was one of the first of the great 19th-century plant hunters, reportedly sent an anemone back to england from Asia in the early 1840's.</p>
        <p>If you are investing in your first fall-blooming anemone, try Anemone x hybrida Japonica Alba. It is a tall, white single variety that blooms in late summer or early fall. Honorine Jobert is another white anemone with particularly attractive yellow stamens. If you tastes run to fluffer flower heads, the white Whrilwind cultivar, with its big semidouble blossoms, is the plant for you.</p>
        <p>Some people find it hard to use the color pink in the garden, especially in the fall. If you don't mind rosy tones, the various pink Japanese anemones blend well with the asters and boltonia that are in thir glory as the season turns. They also provide a fine complement to pastel-tinted roses in the last flush of bloom.</p>
        <p>For sweet simple pink flowers, you can't beat Anemone x hybrida September Charm. It is shorter than some of its cousins, reaching only about two feet in stature. Another pink-flowered single type is Anemone tomentosa Robustissima. It is taller than September Charm, with eye-catching dark stems. The tallest of the pink singles is Anemone Victor Jones, which grows to 40 inches.</p>
        <p>If you revel in double hollyhocks and centifolia roses, then you will certainly find a use in the garden for double pink Japanese anemones.</p>
        <p>Start on the short end of the spectrum with Anemone hupehensis Prince Henry, which has rose-colored petals and sprouts to a height of 18 inches. The pale Alice and the darker Margarette are both more statuesque than Prince Henry, coming in at 32 inches and 36 inches respectively.</p>
        <p>As is often the case in exalted circles, a queen always takes her place head and shoulders above a prince and a couple of commoners. The queen in question is Anemone x hybrida Queen Charlotte, with deep pink double flowers and 3-foot stems.</p>
        <p>Japanese anemones bloom from late summer through the end of September, and the majority will bloom perfectly well in full shade. They like moisture and prefer not to be cultivated in the chilly reaches north of U.S.D.A. Zone 5.</p>
        <p>If you have doubts about whether Japanese anemones will be cold-hardy, protect the plants in the winter. Increase your supplies by division in the spring or fall, or collect seeds from existing plants.</p>
        <p>Enlightened local plant purveyors may have a few Japanese anemones on their shelves at this time of year. Mega-merchandisers do not.</p>
        <p>For the best selection try catalog vendors including Bluestone Perennials (7211 Middle Ridge Road, Madison, Ohio 44057; 800-852-5243; www.bluestoneeperennials.com or Heronswood Nurseries (7530 N.E. 288th Street, Kingston, Wash. 98346; 360-297-4172; www.heronswood.com. Seeds are available from Thompson and Morgan (Post Office Box 1308, Jackson, N.J. 08527; 800-274-7333; www.thompson-morgan.com.</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
