<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unions Turn To Celebrities For Support</title>
    <meta content="Y17UNIO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/national/17UNIO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231386"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Screen Actors Guild</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Federation of Television and Radio Actors</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E6D91E38F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unions Turn To Celebrities For Support</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Screen Actors Guild and American Federation of Television and Radio Actors, locked in little-noticed strike against advertising industry for 20 weeks, enlist some of nation's best-known performers to win public support and turn up pressure on industry; threaten boycotts of leading advertisers; hold bargaining sessions for first time since July; dispute centers on residual payments to actors (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For actors, there is nothing worse than feeling invisible, and with two unions representing 135,000 actors locked in a little-noticed strike against the advertising industry for the past 20 weeks, the actors moved decisively last week to make their struggle more visible.</p>
        <p>Adopting what might be called a celebrity strategy, the unions enlisted some of the nation's best-known performers to win public support and turn up pressure on the $235-billion-a-year industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For actors, there is nothing worse than feeling invisible, and with two unions representing 135,000 actors locked in a little-noticed strike against the advertising industry for the past 20 weeks, the actors moved decisively last week to make their struggle more visible.</p>
        <p>Adopting what might be called a celebrity strategy, the unions enlisted some of the nation's best-known performers to win public support and turn up pressure on the $235-billion-a-year industry.</p>
        <p>In rallies last week in New York City and Los Angeles, Paul Newman, Tom Hanks, Richard Dreyfuss, Susan Sarandon and Valerie Harper threw some highly visible support behind the many lesser known actors locked in a dispute over pay rates for commercials. And Kevin Spacey, this year's Academy Award winner for best actor, showed his support by donating $100,000 last week to the actors' strike fund.</p>
        <p>Mr. Newman explained the reason he helped organize a rally on Wednesday near Rockefeller Center by saying, ''They've been on strike for nearly five months, and nobody knows about it.''</p>
        <p>To increase pressure, the unions began threatening last week to call for boycotts of several prominent advertisers, including Coca-Cola and Procter &amp; Gamble, in the hope of getting those companies to urge the industry to settle.</p>
        <p>While the two unions -- the Screen Actors Guild and the American Federation of Television and Radio Actors -- stepped up pressure, negotiators for the union and the industry held talks last Wednesday, Thursday and Friday, the first time they have bargained since July.</p>
        <p>Ira M. Shepard, one of the industry's chief negotiators, reported progress between the two sides' top bargainers and said full negotiating committees for both sides would meet on Monday in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The central issue is how to pay actors who perform in commercials. The industry is seeking to scrap residual rules from the 1950's when there were only a few television channels.</p>
        <p>Under the current system, most actors receive $475 a day for their work on the set and a residual each time the commercial is shown on television. The industry hopes to replace residuals with a one-time fee for unlimited use during a 13-week period, the same method used for cable.</p>
        <p>But the actors want residuals not only retained for network television, but also extended to cable. Calling the industry greedy, union officials and actors criticize management for seeking to cut payments to actors at a time when the advertising and broadcasting industries are enjoying record profits.</p>
        <p>At a demonstration on Friday in Manhattan, Mr. Dreyfuss, said: ''The industry is operating under a very simple maxim -- that they can get away with it, so why not try it? If they can pay people less, why not do it?'' At the Rockefeller Center demonstration, Treat Williams, star of ''Prince of the City,'' said it was important to preserve the current pay-for-play system, which the actors like because they earn more the more a commercial is played.</p>
        <p>''Show the commercial; show me the money,'' he told an enthusiastic crowd of 1,000 strikers. Underlining the importance of residuals, Mr. Williams said he survived being out of work for two years thanks to residuals from commercials.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shepard said there was progress in last week's talks ''because the union has been on strike for five months, and they want a new contract.'' He said many companies had continued making commercials with nonunion actors despite the strikers' repeated efforts to disrupt shootings.</p>
        <p>But the union says the strike has badly hurt advertisers and the advertising industry, noting, for example, that Sela Ward, who last week won an Emmy award for best actress in a drama, is not making new Sprint commercials.</p>
        <p>Paul Reggio, a union strike coordinator, said management had returned to the bargaining table because ''the actors have held out much longer and shown much more solidarity than the industry ever expected.''</p>
        <p>Union officials say most strikers are struggling actors who make $5,000 to $10,000 a year from commercials. It is the residuals from commercials, many actors say, that enables them to afford taking low-paying acting jobs Off Broadway.</p>
        <p>''This is the bread and butter contract,'' Mr. Dreyfuss said. ''This is the centerpiece of what we do.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
