<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If You're Thinking of Living In/Sea Gate; 'Hamptons West' in Brooklyn</title>
    <meta content="17LIVI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000924T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sea Gate (Nyc)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Radomsky, Rosalie R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E2DB1738F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2135" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If You're Thinking of Living In/Sea Gate; 'Hamptons West' in Brooklyn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROSALIE R. RADOMSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Radomsky, Rosalie R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>If You're Thinking of Living In column on Sea Gate section of Brooklyn, NYC; photos; maps; chart (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HARBOR seals bobbing in the water. Freighters from all over the world floating by. Cormorants spreading their wings on pier pilings and diving for fish. A sandy beach, right in the backyard.</p>
        <p>This is Brooklyn?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HARBOR seals bobbing in the water. Freighters from all over the world floating by. Cormorants spreading their wings on pier pilings and diving for fish. A sandy beach, right in the backyard.</p>
        <p>This is Brooklyn?</p>
        <p>Dr. June Reinisch, 57, and her husband, Dr. Leonard Rosenblum, 64, have been privy to these views of Gravesend Bay -- sometimes using a wildlife spotting scope or a bird guide -- from their windows in the Sea Gate section of Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Two years ago they left their 18-window loft in Boerum Hill for a $465,000 contemporary high ranch along Ocean View Avenue, which they renovated for $150,000.</p>
        <p>The private gated community, which begins where the streets and Boardwalk of Coney Island end, is so far west in the borough and so secluded that Drs. Reinisch and Rosenblum, both psychologists, did not realize it existed when they went to Steeplechase Park in Coney Island as children.</p>
        <p>Donald Nier, who runs Nier Realty from his parents' 11,000-square-foot oceanfront house, likes to call it ''Hamptons West.''</p>
        <p>''We're on the same Long Island barrier beaches as Fire Island and the Hamptons,'' he said, ''but the big difference between us and them is we count the minutes to Manhattan and they count the hours.''</p>
        <p>Mostly one- and two-family homes -- Mediterranean villas, brick houses, high ranches, rambling Victorians influenced by Stanford White -- can be found behind a 12-foot-high chain-link fence stretching along West 37th Street from the ocean to the bay.</p>
        <p>The fence also conveniently helps to form an eruv, an enclosure within which observant Jews are freed from a ban on carrying certain items on the Sabbath, a convenience for Sea Gate's many Orthodox believers.  The enclave has drawn many Jews from Orthodox and Russian communities in other parts of Brooklyn in recent years, residents say.</p>
        <p>Sea Gate's 820 houses are all within a half-dozen blocks of the water -- with 72 along the ocean or bay. Homeowners pay dues and charges -- exactly 12 percent of New York City's property tax assessments -- to the Sea Gate Association, in addition to city property taxes.</p>
        <p>The homeowners' association, established in 1899, owns Sea Gate's four and a half miles of winding tree-lined roads and nine miles of sidewalks, along with six numbered beaches -- only two were used by residents for swimming last summer to hold costs down. It also sells beach passes to residents.</p>
        <p>The association's $2 million budget goes toward its own 25-member Sea Gate state-licensed police force, office staff and street maintenance. The city provides sanitation, additional police, fire and health services.</p>
        <p>Residents use electronic keys to enter the two gates, at Surf and Neptune Avenues, and must notify the community's police of expected visitors. Besides being posted at the gates and patrolling streets, the police tour beaches by sand buggy.</p>
        <p>''Crime is very low in Sea Gate,'' said the community's police chief, Robert Abraham, formerly an inspector with the New York Police Department for 35 years.</p>
        <p>That was not case in the mid-to-late- nineteenth century, however, when Mike Norton of the Tammany Hall political machine ran rowdy saloons and brothels there, giving the area an unsavory reputation as Norton's Point. In 1871, William Marcy (Boss) Tweed hid there for many weeks after escaping prison guards in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>A group of wealthy people acquired the area from the Norton's Point Land Company in 1892, and soon Sea Gate was in its heyday as a summer attraction for the wealthy -- the Vanderbilts, Goulds, Astors and du Ponts -- drawn to its hotels, mansions and the swanky Atlantic Yacht Club. The club, designed by Stanford White, burned down in the 1930's.</p>
        <p>MANY year-round residents moved in when mansions were turned into multiple-family dwellings during the Depression. Among them was Isaac Bashevis Singer, who arrived in New York in 1935 and based his novel ''Enemies: A Love Story'' there.</p>
        <p>During World War II military personnel lived in Quonset huts, and anti-aircraft batteries appeared along the oceanside.</p>
        <p>The soprano Beverly Sills lived there as a child, and the actor Paul Muni and the comedian Soupy Sales had homes here.</p>
        <p>Last year Sea Gate celebrated its centennial with a parade, a concert and display of old photos in the Sea Gate Community Center. The center, once a Protestant chapel, is now used by Boy Scouts and the 60-member garden club and is rented for parties. Sea Gate Association meetings -- where residents recently voiced concerns about potholes on Neptune Avenue -- are also held there.</p>
        <p>Today houses along the water range from  $321,000 for a fixer-upper to more than $1 million. An eye-catching white all-steel 1940 prefab, known as ''the sugar cube,'' is owned by Pete Spanakos, a high school director and a local historian who is also co-president of the Brooklyn Coordinating Council for the Preservation of Neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>During a fierce storm in December 1992, one house was washed into the ocean. ''We live by the tides and the vagaries of nature,'' said Mr. Spanakos, whose deck overlooks a recently formed sandy beach.</p>
        <p>His neighbor, Michael Bresloff, said:  ''When I bought my house in 1992, I wanted to go to work by boat. The water was 6 to 8  feet deep at the end of my pier. Sand started coming in 1995, and all of sudden a beach was forming'' at the end of his pier.</p>
        <p>''Now water is slowly coming back,'' he added. ''It's definitely been exciting.''</p>
        <p>The sand, a byproduct of an Army Corps of Engineers and city program to replenish Coney Island beaches, drifted into the bay, and the newly formed beach created an entrance into Sea Gate for trespassers. After debate with neighbors and the city, the community put up a 10-foot-high fence in 1998 at the northeastern end of the enclave.</p>
        <p>Within the fences is a community made up of relatively spacious lots. ''This is one of the few areas in Brooklyn where you could find several hundred houses on 60 by 100-plus lots,'' said Mr. Nier, the broker. ''Many are modernizing houses and changing them from multifamilies back into one- or two-families.''</p>
        <p>A four-bedroom contemporary brick high ranch with a 40-foot beach that is 400 feet deep, of which 160 feet are under water, is on the market for $1 million on Ocean View Avenue. Seven new houses in the $500,000 range are being developed on empty lots, where houses were razed. And a handful more are empty.</p>
        <p>Along Atlantic Avenue, a 6,000-square-foot Victorian, once home to a dozen families, was sold for $420,000 last year and is being turned into a one-family home. A 9,000-square-foot Mediterranean villa, lately a four-family house, sold for $289,000 last year in foreclosure and has been renovated.</p>
        <p>ALSO being fixed up is a three-story three-bedroom semidetached brick house, which sold for $321,000 in May,  on Beach 45th Street overlooking the ocean.  A 60-year-old two-family brick semidetached with a veranda along Neptune Avenue is on the market for $280,000.</p>
        <p>Sea Gate is not entirely off limits to outsiders. About 1,600 nonresidents -- many once members of the Brighton Beach Baths, which closed in 1997 and has been replaced by a condominium development -- rent lockers or cabanas at the Sea Gate Beach and Cabana Club, which issues temporary keys and leases Beach 1.</p>
        <p>Belonging to Sea Gate, but separated by an entrance outside the gate, is the Mermaid Spa, with a mainly Russian clientele, who relax in steam rooms or schmooze on its lawn or over borscht in its restaurant.</p>
        <p>Abraham House I and II, a single-room occupancy residence for previously homeless people age 55 and older, in separate buildings three blocks apart, often invites the elderly from the community on outings. The elderly also participate in programs at Surf-Solomon Center, just beyond the gate, which serves breakfast and lunch.</p>
        <p>Popular with children in Sea Gate, and beyond, are gymnastics programs at Nova Athletics, which rents space from Kneses Israel, an Orthodox synagogue. Another large synagogue, two small synagogues and a yeshiva are attended by Hasidic Jews in the community.</p>
        <p>THE nearest elementary school, two blocks outside the Neptune Avenue gate, is P.S. 188, which has a program for gifted students, with admission by examination. Graduates of that program often move on to Mark Twain Junior High School for the Gifted and Talented 10 blocks away from the same gate, in District 21 in Coney Island. Many then go on to Edward R. Murrow, John Dewey and Lincoln High Schools. Others attend private schools like Poly Prep Country Day School, grades 5 to 12 in Bay Ridge; yeshivas in Borough Park; or the school at Our Lady of Solace Roman Catholic Church, pre-K to 8th grades, in Coney Island.</p>
        <p>For shopping many walk a block to Key Food from the Neptune Avenue Gate or five blocks from either gate to Pioneer on Mermaid Avenue or drive 5 minutes to Pathmark on Cropsey Avenue or 10 minutes to Edwards on Avenue Y and East 17th Street, both open 24 hours. They also go by car to fruit markets under the elevated subway tracks in Brighton Beach and at 86th Street in Bensonhurst. Cropsey and Neptune Bagels are popular on weekend mornings.  Those looking for glatt kosher stores take a shuttle bus, with pick-up points inside the gate, to Borough Park. A 24-hour Home Depot is to open on Shore Parkway and Cropsey Avenue next year.</p>
        <p>Many Sea Gaters go to old-time family-run Neapolitan restaurants in Coney Island like Garguilo's and Carolina's for homemade pasta and to Totonno's, with pressed tin ceilings, for whole pizzas from its brick oven. Also popular are the newly renovated Retro 50, a Greek diner on Cropsey Avenue, and the numerous Russian restaurants in Brighton Beach; and Lundy's in Sheepshead Bay offers Brooklyn clam chowder. Of course, there is always Nathan's Famous in Coney Island for hot dogs.</p>
        <p>Sea Gaters can jog and walk along the 2.7-mile Boardwalk in Coney Island, go ice-skating at Abe Stark Recreation Center on weekends from October to March and catch a dolphin show at the New York Aquarium. A new 6,500-seat baseball stadium, home to a Mets minor league team, is expected to open next June in old Steeplechase Park.</p>
        <p>Inside Sea Gate, children play in Dave Sevush Playground by the Surf Avenue entrance. In Lindy Park, an undeveloped three acres where the ocean meets the bay, fisherman are catching fluke these days along rock jetties, and other residents walk their dogs, fly kites or simply watch the ships go by.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 24, 2000, Sunday  An article last Sunday about living in the Sea Gate area of Brooklyn misidentified the work by Isaac Bashevis Singer that was set in the neighborhood. It was his short story ''Escape from Civilization.'' His novel ''Enemies, A Love Story'' was set partly in Coney Island, not in Sea Gate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 24, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about living in the Sea Gate area of Brooklyn misidentified the work by Isaac Bashevis Singer that was set in the neighborhood. It was his short story ''Escape from Civilization.'' His novel ''Enemies, A Love Story'' was set partly in Coney Island, not in Sea Gate.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
