<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out on the Road to Burning Man</title>
    <meta content="17PREL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/business/17PREL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRELUDES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Burning Man Festival</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ellin, Abby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Preludes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/On the Road</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Burning Man Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5DE1138F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out on the Road to Burning Man</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY ELLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ellin, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Abby Ellin Personal Business column holds counter-cultural values of annual weeklong Burning Man festival in Nevada desert are seeping into mainstream American culture, or vice versa; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I HAVEN'T yet seen a Burning Man sticker on a Cadillac. But when I do, it won't surprise me. That is because Burning Man, the annual weeklong festival of arts, music and ''radical self-expression'' in the Nevada desert, is rapidly seeping into mainstream American culture -- or is it the other way around?</p>
        <p>Like many other things countercultural and groovy, Burning Man started in the Bay Area, when Larry Harvey built and burned an effigy on a San Francisco beach in 1986. Publicized by word of mouth and on the Web, the event caught the imagination of the digerati and took on a life of its own. Sequels grew so big that Mr. Harvey had to move the pyrotechnics to somewhere a bit less populated -- a desolate stretch of federally owned desert 100 miles north of Reno. This year's event culminated on Labor Day; about 28,000 people participated in the ephemeral makeshift community, Black Rock City, that materializes for the annual torching of a huge wood-and-neon figure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I HAVEN'T yet seen a Burning Man sticker on a Cadillac. But when I do, it won't surprise me. That is because Burning Man, the annual weeklong festival of arts, music and ''radical self-expression'' in the Nevada desert, is rapidly seeping into mainstream American culture -- or is it the other way around?</p>
        <p>Like many other things countercultural and groovy, Burning Man started in the Bay Area, when Larry Harvey built and burned an effigy on a San Francisco beach in 1986. Publicized by word of mouth and on the Web, the event caught the imagination of the digerati and took on a life of its own. Sequels grew so big that Mr. Harvey had to move the pyrotechnics to somewhere a bit less populated -- a desolate stretch of federally owned desert 100 miles north of Reno. This year's event culminated on Labor Day; about 28,000 people participated in the ephemeral makeshift community, Black Rock City, that materializes for the annual torching of a huge wood-and-neon figure.</p>
        <p>Burn Heads are loath to make the comparison, but the festival -- which draws so many people from Silicon Valley that it could easily be called Burn Rate Man -- has much in common with a Grateful Dead concert: young and formerly young people camping out, enjoying performance art (and maybe various levels of undress and altered states of consciousness) and raging against the machine.</p>
        <p>Ostensibly, Burning Man is anti-corporate, anti-consumerism, anti-establishment; people cover over the Ryder logos on their trucks and wear handmade outfits that reflect the Inner Them of the Day. Hard currency will get you only coffee and ice at the festival; you have to bring other supplies along with you, or barter for them. Think ''Survivor'' without the lush foliage.</p>
        <p>''Burning Man co-opts people out of their rut and shows them a different way of living, working, playing and communicating,'' said Larry Smith, 32, the executive editor of Yahoo Internet Life magazine, who has made the pilgrimage six times.</p>
        <p>I attended last year, and for all my skepticism, I have to say that I had a hilarious, if slightly dehydrating, time. But what I found there wasn't a digital-age Woodstock. It was more fascinating: the Internet made flesh.</p>
        <p>''You've got your communities of affinity, viral marketing, information pricing, users-provide-the-content approach, branding, and Larry Harvey is the very essence of today's iconoclast-savant C.E.O.,'' said Brad Wieners, 32, editor of the book ''Burning Man'' (Hardwired, 1997). ''All that's missing is the I.P.O.''</p>
        <p>There are certainly enough dollars involved to go public. Depending on when you buy your ticket, Burning Man can cost $95 to $250. Multiply that by 28,000 and, well, you do the math. And how anti-establishment can an event be when the managing editor of Time magazine makes an appearance? Or when the Green Tortoise travel company advertises package trips to the ''wildest experience you've ever had''? Or when law firms send squads of employees in rented R.V.'s? What's next, a ''Let's Go: Black Rock City'' travel guide?</p>
        <p>Aly Eisenhardt, 22, a junior at Humboldt State University in California who had attended Burning Man twice before, didn't go this year. ''It's gotten too commercial, too big and too hypocritical,'' Ms. Eisenhardt said. ''It's outside the value system of what Burning Man was really about.''</p>
        <p>Anything underground and successful eventually becomes commercial and overdone. Each generation has had its its own counterculture jamboree; images of the Beats, Haight-Ashbury, Monterey, the Dead, Nirvana, mosh pits and techno raves come to mind. Before long, the grownups come piling in and spoil the fun. So, too, with the Web, some would say.</p>
        <p>But not with Burning Man. The dynamic is different. Most participants are not rebellious teenagers, but people in their 20's and 30's with jobs and even companies of their own; more than a few are stock-option millionaires. This generation may not openly condone ''selling out,'' but it certainly doesn't frown on capitalism and getting rich. By past counterculture standards, ''them'' equaled ''us'' from the very beginning.</p>
        <p>MR. WIENERS, who has seen seven Men burn, said that while the festival has been ''legitimized by the establishment,'' that doesn't mean that it is being destroyed. ''There are a lot of paradoxes,'' he said. ''The guy who's the main instigator is making his living off Burning Man, but has he sold out? It's not brought to you by Budweiser. It's kept certain parameters. This year, some of the art had a much higher production value, because artists are getting grants from Burning Man. Is this bad?''</p>
        <p>He added: ''It's discovering that play, folly, make-believe, the way you spent afternoons in the early grades, is a valid thing for an adult to do. It's what a whole lot of companies strive for. Realizing that innovation comes from play, they want to encourage it -- to a point.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps. But if play breeds innovation, and innovation breeds productivity, and productivity breeds sales, one thing is clear: Bumper stickers can't be far behind.</p>
        <p>PRELUDES Abby Ellin is a Manhattan writer. Her column on starting out in the world of money appears the third Sunday of each month. E-mail: preludes@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Abby Ellin is a Manhattan writer. Her column on starting out in the world of money appears the third Sunday of each month. E-mail: preludes@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
