<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Word for Word/Newsboy Nostalgia; Flash! Street Urchins Hawk Tabs on City Streets!</title>
    <meta content="17WORD$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/weekinreview/17WORD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newsdealers and Newsstands</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Daily News</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daily News Express</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharkey, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E4DA1138F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1389" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Word for Word/Newsboy Nostalgia; Flash! Street Urchins Hawk Tabs on City Streets!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SHARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sharkey, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on history of street newsboy in wake of return of 'newsies' on New York City streets with Daily News' publication of free afternoon paper, Daily News Express; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''EXTRA! Extra! Read all about it!'' Remember that cry from those old movies in which scrappy urban newsboys held up papers with screaming headlines?</p>
        <p>Newsies, as the ruddy-cheeked hawkers were sometimes called, were both a useful plot device and an evocation of a time when the evening news was purchased on the street, not seen on television.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''EXTRA! Extra! Read all about it!'' Remember that cry from those old movies in which scrappy urban newsboys held up papers with screaming headlines?</p>
        <p>Newsies, as the ruddy-cheeked hawkers were sometimes called, were both a useful plot device and an evocation of a time when the evening news was purchased on the street, not seen on television.</p>
        <p>Last week, newsies returned when The  Daily News in New York began publishing a slender new afternoon paper, Daily News Express, that is handed out free after 4 p.m. The paper reported that when it held interviews for dozens of modern-day newsies for its street distribution, among those who ''auditioned'' were a Russian acrobat, a children's actor in a dog costume and an opera singer ''who danced a jig dressed as an old-time newspaper boy.''</p>
        <p>Newsboy nostalgia?</p>
        <p>Stranger things have bubbled up in the vast melting pot of popular culture. What's worth remembering, though, is that real-life newsboys, who first appeared in the mid-19th century with the rise of mass-circulation newspapers, were hardly the lovable street urchins of Hollywood myth. They were often wretchedly poor homeless children who shrieked the headlines well into the night and often slept on the streets. Singing and dancing were usually not among their concerns.</p>
        <p>JOE SHARKEY</p>
        <p>In 1866, Charles Loring Brace, a reformer, slum missionary and self-help proponent, wrote a book called ''Short Sermons to News Boys, With a History of the Formation of the News Boys' Lodging House.'' Brace, who called newsboys ''little merchants,'' had been among the founders of the Lodging House, which provided beds, meals and nighttime supervision to homeless boys.</p>
        <p>I remember one cold night seeing some 10 or a dozen of the little homeless creatures piled together to keep each other warm beneath the stairway of The Sun office. There used to be a mass of them also at The Atlas office, sleeping in the lobbies, until the printers drove them away by pouring water on them. One winter, an old burnt-out safe lay all the season in Wall Street, which was used as a bedroom by two boys who managed to crawl into the hole that had been burnt. I was often amused at the accounts of their various lodgings. ''Oh mister,'' one of them said, ''there's nothing like them steam gratins -- it's just as good as a feather-bed. And next to 'em I likes a good box of sand, cause you can git it up all around you.'' . . .</p>
        <p>The great peculiarity of the New York News Boys' Lodging House, as distinguished from similar European institutions, is the payment demanded from the lodgers. (This is now 5 cents for lodging, 3 cents for supper and 1 cent for the use of lockers). The object of this is to cultivate the feeling of independence and self-respect in these children. They value the place more in paying for it.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, it seems, the wily rascals tried to cadge a warm bed without paying, as suggested in an 1854 article in The New York Dispatch about C. C. Tracy, the superintendent of the Lodging House:</p>
        <p>To show how necessary it is for Mr. Tracy to always be on the alert, to keep even with some of his slippery little customers, we may mention that upon one occasion, a boy stated that he had been badly ''stuck'' and had no money to pay, but would liquidate at some other time. Accordingly he was allowed to go to bed without paying, but the next night, he had been stuck again, and this time another boy had been equally unfortunate. This set Mr. Tracy to thinking, and by dint of close listening, he discovered that the youngsters had sewn up their money in their underclothes.</p>
        <p>Despite the reformers' efforts, the newsboys' plight was often depicted as merely an unpleasant fact of life in the big city.</p>
        <p>There are 10,000 children living on the streets of New York. . . . The newsboys constitute an important division of this army of homeless children. You see them everywhere. . . . They rend the air and deafen you with their shrill cries. They surround you on the sidewalk and almost force you to buy their papers. They are ragged and dirty. Some have no coats, no shoes and no hat. Some are simply stupid, others are bright, intelligent little fellows.</p>
        <p>-- ''Lights and Shadows of New York Life,'' by James D. McCabe Jr. (1872)</p>
        <p>In 1899, several thousand newsboys, who made about 30 cents a day, called a strike, refusing to handle the newspapers of William Randolph Hearst and Joseph Pulitzer. Competing papers lavished coverage on the strikers, who were depicted as colorful characters who spoke in an oddly rendered Irish-immigrant dialect and had names like Race Track Higgens and Kid Fish. The news accounts gave much attention to the exhortations of a pint-sized newsboy and strike leader named Kid Blink (because he was blind in one eye).</p>
        <p>Friens and feller workers. Dis is a time which tries de hearts of men. Dis is de time when we'se got to stick together like glue. . . . We know wot we wants and we'll git it even if we is blind.</p>
        <p>-- The New York Tribune, quoting Kid Blink's speech to 2,000 strikers</p>
        <p>De bigger dis parade is de bigger success it is. . . . So I say, we start out from here about 8 or 9 o'clock and go all trough the lower part of the city. If we want ter p'rade again uptown where de loidies kin see us, we kin do it in the evening.</p>
        <p>-- The New York Sun, quoting from the same speech</p>
        <p>The lot of newsboys began to improve as urban child-welfare practices took root and publishers began competing for newsies by giving them prizes and trips. Still, things could get rough.</p>
        <p>Some publishers used intimidation and violence. . . . When William Randolph Hearst moved into the Chicago market at the turn of the century, many newsstands and newsies, bowing to pressure from the already established papers, refused to carry his paper. Hearst and the Annenberg brothers, his circulation managers, armed their delivery men and hired adult thugs to force the dealers and newsies to carry the ''American'' and ''Examiner.'' . . .</p>
        <p>The children lived for the great headline, the red-faced, bold-type banner catastrophes that sold out editions. Murder, mayhem, riot, war, natural disaster; this was the stuff their dreams were made of. . . . During the Great War there was a virtual epidemic of false headlines. In Cleveland, officials were so disturbed by the boys' blatant distortion of the news that they threatened to prosecute those who shouted ''false and amazing statements.''</p>
        <p>-- ''Children of the City,'' by David Nasaw (Anchor/Doubleday, 1985)</p>
        <p>Echoes of the great newspaper wars could be heard in last week's launch of the newsie-propelled Daily News Express. The tabloid's main competitor, The New York Post, responded by cutting its price in half and hiring its own newsies (some dressed in tuxedos and Revolutionary War garb) for publicity. Needless to say, the rival tabloids put a slightly different spin on the week's events.</p>
        <p>Post fever has been sweeping the city ever since its price was slashed in half last week. The Post's success at 25 cents put a big damper on the debut of the anemic-looking free paper peddled by the circulation-losing Daily News. Many readers discarded the freebee in the nearest trash can minutes after taking it from Daily News Express hawkers.</p>
        <p>-- The New York Post, Sept. 13</p>
        <p>Copies of the historic first edition that bore the headline ''Rats!'' -- above a Page One story about the furor over a G.O.P. campaign commercial -- were quickly snatched up by homeward bound workers, travelers and shoppers. . . . The paper is being distributed by specially recruited hawkers. . . . ''Get your free Daily News Express,'' cried one cheerleader. ''The news is hot off the press!''</p>
        <p>-- The Daily News, Sept. 13</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
