<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Other Australia</title>
    <meta content="17SUN1$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/opinion/17SUN1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231374"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aborigines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aborigines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E5DB1E38F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Other Australia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial holds Sydney Olympics will help shine spotlight on Aboriginal culture and its historical plight; says attention should prove uncomfortable to Australian government, which has made great strides on racial front in recent decades but is showing some distressing signs of weariness from the progress and resistance to march onward (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a splendidly diverse and inclusive face Australia presented to the world in the Olympics' opening pageant, particularly by having the Aboriginal sprinter Cathy Freeman carry the torch on the final leg of its journey. As if seeking a mirage,  Freeman walked through a pond toward an idyllic waterfall to light the Games' caldron. This progression of the Olympic flame could well serve as a metaphor for the quest of Aborigines to achieve social justice and historical reconciliation in today's Australia. Unfortunately, in this quest the idyllic waterfall-like destination remains somewhat of a mirage.</p>
        <p>The Sydney Olympics will help shine a spotlight on Aboriginal culture and its historical plight. The attention should prove uncomfortable to the Australian government. The nation has made great strides on the racial front in recent decades, but it is showing some distressing signs of weariness from the progress, and a resistance to march onward. In recent months, the Australian government has ceased cooperating with United Nations human rights monitors looking into the status of Aborigines and has opposed calls for an official apology for past wrongs. Perhaps catching its reflection in the global glare will force Australia to reconsider these positions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a splendidly diverse and inclusive face Australia presented to the world in the Olympics' opening pageant, particularly by having the Aboriginal sprinter Cathy Freeman carry the torch on the final leg of its journey. As if seeking a mirage,  Freeman walked through a pond toward an idyllic waterfall to light the Games' caldron. This progression of the Olympic flame could well serve as a metaphor for the quest of Aborigines to achieve social justice and historical reconciliation in today's Australia. Unfortunately, in this quest the idyllic waterfall-like destination remains somewhat of a mirage.</p>
        <p>The Sydney Olympics will help shine a spotlight on Aboriginal culture and its historical plight. The attention should prove uncomfortable to the Australian government. The nation has made great strides on the racial front in recent decades, but it is showing some distressing signs of weariness from the progress, and a resistance to march onward. In recent months, the Australian government has ceased cooperating with United Nations human rights monitors looking into the status of Aborigines and has opposed calls for an official apology for past wrongs. Perhaps catching its reflection in the global glare will force Australia to reconsider these positions.</p>
        <p>Of course it is difficult for Americans to cast stones on this score. But we can appreciate a democratic Australia's journey to come to terms with the scars of its past because our past horrors are if anything more grave, our own journey equally incomplete. Australia has long hovered on the far reaches of Americans' consciousness, that place where fantasy begins encroaching on reality. We relish the idea of traveling to the ends of the earth to find an island as vast as a continent, inhabited by exotic animals -- what child is not mesmerized by the kangaroo? -- but reassuringly familiar people. They speak English, but also came from someplace else, to build reassuringly clean and modern cities. And like Americans, they started with the same national myth of a fearless band of Europeans claiming a new frontier for humankind. In fact, Aborigines, one of the world's oldest communities, have been in Australia for some 50,000 years.</p>
        <p>The Aboriginal experience since the H.M.S. Endeavour arrived in Botany Bay in 1770 is depressingly similar to that of our nation's Native Americans. The European settlers viciously drove the Aborigines from their lands, massacring thousands with impunity. Today, 390,000 Aborigines account for 2 percent of the nation's population. Their life expectancy is 15 years less than that of the average Australian.</p>
        <p>Throughout much of the 20th century, children of mixed parentage could be removed from their mothers and raised in institutions that sought to assimilate them into white society. This inhumane policy persisted throughout the 1960's, and gave rise to a so-called ''stolen generation'' of children, many of whom grew up not knowing the identity of their parents. Cathy Freeman's own grandmother was taken from her home, and the athlete has denounced Prime Minister John Howard's refusal to issue an official apology for this policy. Instead of  making amends, the government last month secured a victory in court against two claims from removed children seeking reparation.</p>
        <p>Australia's move to stop cooperating with United Nations fact finders monitoring the treatment of Aborigines is distressing. Australia is a resilient enough democracy to take strong criticism, even if the government thinks it is unfair or misguided. But instead the government has set a horribly destructive example at a time when ethnic minorities in a number of less enlightened countries must increasingly rely on international vigilance to ensure their survival.</p>
        <p>Activists will use the Olympic Games to pressure the government to further the nation's reconciliation with the past. For her part, Freeman is expected to carry both the Australian flag and the red, black and yellow Aboriginal flag on her victory lap if she wins a gold medal. Her competitors will pardon us for saying that that would be a wondrous sight.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
