<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; Keeping Friends and the Faith</title>
    <meta content="17NIEB$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/weekinreview/17NIEB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Niebuhr, Gustav</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E0DB1138F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; Keeping Friends and the Faith</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUSTAV NIEBUHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Niebuhr, Gustav</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Millennium Summit of Religious and Spiritual Leaders, diverse gathering at United Nations, produces document signed by several hundred religious leaders pledging them to work for world peace, against poverty and for protection of environment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOW should religious believers respond to the plurality of faiths around them? It's a question that has grown in urgency as waves of immigration and emigration around the world have brought people of very different theologies into the same work places, schools and neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>The question becomes especially pointed when it comes to a faith with a missionary imperative, like Christianity, whose gospels teach that salvation comes through faith in Jesus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOW should religious believers respond to the plurality of faiths around them? It's a question that has grown in urgency as waves of immigration and emigration around the world have brought people of very different theologies into the same work places, schools and neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>The question becomes especially pointed when it comes to a faith with a missionary imperative, like Christianity, whose gospels teach that salvation comes through faith in Jesus.</p>
        <p>In many areas around the globe, Christians continue to follow Jesus's command, recounted in Mark 16:15, to preach the gospel to every living creature. (That this can cause great tension is evident these days in India, where Hindus have accused Roman Catholics of proselytizing, and in Latin America, where Catholics have complained of similar pressures from evangelical Protestants.)</p>
        <p>At least since the 1960's, many of the big, news-making events involving different religious groups have been two-party affairs. Theologians from one group sat down with those from another, and, sometimes after years of discussions, reached tentative agreements about what they could say together. That process produced some truly historic breakthroughs, like a pact between  the Episcopal Church and the Evangelical Lutheran Church in America that brought eight million Protestants into full communion. More breathtakingly still, years of high-level official dialogue between Roman Catholics and Jews reached a climax last March when Pope John Paul II journeyed to Israel and prayed at the Western Wall.</p>
        <p>Recent events have illustrated the conflicting responses that pluralism can arouse.</p>
        <p>Three weeks ago, a meeting at the United Nations brought together hundreds of religious leaders from every inhabited continent to talk about how their diverse traditions can help the cause of world peace. Among those attending was Cardinal Francis Arinze, a Vatican official who specializes in interfaith work.</p>
        <p>A week later, the Vatican published a statement by an even higher-ranking Vatican official, Cardinal Joseph Ratzinger,  saying that the church is the guardian  of religious truth and that the ultimate aim of interfaith dialogue ought to be conversion.</p>
        <p>It was only a month earlier that an international gathering of 10,000 evangelists, who had been meeting in Amsterdam under the auspices of the Rev. Billy Graham's organization, released their own declaration, which dealt partly with the issue of pluralism. (A statement last week by Jewish scholars and rabbis urging Jews to relinquish their fears of Christianity dealt less with issues of ecumenism than with dogma long seen as prejudicial.)</p>
        <p>The two recent Christian statements shared the view that only through Jesus Christ is salvation possible. ''Jesus is, in fact, the Word of God made man for the salvation of all,'' Cardinal Ratzinger wrote. The authors of the ''Amsterdam Declaration'' agreed: ''The only way to know God in peace, love and joy is through the reconciling death of Jesus Christ the risen Lord.''</p>
        <p>And, like Cardinal Ratzinger, the evangelists reaffirmed the necessity of conversion: ''As we enter into dialogue with adherents of other religions, we must be courteous and kind. But such dialogue must not be a substitute for proclamation.''</p>
        <p>SOME might argue that interfaith dialogue need not be an either-or proposition, a choice between a defense of the claims of one's own religion or a mushy relativism. Instead, the search for common ground may be undertaken for goals as readily understood in a secular sense as they are in a sacred one.</p>
        <p>That seemed to be the message of the Millennium Summit of Religious and Spiritual Leaders, the remarkably diverse gathering at the United Nations that produced a document signed by several hundred religious leaders pledging them to work for world peace, against poverty and for the protection of the environment.</p>
        <p>The underlying idea in that statement was more or less described in a brief speech made during the event by Rabbi Jonathan Sacks, chief rabbi of Great Britain, who said that religion has an influence that goes beyond mere political power.</p>
        <p>''Politicians sign peace agreements, but it is our people, out there, on the ground, who will determine whether peace is real, or just a breathing space between wars,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One of those present was James Kenney, international coordinator of the Council for a Parliament of the World's Religions, a Chicago-based organization that has twice convened large-scale interfaith gatherings in the last seven years. The Millennium Summit had its share of tensions between faith groups, but, he said, ''it was a very good symbolic moment, and I'm really a believer in those.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Kenney remains a critic of what he calls ''lightweight pluralism,'' the desire to claim that all religions are really the same, and that differences do not matter.</p>
        <p>As a counter to that tendency, he said, as awareness of global religious pluralism has increased, there has developed also ''an increasingly articulate body'' of religious believers, especially among Christians, who appear ready to grant that enlightenment can be found in other faiths, while still affirming their own religion as utterly unique.</p>
        <p>But the recent statements by the Vatican and the evangelists' meeting strongly suggest that such an approach is a long way from displacing Christianity's view of its exclusive claim to salvation. Instead, as the world grows smaller and as more and more people have increasing contact with those of other faiths, the debate over how to respond to religious pluralism is likely to be just beginning.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
