<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Aging Custodian Worries About a Historic Cemetery</title>
    <meta content="17CEME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: ASTORIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War (US) (1861-65)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Revolutionary War, American (1775-83)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lippincott, E E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lawrence Family</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sheehan, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War (US) (1861-65)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2D81038F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="471" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Aging Custodian Worries About a Historic Cemetery</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. E. LIPPINCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lippincott, E E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James Sheehan, who has been caring for Lawrence family cemetery in Astoria, Queens, for nearly 50 years, worries over what will become of property, where Revolutionary War and Civil War heroes are buried, once he is gone; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>James Sheehan's backyard is full of the bodies of Revolutionary War and Civil War that, records show, were heroes. Officially the site is known as the Lawrence family cemetery, and Mr. Sherman's grandchildren grew up dancing on the flat granite gravestone of William Beach Lawrence, a lieutenant governor of Rhode Island in the 1800's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sheehan has been tending the site for nearly 50 years, paying for repairs out of his own pocket. But now he is 71, and he is worried about what will become of the place once he is gone. He is not a Lawrence. He inherited the property, which is on 20th Road and 35th Avenue, from his father-in law, who had been given the land by a woman named Ruth Lawrence, the last living member of her family. ''I've been maintaining this out of respect for my father-in-law, not the Lawrences,'' Mr. Sheehan said. ''But as you tend this, you come to learn about the people.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>James Sheehan's backyard is full of the bodies of Revolutionary War and Civil War that, records show, were heroes. Officially the site is known as the Lawrence family cemetery, and Mr. Sherman's grandchildren grew up dancing on the flat granite gravestone of William Beach Lawrence, a lieutenant governor of Rhode Island in the 1800's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sheehan has been tending the site for nearly 50 years, paying for repairs out of his own pocket. But now he is 71, and he is worried about what will become of the place once he is gone. He is not a Lawrence. He inherited the property, which is on 20th Road and 35th Avenue, from his father-in law, who had been given the land by a woman named Ruth Lawrence, the last living member of her family. ''I've been maintaining this out of respect for my father-in-law, not the Lawrences,'' Mr. Sheehan said. ''But as you tend this, you come to learn about the people.''</p>
        <p>The graveyard, which is an official city landmark, was founded in 1656 by an Englishman named Maj. Thomas Lawrence, who emigrated to New York in 1651. Among the dozens of prominent figures buried there is Maj. Johnathan Lawrence, a member of the state constitutional convention in the 1770's; Gen. Albert Gallatin Lawrence, a Civil War hero; Abraham Riker Lawrence, a State Supreme Court justice who was related to the Rikers of Rikers Island, and John L. Lawrence, the first president of the Croton Aqueduct.</p>
        <p>Eventually the Lawrences expanded their burial grounds to another site in Bayside, which is run by the Bayside Historical Society.</p>
        <p>The public apparently knows little about the Astoria site. References to famous Lawrences can be found on the Internet, but their burial places are listed as unknown.</p>
        <p>''I thought somebody would help along the line, but they never have,'' Mr. Sheehan said. ''Maybe I just never knew how to ask.''</p>
        <p>The Queens borough historian Stanley Cogan has a special interest in preserving family cemeteries, but he said he realized that obtaining financing for graveyard preservation was difficult. Several months ago, he got financing for a brief exploratory dig at the Jackson-Moore cemetery in Jackson Heights, which belonged to two wealthy families known for their loyalties to the English crown. When Mr. Sheehan heard about the dig, he was shocked. ''The Jackson-Moore cemetery is full of Tories,'' he said. ''These people,'' he added, gesturing to the tombstones in his graveyard, ''are American heroes.''</p>
        <p>E. E. LIPPINCOTT</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: ASTORIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
