<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Student, the Sleuth and the Mysterious Pillow</title>
    <meta content="17FEAT$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231322"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheng, Yao</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crow, Kelly</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFDD1138F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Student, the Sleuth and the Mysterious Pillow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KELLY CROW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crow, Kelly</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on bizarre tale of Yao Cheng, a Columbia University biology whiz, the radioactive pillow found in her apartment in February doused with phosphorus-32 and the attempts by university to keep detailed secret; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YAO CHENG wears no scarlet letter. When she crisscrosses the campus of Columbia University these days, she blends in easily with the fresh-faced students scurrying to class. She, too, is young, just 25, and pretty and smart. But along with her armful of books, Ms. Cheng carries the whisper of scandal and, possibly, the clue to a mystery. Until two months ago, this mystery barred her from setting foot on College Walk. It involved her radioactive pillow.</p>
        <p>Stories often circulate about brilliant students who, for one reason or the other, cannot cope with pressure-cooker universities. Because universities, fearing copycats or bad publicity, tend to play down the crimes or theatrics of such desperate students, these situations are often cloaked in mystery and rumor. When the students are foreign, and suddenly submerged in a new culture, the tangles can thicken.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YAO CHENG wears no scarlet letter. When she crisscrosses the campus of Columbia University these days, she blends in easily with the fresh-faced students scurrying to class. She, too, is young, just 25, and pretty and smart. But along with her armful of books, Ms. Cheng carries the whisper of scandal and, possibly, the clue to a mystery. Until two months ago, this mystery barred her from setting foot on College Walk. It involved her radioactive pillow.</p>
        <p>Stories often circulate about brilliant students who, for one reason or the other, cannot cope with pressure-cooker universities. Because universities, fearing copycats or bad publicity, tend to play down the crimes or theatrics of such desperate students, these situations are often cloaked in mystery and rumor. When the students are foreign, and suddenly submerged in a new culture, the tangles can thicken.</p>
        <p>But to an outsider, the bizarre story of the biology whiz Yao Cheng and the radioactive pillow, found in her apartment in February and doused with phosphorus-32, seemed impenetrable. Pieces of the puzzle made headlines and the evening news, but Columbia kept the details muffled. Those who knew what really happened were afraid or reluctant to talk publicly. Others were bound by legal restraints and could not speak at all.</p>
        <p>Wild theories floated in hallways throughout spring and summer. One was that Ms. Cheng had bowed to the grueling pressure of her graduate program and poisoned the pillow herself. But who would knowingly sleep on radiation? The notion was chilling.</p>
        <p>And yet here she is, back on campus alongside 20,000 other Columbia students who started classes Sept. 5. She will graduate next month.</p>
        <p>What really happened?</p>
        <p>Through it all, Yao Cheng has protested her innocence. And in every telling, she has started her version of the story the same way.</p>
        <p>It was late afternoon on Feb. 8 when she and her partner in the biology lab finished an experiment and a Geiger counter started ticking. It sounded like a cooking timer, only slower and less steady. It began the instant Ms. Cheng peeled off her rubber gloves and put her hands above the counter.</p>
        <p>Such screenings are mandatory after working with radiation, but the two women were startled by the ticking. Her partner waved the wandlike attachment close over Ms. Cheng's fingers. The counter registered radiation levels four times as high as normal.</p>
        <p>''Go wash your hands,'' the partner said, trying to sound calm. Ms. Cheng scrubbed her hands and returned for another sweep. ''Still hot,'' the partner said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cheng ran into the lab of her primary instructor, Lili Yamasaki. Concerned by the news, Dr. Yamasaki checked Ms. Cheng's entire body. Spots of radiation also popped up on her hair, chin, knees and back.</p>
        <p>''Go home, take a shower, and come back tomorrow,'' Dr. Yamasaki said. ''Your levels are high, but we'll do some more tests.''</p>
        <p>But a shower was not enough. The next day, more tests confirmed that Ms. Cheng had been slightly contaminated by a radioactive isotope, phosphorus-32. The diagnosis was especially disturbing because she had not been using P-32 in her experiment.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cheng telephoned her husband, Lei Liu, 27, a graduate student in the computer science department. Upset, he asked if she could check their West 112th Street apartment with a Geiger counter. That night, when she came home with one in hand, he opened the door of their eighth-floor apartment and half-kidding, let out a deep breath in the direction of the shoebox-size counter. A flurry of ticks followed.</p>
        <p>''What's going on?'' he gasped, his smile vanishing. ''Does that mean I swallowed it? Have I swallowed it?''</p>
        <p>As it turned out, Mr. Liu's hair and fingertips were also contaminated. Frantic now, the couple began scouring the apartment, shoving the counter into corners and hoisting it overhead. They found nothing in the tiny kitchen. Nothing in the large living room, with its teal futon and Monet posters. Nothing by the ferns and flowers Ms. Cheng lovingly tended in the corner near the television set. Nothing in the bathroom.</p>
        <p>But when they came to their bedroom, the counter gurgled to life. Ms. Cheng pointed it at the dresser and the pile of dirty clothes, and it ticked. She pointed it at the foot of the bed, and it ticked. And when she held it beside the head of their bed, the ticks became too blurred to be distinct. The couple looked at each other, bewildered.</p>
        <p>The source of the radiation, the thing that had silently poisoned them? A pillow. Their own pink pillow.</p>
        <p>How Did the Pillow Get Hot? The Inquiry Begins</p>
        <p>THE next day, George Hamawy, head of the university's Office of Radiation Safety, learned about Ms. Cheng's contamination. Mr. Hamawy, 53, a short Egyptian-American with a bushy mustache, had previously held a similar post at the Albert Einstein College of Medicine in the Bronx. He ran over to Ms. Cheng's lab in the Sherman Fairchild Center, on the campus's northeast corner. First, he made sure the labs were safe, that no radiation had been leaking and that nothing had been stolen. Everything was normal.</p>
        <p>But after lunch, Dr. Yamasaki and Ms. Cheng walked into his office and told him the strangest story he had heard since coming to Columbia five years earlier.</p>
        <p>A radioactive pillow?</p>
        <p>He sent his assistant to get the pillow, which Mr. Liu had shoved into a trash bag and placed in a closet. Once Mr. Hamawy had the bag, he cleared a space on his desk and untied the knot. The counters on his desk vibrated, all the needles quivering at the far ends of their gauges.</p>
        <p>''What the hell is going on?'' Mr. Hamawy shouted. He saw that the pillow was covered with large blotches, like sweat marks. He touched a spot in the center with a gloved finger and then ran to a counter on the far wall. He held his finger over the box, and it registered maximum readings. This radiation was easily transferred, messy.</p>
        <p>Next, he cut a small patch of pillow fabric and tested it with a liquid scintillator, which deciphers types and concentrations of isotopes. It found phosphorus-32, emitting 50 to 200 millirems an hour. Under normal circumstances, a person encounters 0.02 millirems of radioactivity an hour, or 170 millirems a year. (Health experts put the safe limit at 270 millirems a year.) So, parts of this pillow were giving off an hourly level up to 10,000 times greater than what is found in the environment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hamawy was stunned. All afternoon, he ran tests, but what he learned only puzzled him more. The surface of the pillow was  contaminated, but its innards were not. The pillowcase showed no traces of P-32. The  stains were amoeba-shaped, as though a  substance had been poured, rather than splattered. The amount of P-32 was roughly the same, 0.25 milliliters, as that in the blue vials the university stored in its many unlocked laboratory refrigerators.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Hamawy started his investigation, one fact was settled in his mind, as a report he wrote a few weeks later stated: The contamination was not accidental. He knew of recent cases at the National Institutes of Health and Massachusetts Institute of Technology in which P-32 had been put in food to poison people. But sleeping on radiation? The victim might contract cancer, but it would take years. It was not an efficient way to harm or kill.</p>
        <p>Nothing was missing from Ms. Cheng's lab, but he knew that boxes of P-32 arrived weekly for other labs for teams who were less careful. If one of their vials had been taken, it would not be missed. The incident would, however, be the first time in the city's history that a radioactive substance  had been stolen from a restricted area. Mr. Hamawy kept his investigation discreet.</p>
        <p>The next day, Feb. 11, Mr. Liu met two close friends at John Jay Cafeteria, a campus lunch spot. Mr. Liu told them he had done some research and needed their help. Phosphorus-32 is a common isotope around biology laboratories because it easily marks genetic material like DNA. It has a half-life of two weeks, meaning that every 14 days its radioactivity is cut in half.</p>
        <p>The university concluded that Mr. Liu's exposure had been short, within a few weeks at most, and that his health was in no  danger.</p>
        <p>Columbia and the city's Health Department were already conducting a joint investigation. Still, the three friends sat for hours and talked theories.</p>
        <p>First, the pillow manufacturer: some insane person had poisoned a batch.</p>
        <p>''Sue the manufacturer,'' they said. ''Sue the pillow store.''</p>
        <p>But if the pillow, which he had bought a year ago, had been tainted, it would have caused serious harm by now.</p>
        <p>''It was the subletters,'' the friends suggested. While the couple had been in China for the holiday break, they had sublet the apartment to a friend of a friend. But Mr. Liu did not suspect her.</p>
        <p>''What about a burglar?'' the two men asked. Mr. Liu was having the apartment's locks changed, but nothing had been stolen. University security told him there were no signs of a break-in.</p>
        <p>''He keeps asking us if we have any enemies,'' Mr. Liu said of Mr. Hamawy. ''I can't think of a single one. But do we?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Liu was not the sort of guy to have enemies, the friends thought. He could be shy around strangers, but he was open and humorous around his buddies, most of whom were Chinese. He was the computer guru of his department, and his maturity made him a good match for Ms. Cheng.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cheng was bright-eyed and dimpled, bubbly and talkative. Friends thought she was sometimes naive. She had met Mr. Liu at a school party three years earlier, and  soon they were inseparable, jogging in Riverside Park or reading Chinese poetry.</p>
        <p>They came from relatively similar backgrounds in China. Mr. Liu's parents taught high school science, and he had attended the celebrated Qinghua University in Beijing. Ms. Cheng's father was a heart surgeon, and her mother was an accountant; she, too, had gone to Qinghua. After a brief courtship, the two young people were secretly married at City Hall during summer 1999 and planned to wed according to Chinese custom the following year.</p>
        <p>No, the three friends concluded, there was no one enraged enough to try to poison them with radiation while they slept. If there was, he or she had hidden all the clues. Not to mention the motive.</p>
        <p>Despite the Creepy Theories, Just the Two Suspects</p>
        <p>GEORGE HAMAWY spent the next two weeks investigating the pillow case with the school detective and two members of the city's Bureau of Radiological Health. They checked every surface and scanned every item in the apartment. They went through the building's pipes and tested the water. Negative. There was no radiation anywhere, not even on bedsheets, hairbrushes, doorknobs and elevator buttons.</p>
        <p>If P-32 was so messy, why wasn't it showing up all over the place? It was as if a 20-pound bag of sand had been dumped on a bed without a single grain scattering elsewhere in the room. And that included the bodies of Ms. Cheng and Mr. Liu. The readings on their fingers and the back of their heads were only twice as high as the environment. Their skulls would have blocked most of the radiation, but their eyes would have been vulnerable. Their eyes were fine. The levels in their urine were also low. Too low, Mr. Hamawy decided, for the couple to have slept a single night on the pillow.</p>
        <p>And yet each time he interviewed them, they said they had been sleeping on the pillow for a year. Ms. Cheng wanted Mr. Hamawy to experiment with the thick pillowcase to gauge how much P-32 it could have deflected. But all he could think of was that bag of sand and the missing grains. The thickness of the pillowcase was a moot point, Mr. Hamawy concluded, and he refused to radiate it.</p>
        <p>On Feb. 22, he gave a six-page single-spaced report to the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences. In it, he laid out the inconsistencies between the story he had been told and what he had found for himself.</p>
        <p>Two days later, a messenger arrived at the couple's apartment with two letters from the university. Ms. Cheng and Mr. Liu tore them open. The news was bad. They were both suspended from using university facilities and services except medical ones. Disciplinary hearings were being scheduled, and two committees would be looking into the situation.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, they realized that despite all the creepy theories, they were the only suspects.</p>
        <p>The Tribunal's Verdict: Guilty The Penalty: Expulsion</p>
        <p>ON March 1, Yao Cheng walked into  Low Library for her hearing. She had brought nothing with her -- no lawyer, no papers -- and she was dressed casually in a sweater and jeans. In the hearing room, she saw a long conference table and a committee composed of seven professors and graduate students. Ms. Cheng sat at the head of the table, and for the next 50 minutes the committee members asked questions. Most were about the incident itself, but she was also asked about her access to the labs, which was total; and her feelings about her program, which were mixed. Then they sent her home while they questioned other witnesses, including Mr. Hamawy and Dr. Yamasaki.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cheng returned that evening for follow-up questions, but she was told the committee had no further questions for her.</p>
        <p>''If I have something to tell the committee, can I have a few minutes?'' she asked, surprised to learn that she would not be able to contest the other testimony. ''I just don't think we are done.''</p>
        <p>She was told she could have a few minutes. But as she stood before her jury, all she could think to say was, ''I would just like to express my hope that you will make a decision as soon as possible and give me a fair judgment.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Liu's hearing the next day went much the same way, except for the final act. He was questioned for four hours. But when he was repeatedly encouraged to confess, he angrily asked to be excused. All that night, he lay awake on his bed, thinking he had surely bungled his chances.</p>
        <p>By then, the press had learned about the story, and friends were calling him from as far as California. He knew it was only a matter of time before his parents found out.</p>
        <p>On March 8, the couple got another pair of letters. Ms. Cheng was expelled, and forbidden to enter the campus. Mr. Liu was exonerated, and could return to classes.</p>
        <p>The disciplinary committee had neither pinpointed the source of the radiation nor explained how the pillow was contaminated. But it had decided Ms. Cheng was responsible and Mr. Liu was not.</p>
        <p>But why would she endanger her health and her husband's? Why would she jeopardize her visa and risk being deported? Why would a woman so smart that the Mayo Clinic once offered her a full seven-year scholarship sabotage her career?</p>
        <p>Mr. Liu could not answer such questions, and so the next day he made an appointment with a lawyer, Robert Levy, recommended by a friend. On March 23, Mr. Levy filed an appeal with the university, asserting that the committee had relied on the Hamawy report rather than conducting a separate investigation. As the months passed and there was no word on the appeal, Ms. Cheng fell into a deep depression, sleeping until noon and talking to no one for days at a time. Both their parents had learned the news by watching Chinese television.</p>
        <p>Graduation time came in May, the campus emptied, and still the case dragged on. Students and teachers were still buzzing about it. The university's official comment was no comment, and Mr. Hamawy was asked not to speak publicly. His report, classified as secret but widely circulated, offered the only official theory, and it seemed as strange as the contamination itself. His first clue came on Feb. 11:</p>
        <p>''After Yao's meeting with the city inspectors, she came to my office insisting to know how much exposure she had received. I told her that it would be difficult at this point to calculate accurately the dose that she had received, especially by not knowing when the pillow was contaminated. I asked her what would she do if we find out that she received a large exposure dose? Her answer came fast, that she would change her major. I inquired further about that. She revealed that if we find out that she received a large dose, she would not stay in the biology department, with a potential of further exposure, but she would change her major to a school such as the business school.''</p>
        <p>Of the next day, he wrote: ''Yao also, in the course of questioning that day, stated that she was not happy as a student in the biology department and that she would rather be in the business school. She was asked that if she was so interested in the business school, why she did not apply to the business school? She replied that she does not have a scholarship for the business school as she does for the biology department. Furthermore, she mentioned that if she would leave the biology department without being enrolled in another school, she would lose her visa status and would be deported.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hamawy surmised that Ms. Cheng wanted to appear overexposed so she would no longer be allowed to work with radiation. He then interviewed her colleagues and adviser, and they told a similar story: Ms. Cheng was progressing poorly on her lab project, studying how certain genes affect cancer in mice, and the lack of results had frustrated her and her adviser.</p>
        <p>In the world of scientific research, the relationship between graduate student and adviser is a complex, familial one. Advisers decide when students have progressed far enough in their research to graduate, and advisers help them get jobs. For doctoral students, the third year of a five-year program is the crucial year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cheng was in the middle of her third year. After a while, Mr. Hamawy determined that she never wanted to hurt anyone, least of all herself. She had stolen the P-32, he concluded, because she wanted to find a way to step easily and honorably out of the only world she knew. That desire, he decided, had made her desperate.</p>
        <p>After the Ordeal, Trying to Reclaim a Life</p>
        <p>LEI LIU and Yao Cheng, of course, never sanctioned that theory. Ridiculous, they said. Ms. Cheng loved biology, she insisted; she was the victim. Her friends believed her, and so did some classmates.</p>
        <p>But in the end, it did not matter. After private negotiations with the school, Mr. Levy won his appeal. On July 5, with little fanfare, Columbia released this statement:</p>
        <p>''Columbia University has rescinded the dismissal of Yao Cheng from the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, as the result of an agreement between Ms. Cheng and the university. Ms. Cheng will be continuing her studies at the university this summer and will receive the Master of Philosophy degree in biological sciences in October 2000.''</p>
        <p>It was not the apology or vindication the couple had sought. Columbia did not admit procedural misconduct or confirm her innocence. Her reinstatement also came with conditions: Ms. Cheng would not discuss the settlement or sue the university or go near her old laboratories, whose refrigerators had been outfitted with new locks.</p>
        <p>Close friends said she also abandoned plans to get her doctorate, and that her husband had scaled back his studies and was hunting for a job.</p>
        <p>''It's good news, but we had hoped it would be better,'' said one close friend of the couple. ''Her mood is much better, though. Over time, they will try to carry on.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Cheng can still be found walking around campus or sitting in her spotless apartment, the air of a martyr about her. Her dark hair, once short and bluntly cut, is shoulder-length and shaggy, and her eyes are weary and guarded. In a phone conversation a couple of weeks ago, she said she was satisfied with her reinstatement. She and Mr. Liu would not say much more.</p>
        <p>She knows some people think she poured radiation on her pillow, but she also hopes a few will remember why she came to the United States and Columbia in the first place: to build a life and a career for herself and, maybe, to find a cure for cancer.</p>
        <p>''Now,'' she said, speaking quietly and deliberately, ''I just want to forget about this whole thing as soon as possible.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
