<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Struggling Gators Team Up to Shock Vols</title>
    <meta content="Y17VOL0AD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/sports/17VOLS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231461"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Florida</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Tennessee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E6D81F38F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Struggling Gators Team Up to Shock Vols</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>KNOXVILLE, Tenn., Sept. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Florida defeats Tennessee, 27-23, in college football (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They were an unlikely pair to bail out Florida: a quarterback who had perhaps lost his nerve and a wide receiver who indeed had lost his scholarship. But that was what Jesse Palmer and Jabar Gaffney did in the final 2 minutes 14 seconds here today against Tennessee in what is annually the most important game on the Southeastern Conference schedule.</p>
        <p>The Gators, ranked sixth in the Associated Press poll of reporters, were trailing the No. 11 Volunteers by 3 points, and had 91 yards ahead of them and the full-throated venom of a record crowd of 108,768 at Neyland Stadium ready to battle them all the way. When Palmer, a senior whom Coach Steve Spurrier had warned all week to be good or to get ready to sit the bench, popped his head in the huddle he told his team, ''Let's make some memories.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They were an unlikely pair to bail out Florida: a quarterback who had perhaps lost his nerve and a wide receiver who indeed had lost his scholarship. But that was what Jesse Palmer and Jabar Gaffney did in the final 2 minutes 14 seconds here today against Tennessee in what is annually the most important game on the Southeastern Conference schedule.</p>
        <p>The Gators, ranked sixth in the Associated Press poll of reporters, were trailing the No. 11 Volunteers by 3 points, and had 91 yards ahead of them and the full-throated venom of a record crowd of 108,768 at Neyland Stadium ready to battle them all the way. When Palmer, a senior whom Coach Steve Spurrier had warned all week to be good or to get ready to sit the bench, popped his head in the huddle he told his team, ''Let's make some memories.''</p>
        <p>Nine plays later, when the quarterback buried a rocket in Gaffney's gut for a 3-yard touchdown with 14 seconds remaining, those sentiments were in the books and so was a 27-23 victory -- the Gators' 12th over the Volunteers in their last 15 meetings.</p>
        <p>''We stole this game,'' a relieved Spurrier said. ''Tennessee outplayed us, but we got more points.''</p>
        <p>Until the final drive, Palmer had completed 14 passes in 34 attempts for 206 yards -- numbers that his hypercritical coach usually does not  tolerate. Spurrier realized, however, that they reflected more on the unsure hands of the Gators' wide receivers, who had at least nine dropped passes.</p>
        <p>Gaffney was lucky just to be on the field at all. He was kicked off the team last December for stealing more than $500 in cash and jewelry from members of a high school team that used the Florida locker room during the state playoffs.</p>
        <p>''I told him he was finished,'' said Spurrier, who pulled Gaffney's scholarship.</p>
        <p>But Gaffney's father, Derrick, played at Florida (as well as with the  Jets in the early 1980's), as did three of his uncles, and Jabar knew he had embarrassed and disappointed his family. With his father, he appealed to Spurrier for a second chance, and vowed to return the money and play without a scholarship. In July the coach relented.</p>
        <p>On the winning drive, Palmer slung a laser to Gaffney that he pulled in on the Tennessee 38-yard line for a 33-yard gain.</p>
        <p>''I knew then we weren't going for a field goal and tie,'' said Palmer, who was 6 of 9 for 84 yards on the game-winning drive. ''I knew to keep my eyes on the field. That we were confident and the coach was going to stick with me.''</p>
        <p>Still, Palmer had to throw the game-winner twice. With 30 seconds left, he found Reche Caldwell on a quick slant pattern that appeared to be a 5-yard touchdown. Not quite -- it was called back when a Florida lineman was given a 5-yard penalty for being illegally downfield. After Palmer connected with running back Bo Carroll on a screen pass to the 3-yard line, Florida (3-0, 1-0) called a timeout with 20 seconds left.</p>
        <p>This time the Gators decided to run the slant on the other side, to Gaffney. Palmer took a quick drop and then fired to Gaffney, who had  defensive back Willie Miles behind him. Miles reached inside and knocked the ball loose, but the line judge, Al Matthews, immediately signaled touchdown. The crowd roared in disapproval and the referee Al Ford called for a conference. But moments later, he signaled that the touchdown stood.</p>
        <p>''It's irrelevant,'' Tennessee Coach Phillip Fulmer said of the officials' decision. ''The guy called it a touchdown; it is a touchdown. There were 140 other plays out there. We are not going to hang our heads on one play.''</p>
        <p>The Volunteers (1-1, 0-1) instead wondered how four first-half drives that penetrated Florida's 20-yard line yielded only field goals by Alex Walls. One of the drives was stopped at the 6-yard line, another at the 1 and a third at the 2.</p>
        <p>Even with A. J. Suggs (17 of 29, 140 yards passing), a redshirt freshman, making his first collegiate start, the Volunteers pushed the Gators around the field. But one goal-line situation was thwarted by Suggs's fumble, Travis Henry fumbled on third down at the 1, and the Vols ran out of time with the ball at the 2. With five seconds left in the first half, Fulmer decided to have Walls kick a 19-yard field goal on third down instead of trying to power it over from the 2-yard line.</p>
        <p>''We made too many mistakes when we had chances to get touchdowns,'' said Henry, who ran for a game-high 175 yards and scored Tennessee's only touchdown. ''We just didn't get it done.''</p>
        <p>After the game, both Palmer and Gaffney smiled at the fact that they were the heroes who would be remembered in this latest edition of an old-fashioned rivalry. They directed their thanks to Spurrier.</p>
        <p>''I'm just grateful that Coach gave me a second chance,'' Gaffney said. ''I made a mistake and he gave me the opportunity to correct it.''</p>
        <p>And the quarterback, who had heard all week that his job was in jeopardy, offered the lesson he learned on a hard-hitting afternoon.</p>
        <p>''If you play defensively, you're going to get yanked,'' Palmer said. ''If you play like you believe in yourself, you're going to win. I did that today.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
