<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ailing Yanks Can Rest Easy As Hernandez Stops Indians</title>
    <meta content="Y17YAN$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/sports/17YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleveland Indians</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E0DA1F38F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1096" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ailing Yanks Can Rest Easy As Hernandez Stops Indians</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Cleveland Indians, 6-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Orlando Hernandez strolled from his locker to the trainer's room with so much ice wrapped around his arm from his right shoulder to his elbow that it looked as if he were lugging watermelons underneath the Ace bandages. Hernandez was preparing for his start against the Cleveland Indians by using enough ice for a small barbecue.</p>
        <p>Bernie Williams had a similar look yesterday as he wore a wrap of ice that resembled a flak jacket. Paul O'Neill sat glumly as he waited to get a cortisone shot in his right hip. Derek Jeter fell asleep inside the players' lounge, even as a Rocky movie blared in front of him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Orlando Hernandez strolled from his locker to the trainer's room with so much ice wrapped around his arm from his right shoulder to his elbow that it looked as if he were lugging watermelons underneath the Ace bandages. Hernandez was preparing for his start against the Cleveland Indians by using enough ice for a small barbecue.</p>
        <p>Bernie Williams had a similar look yesterday as he wore a wrap of ice that resembled a flak jacket. Paul O'Neill sat glumly as he waited to get a cortisone shot in his right hip. Derek Jeter fell asleep inside the players' lounge, even as a Rocky movie blared in front of him.</p>
        <p>It was that kind of lazy day for the Yankees. Another day to get ready for the postseason because, unlike the Indians, the Yankees' sizable cushion in the American League East gives them the luxury of resting players. So Williams and O'Neill tried to heal, while Jeter was given the rare chance to nap.</p>
        <p>But Hernandez pitched as some teammates rested and he was the primary reason the Yankees stomped the Indians, 6-3, on a crisp, sunny day at Yankee Stadium. Hernandez retired the first 14 batters of the game and finished with a dominating four-hitter to delight a sellout crowd of 55,097.</p>
        <p>''We need him to be right there,'' catcher Jorge Posada said. ''We did everything we could to get guys out. He was very good to catch. It was a lot of fun. He threw strikes and he was intense.''</p>
        <p>Glenallen Hill walloped a homer in the second inning, his 14th in 109 at-bats as a Yankee; Posada ripped his 26th homer, in the fifth; and Luis Sojo filled in for Jeter by doing an imitation of the shortstop with a single, a triple and three runs batted in.</p>
        <p>While Hernandez (12-11) showed he was rolling into postseason form by winning for the fourth time in his last five decisions, the Indians fell into a virtual tie for the A.L. wild card with Oakland, which beat Tampa Bay, 5-2, yesterday.</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre says Hernandez is pitching as well as he has since joining the Yankees in 1998 because he is challenging left-handed batters with fastballs and pitching economically, compliments that made the mysterious El Duque incredulous.</p>
        <p>''That's Joe Torre,'' said Hernandez, whose first words were how he refused to discuss what types of pitches he had thrown.</p>
        <p>When Hernandez was asked if he agreed with Torre, he snapped, ''I don't agree with anything.''</p>
        <p>But Sojo talked about Hernandez's mind-set heading toward October when he revealed a conversation they had two weeks ago. Hernandez, who started the playoff openers in all three rounds last season and is 5-0 with a 1.02 earned run average in the postseason, conceded that he was peeking ahead.</p>
        <p>''He's preparing for the playoffs,'' Sojo said. ''He's not about stats. He told me he's all about the postseason.''</p>
        <p>Hernandez was the last Yankee to venture onto the field yesterday, and there was polite applause soon after he emerged. Hernandez skipped over the foul line and stared at the ground for a few seconds when he reached the mound, perhaps uttering a prayer.</p>
        <p>But the Indians were the ones who needed divine intervention. Wearing long sleeves and sometimes blowing into his hand, Hernandez threw changeups early in counts, used a moving fastball and had great control while striking out six, walking none and needing 98 pitches for the complete game.</p>
        <p>Hernandez struck out Manny Ramirez to open the second and pumped a fastball past David Segui to end the inning. After he made the dangerous hitters look feeble and the Yankees scored three runs in the bottom of the inning, on Hill's homer and Sojo's two-run single off Jason Bere, the focus was solely on the pitcher.</p>
        <p>When the Yankees extended their lead to 5-0 in the fourth, the suspense was about Hernandez chasing perfection. He started the fifth by striking out Ramirez and Jim Thome, and there was anticipation that he might provide a special memory in the Bronx. But Segui lined an 0-1 pitch past second base for the first hit. Russell Branyan homered in the sixth, and Ramirez had a two-run homer in the ninth.</p>
        <p>Roger Clemens is destined to start the opener of a division series, but Hernandez will be a major factor, too. Torre would probably prefer to use Andy Pettitte in Game 2 at Yankee Stadium, which would leave Hernandez for Game 3 on the road. Torre has spoken about the importance of the third game as a swing game, and Hernandez is a comforting pitcher to have in that position. Even he has pondered it.</p>
        <p>''I think everyone that's playing in here is getting ready for the postseason,'' said Hernandez, and that notion was much more visible in his actions than in his words.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Right fielder PAUL O'NEILL looked like a Little Leaguer whose game had been rained out. After reinjuring his right hip while chasing a fly ball on Friday, O'Neill received his second shot of cortisone in three weeks yesterday. He will miss at least five more games. ''It's driving me crazy,'' O'Neill said. ''Walking into the park today, it was a beautiful day. You want to play a game.'' O'Neill was hampered with a fractured rib last October and a strained hamstring in the 1996 postseason, and he does not want to have a painful recurrence next month. ''I think it'll be gone,'' he said. . . . BERNIE WILLIAMS (strained right rib cage) will probably start today. . . . CHUCK KNOBLAUCH returned after missing Friday's game with a tender right elbow. . . . CLAY BELLINGER ended an 0-for-26 slump with a single in the second inning. . . . JORGE POSADA, with 26 home runs, said he would rather tie, not break, YOGI BERRA's team record of 30 homers for a catcher. . . . The Yankees will pass three million fans at home for the second straight year today.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
