<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; Deep Pockets: How Corzine Spent $35 Million on a Primary</title>
    <meta content="17NWRMTT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231499"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E7D71F38F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="598" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; Deep Pockets: How Corzine Spent $35 Million on a Primary</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David M. Halbfinger</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN TV commercials, Jon S. Corzine, the Wall Street multimillionaire and Democratic nominee for United States Senate, is reassuring New Jersey voters who might be concerned about the costs of his progressive social programs that he has the ''fiscal discipline of a successful businessman.''</p>
        <p>But after spending a record $35 million to defeat former Gov. Jim Florio in the primary last June, Mr. Corzine could find it difficult to make the same claim about his Senate campaign.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN TV commercials, Jon S. Corzine, the Wall Street multimillionaire and Democratic nominee for United States Senate, is reassuring New Jersey voters who might be concerned about the costs of his progressive social programs that he has the ''fiscal discipline of a successful businessman.''</p>
        <p>But after spending a record $35 million to defeat former Gov. Jim Florio in the primary last June, Mr. Corzine could find it difficult to make the same claim about his Senate campaign.</p>
        <p>Forget that the previous high for any Senate primary was $8 million or that Mr. Corzine shattered the record for an entire Senate campaign, $30.1 million, spent by Michael Huffington, the Republican who lost to Dianne Feinstein in California in 1994.</p>
        <p>Just look at how much he paid his pollster, Penn, Schoen &amp; Berland Associates: $2.6 million as of July, with more than four months until he faces his Republican opponent, Representative Bob Franks.</p>
        <p>Doug Schoen, a principal in the firm, said only half of that went for actual surveys, including a June 1999 poll that cost $115,000 and overnight tracking polls at more than $10,000 apiece. The rest paid for telephone banks to identify and court Mr. Corzine's supporters. Still, that's roughly $1.3 million for polls. In 1998, all the candidates in all 34 Senate races spent $3.4 million on polling, according to the Campaign Study Group.</p>
        <p>A New York Times analysis found that most of Mr. Corzine's money went for television and radio commercials to compensate for his oppoent's edge in name-recognition. Mr. Corzine bought $18 million in TV time. Shrum, Devine &amp; Donilon, which booked nearly all of his commercials, was paid $450,000 for producing them and received $488,000 in consulting fees. In comparison, Vice President Al Gore spent $10.8 million and George W. Bush $25.2 million in their national TV campaigns through July 31.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine gave more than $650,000 to local candidates and committees in New Jersey, in what he called party-building. He paid a single consultant $367,000 to cultivate support from labor unions, and $200,000 to a lawyer to hire a private investigator, who in turn dug up damaging material about Mr. Florio.</p>
        <p>His get-out-the-vote effort was unparalleled in the annals of walking-around money. Thousands of volunteers received $25 to $75 each to hang signs and hand out leaflets, and to canvass residents in heavily minority areas and even invite them to catered meet-and-greet affairs.</p>
        <p>The second-largest single recipient of Mr. Corzine's money was Message &amp; Media. It got $3.9 million, including $742,000 in consulting fees, $665,000 for producing and placing radio ads; and $2.2 million for producing direct mail.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Mr. Corzine, Tom Shea, mindful that a recent poll found most voters were not troubled by Mr. Corzine's spending, says it should be viewed as a measure of his commitment. ''He's willing to put his money behind the things he believes in, and he's using that money to communicate a message to the voters of New Jersey,'' Mr. Shea said. ''He's going to spend enough to get his message out.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
