<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Sheridan Square Complaint: Garbage In, But Not Enough Out</title>
    <meta content="17TOUR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231281"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: GREENWICH VILLAGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEED91038F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="386" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Sheridan Square Complaint: Garbage In, But Not Enough Out</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNY LEE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To many residents of Greenwich Village, tourists are pests. When double-decker tour buses began peering into second-story windows, for example, tenants along West Fourth Street screamed and forced some routes changed. ''The tourists are an annoyance, especially in the summer,'' said James LaVigne, who lives near Sheridan Square. ''There's too many people. It's more noise and more garbage, too.''</p>
        <p>Garbage is a sore point. To get more trash collection, local groups are asking the Sanitation Department to designate the area around Sheridan Square a tourist destination, on a par with Times Square. ''This is not some community in the middle of Sheepshead Bay in Brooklyn,'' said Arthur Strickler, district manager of Community Board 2. ''It's the Times Square of Greenwich Village, and we're not getting our fair share of city services.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To many residents of Greenwich Village, tourists are pests. When double-decker tour buses began peering into second-story windows, for example, tenants along West Fourth Street screamed and forced some routes changed. ''The tourists are an annoyance, especially in the summer,'' said James LaVigne, who lives near Sheridan Square. ''There's too many people. It's more noise and more garbage, too.''</p>
        <p>Garbage is a sore point. To get more trash collection, local groups are asking the Sanitation Department to designate the area around Sheridan Square a tourist destination, on a par with Times Square. ''This is not some community in the middle of Sheepshead Bay in Brooklyn,'' said Arthur Strickler, district manager of Community Board 2. ''It's the Times Square of Greenwich Village, and we're not getting our fair share of city services.''</p>
        <p>Peter Zimmer, a chairman of the Central Village Block Association, an advocacy group, said: ''It's like a carnival here every night. The garbage just piles all around. We should be considered a special area.''</p>
        <p>Peter Fenty, a Sanitation Department spokesman, said four more trash baskets were added to the area last weekend. But as for general trash collection, he said, his department does not distinguish between trash created by tourists and by New Yorkers. ''We base our basket collection and street cleaning services on the volume of pedestrian traffic,'' Mr. Fenty said. ''There is no special district.'' Still, he acknowledged that areas like Times Square got special treatment, but not from the city. They rely on business improvement districts for extra collection, he said. Robert Rinaolo, chairman of the Greenwich Village Chamber of Commerce, which represents some 300 local shops and businesses, said his members did not have the luxury of entering such an alliance.</p>
        <p>''With a budget surplus, the city can afford to pick up after some tourists,'' he said. ''It seems like a small step for the city to take so not everyone goes home and says the city is dirty and stinks.''</p>
        <p>DENNY LEE</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: GREENWICH VILLAGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
