<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Everyday Plastic, Spun Into Gold</title>
    <meta content="17CARD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/business/17CARD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231312"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tanner, Jane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE5DE1138F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Everyday Plastic, Spun Into Gold</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE TANNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tanner, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on proliferation of credit card company reward programs, which is encouraging consumers to use credit cards instead of cash or bank checks for small purchases; photo; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT wasn't too long ago that credit cards were reserved primarily for major purchases like furniture, appliances or fine jewelry. But these days, many a consumer routinely pulls out plastic for a cup of coffee, a movie ticket or even a cab ride.</p>
        <p>More people are using credit cards instead of cash or bank checks, and more card issuers are encouraging that behavior, offering reward points to customers for each dollar charged. Depending on the program, those points can be traded for airline tickets, hotel accommodations, gift certificates or even a Mario Lemieux hockey stick. Last year, nearly 17 percent of all consumer purchases were made with credit cards, according to Credit Card News, which tracks the industry, compared with 10 percent in 1993.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT wasn't too long ago that credit cards were reserved primarily for major purchases like furniture, appliances or fine jewelry. But these days, many a consumer routinely pulls out plastic for a cup of coffee, a movie ticket or even a cab ride.</p>
        <p>More people are using credit cards instead of cash or bank checks, and more card issuers are encouraging that behavior, offering reward points to customers for each dollar charged. Depending on the program, those points can be traded for airline tickets, hotel accommodations, gift certificates or even a Mario Lemieux hockey stick. Last year, nearly 17 percent of all consumer purchases were made with credit cards, according to Credit Card News, which tracks the industry, compared with 10 percent in 1993.</p>
        <p>The card issuers are also reaping many rewards. Their earnings and stock prices are up, and their charge-offs are down, partly because of sustained low unemployment and declining personal bankruptcies. Industry analysts say three major indicators of a healthy credit card market may now be in place: a strong economy, stable interest rates and market consolidation.</p>
        <p>''It's the magic elixir,'' said Michael J. Freudenstein, who follows the sector for J. P. Morgan Securities.</p>
        <p>So far this year, stock prices of the top 10  credit card issuers have climbed 28.6 percent, on average, while the shares of companies engaged primarily in the credit card business rose 36 percent, according to a J. P. Morgan sector index.</p>
        <p>The Internet is also helping the industry. Online retail sales reached $20 billion last year in the United States and are expected to grow to $144 billion in three years, according to Forrester Research. ''The Internet and the credit card are a perfect match,''  said Bjorn J. Turnquist, a research director at SNL Securities.</p>
        <p>And while some market experts suggest that the card industry may be dragged down by a saturation of offerings and an anticipated deterioration in credit quality next year,  others predict that the industry will strengthen, partly because consumers are so comfortable with plastic. ''The whole idea of 'buy now, pay later' is very appealing to the American public,'' said Michael Schneider, an analyst at Standard &amp; Poor's Equity Group. ''Consumer spending patterns have been strong and have surprised a lot of people.''</p>
        <p>In Standard &amp; Poor's latest report on the sector, the favored players are American Express, Capital One Financial, Citigroup, MBNA, Morgan Stanley Dean Witter and Providian Financial. Earlier this month, Chase Manhattan was a favored stock, too, but the announcement last week of Chase's $30.9 billion plan to acquire J. P. Morgan prompted S.&amp; P. to downgrade the stock.</p>
        <p>Analysts say American Express -- whose stock, now at $59.31, is near a 52-week high  -- has done well with new revolving credit products. Its earnings grew 14 percent in the first half of the year. Next month, it plans to offer new products geared toward online use, including one that provides shoppers with disposable account numbers for more secure Internet purchases.</p>
        <p>Analysts added that American Express, as well as the the Discover card from Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, could benefit if the Justice Department prevails in its antitrust lawsuit against Visa and MasterCard. The government says the two, the world's largest credit card networks with a combined 75 percent of the $1.3 trillion market, limit competition through exclusive arrangements with bank networks. The trial ended last month, and a decision is expected next month. If Visa and MasterCard lose, banks in the networks would be free to issue American Express and Discover cards.</p>
        <p>Standard &amp; Poor's predicted that MBNA, an aggressive marketer of affinity cards, those aligned with clubs or organizations,  would sign up more groups and grow through acquisitions, much as it did in August when it bought First Union's $5.5 billion credit card portfolio. S.&amp; P. estimated that earnings per share would increase about 20 percent a year over the next three years.</p>
        <p>But Vincent Daniel, an analyst at CIBC World Markets, was not as bullish. He said MBNA carried the most debt, which increased its risks.</p>
        <p>Capital One Financial is considered the leader in mining databases for information about potential card holders. The company offers thousands of card options with varying interest rates, based on spending patterns and other consumer characteristics. ''That is a key to this game and they know how to do it better than anyone else,'' said Mr. Turnquist of SNL Securities.</p>
        <p>S.&amp; P. expects Capital One to sign up at least a million new accounts this year through Internet marketing.</p>
        <p>Providian Financial is also considered strong in scrutinizing large databases and offering cards based on profiles, including poor credit histories. S.&amp; P. expects growth in the company's credit accounts as well as a 25 percent increase in annual earnings per share over the next two to three years.</p>
        <p>CITIGROUP is favored by S.&amp; P. because of its huge customer base, which is likely to expand further as a result of its recently announced deal to acquire Associates First Capital.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schneider expects the strong competitors to take market share from other contenders, like Household International, CompuCredit, CIT Group and Metris. But Mr. Freudenstein likes the prospects of CompuCredit, which went public in 1999 and mines the niche of customers whose credit histories are slightly tarnished. CompuCredit has signed an agreement with Fleet Credit Card Services to look at Fleet's rejected  card applicants and assess whether to give them CompuCredit cards. For each customer that CompuCredit signs on, Fleet gets a referral fee.</p>
        <p>INVESTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
