<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anne Carman, E. J. May</title>
    <meta content="17CARM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARMAN, ANNE COLBY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAY, EDWARD JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E1DA1038F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="511" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anne Carman, E. J. May</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anne Colby Carman, a daughter of Linda Wemyss Carman of Williamstown, Mass., and Edward Caton Carman Jr. of Boston, was married yesterday to Edward John May, a son of Annette and James Francis May of Jamesburg, N.J. The Rev. Peter T. Elvin performed the ceremony at St. John's Episcopal Church in Williamstown.</p>
        <p>The bride, 29, is a sales specialist for Pharmacia Corporation, a pharmaceutical company in Peapack, N.J. She graduated magna cum laude from Harvard. Her father owns the Concord Square Development Company, a real estate company in Boston. Her mother is a general assignment reporter with The Advocate, a weekly newspaper in Williamstown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anne Colby Carman, a daughter of Linda Wemyss Carman of Williamstown, Mass., and Edward Caton Carman Jr. of Boston, was married yesterday to Edward John May, a son of Annette and James Francis May of Jamesburg, N.J. The Rev. Peter T. Elvin performed the ceremony at St. John's Episcopal Church in Williamstown.</p>
        <p>The bride, 29, is a sales specialist for Pharmacia Corporation, a pharmaceutical company in Peapack, N.J. She graduated magna cum laude from Harvard. Her father owns the Concord Square Development Company, a real estate company in Boston. Her mother is a general assignment reporter with The Advocate, a weekly newspaper in Williamstown.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 37, is known as E. J. He is the senior legal analyst in the corporate secretary's office at the Philip Morris Companies in New York. He graduated from Clarion University of Pennsylvania. His mother retired as a pension consultant at Northeast Consulting, an employee benefits company in Cranford, N.J. His father retired as a director of computer systems at CBS Inc. in New York.</p>
        <p>January 1998 was a winter of discontent for Ms. Carman. She had just ended a long-term relationship. A close friend, Beth Andrews, mentioned a brother-in-law, who was, she said, ''good looking and considerate.''</p>
        <p>''Now is probably not a really good time to be set up with anybody,'' Ms. Carman recalled replying, and the matter seemed to drop.</p>
        <p>Then last summer, Ms. Andrews invited her brother-in-law, Mr. May, to Hope Acres in Stockton, N.J., the stable where Ms. Carman keeps her horse. In the stable, he fell into conversation with her. ''I was especially struck by her confidence, which I think comes from having grown up around 1,200-pound beasts,'' he remembered. ''You have to show confidence to get their respect.''</p>
        <p>After that, Mr. May made a point of being at the stable, ostensibly to watch Ms. Andrews ride, but really to watch Ms. Carman.</p>
        <p>She thought he was cute and enjoyed their chats, but both agree that the turning point came six weekends later, when both attended a horse show at Pleasant Hollow, a training center in Coopersburg, Pa.</p>
        <p>''At end of the show, I thought, 'Wouldn't it be nice to have someone ride back to the barn with me?'' Ms. Carman remembered. ''So I asked him.''</p>
        <p>He didn't hesitate at the prospect of a 90-minute drive with a four-horse trailer. By the time Ms. Carman's pick-up truck rumbled to a stop at the stable, they had reached a comfort level.</p>
        <p>They put the horses in the stable and cleaned out the trailer together. Then, in a gesture of bonding best understood by equestrians, Mr. May cleaned her saddle and bridle.</p>
        <p>''I didn't even ask,'' Ms. Carman recalled, ''And I said to myself: 'Look at that. What a find!' ''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
