<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Calls for U.S. Aid to Improve Staffing at Nursing Homes</title>
    <meta content="17RADI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/politics/17RADI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231412"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nursing Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nursing and Nurses</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grassley, Charles E (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Nursing and Nurses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nursing Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nursing and Nurses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4DC1F38F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="586" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Calls for U.S. Aid to Improve Staffing at Nursing Homes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton, holding nursing home understaffing endangers some patients, urges Congress to provide $1 billion in grants to states over next five years to enable homes to hire and train more nurses and nurses' aides, radio speech; responds to pressure from Sen Charles E Grassley, other members of Congress (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton said today that nursing homes were so understaffed that many patients were endangered, and he asked Congress to provide more money to enable homes to hire and train more nurses and nurses' aides.</p>
        <p>The proposal comes in response to pressure from members of Congress, especially Senator Charles E. Grassley, the Iowa Republican who is chairman of the Special Committee on Aging.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton said today that nursing homes were so understaffed that many patients were endangered, and he asked Congress to provide more money to enable homes to hire and train more nurses and nurses' aides.</p>
        <p>The proposal comes in response to pressure from members of Congress, especially Senator Charles E. Grassley, the Iowa Republican who is chairman of the Special Committee on Aging.</p>
        <p>In his weekly radio address, Mr. Clinton said he would send legislation to Congress next week to provide $1 billion in grants to states over the next five years to increase staffing at the nation's nursing homes.</p>
        <p>States could use the money to to help the homes recruit, train and retain workers.</p>
        <p>''Of all the obligations we owe to one another,'' Mr. Clinton said, ''our most sacred duty is to our parents. They kept us safe from harm when we were children. We must do the same for them as they grow older.''</p>
        <p>In a report to Congress in July, the Department of Health and Human Services said that 54 percent of nursing homes fall below a proposed minimum standard of an average of at least two hours a day of care for residents by nurses' aides.</p>
        <p>The report also said inadequate staffing has contributed to an increase in severe bedsores, malnutrition and abnormal weight loss among nursing home residents. Many are hospitalized for life-threatening infections, dehydration, congestive heart failure and other problems that could have been prevented with more employees, the study said.</p>
        <p>Before adjourning next month, Congress is expected to increase Medicare payments to nursing homes and other health care providers, to offset some of the cuts made in 1997. President Clinton said today that he would insist that Congress approve his new proposals as part of such legislation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton asked Congress to require immediate payment of fines imposed on nursing homes for endangering patients.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said nursing homes can now avoid payment for years during appeals. His proposal would require immediate payments, with refunds and interest if an appeal succeeded.</p>
        <p>Fines collected from nursing homes would be used to help finance the proposed new program for the training of nurses' aides.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton also proposed today that nursing homes be required to post detailed information about the number of nurses and nurses' aides who care for patients at different times of day. Such information would be posted on a government Web site as well.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton also ordered the Department of Health and Human Services to develop rules for nursing home staffing levels.</p>
        <p>About 1.6 million people are in 17,000 nursing homes nationwide. Ninety-five percent of the homes participate in Medicaid or Medicare and are subject to federal standards.</p>
        <p>Under a 1987 federal law, nursing homes must have enough staff to enable each patient to achieve ''the highest practicable physical, mental and psychosocial well-being.'' The law does not specify minimum or appropriate staffing.</p>
        <p>Toby S. Edelman, a lawyer at the Center for Medicare Advocacy, which represents patients, and Alan E. DeFend, a spokesman for the American Health Care Association, which represents nursing homes, welcomed the proposal to increase staff levels. But Mr. DeFend said the industry opposed Mr. Clinton's effort to require immediate payment of some fines levied on nursing homes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
