<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mexican Modern: Back to a Future That Fell Behind</title>
    <meta content="17GOLD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/arts/17GOLD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231061"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Amero, Emilio</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bravo, Lola Alvarez</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bravo, Manuel Alvarez</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jimenez, Augustin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Covarrabuias, Rosa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldberg, Vicki</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E7D81738F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mexican Modern: Back to a Future That Fell Behind</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VICKI GOLDBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goldberg, Vicki</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vicki Goldberg reviews abstract Mexican photography by Emilio Amero, Lola Alvarez Bravo, Manuel Alvarez Bravo, Augustin Jimenez and Rosa Covarrubias, mostly from late 1920's and early 1930's, on view at Mexical Cultural Institute in New York City; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE was a point between the two world wars when politics and economics pushed experimental modernism in the visual arts into a corner or simply squashed it in the Soviet Union, Germany, Italy and America. For a while in the 1920's the modernist adventure was still going full throttle. Although many artists in Europe and the United States pulled back toward stylistic reason and classicism immediately after the chaos of World War I, avant-garde experiments like Dada, Suprematism, abstraction and Surrealism continued to strike sparks in much of Europe and the U.S.S.R. in the 1920's and even in the 1930's where dictators did not forbid them or social causes overshadow them.  Mexico was a special case. Early 20th-century art movements had a negligible influence there before the 1920's. Just when they began to have an effect, the Mexican muralist movement spread across the country's walls and by its artistic power, nationalistic appeal and its very size and visibility, marginalized the modernist currents pulsing through the country.</p>
        <p>The muralist movement, set in motion by a government plan for the ''Salvation and Regeneration of Mexico Through Culture'' in 1920, ignored European currents like Cubism and abstraction. Diego Rivera, who had been a Cubist for several years in Europe before turning away from it, devised a mural style that combined realism, primitivism, myth and politics. Neither Jose Clemente Orozco nor David Alfaro Siqueiros paid any more attention to Cubism or abstraction than he did.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE was a point between the two world wars when politics and economics pushed experimental modernism in the visual arts into a corner or simply squashed it in the Soviet Union, Germany, Italy and America. For a while in the 1920's the modernist adventure was still going full throttle. Although many artists in Europe and the United States pulled back toward stylistic reason and classicism immediately after the chaos of World War I, avant-garde experiments like Dada, Suprematism, abstraction and Surrealism continued to strike sparks in much of Europe and the U.S.S.R. in the 1920's and even in the 1930's where dictators did not forbid them or social causes overshadow them.  Mexico was a special case. Early 20th-century art movements had a negligible influence there before the 1920's. Just when they began to have an effect, the Mexican muralist movement spread across the country's walls and by its artistic power, nationalistic appeal and its very size and visibility, marginalized the modernist currents pulsing through the country.</p>
        <p>The muralist movement, set in motion by a government plan for the ''Salvation and Regeneration of Mexico Through Culture'' in 1920, ignored European currents like Cubism and abstraction. Diego Rivera, who had been a Cubist for several years in Europe before turning away from it, devised a mural style that combined realism, primitivism, myth and politics. Neither Jose Clemente Orozco nor David Alfaro Siqueiros paid any more attention to Cubism or abstraction than he did.</p>
        <p>And yet experimentalism did spring up and never died in Mexico; it just stayed in the shade. A glimpse of vanguard modernism in photography, which has been studiously neglected (and probably largely unknown) by historians, may be caught in the gallery of the Mexican Cultural Institute on East 39th street, in a quiet and elegant little show called ''Otras Cosas: Abstract Photography.'' Malin Barth is the curator of this exhibition of 27 images by Emilio Amero, Lola Alvarez Bravo, Manuel Alvarez Bravo, Augustin Jimenez and Rosa Covarrubias, most from the late 1920's and early 1930's, a few from the 1950's. A brief catalog is available.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alvarez Bravo, born in 1902 and by far the best known of the five, is widely recognized as a major player in early modernist photography as well as a vital influence on Mexican photography. His most familiar images, taken on the street, distill the commonplace experiences of a Mexican city into moments pregnant with potential and resonant with mystery.</p>
        <p>Less well known are his modernist experiments with abstraction and ambiguous details in the 1920's, which first brought him to public attention in Mexico in 1928. For a series of ''Paper Games,'' Mr. Alvarez Bravo let his adding machine spew out paper tape that wound itself into unforeseeable shapes, and then photographed the results close up. In 1931 he won first prize in a contest sponsored by the Tolteca Cement Company with a photograph that is at once a geometric exercise and an index to information about the subject. A trapezoidal form, actually a cement wall that recedes too rapidly, stands on a slanted bed of crushed pebbles used for making cement. The dark background, punctuated by lighter diagonal lines, is the ceiling of the cement factory. Mr. Alvarez Bravo's lens turns both site and process into spare emblems of modernity.</p>
        <p>He taught photography to his first wife, Lola Alvarez Bravo (1907-1993), and she made a career of it, keeping his name after they divorced. She is the late comer in this show; though she was photographing by the mid-1930's, most of her pictures then were portraits and street work. The selection here is of landscapes taken in the 1940's and 1950's; they are less devoted to the principles of abstraction than some of the other images in ''Otras Cosas,'' though they immerse the viewer in roots and leaves and branches without horizon, beginning or end.</p>
        <p>As a muralist, Emilio Amero (1901-1976) assisted Rivera and Orozco; later he made experimental films and earned most of his reputation as a lithographer. In the early 1930's he made photograms, a cameraless technique thought of as a pre-eminently modern way to make the familiar strange. Amero experimented with the process and produced an unusual range of tones by exposing the paper to light in the darkroom several times -- most photograms are exposed only once -- and changing the light's intensity. His rigorously constructed compositions, mostly of mass-manufactured objects like gears and springs, include cut-out shapes as well as actual objects placed on the emulsion and proclaim their modernism by technique, composition and the use of machine parts and utilitarian products.</p>
        <p>Augustin Jimenez's (1901-1974) photographs were shown in America and London between 1929 and 1931 to good reviews. He subsequently devoted himself to cinema, collaborating with Sergei Eisenstein and working with Bunuel as well as making some films on his own. In this show, his photographs from around 1931 concentrate on repetitive elements that form patterns when ripped out of context: the spines of a cactus, a line of rifles on a rack, the open-work shadows of some sort of umbrella.</p>
        <p>Rosa Covarrubias (1895-1970), wife of the painter and illustrator Miguel Covarrubias, played with photograms in a manner so different from Amero's that it might be called -- at risk of sounding politically incorrect -- feminine modern. Two of her images begin with drawings of herself in the nude and add emblematic objects like shells, a sunburst, a Mexican ceramic animal, a goblet turned upside down to make the outline of a full-skirted dress that does not obscure her naked body. One photogram of a glass, lace and a butterfly could certainly have been made by a man, but in the context of her other work it looks like a riff on feminine preoccupations. She won third prize in the Tolteca competition, reportedly with the most abstract composition of all.</p>
        <p>Covarrubias was a striking woman even with her clothes on, and Edward Weston took her portrait more than once. He and Tina Modotti, who had moved to Mexico together in 1923, taught her photography. How well she learned the lesson is evident from her photogram of a halved cabbage, most likely made after Weston had left Mexico and certainly before his extreme close-up of a halved artichoke, which it strongly resembles.</p>
        <p>All of this work follows modernist dictates, even regarding experiment, with an air of assurance, suggesting on the basis of limited material that photographic modernism had a respectable outpost in Mexico at the time. The surprise is that it exists in some quantity, since so little of it has been seen here.</p>
        <p>Modernism came to Mexico from abroad. In photography, and to some degree in painting, Weston and Modotti were primary influences (though Covarrubias probably learned about photograms in Europe in 1926 when she became friends with Man Ray). In the 1920's and 1930's, several outstanding foreign photographers, including Weston, Modotti, Paul Strand and Henri Cartier-Bresson (and Eisenstein), worked for a time in Mexico, and their presence enriched the culture of that country, if not as greatly as it enriched the culture of the visitors.</p>
        <p>The beginning of the 1920's, when modern art had its first appreciable impact on Mexico, was almost the exact moment of the muralist movement's embrace of goals quite unlike those of the European avant-garde. There was a divide between the two Mexican artistic impulses, with some artists feeling that no matter how passionate they were about their country's history, art had other purposes.</p>
        <p>By the end of the 1920's the mural movement was so dominant that it had inspired a backlash; still, it got the lion's share of attention. Modern art was already too entrenched in the Western world to be stifled (except in the places where it was outlawed), but it could be pushed out of the spotlight. During the Depression, when the United States elevated documentary above all other forms of art and exalted realism, putting photography in a primary position, art for art's sake and much of modernism were shunted into the wings.  Which is not to say that either modernism or abstraction vanished, only that they were relegated to the sidelines. Or worse. Photographers who did not direct their cameras at social ills sometimes found themselves on the defensive.</p>
        <p>The issue of art for art's sake versus art as evangelism, education or propaganda recurs periodically. Realism overpowered abstraction and its relatives in the 1920's and 1930's wherever nationalism, social utopianism, propaganda -- even, sometimes, humanitarianism -- became primary objectives. In the Soviet Union, where art for art versus art for social ends was vigorously debated, there was a rare and mystical moment of belief, Malevich being its chief representative, that abstraction could change life for the masses in the new nation. The Soviets didn't buy it, and indeed it is not so easy today to imagine the peasants achieving a new society under the impetus of Malevich's colorful geometric forms.</p>
        <p>Mexican artists opted for realism before the U.S.S.R. did, and for different reasons, yet in Mexico, as in most other places, there were otras cosas, art movements that persisted outside the mainstream. There are always brave souls stubbornly, persistently swimming against the current, and though history may inundate them and hide them from view for a time, it can also retrieve them once more from the deep.</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
