<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Region/Westchester; Million-Dollar Condos on the Hudson in Dobbs Ferry</title>
    <meta content="17WCZO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231112"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dobbs Ferry (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vizard, Mary Mcaleer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E0DB1538F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1185" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Region/Westchester; Million-Dollar Condos on the Hudson in Dobbs Ferry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARY McALEER VIZARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vizard, Mary Mcaleer</byline>
      <dateline>DOBBS FERRY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Livingston Ridge, 24-unit luxury condominium development on steep waterfront site overlooking Hudson River in Dobbs Ferry, NY, where apartment prices average $1 million; photo; map (In the Region/Westchester) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A DIFFICULT site, a resourceful developer and the current flush times in the real estate market have come together in a condominium project now rising on a steep waterfront site overlooking the Hudson River where apartment prices average $1 million.</p>
        <p>Called Livingston Ridge, the 24-unit development is being billed as ''the most expensive condominium in Westchester.'' Some units will have elevators that open directly into 3,215-square-foot apartments, said Martin Ginsburg, president of Ginsburg Development, of Hawthorne, which is developing the project. ''They're so large, they're like houses in the air,'' he said ''It's the kind of thing you see in Manhattan, but it's never been tried in Westchester before.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A DIFFICULT site, a resourceful developer and the current flush times in the real estate market have come together in a condominium project now rising on a steep waterfront site overlooking the Hudson River where apartment prices average $1 million.</p>
        <p>Called Livingston Ridge, the 24-unit development is being billed as ''the most expensive condominium in Westchester.'' Some units will have elevators that open directly into 3,215-square-foot apartments, said Martin Ginsburg, president of Ginsburg Development, of Hawthorne, which is developing the project. ''They're so large, they're like houses in the air,'' he said ''It's the kind of thing you see in Manhattan, but it's never been tried in Westchester before.''</p>
        <p>Due to the difficulty of the development's two-and-a-half-acre site, which is on a steep slope rising 100 feet from the Metro-North railroad tracks to Livingston Street, the developer had to design a range of housing configurations to fit the topography.</p>
        <p>There are 14 two-  and three-bedroom attached town houses, ranging from 2,870 to 3,606 square feet. And the centerpieces of the project are two midrise buildings with seven levels on the river side and two on the other side and a total of 10 units. The buildings have elevators that open directly into the two-bedroom apartments. ''The elevators in each building will service three homes each,'' Mr. Ginsburg said. Included are two penthouses, with 5,000 square feet each, which will have separate entrances.</p>
        <p>''We came up with the idea of apartments primarily because it was a way to fit the housing into the hill,'' Mr. Ginsburg said. ''The apartments all have floor-to-ceiling windows on the river side so everyone can take advantage of the wonderful views.''</p>
        <p>The site plan for the entire project, Mr. Ginsburg added, was designed to ensure that all the housing had views of the river. ''That's really what we're selling here,'' he said. In addition, all units have eat-in kitchens with center islands; granite counter tops; marble bathrooms; family rooms with fireplaces; and garages for two to three cars.</p>
        <p>Since sales opened last year, 17 units have been sold, Mr. Ginsburg said. Eight units have been completed and four families are now living there. Ten units are under construction. Prices range from $750,000 for a two-bedroom town house to $1.5 million for a penthouse apartment.</p>
        <p>Dobbs Ferry's mayor, Brian Monahan, said that while he supported the need for condominium development, he did not think Livingston Ridge would do much to fill the village's needs. ''We don't have many condominiums available now,'' the mayor said. ''And a lot of people who sell their homes would like to remain in the village and can't due to a lack of availability. But these units are only for people who have been very successful in their careers. They serve a very specialized market.''</p>
        <p>''Most buyers so far are empty-nesters,'' Mr. Ginsburg said. ''They come for the river.'' Barbara Ginsberg, an elementary-school teacher, and her husband, Henry, a professor of medicine at Columbia University, were the first to move into Livingston Ridge.</p>
        <p>The couple had been living at another Ginsburg development in Greenburgh, called Boulder Ridge. ''When we heard they were building condominiums on the water, we called up immediately and asked them to hold a unit for us,'' Ms. Ginsberg said. ''We liked where we were, but I couldn't resist being directly on the Hudson. It's so incredible.''</p>
        <p>Livingston Ridge is one of two condominium projects being built in Dobbs Ferry. The other is the Landing, a 104-unit complex, also on the Hudson. Prices there, for two-  and three-bedroom town-house units, are expected to be from $409,900 to $599,900.</p>
        <p>''I expect that those condos will sell as soon as they're ready,'' said Sarah Hughes, an associate broker for Houlihan/Lawrence, in Tarrytown. ''That's the price range most people are looking for. Livingston Ridge is more specialized; no one has come into the office looking for units there.''</p>
        <p>The inventory of condominiums in Westchester is at historic lows, according to a midyear report of the Westchester County Board of Realtors. At the end of the second quarter, there were only 50 on the market, a 51 percent drop from the same time last year, compared with co-ops, where there are 742 now available. But many buyers prefer condominiums because they tend to be larger and have more amenities.</p>
        <p>''Condos in all price categories are few and far between,'' Ms. Hughes said. As a result, prices have risen about 25 percent from last year. ''We have a listing now for a three-bedroom, two-and-a half-bath condo in Tarrytown for $465,000,'' Ms. Hughes said. ''Last year, the same condo would have sold for $395,000.''</p>
        <p>WHEN Joanne and and John Hogan put their condominium in Hastings on the market, it sold in a week. ''We couldn't believe it,'' she said. ''We were in contract in two weeks.'' The Hogans are now living in a rental apartment in Yonkers while waiting for their new home in Livingston Ridge to be completed. ''We were perfectly happy where we were,'' Ms. Hogan said, ''until we heard about this new complex on the water. That's what sold us.''</p>
        <p>The Hogans are typical of customers for Westchester's high-end condominiums since they also have a home in Florida. ''The people who buy the more expensive condominiums often have winter homes,'' said Robin Friedman, manager of Houlihan/ Lawrence's Irvington office. ''But they also want to be near children and family in New York.''</p>
        <p>It took seven years for Livingston Ridge to get through the approval process, primarily because it is on ''an extremely difficult piece of property,'' the mayor said. ''There were lots of environmental concerns and that held things up,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ginsburg, who has been building in Westchester for more than 35 years, said that the property ''was definitely one of the hardest sites I've ever worked with; if I had to do it over again, I might pass it up.'' To shore up the property on the steep slope, he had to build 75 feet of retaining walls, which are interspersed throughout the project. ''The housing is built using pre-stressed concrete,'' Mr. Ginsburg said. ''It's all very expensive. We had no choice but the make this a very high-end project. It's doubtful that anyone will ever duplicate it.''</p>
        <p>While it did not have to deal with a steep slope like Livingston Ridge, the Landing was mired in years of contentious debate and a decade-long approval process. ''That was far more contentious than Livingston Ridge,'' the mayor said, due mostly to claims that it was being built over a Native American archaeological site.</p>
        <p>Despite fierce community opposition, the village eventually allowed the project to go forward, and the sales office is expected to open soon. ''It's been a long haul with both of these projects,'' the mayor said, ''but once they're completed, people will forget about all the problems, and they'll just blend in and be assetsto the village.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
