<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High-Tech High School</title>
    <meta content="17TECH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231105"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kiley, Kathleen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E2DC1538F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1926" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High-Tech High School</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHLEEN KILEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kiley, Kathleen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Academy of Information Technology in Stamford, first high school in Connecticut whose mission is to train students in information technology; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE latest high-tech enterprise in Stamford doesn't have anything to do with venture capitalists or initial public offerings. But given the urgency with which Stamford went about creating the Academy of Information Technology, it is clear the city sees its new high school as a major investment. And if it delivers on its promises, the school could become a model to emulate statewide.</p>
        <p>On Sept. 5, after just a year of preparation and planning, the academy opened its doors for the first time, admitting about 225 of the approximately 300 students who had sought admission.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE latest high-tech enterprise in Stamford doesn't have anything to do with venture capitalists or initial public offerings. But given the urgency with which Stamford went about creating the Academy of Information Technology, it is clear the city sees its new high school as a major investment. And if it delivers on its promises, the school could become a model to emulate statewide.</p>
        <p>On Sept. 5, after just a year of preparation and planning, the academy opened its doors for the first time, admitting about 225 of the approximately 300 students who had sought admission.</p>
        <p>It is the first high school in the state where the mission is to train students in information technology, the high-tech field that encompasses the Internet. The logic of the move was obvious. After all, the school is located in an area that has hundreds of high-tech companies and not enough workers to run them. The Connecticut Internet Association of Stamford estimates that one out of four  high-tech jobs remain unfilled in the state. If anything, it is a wonder that the creation of such a school took so long.</p>
        <p>''A.I.T. is unique and it's the first in the state to do something like this,'' said Tom Murphy, spokesman for the state Department of Education. ''Connecticut schools are moving in the direction of providing more technology courses, but it's not as structured as A.I.T., it's more ad hoc.''</p>
        <p>Staples High School in Westport, for example, uses technology to teach and offers technology electives, such as programming. But its emphasis isn't on training people in technology, said Lynne Shain, assistant superintendent of curriculum and staff development. ''We're not teaching technological skills to stand alone.''</p>
        <p>The academy, and its 15 classrooms, is located in the Rippowam Center, Stamford's magnet middle school. The students will have access to desktop and laptop equipment, where they can learn about computer graphics, Web design, programming and database and network administration. Students will design Web sites, build computers and computer networks and learn how to program. Students will have mentors from local high-tech companies and will be offered internships.</p>
        <p>''It's a great way to get students started on a technology training track,'' said Terri Kochersperger, a senior vice president at Priceline.com of Stamford. ''Why wait until they get to college?''</p>
        <p>And some companies are willing to hire students with high-tech training before they even get to college. Barry Monies, president of Computronix, a network service provider in Stamford, said he might hire, fresh out of school, academy graduates who have advanced network training.</p>
        <p>''It's a talent pool for us,'' he said. ''I wish something like this was here when I was going to school.''</p>
        <p>The idea for the academy began last fall, when Anthony Mazzullo, superintendent of Stamford schools, was chatting with William Schwab, president of Norwalk Community College, about a possible joint project that would involve information technology.</p>
        <p>After more discussion, between themselves and with others, including business people, politicians and educators, they came up with the idea to develop a high school that would not only integrate technology into teaching, but also offer heavy-duty technology courses. ''This will hopefully help narrow the digital divide,'' Mr. Schwab said.</p>
        <p>As with many high-tech startups, it's a race to turn concepts into tangible items, because in these Internet days, time is compressed. What used to take a year, now takes three months. So the luxury of waiting and debating a new concept is gone. Christine Casey, assistant superintendent of Stamford schools, seemed amenable to this approach. Like a hot startup selling to investors, she and her supporters were able to cut through the ''political fog,'' as one supporter put it, and get the project approved in warp speed.</p>
        <p>What makes it even more amazing is that it was a collaborative effort among community groups and businesses. ''We're blurring the lines'' Dr. Casey said. That isn't easy because the barriers dividing business and education tend to be rigid, she added. But as one colleague commented, ''Chris doesn't know the meaning of 'no'.''</p>
        <p>The blurring is happening on many levels. Curriculum design was moving solely out of the hands of educators. The entire process of developing a curriculum, which at times can be an insular exercise, Dr. Casey said, was created with the help of local high-tech business leaders, Norwalk Community College, Stamford administrators and teachers.</p>
        <p>''We went after a select number of small companies, because we needed help in developing the curriculum and getting internships that were meaningful,'' said Harry Orlick, chairman of the school's advisory board and a retired I.B.M. executive. ''Plus we needed some teaching support from the outside.''</p>
        <p>While the initial focus will be on providing a high school education, with an emphasis on technology, Dr. Casey and others envision opening the academy to the public. By next year, the school will be able to accommodate more people when the middle school moves to another building. ''There is a huge need to provide adult education in the community,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Some involved with the project didn't think the school would get beyond the planning stage, mostly because there was no real model to convince people that it would work. ''We pounded out the numbers around January and it was about a $1 million project, at the time, and I thought that would be the end of it,'' said John Lindquist, director of information technology for Stamford. ''There was no real model, and they said, 'Let's do it.' ''</p>
        <p>Not having a template seemed a blessing, Dr. Casey said, because it may have forced decision-makers to become visionaries. ''We had a vision to provide a place that would give the kids the opportunities to take the technology they already know and build upon it,'' she said. ''Why start them on a keyboard learning to type when they already know how to build a Web site?''</p>
        <p>That's an understatement. Some academy students are running PC repair shops out of their basements and taking high-level networking courses at the school. ''It's about 50-50 in terms of their level of knowledge,'' said Jeanne Lauer, who left Westhill High School to teach a training program designed by Cisco Systems, a networking company in San Jose, Calif. at the academy. ''Some have no knowledge, while others have tried to learn on their own, while others are taking the high-level Cisco networking course.''</p>
        <p>Although there were some technically savvy candidates that applied to the academy, they didn't have an advantage over those who had only a smattering of tech know-how. The academy considered all students, regardless of their school performance. The entrance requirements consisted of a 250-word essay explaining their interest in technology and a personal interview.</p>
        <p>Henry Jones, student recruiter and consultant on the project, who has spent the bulk of his career developing youth programs, interviewed hundreds of students. ''Many of these kids want to own their own businesses and be in charge of their own destiny,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Some will realize it earlier than others. Nigel Johnson and James Simon, both 17 and seniors at the school, run a business called PC Junkies, a PC problem-solving enterprise, out of Mr. Johnson's basement. In addition, they are halfway through the first level of Cisco System's online networking training course.</p>
        <p>''If they complete the first level of training, these kids could be making $50,000 to $70,000 right out of school,'' said Michael Pensiero, applications support manager for the city's information technology department.</p>
        <p>The money is alluring, but the advanced placement seniors insist that isn't the only draw. ''It's not really the money, but if you have to do something you might as well like it,'' Mr. Johnson said.</p>
        <p>''Yeah,'' Mr. Simon added, ''I didn't find out about what type of salary I could make until I was accepted at A.I.T.''</p>
        <p>As seniors, they already have all but one English course to meet graduation requirements, and they plan to load up on technology electives, they said. Mr. Simon is taking college-level English, which is being taught at the Academy by Norwalk Community College teachers and can be applied toward college credit or toward the academy's five-year high school and associate's degree program with the college.</p>
        <p>They also have big plans for building the school's Web site, envisioning such things as a school newspaper, listings of internships, student of the month and student portfolios. And if they have time, both students may continue working throughout the school year. They were among the dozen summer interns hired by Stamford's information technology department to trouble-shoot and update computers in the city's 19 schools.</p>
        <p>Some might argue that these teenagers are spreading themselves too thin, while others say the continuous mental stimulation is healthy. ''Every day, you should try to keep feeding the mind,'' said Johnnye Mae Britt, grandmother and legal guardian of two of the academy's students.</p>
        <p>Then there are students like Peter Telesco Jr., 14, a ninth grader at the academy. According to his father, Peter, his son has been an under performer. ''It's very unusual, that he's motivated to go to school,'' Mr. Telesco said. ''He's a bright kid, but if he loses interest, forget it.''</p>
        <p>But Peter is crazy about computers and his father hopes the academy can leverage that interest. ''He and his friend Mike have a mock business, and they're on that computer all day and all night,'' Mr. Telesco said. ''Now that he's working with computers, he might like science and other subjects.''</p>
        <p>Lt. Gov. Jodi Rell, who is responsible for developing a plan to modernize Connecticut schools and libraries, is also looking for that hook. After touring the state for four months last year, she said, ''Not every school was wired, and not every school has access to Internet, and not all teachers are trained.''</p>
        <p>This view is supported by the Progressive Policy Institute, a Washington, D.C.-based research and policy maker, which ranked the 50 states in terms of economic indicators and overall readiness to compete in the new economy. Connecticut ranked fifth in economic indicators, but the state's schools ranked 42nd in their preparedness in using technology to teach.</p>
        <p>To change this, the state recently earmarked $32 million to connect all classrooms to the Internet over the next few years and digitize the state's libraries. Other initiative also include encouraging businesses, via tax breaks, to donate used computers that are less than two years old.</p>
        <p>Improving schools on this level, can't happen soon enough. With unemployment hovering at around 2 percent and the state becoming a home to more high-tech companies, businesses need more skilled labor, said Mark Pruner, president of the Connecticut Internet Association and Web Counsel, an interactive market agency for the legal community. ''So what it comes down to is redefining education -- this is something that has to be done,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
