<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic of Army Is Assassinated in Secessionist Region of Indonesia</title>
    <meta content="17INDO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/world/17INDO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Aceh Province (Indonesia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Banda Aceh (Indonesia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jakarta (Indonesia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Idris, Tengku Safwan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muni, Ayah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sims, Calvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hutomo Mandala Putra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia/Jakarta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E0DE1F38F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic of Army Is Assassinated in Secessionist Region of Indonesia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CALVIN SIMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sims, Calvin</byline>
      <dateline>JAKARTA, Indonesia, Sept. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tengku Safwan Idris, Islamic university rector and leading candidate for governor of Aceh, Indonesia, is assassinated at his home, Banda Aceh; was outspoken critic of use of military force to settle secessionist issue in province; police are unsure who is behind killing; secessionist leader Ayah Muni blames military; Hutomo Mandela Putra (Tommy Suharto) meets voluntarily with police and denies involvement in series of Jakarta bombings; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A prominent Islamic university rector who was a leading candidate for governor of Aceh, a province roiled by secessionists, was assassinated early today, underscoring the violence that has plagued the region and all Indonesia in recent months.</p>
        <p>The police said two unidentified men shot the rector, Tengku Safwan Idris, in the neck at his home in the outskirts of Banda Aceh, the provincial capital. Mr. Idris, 51, director of the State Institute of Islamic Studies, was taken to a hospital, where he died, the police said. Mr. Idris was an outspoken critic of the use of military force to settle the secessionist issue in Aceh.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A prominent Islamic university rector who was a leading candidate for governor of Aceh, a province roiled by secessionists, was assassinated early today, underscoring the violence that has plagued the region and all Indonesia in recent months.</p>
        <p>The police said two unidentified men shot the rector, Tengku Safwan Idris, in the neck at his home in the outskirts of Banda Aceh, the provincial capital. Mr. Idris, 51, director of the State Institute of Islamic Studies, was taken to a hospital, where he died, the police said. Mr. Idris was an outspoken critic of the use of military force to settle the secessionist issue in Aceh.</p>
        <p>While the police said they were uncertain who is behind the killing, Ayah Muni, a commander of the separatist Free Aceh Movement, immediately blamed elements in the military. ''This is the work of the Indonesian military,'' Mr. Muni said. ''They must be held responsible for what happened.''</p>
        <p>The Free Aceh Movement, angry over what it says is the central government's economic exploitation of Aceh's rich oil and gas resources, has been fighting to create an independent Islamic state since 1976. The movement has gained strength in recent years as a result of an aggressive military campaign to crush the separatists. Up to 5,000 people, mainly civilians, are estimated to have been killed in the past decade.</p>
        <p>The violence has intensified in recent weeks, with thousands fleeing their homes. Mr. Idris's murder raises to 120 the number of people killed in Aceh since an internationally brokered cease-fire was reached between separatist guerrillas and the military in May. The shooting came a day after the central government postponed talks in Switzerland on a permanent extension of the truce, which technically ended on Sept. 2.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview from Banda Aceh, a leading human rights activist, who spoke on condition of anonymity for fear of reprisals, called the assassination of Mr. Idris a ''national tragedy.'' He called on foreign nations to condemn the violence, which he said was being instigated by the military seeking to retain lucrative business interests.</p>
        <p>Mr. Idris was a popular and well-respected figure in Aceh, which is on the northern tip of Sumatra, about 1,100 miles northwest of Jakarta. The former Indonesian president, B. J. Habibie, had appointed him to a committee established to investigate the unrest in Aceh.</p>
        <p>In another development, the son of former President Suharto denied any involvement in a series of bombings in Jakarta, including one on Wednesday that killed 15 people at the stock exchange.</p>
        <p>The accused, Hutomo Mandela Putra, who is Mr. Suharto's youngest son and is known as Tommy, met voluntarily this morning with the Jakarta police, who questioned him for more than two hours.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
