<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Swiss to Vote On Plan to Set Limit on Influx Of Immigrants</title>
    <meta content="Y17SWIS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/world/17SWIS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231339"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Quotas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Switzerland</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olson, Elizabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Quotas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EFDA1138F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Swiss to Vote On Plan to Set Limit on Influx Of Immigrants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH OLSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olson, Elizabeth</byline>
      <dateline>GENEVA, Sept. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Switzerland to vote on proposal to restrict foreigners to 18 percent of population, now 7.3 million; nation, with largest number of foreigners per capita in Europe, is caught up in anti-foreigner sentiment; government is lobbying strongly against quota (M)/</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bannered across the photograph of angry young men, heads shaved and arms extended in Nazi salutes, is the appeal, ''Xenophobia isn't Swiss.'' In smaller print, the newspaper advertisement urges voters to reject a quota on foreigners in Switzerland.</p>
        <p>Nationwide, the Swiss will decide next weekend whether to restrict foreigners to 18 percent of their population, now 7.3 million. Like neighboring Austria and Germany, Switzerland has been caught up in anti-foreigner sentiment, inflamed by charges that the country is inundated with immigrants. Statistics show that Switzerland has the largest number of foreigners per capita of any European country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bannered across the photograph of angry young men, heads shaved and arms extended in Nazi salutes, is the appeal, ''Xenophobia isn't Swiss.'' In smaller print, the newspaper advertisement urges voters to reject a quota on foreigners in Switzerland.</p>
        <p>Nationwide, the Swiss will decide next weekend whether to restrict foreigners to 18 percent of their population, now 7.3 million. Like neighboring Austria and Germany, Switzerland has been caught up in anti-foreigner sentiment, inflamed by charges that the country is inundated with immigrants. Statistics show that Switzerland has the largest number of foreigners per capita of any European country.</p>
        <p>Isolationist sentiments are firmly woven into the Swiss political fabric, particularly in the German-speaking eastern portion of the country. The Swiss have voted seven times since 1964 to limit the number of foreigners here. Just last spring, national debate flared when residents of a Lucerne suburb rejected citizenship requests from otherwise qualified immigrants, including all the applicants from the Balkans.</p>
        <p>The debate over Swiss willingness to accept outsiders has been rekindled in the preparation for the quotas-on-foreigners vote set for Sept. 24. With one out of every five inhabitants foreign-born (and that doesn't count diplomats and United Nations workers here), the Swiss will decide whether to adopt the right-wing ideal of closing their borders.</p>
        <p>In contrast to earlier votes, the stakes are higher now because Switzerland has taken more steps into the outside world, with new links this spring to the European Union and with its banks increasingly global through high-profile acquisitions.</p>
        <p>The government, worried that a yes vote will damage Switzerland's image while it is trying to recover from the storm over its treatment of Holocaust victims, is lobbying strongly against it. Approving a cap, transportation minister Moritz Leuenberger warned, would mean ''reducing the question of foreigners to a number and blaming them for all evil.''</p>
        <p>Officials argue that quotas on foreigners also could undermine the blossoming Swiss economy, in the doldrums for a decade, and jeopardize accords tying Switzerland's economy closer to the European Union's 15 member countries. The accords require freer movement of the union's citizens across Swiss borders. With one of the lowest jobless rates in Europe, Swiss companies must look abroad to fill job vacancies and are staunchly opposed to numerical restrictions.</p>
        <p>Yet, many Swiss believe foreigners are taking their jobs. In a Geneva suburb, a young hairdresser, Vanessa Wanner, who has a Danish mother, said that only two Swiss apprentices in her 1997 graduating class had found jobs in the profession. ''The salons prefer to hire foreigners because they can pay them much less,'' the 22-year-old said. ''I like foreigners here. It's interesting to know their ways, but they take jobs from us.''</p>
        <p>Stung by the recurring furor over foreigners, the Bern government already has moved to tighten residency permits for non-European Union citizens, and to explore ways to make naturalization easier for non-Swiss. This would lower the overall percentage of foreigners.</p>
        <p>Critics worry that the vote's outcome may be closer than fluctuating polls indicate, particularly because of a recent surge in neo-Nazi activity.</p>
        <p>Opinion polls found that closing borders appeals to some surprising groups including younger, educated mothers who fear that increasing numbers of non-German- or non-French-speaking children in schools will drag down the quality of education.</p>
        <p>Strict quotas also would strike at the country's humanitarian traditions by hampering the government's ability to accept refugees, argued Paul Huber, head of the federal refugee office. ''We are obliged by law to take in those genuinely persecuted in their country, but we won't be able to give temporary protection to refugees from places like Bosnia and Kosovo if this succeeds,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
