<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Racing Nuts Never Fall Far From Tree</title>
    <meta content="17JOUR$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231128"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Hot Rod Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E3D91538F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Racing Nuts Never Fall Far From Tree</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Team Long Island, totaling 15 young members, is only National Hot Rod Assn Junior Dragster league on Island; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IAN POWELL inched his sleek blue car, Split Second, up to the starting line. He revved the motor, and as the lights on the ''Christmas tree'' flicked from red to yellow to green, he floored the accelerator. His 12 1/2-foot, 225-pound Junior Dragster flew down the track, hitting 65 miles an hour in 9.8 seconds.</p>
        <p>When Ian reached the end of his run and car braked to a stop, his father, Charles Powell, flicked the kill switch, and the engine died. He then hitched the car to a tow rope attached to the back of a blue minibike.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IAN POWELL inched his sleek blue car, Split Second, up to the starting line. He revved the motor, and as the lights on the ''Christmas tree'' flicked from red to yellow to green, he floored the accelerator. His 12 1/2-foot, 225-pound Junior Dragster flew down the track, hitting 65 miles an hour in 9.8 seconds.</p>
        <p>When Ian reached the end of his run and car braked to a stop, his father, Charles Powell, flicked the kill switch, and the engine died. He then hitched the car to a tow rope attached to the back of a blue minibike.</p>
        <p>There was no problem with the engine. A tire hadn't blown. But Ian, though he has already been racing dragsters for three years, has just turned 13 and sois still at least four years away from a New York State driver's license. Because of that, and because of the track's insurance regulations, he cannot drive back through the pits to the starting line at Long Island Motorsports Park in Westhampton.</p>
        <p>Ian, who lives in Bayport, is one of 15 racers on Team Long Island, the only National Hot Rod Association Junior Dragster league on the Island. Its members, who are 8 to 17 years old, drive half-scale copies of adult-sized dragsters, dangling stuffed animals and plastic comic-book characters from their roll cages. The cars, powered by modified Briggs &amp; Stratton one-cylinder lawnmower engines, are not as fast as the full-sized dragsters, but they have the same verve and vroom.</p>
        <p>Especially for the crew chiefs, nearly all of  whom are the racers' fathers. ''My dad's a big motorhead who liked racing,'' said Ian, an eighth-grade honors student at James Wilson Young Middle School in Bayport with a penchant for acting in school productions and two local theater groups. ''He asked me if I wanted to try it, and I said O.K.''</p>
        <p>His father, 47, is a special-education teacher at Robert Moses Middle School in North Babylon. As a teenager, he sold souvenirs at racetracks around the country. He thought the league, formed in 1992, would provide the opportunity for his son to race that he never had.</p>
        <p>''To a large degree, it's vicarious,'' Mr. Powell said. ''It's something you always wanted to do or used to do as a child. It's one type of experience you can give your kid. It certainly isn't your standard baseball or soccer. It is far off the beaten path.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Powell handles most of the mechanical chores. ''Daddy does all the rough work, all the maintenance,'' he said. ''Ian's learning as he's capable. Primarily, he's my hired driver. He works for room and board.'' While the fastest full-sized dragsters can hit 330 miles an hour in a quarter mile, the junior versions, which run on alcohol, because it burns at a more consistent temperature than gasoline, can hit 80 m.p.h. on the 660-foot track, an eighth of a mile. The steering is rudimentary, and there's no transmission.</p>
        <p>So while Mr. Powell and the other fathers tested the engines, adjusted belts and changed the oil in  preparation for the first of the day's three timed trials, the drivers played freeze tag and sprayed each other with water guns in the parking lot.</p>
        <p>Drag racing, in Mr. Powell's view, is an educational experience. It requires concentration, hand-eye coordination and trained reflexes. And learning how to lose provides Ian with an important lesson. ''It teaches a lot of skills,'' he said. ''There are the mechanical and technological aspects. He learns about changing weather conditions. We have to alter things depending on how the air changes.''</p>
        <p>And then there's math. Barreling full-throttle down the strip doesn't win a Junior Dragster race. Instead, it's consistency, not just speed, that counts. Based on weather, track conditions and the time trials run before the racing begins, the children predict how many seconds it will take them to complete the actual race.  They use a thermometer to measure the air temperature, a hygrometer for relative humidity and a barometer for air pressure. After considering all the factors, they predict their time, and they write this figure, known as the dial-in number, in shoe polish on their windshields. To win, they must finish as close to their predicted time as possible, without going faster or ''breaking out.''</p>
        <p>Two cars at a time compete in a tournament-style elimination. The slower car is given a head start to equalize the difference between estimated times. Starting before the ''Christmas tree'' lights change to green results in instant elimination.</p>
        <p>But for Amy Dobrie, 11, of Eastport, and Shana King, 12, of East Meadow, two of the three girls on the team, drag racing is only about fun.  ''I like going down the track and going fast,'' Amy said, showing off Never Satisfied, her pink racer with red and blue pinstripes and a stuffed Bullwinkle mascot.</p>
        <p>Amy has been coming to the strip for three years. Her father, Gary Dobrie, used to drag-race a '68 Camaro. When her brother Jason, 14, joined the team, Amy didn't want to be left out. And her mother, Joan, a florist, comes along to cheer, making the races a family affair.</p>
        <p>Shana's purple racer is Wildfire, and she paints her nails to match the blue flames that decorate it. After watching Junior Dragsters at Raceway Park in Englishtown, N.J., a few years ago, she told her father, Phil King, who used to race motorbikes, monster trucks and dragsters, that she wanted to give it a whirl. That Christmas, she got her $5,000 speedster.</p>
        <p>''I love racing,'' said Shana, who added that she prefers it to her other pastimes, playing the violin and modeling. ''It's something that not a lot of kids get to do. My friends think it's cool. A lot of them are shocked that I get into a car and just drive. I can't drive around in the street, but I can get into a car and go 75 to 85 miles per hour down the track.''</p>
        <p>Drag racing is not a ''boy sport,'' she said. ''It's really neutral,'' she added. ''Anyone can do it. Whoever finds something interesting, they should just go for it.''</p>
        <p>Safety is not an issue, the young racers, their parents and the track manager contend. ''Kids are safer in these cars than they are on bicycles,'' said Mr. King, who became the league coordinator last year. ''We have a roll cage, a five-point harness they are strapped into, a neck brace, a helmet, arm restraints so their arms can't fly out if they do roll over. Technically, you may think of a bike as not dangerous, but if you only have a helmet on, all your extremities are exposed. With these cars, they can roll at 150 miles per hour, and they won't get hurt. They might get banged up a little bit from bouncing around, but they're not going to be ripped up like they would if they got hit by a car or fell off the bicycle in the street.''</p>
        <p>Because the engine is mounted at the rear of the car, the young drivers won't be sprayed with hot oil or flying parts if it malfunctions.</p>
        <p>No Junior Dragsters have been hurt at the park since the league started, said Walter Frey, the track manager. ''It's so much safer than Go-Karting races,'' he said. ''They run side by side. They don't turn. They have more of a chance of getting injured shooting hoops.''</p>
        <p>A Junior Dragster is not meant for street use. ''It's only made for the strip,'' Mr. King said. ''It only goes in a straight line.''</p>
        <p>Originally opened as Westhampton Raceway in 1953 as a dirt drag strip, the Long Island Motorsports Park calls itself the longest continuously operating purpose-built drag strip in the United States. ''We're not a super track,'' said Mr. Frey, the track manager. ''We're a mom-and-pop sort of business. My main concern is to keep the sport alive on Long Island.''</p>
        <p>Because of the Town of Southampton's noise ordinances, and because its blue laws prohibit racing on Sunday mornings, the strip is only open in the afternoons, Friday through Sunday.</p>
        <p>The junior racers pay a $35 entry fee per car plus $5, which goes toward paying to have an ambulance on hand, as required under the hot rod association's rules. Each dragster gets a safety check before the racing begins, and the children must have a hot rod association license, although they only have to fill out a form to get one. No test is necessary. Racers who are 8 and 9 years old can't exceed an elapsed time of 12.90 seconds for the one-eighth mile, or a top speed of 45 to 50 m.p.h. For 10-to-11-year-old racers, the fastest time is 10.90 seconds, or a top speed of about 60 m.p.h., and those 12 and older can go as fast as 7.90 seconds, or 85 m.p.h.</p>
        <p>About 130 tracks in North America have Junior Dragster programs. Since 1992, the league has grown to about 4,000 drivers, whose average age is 12. The racing season runs from April through October.</p>
        <p>Sitting in a banana-yellow car emblazoned with a custom-made Scooby-Doo decal, Andrew Heitzler, 12, of Bay Shore, zipped up his fire-retardant racing jacket and slipped on his sunglasses. His father, David Heitzler, 38, a commercial carpentry contractor, attached his arm restraints and gave him some last-minute advice.</p>
        <p>''Dad's a big kid,'' said Mr. Heitzler, who owns nine Go-Karts, five quads (like off-road minibikes  but with four wheels), eight minibikes, two motorscooters and two Go-Peds. ''It's also a way that I can race and be involved.''</p>
        <p>A few minutes later, Shana's purple car was pushed to the starting line. Within seconds, as she was roaring down the strip, the connecting rod blew. Shana started to cry. Quickly, Mr. Heitzler offered her the backup engine he kept in his trailer. Working with several of the older children, the two dads made the switch. Shana was back in the next round.</p>
        <p>''I have spare cars,'' Mr. Heitzler said. ''I have spare parts. If you don't have anybody to race, what good is that? It comes down to the kids having fun. If you can keep them running, you have competition.''</p>
        <p>The day after the meet the Heitzlers planned to pick up Andrew's new $6,000 Junior Dragster. It was ordered with an extra two inches in height and an extra inch in the body so that Mr. Heitzler can drive it, too ''When he gets out, I'll get in,'' Mr. Heitzler said excitedly. ''I've loved race cars my whole life.''</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
