<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Public Library, New Building Within the Old One</title>
    <meta content="17MCDO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231110"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Public Library</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcdowell, Edwin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E1DB1538F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1348" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Public Library, New Building Within the Old One</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWIN McDOWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcdowell, Edwin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on four-story building, made mostly of glass, that is being built within South Court, 80-by-80-foot enclosed courtyard in New York Public Library on Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street; diagram; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the 89 years since the New York Public Library opened at Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street, not a single permanent structure has been added to it. But that is changing.  For almost a year, a four-story building made mostly of glass has been under construction on the library site, and it is scheduled to open next fall.</p>
        <p>But admirers of the library's Beaux-Arts design need not worry that the iconic Carrere &amp; Hastings building will be obscured.  Library officials say that the as-yet-unnamed building will not be noticeable from the street and barely noticeable from the main library.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the 89 years since the New York Public Library opened at Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street, not a single permanent structure has been added to it. But that is changing.  For almost a year, a four-story building made mostly of glass has been under construction on the library site, and it is scheduled to open next fall.</p>
        <p>But admirers of the library's Beaux-Arts design need not worry that the iconic Carrere &amp; Hastings building will be obscured.  Library officials say that the as-yet-unnamed building will not be noticeable from the street and barely noticeable from the main library.</p>
        <p>Instead, the new building will be tucked within South Court, an 80-by-80-foot enclosed courtyard that for the better part of a century has been unknown to most outsiders and even to some library staff members.  Although it would seem that a four-story building would rise above the three-story main building, both buildings will be about the same height.</p>
        <p>But at 42,222 square feet, the South Court building, which will cost $22.5 million, will be minuscule compared with the main building's 527,000 square feet. And because it is being built in an era far removed from that of Carrere and Hastings, it will differ almost totally in appearance and function from that of the Center for the Humanities, the formal name of the main library.</p>
        <p>''That courtyard had been an entrance for a horse and carriage,'' said Lewis Davis, the founding partner of Davis Brody Bond, the architectural firm that designed the new building, and was responsible for the $15 million restoration of the library's main reading room. ''Then over the years it became a repository for every piece of junk the library had.''</p>
        <p>In later years the library's exhibition-design office was housed in a shed in the courtyard. ''But we thought the courtyard should be, and could be, as good as every place else in the library,'' Mr. Davis said.</p>
        <p>The new building will be 73 by 73 feet,  meaning there will be a mere 3 1/2-foot clearance between the new building and the surrounding structure. The original walls of the main library will in effect double as the courtyard enclosure and as the walls of the  new building, yet the only points at which the buildings will touch will be where glass-railed bridges on each floor span the space between them.</p>
        <p>''The biggest challenge,'' said Robert D. Trostle, project manager for F. J. Sciame Construction Company, ''has been building a building within a building, especially working within a historical facade without damaging the existing architectural elements. The other challenge has been not to disturb the library occupants. In fact, few of the visitors even know the construction's going on.''</p>
        <p>That entailed scheduling early morning and evenings for noisy work. To put up the structural steel, for example, the steel beams had to be put in place before the library's opening hours. And to put them in place, the beams -- some of which weighed 40 tons -- had to be lifted 20 feet over the library by a crane with a 180-foot boom. It required 18 flatbed trucks to deliver the crane to the north side of 40th Street, where it was parked for one month. In addition, because of limited loading-dock space, deliveries of construction material were coordinated with the library's own deliveries, and also had to be coordinated with events scheduled for Bryant Park.</p>
        <p>UPON entering the South Court building, visitors will find, in addition to extra room for library staff, a space where the public can receive free lessons in using computers to access the wealth of information in the database of the New York Public Library and the databases of much of the rest of the world.</p>
        <p>There is already an obvious thirst for such information, according to Dr. Paul LeClerc, the library's president since December 1993. Last year, for example, the library system's Web pages were visited an average of 1.1 million times a month by computer users from more than 70 countries -- a 48 percent increase in visits over the year before. Surprisingly, the most visited site was the children's page, ''On-Lion'' for Kids, followed by the catalogs for the research and branch libraries.</p>
        <p>''When we designed the Science, Industry and Business Library in 1996,'' said Dr. LeClerc, who was the president of Hunter College before he took over the New York Public Library, ''we couldn't assume the public would know how to use these new forms of information. So we built four classrooms where we trained the staff, then offered six to eight classes a day having to do with electronic resources. So far, we've already trained close to 50,000 people in SIBL'' -- the acronym for the Science, Industry and Business Library.</p>
        <p>The goal now is to train even more people -- many more. ''This is already one of the most advanced-information technology libraries on the planet,'' Dr. LeClerc said recently, and the goal of the new building's facilities for teaching information technology, which will be free to the public, is to make it even more so.</p>
        <p>Most visitors to the South Court building will enter through Astor Hall, the grand marble lobby off the Fifth Avenue entrance to the main library. Once inside they will encounter an orientation room, where they will be able to view a short film about the New York Public Library system with its four research libraries and 86 branches.</p>
        <p>THE research libraries, in addition to the Center for the Humanities, are the Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture, at 515 Malcolm X Boulevard; the Science, Industry and Business Library, at 188 Madison Avenue, the old B. Altman building at 34th Street; and the New York Public Library for the Performing Arts, at Lincoln Center.</p>
        <p>(The Performing Arts library is closed for alterations; its circulating collection is at the Mid-Manhattan Library at 455 Fifth Avenue, at 40th Street, and its research collection in the library's annex at 521 West 43rd Street, between 10th and 11th Avenues.)</p>
        <p>South Court's top floor will be encased within a glass curtain wall, and the other floors, which will not have exterior walls, will be ringed by three-foot-six-inch-high glass guard rails. An angled glass skylight will connect the South Court building to the main building at the third floor level, allowing natural light to pour into the lower floors and illuminate the existing historical facades. The four columns on each floor will be sheathed in stainless steel.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to restore the majesty of that courtyard,'' said Mr. Davis, the architect.  ''That meant having as much light as possible. It meant bathing the four walls in light.''</p>
        <p>A glass staircase will descend from the first-floor level to the 186-seat auditorium, the below-grade gathering place for library-sponsored exhibits, lectures, debates and conferences. The architectural design calls for two of the original foundation walls to be exposed at the bottom of the staircase.</p>
        <p>South Court is also designed for members of the library staff. ''As we renovated public spaces in the building, including moving the copying center from the main reading room, we knew we needed some place for people we were displacing,'' Dr. LeClerc said.</p>
        <p>So the top floor will have a staff lounge, a portion of which will contain a ''quiet room'' where during breaks staff members will be able to relax while sitting and thinking, sitting and meditating, or simply enjoying a pause in the day's occupation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
