<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don't Worry About It, Girl, You're History</title>
    <meta content="17COVHDS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231446"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COVER STORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Scholastic Books</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graeber, Laurel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Royal Diaries, The (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E0D91F38F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1272" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don't Worry About It, Girl, You're History</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Laurel Graeber</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Graeber, Laurel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses upcoming HBO series The Royal Diaries, based on Scholastic Books series of same name; each episode focuses on princess who came to rule powerful nation; Cleopatra, Elizabeth I and Isabella of Castilla are subjects; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU have to feel sorry for HBO's latest young heroine. Her preoccuppied and self-centered father is in danger of losing his job. She may have to move out of her home. Her cat disappears. One of her older sisters has it in for her.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU have to feel sorry for HBO's latest young heroine. Her preoccuppied and self-centered father is in danger of losing his job. She may have to move out of her home. Her cat disappears. One of her older sisters has it in for her.</p>
        <p>These may sound like the ordinary travails of a contemporary adolescent. But this girl's father is Ptolemy Auletes, ruler of Egypt. Her home is the pharaoh's palace. Egyptian cats were more than ordinary house pets in 57 B.C. And her sister Tryphaena really does have it in for her: for political reasons, Tryphaena would like both her sisters out of the way.</p>
        <p>This heroine is none other than Cleopatra, whose story will be revealed in ''Celopatra: Daughter of the Nile,'' to be broadcast tomorrow night at 7:30 on HBO, as well as six more times throughout the month. The stories of other intrepid princesses will follow: in November, ''Elizabeth I: Red Rose of the House of Tudor,'' and in December, ''Isabel: Jewel of Castilla.'' Together they make up ''The Royal Diaries,'' a set of dramas based on the Scholastic Book series of the same name.</p>
        <p>''The Royal Diaries'' are largely an outgrowth of ''Dear America,'' another historical HBO venture inspired by books from Scholastic. But while ''Dear America'' focuses on imaginary girls growing up along with a fledging country, these shows, like the books that inspired them, center a real young women who came to rule powerful nations. What the series have in common is a plot structure that relies on the heroines' fictional journals. The result is history presented in a way it's seldom seen: through teenage eyes, and female ones at that.</p>
        <p>Viewers will ''see people that act like them, look like them and have the same concerns,'' said Dolores Morris, vice president of HBO family programming.</p>
        <p>This is not to say, of course, that you will see Cleopatra obsessing over an outbreak of acne or Elizabeth worrying about a Latin test. These historical figures do, however, agonize over their relationships with adults, the impressions they make and how they can resolve family conflicts. (Could you find a more dysfunctional household than Henry VIII's?) Such portrayals are not presented by school history courses, which tend to focus on these women's accomplishments as rulers. But if textbook writers aren't interested in a teenage Cleopatra, the producers say they are confident that 9- to 14-years-olds will be. Imagine, for instance, how alluring adolescents would have found Elizabeth I in ''Shakespeare in Love'' if she had been played by Gwyneth Paltrow.</p>
        <p>''We want to make sure our audience becomes personally and emotionally invested, because otherwise they won't be interested in the history,'' said Deborah Forte, an executive vice president at Scholastic and executive producer of ''The Royal Diaries.''</p>
        <p>The shows' creators hope not only to attract girls to scholarship but also to give them confidence. After all, if these historic young women could triumph over threats of assassination and plagues, how can a 21st-century girl not feel ready to take on the world?</p>
        <p>Showing Cleopatra, Elizabeth and Isabel as metaphorical queens before they were real ones presented problems, however. Because hourlong prime time slots for family programming are hard to come by, the producers had to cram each royal adolescence into half an hour. The shows' creators eventually decided to get ''right into it,'' as Ms. Forte put it, developing the background through dialogue and action. Each show concludes with a brief epilogue summing up the heroine's life as an adult.</p>
        <p>Budget was another issue. Although Ms. Forte wanted each show to be ''a mini-movie,'' the producers could not afford to shoot on location. They found their solution in the Toronto area, using parkland for the Castilian countryside and Knox College as a Tudor world. As for Cleopatra's story, ''the lovely Nile River is Lake Ontario,'' Ms. Forte said with a laugh.</p>
        <p>The show's creators also worked to transform contemporary adolescents - Elisa Moolecherry as Cleopatra; Tamara Hope as Elizabeth and Lisa Jakub as Isabel - into highborn young women of centuries past. ''Young actors tend to be very contemporary in their movements.'' Ms. Forte observed. But before long, the actresses were able to envision themselves in their characters' bodies as well as their minds.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the greatest challenge, though, was the make the princesses' tales personal while remaining true to the facts.</p>
        <p>''We don't change history in these stories,'' Ms. Forte said. ''We are taking a moment in time.'' But in setting up that moment, ''the information we give is accurate,'' she added.</p>
        <p>It is not known, for instance, if Cleopatra really interceded with the Romans on her father's behalf, as she does in ''Daughter of the Nile.'' But she certainly could have, Ms. Forte said. ''I believe Cleopatra did get smuggled to her father to go to Rome,'' she said. ''Whether it was inside of a rug, I don't know,'' she added, referring to a scene in which the young Cleopatra literally tumbles out at Ptolemy's feet while he is in hiding. Similarly, no one knows if young Elizabeth really saved the head of her stepmother, Catherine Parr (no one doubts that Catherine was in danger of losing it), or if Isabel was as successful a political player as a teenager as she will appear to be on television. But what is sure is that these were women of very strong character and courage, traits that were unlikely to have developed suddenly when they were over 30.</p>
        <p>The future queens also had flaws, which raised other issues. For instance, the series creators decided that the epilogue for Isabel's story had to mention her role in starting the Spanish Inquisition. In their view, its horrific consequences demanded honesty. They did not however, feel obliged to give a complete picture of Cleopatra's demise. ''Daughter of the Nile'' offers a half-truth: that she died of a snake bite.</p>
        <p>''We want to leave these stories with a positive note,'' Ms. Morris said, ''so, yes, we slid through that one a little bit. After building up how she came into her own and became a terrific ruler, it would be very upsetting to hear, 'Oh, and she killed herself.''</p>
        <p>It is clear, though, that all these young women lived in cultures whose practices would be seen as barbaric today. The scripts are ''true to the cruelties of the time,'' Ms. Morris said. The viewers, for example, will see Cleopatra order a royal attendant to taste the contents of a goblet intended for the pharaoh. (Not surprisingly, the servant falls dead.) And both she and Elizabeth record in their diaries the gruesome fates their fathers ordered for other members of the family.</p>
        <p>But the danger and high stakes surrounding these young women's choices also make their stories more fascinating material for television, Ms. Forte said. As she put it, ''In a lot of these families, love was politics, and politics was love.''</p>
        <p>COVER STORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
