<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>JERSEY DIARY</title>
    <meta content="17DIAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3D71238F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="496" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>JERSEY DIARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Scene: A New Jersey Transit train on the way to Pennsylvania Station in Manhattan during the morning rush one morning recently.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Scene: A New Jersey Transit train on the way to Pennsylvania Station in Manhattan during the morning rush one morning recently.</p>
        <p>Conductor (full volume on the intercom): ''Will the individual doing their nails in the first car please stop! It is making the engineer dizzy!''</p>
        <p>Harold N. Krauss  (Well, since he put it like that . . . )</p>
        <p>Overheard in the checkout line at Staples in Randolph:</p>
        <p>First woman: ''In all my years of teaching kindergarten, I've never run into so many cases of separation anxiety.''</p>
        <p>Second woman: ''I suppose I'm lucky. By third grade, the kids have adjusted.''</p>
        <p>First woman: ''Forget the kids. I'm talking about the parents.''</p>
        <p>Audrey Corn</p>
        <p>And speaking of the reopening of school, this was overheard during a recent shopping excursion:</p>
        <p>Man: ''Kids go back to school yet?''</p>
        <p>Woman: ''Wednesday.''</p>
        <p>Man: ''Happy Mother's Day.''</p>
        <p>Dorothy Leichter</p>
        <p>Recently I suffered a bout of intermittent hoarseness that required a trip to the doctor He gave me some throat spray and allergy medicine and sent me home.</p>
        <p>When my neighbor, Bill, asked me how the visit went, I told him the doctor said my hoarseness was the result of an overindulgence of sex and alcohol.</p>
        <p>(I wish.)</p>
        <p>A few days later when I saw Bill in the backyard and asked him how he was doing, he motioned me over and croaked, ''Do you want a cough drop?''</p>
        <p>Art Simeone</p>
        <p>At a recent recent church picnic for St. Matthew's in Randolph, many of the picnickers were stood in front of the tables while a sermon was delivered, with mothers and fathers holding back their children, who wanted to munch on hot dogs and play.</p>
        <p>As the pastor continued to deliver the sermon over a loudspeaker -- mostly in a monotone -- the chatter of nearby tennis players was drowning him out.</p>
        <p>Then, as he neared the end, he raised his voice sharply and shouted, ''Let us praise God . . . ''</p>
        <p>At that point, totally unaware of his timing, a teenager who was hitting with a tennis instructor missed a shot and shouted in frustration, ''Oh.  . . . God!''</p>
        <p>Even some of the adult church picnickers snickered.</p>
        <p>Dawn D'Aries Challis</p>
        <p>One morning I heard much commotion and ''En garde'' coming from my kitchen. When I got there, I saw my 8-month-old Westie (her name is Fitzie) in a fierce tug of war with my 5-year-old daughter's dress, which she happened to be wearing.</p>
        <p>''Stop that immediately,'' I hollered.</p>
        <p>The dog retreated and my daughter responded, ''It was Fitzie's idea.''</p>
        <p>''Oh, please,'' I said. ''Dogs don't think like that.''</p>
        <p>''Really,'' my daughter answered. ''Then why are you always saying that dog has a mind of her own?''</p>
        <p>Deirdre Flanagan Ward</p>
        <p>While enjoying the wonders of the cosmos recently at the Hayden Planetarium, I was seated next to a father and his little boy, about 4 years old, who asked during a quiet mement in the presentation, ''Daddy, are we still on Earf?''</p>
        <p>Mary Walling-Roche</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
