<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Flat Amsterdam Is a Biker's Nirvana</title>
    <meta content="BIKE.$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/travel/BIKE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Amsterdam (Netherlands)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yarnall, Judith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands/Amsterdam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EED71F39F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Flat Amsterdam Is a Biker's Nirvana</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDITH YARNALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yarnall, Judith</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Judith Yarnall travel article on bicycling in Amsterdam; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS Dutch as tulips and considerably more fun, bicycles -- or fietsen, as they're called in Amsterdam -- are ideally suited to the brick-paved canal streets of the old central city and to the flat landscape surrounding the urban area. They're everywhere: chained to bridges, parked by the hundreds outside Centraal  Station, rolling steadily by (often with one or two small passengers aboard) as you sit in outdoor cafes. Because municipal policy actively promotes bicycle commuting, lanes and paths reserved for their use abound.</p>
        <p>On a trip this past July, my companion, Victor, and I decided to join the locals. We wanted to bike south out of the city along the Amstel, to the town of Ouderkerk, where the old Portuguese Jewish cemetery is situated, and also to explore the placid Waterland region across the IJ harbor (pronounced eye) to the north.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS Dutch as tulips and considerably more fun, bicycles -- or fietsen, as they're called in Amsterdam -- are ideally suited to the brick-paved canal streets of the old central city and to the flat landscape surrounding the urban area. They're everywhere: chained to bridges, parked by the hundreds outside Centraal  Station, rolling steadily by (often with one or two small passengers aboard) as you sit in outdoor cafes. Because municipal policy actively promotes bicycle commuting, lanes and paths reserved for their use abound.</p>
        <p>On a trip this past July, my companion, Victor, and I decided to join the locals. We wanted to bike south out of the city along the Amstel, to the town of Ouderkerk, where the old Portuguese Jewish cemetery is situated, and also to explore the placid Waterland region across the IJ harbor (pronounced eye) to the north.</p>
        <p>But our first task was to reacquaint ourselves with the Jordaan, the old working class district that we planned to use as our base. Situated immediately to the west of the Prinsengracht, the outermost of the concentric horseshoe canals that are the main feature of the city's enduring 17th-century plan, the intimately scaled Jordaan charms you into believing that beauty is compatible with comfort. Its two diagonal canals, the Bloemgracht and the Egelantiersgracht, are perhaps the loveliest in the city and also superb places for listening to the bells of the Westerkerk, the light-filled church where Rembrandt is buried. Anne Frank, while in hiding around the corner, regarded its clock tolling each quarter hour as a ''faithful friend.''</p>
        <p>Our hotel, the Acacia, was almost out of the carillon's range, though still within the Jordaan. When we saw our room there we couldn't believe our good fortune: half of a houseboat, complete with kitchen facilities, a slant window near the bed for watching ducks glide by, and a small deck above the prow, perfect for relaxing after expeditions. We felt like part of the neighborhood, an illusion that the Acacia's owner, Hans van Vliet, is pleased to foster among his guests by providing a few houseboat rooms in addition to those within the hotel's main building.</p>
        <p>After settling in we headed for Bike City, a rental and repair shop on the Bloemgracht with an atmosphere of funk and competence, quintessentially Amsterdam. About 15 minutes later we emerged with pleasantly anonymous, one-speed machines, adequately equipped for terrain where the closest thing to a hill is the arch of a bridge or the grassy approach to the top of a dike. Rob Olykan, the manager of Bike City, instructed us in snakes and rear wheel locks, antitheft devices that our rental included. He also recommended we drop by Pied a Terre, a shop carrying detailed maps for hiking and cycling. There we purchased a set of four maps of the districts outlying Amsterdam, which nicely complemented a huge bicycle map of the city and its immediate fringe we had bought earlier.</p>
        <p>On our ride back to the Acacia we stopped by the Westerkerk to check posters announcing coming musical events, many of which are free. (We had heard Bach's Christmas Oratorio and Mozart's Requiem in this lovely, reverberant church on previous trips.)</p>
        <p>From there it was a two-minute ride to Cafe 't Smalle. Inside this small and genial establishment you can find peace for journal writing; outside, a deck overhangs the waters of the Egelantiersgracht. We spread our maps on an outdoor table and talked over the evening's and next day's possibilities. Dinner would be at Avare, a Turkish restaurant with an abundance of tasty  choices on the Lindengracht, one of the Jordaan's two restaurant streets. After that we'd go back to the Westerkerk, for a concert by a visiting organist from Stuttgart.</p>
        <p>The next morning we prepared ourselves for our trip to Ouderkerk aan de Amstel by first visiting the Portuguese synagogue, about a 15-minute ride from our hotel. Dedicated in 1675, it is still used for Sabbath services in warm weather. The community that built this synagogue suffered great hardship: they took refuge in Portugal after having been expelled from Spain in 1492, only to be expelled from Portugal four years later or else forcibly baptized beginning in 1497. A hundred years later, around the turn of the 17th century, their descendants reached tolerant Amsterdam. Holland was rebelling against the Spanish Hapsburgs at the time, so the Iberian newcomers wisely chose to identify themselves as Portuguese. With its culture and wealth, this community contributed immeasurably to its host city.</p>
        <p>One of its members, a merchant named Isaac de Pinto, lived on St. Antoniebree straat in an elegant house with painted ceilings that is now a branch of the Amsterdam public library. Another, Baruch Spinoza, the 17th-century philosopher (and lensmaker), was excommunicated for ideas deemed heretical by its rabbis.</p>
        <p>To reach the synagogue in the old Jewish quarter, which lies across the Amstel, we took the long way around, avoiding the traffic on the direct route through Dam Square and instead following the stately Herengracht all the way to the river. (If you're a tourist-biker, it makes sense to stick to the old waterways: aesthetics will reward your prudence.) We were impressed by the building's barrel-vaulted ceiling and tall windows, the rich woods housing its scrolls.</p>
        <p>Built roughly four decades after the Westerkerk, the Portuguese Synagogue has nearly identical brass chandeliers, all orb and curve and swoop. They contain more than a thousand candles, because the building has never been electrified. Imagine High Holy evenings by candlelight, a sight now rarely seen.</p>
        <p>In the 17th century members of the  synagogue bought land for a cemetery they named Beth Haim (the House of Life) five and a half miles south of the city, at  Ouderkerk, where the smaller Bullewijk converges with the Amstel. We headed there, cycling toward the road that runs along the Amstel dike. At first our view  of the river was blocked by wall-to-wall houseboats, while far-off cranes leaned  like giraffes over half-finished apartment blocks.</p>
        <p>But after we passed under the thick ring road that girds the city, vistas opened out. Here were cattails and parkland, a lazy river traffic of yachts with their masts down in preparation for the bridges ahead. The Amstel brims, as if one added cup would make it tremble over its dikes. And yet that impression ignores the intricacies of Dutch hydraulics, for the system of pumping and drainage is so carefully calibrated that as you ride along you can see simultaneously three different levels of water-fenced fields, where sheep and cows never encounter barbed wire.</p>
        <p>Our plan for this day's ride was to follow the route that funerary barges took in previous centuries as they made their way toward the water landing at Beth Haim. When we arrived, we locked up our bikes by the cemetery fence and immediately noticed evidence of a drainage and construction project, as well as a placard directing us to Kerkstraat 7 across the street for more information. There we were delighted to talk with Derek Brown, office manager for the cemetery and its restoration. Many of the cemetery's 27,000 graves, he told us, have now disappeared into marsh, though in the late 19th century a member of the community, David Henriques de Castro, had personally paid for the raising, restoring and photographing of 70 of its most elaborately carved marble tombs. Even these have now resettled much lower. But they can still be seen, along with numerous other handsome, ornate tombs set among Beth Haim's acres of grassy fields and gracious old trees.</p>
        <p>Part of what makes this site so exceptional -- perhaps the most exceptional Jewish cemetery in Europe -- is the Amsterdam Sephardic community's loose interpretation of the biblical proscription against images of God. One stone shows divine hands gripping a hatchet to fell the tree of life, another an angel descending just in time to rescue a kneeling Isaac from his father's knife -- though most, like that of Rembrandt's next door neighbor Daniel Pinto, are more conventional, with skillfully executed floral motifs. As we wandered around, Victor and I searched for Spinoza's parents (grave No. 31 on Henriques de Castro's map), but could not find them -- an unfulfilled quest that seemed appropriate to this evocative, elm-shaded place.</p>
        <p>The next morning we awoke not to a complex, painterly Dutch sky but to something more rare in the Netherlands: pure sun. We headed for the free bicycle ferry in back of Centraal Station, which crosses the IJ every few minutes. Its berth on the north side of the harbor almost adjoins the shady bike path along the Noord Hollands Canal. Dug in 1819-1825 and intended to ease the passage of oceangoing ships into Amsterdam, the canal today provides an amenity for cyclists and houseboat owners, though its drawbridges still get some use from barge-pushing tugs. It's a smooth conduit into Waterland, a region of lush polders formed from lakes drained in the 17th century, Mondrian-straight bike paths and unspoiled villages.</p>
        <p>Waterland now borders the IJsselmeer, the freshwater lake formed in 1932 from the damming of the Zuider Zee. Both Jeroen, my Dutch son-in-law, and Rob at Bike City had mentioned looping through it as a favorite ride, one offering a wide horizon on Dutch culture. And when we saw the church spires of our destination towns miles away rising over the plain, we felt as if we were cycling through a Ruisdael painting.</p>
        <p>The first of these spires belonged to the Protestant church of Broek in Waterland, Hans Brinker's village. Although the beautifully detailed church is steeped in history (built in the 14th century, burned by Spanish soldiers in the 16th, rebuilt in the 17th), its contemporary members aren't cowed by it. Their information sheet directs visitors' attention to a stained-glass window depicting the great conflagration, but someone has also provided a soft sculpture granny who's asleep in one of the pews.</p>
        <p>On the outskirts of Broek we spied the towers of Monnickendam, an old port town about two miles northeast, noted for its fish restaurants and pleasure boats. Following signs for the town's ''haven,'' or harbor, we came to the waterside terrace of 't Markerveerhuis, where we lunched very pleasantly. But outside Monnickendam, we gave up our spire-markers to follow the long curves of the path atop the IJsselmeer dike.</p>
        <p>Jeroen had warned us about prevailing winds on the dike and on the causeway out to the nearby island of Marken in the late afternoon. Today, however, we had nothing to worry about: the IJsselmeer was an unruffled sheet of haze, still as the herons perched by the polders' ditches. We veered southeast down the headland, glorying in the dike's exposure.  Approximately five miles beyond Monnickendam we turned inland, toward the tiny, boggy village of Holy sloot. Its attraction was a bicycle ferry, indicated on our map, which made possible a shortcut back to the city.</p>
        <p>The first person we queried in Holysloot turned out to be the ferryman himself, who sold us cold drinks while we waited for a boatful of cyclists to accumulate. The ferry dropped us off in a cow-pied pasture -- no bike path in sight, only five white sawhorselike structures that upon closer inspection included narrow rails at ground level. These were loopbruggen, as we learned from a sign, ditch-spanning bridges intended for cyclists on foot pushing their bikes.</p>
        <p>The sophistication of Amsterdam seemed a long way off, though in fact we were back within city limits in less than an hour. In the trickiest part of the whole expedition, we had to chart a careful course back across the Noord Hollands Canal in order to reach the IJ bicycle ferry, which docks on its western side. Our ride to and through Waterland had totaled nearly 19 miles -- about 7 more than the previous day's -- leaving us pleasantly tired when we returned to our temporary home in the Jordaan.</p>
        <p>Any of the towns along our routes, even diminutive Holysloot, can be reached by bus from Amsterdam. But the slower pace and unframed vista of bicycle travel give one -- besides the chance to be a reborn 10-year-old -- ample time to absorb the landscape. In this city and its surroundings, where not only architecture and history are human creations but also much of the land itself, the lack of velocity offers a special opportunity. And it won't take your breath away.</p>
        <p>Perhaps a houseboat on a canal?</p>
        <p>Lodging</p>
        <p>Hotel Acacia, Lindengracht 251, (31-20) 622-1460; or fax (31-20) 638-0748, has 14 rooms, 2 studio rooms with kitchenettes, and 5 houseboat rooms furnished as studios, which can accommodate two to five people; all have private baths. Though in a quiet, peripheral location, the Acacia offers easy access to the city center from a nearby tram stop. Doubles range from $62.50 for a regular room to $90 for houseboat accommodations, breakfast included.</p>
        <p>The Canal House Hotel, Keizersgracht 148, (31-20) 622-5182, fax (31-20) 624-1317), offers some of the area's most pleasant and elegant accommodations. Breakfast (included in the price) is served in a large room, with grand piano, overlooking the garden. Its 26 antique-furnished rooms range from $115 (single) to $150 (double).</p>
        <p>Hotel van Onna, Bloemgracht 102-108, (31-20) 626-5801, is a small budget hotel in a beautiful location. Rooms are clean but spartan; all have private baths but no telephones. Rates are $32 a person per night, breakfast included.</p>
        <p>Food</p>
        <p>Two streets in the Jordaan contain numerous ethnic restaurants and cafes: the Lindengracht and the Eerste Leliedwarsstraat (which veers off the Bloemgracht and changes its name every block).</p>
        <p>Avare, Lindengracht 248, (31-20) 639-3167, serves an extensive menu of fresh, well-prepared Turkish food in a cozy atmosphere; dinner for two, with wine and tip, is about $50.</p>
        <p>Cafe 't Smalle, Egelantiersgracht 12, (31-20) 623-9617, offers a long list of reasonably priced sandwiches and drinks, as well as delicious soups of the day.</p>
        <p>Bikes</p>
        <p>One- or multispeed bicycles can be rented at Bike City, Bloemgracht 68-70; (31-20) 626-3721; MacBike, Mr. Visserplein 2, (31-20) 620-0985; and Holland Rent a Bike, Damrak 247, (31-20) 622-3207. All three charge $5 for the first day of renting a one-speed. Their weekly rental rates for one-speeds are, respectively, $20, $24 and $26.</p>
        <p>Yellow Bike, Nieuwezijds Kolk 29, (31-20) 620-6940, runs daily bike tours from April 1 to Nov. 1 of the Amsterdam and Waterland areas. The tours, which are led by English-speaking guides, cost $13 (in the city) and $17 (in the country); the fee includes bike rental but not lunch.</p>
        <p>Pied a Terre, Singel 393, (31-20) 627-4455, has a large selection of hiking and biking maps and travel books; it's a great place to browse.</p>
        <p>The ferry at Holysloot costs 40 cents; it runs from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. every day in July and August, and on Saturdays and Sundays in other warm weather months.</p>
        <p>Places to See</p>
        <p>The Westerkerk is at Prinsengracht 281; (31-20) 624-7766. Groups form there for hourly tours of the tower from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Monday to Saturday, April through September; $1.20 a person; if you join the Tuesday noon tour, you'll see the carillon player at his strenuous art. Part of the church's concert schedule is posted on its organist's Web site: www.josvanderkooy.com.</p>
        <p>At Mr. Visserplein 3, the Portuguese Synagogue, also called the Esnoga, is across from the Jewish Historical Museum and quite close to the Rembrandthuis. It is open all year round Sunday to Friday from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. The admission charge is $3. For more information, call</p>
        <p>(31-20) 624-5351 or visit www.esnoga</p>
        <p>.com.</p>
        <p>Beth Haim is where two rivers converge in the attractive old town of Ouderkerk aan de Amstel. For more information check its Web site: www .bethaim.com.</p>
        <p>JUDITH YARNALL travels to the Netherlands frequently.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">JUDITH YARNALL travels to the Netherlands frequently.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
