<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Holy Places, Stormy Night: A Palestinian View of Camp David</title>
    <meta content="Y17MID$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/world/17MIDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231410"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Israel-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanieh, Akram</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE6DC1F38F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1059" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Holy Places, Stormy Night: A Palestinian View of Camp David</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Akram Hanieh, who accompanied Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat to Camp David, describes failed peace summit in series of articles in Palestinian newspaper; says Pres Clinton, on last stormy night, scored Arafat's intransigence on Jerusalem; says Arafat indicated that he feared for his life if he yielded on Jerusalem and holy sites; holds American officials working for Clinton were consistently allied with Israelis (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a dramatic account in a Palestinian newspaper on what happened at the Camp David summit meeting this summer, a confidant of the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, describes how Mr. Arafat castigated President Clinton on the last stormy night.</p>
        <p>The author, Akram Hanieh, who accompanied Mr. Arafat to the meeting and served as a chronicler for the Palestinians, wrote that after Mr. Clinton charged Mr. Arafat with being unyielding on the question of Jerusalem, Mr. Arafat retorted: ''Do you want to attend my funeral? I will not relinquish Jerusalem and the holy places.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a dramatic account in a Palestinian newspaper on what happened at the Camp David summit meeting this summer, a confidant of the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, describes how Mr. Arafat castigated President Clinton on the last stormy night.</p>
        <p>The author, Akram Hanieh, who accompanied Mr. Arafat to the meeting and served as a chronicler for the Palestinians, wrote that after Mr. Clinton charged Mr. Arafat with being unyielding on the question of Jerusalem, Mr. Arafat retorted: ''Do you want to attend my funeral? I will not relinquish Jerusalem and the holy places.''</p>
        <p>The article does not specifically explain Mr. Arafat's words, but it is clear from the context that Mr. Arafat was telling Mr. Clinton that he feared for his life if he deviated from his demand that East Jerusalem and Haram al Sharif, known to Jews as the Temple Mount, come under Palestinian sovereignty.</p>
        <p>A senior Clinton administration official confirmed on Friday that the exchange took place.</p>
        <p>The seven-part series of articles, which is considered to be the only first-hand description of the summit meeting to be published so far, appeared in Arabic in Al Ayyam, a Palestinian daily printed in Ramallah.</p>
        <p>The newspaper conveys the official point of view of the Palestinian Authority. And Mr. Hanieh, whom American officials know from his long association with Mr. Arafat, is its editor in chief.</p>
        <p>In many respects, the articles conform with much that has already emerged from Camp David but shed a Palestinian perspective on the events, the major players and the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hanieh describes the rural compound in the Maryland hills as an ''unreal world, far removed from the chaotic world we live in.'' He writes that the Americans laid down rules, especially a casual dress code, which, the author notes, was no problem for Mr. Arafat.</p>
        <p>''It seems that the Americans assumed that distance from formalities could break down barriers between negotiators,'' he wrote. He calls Mr. Clinton a ''son of the 60's'' who as president is the ''chairman of the board of the globe.''</p>
        <p>An English version of the articles is circulating around the State Department and the White House, where participants in the Camp David meeting say they are amused to read about themselves, although they are generally referred to -- collectively and disparagingly -- as the American Peace Team.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hanieh writes that the American officials working for Mr. Clinton were consistently allied with the Israelis.</p>
        <p>At one point, Mr. Hanieh dismisses the idea of ''vertical sovereignty'' over Haram al Sharif as the handiwork of the American ''legal genius.''</p>
        <p>Under this idea, Palestinians would have sovereignty over the land where the Haram stands, and Israel would have sovereignty under it where the great Jewish temples once existed.</p>
        <p>The Americans suggested, Mr. Hanieh says, that an international committee consisting of the United Nations Security Council and Morocco, the nation that serves as chairman of the Jerusalem committee of the Organization of the Islamic Conference, ''would give the State of Palestine custody of the Haram with Israel retaining sovereignty.''</p>
        <p>American officials said this week that a variation of this idea was being revived in talks that are now going on between the United States and the two sides in New York City.</p>
        <p>Throughout, Mr. Hanieh stresses that Mr. Arafat told Mr. Clinton that he could not make a decision on the future of Jerusalem alone.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat, he wrote, told the president: ''Jerusalem is not a Palestinian city only; it is an Arab, Islamic and Christian one. If I am going to take a decision on Jerusalem, I have to consult with the Sunnis and the Shiites and all Arab countries.''</p>
        <p>At another point, Mr. Hanieh quotes Mr. Arafat as saying: ''If I cannot liberate Jerusalem and raise the Palestinian flag there, one day someone else will liberate it and raise his country's flag.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hanieh gives specific details of the proposals that the Americans gave to Mr. Arafat as the summit meeting unfolded.</p>
        <p>On the seventh day -- July 17, he writes -- Mr. Clinton gave Mr. Arafat a proposal that called for ''a satisfactory solution to the refugee issue'' and the annexation of 9 percent of Palestinian land to Israel.</p>
        <p>The proposal then went on to deal with Jerusalem, granting Palestinian sovereignty to the Islamic and Christian quarters; the Armenian and Jewish quarters ''would be annexed to Israel.'' The proposal also outlined the idea that the Security Council and Morocco would grant custody to the Palestinian state to administer Haram al Sharif.</p>
        <p>At close to midnight on the final night, after his stormy meeting with Mr. Arafat, Mr. Clinton made a final proposal regarding Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hanieh described it in the following way, which does not contradict other published versions:</p>
        <p>*A committee that included the Security Council and Morocco would grant Palestine ''sovereign custody'' of the Haram, while Israel would retain ''residual sovereignty.''</p>
        <p>*The Muslim and Christian quarters of the Old City would come under Palestinian sovereignty. The Jewish and Armenian quarters would fall under Israeli sovereignty.</p>
        <p>*The Palestinians would have functional jurisdiction in what was called the internal neighborhoods, including Musrarah and Wadi al Joz.</p>
        <p>*Palestinian sovereignty would extend to the external neighborhoods of Jerusalem, or Palestinian sovereignty would cover the internal neighborhoods of Jerusalem and a special regime would be adopted in the Old City, the details of which would have to be agreed upon.</p>
        <p>After presenting this to Saeb Erekat, one of Mr. Arafat's senior aides, Mr. Clinton told Mr. Erekat to go to ''his leader'' and come back with an answer, Mr. Hanieh wrote.</p>
        <p>Mr. Erekat returned with a letter at about 1 a.m. Mr. Arafat wrote that he valued Mr. Clinton's efforts and hoped that they would continue. But the letter said the proposals on Jerusalem ''were in contradiction'' to ''international references.''</p>
        <p>After hearing a translation of the letter, Mr. Hanieh says, Mr. Clinton replied, ''I expected this answer.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
