<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blinding Them With Smiles</title>
    <meta content="17NOTI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/living/17NOTI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NOTICED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teeth and Dentistry</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hayt, Elizabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Teeth and Dentistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teeth and Dentistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EFD91038F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1329" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blinding Them With Smiles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH HAYT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hayt, Elizabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cosmetic dentists say more and more patients, apparently influenced by cosmetically enhanced smiles on people in movies, ads and on television, are having their teeth bleached very white; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT first glance, Bridget Fojut's teeth are so perfect -- two rows of straight, big, white Chiclets -- it's hard to believe she is in the chair of Dr. Jeff Golub-Evans, a cosmetic dentist on the Upper East Side, to undergo a bleaching treatment. But Ms. Fojut, 28, an artist and bartender at the W Hotel, believes that her teeth have a slightly yellowish cast, particularly when she wears her favorite lipstick -- ''a Barbie doll pink by Christian Dior.''</p>
        <p>Preferring to pay $350 to bleach her teeth rather than $22 to switch lipsticks, Ms. Fojut told her dentist that she wants her teeth as light as the whites of her eyes. ''I think my teeth are white, and I'm pro natural things,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT first glance, Bridget Fojut's teeth are so perfect -- two rows of straight, big, white Chiclets -- it's hard to believe she is in the chair of Dr. Jeff Golub-Evans, a cosmetic dentist on the Upper East Side, to undergo a bleaching treatment. But Ms. Fojut, 28, an artist and bartender at the W Hotel, believes that her teeth have a slightly yellowish cast, particularly when she wears her favorite lipstick -- ''a Barbie doll pink by Christian Dior.''</p>
        <p>Preferring to pay $350 to bleach her teeth rather than $22 to switch lipsticks, Ms. Fojut told her dentist that she wants her teeth as light as the whites of her eyes. ''I think my teeth are white, and I'm pro natural things,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Not long ago, patients like Ms. Fojut were highly unusual: the owners of beautiful smiles, who want to turn up the wattage even brighter. But standards of what constitutes an attractive smile have changed, say cosmetic dentists and the makers of dental products like porcelain laminates and crowns. Influenced by the cosmetically enhanced smiles flashed in movies, advertising and on television, patients insist on teeth that are white, whiter, whitest.</p>
        <p>Several dentists cited the influence of Regis Philbin, whose blinding pearly whites appear to have penetrated the American consciousness as profoundly as his offer to mint new millionaires. Dr. Golub-Evans, for one, calls the dental shade of choice today ''Regis White.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Stephen Sylvan, a cosmetic dentist with offices in Manhattan and Great Neck, N.Y., said: ''You don't see crooked or dark teeth anymore in movies or on TV. Whiter and whiter teeth have become an accepted possibility for everyone.''</p>
        <p>A look at dentists' shade guides, or standards for matching a patient's natural teeth to dental products, shows that the bright smile of several years ago appears to be too dim today. In the last few years, laminates, crowns, inlays and filling material have become lighter, dentists say. What was once perceived as so bright it was fake-looking is now considered fabulous.</p>
        <p>''Initially when I started, the natural look was different than it is today,'' said Adrian Jurim, a dental ceramist in Great Neck, who has been manufacturing porcelain laminates since the early 1980's.</p>
        <p>''People emulate what they see on the screen or tube. A few years ago, today's shades would have been considered ridiculous or laughable,'' he said. Six years ago, Bob Pisarro, an owner of America's Dental Laboratory in New York, created a line of camera-friendly laminates -- thin shells of porcelain custom-fitted to the teeth -- for people in the entertainment business. Now, the shade, called Hollywood White, has become the favorite for average patients who simply want Hollywood-style glamour.</p>
        <p>Other dental product makers report a similar shift to the blinding end of the spectrum. Cosmedent in Chicago and Ultradent in Salt Lake City have added lighter shades named Bleach White and Opaque Snow, respectively.</p>
        <p>Fifteen years ago, the model Paulina Porizkova had her teeth bonded, a technique in which resin is applied to correct dental defects. But now she is getting a ''smile makeover'' from Dr. Golub-Evans to make her teeth even whiter. ''This is America, land of refrigerator teeth,'' said Ms. Porizkova, who is back before the cameras this week as host of the Style Network's cable coverage of the New York fashion collections.</p>
        <p>The specialty of cosmetic dentistry -- which focuses on appearance, as opposed to health -- is growing as more and more patients decide that the ideal smile is no longer simply showing straight, cavity-free teeth, said Dr. Michael C. Alfano, the dean of New York University College of Dentistry. N.Y.U. is constructing a building to house a cosmetic dentistry institute. ''We expect it to become a major part of our curriculum because that's what dentists are being asked to do,'' Dr. Alfano said.</p>
        <p>A survey last year by Dental Products Report, a trade journal, found that 96 percent of American dentists offer at-home tooth whiteners, and 55 percent provide bleaching in their offices. The American Academy of Cosmetic Dentistry, whose membership this year, 4,698, is twice what it was in 1996, noted in its spring 2000 newsletter that there has been a threefold increase in bleaching over the last five years. The five most popular procedures are whitening, laminates, tooth-colored inlays and onlays, tooth-colored crowns and bonding.</p>
        <p>Bleaching, in fact, has created a new population of ultra-white smiles, as patients fight the natural yellowing of the teeth that comes with age, and discoloration caused by smoking or drinking colas, coffee and red wine.</p>
        <p>The basic bleaching agent is peroxide. Mild solutions are used in at-home kits. A dentist makes the patient a custom mouth guard or teeth tray, which is injected with a whitening gel, and worn from two hours to overnight for about two weeks. The cost is about $600. More intense concentrations are used in in-office bleaching, also known as laser or power bleaching; the dentist applies a whitening agent to the teeth, which is then activated by a special light.</p>
        <p>There are no proven problems associated with the treatments, Dr. Alfano of N.Y.U. said, other than temporary tooth sensitivity and gum irritation that some experience.</p>
        <p>Bleaching is only the latest step in the brightening of the American smile that began with fluoridating drinking water two generations ago and continued with widespread access to orthodontia.</p>
        <p>Cy Curnin, lead singer for the band the Fixx, who is from London but lives in New York, scoffed at Americans' obsession with newscaster dentition. ''When I go on tour, I know which country I'm in because of the smiles in the audience,'' he said. ''You know you're in America because of the piano teeth. Everyone is having UV lights installed in their mouths. It's all about homogeny -- eating at McDonald's and having white teeth. When we're on stage, I tell the band to open their mouths to show the audience what real English teeth look like -- a graveyard.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes the demand for superwhite teeth exceeds the results that even the latest bleaching technology can offer, and then patients seek laminates, despite costs that can reach $1,000 a tooth. Laminates, also known as veneers, are fitted to the front surface of each tooth after it has been shaved down half a millimeter, the thickness of a fingernail.</p>
        <p>The alteration of the actual tooth is irreversible, although some patients eventually change laminates. Dr. Ken Hamlett, a cosmetic dentist in Dallas, said that five years ago a patient, a venture capitalist, got veneers in the lightest shade. Now the man wants his mouth relaminated in a newer, lighter shade, which the dentist likens to porcelain china.</p>
        <p>Can teeth ever be too white? ''I think yes,'' Dr. Alfano said. ''It's not that it damages the function of the teeth, but they can look unnatural.''</p>
        <p>A patient of Dr. Sylvan's, a homemaker, had her teeth laminated in 1987 because they were yellowing and uneven. ''They came out really nice,'' said the patient, who didn't want anyone to know she had her teeth whitened. ''I was happy. In those days, the idea was to look natural, as if they weren't done. It's not like that now. Because of teeth bleaching, everyone has white teeth these days. I redid them recently because I saw my manicurist's teeth. She had had her's done, and they looked great. I'm happy with mine now, but in my mind, they could even be whiter. You start this and you get crazy.''</p>
        <p>NOTICED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
