<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crafts and Community</title>
    <meta content="17SEAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN SEARCH OF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Handicrafts</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Peters Valley Craft Center</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'agnese Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicrafts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EEDE1338F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crafts and Community</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH D'AGNESE</byline>
      <dateline>LAYTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Peters Valley Craft Education Center, school for craft artists in Layton, NJ, within Delaware Water Gap Naitonal Recreation Area, where classes are open to all; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EACH night this past summer, after classes, after dinner, David Bogus sneaked off with his pals to the ceramics studio in the woods near the Delaware River here. He turned on some music, and took his place at the wheel. As night closed in and fireflies flickered, the 22-year-old potter turned clay into art.</p>
        <p>All told, he would spend 17 weeks assisting instructors in the ceramics classes here, but the nights belonged to him. ''The pots just keep getting better,'' Mr. Bogus said recently. ''But I worked really hard. All night, every night. It was like a community in itself.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EACH night this past summer, after classes, after dinner, David Bogus sneaked off with his pals to the ceramics studio in the woods near the Delaware River here. He turned on some music, and took his place at the wheel. As night closed in and fireflies flickered, the 22-year-old potter turned clay into art.</p>
        <p>All told, he would spend 17 weeks assisting instructors in the ceramics classes here, but the nights belonged to him. ''The pots just keep getting better,'' Mr. Bogus said recently. ''But I worked really hard. All night, every night. It was like a community in itself.''</p>
        <p>That sense of community is practically palpable at the Peters Valley Craft Education Center, a school for craft artists that occupies some 3,600 acres within the Delaware Water Gap National Recreation Area.  Weekend tourists who meander the winding roads in the area are often stunned to find artists living and working in the old farmhouses and barns that dot the roads. (Fourteen of the structures are on the National Historic Register.) But perhaps they shouldn't be surprised; the Peters Valley artists have peacefully coexisted with the park for 30 years, earning an international reputation in the process. But one does not have to be a galleried artist to learn here; classes are open to all.</p>
        <p>Each year tens of thousands people do their gift buying at the school's gallery and shop, a renovated general store that offers the work of 300 craftspeople worldwide, many of them the school's instructors, alumni and students. Found here are pieces of fine ceramics, jewelry, clothing, basketry, metal sculpture, and more. And nearly 15,000 art-hungry travelers will descend on these hills next weekend (Sept. 23 and 24) for the Peters Valley Craft Fair, an annual event featuring the work of 160 artists selected in a rigorous jury process. Visitors come to snap up one-of-a-kind pieces, sample the food, and listen to the music.</p>
        <p>From now until then, the artists are readying themselves for the big weekend. The fair, the 30th annual event, and its accompanying dinner and auctions, contribute 9 percent of the center's annual operating budget. This year, more than 100 artists are expected to donate pieces to Saturday  night's live auction, and to the silent auction held over the entire weekend. (Prices range from $50 to $3,000.)</p>
        <p>Kenn Jones, the center's director, tells of a distraught woman who last year politely requested that her $5 entrance fee be refunded. ''I came for crafts,'' she said, ''but this isn't arts and crafts. It's fine art.'' The story illustrates how the word ''craft'' is often misunderstood in the culture, and why Peters Valley must re-educate the public each year. Now, said Mr. Jones, ''I like to say that these are artists who make things that just happen to be made of wood and  clay and other natural elements.''</p>
        <p>On a recent Saturday, the studios hummed with activity. In the commissary, the chef, Susanne Wilson, seasoned chicken for dinner as the sounds of jazz wafted through her kitchen. Down the hill, an instructor hammered and sanded a wooden piece of artwork on the second-story porch of ''the Greek,'' a striking Greek Revival farmhouse where classes in drawing and painting are conducted. The porch was littered with power tools and an odd-looking frame. Mr. Jones led a visitor up for a peek. ''I think they're going to stretch a canvas over the top of it,'' he said. ''He's making a piece for our auction.'' Downstairs in the front hall, a clothes line ran along the wall, clipped with drawings of lounging life-class nudes. The front and back doors of the Greek were propped open, offering a view of black-eyed Susans swaying in the yard.</p>
        <p>A short drive away, on Thunder Mountain, where the center operates four studios, photography students pored over color slides, and students in Susan Sloan's fine metals class sanded pendants and brooches they had created. Patricia Bronstein, a Cliffside Park resident, had embedded a pair of actual insect wings in a block of pink epoxy resin. Ms. Bronstein, who has a house in Milford, Pa., and has taken courses at the center for years, allowed that the piece's  genesis was more serendipitous than inspired: ''I found those moth wings outside when I was walking my dog.''</p>
        <p>Next door, in the fibers studio, Dorothy Caldwell's students imprinted swatches of fabric with designs using rice paste. They  would later dye the fabric, rub off the paste, and expose the design.</p>
        <p>May Eason, a perennial craft fair participant, was stenciling the single image of a bamboo branch and a spray of leaves onto a trio of silk scarves.</p>
        <p>For the younger student assistants who work summers here for a stipend and the opportunity to create, the fair is a kind of  debutante ball, a chance to make public what flows from their hearts and hands. Peters Valley is a transition zone between  university life and the outside world.</p>
        <p>Such is the case for Ms. Caldwell's assistant, Dana Naugle, who, in a corner of the fibers studio, unfolded her summer's work: a number of scarves, a shawl and a beaded bag. The chenille fabric, rendered in bright blues, purples, greens and yellows, had a characteristically nubbly feel. The 80-by-33-inch shawl took nearly 14 hours to produce.</p>
        <p>Ms. Naugle, a 22-year-old crafts graduate of Kutztown University, jokes that the fringe alone took ''two movies'' to do. At the fair, she and her fellow student assistants will display their work in a booth. Scarves will fetch $50 to $75, the shawl, $250. ''The  shawl I completely wanted to keep for myself,'' said Ms. Naugle. ''But I tell myself I can always make myself another one.''</p>
        <p>Peters Valley also offers coveted artist-in-residence posts to accomplished instructors. Bruce Dehnert, the head of the ceramics department who has taught in Manhattan, Borneo and New Zealand, shares a private studio on the center's grounds with his wife, the painter Kulvinder Kaur Dhew. Her vibrant, colorful canvases hang on one wall, while his wheel and bench take up the other side of the studio.</p>
        <p>''There's a dividing line down the middle of the room,'' Mr. Dehnert said, chuckling. This summer Mr. Dehnert supervised 3 assistants and 17 instructors. This fall, he will coordinate eight different classes, some available for college credit. In between, he'll try to squeeze in his own work.</p>
        <p>On a tour of the center's five working kilns, Mr. Dehnert professed reverence for the center's two wood-burning kilns: the  noborigama, or multichambered kiln, and the anagama, or tunnel kiln, built into a hillside. Both achieve temperatures of 2,400 degrees Fahrenheit. Once fired up, the anagama is kept running for at least five days and nights. Caretaking the kiln becomes something of a ritual, as teachers and students take shifts tending the fire. Clay  works are coated not with glaze, but cast-off ash, then inserted in the kiln. At that heat, fire and ash augment the potter's craft,  unpredictably altering each piece. What emerges after each firing is a collaboration of man and flame.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dehnert lifted a bowl from a table where months of Mr. Bogus's work lay in a jumble: platters and cups and bowls streaked with earthy yellow, green and olive glazes. On most, molten glaze had cooled at the bottoms of the pieces. Sometime before the fair, Mr. Bogus will grind down the bottom drips only.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Dehnert explained, the haphazard markings were highly desirable. ''Here the glaze dripped down,'' Mr. Dehnert said. ''Here, the flame came up like this, like a river of water. As you turn the pot, you can look at the glaze and it's almost as if it tells the story of what happened in the kiln.''</p>
        <p>The story of creation.</p>
        <p>In Their Hands</p>
        <p>The Peters Valley Craft Fair takes place 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. next Saturday, and 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. next Sunday, at the Peters Valley Craft Education Center, 19 Kuhn Road, Layton, in the Delaware Water Gap National Recreation Area; (973) 948-5200. Admission is $5; children under 12 admitted free. Auction and dinner begins 6:30 p.m Saturday night; cost is $35 a person. Call the office for advance ticket sales. For more information on the fair or classes, see www.pvcrafts.org.peters valley.doc</p>
        <p>IN SEARCH OF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
