<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All Together Now</title>
    <meta content="SPAIN.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/travel/SPAIN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marin, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EED71F39F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1319" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All Together Now</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK MARIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marin, Rick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rick Marin travel essay describes weeklong trip to Spain with girlfriend, his mother, girlfriend's best friend and her husband and 1-year-old daughter; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ORIGINALLY my girlfriend, my mother and I were going to Spain for a week, a combination whose wisdom had been called into question by some skeptical parties. (''Your girlfriend and your mother?'') Then it turned out that my girlfriend's best friend and her husband were going the same week, with their 1-year-old daughter. Why not all go together?</p>
        <p>More skeptical parties weighed in: ''Your girlfriend, your mother and a baby? You're nuts!'' Words to that effect.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ORIGINALLY my girlfriend, my mother and I were going to Spain for a week, a combination whose wisdom had been called into question by some skeptical parties. (''Your girlfriend and your mother?'') Then it turned out that my girlfriend's best friend and her husband were going the same week, with their 1-year-old daughter. Why not all go together?</p>
        <p>More skeptical parties weighed in: ''Your girlfriend, your mother and a baby? You're nuts!'' Words to that effect.</p>
        <p>But Cynthia (the best friend), a pathological optimist, was having none of that. ''It'll be like when Lucy and Ricky and Fred and Ethel and Little Ricky and Mrs. Trumbull the baby sitter went to Europe,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ilene (the girlfriend) agreed, as long as we got to be the Ricardos and they were the Mertzes. After all, I'm the half-Spanish one. Either way, the main issue remained: could three generations travel together to a foreign land without driving one another  crazy?</p>
        <p>Cynthia took along a copy of ''The Sun Also Rises'' -- not a pretty picture of what happens when friends travel to Spain together.  What fino-induced fisticuffs, what doomed affairs  with bullfighters, what dark novelistic dramas awaited our Spanish holiday?</p>
        <p>First, buying tickets. Coordinating June departure and return dates for six people at the last minute ensured that our seats were economy-class in name only.</p>
        <p>Baby Kit was very well behaved on the standing-room-only flight over. I cried more than she did.</p>
        <p>Our itinerary was to fly from New York to Madrid for the first weekend, split up for a few days, then reconnoiter at the end of the week in Barcelona. If we'd had enough of communal travel in the first 48 hours, there was a built-in separation mechanism.</p>
        <p>Our agendas were different. My mother  and I were going to see relatives -- my three Spanish aunts, my father's sisters, who hadn't seen us since some years before my father died three years ago. Cynthia and Bill had never been to Spain and wanted to cover as much ground as they could.</p>
        <p>For the days we were together, our brilliant idea was that the four of us could leave the baby at the hotel with my mother while we partied into the night. She said no: too heavy a responsibility in a foreign country. Also, it turned out she, too, wanted to party into the night. Fair enough: no baby-sitting. The parents would handle that.</p>
        <p>At Barajas Airport in Madrid, I sailed through customs with my Spanish passport and waited for the rest of our caravan to catch up and collect the bags. Luggage is one of the many things that the older and the infant traveler have in common, in the sense that they can usually get other people to carry it.</p>
        <p>My mother, who is 77, needs a little help. She likes having a cane to hold on one side and a firm arm on the other. Being a model son, I was of course happy to oblige. On Day 2 in Madrid, my back went out from obliging. This was my fault, though I may have suggested otherwise at the time.</p>
        <p>We'd gone to the Reina Sofia modern art museum, but it was closed, so we thought we'd try the Thyssen-Bornemisza Museum, just up the Paseo del Prado. I had the bright  idea that we should walk there. In the rain. Ilene sprinted ahead, to avert a hair disaster. My mother leaned harder and harder on my left arm. I spent the next week walking like Groucho Marx. From then on we took cabs.</p>
        <p>The usual problem with group activity is centrifugal. Someone wants to go to a bullfight. Someone else thinks it's a barbarous pagan ritual. The advantage of being more than two people is that odds are you won't be on your own whichever side you're on. For the most part we achieved consensus, with the exception of several hours in a flamenco dress shop. Shopping should never be attempted in groups larger than one.</p>
        <p>After our weekend in Madrid, Cynthia, Bill and baby drove north, to Biarritz, San Sebastian and Bilbao. We took the train south, into La Mancha. Two of my aunts awaited us in the village of Calzada de Calatrava, where they and my father had grown up.</p>
        <p>After a huge lunch, we walked to the park past the street named for my great uncle -- the Spanish Army's top veterinarian in the days when armies had top veterinarians. Ilene napped on a bench while the aunts reminisced about my father. The next night there was more heartfelt nostalgia in Torrevieja, a resort town on the Mediterranean where my third aunt, Paca, lives in an apartment near the ocean.</p>
        <p>I mention all the family time being logged as prelude to Ilene's early departure for a day of nonrelative time in Bilbao. This could have been some sort of drama op: the girlfriend chooses friends and the Guggenheim over family! But no feathers ruffled: it seemed like a perfectly sensible thing to do.</p>
        <p>The separation didn't last long. The next day the six of us ended up in the Barcelona airport at the same time. After some joking about not being able to shake one another, we headed for the Hotel Arts, part of the Olympic waterfront reclamation. The management of this gleaming Ritz-Carlton had upgraded us, thanks to Cynthia's high-powered travel agent, to enormous high-floor suites with staggering views of the city, mountains and sea. Each couple had one, and so did my mother, who was having a problem with the decadence level.</p>
        <p>The Arts is high tech in an anticonvenient way. The bedside master-control consoles are marginally less complicated than the cockpit of a 747. You spend more time trying to figure out which button  turns out the bathroom light than it would  take just to get out of bed, walk over and  do it the old-fashioned way.</p>
        <p>Generational priorities were suddenly thrown into stark relief. My mother, a child of the Depression, became the first person in hotel history to request a downgrade. Even in the smaller room, she still couldn't figure out the stereo. But then neither could I. The baby had her own reaction to the over-the-top opulence. She threw up.</p>
        <p>Traveling is often said to be the litmus test of a relationship. You'd think the litmus would be at least doubly exacting for two couples, one mom and a kid. But I think it was easier. You can't really stop speaking to your girlfriend in front of another couple. Well, you can try, but you feel like an idiot pretty fast.</p>
        <p>We celebrated our last night in Madrid at a restaurant favored by matadors and bullfight aficionados. A place called Ricardo's. That was as close as we got to Lucy and Ricky on the trip -- or to Jake Barnes and Lady Brett Ashley. In ''The Sun Also Rises'' the most damning thing you could say about someone was that he or she had ''behaved badly.'' If only we could have behaved badly! The presence of an elder and a helpless child necessitated an inordinate amount of responsible behavior. The late-night partying never happened, unless you count an after-hours drink on a terraza with a couple of Madrilenos.</p>
        <p>Boring? You could look at it that way. Only it wasn't. We didn't drive one another mad, after all. The occasional difference of opinion maybe. But no lives taken, nor years added on to anyone's therapy. It was merely fun, good and clean. A functional family vacation. Maybe there is something new under the sun.</p>
        <p>RICK MARIN is a reporter in the style department of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">RICK MARIN is a reporter in the style department of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
