<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nice View, but Watch Where You Step</title>
    <meta content="17AMMO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/nyregion/17AMMO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cornwall (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Storm King State Park (NYS)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Military Academy (West Point, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foderaro, Lisa W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E0DE1F38F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1185" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nice View, but Watch Where You Step</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA W. FODERARO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Foderaro, Lisa W</byline>
      <dateline>CORNWALL, N.Y., Sept. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Artillery shells that are up to 100 years old are buried just beneath surface at Storm King State Park in Cornwall, NY; park is adjacent to old artillery range belonging to United States Military Academy at West Point that operated in mid-19th century; cadets and foundry workers would fire munitions at range and some failed to explode; heat from forest fire in 1999 set off several shells, forcing temporary closing of area, and bringing to light 1994 Army study reporting unknown number of unexploded shells; bomb-disposal specialists, surveyors and navigation experts are combing trails, using global positioning technology and metal detectors to locate ordnance; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the warm breath of summer gives way to crisp autumn breezes, people who love the outdoors put on their hiking boots and head for the hills. But this fall, a favorite mountain in the New York region, Storm King -- prized for rugged terrain and panoramic views of the Hudson River -- will be off limits.</p>
        <p>It is not over concern that a rattlesnake may bite a hiker in the leg, though there are rattlesnakes here aplenty. It is that a hiker may lose a leg altogether.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the warm breath of summer gives way to crisp autumn breezes, people who love the outdoors put on their hiking boots and head for the hills. But this fall, a favorite mountain in the New York region, Storm King -- prized for rugged terrain and panoramic views of the Hudson River -- will be off limits.</p>
        <p>It is not over concern that a rattlesnake may bite a hiker in the leg, though there are rattlesnakes here aplenty. It is that a hiker may lose a leg altogether.</p>
        <p>By a quirk of location, Storm King State Park has the kind of hazard more likely to be expected on a battlefield, albeit one with striking scenery. Artillery shells that are up to a century old -- some of them are still live -- are buried just beneath the soil, lurking next to lichen-covered boulders and wispy wildflowers. A delicate military operation, involving 19 technicians using computerized sensing equipment, is now under way to ferret them out.</p>
        <p>''It was a shock,'' said Jan Hesbon, executive director of the New York-New Jersey Trail Conference, a federation of hiking clubs and environmental groups that maintains 1,300 miles of trails in the two states, including those at Storm King. ''Part of the shock is that these things have been there for more than 100 years. During all that time, they had been forgotten.''</p>
        <p>The 1,874 acres of parkland lie adjacent to an old artillery range that is on property belonging to the United States Military Academy at West Point. The park, about 50 miles north of New York City, is also just across the Hudson River from a gun foundry in Cold Spring, N.Y., that operated in the mid-19th century. Over the decades, both cadets and foundry workers fired munitions at the range. ''Unfortunately, they missed from time to time,'' said David Brouwer, the Army Corps of Engineers project manager in charge of the ordnance removal here.</p>
        <p>A result was that Storm King Mountain, a state park since the 1920's, was pelted with wayward rounds until the range was closed around 1940, and some of those shells failed to explode. Apparently no one paid much heed. In August 1999, however, the ordnance announced itself with a bang when heat from a forest fire in the park set off several shells, blasting small craters in the earth and forcing firefighters to retreat.</p>
        <p>A 1994 Army study, which came to light only after the forest fire, reported an unknown amount of unexploded shells on Storm King.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brouwer said that after the 1994 report, ''the people who evaluated the data concluded that there wasn't great enough risk to warrant immediate action. But that all changed with the fires.''</p>
        <p>The park has been closed since the shells exploded, and this summer, the Army Corps of Engineers finally began to search for live shells within 25 feet of hiking trails, around four parking areas and along two roads. So far, workers have discovered seven live 75-millimeter artillery shells, the kind commonly used during World Wars I and II, and have blown them up on the site. The search is about half done, Mr. Brouwer said.</p>
        <p>No Civil War-era ordnance has turned up during the search. But remnants of shells from that era have been found in the park over the years, and this is why the Army believes that the gun foundry also fired rounds at the range.</p>
        <p>Bomb-disposal specialists, surveyors and navigation experts are combing the rock-strewn trails in the park, using global positioning technology and metal detectors. Two searchers carry a scanner on a stretcher-like frame back and forth across the trails while another worker monitors their progress on a nearby computer. Any metal object found within a foot of the surface is indicated on the computer screen.</p>
        <p>While no one on the search team is complaining about the views, the conditions have been less than ideal. Because of persistent rain, a cloud of gnats surrounds the workers.</p>
        <p>Then there was the rattlesnake den. ''One of the guys caught one and chopped its head off,'' said Bob Harrer, the safety patrol officer for the project.</p>
        <p>The exact extent of the danger posed to hikers remains unclear. Over the years, no one has been injured by the unexploded ammunition, Mr. Brouwer said.</p>
        <p>Heat can cause a live shell to explode, but campfires are prohibited in the park. Hunters use the park, too, however, and a bullet striking a live shell could detonate it. Experts say that simply walking on soil over an unexploded shell is unlikely to set it off. ''Unless someone really starts to beat them, they normally won't go off,'' Mr. Harrer said. ''But normally is a big word.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brouwer recalled a 1983 accident in which three boys in San Diego found an unexploded shell in a residential neighborhood that had been built in the 1960's on the site of an old artillery range. The shell went off as they played with it, killing two of them. ''It can happen,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mindful of examples like that one, officials say the park will remain closed at least until November, when a final report on the search is expected. ''Based on what we've seen so far, my inclination would be to say the park is probably safe once we get done, as long as we have brochures at the trail heads to make sure people in the park are aware of the hazard'' farther off the trails and roads, Mr. Brouwer said.</p>
        <p>The Army plans to spend about $800,000 on the operation this year, Mr. Brouwer said. It plans to spend $700,000 next year on a more extensive survey to define the ''nature and extent of contamination'' in the park, he said.</p>
        <p>United States Representative Sue W. Kelly, whose district includes the park, pressed the Army to move ahead with the cleanup after the shells exploded last summer. A spokesman for Mrs. Kelly, Rob Ostrander, described the inaction on the Army's part after the 1994 study as ''curious,'' adding that ''any risk is unacceptable.''</p>
        <p>Hikers are relieved that the park is being made safe. But some are sad that another fall will come and go without the pleasure of trekking the lofty Stillman Trail or surveying the Hudson from the dramatic overlook at Pitching Point.</p>
        <p>''It's a favorite viewpoint to look up and down the Hudson, across at Bannerman's Island and the ridges on the east Hudson,'' said Mr. Hesbon, of the New York-New Jersey trail group. ''Regardless of how you get to the top, it's spectacular.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
