<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sept. 10-16; The Three R's of the Moment</title>
    <meta content="17BOXA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231321"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E3DD1138F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="348" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sept. 10-16; The Three R's of the Moment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Marks</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reversals, reading and rats.</p>
        <p>The topics that dominated the political news last week spelled strategic difficulties and odd distractions for the Bush campaign.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reversals, reading and rats.</p>
        <p>The topics that dominated the political news last week spelled strategic difficulties and odd distractions for the Bush campaign.</p>
        <p>In the realm of tactical reversals, Gov. George W. Bush beat a wholesale retreat from his attempt to sidestep the Commission on Presidential Debates and impose his own debating schedule. On Thursday, the Bush campaign dropped any remaining objections it had to the commission plan and agreed to debate under all the original conditions laid out by the panel.</p>
        <p>As for reading and rats: these involved potholes on the campaign trail unearthed by the news media. An article in Vanity Fair offered an armchair assessment of Mr. Bush's propensity for mispronunciations: Dyslexia, a condition associated with problems in deciphering the written word. Mr. Bush, campaigning on health care issues in Florida, reacted by saying he had never been tested for dyslexia but dismissed the idea as media fancy.</p>
        <p>And then there was ''Rats.'' The word appeared for a split second in an anti-Gore commercial running in more than a dozen states across the country. The word was excused as a fragment of the word bureaucrats, various pieces of which flashed across the television screen in the spot by the Republican National Committee. When The New York Times ran a front-page article about it on Tuesday, the story quickly took on a life of its own, with Democrats crying foul and Republicans calling it an innocent oversight.</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign seemed happy to watch Mr. Bush's struggles from the media sidelines. On Wednesday, as Mr. Bush embarked on a major swing through Washington and California (total electoral votes: 65), Mr. Gore spent much of the day at a high school in Maine (total electoral votes: 4).</p>
        <p>Peter Marks</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
