<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN BRIEF</title>
    <meta content="17BBIZ$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Northrop Grumman Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TJ Enterprises</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strugatch, Warren</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E2D91538F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="315" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN BRIEF</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Warren Strugatch</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strugatch, Warren</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>T J Enterprises, owner of Leslie Alexander, whose business interests include Houston Rockets basketball team and North Fork vineyards, buys 20-acre parcel in Calverton, Long Island, from Northrop Grumman Corp for $2.8 million (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Leslie Alexander Buys 20 Acres From Grumman</p>
        <p>TJ Enterprises, which is owned by Leslie Alexander, whose business interests include the Houston Rockets basketball team and vineyards on the North Fork, has bought 20 acres in Calverton from the Northrop Grumman Corporation. The price was $2.8 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Leslie Alexander Buys 20 Acres From Grumman</p>
        <p>TJ Enterprises, which is owned by Leslie Alexander, whose business interests include the Houston Rockets basketball team and vineyards on the North Fork, has bought 20 acres in Calverton from the Northrop Grumman Corporation. The price was $2.8 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alexander is currently building a house in Southampton.</p>
        <p>The Calverton property, formerly used by Grumman in building warplanes for the Navy, contains three buildings totaling 125,500 square feet of office and laboratory space. Mr. Alexander said he had no immediate plans for the site.</p>
        <p>Bioscience Park Opens At Farmingdale Campus</p>
        <p>James Watson, the president of Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, joined officials from the State University at Farmingdale and the New York State Economic Development Corporation at the opening Monday of the Broad Hollow Bioscience Park, a $15 million, 50,000-square-foot complex on the SUNY-Farmingdale campus, off Route 110. The park is a collaboration between the university and the laboratory.</p>
        <p>Three start-up companies will move in this fall. OSI Pharmaceuticals, a drug-discovery company in Uniondale, plans to move in sometime next year as the anchor tenant.</p>
        <p>Plans include adding a second wing and a 13,000-square-foot addition.</p>
        <p>Symbol Founder Receives Postal Service Award</p>
        <p>Postmaster General William J. Henderson presented Dr. Jerome Swartz, the chairman and founder of Symbol Technologies (NYSE: SBL) in Holtsville, with the Postal Service's Partnership for Progress award on Monday at a national mailing industry conference in Anaheim, Calif. More than 300,000 Postal Service carriers and clerks use Symbol hand-held scanning computers to track mail deliveries.</p>
        <p>Symbol's bar-code technology is also used by the Postal Service in its PC Postage program, which enables consumers to print out postage over the Internet.</p>
        <p>In presenting the award, Mr. Henderson said that Symbol's efforts have helped increase productivity and efficiency and have given the Postal Service new tools to meet the customer demands.</p>
        <p>E-mail: libiz@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: libiz@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
