<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making the Best Choice For Beloved Old Trees</title>
    <meta content="17CUT.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/living/17CUT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raver, Anne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forrest, Todd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3D91038F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1160" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making the Best Choice For Beloved Old Trees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raver, Anne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Botanical Garden curator of trees and shrubs Todd Forrest offers advice on caring for old trees; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THESE great old trees really define the character of the landscape, so we do everything we can to preserve them,'' Todd Forrest, the curator of trees and shrubs at the New York Botanical Garden in the Bronx, said the other day.</p>
        <p>I had gone up to the garden to get some advice on nursing along the century-old maples that shade our farmhouse in Maryland -- and on deciding whether it was time to take them down. Mr. Forrest stands staunchly on the side of keeping them, whenever possible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THESE great old trees really define the character of the landscape, so we do everything we can to preserve them,'' Todd Forrest, the curator of trees and shrubs at the New York Botanical Garden in the Bronx, said the other day.</p>
        <p>I had gone up to the garden to get some advice on nursing along the century-old maples that shade our farmhouse in Maryland -- and on deciding whether it was time to take them down. Mr. Forrest stands staunchly on the side of keeping them, whenever possible.</p>
        <p>We stood in front of the two Sargent weeping hemlocks that frame the fountain in front of the garden's century-old museum building.</p>
        <p>''These are close to 100 years old,'' Mr. Forrest said. ''Hemlocks can live for 300 years, but the urban landscape is not as conducive to health as the wild, so we try to improve the growing conditions.''</p>
        <p>The trees had a thick layer of composted leaf mold beneath their branches, from trunk to drip line (where rain drips off the edge of the canopy, just as it does from an umbrella). The mulch, which can be spread as thickly as two to four inches, helps prevent soil compaction, and reduces the competition from grass, which sucks water and nutrients away from the trees' roots.</p>
        <p>''If a tree is starting to decline, the first thing to do is make sure you're protecting the root system,'' Mr. Forrest said. (How many of you out there grow grass right up to the trunk of the tree, and then run that mower under the canopy, walking on the roots as you go?)</p>
        <p>And if you are having construction done, like putting in a driveway near the tree, keep trucks and bags of gravel and such away from the root zone, which can extend as far as twice the height of the tree. ''The feeder roots are only six inches beneath the soil,'' Mr. Forrest said.</p>
        <p>In times of drought, put a sprinkler under the drip line, and let it water the tree until the ground is moist.  ''You might look silly out there beneath your huge oak, but think of all those leaves evapo-transpiring all day long,'' Mr. Forrest said. ''A big tree can use hundreds of gallons of water on a hot, sunny day.''</p>
        <p>Proper pruning -- removing any dead wood or crossed branches -- can also extend the life of an old tree, and maintain vigor in a young one.</p>
        <p>If pruning, mulching and judicious watering don't do the trick, the tree might improve with a slow-release fertilizer. About two pounds of nitrogen per 1,000 square feet is the rule of thumb, and it should be applied starting three feet out from the trunk, working out to the drip line.</p>
        <p>We stared up into the branches of a tulip poplar, 60 feet high, with a canopy just as wide. To calculate the proper amount of fertilizer, we multiplied height by canopy width to get the area of ground to be covered, 3,600 square feet, and figured on using about seven pounds of fertilizer.</p>
        <p>''Apply a slow-release form in the fall, after leaf drop, which means growth has stopped, or in the early spring,'' Mr. Forrest said.</p>
        <p>But what if you've taken all these measures, and the tree is still looking sickly? Maybe its leaves are drooping, or you see evidence of insects. Don't run for the insecticide. A vigorous tree can often throw off a fungus or insects, so sometimes it's best just to wait. But it's wise to call in a professional tree care service, to help you diagnose the problem.</p>
        <p>''A declining tree is going to be a flag to all the pests in the neighborhood, and it may create more problems for your healthy trees,'' Mr. Forrest said. For instance, both the pine engraver beetle and the elm bark borer give off pheromones to fellow insects when they find a tree to their liking. ''It's just like a condo in Florida,'' Mr. Forrest said. ''Come on down for the cheap food and fun.''</p>
        <p>On the other hand, don't get hysterical if your London plane tree loses its first flush of leaves in the spring, because of a fungal disease called anthracnose. The leaves will grow back, and the tree will carry on, a bit tattered, but not too much the worse for wear. We gazed at just such a tree on the edge of the garden.</p>
        <p>''In May, it looks horribly unhealthy,'' Mr. Forrest said. ''And if we used that as the sole judge of health, we'd make the wrong decision. But this fungus only attacks in spring. After the second flush of leaves, the tree does O.K.''</p>
        <p>A more serious problem is when aging trees begin to split, or lose such heavy limbs that their trunks can be damaged. Cabling them -- stretching tension wires between the opposing limbs -- can prevent that type of injury. But let a professional do the job. Eye bolts have to be inserted into the cambium, or living tissue, and the cables adjusted properly (not too loose or too tight).</p>
        <p>''We have some 150-year-old sugar maples at our family farm in Connecticut,'' Mr. Forrest said. ''They're right along the road, so they get a lot of salt. And they've lost a lot of large limbs, so they have large cavities. But they still provide glorious shade, and that electric color in the fall.'' So they cable them, and fertilize and water and mulch. ''Ultimately, we hope they live another 100 years,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Deciding on doomsday is as subjective a decision as the one to end a beloved old pet's life. Maybe 70 percent of the canopy is gone. Maybe the tree is in danger of falling on the roof.</p>
        <p>''But if it's not going to fall on your house or attract insects to other trees, it depends upon your tolerance for looking at an ugly tree,'' Mr. Forrest said.</p>
        <p>But what's ugly? Some people think of a dead tree as the grand last scene of the cycle of life. They think of the birds that will nest there, feasting on its insects.</p>
        <p>That's a bit dreary, though, for the front yard. We'll probably plant some younger trees a good distance from the aging ones, so that when the inevitable day arrives, and the trees are removed, the replacements will be more than sticks. If I win the lottery, I'll simply buy the biggest specimens I can find -- and care for them for the future generations.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
