<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Please the Mind, Please the Eye</title>
    <meta content="17OPOP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Jonge, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Liebenson, Bess</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDD1738F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Please the Mind, Please the Eye</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BESS LIEBENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Liebenson, Bess</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bess Liebenson reviews one-woman show by artist Jane de Jonge at Art/Place, Southport, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE artist Jane de Jonge does more than tease the eye. She creates witty, thought-provoking assemblages that focus on the fleeting pleasures of life and taking a chance as well as expressing the hopes and terrors of the computer age. In ''Impossible Dreams,'' a one-woman show at Art/ Place in the Southport train station, her works will engage the mind and beg the dream.</p>
        <p>Her Stamford studio, a 40-foot-long gallery-like contemporary space with windows on two sides, is on the second floor of a traditional Colonial home. Ms. de Jonge, who is a Mount Holyoke College graduate, said she is dyslexic, but won the coveted philosophy prize and later earned a Master of Arts degree at Columbia. She spoke of moving from painting to collage to free-standing soft sculpture.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE artist Jane de Jonge does more than tease the eye. She creates witty, thought-provoking assemblages that focus on the fleeting pleasures of life and taking a chance as well as expressing the hopes and terrors of the computer age. In ''Impossible Dreams,'' a one-woman show at Art/ Place in the Southport train station, her works will engage the mind and beg the dream.</p>
        <p>Her Stamford studio, a 40-foot-long gallery-like contemporary space with windows on two sides, is on the second floor of a traditional Colonial home. Ms. de Jonge, who is a Mount Holyoke College graduate, said she is dyslexic, but won the coveted philosophy prize and later earned a Master of Arts degree at Columbia. She spoke of moving from painting to collage to free-standing soft sculpture.</p>
        <p>''I started doing full-length figures like a Matisse odalisque,'' Ms. de Jonge said. ''Instead of wedges for couches, I thought it would be more fun to contour them as a woman. Bloomingdale's buyer Robin Burns, who was on a fast track and became president of Estee Lauder, bought it and put it in the window, then followed this with a request for imaginative pillows.''</p>
        <p>In response, Ms. de Jonge provided kissing heads with magnetic attraction and cowboy boots. Bloomingdale's found the manufacturer who in turn hired Ms. de Jonge as a product designer and sent her to India to set up a factory -- it became a 10-year sojourn.</p>
        <p>''But I wanted to do something in art that was different from what I was doing commercially,'' Ms. de Jonge said, adding thoughtfully, ''The best things in my life and in art have happened on the way to something else, like this manufacturing job that took me all over the world, including into factories in the South. I was a philosophy major and this was a major adventure.''</p>
        <p>Bearing in mind, she said, that her art is tuned into the problems and feelings of ordinary people, she said she stretched the three-dimensionality of soft sculptures into assemblages using found objects to make a statement.</p>
        <p>''When I worked in the factory there was a lot of dead time waiting for things to happen,'' she recalled. ''I visited hardware stores and flea markets and found things that reflected the life of that particular town, then took them home and made worlds for them.''</p>
        <p>For one recent exhibition Ms. de Jonge went to Vulcan, an industrial dump in Stamford that has all kinds of industrial discards. Assemblages were created from these bits and pieces of abandoned technology to which she added mirrors, marbles and three-dimensional figures found in cake stores, toy stores and flea markets.</p>
        <p>''They address the connection between technology and the people impacted by it,'' Ms. de Jonge said. ''Each dream features a human response to the advancing and declining machine.''</p>
        <p>She created wonder women and super men as metaphors for the men and women of today -- expressing new ways of relating both to themselves and each other.</p>
        <p>One was called ''Yeah, Yeah but What's for Dinner,'' another ''Job Description'' and a third ''Not Now, Can't You See I'm Busy.'' The Zimmerli Art Museum at Rutgers University in New Jersey acquired all three in 1997 for their National Association of Women Artists permanent collection. It includes works by Mary Cassatt, Louise Nevelson and Judy Chicago.</p>
        <p>For Ms. de Jonge's current exhibition in Southport, playful assemblages, some clever calendars as well, are conceived with paint, toys, computer parts, action figures, magnets and mirrors.</p>
        <p>Press a button in ''Once Upon a Time,'' a three-tiered affair topped with a music box, and doors open as girls with wands spin out and fairy godmothers peer into mirrors wishing for an easier life and someone to grant their wishes. ''The Fountain,'' topped with a Taco Bell dog representing a guru, spins and lights up as a specimen male looks up dreaming of an idealized Barbie-style woman.</p>
        <p>And there are mixed-media constructions fashioned as mouth-watering layer cakes embellished with strawberries, cherries, truffles, cookies and cupcakes (all perpetual calendars as well). A magnetic bundle of Tootsie Rolls or an ice cream soda, for example, gets moved in front of the days and the months.</p>
        <p>''Assemblages are not a new form,'' she said. ''Picasso put found objects together but not in this particular way -- opining about the world, addressing problems or issues. They're unusual and, hopefully, not pedantic.''</p>
        <p>Art/Place (in the westbound side of the Southport train station) is open Wednesday through Sunday, noon to 4:30 p.m. and by appointment. The public is invited to a reception today from 2 to 4:30 p.m. The number to call for more information is (203) 255-9847.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
