<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tap or Bottle? Old Issue, New Slant; Contamination Cases Alter Debate: What's in the Glass?</title>
    <meta content="17WATE$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/nyregion/17WATE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bottled Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ammonia</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sodium Hydroxide</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Perrier Group of America</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Poland Spring</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aquafina</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Dean E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E2DA1F38F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1375" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tap or Bottle? Old Issue, New Slant; Contamination Cases Alter Debate: What's in the Glass?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEAN E. MURPHY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Murphy, Dean E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nearly two dozen complaints about mouth burns after drinking Perrier, Poland Spring and Aquafina bottled water prompt New York City and federal officials to investigate possibility of tampering; health officials report water in three incidents was contaminated with ammonia, sodium hydroxide (caustic soda) and possibly other substances; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a Manhattan corner delicatessen last week, two sisters were discussing the merits of bottled water. One refused to buy it. The other could not imagine living without it.</p>
        <p>''I work with people who are homeless and mentally ill,'' said Kathleen Rhoads, director of training at Fountain House, a mental health center on West 47th Street. ''I can't imagine paying all that money for water just so you can walk around with your bottle and look hip.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At a Manhattan corner delicatessen last week, two sisters were discussing the merits of bottled water. One refused to buy it. The other could not imagine living without it.</p>
        <p>''I work with people who are homeless and mentally ill,'' said Kathleen Rhoads, director of training at Fountain House, a mental health center on West 47th Street. ''I can't imagine paying all that money for water just so you can walk around with your bottle and look hip.''</p>
        <p>Colleen Rhoads, a former New Yorker who is a supervisor for Alaska Airlines in Seattle, offered no apologies for her bottle-a-day habit. ''I think the bottled water tastes better,'' she said. ''I've tried filling my bottle from the tap, but it just isn't the same.''</p>
        <p>City and federal authorities are investigating the possibility that someone is fiddling with the bottled water in New York. Nearly two dozen people have complained about getting mouth burns after drinking Perrier, Poland Spring and Aquafina since early August. Health officials have said the water in three incidents was contaminated, with ammonia, sodium hydroxide (or caustic soda) and possibly other substances. They are still trying to figure out whether the contamination was deliberate, and how widespread it might be.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, prominent New Yorkers -- chief among them, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani -- are offering public lessons in how to drink bottled water safely. Twist the cap and listen (an unbroken seal cracks audibly when opened), take a whiff (nasty chemicals usually smell foul) and sip delicately (gulping has always been unseemly, but it is now also potentially dangerous).</p>
        <p>What the Rhoads sisters were debating outside the Smilers deli on Ninth Avenue, however, flows deeper and wider than the current contamination scare: Why drink the bottled stuff at all?</p>
        <p>''Anyone who drinks things like Perrier -- well, they are snobs,'' Kathleen Rhoads said. ''New York City water is some of the best in the world.''</p>
        <p>''The water in the bottle does taste better,'' her younger sister insisted.</p>
        <p>''It is in your head,'' came the stern reply.</p>
        <p>The little sister lost the sidewalk tussle, but if New Yorkers were voting with raised bottles, she would have won by millions. Nationwide, bottled water consumption grew by 11 percent last year, to 17 gallons per capita, making it the fastest growing beverage in the country and more popular than fruit drinks for the first time, according to the Beverage Marketing Corporation, a research and consulting company in Manhattan. New York State ranked fourth in total consumption.</p>
        <p>Taste? Prestige? Convenience? Hype?</p>
        <p>''People are becoming aware of the importance of hydration to their overall health and wellness,'' said Stephen Kay, spokesman for the International Bottled Water Association. ''We offer the consumer a choice in drinking water. It is one choice, one that is obviously appealing to more and more consumers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kay may seem a bit cocky, but then about half of Americans now drink bottled water. His is a $4 billion industry. Still, New York City water officials prefer to see the municipal water glass as half full, and some independent experts seem to share their optimism.</p>
        <p>''Best in the world!'' Geoff Ryan, spokesman for the City Bureau of Water Supply, Quality and Protection, blurted in a nanosecond when asked about New York's tap water in comparison to bottled water.</p>
        <p>An exaggeration, Mr. Ryan just as quickly acknowledged, but his point is not entirely missed. The Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental advocacy group, issued a survey last year that concluded that bottled water was not necessarily any purer or safer than most ordinary tap water, including the New York region's.</p>
        <p>In fact, about one in every four gallons of bottled water sold in the United States is nothing more than plastic-wrapped municipal water, often with no additional treatment, the council said.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people have been misled to believe that bottled water is all from pristine sources and is incredibly pure,'' said Erik Olson, a drinking water specialist at the council's  Washington headquarters. ''That is certainly not always true. Both Coke and Pepsi have their own brands, which are tap water that has been treated.'' (Coke's brand is Dasani, Pepsi's Aquafina.)</p>
        <p>Tap water also receives greater public scrutiny and monitoring than does the bottled variety. Municipal water supplies are regulated by the federal Environmental Protection Agency, bottled water by the federal Food and Drug Administration.</p>
        <p>But the Natural Resources Defense Council survey found that about two-thirds of bottled water sold in the United States is exempt from most federal regulations because it never crosses a state line. State regulations, while plentiful, are mostly unenforced; more than 40 states did not have a full-time employee assigned to enforcing bottled water laws, the survey found.</p>
        <p>Charles G. Sturcken, chief of staff at the city's Department of Environmental Protection, said he had given up trying to understand the public's unquenchable thirst for bottles.</p>
        <p>Not only do some plastic bottles make the water taste funny, independent consumer tests say, but also what goes in them is checked by far fewer people than are inspecting tap water. Mr. Sturcken did not want to offend his friends in the packaged water world, but he confidently predicted that no bottled water could match New York's quality and price drop for drop.</p>
        <p>''The water here definitely has a sweet taste to it,'' he said. ''And we like to say it is a great bargain. We sell it for $1.31 for 100 cubic feet, or 748 gallons. If you're talking 16-ounce bottles, that's 6,000 bottles.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sturcken does not usually talk bottles (he is a tap and pipe man), but it is a subject that he and other water officials have given considerable thought to. In a concession to the designer-water trend, the city now produces plastic bottles -- ''New York City Water: It Hits the Spot'' -- that are distributed to school children and community groups, with instructions to fill with tap water. Mr. Sturcken also occasionally sends the bottles to sports stars and other celebrities who appear on television drinking bottled water, one of his greatest peeves.</p>
        <p>''We tell them, 'We know you like New York, so we would hope that you would try New York City water,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>The response has been less than a trickle. Mr. Sturcken could not come up with a larger-than-life personality who now swears by the New York faucet. But he blames the marketing effort and the uncool slogan, not the water. (The city's strength is not in selling bottles, he repeats.) Next year, the department will try again. It will introduce a collapsible water bottle with a new slogan: ''Forget the rest, drink the best: New York City water.''</p>
        <p>Officials say they are also contemplating entering the retail market. Most of the city's water comes from reservoirs in the Catskills, and despite general complaints that the quality has slipped, it still scores well in independent taste and quality tests. Last month, the city's water finished second in a regional taste testing at the American Museum of Natural History.</p>
        <p>''We haven't come to a conclusion,'' Mr. Sturcken said. ''We get it to nine million people now. We don't know if it would be worth the whole host of regulations from the state and the F.D.A. to ship it out of state.''</p>
        <p>New York City water as a consumer product may sound far-fetched, but marketing experts do not dismiss the idea out of hand. The bottled water craze defies logic. A company in Florida has marketed groundwater in that state as glacier water. Great Bear bottled water, from Breinigsville, Pa., has as its symbol a polar bear on an ice cap. And America's best selling single-serving bottled water is Aquafina. The source? Mostly municipal water supplies across the country.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
