<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>$240,000 for 3 Bedrooms: How 'Affordable' Is That?</title>
    <meta content="17HOUS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231129"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOUSING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rye Brook (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Filipowski, Francis L (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lombardi, Kate Stone</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E3D91538F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>$240,000 for 3 Bedrooms: How 'Affordable' Is That?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE STONE LOMBARDI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lombardi, Kate Stone</byline>
      <dateline>RYE BROOK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Francis L Filipowski of Rye Brook, NY, balks at $240,000 price tag put on 12 moderately priced units in three town houses being built as stipulation connected with construction of BelleFair development, where home prices range from $500,000 to $700,000; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFFORDABLE is a relative concept, especially when it comes to housing in Westchester. Even modest family homes here can carry price tags that would guarantee luxury real estate in other parts of the country.</p>
        <p>Defining a fair price for affordable housing is now at issue in Rye Brook.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFFORDABLE is a relative concept, especially when it comes to housing in Westchester. Even modest family homes here can carry price tags that would guarantee luxury real estate in other parts of the country.</p>
        <p>Defining a fair price for affordable housing is now at issue in Rye Brook.</p>
        <p>In 1998, when the village approved construction of the the BelleFair development, which offers homes at prices ranging from $500,000 to $700,000, it was with the stipulation that it would include 12 moderately priced units in three town houses, with priority given to Rye Brook employees.</p>
        <p>But when the price of those homes was recently revealed -- $240,000 for a three-bedroom unit -- Mayor Francis L. Filipowski balked.</p>
        <p>''I question the calculations that led them to consider that this is a fair number and in keeping with the spirit and intention of affordable units,'' Mayor Filipowski said. ''I believe that the developer has to sharpen his pencil quite a bit more to come up with a figure that would work for municipal employees and teachers to truly afford this housing.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Filipowski has suggested the units should sell for $190,000. But the developers counter that they worked closely with the village planner to come up with a reasonable price.</p>
        <p>Mitchell Hochberg, the president of Spectrum Skanska Construction, a Valhalla-based company that is one of three partners in the joint venture, said that the town house units were being sold at cost and that the only way the price could be lowered would be to reduce their size.</p>
        <p>He said the price was based on a formula that would allow people who are making 125 percent of the median income of Westchester County residents to qualify.</p>
        <p>The median income of Westchester residents is $83,100. But Mr. Hochberg said that with two-income families, the units would be within reach of local employees. He added that it was Rye Brook's village planner who was concerned that a price based on 100 percent of the median income would disqualify some double-wage earners.</p>
        <p>''We have asked the village to work with us to do a survey of village and school employees to determine what their income levels are, taking into consideration base salaries and second incomes in the family,'' Mr. Hochberg said. ''We believe that the data will confirm that between 40 and 50 percent of that group will qualify.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hochberg said that the $240,000 price is half of the average selling price for homes in Rye Brook and 30 percent of the current selling price of homes at BelleFair. Further, he observed that the units were meant to be middle-income, not low-income housing.</p>
        <p>County Executive Andrew J. Spano has called the lack of affordable housing Westchester's No. 1 problem, saying it undermines the stability of communities because young adults cannot afford to stay in the towns where they were raised. Retirees are also forced to move, and police officers, teachers and other municipal workers cannot afford to live in the towns they serve.</p>
        <p>But the county government has no formal power to control land use decisions by its 43 municipalities. Rather, each municipality has the authority to draft its own zoning regulations and approve or reject projects.</p>
        <p>The BelleFair project was designed to re-create some aspects of small town life.</p>
        <p>The development, built on 140 acres, is to include 249 single-family homes, the 12 middle-income town houses and a 165-unit mid-rise building for the elderly. Half of all the housing is to be marketed to elderly empty nesters and the other half to young families.</p>
        <p>The housing looks out on a village green, and the project will include a general store, a community center and a day-care center. Garages are built in back of the homes, and porches in front -- all to encourage interaction among a mix of residents, precisely the kind of community that proponents of affordable housing say is disappearing because of rising real estate costs.</p>
        <p>HOUSING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
