<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rocking Roots, but Don't Call It Retro</title>
    <meta content="17DICK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Deke Dickerson and the Ecco-Fonics (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dickerson, Deke</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woliver, Robbie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDD1338F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="716" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rocking Roots, but Don't Call It Retro</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBBIE WOLIVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Woliver, Robbie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on singer-songwriter Deke Dickerson, whose style incorporates country, alternative country, rockabilly, hillbilly, blues, Western swing and rock 'n' roll and who will perform with Ecco-Fonics at Maxwell's in Hoboken, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE singer-songwriter Deke Dickerson does not like to be categorized, which is too bad, considering that musical labels suit him well. As a roots rocker, he has become used to having his music called country, alternative country, rockabilly, hillbilly, blues, Western swing and rock 'n' roll. The fact is, his style does incorporate all those musical genres, and does so in an entertaining mix that translates very well to live performance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dickerson, 32, grew up in Missouri, where his country and bluegrass roots developed. But, along with his record-collector father, he also listened to blues, rhythm and blues and early rock 'n'roll. He doesn't like the retro tag. Instead, he wants to be regarded more in the vein of Johnny Cash, James Brown and Buddy Holly -- performers known for their individual style, and not by those who have influenced them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE singer-songwriter Deke Dickerson does not like to be categorized, which is too bad, considering that musical labels suit him well. As a roots rocker, he has become used to having his music called country, alternative country, rockabilly, hillbilly, blues, Western swing and rock 'n' roll. The fact is, his style does incorporate all those musical genres, and does so in an entertaining mix that translates very well to live performance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dickerson, 32, grew up in Missouri, where his country and bluegrass roots developed. But, along with his record-collector father, he also listened to blues, rhythm and blues and early rock 'n'roll. He doesn't like the retro tag. Instead, he wants to be regarded more in the vein of Johnny Cash, James Brown and Buddy Holly -- performers known for their individual style, and not by those who have influenced them.</p>
        <p>''I don't approach this from a nostalgic or retro place,'' said Mr. Dickerson, from Fort Collins, Colo., where he was performing. ''It just bums me out that these boneheads who try to market my records have no idea what I'm doing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dickerson has been on the music scene since his early teens, and he made something of a name for himself leading the Untamed Youth, a surf-rock garage band in the late 1980's and early 1990's. He then formed, along with his friend Dave Stuckey, the Dave &amp; Deke Combo, a rockabilly band that released several albums, again gaining the attention of the critics and a small, devoted group of fans who were part of the Americana roots-music movement.</p>
        <p>Since 1998, he has been playing with the Ecco-Fonics, touring the country nonstop. Their HighTone Records debut, ''No. 1 Hit Record,'' displayed Mr. Dickerson's sweet, fluid vocals, dazzling guitar playing and wide-ranging style. If he thought he was going to lose all the genre labels with this recording, he could not have been more mistaken. From the boom-chicka-boom Johnny Cash-beat of ''Feelin' Low'' to the swampy blues of ''Snatch It and Grab It,'' he is all over the musical map. And since he masters all genres, he has become a difficult artist to pigeonhole. Hence, the cult -- from folkies and hillbillies to bikers and punks.</p>
        <p>Thanks to a well thought-out tour in which he opened for Mike Ness, formerly of the rock band Social Distortion, he won over a new group of fans who usually listened to hard-core, alternative and punk rock.</p>
        <p>In 1999, Deke and the Ecco-Fonics recorded ''More Million Sellers,'' which pushed the envelope even further. This time around the irreverent Mr. Dickerson included jump blues (''Mean Son of a Gun''), rap (''My Name is Deke,'' which is more like Jimmy Dean's ''Big Bad John'' than Snoop Doggy Dogg), a gorgeous Roy Orbison-styled pop song (''I Gave My Heart Before'') and a wild guitar instrumental that rips the roof off every concert house they play (''The Rockin' Gypsy'').</p>
        <p>For an even better insight into his offbeat sensibility, the album is introduced by Billy Barty (one of the Munchkins in of ''The Wizard of Oz'') and ends with Jerry Scoggins, the vocalist who sang the theme for ''The Beverly Hillbillies,'' this time singing Mr. Dickerson's praises to that well-known song. But Mr. Dickerson takes his musical history seriously as well, by including Joey D'Ambrosia, the sax player on ''Rock Around the Clock'' and sharing a duet, ''You're My Cadillac,'' with the octogenarian boogie pianist Hadda Brooks.</p>
        <p>On Oct. 10, he will release ''Rhythm, Rhyme and Truth,'' an album, he said, ''that will be more serious and include darker country material.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dickerson, who plays a custom double-neck Mosrite guitar, is a showman extraordinaire. How could he not be, playing such dance-hall-friendly music? There is a reason why 1950's and early-1960's rock 'n' roll is still popular, why rockabilly remains timeless and why swing is still the rage. ''It's timeless and continuously entertaining,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''We've been attracting every conceivable demographic. We're good entertainers, and that's something that's been lost. There are all those singers who stare at their shoes and don't talk between songs. We wear our fingers off trying to put on a good show.''</p>
        <p>DEKE DICKERSON AND THE ECCO-FONICS  Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken.  Next Saturday at 10:30 p.m.  (201) 653-1703.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
