<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Guevara to Reagan, and Beyond</title>
    <meta content="17PROF$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/business/17PROF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRIVATE SECTOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">David A. Stockman</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Heartland Industrial Partners</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stockman, David a</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deutsch, Claudia H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E1DE1138F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Guevara to Reagan, and Beyond</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA H. DEUTSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Deutsch, Claudia H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of David A Stockman, former Reagan administration official who recently founded Heartland Industrial Partners, a buyout firm; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the 1960's, David A. Stockman borrowed a bus from his pastor to drive fellow Michigan State students to an antiwar protest. He got the bus free, but he charged his fellow travelers $18 a head. ''We used the profits for a Che Guevara memorial fund to do good works,'' Mr. Stockman recalled.</p>
        <p>So who was the young Dave Stockman? An anti-establishment protester or a nascent capitalist?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the 1960's, David A. Stockman borrowed a bus from his pastor to drive fellow Michigan State students to an antiwar protest. He got the bus free, but he charged his fellow travelers $18 a head. ''We used the profits for a Che Guevara memorial fund to do good works,'' Mr. Stockman recalled.</p>
        <p>So who was the young Dave Stockman? An anti-establishment protester or a nascent capitalist?</p>
        <p>The answer, of course, was both. But the categorization process has not become any easier.</p>
        <p>At 53, Mr. Stockman has already been a farmer, Congressman, author, investment banker and, most famously, director of the Office of Management and Budget in the Reagan administration.  In May, he added another line to his resume: a founder of Heartland Industrial Partners, a buyout firm with dual headquarters in Greenwich, Conn., and Detroit. Heartland will buy  small old-economy companies, aggregate them into behemoths and take them public again.</p>
        <p>Last month, Heartland, which has raised $1.2 billion in private equity, bought its first company, MascoTech, a small metal forger that  Mr. Stockman thinks  can be the nucleus of a  huge company that makes all the systems that go into a car.</p>
        <p>''Lots of small manufacturers have survived decades of hard times,'' said Mr. Stockman, who spent the last 12 years as a partner at the Blackstone Group, another buyout firm. ''Heartland will buy and combine those winners.''</p>
        <p>Wait a minute. David Stockman as old-economy champion? The same man who as a Congressman -- from Michigan, no less -- argued against the government's bailout of Chrysler in 1979? (''Lee Iacocca still hasn't forgiven me for that!'' he said with a laugh.) Again, will the real David Stockman please stand up?</p>
        <p>It is tempting to accuse Mr. Stockman of intellectual Zeligism. But those who know him say it would also be dead wrong. They describe him as an unusual combination of number cruncher and strategist whose opinion can always be swayed by facts. They say he can analyze reams of data and come up with an accurate view, not only of what a company is, but also of what it can become.</p>
        <p>''David was wrong about Chrysler then, but that won't stop him from embracing the reindustrialization of America now,'' said Richard E. Dauch, chairman of American Axle and Manufacturing, an automotive parts company on whose board Mr. Stockman served until last month.</p>
        <p>Clearly not. ''I'm still against government bailing out businesses,'' Mr. Stockman said, ''but the public markets aren't providing the capital that small businesses need. It's ironic, maybe, but that's why Heartland will succeed.''</p>
        <p>The oldest of five children, David Stockman grew up milking cows and picking fruit on the family farm in St. Joseph, Mich. He majored in horticulture at Michigan State, with an eye toward running the farm for life.</p>
        <p>But Michigan State was a hotbed of 60's radicalism, ''and I picked up the disease,'' he recalled. ''I wore long hair, read long books, thought deep thoughts,'' he added. Soon, it was goodbye to farming, hello to Harvard Divinity School.</p>
        <p>He quickly abandoned his radicalism. ''It was hard to stay zealous when I saw allegedly peace-loving activists toting guns and burning buildings,'' Mr. Stockman said. In Cambridge, he bunked in Daniel Patrick Moynihan's attic, trading baby-sitting and chores for rent. Late-night debates came with the territory. ''That house was a re-education camp for me,'' Mr. Stockman said.</p>
        <p>He soon left Harvard and went to Washington, as an aide to Representative John Anderson. Though remaining a social liberal, he became a fiscal conservative and free-market economist.</p>
        <p>He often demonstrated his penchant for data. When he ran for Congress himself in the mid-1970's, he used computers to catalog primary voters and their interests, and to focus his message accordingly. He won by a landslide.</p>
        <p>(His computer skill has served him well personally, too: he married Jennifer Blei, the I.B.M. sales representative on  his account. They have two teenage daughters and live in Greenwich.)</p>
        <p>In his early days in Congress, Mr. Stockman recalled fondly, he hotly debated energy and environmental policy with another brash young freshman named Al Gore. ''We argued incessantly, to the chagrin of the senior members, who felt the kids shouldn't talk at all,'' Mr. Stockman said.</p>
        <p>His friends from those days said Mr. Stockman was a persuasive arguer. ''Dave is shy, but he really knew how to use numbers to support his policies,'' said David Gerson, one of Mr. Stockman's Washington roommates and now executive vice president of the American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research.</p>
        <p>LATER, as the O.M.B. director, Mr. Stockman used the same techniques. Daniel P. Tredwell, a Washington aide in the 1970's and now a Heartland partner, recalled that Mr. Stockman came to Appropriations Committee meetings with black binders full of facts and figures.</p>
        <p>''We staffers made a sport of trying to stump him, but he could answer any question within minutes,'' Mr. Tredwell said.</p>
        <p>But while others saw Mr. Stockman as a just-the-facts guy, ''I still saw myself as an intellectual and philosopher,'' Mr. Stockman said with genial self-mockery. So, perhaps inevitably after he left government, he wrote a book.</p>
        <p>He said that book, ''The Triumph of Politics: Why the Reagan Revolution Failed,'' was a treatise on Reaganomics. But he acknowledged that much of Washington saw it as a tell-all betrayal. ''The press kept quoting the sound bites instead of the policy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Actually, although Mr. Stockman may never ''eat lunch in that town again,'' it doesn't much matter. There are enough numbers to crunch in Rust Belt America to keep him occupied.</p>
        <p>PRIVATE SECTOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
