<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Untangling The Wireless Web; 'Next Big Thing' Has Big Promise But a Few Kinks</title>
    <meta content="10APPS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000711T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213855"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pagers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Voice Recognition Systems</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hansell, Saul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sound</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E2D91538F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Untangling The Wireless Web; 'Next Big Thing' Has Big Promise But a Few Kinks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAUL HANSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hansell, Saul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Creating services for wireless Internet devices that are as easy, useful and profitable as those offered by wired machines presents a challenge that is in danger of being overlooked; proponents are confident that Americans will put up with expensive, hard-to-use data services for the sake of mobility and that future technology will allow bigger screens, faster data and some sort of easy way to enter text, possibly voice recognition; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is going to change everything, they say. A new wave of technology will put the world at people's fingertips. Pundits speak breathlessly of checking stock quotes, sending e-mail, even buying books at the touch of the button. And investors are racing to buy into the companies making it happen.</p>
        <p>Sound like the Internet in 1995? Indeed it does. But today all the same hope and promotion are directed at a new generation of services offered through cellular telephones, pagers and myriad other radio-wave gizmos. All that is missing is a glossy magazine to chronicle it all, called, say, Unwired.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is going to change everything, they say. A new wave of technology will put the world at people's fingertips. Pundits speak breathlessly of checking stock quotes, sending e-mail, even buying books at the touch of the button. And investors are racing to buy into the companies making it happen.</p>
        <p>Sound like the Internet in 1995? Indeed it does. But today all the same hope and promotion are directed at a new generation of services offered through cellular telephones, pagers and myriad other radio-wave gizmos. All that is missing is a glossy magazine to chronicle it all, called, say, Unwired.</p>
        <p>In some ways, the wireless Internet will spread even more quickly than the wired one. That is because, from now on,  nearly every cell phone sold will have standard Web-browser software built in. Adapting existing Web sites for use by these wireless browsers is a relatively small additional expense. And thanks to the wired Internet, tens of millions of people are already in the habit of communicating electronically; the transition to wireless access should seem but a natural next step to them.</p>
        <p>But despite the analogies to the wired Internet, it is likely to be much harder to create services for wireless devices that are easy, useful and profitable than it has been for the wired world.</p>
        <p>To start with, slow speeds, tiny screens and tortured methods of entering text can make surfing the Net on a cell phone about as satisfying an experience as reading a newspaper on a ticker tape would be. And while the browser software does not add to the price of a phone, most carriers charge users extra fees and per-minute rates to send or receive data.</p>
        <p>As for devices like two-way pagers and Palm hand-held computers, which  have bigger screens and easier ways to enter text, the hardware and monthly service fees are even more costly than the cell phone services.</p>
        <p>For that matter, it is not clear how much business can be done when it takes five minutes and 100 clicks to make an airplane reservation wirelessly. And whatever limitations banner advertisements may have on the Internet, they are Hollywood productions compared with the possibilities on a cell phone screen that shows four lines with a maximum of 22 text characters a line.</p>
        <p>''The companies who are marketing this as the Web in your pocket are over-promising by a long shot and well could sour the market,'' said Seamus McAteer, an analyst for Jupiter Communications. ''A lot of the stuff on the Web just doesn't translate to a wireless device today. A kid just isn't going to do research for his homework on a cell phone.''</p>
        <p>Wireless proponents argue that people love their mobility so much that they will put up with expensive, hard-to-use data services, just as they tolerate the static and cost of cell phones themselves. They point to the mobs of teenagers in Japan and Finland using cell phones to send wireless love notes with their thumbs.</p>
        <p>America Online, for one, is making a big bet that the most popular application on wireless phones, as on its computer service, will be buddy lists and instant messages.</p>
        <p>Moreover, proponents argue that in the future technology will allow bigger screens, faster data and some sort of easy way to enter text -- possibly voice recognition. And they envision complementary uses, PC's at home for detailed information searches and exchanges and small wireless devices for terse updates.</p>
        <p>''The things that people will do on mobile devices will be completely different than on the Web,'' said Naveen Jain, chairman of Infospace, a company that operates parts of the mobile data service offered by carriers like AT&amp;T and Verizon Wireless. ''You want utilitarian, personalized and actionable information.''</p>
        <p>Wireless Internet services have been available for several years, first in the form of radio modems for laptops that were mainly used by corporations that wanted to stay in touch with their traveling sales force. More recently, two-way pagers, like the Blackberry, made by Research in Motion, have become a status item for executives who want to send e-mail on the run.</p>
        <p>The first mass-market wireless data service was over the Palm VII, a version of 3Com's popular organizer introduced a year ago with a wireless modem built in. So far, the Palm has attracted somewhat more than 100,000 wireless customers. More important, it has attracted a host of developers creating wireless services.</p>
        <p>Amazon.com, for example, lets wireless Palm VII users search its huge selection of books and other products, read user comments and order with their one-click accounts. Web portals, including Yahoo and Excite at Home's Excite, enable wireless users to tap into services like e-mail and stock quotes. Other companies, like Omnisky and Go America, have introduced online services and clip-on modems that can provide wireless connections for existing hand-held devices.</p>
        <p>But experts predict that wireless access on hand-held computers will be overshadowed by the use of cell phones. Sprint PCS introduced its Wireless Web service last November. It says a third of its seven million phones are now capable of browsing wireless Web sites and more than a million have. Last month, AT&amp;T introduced a similar service and today Verizon, which was formed by the combination of Bell Atlantic AirTouch and GTE and is the nation's largest wireless carrier, plans to do the same.</p>
        <p>Faced with customer turnover and price wars, the carriers hope data services can  help restore their profit margins. But they are taking sharply divergent approaches to designing and pricing their data services.</p>
        <p>Some, like Sprint and Verizon, see wireless data as a major source of new revenue. They charge customers a monthly fee of $7 to $10 to gain access to data services and then a per-minute fee for each minute spent surfing or talking, with a set number included with the monthly service plan.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T has a very different model. For customers who buy a new Web-enabled phone, the company will give unlimited free access to some 40 information and commerce sites. AT&amp;T customers who want to use e-mail must pay $7 a month, and customers who want both e-mail and the freedom to go to other wireless sites of their own choosing must pay $15 a month. But there is no per-minute charge on either plan.</p>
        <p>Much like an advertising-supported Web site, AT&amp;T intends to earn money from its free service through commissions from the sales Web sites make to AT&amp;T's Web-phone users. It also hopes that users whose appetites are whetted by the free service can be persuaded to upgrade to the pay services.</p>
        <p>It is unclear, though, how customers will react to AT&amp;T's free offer as they discover that the wireless Internet the company promises does not include leading services like AOL and Amazon.com.</p>
        <p>''Some of the carriers want to be the control points,'' said Mohan Vishwanath, vice president of Yahoo's mobile unit. ''But we all know that if anything is going to grow at the rate of the Internet, it has to be open.''</p>
        <p>The other carriers are not limiting access, but they are nonetheless charging Web sites fees to be listed in prominent positions in their cramped on-screen menus. Recently, America Online supplanted Yahoo as the top item on Sprint's menu after reportedly agreeing to a sizable payment.</p>
        <p>''We believe the first several positions are of great value, and we have charged for it,'' said John Garcia, Sprint marketing director. He declined to discuss details of the payments.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia did say, though, that Sprint is not yet sure how crucial such payments will be to its business over all. ''The most important thing now is how many minutes we rack up,'' he said. But over time, the company may experiment with services in which advertisements and commissions subsidize some or all of the air time, as AT&amp;T is doing.</p>
        <p>Some Web site operators are bristling at the demands for payment.</p>
        <p>''We don't believe in paying tremendous amounts to get listed,'' said Ali Hussein, the marketing director for Amazon.com's wireless service. ''There is a definite benefit to the carriers to have Amazon's brand and features on their service.''</p>
        <p>That said, nearly every major Web site is developing a wireless version of its service and is paying whatever it takes to be on as many menus as possible. Amazon, for example, has reached deals for prominent display on Sprint and Verizon's service, but not on AT&amp;T's.</p>
        <p>But it is not clear just how most Internet sites might benefit from these wireless deals. For now, the sites primarily want to retain their customers who happen to use wireless services, even if there is no immediate revenue to be gained.</p>
        <p>Travelocity.com, the online travel service, will soon allow people to make reservations from a cell phone, though it expects people will not want to do that very often.  More valuable, perhaps, as a convenience to its most profitable business travelers, is the new system Travelocity has developed that will let travelers change their return flights with just a few clicks.</p>
        <p>''You're not going to use a phone to say 'Where should I go for a cruise?' '' said Terrell B. Jones, chief executive of Travelocity. ''But if you are in a meeting that is running long, wouldn't you like to use your phone to pull up your reservation and click a button marked 'Later?' ''</p>
        <p>So far there are no banner ads on wireless services, but the Web sites are looking for ways to weave advertising in somewhere. Yahoo, for example, offers a service that will send brief news, weather or sports reports to users' phones, and those messages are sponsored by advertisers.</p>
        <p>ZDnet, the technology information site, will also soon weave some advertising into the text of its articles about computers and technology that users read wirelessly. Later, ZDnet hopes to earn fees from referring customers to computer stores.</p>
        <p>In short, the wireless strategy for most Web sites is to become big fast and figure out how to make money later.</p>
        <p>See? It does sound like the Internet all over again, doesn't it?</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 11, 2000, Tuesday  A chart in Business Day yesterday with an article about hand-held devices used for wireless data communications misstated the range of the monthly prices for two-way paging services offered by three companies. BellSouth Wireless Data's service, with unlimited use, costs $69.95 a month. GoAmerica Communications' unlimited service costs $59.95, and Research in Motion's unlimited service costs $39.95. The price is not $200 to $500 a month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 11, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A chart in Business Day yesterday with an article about hand-held devices used for wireless data communications misstated the range of the monthly prices for two-way paging services offered by three companies. BellSouth Wireless Data's service, with unlimited use, costs $69.95 a month. GoAmerica Communications' unlimited service costs $59.95, and Research in Motion's unlimited service costs $39.95. The price is not $200 to $500 a month.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
