<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Advertising; A campaign stresses customized beauty products sold online.</title>
    <meta content="10ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213859"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Deutsch Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Reflect.com</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Procter &amp; Gamble Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE0D91538F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Advertising; A campaign stresses customized beauty products sold online.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Print ad campaign for Reflect.com, an online retailer started by Procter &amp; Gamble and two venture capital funds, emphasizes that beauty products sold at its site are blended to order based on answers to questions asked of women who visit site and are shipped to them in packages labeled with their name; Deutsch Inc is agency; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A HIGH-PROFILE entrant in one of the most crowded categories of e-commerce is hoping to gain a competitive edge with a campaign that plays up what are deemed to be its beautiful points of differentiation.</p>
        <p>Reflect.com L.L.C., formed by the household products giant Procter &amp; Gamble and two venture capital funds, is introducing quirky-looking print advertisements that seek to gain attention for -- and drive traffic to -- its Web site (www.reflect.com). The site sells the lotions and potions that have long been emblematic of the beauty products business, from makeup and fragrances to skin creams and shampoos.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A HIGH-PROFILE entrant in one of the most crowded categories of e-commerce is hoping to gain a competitive edge with a campaign that plays up what are deemed to be its beautiful points of differentiation.</p>
        <p>Reflect.com L.L.C., formed by the household products giant Procter &amp; Gamble and two venture capital funds, is introducing quirky-looking print advertisements that seek to gain attention for -- and drive traffic to -- its Web site (www.reflect.com). The site sells the lotions and potions that have long been emblematic of the beauty products business, from makeup and fragrances to skin creams and shampoos.</p>
        <p>Of course, that merchandise is also being sold online by companies like Eve.com, Gloss.com, Ibeauty.com and Sephora.com. And those goods were being sold by online retailers that have already become casualties of the dot-com downturn; among them are Beauty.com, Beautyscene.com and Jasmin.com.</p>
        <p>Executives at Reflect.com and its agency of record, Deutsch Inc. in New York, hope to distinguish the newcomer from its rivals by stressing the customized products sold at the site, which are, as the saying goes, not available in stores. The merchandise is blended to order based on answers to questions asked of women who visit the site and is even shipped to them in packages labeled with their names.</p>
        <p>That customization -- underlined by the theme of the campaign, ''Active ingredient: You'' -- is indicative of the increasing emphasis on relationship marketing by Internet advertisers. They are placing more importance on turning consumers into customers, particularly as it becomes more difficult and expensive to prospect for computer users who have still not visited their sites.</p>
        <p>''We view ourselves as a beauty brand that is Internet-enabled instead of an Internet brand of beauty care products,'' said Richard Gerstein, vice president for marketing and design at Reflect.com in San Francisco, which was started by P.&amp; G. in September along with Institutional Venture Partners and Redpoint Ventures.</p>
        <p>''We're really happy to see the dot-com shakeout,'' Mr. Gerstein said. ''It allows our business model to rise to the top. Owning your own brand allows you to be funded and make money.</p>
        <p>''There were a lot of inexperienced people with too much money getting bad advice,'' he added, referring to the general e-commerce field. ''They focused on building awareness, not long-term brand equity, and didn't give consumers a reason to stick with them.''</p>
        <p>The reason for women to glue themselves to Reflect.com, according to the campaign, is its ability to provide what are described as ''one-of-a-kind'' products ''that don't exist until you help create them.'' The print ads use low-key humor, underscored with whimsical drawings by an illustrator, Trisha Krauss, to express that thought.</p>
        <p>For instance, one ad asserts, ''It's not magic, it's interactive.'' Another ad declares: ''Supermodels are under contract. They have to wear certain products. You, luckily, are free to create your own.'' An ad under development tentatively carries this headline: ''For years, women have been told what they need. Maybe it's time for you to tell us.''</p>
        <p>Liz Gumbinner, vice president and group creative director at Deutsch, which joined the Procter agency roster in October with the Reflect.com assignment, called the understated approach deliberate.</p>
        <p>''If we said 'It's a revolution in beauty care,' people wouldn't believe it, because they've been hearing that their whole lives,'' Ms. Gumbinner said. ''It's like airline advertising; you're stuck on a runway for six hours with nothing but peanuts and that's what people remember, not the beautiful skies.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most visible aspect of the unconventional approach the campaign takes is how the drawings depict the Reflect.com customers. They are far more ''real-looking'' than women typically are in pitches for beauty products.</p>
        <p>''It's a challenge to the way the beauty industry portrays women, on a pedestal,'' Mr. Gerstein said. ''We're not suggesting you have to be a perfect, touched-up person, which is where we think the future is, allowing women to focus on what's right for them.''</p>
        <p>Adam M. Levine, executive vice president and brand director at Deutsch, noted that there was a deliberately ''unfinished quality to all the illustrations,'' which were painted by Ms. Krauss on plywood.</p>
        <p>''That way, it's easier for women to project themselves into the ads,'' Mr. Levine said, ''which is also a way to get at the interactivity.</p>
        <p>''Women still have that hope there can be, will be, something better out there,'' he added, ''and they will try things.''</p>
        <p>To capitalize on that quality among consumers whom Mr. Levine labeled as ''beauty-involved,'' the ads will appear in magazines with a beauty and fashion editorial focus like Allure, Cosmopolitan, Elle, Essence, Glamour, In Style, Mademoiselle, Marie Claire, Self, Shape and Vogue. The ads will also run in publications like Entertainment Weekly and People.</p>
        <p>The budget for the campaign is $3 million to $5 million for the third quarter. The work by Deutsch is in addition to a campaign created by the interactive agency of record for Reflect.com, Critical Mass in Calgary, Alberta, half owned by Rapp Collins Worldwide in New York, part of the Omnicom Group.</p>
        <p>Rapp Collins had been handling direct marketing duties for the site, but Mr. Gerstein said that he was ''no longer working with'' that agency and was instead producing direct mail ''using the Deutsch creative.''</p>
        <p>''Now that we have a campaign women have told us they love,'' he added, ''we are starting to integrate it into other elements of our program.''</p>
        <p>Or as that great philosopher, Madonna, once said, ''Beauty's where you find it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
