<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Envoy Tries to Aid Peace Effort in 'Unique' Colombia War</title>
    <meta content="Y10COL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Colombia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egeland, Jan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE3DE1238F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1207" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Envoy Tries to Aid Peace Effort in 'Unique' Colombia War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>BOGOTA, Colombia, July 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Jan Egeland, UN emissary in Colombia who is leading efforts to settle 35-year-old civil conflict; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He organized the ''Norwegian channel'' that led to a peace plan between Israelis and Palestinians, and has had a hand in peace talks from Central America to Central Africa. Now, as a United Nations emissary in Colombia, Jan Egeland is leading efforts here to solve a a 35-year conflict unlike any he had ever seen.</p>
        <p>''What is unique in Colombia compared with most other processes is the size and scale of the armed actors and armed conflict, and the size of the black money associated with drugs and other criminal activities,'' Mr. Egeland said in an interview here. ''So the sources fueling the conflict are bigger than they have been in many other places, and that makes it more challenging.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He organized the ''Norwegian channel'' that led to a peace plan between Israelis and Palestinians, and has had a hand in peace talks from Central America to Central Africa. Now, as a United Nations emissary in Colombia, Jan Egeland is leading efforts here to solve a a 35-year conflict unlike any he had ever seen.</p>
        <p>''What is unique in Colombia compared with most other processes is the size and scale of the armed actors and armed conflict, and the size of the black money associated with drugs and other criminal activities,'' Mr. Egeland said in an interview here. ''So the sources fueling the conflict are bigger than they have been in many other places, and that makes it more challenging.''</p>
        <p>Officially, Mr. Egeland's title is merely that of special adviser to the secretary general on international assistance to Colombia. But after six months on the job, Mr. Egeland, 42, has emerged as a trusted intermediary between the Colombian government and left-wing guerrilla groups, which until recently agreed on one thing: They did not want any foreigners in the negotiations.</p>
        <p>''In Colombia we have always had the fear that internationalizing the peace process would also mean internationalizing the conflict, so we were suspicious of outsiders wanting to enter,'' said Fernando Cepeda Ulloa, a former interior minister. ''So Egeland's presence here is a good thing because it means a barrier has been breached.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Egeland, who has been a journalist, deputy foreign minister of Norway and a Red Cross official, is careful to play down his own role.</p>
        <p>''We have no formal third party role vis-a-vis the Colombian conflict, nor are we seeking one,'' he said. While acknowledging that he is in constant contact with both sides, he cautioned, ''It may be premature to say that we are facilitating any kind of peace process because none of the parties have asked anyone to really play that kind of an activist role.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Egeland has been instrumental in ''attempting to get the guerrillas out of the jungle and into the modern world,'' said Cynthia Arnson, editor of a new book ''Comparative Peace Processes in Latin America'' (Woodrow Wilson Center Press, 2000). As in Guatemala, she noted, here you had ''a guerrilla movement that was so isolated politically and had operated so long in clandestinity that it had lost touch with politics and public opinion and needed to be reacclimated.''</p>
        <p>While both the Palestine Liberation Organization and the Guatemalan guerrillas were nearly bankrupt when they began peace talks, here the two main insurgent forces are flourishing as a result of their links with drug trafficking, kidnappings and extortion. In addition, the biggest group, the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia, has formally been given control of an area the size of Switzerland, and now seems to want to deal with the government on almost a state-to-state level.</p>
        <p>''Our situation is very odd and ambiguous, in that there is a coexistence between the government and the guerrillas that I don't see elsewhere,'' said Mr. Cepeda Ulloa. ''That makes Egeland's job more difficult, in that the guerrillas think it perfectly natural to ask the state for territory or the international community for financing.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Egeland said that in some other respects, the issues being confronted here are not as intractable as elsewhere. ''It is more difficult to negotiate Jerusalem than agrarian reform in Colombia,'' he said. ''One of the positive aspects of Colombia compared with other places is that the parties are not necessarily so much poles apart on some of the issues as many believe.''</p>
        <p>At the moment, the Revolutionary Armed Forces and the other main left-wing guerrilla group, the Army of National Liberation, are engaged in separate but parallel negotiations with the government. But ''later on,'' Mr. Egeland said, ''there should be a convergence'' of the two sets of talks because ''in the end there is only one country and society to reform.''</p>
        <p>In an essay in ''Herding Cats,'' a new book about peacemaking, (U. S. Institute of Peace Press, Washington, 1999), Mr. Egeland writes that he agrees with the refusal of the government here to negotiate with right-wing paramilitary groups because they are ''criminal terrorist organizations that should only be met with to discuss the laying down of arms.'' His opinion is that ''the random killing of fellow citizens in a society should not lead to negotiations in the presidential palace.''</p>
        <p>But in an interview here, he softened his tone somewhat. The paramilitaries have ''little political content, and a big human rights violation content,'' he said, so ''they should be treated differently from other actors.'' But ''one should not be categorical about leaving anyone in or out'' of the negotiations, he added.</p>
        <p>Such a pragmatic approach would be a concession to the political realities prevailing here. Previous efforts to negotiate an end to the conflict have foundered at least in part because there was nothing to prevent right-wing death squads from killing guerrillas who had agreed to lay down their arms.</p>
        <p>''My sense is that some point down the road the paramilitaries have to be brought into the peace negotiations,'' said Dr. Arnson, who is deputy director of the Latin American program at the Woodrow Wilson Center in Washington.</p>
        <p>''At what time or circumstances is open to question, but you can't convince the guerrilla movements to re-enter the political process so long as their members are subject to elimination,'' he said, alluding to the death squads.</p>
        <p>Thus far, the Clinton administration has kept a distance from the peace negotiations here because of a ban on contacts with the guerrillas and on the theory that, as one official in Washington put it, any formal involvement ''might well be more harmful than helpful.'' But the State Department welcomes Mr. Egeland's presence ''as the injection of another element, curbing rebel misbehavior,'' and said it would not oppose a more prominent role for him.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Egeland is reluctant to discuss assuming a mediator's role or to speculate about a timetable, other than to caution that the situation here could just as easily deteriorate as improve. ''It is terrible here, and it could get much worse,'' he said, before adding that ''part of my job is to be an optimist.''</p>
        <p>In one sign of progress, the government and the Revolutionary Armed Forces group exchanged proposals on July 3 for a cease-fire. Mr. Egeland said that while ''one should not be overly optimistic about them agreeing,'' he did expect the talks to produce some sort of accord that would halt the killing of civilians.</p>
        <p>''This should happen this year,'' he said. ''It would be another great defeat for all of us if it doesn't happen this year.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
