<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brash, Hard-Driving Executive Steers CNBC to Top of Cable News</title>
    <meta content="10CNBC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000718T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213858"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cable News Network</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cnbc (Cable Network)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bolster, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1D91538F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1401" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brash, Hard-Driving Executive Steers CNBC to Top of Cable News</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Bill Bolster, president of CNBC, who has made network the highest-rated news and information network on cable television, surpassing CNN, in just three years; he is widely described as a tyrannical bully who often offends colleagues, but he is admired as a TV genius gifted not only at packaging and promoting programming but also at selling it to advertisers at top dollar; graph; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three years ago, Bill Bolster, still new to the president's job at CNBC, announced an ambitious dream: his financial news network would beat CNN, then the dominant news provider on cable, in the cable TV ratings war.</p>
        <p>Though it seemed at the time a distant, almost improbable goal, two weeks ago Mr. Bolster achieved it. New Nielsen Media Research data showed that for the first time in its 11-year history, CNBC had averaged a higher daily audience than CNN for a three-month period.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three years ago, Bill Bolster, still new to the president's job at CNBC, announced an ambitious dream: his financial news network would beat CNN, then the dominant news provider on cable, in the cable TV ratings war.</p>
        <p>Though it seemed at the time a distant, almost improbable goal, two weeks ago Mr. Bolster achieved it. New Nielsen Media Research data showed that for the first time in its 11-year history, CNBC had averaged a higher daily audience than CNN for a three-month period.</p>
        <p>In short, CNBC had become the highest-rated news and information network on cable television, ending CNN's long reign and cementing its reputation as a leading media organization of the new economy.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Bolster, 56, the ratings represent a crowning victory in a 35-year career in broadcasting. Although he is widely described as a tyrannical bully who often offends colleagues, he is admired as a TV genius gifted not only at packaging and promoting programming but also at selling it to advertisers at top dollar.</p>
        <p>But despite his status as king of TV financial news, Mr. Bolster is more a product of Main Street than of Wall Street -- a media mogul who is far from media-ready.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolster, who is 6-foot 4-inches tall and hulking, has spent most of his career in local markets out of the glare of the national spotlight, making him an unlikely leader for a network noted for having made financial news interesting to everyday people around the country. CNBC is now a regular fixture not only in brokerage houses and newsrooms, but also in gyms and bars.</p>
        <p>''As the market has gone up, and in some ways become, at its worst, the national lottery, CNBC has grown right along with it,'' said Tom Wolzien, a media analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein. ''They're part of the democratization of the stock market.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolster is credited both inside and outside his organization with making CNBC a highly profitable entity with mass appeal by incorporating some of the flashy graphics and hype associated with local television news while applying some of the bare-knuckled sales tactics emblematic of local markets.</p>
        <p>Under his tenure, CNBC's ad rates have risen more than threefold, and profits have more than doubled, executives said. CNBC, which does not break out its financial results separately from its parent, General Electric, estimates that it will end the year with $280 million in profit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolster first learned about sales, he said, from his father William, who owned Sweeney's, a women's ready-to-wear business in Waterloo, Iowa, and who also had an investment in Black Hawk Broadcasting , which started out as a small radio group. As a teenager, he would help his father with the books.</p>
        <p>''That's where I learned the fundamentals of business,'' Mr. Bolster said during an interview at CNBC headquarters in Fort Lee, N.J. But he said he did not become hooked on broadcasting until after college, when he became an announcer and ad salesman at KDTH radio in Dubuque, Iowa. He later moved to Waterloo's KWWL-TV, which was owned by Black Hawk, working up to general manager before moving in 1983 to KSDK-TV, the NBC affiliate in St. Louis, as general manager.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolster produced major victories during his time in local television. KSDK was the No. 3 station in St. Louis when Mr. Bolster arrived. He brought it to first place in two years with heavy promotions; an early-morning local news program, which was the first in St. Louis; and an afternoon talk show, ''The Sally Jesse Raphael Show.''</p>
        <p>As head of the news committee of the NBC network's affiliates board, he helped persuade the network in 1991 to delay the beginning of ''The Tonight Show'' by five minutes, so stations would have more ad time to sell during their late newscasts. Mr. Bolster arrived in New York as a virtual unknown in late 1991, as the general manager of the local NBC station, WNBC-TV, and scored early ratings victories by heavily using promotions, starting the city's first early-morning local news program and introducing flourishes like a news helicopter and high-technology weather radar.</p>
        <p>''All of his competitors were saying, 'Who is this guy from St. Louis?' '' said Tony Guida, now an anchor with CNNfn who was at WNBC when Mr. Bolster arrived. ''He just cleaned their clocks. He knew how to market and sell TV better than anyone I've ever worked with.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Guida added, ''And I say that grudgingly because there is no love lost between us.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Guida is one many on-air people and broadcasting executives who say they have clashed with Mr. Bolster, and who use the phrase ''bull in a china shop'' to describe him.</p>
        <p>He is said to have a propensity for making off-color remarks and riding people extremely hard. ''He is coarse, impolitic, boorish -- a bully,'' said Peter W. Barnes, a former CNBC reporter now working for a new financial news Web site, JAGfn.com. Mr. Barnes said he had clashed with Mr. Bolster when he tried to break his contract a few months early and was refused.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolster describes himself as one to speak his mind but says that he never intends to purposely offend. ''If I've done something, uncharacteristically, that offends on a very personal basis -- not professionally, because professionally, that's my job -- I've got to go back and say I'm sorry, I'm wrong,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Certainly his business manner is full-speed ahead. Upon his arrival at CNBC in 1996 Mr. Bolster quickly began making changes.</p>
        <p>Within two weeks, he had changed the CNBC logo, incorporating the NBC peacock. He introduced new wrinkles like real-time stock quotes and market meters that perpetually run on the screen.</p>
        <p>He raised ad rates by arguing to Madison Avenue that he was delivering a higher-income viewer whom Nielsen could not measure. To prove it, he gave a real estate firm free time slots advertising a $3.5 million house in Fort Lauderdale, Fla. There were 400 respondents.</p>
        <p>On programming, he and his team approached the stock market as a big event, a daily Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>''So you say, geez, let's do a pregame show, and it's going to be 'Squawk Box,' '' Mr. Bolster said, referring to CNBC's opening-bell show. ''Then you've got a game. And then the post-game show.''</p>
        <p>Unfortunately for CNBC, once the game is over -- once the main stock exchanges close for the day -- viewers tend to wander off. Despite CNBC's daytime gains, its prime-time ratings were down by about 24 percent this spring compared with last, pulling significantly smaller audiences than CNN and the Fox News Channel in the time period.</p>
        <p>Today, executives plan to announce that one nonfinancial show, ''Upfront Tonight,'' Geraldo Rivera's half-hour news program weeknights at 7:30, will be replaced by an additional half-hour of ''Business Center.''</p>
        <p>There is some debate over how much of CNBC's success belongs to Mr. Bolster, given the public's ravenous appetite for stock market news. And the network's big name stars like Maria Bartiromo were there when he arrived.</p>
        <p>But media industry executives say that even if Mr. Bolster was dealt a great hand, he has played it masterfully. ''When he first started, I remember he was saying how he was going to take on CNN and win, and I thought he was being overly optimistic,'' said Tim Spengler, senior vice president at Initiative Media, a media buying firm. ''But he was right. He saw what he had.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA  Correction:  July 18, 2000, Tuesday  An article in Business Day on July 10 about Bill Bolster, the president of CNBC, misstated his role in the expansion of local morning news programming in New York City. What he started in 1992 was the first weekend morning program, not the first morning program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 18, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on July 10 about Bill Bolster, the president of CNBC, misstated his role in the expansion of local morning news programming in New York City. What he started in 1992 was the first weekend morning program, not the first morning program.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
