<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At a Crossroad, PeopleSoft Bets on the Future of Internet-based Software</title>
    <meta content="10PEOP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Peoplesoft Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oracle Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sap Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richtel, Matt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D81538F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1246" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At a Crossroad, PeopleSoft Bets on the Future of Internet-based Software</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT RICHTEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richtel, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, July 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>PeopleSoft is set to unveil 'enterprise software' that will allow companies to use a Web browers to automate dozens of tasks instead of tapping into an internal corporate software program; industry analysts say it remains to be seen whether PeopleSoft can revive its fortunes and catch Oracle and SAP, which released their Internet-centric enterprise software products months ago; graph of PeopleSoft's stock price (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Investors, clients and competitors are wondering if PeopleSoft's newest product, a software rooted to the Internet, will lead to the demise or revival of the once highflying company. The answer may become clearer on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>At a news conference in New York, PeopleSoft plans to show the latest version of its ''enterprise software,'' a huge and complex program that companies use to automate dozens of tasks, like managing customer relations and human resources, sales support and marketing efforts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Investors, clients and competitors are wondering if PeopleSoft's newest product, a software rooted to the Internet, will lead to the demise or revival of the once highflying company. The answer may become clearer on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>At a news conference in New York, PeopleSoft plans to show the latest version of its ''enterprise software,'' a huge and complex program that companies use to automate dozens of tasks, like managing customer relations and human resources, sales support and marketing efforts.</p>
        <p>The key to the newest version is that it will be Internet-based, meaning company employees and customers can use the program with an ordinary Web browser, instead of tapping into an internal corporate software program.</p>
        <p>The trouble is, PeopleSoft's release is months behind the Internet-centric releases of its competitors and the industry's market share leaders, Oracle and SAP.</p>
        <p>Plus, PeopleSoft is coming off a disappointing year of flat revenue and a falling stock price -- after years of double-digit growth -- and a management overhaul that moved the company's founder, David A. Duffield, out of the chief executive position, leaving him as chairman.</p>
        <p>PeopleSoft shares closed at $18.375 on Friday, a drop of over 30 percent since January. Adding to the company's challenges, a shareholder lawsuit, filed on June 30 in Alameda County Court in California, accuses company officials of insider trading. The company declined to comment.</p>
        <p>But PeopleSoft said its two-and-a-half-year development of the new version would signal a rebound.</p>
        <p>''This could shift the landscape,'' said Craig A. Conway, who in May 1999 replaced Mr. Duffield as chief executive. He predicted the overhauled software would provide a resurgence for PeopleSoft against Oracle and SAP. ''We've got an ace up our sleeve,'' he added.</p>
        <p>That trump card consists of additional features to the software that the company gambled a significant portion of its budget developing, he said. The features include 50 highly tailored programs like Internet-based support for company technicians and salespeople, and Internet-based customer scorecards for clients.</p>
        <p>Partly in anticipation of the release, Lehman Brothers raised its rating of PeopleSoft to ''outperform,'' up from ''neutral.''</p>
        <p>But more generally, industry analysts say it remains to be seen whether PeopleSoft, based in Pleasanton, Calif., can revive its fortunes and catch Oracle, also based in Northern California, and SAP of Germany.</p>
        <p>Exact market share figures are difficult to come by because each company has different definitions of what constitutes enterprise software. SAP says it has 18,000 enterprise software customers; Oracle claims 8,500; and PeopleSoft, 4,000.</p>
        <p>But Thomas P. Berquist, senior electronic commerce analyst with Goldman, Sachs, said that of the 55 competitors in the field, SAP leads with 10,000, Oracle follows with 6,000, and PeopleSoft has 3,000.</p>
        <p>More generally, analysts say much remains undecided in an industry that has undergone fundamental change in the last three years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berquist said the industry peaked in 1997 with about $35 billion in revenue. Since then, the industry has languished at between $25 billion and $30 billion in revenue, and he and other analysts say that one main reason for the drop was the Year 2000 glitch.</p>
        <p>The theory goes that many companies last year simply stopped buying enterprise software, which can cost hundreds of thousands to hundreds of millions of dollars, when they realized they could not have it in place and tested in time for any possible millennium trouble.</p>
        <p>A second factor was that the makers of this software -- led by Oracle, which pushed the idea early on -- promised a new generation of programs run entirely over the Internet. They said the upgrade would be profound because companies would be able to provide essential software to employees without the company ever having to configure their individual computers.</p>
        <p>Rather, when employees wanted to file an expense form, check product updates, look into their retirement portfolio or contact suppliers, they would do so by logging into an Internet site on which all the information was kept. Oracle said that it saved $1 billion on operating expenses last year by using its own Internet-based software internally.</p>
        <p>This shift to Internet-based software from so-called client-server based software -- in which some parts of the program are kept on a central server and some on individual computers -- signals a radical shift in the industry, Mr. Conway said.</p>
        <p>''When the architecture gets reshuffled, it's the single greatest transition an industry can go through,'' he said. He said the change is analogous to the shift in 1990 to the client-server era from making enterprise software for mainframe computers, a transition he said caused fits for the market leaders of the day, Dun &amp; Bradstreet and MSA.</p>
        <p>Industry analysts say the present-day transformation is causing consolidation among the smaller players in the industry and some business failures. Baan, one of the top five enterprise software competitors the last several years, in May announced that it had sold its operations to Invensys, after seven quarters of losses.</p>
        <p>Oracle, however, announced its Internet-based product, 11i, last year, deployed it piecemeal, but still racked up more than $400 million in sales the company's fiscal fourth quarter 2000. It began shipping the software in complete form in May. Its head start gave it ''a big marketing lead,'' said Nicole S. Gemmer, a research associate with Chase H &amp; Q.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, SAP introduced its product, mySAP.com, in the spring of 1999 and began shipping in November. People familiar with the company say the new product has 300 customers, including a deal announced on June 14 to license mySAP.com to Nestle for use by 230,000 employees, a contract said to be worth $200 million.</p>
        <p>PeopleSoft plans to start shipping its product, PeopleSoft 8, in September. Jenni Lehman, an analyst of human resources software with the Gartner Group, said PeopleSoft's late entrance can cut both ways. ''There's no question they did get there late,'' she said, but she added that they have the advantage of learning from the efforts, and failings, of SAP and Oracle.</p>
        <p>Indeed, PeopleSoft executives say they have one key edge: that their product is the most completely Internet-based. Indeed, Mr. Berquist, from Goldman, Sachs, said that some portions of the SAP and Oracle programs still reside on the desktop computers of employees, meaning PeopleSoft's offering could find a receptive audience among companies looking for a truly Internet-only solution.</p>
        <p>PeopleSoft's gamble was expensive. The company spend 27 percent of its budget last year on research and development, Mr. Conway said.</p>
        <p>But he said he was willing to bet that if PeopleSoft successfully shifted its products to being Internet-based, it could return to its glory days.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berquist said the answer will soon become clear -- perhaps not by Tuesday, but before too long.</p>
        <p>''The street is looking for evidence that with the release of pure Internet applications, growth will be stimulated'' in the enterprise section, he said. ''It may take a quarter or two to know. We'll all be watching closely.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
