<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BASEBALL: Hampton and the Mets Get Tough and Then Get Even; Yanks Are Shut Down While Piazza Sits Out</title>
    <meta content="10METS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4DA1238F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="930" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BASEBALL: Hampton and the Mets Get Tough and Then Get Even; Yanks Are Shut Down While Piazza Sits Out</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat New York Yankees, 2-0; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like the rest of his teammates, Mike Hampton was horrified when he saw Roger Clemens bean Mike Piazza on Saturday night. Hampton was starting the next game, and he promised not to initiate any disturbances. When he left Yankee Stadium and heard fans chanting ''Sweep! Sweep!'' Hampton decided to retaliate another way.</p>
        <p>''Last night on the bus ride home, I thought a lot about how we need to win this game,'' Hampton said. ''We need to prove not only to them but to ourselves that we can compete. We had some close games that could have gone either way, and they got a lot of the breaks in the early games.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like the rest of his teammates, Mike Hampton was horrified when he saw Roger Clemens bean Mike Piazza on Saturday night. Hampton was starting the next game, and he promised not to initiate any disturbances. When he left Yankee Stadium and heard fans chanting ''Sweep! Sweep!'' Hampton decided to retaliate another way.</p>
        <p>''Last night on the bus ride home, I thought a lot about how we need to win this game,'' Hampton said. ''We need to prove not only to them but to ourselves that we can compete. We had some close games that could have gone either way, and they got a lot of the breaks in the early games.</p>
        <p>''I was like, the best thing we can do is go out and win.''</p>
        <p>The Mets knew they had much to lose if Hampton touched something off. They needed to win a baseball game, not a beanball war, and Hampton gave them their best chance. He stayed out of trouble and worked seven shutout innings last night in front of 54,286 at Shea Stadium as the Mets beat the Yankees, 2-0, for their only victory in this four-game series.</p>
        <p>Piazza watched from the bench, recuperating from a concussion that will force him to miss tomorrow's All-Star Game. His replacement, Todd Pratt, threw out two runners trying to steal. Pratt was one of several Mets who spoke passionately Saturday about Clemens's pitch and the respect he had lost for the future Hall of Famer. But like Hampton, Pratt decided winning was the best revenge.</p>
        <p>''With the feelings of anger I had last night and some of the emotions I expressed, I came in today and talked to a few of our pitchers and some of our veteran everyday players and just said the most important thing today is to get a win,'' Pratt said.</p>
        <p>''It's senseless to start something out there today when players on the field yesterday aren't there today. We start something, they're still going to have a free shot at one of our guys. We can't afford that.''</p>
        <p>The Mets survived one injury last night, though it was probably minor. Hampton felt a muscle cramp during warm-ups before the eighth inning, causing his thumb to lock up when he threw his breaking pitches. He told Manager Bobby Valentine he would try to continue, but Valentine called on Armando Benitez.</p>
        <p>Benitez recorded his first two-inning save of the season, his 19th save over all, getting strikeouts for three of his six outs and a game-ending groundout from Felix Jose with two runners on.</p>
        <p>Hampton said he was not concerned about the muscle cramp, and guessed it probably came from giving a ''max-effort'' performance in the final game before the All-Star Game break.</p>
        <p>Hampton was pitching on three days' rest after throwing just 79 pitches in beating Florida last week, and last night's effort capped an impressive stretch of pitching.</p>
        <p>Hampton, who improved to 9-5, was hardly a consideration for the All-Star team; a 2-4 start in which he posted a 6.52 earned run average took care of that.</p>
        <p>But in his last 12 starts, he has been one of the majors' best pitchers, going 7-1 with a 1.87 E.R.A., displaying a command of his sinking fastball that had eluded him early on.</p>
        <p>Hampton gave credit to Pratt last night, but Pratt laughed it off.</p>
        <p>''A rookie could go back there if a guy's throwing strikes and throwing it where he wants it,'' Pratt said.</p>
        <p>The Mets got all the run support Hampton needed with one swing from Todd Zeile, who has been among the most reliable Mets hitters this year.</p>
        <p>In the 10 games preceding last night's, he was batting .353 -- the same average Zeile had in his career off Andy Pettitte before the game.</p>
        <p>Zeile was the first batter in the fourth inning, and he sliced a ball to right field. On Friday night, Paul O'Neill had made a game-saving catch in nearly the same spot when he planted himself under a high fly by Derek Bell, leaped straight up and robbed Bell of a game-tying homer in the Yankees' 2-1 victory.</p>
        <p>Zeile's hit was more of a line drive, and O'Neill first turned to his left in pursuit. He reversed himself at the warning track and jumped to his right, but the ball made it into the bullpen safely for a home run, Zeile's 14th. O'Neill slapped the plexiglass with his glove in frustration.</p>
        <p>The Mets scored their next run in the seventh, without getting a hit. Pratt -- who is 0 for 28 since June 2 -- led off with a walk. Hampton sacrificed him to second, and when Jeff Nelson came in to relieve Pettitte, a wild pitch brought Pratt to third. Melvin Mora scored him with a sacrifice fly.</p>
        <p>Pettitte (9-5) worked six and a third innings, allowing two runs, five hits and four walks. Like Hampton, he played it straight.</p>
        <p>The crowd stirred in the fourth inning, when Pettitte buzzed a pitch near Robin Ventura's knees, but there were no other hints of tension.</p>
        <p>''Unless Roger was back on the mound and held a bat in his hand,'' Zeile said, ''I think that incident was behind us.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
