<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Bar the Yankees From Workout Room</title>
    <meta content="10NOTE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213951"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">All Star Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clemens, Roger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Phillips, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">All Star Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E7DA1238F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="368" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Bar the Yankees From Workout Room</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets general manager Steve Phillips, angered by Roger Clemens pitch that injured Mike Piazza, bars Yankees from Mets workout room; cancels plan for Mets All-Stars to share charter plane to Atlanta with Yankees (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Relievers Jason Grimsley and Mike Stanton and outfielder David Justice were the first Yankees to learn yesterday that the Mets were still very angry about Saturday night's beaning of Mike Piazza. They were ordered to leave the workout room at Shea Stadium by Steve Phillips, the Mets' general manager, about three hours before last night's game.</p>
        <p>And those plans to have All-Stars from both teams share a charter plane to Atlanta? They were called off, Phillips said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Relievers Jason Grimsley and Mike Stanton and outfielder David Justice were the first Yankees to learn yesterday that the Mets were still very angry about Saturday night's beaning of Mike Piazza. They were ordered to leave the workout room at Shea Stadium by Steve Phillips, the Mets' general manager, about three hours before last night's game.</p>
        <p>And those plans to have All-Stars from both teams share a charter plane to Atlanta? They were called off, Phillips said.</p>
        <p>Jeff Mangold, the Yankees' strength and conditioning coach, was in the Mets' workout room with the Yankee players long before game time, a courtesy that is generally extended by teams throughout both leagues. At Shea, visiting players must walk through the Mets' clubhouse to get to the workout room.</p>
        <p>Phillips summoned Mangold from the weight room, and told him directly that in light of what had happened -- Clemens's hitting Piazza with the pitch -- the Yankees were not welcome in the workout room. Brian Cashman, the Yankees' general manager, called Phillips to ask about the decision, and Phillips told him that given the heightened emotions, he did not think it was appropriate for the Yankees to be in the Mets' clubhouse under any circumstance.</p>
        <p>The Yankees were allowed access to the indoor batting cages, which are not adjacent to the Mets' clubhouse. Cashman accepted Phillips's explanation. Joe Torre, the Yankees' manager, called the decision unprofessional, saying the Mets had access to the weight room in Yankee Stadium. ''We like to conduct what we do with class, and that's the way I anticipate other people conducting themselves,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Phillips said: ''I thought it was unprofessional that their pitcher threw at our catcher, so I don't care at all what Joe Torre thinks.''</p>
        <p>Torre and the other Yankee All-Stars -- Derek Jeter, Mariano Rivera, Bernie Williams and Jorge Posada -- were scheduled to fly to Atlanta on a charter after last night's game, for today's workout. Torre mentioned that Piazza and the other Mets' All-Stars, Al Leiter and Edgardo Alfonzo, were supposed to share the flight. But Phillips said the Mets' All-Stars will find other travel arrangements.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
