<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The State Pie And How To Cut It</title>
    <meta content="10MATT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="METRO MATTERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purnick, Joyce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E3DD1238F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The State Pie And How To Cut It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE PURNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purnick, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joyce Purnick column on New York suburbs as battleground in senate and presidential races holds suburban sprawl has expanded NY suburbs to some 11 counties from traditional three or four; notes 11 counties accounted for some 32 percent of statewide vote in recent elections, compared with 29 percent for New York City without suburban Staten Island and 39 percent for 47 upstate counties (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE city, upstate and the suburbs. It's the classic three-way cut, how candidates, political analysts and pollsters always divide up New York State.</p>
        <p>Elections are more than statistics, but numbers are inescapable, and crucial, which raises a provocative question: are we defining each of the three slices of the state pie correctly? That's always easier to answer after the fact, but so far, it looks as if the answer is no. The suggestion here is that candidates, pollsters, strategists and journalists belatedly faced facts and overcame their New York City-centrism, but haven't begun to pay enough attention to the suburbs. That could be a problem, especially this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE city, upstate and the suburbs. It's the classic three-way cut, how candidates, political analysts and pollsters always divide up New York State.</p>
        <p>Elections are more than statistics, but numbers are inescapable, and crucial, which raises a provocative question: are we defining each of the three slices of the state pie correctly? That's always easier to answer after the fact, but so far, it looks as if the answer is no. The suggestion here is that candidates, pollsters, strategists and journalists belatedly faced facts and overcame their New York City-centrism, but haven't begun to pay enough attention to the suburbs. That could be a problem, especially this year.</p>
        <p>The Republican candidate for Senate, Rick A. Lazio, represents Suffolk County, on the state's eastern stretch of suburban life, Long Island. The Democrat, Hillary Rodham Clinton, moved from the White House to Chappaqua, in suburban Westchester. And the Republican presidential candidate, George W. Bush, is running as a social moderate and fiscal conservative -- in other words, he's positioned himself as the candidate of suburbia.</p>
        <p>The suburbs could well emerge as the battleground in New York, yet the pros still think of them as basically three or four places -- Nassau, Suffolk, Westchester and maybe Rockland -- as if suburban sprawl hadn't come to New York. It has. And in more than three or four places.</p>
        <p>There is Staten Island (Richmond County), which votes more consistently with the suburbs than with the other four boroughs. Why not lump it with the suburbs? There are also what might be called the extended suburbs, the counties north and west of the city: Orange, Putnam, Sullivan, Ulster, Dutchess, Columbia and (again) Rockland. Those 11 counties have accounted for about 32 percent of the statewide vote in recent elections, compared with 29 percent for the city without Staten Island (or 31 percent with), and 39 percent for upstate (the 47 counties north and west of Columbia County). It makes sense to view the counties as a voting bloc, says Philip Friedman, a political strategist and proponent of this theory.</p>
        <p>''The fact is, they vote cohesively, share the same concerns and have proven a willingness to split tickets, and so deserve maximum attention from both candidates,'' said Mr. Friedman, who supports Mrs. Clinton and provides his observations to some of her advisers, but is not working for any candidate in New York this year.</p>
        <p>Elections are won or lost on a lot more than numbers, of course. Disaffection with Mario M. Cuomo, for instance, energized voters upstate, severely injuring him in the 1994 gubernatorial race. Four years later, Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato lost to Charles E. Schumer in part because he had worn out the welcome he once enjoyed among Democratic city voters.</p>
        <p>This year, such ambiguous factors as Clinton fatigue and Mr. Lazio's callow image seem to be influencing voters. But demographics and voting patterns will still play a role, and there's a good argument that the conventional wisdom hasn't caught up with reality.</p>
        <p>FOR instance, the city vote remains solidly Democratic, but now that it accounts for as little as 29 percent of the statewide vote (down from 41 percent in 1960), Mrs. Clinton and Al Gore will need to do well upstate and in the suburbs even if they get overwhelming support in the city.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton is spending a great deal of time upstate, but recent election results show that while the suburbs lean to the Republicans, they are less ideological, more flexible, and voters there are more willing to switch parties: the 11 suburbs strongly supported Gov. George E. Pataki in 1998, and 10 of the 11 voted for Mr. Clinton in 1996 (only Putnam supported Bob Dole).</p>
        <p>In addition, the suburbs -- more than the four core city boroughs -- are growing, while upstate has lost population, estimates show. The suburban counties also consistently vote alike; all 11 voted the same way (mostly Republican) in 7 of the last 10 presidential elections, for example.</p>
        <p>While the suburban counties are traditionally Republican, Nassau and Westchester increasingly vote Democratic, and all 11 counties are ideologically flexible. The voters care about the same issues that interest suburbanites everywhere. Polls show they are socially moderate and fiscally conservative, in favor of gun control and abortion rights. ''They care about quality of life,'' said Mr. Friedman, the political strategist. ''These are people worried about schools, safety, the environment, property taxes.''</p>
        <p>So it is reasonable to expect a campaign dominated by talk about those very issues. Assuming the candidates have figured out the not-so-complicated State of New York.</p>
        <p>METRO MATTERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
