<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Allenby Wins On the First Playoff Hole</title>
    <meta content="10GOLF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Western Open Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Allenby, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Price, Nick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E5DC1238F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Allenby Wins On the First Playoff Hole</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>LEMONT, Ill., July 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert Allenby wins Western Open golf tournament in playoff, defeating Nick Price; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert Allenby finds a way to make playoffs pay off.</p>
        <p>In May, Allenby captured his first victory on the PGA Tour by defeating Craig Stadler in a four-hole playoff in the Houston Open. Today in the Western Open, Allenby triumphed in another playoff. After losing a three-stroke lead on the back nine in regulation, Allenby outlasted Nick Price, winning on the first hole of sudden-death with a par after Price's poor tee shot led to a bogey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Robert Allenby finds a way to make playoffs pay off.</p>
        <p>In May, Allenby captured his first victory on the PGA Tour by defeating Craig Stadler in a four-hole playoff in the Houston Open. Today in the Western Open, Allenby triumphed in another playoff. After losing a three-stroke lead on the back nine in regulation, Allenby outlasted Nick Price, winning on the first hole of sudden-death with a par after Price's poor tee shot led to a bogey.</p>
        <p>Shooting a final-round four-under-par 68 at Cog Hill Golf and Country Club, Allenby finished at 14-under-par 274 with Price, who shot a 69. Jim Furyk, Greg Kraft, and Shigeki Maruyama finished in a three-way tie for third at 12 under par, while Tiger Woods, the world's No. 1 player and the defending champion, shot a final-round 72 to finish tied for 23rd.</p>
        <p>Why is Allenby so cool under pressure? Perhaps because life has forced him to put golf in perspective. In 1996 Allenby was almost killed in a car accident in Spain, with multiple injuries putting his career in jeopardy. Then in 1998, the wife of his fellow Australian Stuart Appleby, Allenby's closest friend on the tour, was killed in an automobile accident in England. Allenby helped Appleby through his darkest days, staying with him for about a month, then deciding to play in the United States largely because he wanted to play with Appleby.</p>
        <p>But today Allenby, who turns 29 on Wednesday, took another step toward being recognized as one of the tour's better players. He became the tour's sixth multiple winner this year, joining Woods, Phil Mickelson, Hal Sutton, Jesper Parnevik and Notah Begay III. That is the kind of company Allenby wants to keep. And with another playoff victory, he proved again he knows how to capitalize when he senses a chance to win.</p>
        <p>''Playoffs must agree with me,'' said Allenby, who started the day three strokes off the lead but who made eight birdies, including seven in a 10-hole stretch. ''To beat Nick Price in a playoff is awesome. He's a great player. He's pretty good under the heat.''</p>
        <p>For Price, who has not won since the 1998 St. Jude Classic, it was another lost opportunity. Price was doomed after his tee shot on the playoff hole, the par-4, 452-yard No. 18. His drive drifted into the right bunker, near the front lip, with trees blocking his path to the green. His only choice was to hit a sand wedge back into the fairway, leaving him 107 yards from the green.</p>
        <p>After seeing Price hit his tee shot in the bunker, Allenby wisely hit a 3-wood off the tee into the middle of the fairway, then hit an approach shot 18 feet from the pin. Price's third shot, a sand wedge, rolled off the green and down into the rough, 20 yards from the cup. After Allenby two-putted for par, Price needed to make a chip shot to keep the match going. But it slid past the hole, giving Allenby the victory and Price a headache.</p>
        <p>''I'm a little disappointed, giving it to Robert on a platter there,'' Price said. ''The last 13 holes, I hit three good tee shots. I think I could have won quite comfortably if I had driven the ball well. Let's put it this way, I don't think that driver's going to see the light of day again.''</p>
        <p>With birdies on eight of his first 15 holes, Allenby reached the 16th tee holding a three-stroke lead over Price, who was on the 15th hole. But Allenby bogeyed both No. 16 and No. 18, while Price birdied No. 15.</p>
        <p>For Woods, it was the first time he did not finish in the top 20 since the Sprint International last August, ending a streak of 23 top-20 finishes. Woods did not sound concerned about his putting, however, as he looked ahead to his next tournament, the British Open, where he will try to complete a career Grand Slam.</p>
        <p>''I putted absolutely terrible going to the United States Open, and I did all right there,'' said Woods, who was headed to Ireland for a week of golf and fishing before the British Open. ''I just couldn't get it going this week. I tried my best. I drove it great. I just didn't make any of those 10- to 15-footers to get momentum going.''</p>
        <p>So it was Allenby who left with another victory, and $450,000. Once again, he was forced to work overtime. Once again, it was worth it.</p>
        <p>''I've been in six playoffs and I've won all six,'' said Allenby, counting victories on other tours around the world. ''To win when Tiger's in the field is awesome. He doesn't lose too many these days.''</p>
        <p>CHIP SHOTS</p>
        <p>TIGER WOODS hit a spectator with his second shot at No. 5. The fan, WILLIAM FICK of Antioch, Ill., had a bloody nose but did not need medical treatment. ''I didn't know it hit him in the face at first,'' Woods said. ''I got up there and it was kind of a shock to see him bleeding. . . . The third-round co-leaders, BRIAN HENNINGER and STEVE FLESCH, both faded. Henninger shot a 71 and tied for sixth at 277. Flesch shot a 75 and tied for ninth at 278.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
