<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beijing Journal; For Chinese Students, Fate Is a Single Exam</title>
    <meta content="10BEIJ$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; World; Front Page; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213915"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chinese Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eckholm, Erik</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chinese Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EEDE1238F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1303" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beijing Journal; For Chinese Students, Fate Is a Single Exam</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIK ECKHOLM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eckholm, Erik</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING, July 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Four million high school seniors across China engage in annual 'Black July' ritual, taking critical three-day examination that will determine who goes to college in country where degree is seen as ticket to prosperity and failure consignment to drudgery; are accompanied to test sites by nervous parents, many of whom were robbed of chance at higher education during turmoil of Mao's Cultural Revolution and have at least as much invested in result; in five-part exam, universally agreed to be murderous, all candidates must take tests in Chinese, English and mathematics and then must choose either science track involving tests in chemistry and physics, or liberal arts track with tests in politics and history; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Madly poring over notes one last time, giddy after months of dawn-to-midnight cramming, the students skittered into the exam site, a Beijing high school.</p>
        <p>Outside the school gates, hundreds of parents just stood and stared for hours, fanning themselves furiously, as if to dissipate their tension along with the muggy summer heat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Madly poring over notes one last time, giddy after months of dawn-to-midnight cramming, the students skittered into the exam site, a Beijing high school.</p>
        <p>Outside the school gates, hundreds of parents just stood and stared for hours, fanning themselves furiously, as if to dissipate their tension along with the muggy summer heat.</p>
        <p>This is ''Black July'' in China, time for the long-anticipated single exam that determines who goes to college in a country where a degree is seen as a ticket to prosperity, and failure can mean consignment to drudgery.</p>
        <p>The four million high school seniors who took the entrance exam these past three days across China have worlds riding on the outcome -- what rank of college they may enter, or whether they can attend college at all.</p>
        <p>Their parents, many of whom were robbed of a chance at higher education by the turmoil of Mao's Cultural Revolution, are often more nervous than their offspring, and have at least as much invested in the result.</p>
        <p>''In our time, young people had to go work in the countryside,'' said Zhang Mei, whose 19-year-old daughter and only child, Li Hui, hopes to study business management and somberly called the exam ''a turning point in my life.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Zhang and her husband were among those who missed out on college in Mao's upheaval, and then, as things returned to normal in the late 1970's, were held to a single child by newly stringent family planning rules. So their daughter is the repository of stifled dreams. ''We weren't well educated,'' said Ms. Zhang, who works in a railway personnel office. ''But to make it in society these days you just have to go to college.''</p>
        <p>Like a growing number of parents, Ms. Zhang and her husband splurged to rent an air-conditioned hotel room near their daughter's assigned test site, so she would have a comfortable place to rest between sessions.</p>
        <p>''This is a really big event in her life,'' Ms. Zhang said. ''She needs to be relaxed.''</p>
        <p>Unlike some classmates, though, her daughter decided not to supplement her fierce studying with much-advertised pills like ''Brain Relaxer'' or ''Never Forget,'' fish-oil products said to improve blood flow in the brain and to enhance memory.</p>
        <p>''I'm more nervous than my daughter,'' said Yan Yanan, one of the furiously fanning mothers waiting outside the Chen Jinglun High School, one of 77 testing sites in Beijing, and another parent whose own educational hopes were crushed by Maoist excess. ''I'm worried that she might fail, or have to go to a second-rate university, but college has become a must these days.''</p>
        <p>In just one sign of the importance attached to this exam, the Beijing city government banned nearly all nighttime construction work for the last few weeks, lest any student's concentration be disturbed. Newspapers have been filled with admonitions not to put pressure on the students, about ideal diets and even strategies for how to avoid traffic jams en route to the test.</p>
        <p>In the five-part exam, universally agreed to be murderous, every candidate must take the tests in Chinese, English and mathematics and then must choose either the science track, involving tests in chemistry and physics, or the liberal arts track, with tests in politics and history.</p>
        <p>According to government projections, only about half of the test-takers -- themselves an elite who tested well enough to get into academic high schools after junior high -- will gain entry to college. Over all, because of the scarcity of slots, only about 12 percent of young adults in China can attend college, a far lower share than in most Western countries, which only enhances the value of a degree.</p>
        <p>''This exam is like a big mountain in front of you,'' said He Jianming, a Beijing writer who just published a book about its social impact. ''If you get over the top, you'll see a bright future, the pot of gold. If you fail, your life seems to be at an end.''</p>
        <p>In Beijing, most of those sitting for the exam will find their way to college -- preferably, of course, into the most prestigious schools like Beijing University or Qinghua, China's equivalents of Harvard and M.I.T.</p>
        <p>The stakes are incomparably higher for students in smaller towns and rural areas, for whom a good score can mean the difference between a life with open horizons -- including the prized right to live and work in a big city -- and a life of near-certain hardship.</p>
        <p>Wang Guangli knows all about the pressures and potential payoffs. In 1985, as a student from a poor farm town in Sichuan Province, he tested brilliantly, escaped to university in Shanghai and is now a successful documentary film maker in Beijing.</p>
        <p>''My classmates who didn't pass have horrible lives now,'' he said bluntly. Most of them, he said, either remained as poor farmers or became migrant workers in the cities, holding menial jobs, at best.</p>
        <p>Late last week, Mr. Wang flew back to his hometown, Meishan, to help his nephew, Zhao Hao, prepare for the exam. He did this, Mr. Wang said, not to tutor the boy -- he had already studied 16 hours a day for months -- but to help him relax in the final hours by talking about anything but chemistry and math.</p>
        <p>On the eve of what he hopes will be his ticket to a legal career, the nephew sounded more philosophical than his uncle. ''They say all roads lead to Rome,'' the boy said by telephone. ''But I think the college exam is a shortcut.''</p>
        <p>Everyone complains about the iron rule of this single, standardized test and the way it distorts young people's lives and the curriculum they study. Yet the exam, which prolongs a venerable imperial tradition of examinations for high office, is also seen as a relatively fair and honest way to hand out scarce college places.</p>
        <p>But complaints are growing about the system's discrimination in favor of already privileged residents of Beijing and Shanghai. Many universities, including the nation's finest, are located in these two cities, and a disproportionate number of their slots are allocated to local residents.</p>
        <p>As a result, Beijing students are admitted to good universities with scores far below those of students from large provinces like Hunan or Hubei who may find no college spot at all.</p>
        <p>While the exam still provides a way for smart students from poor families to crack into the elite, its equalizing effect is also undermined by the rising tuition and other fees charged by public universities. Since they know their families could never raise the $1,000 a year or more that is required to attend college these days, said Mr. He, some bright students do not even bother to enroll for the entrance exam.</p>
        <p>Children from better-off families, even if they test abysmally, can also pay to attend one of the hundreds of generally second-rate private colleges that have sprung up to meet the demand for college degrees.</p>
        <p>In the final days of July, students will learn their test scores. Those who do not make it to college have a dismal fallback: they can try again next ''Black July,'' in fact every July until they turn 25.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
