<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BARAK'S COALITION CRUMBLES ON EVE OF SUMMIT TALKS</title>
    <meta content="10ISRA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213928"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E5DC1238F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BARAK'S COALITION CRUMBLES ON EVE OF SUMMIT TALKS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, July 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israeli government of Prime Min Ehud Barak crumbles as three rightist parties quit in protest against anticipated concessions to Palestinians, leaving him on uncertain ground on eve of departure for Camp David summit with Yasir Arafat and Pres Clinton; loses parliamentary majority and broad coalition, constructed precisely to build stable foundation of support for difficult peace moves; three parties reject Barak's pleas for unity, defecting to previously weak opposition and upsetting political balance of power; Barak addresses nation; defiantly says coalition will not affect trip to summit, which he maintains is backed by Israelis who elected him by overwhelming majority on peacemaking platform; says as lifelong soldier and fledgling politician he has direct bond with voters; possible effects of government's collapse on three-way retreat-style summit discussed; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak's government disintegrated today as one right-leaning party after another quit in protest against anticipated concessions to the Palestinians, leaving him on unsteady ground on the eve of his departure to the Camp David summit meeting.</p>
        <p>Ignoring Mr. Barak's pleas for unity, three parties, including the ultra-Orthodox Shas, defected to the previously weak opposition, upsetting the political balance of power in a single afternoon. Mr. Barak lost his parliamentary majority, and his broad coalition, which was constructed precisely to build a stable foundation of support for difficult peace moves, shriveled to a weak center-left government.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak's government disintegrated today as one right-leaning party after another quit in protest against anticipated concessions to the Palestinians, leaving him on unsteady ground on the eve of his departure to the Camp David summit meeting.</p>
        <p>Ignoring Mr. Barak's pleas for unity, three parties, including the ultra-Orthodox Shas, defected to the previously weak opposition, upsetting the political balance of power in a single afternoon. Mr. Barak lost his parliamentary majority, and his broad coalition, which was constructed precisely to build a stable foundation of support for difficult peace moves, shriveled to a weak center-left government.</p>
        <p>In an address to the nation, Mr. Barak defiantly said that the collapse of his coalition would not affect his trip to Maryland, which he said was backed by a mandate from the Israelis who elected him by an overwhelming majority on a peacemaking platform.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak asserted that, as a lifelong soldier and fledgling politician, he had a direct bond with the voters that existed in a kind of extrapolitical space.</p>
        <p>''Citizens of Israel, approximately one year ago I was elected by you to be the prime minister of Israel in order to lead the state of Israel to a safer reality and in order to create a better future for our children,'' Mr. Barak said. ''I did not receive my mandate from the politicians or from the parties. I received my mandate from each one of you.''</p>
        <p>Experts say that by adding new small parties to his government and relying on the support of Arab parties Mr. Barak could still win a parliamentary majority for any deal that might be reached at the summit meeting. But it would not be the ''Jewish majority'' that he originally sought in hopes of moving toward peace without deepening divisions that could destabilize not just his government but also the country.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak repeated that he would rely on a popular vote, in the form of a referendum on an agreement, to try to resolve those rifts. And his office predicted tonight that any agreement he achieved at Camp David would be ratified by a significant popular majority.</p>
        <p>It is hard to imagine that the new Israeli political reality will not alter the dynamic of the three-way retreat-style summit meeting, where the goal will be to end a 52-year conflict and resolve the most divisive issues between the Israelis and Palestinians.</p>
        <p>But precisely how is uncertain. Palestinian negotiators could now perceive Mr. Barak as a weakened leader unable to deliver on his promises. While the prime minister could face a strengthened opposition, he may also now feel free to make concessions without worrying which political partner he might lose.</p>
        <p>In any case, Palestinian officials said tonight that they would try to shut out the Israeli political convolutions and, although they were skeptical even before today's events, focus on trying to achieve an agreement.</p>
        <p>Some Palestinian officials also said they were suspicious that Mr. Barak was engineering his own political difficulties so that he could hide behind them at the bargaining table.</p>
        <p>''It's not the first time that we have witnessed such a show on the stage of Ehud Barak,'' said Abdul Ahmed Rahman, the secretary general of the Palestinian cabinet. ''This is not credible. If Barak thinks that he can manufacture the impression that he is restricted, well, such maneuvers will be transparent to the Americans as well as to us.''</p>
        <p>Kicking off the snowballing dynamic of the day, Foreign Minister David Levy told Mr. Barak this morning that, in protest at what he labeled the Palestinians' hard-line positions and threats of violence, he would not join the delegation traveling to Camp David. He did not speak publicly about his decision, but associates said he was pessimistic that anything would come of the talks, which are supposed to start on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Yaron Dekel, a political analyst, said he saw this as ''a slap in the face'' to Mr. Barak and a no-confidence vote in Mr. Barak's policy.</p>
        <p>Then Interior Minister Natan Sharansky, leader of a small Russian immigrant party, resigned, saying that Mr. Barak had obstinately refused to divulge his positions in advance and to build the internal support needed for what could be difficult concessions ahead. Mr. Sharansky had been pushing Mr. Barak to form a unity government with the rightist Likud Party.</p>
        <p>''You are arriving at the summit in the United States weakened, without red lines, without the support of the government and without the support of most of the people,'' Mr. Sharansky wrote in his resignation letter to Mr. Barak.</p>
        <p>''Under these conditions,'' he continued, ''the agreement that you will be able to reach is dangerous from a diplomatic point of view and has the potential to cause a split in the people, a split from which, God forbid, there will be no turning back.''</p>
        <p>Several hours later, the Shas Party, whose balkiness has unsettled the government since it took office last July, finally walked out for good.</p>
        <p>Shas is a religious party that doubles as an ethnic pride movement for working-class Jews of Middle Eastern origin. In its routine threats to quit, it was perceived to be maneuvering for its party's interests, particularly the financial health and independence of its religious school system.</p>
        <p>If Shas was satisfied, the common wisdom said, it would support peacemaking based on its spiritual leader's religious ruling that territory could be conceded if lives would be saved as a result.</p>
        <p>But analysts repeatedly predicted that Shas, whose constituency leans to the right, would get the jitters when a crucial moment arrived. Indeed, by day's end, when it became clear that it would be the only right-leaning party left in the government, Shas made the decision to quit.</p>
        <p>''Shas entered the coalition because the peace process is very important to us and we would have expected to have been genuine partners,'' said Eli Yishai, Shas's political leader. ''But to be partners on the road taken one needs to know the road. And we don't. We don't know Barak's red lines. The red lines that he demarcated and presented to the people are obscure and unclear.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak's office, in a statement, countered that his red lines -- which the Palestinians regularly and glumly cite as evidence that an agreement will be difficult to achieve -- have been well known since his campaign. The statement said that revealing them in greater detail would weaken Israel's negotiating position.</p>
        <p>The statement reiterated Mr. Barak's absolutes: no return to 1967 borders, ''a united Jerusalem under Israeli sovereignty, no foreign army west of the Jordan River, a majority of the Jewish settlers to remain in settlement blocs, and no Israeli recognition of legal or moral responsibility for creating the refugee problem.''</p>
        <p>Officials of the leftist Meretz Party, who recently resigned their cabinet positions so that Shas would stay in the government, were furious. ''All through the years we heard of the moderate stand taken by Shas because Rabbi Ovadia Yosef, their leader, he puts foremost the saving of lives -- that saving lives is more important than territories,'' said Ran Cohen, the former trade minister.</p>
        <p>''Now Barak comes along and with tweezers goes over every detail, every settlement, every road, every section, measures exactly as possible in order to save lives, to prevent returning to the killing of Jews and Arabs in a continuation of 100 years of war, and the Shas people, the moment they stand before the most important diplomatic, ideological, test of principle, they say they are about to quit?''</p>
        <p>''For what? Do they want to return to the intifada?'' he asked, referring to the uprising of the late 1980's.</p>
        <p>After Shas's resignation, the National Religious Party, which represents religious Zionists and the settlers, said that its central committee had voted unanimously to pull out of the government.</p>
        <p>All three parties that quit were part of the rightist government of former Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, which fell after Mr. Netanyahu concluded an interim peace agreement with the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak faces a no-confidence motion in his government on Monday, which was submitted by the Likud Party on the basis of his supposed ''capitulation'' to Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader. Analysts predict that Mr. Barak will survive it, but his office said tonight that he had changed his travel plans to return to Israel from a trip to Egypt on Monday so that he could be present in the Parliament later in the day. Then he will proceed to the United States.</p>
        <p>The parties' resignations will reduce Mr. Barak to a 42-member government in a 120-member Parliament. He could build a heftier minority government of 52 members by pulling in three other small parties: a liberal Russian immigrant faction, a secularist party and a trade unionists' party.</p>
        <p>But it would be an unstable political base for running the government, and it remains to be seen how Mr. Barak will handle either a success or failure at Camp David. Political analysts consider new elections likely.  As a leader routinely accused of haughtiness and autocratic behavior, Mr. Barak is taking a risk in his bid  to ignore the political system and appeal directly to the people.</p>
        <p>''Had I been forced to listen to all the prophets of doom -- the very same prophets who are now speaking at large -- I suppose that our children would still be in the Lebanese mud,'' he said, referring to those who predicted that the Israeli troop withdrawal from southern Lebanon in May would lead to war. ''No one will teach me what security is.''</p>
        <p>He continued: ''I have to rise above all of the political disputes and above all party considerations and exhaust all of the possibilities on the way to a peace agreement that will put an end to the bloody conflict between us and our neighbors. Put an end to it at the negotiation table and not in the battlefields and in terror-stricken streets.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
