<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Owensboro Journal; Rooms Available in Gated Community: $20 a Day</title>
    <meta content="Y10JAIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kentucky</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E2D71538F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1136" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Owensboro Journal; Rooms Available in Gated Community: $20 a Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>OWENSBORO, Ky., July 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New law will permit Kentucky's 85 jails to charge up to $50 per day for room and board, plus $20 paperwork fee and other special charges for unruly inmates; pay-your-way practice dates to medieval England and is finding fresh life in US, global leader in incarceration; maps; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The county jailers of Kentucky are eagerly preparing to levy room, board and medical charges on inmates under a pay-your-way practice that dates to medieval England but is finding fresh life in America, the global leader in incarceration.</p>
        <p>The chief jailer in Daviess County, Harold N. Taylor, is awaiting his new hotelier's powers with a touch of nostalgia for his salad days as a deputy sheriff in the 1960's. Back then, he recalled, respectful town drunkards barely taxed the public budget as they gratefully slugged down black coffee and slept off their misdeeds in a far less complex world of the jail house.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The county jailers of Kentucky are eagerly preparing to levy room, board and medical charges on inmates under a pay-your-way practice that dates to medieval England but is finding fresh life in America, the global leader in incarceration.</p>
        <p>The chief jailer in Daviess County, Harold N. Taylor, is awaiting his new hotelier's powers with a touch of nostalgia for his salad days as a deputy sheriff in the 1960's. Back then, he recalled, respectful town drunkards barely taxed the public budget as they gratefully slugged down black coffee and slept off their misdeeds in a far less complex world of the jail house.</p>
        <p>''Nowadays, you have the situation where one inmate went to court to sue me to get all his teeth replaced,'' said Mr. Taylor, echoing the complaints of county jailers across the country that rising medical and housing costs in small-town jails necessitate turning to the inmates to help pay the bill.</p>
        <p>Under a new law that takes effect this month, the state's 85 jails will have the power to charge up to $50 a day for room and board, plus a $20 paperwork fee and other special charges for unruly inmates who sling their food about or damage bunks or plumbing.</p>
        <p>''More and more jails across the country are turning to these fees,'' said Stephen Ingley, executive director of the American Jail Association, which has 5,000 members. Each year the nation's jails have 20 million admissions and exits, with more than 600,000 inmates in residence each day, including many felony defendants awaiting trial. Handling this torrent is no longer a sleepy-time industry, Mr. Ingley said, and inmates are covered by federal and state standards for housing, diet and medical care that have grown stronger and more expensive in the last two decades.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor, who lobbied for the new law as chief of the Kentucky Jailers Association, said: ''There's the old saying, 'Crime doesn't pay.' Well now there's the thought that maybe the criminals should start paying.''</p>
        <p>Local jailers say that jails in Florida, Iowa, Michigan, West Virginia and other states experienced improvements in budgets and inmate behavior when they began levying  fees in recent years. In response to  complaints from civil libertarians that the levy amounts to a double-dipping of punishment, jailers say that judges have long had the power to impose court costs on defendants and there has been no attendant controversy.</p>
        <p>''This is not a law without compassion,'' said State Senator David E. Boswell, a Democrat from Owensboro who was the chief sponsor of the measure. ''It has to be shown an inmate can afford to pay, and a jailer has up to a year to collect once an inmate becomes a productive citizen again.''</p>
        <p>The law sailed through the Legislature with barely a dissent. It covers only county inmates typically sentenced to a year or less in jail, not state and federal felons who serve longer terms in prisons. Proponents contend that it can provide an extra measure of deterrence when the public sees, for example, a drunken driver doing his jail time but also tapping his own resources for good measure. Proponents of the law also cite the potential for compensation in coping with modern criminal life in which well-capitalized drug dealers routinely cycle through local jails.</p>
        <p>''A lot of dealers come through here after arrest with $2,000 or $5,000 in their pockets,'' Mr. Taylor said, putting such inmates at the top of his most-lucrative lodger list.</p>
        <p>Jailers will have the power to take money from inmates' commissary accounts and even pursue them through collection agencies if jailers decide it is worth the trouble. The levy has practical limits for the many jail-house deadbeats serving time, but Mr. Taylor hopes to net $250,000 a year for his $3 million budget, and proponents of the law  promise millions more for the state's other 119 counties.</p>
        <p>''We know you can't get blood out of a turnip,'' said Dan Fackler, the jailer for Bullitt County, sympathizing with some down-on-his-luck inmate suddenly shocked with a lodging bill at checkout. ''But we hear they're getting maybe 30 cents on each dollar due with this in other parts of the country, and taxpayers think it's a step in the right direction. You should pay for what you do in this life, whether it's good or bad.''</p>
        <p>Jail-house costs vary, but the federal government estimates that the average room and board expenses are $34 per day, with medical costs additional. Jailers say that the rising expense of mandated medical care, more than any other factor, is spurring the current move to levy fees on inmates.</p>
        <p>''We're becoming more like a hospital and a care center,'' Mr. Fackler said. ''That's O.K. -- it could be my brother in there with a need -- but nowadays his medicine can cost $300.'' And under the current state mandate of three jail beds for every 1,000 citizens, Mr. Fackler said he must find extra resources to help build a $8 million, 300-bed jail for his fast-growing county south of Louisville.</p>
        <p>''That's what got people tore up around here,'' Mr. Fackler added. ''So if, say, Mr. McAdoo owes me $495 when he's checking out and he only has $180, well I'll just take the hundred-eighty and say thank you, McAdoo.''</p>
        <p>Under the law, Kentucky jailers will have the option to charge their inmates or not, to negotiate a compromise payment, and even to carry negative balances on the books for the next time a repeat offender may return flush with cash.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor intends to charge $20 a day for room and board plus medical costs and a $20 admission fee. ''In the old days, you'd find someone curled up on the sidewalk with his bottle of Thunderbird; you'd take him in,'' he recalled. A regular miscreant might not even have been written up back then, and there was a mutual kindness of jailer and inmate that, Mr. Taylor insisted, was as commonplace as the jail's old baloney sandwich. ''Now we've got a minimum of two hot meals a day and each inmate has his required square footage,'' said the jailer, busily preparing a detailed computer program to retally a modern inmate's debt to society.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
