<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Movement for Fishing Quotas Creates Some Unlikely Allies</title>
    <meta content="Y10FISH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Quotas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gulf of Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hulse, Carl</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Quotas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E4D71538F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Movement for Fishing Quotas Creates Some Unlikely Allies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARL HULSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulse, Carl</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fishermen seeking to end frenzied competition for prime catch in Gulf of Mexico strike alliance with conservation groups; are seeking to end scramble associated with so-called derby approach, in which captains are given strict limit of fish to compete for and brief time to catch them (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For Wayne Werner, a commercial fishing skipper, and his boat's crew, the frenzied competition for prime catch in the Gulf of Mexico is a no-win proposition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Werner, captain of the Wayne's Pain in Galliano, La., says short seasons for prized fish like red snapper and king mackerel are proving hazardous, occasionally forcing boat crews to choose between braving threatening weather and skipping a payday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For Wayne Werner, a commercial fishing skipper, and his boat's crew, the frenzied competition for prime catch in the Gulf of Mexico is a no-win proposition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Werner, captain of the Wayne's Pain in Galliano, La., says short seasons for prized fish like red snapper and king mackerel are proving hazardous, occasionally forcing boat crews to choose between braving threatening weather and skipping a payday.</p>
        <p>''If you have 10 days to fish in September and a hurricane comes along, you either don't fish or you go out and it is dangerous,'' said Mr. Werner, 42. He said he knew of three members of Gulf fishing crews lost in rough seas in recent years, and a couple of boats sunk.</p>
        <p>''You are running for 20 hours,'' Mr. Werner said. ''It is inevitable you are going to have accidents. It is just such a race for fish.''</p>
        <p>Hoping to restore a bit of calm to fishing in the Gulf and elsewhere, some fishermen have struck a rare alliance with conservation groups. They are seeking to end the scramble associated with the so-called derby approach, in which captains are given a strict limit of fish to compete for and a brief time to catch them.</p>
        <p>For instance, red snapper fishing was allowed in the first 10 days of February, March and April but was cut off early in May when the spring quota of three million pounds was reached. The fall season will open Sept. 1 with a smaller goal of about 1.6 million pounds.</p>
        <p>Those unhappy with this system would instead allot fishermen individual quotas, enabling captains to spread their trips out over the year, reducing risk and making fresh fish more regularly available at the seafood counter.</p>
        <p>Under a typical quota program, the total catch of a species would be divided among eligible captains, each receiving shares based on his fishing history.</p>
        <p>''The derby fishery is unnecessarily subjecting us to dangerous conditions all the time,'' said Felix Cox, a snapper captain from Aransas Pass, Tex. ''We don't have the flexibility to make the judgment calls it takes to run a business like this.''</p>
        <p>A four-year federal moratorium on new individual fishing quota programs is to expire Sept. 30. But some members of Congress, moving to protect fishing interests in their regions that oppose the idea, are poised to extend the moratorium.</p>
        <p>Senator Olympia J. Snowe, the Maine Republican who is chairwoman of the Commerce Subcommittee on Oceans and Fisheries, wants to keep the ban in place for three more years as part of a fishery management measure facing a committee vote. Ms. Snowe has enlisted backing from the Senate majority leader, Trent Lott, Republican of Mississippi, those following the legislation say.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Ms. Snowe said that even though a series of hearings she had conducted found support for individual quotas in the Gulf of Mexico and the Pacific Northwest, the senator was worried that they could be acquired by large commercial interests that would squeeze out smaller independent fishermen.</p>
        <p>Dave Lackey, an aide to Ms. Snowe, said that in New England the individual quotas were ''pretty broadly opposed.''</p>
        <p>Not all environmental groups are ready to see the moratorium expire either. Lee Crockett, executive director of the Marine Fish Conservation Network, an umbrella organization of environmental and commercial fishing groups, said the moratorium should not be lifted without the enactment of strict regulations. Those would include a fair allocation system, a five-year term on any quotas and a mechanism to let conservation groups buy and hold quota shares -- never actually catching the fish -- to protect and replenish fish stocks.</p>
        <p>Environmental Defense, a group that advocates market-based techniques to protect the environment, is strongly behind the fishermen in their push for individual quotas, calling them a common-sense solution to fishing problems like weather risks and the discarding of millions of pounds of fish unintentionally caught out of season.</p>
        <p>The group has been lining up support for eliminating the moratorium from senators like Kay Bailey Hutchison, Republican of Texas, and John B. Breaux, Democrat of Louisiana. Senator Ted Stevens, Republican of Alaska, who was a chief proponent of the ban when it was imposed in 1996, has signaled a softening in his stance. Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the probable Republican presidential nominee, also favors individual quotas.</p>
        <p>''This tool vests fishermen with an incentive to conserve the fishery, eliminates such bureaucratic restrictions as minimum size limits and season closings and reduces dangerous operating conditions,'' Mr. Bush wrote in an April 28 letter to Ms. Hutchison.</p>
        <p>A National Research Council report issued last year also recommended that regional fishery councils be given the option of trying individual quotas, a concept in limited use domestically but employed on a broad scale internationally.</p>
        <p>A study of Alaskan halibut, one of the few fish covered by individual quotas, done for Environmental Defense found measurable safety improvements since the mid-1990's, when fishermen were allowed a few chaotic 24-hour periods each year in which to make their catch.</p>
        <p>''In one 24-hour opening, 2,000 or more boats might enter the fishing grounds, regardless of weather conditions, each setting excessive amounts of gear in a make-or-break race to land a full year's catch,'' the report said.</p>
        <p>Search-and-rescue missions by the Coast Guard were reduced to 7 in 1996 from 33 in 1994 under the halibut quota system. No halibut-fishing fatalities occurred from 1995 to 1996, compared with 11 from 1991 to 1994, Environmental Defense said.</p>
        <p>Fishermen say some of the opposition to individual quotas comes from fish dealers and processors, who enjoy an advantage under the current system because the supply of fish is so large during short seasons.</p>
        <p>''Now the dealer has control,'' said Mr. Cox, the Texas fishermen, who said Gulf fishermen were getting prices for snapper and mackerel below those of a decade ago. ''With quotas, the fisherman would regain the power he has lost through regulation over the years.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
