<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>XM Satellite Radio Completes Its Financing</title>
    <meta content="10RADI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213869"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Xm Satellite Radio Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5D81538F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="375" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>XM Satellite Radio Completes Its Financing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romero, Simon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>XM Satellite Radio reportedly raises $235 million from a group of investors, bringing total financing to $1.26 billion (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a sign that long-promised satellite radio broadcasting is coming closer to fruition, XM Satellite Radio is expected to announce today that it has completed its planned financing, raising the last $235 million from a group of investors, people close to the transaction said.</p>
        <p>This latest investment includes $50 million from the Honda Motor Company's sales and marketing subsidiary in the United States, $20 million from DirecTV, a provider of satellite-delivered television service and money from several private investment firms. The investors received convertible preferred stock in XM, which is based in Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a sign that long-promised satellite radio broadcasting is coming closer to fruition, XM Satellite Radio is expected to announce today that it has completed its planned financing, raising the last $235 million from a group of investors, people close to the transaction said.</p>
        <p>This latest investment includes $50 million from the Honda Motor Company's sales and marketing subsidiary in the United States, $20 million from DirecTV, a provider of satellite-delivered television service and money from several private investment firms. The investors received convertible preferred stock in XM, which is based in Washington.</p>
        <p>The transaction brings XM one step closer to its plan to introduce satellite-delivered radio by the middle of next year. The company would compete with Sirius Satellite Radio, which also plans to provide nationwide satellite radio broadcasts. Each company would charge approximately $10 a month for as many as 100 different audio channels.</p>
        <p>So far, XM has raised a total of $1.26 billion with the private placement on Friday of this latest round of stock. Most of the company's capital will be used to launch the satellites it needs to start service. The company also plans to officially open its headquarters today in Washington, where much of the radio programming will be produced.</p>
        <p>Much in the same manner that cable and satellite television have changed the way television programming is delivered, proponents of satellite radio are hoping that a broader array of listening options and improved broadcast quality will appeal to consumers. People whose cars would be equipped with small satellite receivers are intended to be a prime audience.</p>
        <p>XM's backers include General Motors, with which it has an installation agreement, and the company is discussing a similar agreement with Honda, people close to the talks said. Sirius, which is based in New York, has installation deals with DaimlerChrysler, Ford Motor and BMW.</p>
        <p>XM and Sirius have been awarded the only licenses that the Federal Communications Commission has granted so far for satellite radio service. Sirius successfully launched its first of three satellites last week at a site in Kazakhstan.</p>
        <p>XM is planning to launch a satellite, the first of two it plans to send into space, from a mobile launching vessel in the Pacific Ocean later this year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
