<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Powells Are Sticking Together</title>
    <meta content="Y10LAX$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213906"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LACROSSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hollander, Sophia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powell, Casey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powell, Ryan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E0DF1238F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1013" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Powells Are Sticking Together</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOPHIA HOLLANDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hollander, Sophia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brothers Casey and Ryan Powell and 40 other top lacrosse players are part of two all-star teams traveling in East thsi summer in effort to promote first professional outdoor league; they comment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ryan Powell's teammates funneled him passes as he hovered around the goal in the men's national lacrosse final against Princeton on May 29. It was the last game of the 22-year-old attackman's storied career at Syracuse, and there were seven minutes left, then four, then one. Though he would get his first championship, with a 13-7 victory, he was a single point from tying his older brother Casey's school record of 287 career points.</p>
        <p>The brothers had competed with one another their entire lives, trying to be the best in every sport they played. But in this moment, Casey rooted for his brother to break his record, and Ryan decided he wanted to tie it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ryan Powell's teammates funneled him passes as he hovered around the goal in the men's national lacrosse final against Princeton on May 29. It was the last game of the 22-year-old attackman's storied career at Syracuse, and there were seven minutes left, then four, then one. Though he would get his first championship, with a 13-7 victory, he was a single point from tying his older brother Casey's school record of 287 career points.</p>
        <p>The brothers had competed with one another their entire lives, trying to be the best in every sport they played. But in this moment, Casey rooted for his brother to break his record, and Ryan decided he wanted to tie it.</p>
        <p>Casey, 24, watched tensely from the stands in College Park, Md., as the final seconds left the clock. Then, Ryan scooped up the ball and smoothly flipped a pass to a penetrating Ethan Mills, who scored with 18 seconds left. Ryan had done it. As he raced to the sideline, arms raised, his brother roared. It had been two years since they played on the same front line at Syracuse, but the four-time all-Americans became linked in school lacrosse lore.</p>
        <p>On Saturday night, the Powell brothers stood on a field in Columbus, Ohio, and again made their mark. They were the starting attackmen for one of two all-star lacrosse teams that are traveling in the East this summer as part of an ambitious experiment to promote the first professional outdoor lacrosse league. Their team lost, 23-21, but Ryan had four goals and one assist, and Casey had three goals and three assists.</p>
        <p>''There's a little bit of strangeness because I don't get to go out and play with him that much,'' Ryan said, ''but every time that we go out there and step on the field it seems like we always want to bring our 'A' game to the table because we don't want to get shown up by the other one. So that helps us play a lot better.''</p>
        <p>The Powell brothers and 40 other top players will showcase Major League Lacrosse in six more cities: Philadelphia; Baltimore; Uniondale, N.Y.; Buffalo; Rochester; and Newark in the conclusion of the tour on Aug. 19.</p>
        <p>The league's co-founder, Jake Steinfeld, has said that a crowd of  5,000 is the target for each site. Strong support would mean the founding of an official league next summer.</p>
        <p>On the surface, it seems like a risky proposition. Lacrosse remains rooted in the Northeast, though it has still failed to catch on in major Eastern cities, including New York.</p>
        <p>Steinfeld, chairman of Body By Jake Enterprises, is joined by his league partners: Dave Morrow, president of Warrior Lacrosse, a leading lacrosse equipment company he founded while playing at Princeton; Timothy Robertson, former chief executive officer of the Family Channel and the SFX Sports group; and Frank Vuono, president of Integrated Sports International.</p>
        <p>All the games will be televised, two nationally. A shot clock and a 2-point play will be added in an effort to inject more excitement and draw in viewers unfamiliar with the game. Fireworks and halftime contests are planned and tickets range from $9 to $15.</p>
        <p>Where sports like soccer have struggled to generate and promote a series of stars, SFX, which represents Michael Jordan and Kobe Bryant, will concentrate on creating recognizable faces. The Powell brothers' extraordinary physical talent and competitiveness, combined with their open, embracing personalities, have placed them at the center of that strategy.</p>
        <p>Growing up in Carthage, N.Y.,  about an hour outside of Syracuse, the Powells were introduced to lacrosse when an elementary school gym teacher brought in a lacrosse stick to show his classes.</p>
        <p>''My dad was like: 'You've got your baseball gloves, football, basketball. What do you need these sticks for? What's this game?' '' Casey recalled.</p>
        <p>After their two weeks of whining, their father finally agreed to buy the $30 sticks. The Powell brothers carried them onto the school playground, where they chalked boxes, devised challenges and broke school windows, and into their backyard, where they would play for hours.</p>
        <p>Through high school they teamed up to do paper routes, mow the lawn at the local cemetery and sell candy at school to raise money to compete in summer lacrosse camps.</p>
        <p>After high school they went to Syracuse, where they quickly became role models for star-struck lacrosse students. They left New York State for the first time as they traveled to games, staying in different hotels, in different cities, eating in different restaurants.</p>
        <p>They are still adjusting to new experiences in large cities. When they were told to dress casually for breakfast at the Plaza hotel in Manhattan, they threw on a pair of shorts  and T-shirts and cheerfully entered the dining room ready to eat. They were approached and politely informed that shorts were not allowed. They looked at each other.</p>
        <p>''Is there anywhere else to eat?'' Casey said.</p>
        <p>''Well,'' they were told, ''room service is available.''</p>
        <p>So they went back up to their room, pulled out wrinkly pants and went back down to have breakfast.</p>
        <p>''Lacrosse allowed me to do so many things in my life that I would never have been able to,'' Ryan said. ''Since I've been in New York, I kind of find myself sitting around people-watching because it's just so exciting to see every different culture. It all collides here in New York.''</p>
        <p>The Powells are trying to savor the opportunities that lacrosse has given them. Best of all, they get to do it together.</p>
        <p>LACROSSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
