<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N.'s Plan for Kosovo Threatens to Unravel</title>
    <meta content="Y10KOSO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213889"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kosovo (Serbia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E0D71538F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1141" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N.'s Plan for Kosovo Threatens to Unravel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>GRACANICA, Kosovo, July 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First agreement between Serbs and UN administration in Gracanica, Serbia, which may provide better protection for Serbian minority, threatens to unravel key Albanian participation in international efforts to build democratic, tolerant Kosovo; year into effort to rebuild new Kosovo, many in UN administration express weariness over recalcitrance of Albanian leaders who are jostling for power and seem willing to fight out differences on streets; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first agreement between the Serbs and the United Nations administration here may provide better protection for the Serbian minority, but it threatens to unravel key Albanian participation in international efforts to build a democratic, tolerant Kosovo.</p>
        <p>Maneuvering by the province's majority Albanians and the Serbs is intensifying ahead of municipal elections scheduled for October. The international administration here hopes that this ballot will be the first step toward cutting Kosovo loose from its foreign lifelines, but so far almost no Serbs have registered to vote.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first agreement between the Serbs and the United Nations administration here may provide better protection for the Serbian minority, but it threatens to unravel key Albanian participation in international efforts to build a democratic, tolerant Kosovo.</p>
        <p>Maneuvering by the province's majority Albanians and the Serbs is intensifying ahead of municipal elections scheduled for October. The international administration here hopes that this ballot will be the first step toward cutting Kosovo loose from its foreign lifelines, but so far almost no Serbs have registered to vote.</p>
        <p>And Albanian leaders jostling for power seem to be increasingly willing to fight out their differences on the streets.</p>
        <p>A year into the effort to rebuild Kosovo, many in the United Nations administration say they are wearying of the recalcitrance of Albanian leaders. They are also under new pressure to protect the Serbian minority better against persistent attacks, especially the more openly cooperative Serbs grouped around the religious leaders Bishop Kyr Artemije and the Rev. Sava Janjic -- known as Father Sava -- who are based at the early 14th-century Serbian Orthodox monastery here.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration has negotiated with Bishop Artemije to persuade him to join the executive council established by Bernard Kouchner, the chief United Nations administrator. The bishop's decision to do so was viewed as traitorous by the Yugoslav government of President Slobodan Milosevic in Belgrade and by a rival Kosovo Serb grouping led from the northern town of Mitrovica.</p>
        <p>Some formal participation by Serbs is considered vital to the success of the Western effort to turn Kosovo into a democratic, self-governing entity where all ethnic groups can live peacefully -- even if separated into enclaves behind barbed wire and guarded by foreign peacekeepers.</p>
        <p>And there is pressure from Washington to begin the return to Kosovo of at least some Serbs who fled Albanian revenge when NATO's bombing war against Yugoslavia ended a year ago, enabling hundreds of thousands of Albanians driven from home by the Serbs to return.</p>
        <p>Washington is eager to promote the bishop and his Serbian National Council over the harder-line Mitrovica Serbs led by Oliver Ivanovic, who is more closely, if not definitively, allied with Belgrade.</p>
        <p>Therefore, after Bishop Artemije protested increased attacks on Serbs last month by walking out of Mr. Kouchner's council, the Clinton administration helped the bishop's group of Serbs and the United Nations to negotiate an agreement on security for the Serbian minority that coaxed the bishop back in, at least for three more months.</p>
        <p>It was the first direct accord between the United Nations and Kosovo Serbs.</p>
        <p>''We have no other choice but to participate,'' said Father Sava, the bishop's aide and spokesman. ''We cannot live on rhetoric and criticism, but we have to give our own constructive contribution.''</p>
        <p>The memorandum drew fierce protests from other Serbs, nearly every Kosovo Albanian party and the government of neighboring Albania.</p>
        <p>Hashim Thaci, once the leader of the Kosovo Liberation Army and now head of the Democratic Party of Kosovo, himself withdrew from United Nations councils, at least ''temporarily,'' on July 4, just before attending a party at the American diplomatic mission here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thaci says the agreement, which he first read about in newspapers, ''opens the door'' to the partition of Kosovo into separate ethnic enclaves. What bothers him most, his aides say, is not Gracanica and its Serbs, but partitioned Mitrovica, which is divided into a Serbian-dominated north and an Albanian-dominated south and where the Ibar River still marks the effective beginning of Serbia proper, though the actual border is further north.</p>
        <p>Mitrovica remains a neuralgic point for Albanians. Mr. Thaci's aides say Mr. Kouchner and the NATO officers who lead the peacekeeping force here may mean well but are naive and open to Serbian manipulation.</p>
        <p>Indeed, United Nations and NATO officials admit privately that it is less and less likely that the West will act forcefully to end the partition of Mitrovica, and therefore of Kosovo itself, because of the risk to alliance troops and the fear that such action would drive thousands more Serbs from the province.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement with Bishop Artemije, the United Nations promises to improve the safety and freedom of movement of Serbs by developing a special police task force for Serb enclaves; to get more Serbs, particularly those nominated by the bishop, into Kosovo's multiethnic police force; to promote the return of Serbs, find more Serbian and international judges to adjudicate crimes and disputes; and, crucially, to establish up to 20 ''local community offices'' in Serbian areas.</p>
        <p>Albanians criticize the special offices and arrangements for Kosovo Serbs, saying they undermine the principle of a unified and multiethnic Kosovo.</p>
        <p>But Father Sava points to Albanian attacks on Serbs that make enclaves necessary, and notes that if the United Nations and NATO peacekeepers do not deliver, the position of Gracanica's Serbs will be further undermined.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kouchner emphasizes that every institution is ultimately under his control. He admits that he did not consult Mr. Thaci or other Albanian leaders, saying he has always dealt with security issues as his responsibility.</p>
        <p>''Personally, I have always been on the side of those who suffer,'' Mr. Kouchner said. ''Earlier they were the Albanians, but now it is the Serbs and members of other communities.''</p>
        <p>An aide to Mr. Kouchner suggested that Mr. Thaci was losing popularity and needed to stand up to the United Nations, although he conceded there were deeper issues at stake. He noted that Ibrahim Rugova, the more moderate Albanian leader of the Democratic League of Kosovo, had not left the council.</p>
        <p>The aide predicted that the summer months, leading up to the first elections in postwar Kosovo, were likely to be marked by more violence, especially among the Albanian parties.</p>
        <p>Already Mr. Thaci's followers and those of Ramush Haradinaj, a former Kosovo Liberation Army commander who heads another rival party, the Alliance for the Future of Kosovo, have been attacking each other, as well as Mr. Rugova's followers.</p>
        <p>[In one such attack early Friday morning, Mr. Haradinaj and his brother were wounded in an exchange of fire with Rugova supporters in the village of Stroece, near Pec. Mr. Haradinaj, the third former K.L.A. leader attacked in recent weeks, was flown on Sunday to an American military hospital in Germany.]</p>
        <p>The continuing violence -- both intra-Albanian and interethnic -- has depressed United Nations workers who are struggling to build a new Kosovo with limited resources.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
