<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Editorial Observer; The Coming Backlash Against 'the Big Test'</title>
    <meta content="10MON4$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213934"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Scholastic Assessment Test</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mount Holyoke College</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Staples, Brent</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFDC1238F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Editorial Observer; The Coming Backlash Against 'the Big Test'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRENT STAPLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Staples, Brent</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brent Staples Editorial Observer column on decision by Mount Holyoke to drop requirement that applicants sumbit Scholastic Aptitude Test scores (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The national obsession with getting into a brand-name college has bled down into grade school, where children who have yet to reach puberty are biting their nails over the SAT. More than two million high school students will sit for the tests this year, after concerned parents have shelled out tens of millions of dollars for special preparation classes. In the frenzy of practice and preparation, students will ignore the carefully worded booklet from the College Board, which sponsors the tests. The booklet notes that the tests have nothing to do with innate intelligence -- suggesting that no such thing exists. Nor do they measure either what was learned in high school or motivation, creativity and special talents,  factors that affect success in college. The SAT is rather a test of mental dexterity, one element among many in predicting college performance.</p>
        <p>These caveats have always been true. Even so, the SAT was promoted as a sacred index that tells all about the individual. Real estate agents sell houses based on scores at nearby public schools. Educational rating services evaluate colleges based partly on average SAT scores. Bond-rating companies are said to take the scores into account when judging a college's creditworthiness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The national obsession with getting into a brand-name college has bled down into grade school, where children who have yet to reach puberty are biting their nails over the SAT. More than two million high school students will sit for the tests this year, after concerned parents have shelled out tens of millions of dollars for special preparation classes. In the frenzy of practice and preparation, students will ignore the carefully worded booklet from the College Board, which sponsors the tests. The booklet notes that the tests have nothing to do with innate intelligence -- suggesting that no such thing exists. Nor do they measure either what was learned in high school or motivation, creativity and special talents,  factors that affect success in college. The SAT is rather a test of mental dexterity, one element among many in predicting college performance.</p>
        <p>These caveats have always been true. Even so, the SAT was promoted as a sacred index that tells all about the individual. Real estate agents sell houses based on scores at nearby public schools. Educational rating services evaluate colleges based partly on average SAT scores. Bond-rating companies are said to take the scores into account when judging a college's creditworthiness.</p>
        <p>When the scores are mailed out this year, high school guidance offices will fill with anguished, tearful teenagers for whom disappointing results will seem a stain on their lives, if not the end of the world. These teenagers and their parents were the target audience when Mount Holyoke College in Massachusetts announced that prospective students would no longer be required to submit SAT scores with their applications. Over all, about 390 of the country's 1,800 four-year colleges and universities do not require the tests. But in discarding the SAT requirement, Mount Holyoke followed several other quality liberal-arts institutions, including Bates, Bowdoin, Bard and Connecticut College.</p>
        <p>Mount Holyoke had long since counted the test as no more than about 10 percent of the admission process, relying instead on high school transcripts, graded papers, letters of recommendation and an evaluation scheme that rates high schools in terms of academic rigor. A faculty committee at Holyoke concluded after several years of research and internal debate that the test should be optional. Holyoke's president, Joanne Creighton, was personally convinced by reading Nicholas Lemann's 1999 book, ''The Big Test: The Secret History of the American Meritocracy,'' which documents how the SAT became a tool for class segregation. Ms. Creighton describes Holyoke's decision as a way of saying that ''our process is individualized, rigorous and includes qualitative material'' -- and does not favor the rich, who can lay out large sums for test preparation.</p>
        <p>But this was also a marketing decision. In general, a school that drops the test requirement enjoys a surge of applications that allows it to remain highly selective, while attracting a stronger, more diverse student body. Holyoke is hoping to replicate what happened at Bates College in Maine, which has seen its application pool double since 1984, when SAT scores were no longer required. More than a quarter of Bates students come with no SAT scores. A study found that these Bates students had the same grade point averages and the same graduation rates as Bates students who submitted SAT scores, which raises profound doubts about why the tests are given such weight in the first place. ''These students say, 'I am not being accurately measured by these standardized tests,' '' said William Hiss, a vice president at Bates.</p>
        <p>''We misunderstand intelligence when we think of it as a unidimensional quality -- or in terms of the math and verbal scores on the SAT,'' Mr. Hiss said recently, adding that Bates seeks out students who have shown ''disciplined success'' in a variety of areas, including those who write exceptional application essays or who have made a definitive difference in their communities.</p>
        <p>The positive response from guidance and college communities suggests that Holyoke's decision could herald a backlash against the tyranny of the big test.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
