<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Zito's Albert the Great Pulls Surprise in Dwyer</title>
    <meta content="10RACI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dwyer Stakes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Durso, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E3DF1238F933A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="829" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Zito's Albert the Great Pulls Surprise in Dwyer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Durso, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Albert the Great wins Dwyer Stakes at Belmont Park in upset; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nick Zito's rookie star, Albert the Great, threw his hat into the ring for 3-year-old honors yesterday when he opened the second half of the racing season by outrunning three veterans of the Triple Crown and leading all the way to score a 3-length upset in the Dwyer Stakes at Belmont Park.</p>
        <p>Zito reasserted himself after his Triple Crown candidate Greenwood Lake was injured before the Kentucky Derby. And this was a trainer who won the Derby with Strike the Gold in 1991 and Go for Gin in 1994. But Zito bided his time, found a new runner in his barn -- a son of Go for Gin, at that -- and unleashed him yesterday in a four-horse field that included More Than Ready, fourth in the Derby; Red Bullet, winner of the Preakness; and Commendable, winner of the Belmont Stakes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nick Zito's rookie star, Albert the Great, threw his hat into the ring for 3-year-old honors yesterday when he opened the second half of the racing season by outrunning three veterans of the Triple Crown and leading all the way to score a 3-length upset in the Dwyer Stakes at Belmont Park.</p>
        <p>Zito reasserted himself after his Triple Crown candidate Greenwood Lake was injured before the Kentucky Derby. And this was a trainer who won the Derby with Strike the Gold in 1991 and Go for Gin in 1994. But Zito bided his time, found a new runner in his barn -- a son of Go for Gin, at that -- and unleashed him yesterday in a four-horse field that included More Than Ready, fourth in the Derby; Red Bullet, winner of the Preakness; and Commendable, winner of the Belmont Stakes.</p>
        <p>The only outsider was Albert the Great, who did not race as a juvenile but who won his previous three races this year while the others were competing in Triple Crown events. It was a rare lineup of classic winners and contenders, and they produced a rare result: Albert the Great first by 3 lengths, More Than Ready second by 1 3/4 lengths, Red Bullet third by half a length and Commendable last in a select field.</p>
        <p>''I'm ecstatic,'' said Zito, who had predicted that his colt would make a second-half impact in the race for the year's honors. ''It's the best feeling to be opening the second half of the season by getting back in the 3-year-old campaign.''</p>
        <p>The odds at post time reflected the unlikely mix of star horses and their stories. Red Bullet, who had not run since he won the Preakness almost two months ago, was the favorite at 3-5. More Than Ready, who had not run since finishing fourth in the Kentucky Derby two months ago, was next at 9-5. Commendable, who had not run since he won the Belmont four weeks ago, was a juicy 9-1. And Albert the Great, who had not run since he won an allowance at Belmont Park last month, was listed at 7-1 as he took the long stride upward into stakes racing in his eighth start.</p>
        <p>The principal absentee was Fusaichi Pegasus, winner of the Wood Memorial and the Kentucky Derby, who was widely rated the horse of the year until he sustained a minor foot injury and missed the Preakness and the Belmont. But his spirit, and his record, hung over the four horses as they raced to overtake him.</p>
        <p>''Now that it's over, you can come up with a million reasons why you won,'' Zito said. ''Red Bullet, coming off the Preakness win and having time off; Commendable, coming off the mile-and-a-half Belmont; and More Than Ready, coming off the Derby, all favored Albert. It takes an exceptional horse to come off allowance wins and beat those type of horses.''</p>
        <p>Richie Migliore, the rider on Albert the Great, reported that ''we bounced out of the gate perfectly,'' and added: ''He really has a smooth stride once he gets going. Nick and I talked before the race and figured we wanted to be outside because the rail was a little dead. Commendable came to me on the outside, but we pushed it out a notch. More Than Ready came up the inside of us, and my horse just took off. This colt is only going to get better.''</p>
        <p>Todd Pletcher, who trains More Than Ready, said, ''The winner came over on More Than Ready in the homestretch, but didn't make contact and he was clear.</p>
        <p>''For not having raced in two months, that was a good race for him. He beat the Preakness and Belmont winners, and he finished second.''</p>
        <p>Jerry Bailey, back to work after contending with a kidney stone last week, noted that Red Bullet ''flipped in the gate'' and ''he just didn't have anything.'' And Joe Orseno, who trains the colt for Frank Stronach, said Red Bullet was ''totally flat, and we'll have to rethink our plans.''</p>
        <p>But D. Wayne Lukas said his plans for Commendable had not changed: next is the Haskell at Monmouth Park on Aug. 6.</p>
        <p>''When you come off the Triple Crown,'' he said, ''you have to regroup for the second half of the season. You can't crank them up for every start.''</p>
        <p>Albert the Great ran the mile and a sixteenth in 1:42 3/5, paid $16 for a $2 bet to win and earned $90,000 for his arrival in the big leagues.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
