<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Dahl-Wolfe's Eye Created in a Lens</title>
    <meta content="06DRES$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205168"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fashion Institute of Technology</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellafante, Ginia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dahl-Wolfe, Louise</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E2DC173FF935A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1466" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Dahl-Wolfe's Eye Created in a Lens</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINIA BELLAFANTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Museum of Fashion Institute of Technology to present full-scale retrospective of work of late fashion photographer Louise Dahl-Wolfe; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Carmen Dell'Orefice was 15 and modeling to help her mother pay the rent on a Third Avenue walk-up, she made a visit to the 57th Street studio of Louise Dahl-Wolfe. At the time, 1946, Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe, 51, was in her 10th year as the reigning photographer at Harper's Bazaar and her umpteenth as a woman who looked like a home economics teacher at a girls' reform school.</p>
        <p>''She seemed ancient,'' Ms. Dell'Orefice recalled a few weeks ago. ''The first thing she said to me was, 'Your mother shouldn't let you wear makeup.' '' When Ms. Dell'Orefice answered that she wasn't wearing any, the photographer dragged her to a window and pinched her eyelashes for proof. Finally, Ms. Dell'Orefice was sent home on the grounds that she was too young to stand in front of a tripod for money, or at least too young for Bazaar's older readers. Not long after, she appeared on the cover of Vogue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Carmen Dell'Orefice was 15 and modeling to help her mother pay the rent on a Third Avenue walk-up, she made a visit to the 57th Street studio of Louise Dahl-Wolfe. At the time, 1946, Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe, 51, was in her 10th year as the reigning photographer at Harper's Bazaar and her umpteenth as a woman who looked like a home economics teacher at a girls' reform school.</p>
        <p>''She seemed ancient,'' Ms. Dell'Orefice recalled a few weeks ago. ''The first thing she said to me was, 'Your mother shouldn't let you wear makeup.' '' When Ms. Dell'Orefice answered that she wasn't wearing any, the photographer dragged her to a window and pinched her eyelashes for proof. Finally, Ms. Dell'Orefice was sent home on the grounds that she was too young to stand in front of a tripod for money, or at least too young for Bazaar's older readers. Not long after, she appeared on the cover of Vogue.</p>
        <p>Louise Dahl-Wolfe would see dozens of models rise and fall before she died 43 years later, in 1989, at 94. On June 12, the Museum of the Fashion Institute of Technology will present the first full-scale retrospective of her work, little of which points to the kind of benighted sensibility her behavior, and a hair bun slathered with beeswax, might have led one to expect.</p>
        <p>Curated by Irving Solero and Nan Richardson, the exhibition will run through Aug. 12 and move to the Center for Creative Photography in Tucson in September. A companion book by Ms. Richardson, ''Louise Dahl-Wolfe: A Retrospective,'' is due from Harry N. Abrams this summer. Some of Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe's black-and-white images are on view at the Staley-Wise gallery.</p>
        <p>During her time at Bazaar, a 22-year tenure that ended when she quit in 1958, after the magazine's editor, Carmel Snow, and the legendary art director Alexey Brodovitch both resigned, Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe chronicled the birth of a looser, less pinched spirit in American fashion. With Diana Vreeland as her fashion editor, Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe traveled around the world, shooting that new concept, sportswear, out of doors where it comfortably breathed. Before the triumvirate of Mrs. Snow, Mrs. Vreeland and Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe, American style, as Richard Avedon has put it, did not exist.</p>
        <p>''Louise has a pivotal role moving fashion photography out of formal studio work into a portrayal of the active, modern American woman,'' Amy Rule, an archivist at the Center for Creative Photography, said.</p>
        <p>Other photographers, like Martin Munkacsi and Toni Frissell, were already capturing the new mood, but Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe distinguished herself with images that implied a languorous sexuality. She often photographed models on the beach, in repose, their eyes closed or averted, their bodies positioned -- trapped -- rigidly in the frame. Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe seemed to realize that new sportswear by Claire McCardell and Bonnie Cashin offered women the semblance of an unconstricted life, not the real freedom that only a challenge to accepted social arrangements could bring.</p>
        <p>The daughter of a Norwegian marine engineer, Louise Dahl was born in San Francisco in 1895 and showed no tendencies during her young womanhood to live within the narrow corridor of risk laid out for her sex. After studying art in San Francisco, she moved to New York to take classes in architecture and design. In 1927, she embarked on a tour of Europe with her friend Consuela Kanaga, a news photographer. A year went by, and when the women were bored with the Continent they headed for North Africa.</p>
        <p>It was on a train platform in Tunisia in 1928 that Miss Dahl, 32, spotted her future husband, a sculptor from Tennessee named Meyer Wolfe. ''She saw him,'' Irving Solero, who befriended Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe in 1978, recalled, ''and said, 'That's for me.' '' The two married that same year.</p>
        <p>Without fail, those who knew Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe remark on the intense bond she and her husband shared. ''They lived together nonstop, 24 hours a day,'' said Mr. Solero, who spent time with the couple in their Frenchtown, N.J., home, known as the Creamery. ''They fought all the time, but a fight would erupt for five seconds and then it was over.'' Mr. Wolfe would travel with his wife, typically picking her up for lunch during out-of-town shoots.</p>
        <p>''When he died at 88 she was self-abandoned,'' Mary Jane Russell, a friend and favorite model of Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe's, said recently. ''Her mourning was coupled with anger: 'How could he have left me? Why couldn't I be first?' ''</p>
        <p>While she was close to Mrs. Russell, her relationships with others in the Harper's Bazaar orbit were more complex. Well into the 70's and 80's, Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe would talk about her former colleague Mr. Avedon ''as though he were a kid,'' Mr. Solero said, adding, ''She'd say, 'He has a long way to go.' ''</p>
        <p>Lillian Bassman, whose impressionistic photographs began appearing in Bazaar around 1950, said that Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe repeatedly tried to have her fired. In the mid-40's, when Ms. Bassman was still working in the magazine's art department as an apprentice, Carmel Snow sent her to Paris to try to find photographers who had worked for Bazaar before the war. Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe was so irritated at the prospect of competition, Ms. Bassman said, that she complained to Mrs. Snow that the art-director-in-training had been maligning her. Mrs. Snow swiftly dispatched Ms. Bassman to the country and out of the way. ''It was a testimony to Louise's stature at the magazine,'' Ms. Bassman said. After that, their relationship was ''a mess,'' she added.</p>
        <p>With underlings in the fashion department, Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe often played the taskmaster. Some 50 years ago, the fashion editor Polly Mellen traveled to Jamaica with Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe for a shoot and recalled waking up every morning at 4:30 to braid the hair that would eventually be cranked into the photographer's signature bun. ''In my growing years, she was one of the few people who really formed me,'' Ms. Mellen said. ''She taught me extreme discipline.'' And demonstrated a certain largesse as well. When Ms. Mellen left Bazaar to marry in 1952, Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe gave her a going-away party and took her wedding pictures. ''If she was on your side, you were most fortunate,'' Ms. Mellen said.</p>
        <p>After Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe left Bazaar, she worked briefly for Vogue before relinquishing photography in 1960, saying that advertisers had gained too much influence over magazines. But however frustrated she had become with what she saw as the commercialization of magazines, she was never the sort who demanded that some notion of artistic vision take precedence over the business of showing off clothes. One hallmark of her thousands of published images, 86 Bazaar covers among them, is that the gowns and bathing suits and ski clothes are always visible front and center. ''She worked for the magazine because she showed the frocks,'' said Martin Harrison, a curator and historian of photography. ''The models were good-looking, and it was a great time for American fashion.''</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Harrison, a detractor, admits that Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe had a talent for color. In her effort to show garments to their best advantage, she would typically go to the printing press where Bazaar was churned out and nudge engravers to change a blue backdrop to, say, a yellow one if it made a dress look better. ''It was almost as if she were a set designer,'' said Christopher Greene, who produced prints from Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe's negatives late in her life.</p>
        <p>While Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe might flinch at the sort of images that today fill the pages of avant-garde fashion magazines like Dazed and Confused, the striking, saturated colors that are their trademark hark back, in some sense, to her. Before the rise of digital technology, it was impossible to reproduce prints from Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe's Kodachromes that resembled what appeared on the printed page.</p>
        <p>That is one reason, said Ms. Richardson, the Fashion Institute curator, that a coffee-table book of her work has never been published before.</p>
        <p>Another is that Mrs. Dahl-Wolfe always thought the notion rather flashy and pretentious.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
