<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Man Charged With Forgery in E-Mail Scheme</title>
    <meta content="06SPAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forgery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Market Vision Studios</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garon, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E1DB173FF935A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Man Charged With Forgery in E-Mail Scheme</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS, June 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Westchester County (NY) grand jury indicts Jason Garon on charges of forgery and computer tampering, saying that he crashed computer system of Market Vision Studios by using it to relay tens of thousands of e-mails offering pornography and get-rich quick schemes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Westchester County grand jury indicted a California man today on charges of forgery and computer tampering, saying that he crashed the computer system of an Irvington-based computer design company by using it to relay tens of thousands of e-mails offering pornography and get-rich-quick schemes.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said they hoped that forgery charges would become a new weapon in the fight against junk e-mail, but some legal experts are questioning the tactic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Westchester County grand jury indicted a California man today on charges of forgery and computer tampering, saying that he crashed the computer system of an Irvington-based computer design company by using it to relay tens of thousands of e-mails offering pornography and get-rich-quick schemes.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said they hoped that forgery charges would become a new weapon in the fight against junk e-mail, but some legal experts are questioning the tactic.</p>
        <p>The man, Jason Garon, 46, of Mission Viejo, Calif., was arraigned in Westchester County Court by Judge Mary H. Smith. Prosecutors contend that the flurry of Mr. Garon's e-mail, known in computer jargon as spam, were forgeries because the return addresses were fake.</p>
        <p>''E-mail is a written instrument,'' said Jeanine F. Pirro, the Westchester County district attorney. ''These e-mails were disguised to look as if they came from a legitimate company, in this case I.B.M., when in fact our investigation showed that the source of these e-mails was Mr. Garon's residence. This establishes a forgery.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Garon pleaded not guilty at today's arraignment. ''Our position is that no crime was committed,'' said Bruce B. Bendish, Mr. Garon's lawyer.</p>
        <p>Cyberlaw experts are currently debating whether or not junk e-mail can be considered forgery.</p>
        <p>''There is no way this is second-degree forgery,'' said Mark D. Rasch, vice president for cyberlaw at the Global Integrity Corporation, a computer security consulting firm in Reston, Va., and the former head of the United States Justice Department's computer crime unit.</p>
        <p>''Frankly, if this is forgery then everybody who uses an anonymous e-mail address is committing a felony,'' Mr. Rasch said. ''When you take traditional legal concepts and apply them to the Internet, it is not a good fit. The laws were not written to deal with this conduct. If you want to make it a crime, then write a statute. It is not the responsibility of the prosecutor to do that. It is the responsibility of the legislature to create a law after much public debate.''</p>
        <p>Junk e-mail can be an expensive problem for businesses, particularly Internet service providers, who say that seven percent of their customers change providers annually in order to get a new spam-free e-mail address, according to Sunil Paul, the chairman of Brightmail, a San Francisco company that makes anti-spam software.</p>
        <p>In this case, Edward L. Greenberg, president of Market Vision Studios in Irvington, said his business lost $18,000 in three days in September 1998 when his computer system was filled with junk e-mail that was then relayed to tens of thousands of other computers with his company's name attached to it.</p>
        <p>''I called AOL and they wouldn't talk to me because they thought we were sending the e-mail,'' Mr. Greenberg said. ''Then I called the police, and to my surprise, they knew what we were talking about. Two days later, the district attorney was involved and I.B.M. was involved and a whole investigation was under way.''</p>
        <p>So far 11 states have passed laws against spamming, Mr. Paul said, but the laws are not much of a deterrent because the e-mailers can easily move to another state or country. The payoff can be big.</p>
        <p>''The key to spamming is that it costs just about nothing to do,'' Mr. Paul said. ''For less than $1,000 you can buy the software that puts false headers on a document, buy e-mail lists and send out a million e-mails. Then they sit back and get paid per click.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Pirro said that Mr. Garon, who was running his business from his home computer, had $1 million in offshore bank accounts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
