<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unearthing Dinosaurs, Undoing Stereotypes</title>
    <meta content="06PROF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205263"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">MARK A. NORELL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Museum of Natural History (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wadler, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norell, Mark A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E1DE143FF935A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unearthing Dinosaurs, Undoing Stereotypes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE WADLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wadler, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column on career of Mark A Norell, paleontologist who has put together Fighting Dinosaurs exhibit at American Museum of National History; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MARK A. NORELL, the groovy paleontologist who has put together the ''Fighting Dinosaurs'' exhibit at the American Museum of National History, has his back turned and is answering his e-mail when visitors are brought around, and though he's already a little late for the interview, he stays with the computer for 5 to 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>What is time when you have unearthed dinosaur fossils 80 million years old?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MARK A. NORELL, the groovy paleontologist who has put together the ''Fighting Dinosaurs'' exhibit at the American Museum of National History, has his back turned and is answering his e-mail when visitors are brought around, and though he's already a little late for the interview, he stays with the computer for 5 to 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>What is time when you have unearthed dinosaur fossils 80 million years old?</p>
        <p>Anyway, if you are in the process of killing it, there are worse places to do so than the office of Dr. Norell.</p>
        <p>Rock 'n' roll, in this case Marc Bolan, is playing at appropriate rock 'n' roll volume, which is to say loud; the large, sun-drenched office, with its tall grimy windows overlooking Central Park West, is scattered with dinosaur bones -- props, Dr. Norell will say later, for television shoots. For some reason people expect a paleontologist to have dinosaurs around. On the wall next to Dr. Norell's desk there is a framed magazine cover of Sports Afield, with a photo of a long-haired fellow in filthy T-shirt and blue jeans leaping in the air, screaming.</p>
        <p>''Secrets of the Wildman,'' the cover line reads.</p>
        <p>As Dr. Norell's face is still covered by a curtain of hair, one has to ask the question: The wildman on the cover -- you?</p>
        <p>''Yes,'' says Dr. Norell, emerging from computer space, in chinos and a black T-shirt.</p>
        <p>You sure don't look like the tweedy academic one expects to find as head of the department.</p>
        <p>Acquiescence from the man who chairs the museum's Division of Paleontology and who specializes in research on the evolutionary relationship between small meat-eating dinosaurs and present-day birds.</p>
        <p>''That's an attitude I don't like to participate in or perpetuate,'' he says.</p>
        <p>''Fighting Dinosaurs: New Discoveries from Mongolia,'' features fossils which have never before been seen in North America. The two dinosaurs from which the exhibit takes its name, a Protoceratops and a Velociraptor, appear to have died locked in combat, probably in an avalanche of sand. They were discovered in 1971 by a Mongolian-Polish expedition. During the period, Mongolia, under Soviet domination, was closed to the West.</p>
        <p>A number of other important fossils, however, were found by teams of researchers from the Museum of Natural History and the Mongolian Academy of Sciences, in a program that began in 1990.</p>
        <p>Dr. Norell, 42, who tends to speak science, however fond he is of rock 'n' roll, has been in the field, in the Gobi Desert of Mongolia, almost every year since since the program started. (He took off only in 1996, the year his daughter was born.) He and his team discovered the Ukhaa Tolgood fossil field, which is considered to be the richest vertebrate site in the world. ''Somewhat larger than the footprint of the museum,'' is how Dr. Norell describes it, when asked its size. He also discovered Mononykus (a small, bird-like specimen),  the first embryo of a meat-eating dinosaur and a nesting Oviraptor. He has written 64 technical papers and a number of popular books on dinosaurs.</p>
        <p>IT was Dr. Norell's no-frills camping ability in the Gobi desert, however, that made him the cover boy for Sports Afield and the hero of a piece on ''dirtbag camping.'' In that story it was revealed that Dr. Norell, in a five-week research expedition, changed clothes once and bathed twice. ''I bring stuff I can wear and dispose of,'' Dr. Norell says. ''A ripped and trashed T-shirt with a little gasoline on it starts a pretty good campfire.''</p>
        <p>Even so, Dr. Norell does not stint on food. On expedition, he does much of the cooking and the food, if he says so himself, has been pretty good: cassoulet, pizza, even sushi. Sushi isn't tough: You just use vacuum packed eel, shrimp and seaweed, and cook up some rice.</p>
        <p>There were times last summer when the temperature hit 120 degrees. ''If people are going to work under extreme situations, they have to be having a good time,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Dr. Norell was born in St. Paul, but his home, geographically and spiritually, is Southern California, where he lived from the time he was in third grade. His father was an architectural engineer, his mother a housewife who later became involved in volunteer work, but both parents were interested in science. Copies of National Geographic and Scientific American were around the house, and his father did volunteer work for archeologist friends. Dr. Norell has memories of him working up renderings of Mayan ruins. In high school he went on expeditions in Mexico.</p>
        <p>Dr. Norell has an undergraduate degree in zoology from the California State University at Long Beach; a master's in biology from San Diego State, and a Ph.D. in biology from Yale.</p>
        <p>Ask him the snob Eastern question -- why do Cal State when he might very well have gotten an undergraduate degree in Yale? -- and he gives you an answer that's equal parts science and lifestyle. He wanted to do ''creative research'' and was willing to give up an ''elite'' eastern school  to live in La Jolla, hang out at the beach and commute in shorts.</p>
        <p>He has that freedom. He has spent 5 to 13 weeks away on expedition, is just back from China, will leave at the end of June for two months in Mongolia. His birthday has often been spent in the desert. With, of course, Champagne.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
