<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peace Across the Hudson</title>
    <meta content="06TUE1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205209"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Port Authority of New York and New Jersey</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E1D8173FF935A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="541" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peace Across the Hudson</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial praises accord between New York and New Jersey ending 18-month stalemate over Port Authority's subsidies and projects; says agreement is welcome stewp, but that much more thinking is needed to revitalize authority as engine of economic growth (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The biggest network of airports, train lines, bus terminals and port facilities in the New York region is run by one giant agency, the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey. Last week, Gov. George Pataki and Gov. Christine Todd Whitman reached an important agreement to end a fight over distribution of the authority's subsidies and projects. The accord, which ends 18 months of paralysis, grants Mr. Pataki's request for more resources spent in New York. It was a welcome step, but much more thinking is needed to revitalize the authority as an engine of economic growth.</p>
        <p>The authority runs some operations that are profitable and others that lose money. Its stated goal has always been to mix burdens and benefits in a way that is fair to both sides. Since World War II, however, it has made sense for both states to allow shipping terminals to move to New Jersey, where there are better links to the continental United States and more room for container operations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The biggest network of airports, train lines, bus terminals and port facilities in the New York region is run by one giant agency, the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey. Last week, Gov. George Pataki and Gov. Christine Todd Whitman reached an important agreement to end a fight over distribution of the authority's subsidies and projects. The accord, which ends 18 months of paralysis, grants Mr. Pataki's request for more resources spent in New York. It was a welcome step, but much more thinking is needed to revitalize the authority as an engine of economic growth.</p>
        <p>The authority runs some operations that are profitable and others that lose money. Its stated goal has always been to mix burdens and benefits in a way that is fair to both sides. Since World War II, however, it has made sense for both states to allow shipping terminals to move to New Jersey, where there are better links to the continental United States and more room for container operations.</p>
        <p>New York still gains from being the site of many businesses that serve the shipping industry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki has cried foul, however, as New Jersey also got the benefits of a new airport at Newark. In addition, the authority subsidizes the PATH lines and buses, enabling New Jersey commuters to pay lower fares than their counterparts on New York City's subways and buses.</p>
        <p>The accord announced last week will restore some balance. For New Jersey, it approves a 30-year lease at Elizabeth Marine Terminal to the Maersk-Sealand container shipping company, which was threatening to go to Baltimore or Halifax. The authority will spend $575 million over 30 years to deepen the channel and make other improvements. But New Jersey commuters will also have to pay more in bus and subway fares.</p>
        <p>New York is to gain by being able to sell or privatize the World Trade Center, sell air rights over the Port Authority Bus Terminal in Manhattan and embark on several beneficial projects. One could lead to a nonstop transit ride to Kennedy Airport, while another would help build a new Penn Station at the post office building on 34th Street.</p>
        <p>New Yorkers should not give up on the Port Authority, as Mayor Rudolph Giuliani has with his effort to take over operations of Kennedy and La Guardia Airports. Instead of balkanizing the authority, its resources should be spread to benefit everyone. In the years ahead, the authority can do much to help commuters in New York. One positive step would be for the authority to help extend the No. 7 line from Grand Central to Pennsylvania Station and the Hudson River, where it could provide a link from Queens to the New Jersey transit lines and spur economic growth on Manhattan's West Side.</p>
        <p>Nearly 80 years ago, the Port Authority's creation was hailed as a landmark in regional cooperation. It is time to look beyond the spoils and get back to a vision as valid today as it was back then.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
