<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Him. Them. Us. Vote.</title>
    <meta content="06GREE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000610T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenfield, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E0DD173FF935A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Him. Them. Us. Vote.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jeff Greenfield</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenfield, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by television commentator Jeff Greenfield on tenor and dynamics of 2000 presidential campaign between Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Al Gore. George Bush. Two candidates. Four syllables. That's the choice. Coincidence? Uh-uh. Those four syllables speak volumes. Not about them. About us. About what's happened. What's happened to our politics. What's happened to our attention span.</p>
        <p>Once it took more than four guttural grunts to list America's choices. In 1900, Americans chose among William Jennings Bryan, William McKinley and Eugene Victor Debs. The names rolled slowly off the tongue, lingered for a moment in the air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Al Gore. George Bush. Two candidates. Four syllables. That's the choice. Coincidence? Uh-uh. Those four syllables speak volumes. Not about them. About us. About what's happened. What's happened to our politics. What's happened to our attention span.</p>
        <p>Once it took more than four guttural grunts to list America's choices. In 1900, Americans chose among William Jennings Bryan, William McKinley and Eugene Victor Debs. The names rolled slowly off the tongue, lingered for a moment in the air.</p>
        <p>Those were the days when we wrote lengthy epistles to each other, not e-mails spattered with acronyms. It was a more reflective time, a time when we had the patience to pause and listen to the name of a multisyllabic officeseeker. And so it was through most of the century: indeed, a high point was reached in 1952, when Dwight Eisenhower defeated Adlai Stevenson -- a 10-syllable battle, even without middle initials. (Eisenhower also holds the distinction of having the most unusual last name of any president, thus proving that if you win a world war, you need hold neither previous political office nor an easily accessible name).</p>
        <p>By the century's close, the inexorable erosion of the American attention span had slammed full force into our political campaigns. The half-hour speeches had long since been replaced by the 30-second commercial. The network news had cut the average sound bites of the major candidates from about 50 seconds in 1968 to barely 9 in 1988. (Had Franklin Roosevelt been running that year, his most famous utterance would have been reported: ''The only thing we have to fear is fuhhhh--'') It was only a matter of time before the candidates themselves would be judged, however subconsciously, on how quickly the voters could absorb their names.</p>
        <p>Once Michael Dukakis crashed and burned in '88 -- ''I don't even know how to say his name!'' one of George Bush's country-western singer supporters had declared that year -- the die was cast. In 1992, Bill Clinton, Bob Dole and Ross Perot combined had a shorter syllable count than Adlai and Ike. In 1996, with Mr. Perot shunted to the sidelines, Mr. Clinton and Mr. Dole produced a grand total of five.</p>
        <p>The situation is even more dramatic when we fold in the running mates. In 1844, Henry Clay could choose a running mate so syllabically endowed that their campaign song became a classic: ''Hurray! Hurray! The country is a-rising!/Hurray! Hurray! For Clay and Freylinghausen!''  And in that landmark year of 1952, Stevenson had no qualms about running with Estes Kefauver.</p>
        <p>By contrast, what have we been offered in recent tickets? In 1992, Clinton-Gore defeated Bush-Quayle. Four years ago, Clinton-Gore beat Dole-Kemp. And this year, some of the likeliest possibilities sound more like a series of Cro-Magnon grunts than a ticket: Bush-Ridge; Gore-Graham; Bush-Dole. (Memo to Pataki and Lieberman: Don't hold your breath).</p>
        <p>The next step? Since it's widely believed that politics is mostly show business, let future candidates take their cue from that universe: single-name candidates. In fact, short-single-name candidates. We're not talking Coolio or Madonna. We're not even talking Donahue or Oprah. We're talking Cher. We're talking Prince.</p>
        <p>Jeff Greenfield, a senior analyst at CNN, is author of the forthcoming novel ''Jackpot.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 10, 2000, Saturday  An article on Tuesday by Jeff Greenfield incorrectly identified Adlai Stevenson's running mate in the 1952 presidential election; it was John Sparkman, not Estes Kefauver. The article also misspelled the last name of Henry Clay's running mate in the 1844 presidential election; it is Frelinghuysen, not Freylinghausen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 10, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Tuesday by Jeff Greenfield incorrectly identified Adlai Stevenson's running mate in the 1952 presidential election; it was John Sparkman, not Estes Kefauver. The article also misspelled the last name of Henry Clay's running mate in the 1844 presidential election; it is Frelinghuysen, not Freylinghausen.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jeff Greenfield, a senior analyst at CNN, is author of the forthcoming novel ''Jackpot.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
