<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Briefing</title>
    <meta content="06MBRF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205219"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E2D7173FF935A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>TRENTON: SCHOOL FINANCING BILL  The State Assembly passed a bill yesterday to provide complete state financing for construction projects in poor school districts. The legislation was in response to the Supreme Court's spring deadline for providing full state financing to replace or repair school buildings in needy districts. Most Democrats opposed the bill because of amendments that enforce spending limits and require all construction plans to be reviewed by the Legislature.</p>
        <p>Kushanava Choudhury (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>TRENTON: SCHOOL FINANCING BILL  The State Assembly passed a bill yesterday to provide complete state financing for construction projects in poor school districts. The legislation was in response to the Supreme Court's spring deadline for providing full state financing to replace or repair school buildings in needy districts. Most Democrats opposed the bill because of amendments that enforce spending limits and require all construction plans to be reviewed by the Legislature.</p>
        <p>Kushanava Choudhury (NYT)</p>
        <p>PATERSON: BOY DIES IN FIRE  An 8-year-old handicapped boy breathing with the help of an oxygen tank was killed when flames filled his bedroom in a three-family house around 1:30 a.m. yesterday. The mother of the victim, Brian Artis, safely led her 4-year-old daughter from the burning room, but flames prevented her from returning to get her son, the authorities said. The cause of the fire is under investigation.</p>
        <p>Robert Hanley (NYT)</p>
        <p>PATERSON: MOTHER CHARGED  A 17-year-old Paterson mother was charged yesterday with murdering her 15-month-old son and throwing his body into the Passaic River Saturday night about a half mile upstream of the Great Falls, the authorities said. Divers searched the river yesterday without finding the body, said the Passaic County first assistant prosecutor, Boris Moczula. Citing juvenile confidentiality laws, Mr. Moczula declined to identify the girl.</p>
        <p>Robert Hanley (NYT)</p>
        <p>ROXBURY: OFFICERS HURT  Newark's police chief and seven other people were injured, one seriously, on Sunday when the two boats they were using collided on Lake Hopatcong. The officers were off duty. The chief, Anthony Ambrose, 41, of East Hanover, was hurt when his boat was struck from behind by a boat piloted by Officer Joseph Watson 3rd, 37, of Union, said John Hagerty, a state police spokesman. Mr. Hagerty said that an officer's wife, Stella Muscarella, 43, who was in the first boat, was the most seriously injured, suffering eight broken ribs.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: CHARGES DROPPED  Assault charges were dropped yesterday against the former New York Knick Anthony Mason, his cousin and three friends after Manhattan prosecutors said they did not have enough evidence to prove that the men had participated in a brawl at a Harlem bar in February. Mr. Mason, who now plays for the Charlotte Hornets, and the other men had been charged with third-degree assault after three people were injured during a brawl at a bar called Perk's. His lawyer, Don Cronson, said that Mr. Mason had only defended himself.  Katherine E. Finkelstein (NYT)</p>
        <p>ALBANY: POLICE LEGISLATION  Responding to recent police shootings of unarmed civilians, the Assembly yesterday passed a series of bills on police accountability. One bill would allow New York City to require that its officers live in the city, another would mandate drug and alcohol testing for any officer who fires a gun on duty, and a third would send police misconduct cases to the state attorney general instead of to local prosecutors. Relatives of Amadou Diallo, Patrick Dorismond and others killed by officers urged the Senate and Gov. George E. Pataki to support the legislation.</p>
        <p>Richard Perez-Pena (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: ANTI-N.R.A. VOTE  The City Council adopted a resolution yesterday urging the National Rifle Association to abandon plans for a theme restaurant and game arcade in Times Square. Stephen DiBrienza, left, a sponsor of the resolution, said that the council had no power to stop the N.R.A. but that the vote at least expressed the idea that the restaurant was considered ''outrageous.'' William Powers, a spokesman for the N.R.A., said: 'What if the City Council decided they didn't like basketball? It's political correctness run amok.''</p>
        <p>Elisabeth Bumiller (NYT)</p>
        <p>WALTON: BACTERIA INQUIRY  State and federal food officials are searching for the source of E. coli that contaminated some of the cottage cheese made in a Kraft Foods plant. The municipal water system that serves the plant in the town of Walton, 80 miles southeast of Syracuse, has been ruled out as a source. Kraft has recalled 1,100 cases of six products, but no illnesses linked to the Kraft plant have been reported.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>BRENTWOOD: SON IS KILLED  A man attacked his sons -- killing one of them -- when they refused to say where his wife had been living since leaving him, the Suffolk County police said. The man, Carlos Barrientos, 43, confronted his sons early yesterday with a shotgun, said Detective Lt. John Gierasch. The sons locked themselves in a bedroom, but their father fired at the door, killing his son John, 21. The other son, Richard, struggled with his father over a knife, the police said. Richard Barrientos, whose age was not known, was in stable condition at Southside Hospital in Bay Shore.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>BRIDGEPORT: CASE GOES TO JURY  A jury began deliberations yesterday in the trial of Russell Peeler, who is  accused of ordering the murders of an 8-year-old boy and his mother. The boy, Leroy Brown Jr., and his mother, Karen Clarke, were shot in their home on Jan. 7, 1999. The child had been scheduled to testify against Mr. Peeler in another murder case. Prosecutors say Russell Peeler, 28, asked his younger brother, Adrian, 25, to kill the woman and boy. Adrian Peeler will stand trial later. Both brothers face the possibility of the death penalty if convicted.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW HAVEN: UNION ELECTION  Despite being fired for alleged incompetence, a city teacher is in the running to be president of the union representing 1,400 city teachers. The teacher, Joseph A. Samela, was fired April 26 after the Board of Education cited a pattern of teaching incompetence and other policy violations. Samela is considered an active union member as long as he is appealing the termination and can possibly be recalled to his job. The union had been looking into whether Mr. Samela was eligible to run as an independent after he nominated himself during a membership convention May 17.  (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
