<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Justice Dept. Rejects Big Changes in Its Breakup Plan for Microsoft</title>
    <meta content="Y06SOFT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205189"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brinkley, Joel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Thomas Penfield (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0DA173FF935A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="693" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Justice Dept. Rejects Big Changes in Its Breakup Plan for Microsoft</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL BRINKLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brinkley, Joel</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Justice Department responds in detail to Microsoft Corp's criticisms of its plan to break up the computer software giant; rejects any changes in its proposal, noting that most of the company's proposed revisions 'would undermine or frustrate the purpose and effectiveness' of the remedy; Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson has postponed his final ruling to allow two additional filings, including today's filing by Justice Department (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Responding in detail to Microsoft's criticisms, the Justice Department today rejected any substantive changes in its plan to break up the company.</p>
        <p>Most of the company's proposed revisions ''would undermine or frustrate the purpose and effectiveness'' of the remedy proposal, the government said in a brief filed with the judge in the long-running antitrust trial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Responding in detail to Microsoft's criticisms, the Justice Department today rejected any substantive changes in its plan to break up the company.</p>
        <p>Most of the company's proposed revisions ''would undermine or frustrate the purpose and effectiveness'' of the remedy proposal, the government said in a brief filed with the judge in the long-running antitrust trial.</p>
        <p>After Microsoft filed its proposal last week to water down the government plan -- while still disputing its very premise -- the Justice Department and 19 state governments that are partners in the antitrust suit asked for a chance to respond. As a result, Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson postponed his final ruling, expected at the end of last week, and scheduled two additional filings, including the government document issued today.</p>
        <p>Microsoft now has until Wednesday to respond, and Judge Jackson will probably rule late this week. He is widely expected to accept the government's breakup plan.</p>
        <p>Jim Cullinan, a Microsoft spokesman, said the government brief makes ''only cosmetic changes'' and therefore remains ''vague and ambiguous as well as excessive and harmful to consumers and the industry.''</p>
        <p>The government filing today notes that Microsoft had asked Judge Jackson in court on May 24 for an opportunity to comment on ''the form'' of the government's remedy proposal. But ''many of Microsoft's comments go beyond merely addressing the proposed form'' and ''make arguments about the merits that Microsoft has previously raised and that plaintiffs have addressed in their prior filings,'' the brief states.</p>
        <p>It also notes that Microsoft, in its proposed revisions, repeatedly tried to reargue the facts of the case, even though Judge Jackson issued a final ruling on April 3 declaring Microsoft in wide violation of state and federal antitrust laws. ''Microsoft's effort to reargue its position should be rejected,'' the brief says.</p>
        <p>The document lists the few Microsoft revisions the government is willing to accept. Most deal with punctuation or semantics. For example, Microsoft heatedly objected to the government's characterization of the breakup plan as a ''reorganization.'' A Microsoft spokesman, Mark Murray, said, ''That's like saying, when a tornado hits a house, it's a spring cleaning.''</p>
        <p>As a result, the government agreed to call the breakup a ''divestiture.'' The other changes are of about the same magnitude.</p>
        <p>As for the rest of Microsoft's proposed changes, the government argues that they ''would create loopholes and permit Microsoft to continue to engage in anti-competitive practices.''</p>
        <p>For example, the company had objected to the date when its intellectual property holdings would be considered allocated to specific divisions for purposes of any breakup. The government had set the date at April 27, the day before its remedy proposal was published, to prevent Microsoft from changing plans once it knew the specifics of the government's proposal. Microsoft wanted the date moved forward. But today's brief says: ''Microsoft's proposal would allow the company to shift assets before the plan of divestiture is implemented to frustrate the effectiveness of the final judgement.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, the company, in its revision, struck out a provision requiring Microsoft to inform computer manufacturers -- known as original equipment manufacturers, or O.E.M.'s --  of future plans for Microsoft products. Today the government said: ''The proposed change would allow Microsoft to withhold critical information about its future plans from certain O.E.M.'s in retaliation for their supporting non-Microsoft products, an O.E.M. concern that was expressed at trial.''</p>
        <p>Microsoft tried to write the state attorneys general out of the case during enforcement of the remedy. The government rejected that.</p>
        <p>The government also turned back Microsoft's proposal to delay preparation of a plan for carrying out the breakup for a year instead of four months, as the plaintiffs had proposed.</p>
        <p>''It is in the public interest that the remedy contemplated by the final judgment be implemented as soon as possible,'' the government said, ''and the time periods proposed by plaintiffs are adequate to perform the specified tasks.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
