<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Demographics on Ice: N.H.L. and Television Fail</title>
    <meta content="06SAND$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205274"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6DD143FF935A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="968" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Demographics on Ice: N.H.L. and Television Fail</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>TV Sports column discusses low television ratings of National Hockey League Stanley Cup playoffs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You wonder if the concept will kick in, if the fantasy of the National Hockey League attracting a broad TV viewership will ever come true.</p>
        <p>You hear the league talk about its Sun Belt strategy, youngsters playing roller hockey and a 28-team confederation expanding to a 30-franchise national footprint next season. (Adding Columbus, the nation's No. 34 market, will surely make all the difference!)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You wonder if the concept will kick in, if the fantasy of the National Hockey League attracting a broad TV viewership will ever come true.</p>
        <p>You hear the league talk about its Sun Belt strategy, youngsters playing roller hockey and a 28-team confederation expanding to a 30-franchise national footprint next season. (Adding Columbus, the nation's No. 34 market, will surely make all the difference!)</p>
        <p>You also hear about improving male demographics on ESPN and ABC, and yes, they are higher. But when your hold on young males starts at a minuscule level, a two-tenths-of-a-point increase amounts to a big leap up to Tinyville.</p>
        <p>Regardless of the quality of the Devils-Dallas Stanley Cup finals, cross-promotion between ESPN and ABC and the synergy of ABC rerunning ''The Mighty Ducks'' Sunday night, N.H.L. ratings remain unimpressive. The ESPN-ABC marketing machine that was to churn out ratings and profits, as predicted two years ago, needs more oil.</p>
        <p>The ratings are so unimpressive that the wisdom of the five-year, $600 million ESPN-ABC deal, questionable when it was signed in 1998, must still be questioned. But you can't blame the N.H.L. for taking the money and giggling. As Gary Bettman, the N.H.L. commissioner, said at the time, ''I didn't attend the negotiations wearing a mask and a gun.''</p>
        <p>Five seasons on Fox -- the league's first United States network exposure in two decades for only $31 million a year -- didn't make the N.H.L. more than a sport best suited to cable. There is nothing wrong with that; clearly the ABC-ESPN deal was made to preserve ESPN and ESPN2's tight grip on hockey. But implicit in spending $120 million a year was the belief that hockey was within reach of some kind of broadcast breakout.</p>
        <p>That clearly seems a long shot, especially considering the ratings for Saturday night's Game 3. It was won by the Devils, 2-1, and more exciting games are hard to come by.</p>
        <p>But the 3.1 overnight Nielsen rating -- achieved against undistinguished reruns on other networks and a live Marc Anthony concert on HBO -- was 18 percent below the 3.8 last year for the comparable Dallas-Buffalo finals game on Fox.</p>
        <p>The rating locally on Channel 7 jumped 76 percent from last year but only to a meager 4.4, not surprising because there is a local rooting interest. (On Saturday night on Channel 11, largely against hockey, the Mets-Tampa Bay game produced a local 5.0 rating.)</p>
        <p>But the Dallas market's rating tumbled 25 percent to a 20.0. Same team as last year, less viewership.</p>
        <p>Eleven of 20 N.H.L. markets measured by Nielsen saw lower Game 3 ratings compared with the comparable network game last year.</p>
        <p>Game 3's performance follows ABC's 1.5 average national rating for its six playoff ratings, which equaled Fox's from last year. The network's 1.3 rating for its four regular-season games also matched Fox's for comparable time slots.</p>
        <p>Lacking healthy ratings, ABC and ESPN are instead selling the concept of a combined 20 percent increase in ratings for men 18 to 34. For ESPN, the demographic is up 37 percent in the playoffs; for ABC, it is up from a 1.4 to a 1.6.</p>
        <p>''Regardless of the small base that we started with, we've been able to grow it 20 percent,'' said Ed Erhardt, president of the ESPN-ABC Sales Group. ''I don't know of any sport that can boast that kind of growth.''</p>
        <p>With the rest of the finals on ABC in prime time, including last night's game, the network is certain of seeing these broadcasts sit in the basement with its worst-rated programs.</p>
        <p>The only way to avoid that fate might be to dress the Devils and the Stars in Regis Philbin's monochromatic ensembles and promote the games as ''Celebrity 'Who Wants to Be a Millionaire' on Ice,'' called by Dick Button and Peggy Fleming.</p>
        <p>Saturday nights, when fewer households watch TV than any other night, are lousy. Predictably, that's when ABC started its finals coverage. Still, ABC has seen an ice-bound sport do far better in prime time. On April 1, the women's long program in the world figure skating championships rated a 5.9, helped by the kind of strong female viewership that hockey lacks.</p>
        <p>Had the Devils-Dallas game been shown Sunday in prime time, it would probably have been trounced by the National Basketball Association playoffs. On Sunday night, Game 7 of the Western Conference finals generated a 14.5 overnight rating, as the Lakers stormed back from a 15-point fourth-quarter deficit to defeat the Trail Blazers. It was the highest-rated Western Conference finals Game 7 in N.B.A. history.</p>
        <p>Airwaves</p>
        <p>Miking N.B.A. coaches is gone for now, but NBC's audio picked up illuminating instructions Sunday night from Lakers Coach Phil Jackson regarding Shaquille O'Neal, who was having trouble getting shots, with Portland leading, 75-65: ''Forget about Shaq. If he's not open, don't change your game to go into him.'' After the Lakers' 89-94 victory, O'Neal told NBC's Ahmad Rashad how he exhorted teammates during a late-game huddle (''I told my guys: 'It's do or die, the time is now,' '' he said); Rashad, not listening, asked, ''What happened when you brought everybody together?'' O'Neal pretended he hadn't answered the question.</p>
        <p>One person involved in ''Monday Night Football'' auditions said ABC is looking at one solid analyst, like ESPN's Sterling Sharpe, and a rotation of a third man in the booth.</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
