<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bolshoi's New 'Quixote' Is Faithful to the Old Yet More Classical in Its Mien</title>
    <meta content="06QUIX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bolshoi Ballet</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kennedy, John F, Center for the Performing Arts (Washington, DC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DEFDE173FF935A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1187" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bolshoi's New 'Quixote' Is Faithful to the Old Yet More Classical in Its Mien</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff reviews Bolshoi Ballet performances of Don Quixote and Romeo and Juliet at Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lucky Chicago, Seattle, Los Angeles and Costa Mesa. Audiences there will be able to see the Bolshoi Ballet on its current national tour in ''Don Quixote'' and as the weekend's performances here at the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts confirmed, nobody dances ''Don Quixote'' like the Bolshoi. The effect is overwhelming, a blaze of color on every level of perception.</p>
        <p>New York is to see the company from Moscow in a separate engagement. Beginning July 18, Lincoln Center Festival 2000 will present the Bolshoi in ''Giselle'' and a mixed bill that includes George Balanchine's ''Symphony in C.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lucky Chicago, Seattle, Los Angeles and Costa Mesa. Audiences there will be able to see the Bolshoi Ballet on its current national tour in ''Don Quixote'' and as the weekend's performances here at the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts confirmed, nobody dances ''Don Quixote'' like the Bolshoi. The effect is overwhelming, a blaze of color on every level of perception.</p>
        <p>New York is to see the company from Moscow in a separate engagement. Beginning July 18, Lincoln Center Festival 2000 will present the Bolshoi in ''Giselle'' and a mixed bill that includes George Balanchine's ''Symphony in C.''</p>
        <p>In Washington the company came fully into its own with different casts in contrasting signature pieces: Leonid Lavrovsky's 1940 ''Romeo and Juliet'' and Aleksei Fadeyechev's spanking new production of ''Don Quixote,'' based on the exuberant version that has come down from early-20th-century stagings by Aleksandr Gorsky.</p>
        <p>There was a time when the Bolshoi broke the rules of polite ballet behavior. ''Don Quixote'' was the epitome of the expressive Bolshoi style. The niceties of precision in classical dancing were less important than dramatic power projected through technique.</p>
        <p>Sir Frederick Ashton, the great English choreographer, stunned by the Bolshoi's initial impact in the West, felt compelled to reaffirm his faith in the ''correct'' textbook style of classical dancing. Yet he added that if the British were right in their restrained approach, they were right like pygmies while the Bolshoi, even if wrong, were giants.</p>
        <p>The Bolshoi Ballet on view today is a very different company. Most of the principals joined in the late 1980's or 90's; their schooling and coaching have groomed them in a more classical direction. They look more like their Western counterparts.</p>
        <p>The ''Don Quixote'' of the 1960's identified with the great performances of Vladimir Vasiliev and Yekaterina Maksimova, not to speak of Maya Plisetskaya, cannot be reproduced. Dancers of such power do not exist anymore. Mr. Vasiliev has, in fact, been general and artistic director of the entire Bolshoi Theater since 1995.</p>
        <p>Although the company had two badly organized engagements in Las Vegas and Los Angeles in 1996, this is its first United States national tour in 10 years, under the direction of Mr. Vasiliev and Mr. Fadeyechev, who is artistic director of the ballet company.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Fadeyechev has done in his new ''Don Quixote'' is to remain faithful to the old one that the Bolshoi has had as a touchstone for a century. There are new sets by Sergei Barkhin, but the costumes are based on a 1903 production, with sketches by Vassily Dyachkov.</p>
        <p>The grand theatrical spectacle, aflame through its unusually numerous Spanish dances, the animation in the crowd scenes and the ensemble spirit that links the very young men in the Gypsy dances to the ballerina in her tutu in the classical showpieces: all this and more came together in the performances on Friday night and Sunday afternoon at the Kennedy Center.</p>
        <p>If the Bolshoi dances ''Don Quixote'' differently from other companies, this is because it stages it differently and more dynamically. In no small part, much is owed to the character dancers. Here one must single out the stunning performances of Vladimir Moiseyev, grandson of Igor Moiseyev, director and founder of the famed Moiseyev Folk Company.</p>
        <p>In ''Romeo and Juliet'' on Saturday, Mr. Moiseyev's ferocious Tybalt was mocking and snarling and above all imbued with an animal energy that propelled him around the stage in pursuit of his prey. As the bullfighter in ''Don Quixote,'' he was grandly over the top: a vain cape twirler, mannered but virile in an amazing Baroque performance.</p>
        <p>In the same way Aleksandr Petukhov as Sancho Panza offered a gem: everything was acted out in movement, expression and gesture, describing a tubby loyal servant, not a clown. Happy as a clam when things go right, he evoked sympathy when ridiculed and clung to his master's leg. Aleksei Loparevich, determined as the Don on Friday night, and Andrei Sitnikov, more of a dazed visionary on Sunday, made the title character believable in a version that integrates this mime role into the plot, such as it is.</p>
        <p>Here again, Basil the barber and his sweetheart, Kitri, outwit Kitri's father, who wants to marry her off to a rich fop. Don Quixote wanders through the plot in a context enriched by highly individualized performances that relate to him. There is not one dead spot, and the familiar Ludwig Minkus score, conducted on Friday by Aleksandr Kopylov, and on Sunday by Aleksandr Sotnikov, kept up the same dynamic pace. No sooner had a classical variation been completed than the Spanish character dances, scintillating in their frontal attack, poured onto center stage.</p>
        <p>It was thanks to Gorsky, who revised Marius Petipa's 1869 ''Don Quixote'' in 1900 and 1906, that the Moscow version has kept its animated bustle.</p>
        <p>In 1946 the ballet was restaged at the Bolshoi by Rostislav Zakharov. Mr. Fadeyechev has kept that choreographer's interpolations as well as those by Anatoly Simachyov and Kasyan Goleizovsky, whose solo for a Gypsy woman was executed by Yuliana Malkhasyants with the back-arching mastery of a veteran character dancer.</p>
        <p>Even more thrilling was the racing circle of bullfighters around the stage and the group dances. Nonetheless the leading roles are not lost in this rich and coherent tapestry. As Kitri, Mariya Aleksandrova is a golden girl, a streamlined dancer with the extraordinary Bolshoi spring in her leaps. She has beautiful placement, flair and sex appeal. Dmitri Belogolovtsev, the Basil on Sunday, looks better as a partner than a soloist, although he has been seen to stronger effect in guest appearances. On Friday night Galina Stepanenko was impressively solid as Kitri if less vivacious with Sergei Filin, an inconsistent but passionate classical dancer. The men, surprisingly by Bolshoi standards, are not as strong as their counterparts in the West.</p>
        <p>Yet the entire company is not on view on this tour, and the idiosyncrasies of Bolshoi's style should not always be confused with bad habits. The women still throw their arms up during their jetes, and the dynamism of this image, no matter how at odds with academic style, is indisputable.  In the final act, the grand pas de deux is danced at the court of the Duke and Duchess, who are absent from many Western productions. Similarly, the Bolshoi begins ''Romeo and Juliet'' with a rarely seen tableau in which the lovers and Friar Laurence are pictured as statues. On Saturday afternoon Inna Petrova, a superb dancer, and Andrei Uvarov touched an emotional chord.</p>
        <p>They danced best of all and yet on Saturday night, Ms. Stepanenko and Mr. Filin captured the 1940's style, with its special flow, more persuasively. The Bolshoi today may not break rules but it plays by its own rules.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
