<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Shatner Hath Wrought; The Intersection of the Internet and Celebrity</title>
    <meta content="Y06STA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Creative Artists Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Priceline.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shatner, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Startup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Talent Agencies/Creative Artists Agency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E4DA173FF935A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1543" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Shatner Hath Wrought; The Intersection of the Internet and Celebrity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA M. HOLSON</byline>
      <dateline>SAN JOSE, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Celebrities from various entertainment arenas and their agents are visiting Silicon Valley hoping to cash in on the dot-com boom, but with a twist; days of simply seeking salary for product endorsement are passe, with celebrities now wanting piece of the ownership; Web companies that need instant branding but have little cash on hand can offer lure of stock options and potential market riches; one example of this blend is success of William Shatner, former Star Trek icon, who received 125,000 stock options--worth millions today--to promote Priceline.com; even Hollywood agents, such as Creative Artists Agency, are getting into the act; some Silicon Valley entrepreneurs comment on potential pitfalls in involving celebrities in actually building Web business; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joe Montana and Ronnie Lott, former stars of the San Francisco 49ers, were there. So was Keyshawn Johnson, the outspoken wide receiver who was recently traded to the Tampa Bay Buccaneers from the New York Jets.</p>
        <p>So it was no surprise that dozens of venture capitalists and various other boys of Silicon Valley were giddily gathering around their Sunday afternoon heroes seeking autographs and exchanging back slaps.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joe Montana and Ronnie Lott, former stars of the San Francisco 49ers, were there. So was Keyshawn Johnson, the outspoken wide receiver who was recently traded to the Tampa Bay Buccaneers from the New York Jets.</p>
        <p>So it was no surprise that dozens of venture capitalists and various other boys of Silicon Valley were giddily gathering around their Sunday afternoon heroes seeking autographs and exchanging back slaps.</p>
        <p>But the fawning was mutual at the Fairmont Hotel where an all-star roster of football and baseball players gathered one rainy afternoon in February for the annual meeting of Champion Ventures, an investment fund set up for pro athletes. The athletes may not have seemed as star-struck, but they were eager to be there, too, seeking a piece of the dot-com action and hoping a little Silicon Valley magic would rub off on them.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, I want equity,'' said Mr. Johnson, eyeing his agent warily across the ballroom. ''I don't want to be just the guy with the name.''</p>
        <p>Talk about convergence. For all the buzzwords about the future melding of high-technology, multimedia and telecommunications, the real buzz these days has more to do with the coming together of Silicon Valley money and the culture of celebrity.</p>
        <p>''It's that little extra cachet,'' said Kevin Fong, a venture capitalist with the Mayfield Fund who hopes big-name athletes will give an advantage to the companies he has helped foster. ''Everyone is jaded. They want a hot company right on the fine edge. Celebrities do that.''</p>
        <p>If Silicon Valley is beginning to resemble Hollywood, chalk it up to more than the Spago in downtown Palo Alto. A parade of agents and celebrities has been making the pilgrimage to the Valley in recent months in the hope of using fame to cash in on the dot-com boom. The days, it seems, of demanding simply a paycheck for a product endorsement are passe. Now, celebrities expect to be owners.</p>
        <p>Of course, the peculiarities of the Internet phenomenon have made all that possible. Web companies that need instant branding but have little cash on hand can offer the lure of stock options and potential market riches. And who better than a movie star or athlete to help them? Especially considering the success of William Shatner, the former Star Trek icon, who received 125,000 stock options -- worth millions today -- to pitch for Priceline.com. Or Cindy Crawford who became the name and face of the online fashion retailer estyle Inc. for a stake in the company and a seat on the board.</p>
        <p>Even Hollywood agents are getting into the act, carving out a niche in the lucrative new-media trade. The Creative Artists Agency has teamed up with Idealab, the creator of on-line ventures like Etoys that is based in Pasadena, Calif., to build entertainment sites for the agency's clients. And that doesn't even begin to factor in what will happen when large media and entertainment companies catch up. Then the lines between e-commerce, sports and entertainment will blur further.</p>
        <p>''A lot of companies are realizing that entertainment might help them get above the clutter,'' said John Mass, a vice president at the William Morris Agency in Los Angeles. ''There is finally a role for media and entertainment having an effect on technology.''</p>
        <p>As a result, venture capitalists are beginning to act a little more like Hollywood agents. ''To the extent Hollywood is about access, we have it,'' said Mr. Fong. And agents, who control the talent, are beginning to think more like dot-com venture capitalists.</p>
        <p>If anyone would understand this, Mr. Mass would. For eight years, Mr. Mass, a former investment banker, has headed the new-media group at William Morris, a talent agency known more for its roster of movie stars than its corporate accounts.</p>
        <p>Several clients -- including Lucent Technologies and Anheuser-Busch -- have knocked on his door recently seeking help to execute their new-media strategies. In particular, he said, William Morris arranged a meeting between executives at SportsLine.com and Intel before SportsLine went public. As a result, Intel made a 4.9 percent investment in the company. ''This gave SportsLine the halo of a technology company,'' he said.</p>
        <p>William Morris has been equally active in matching up stars with Internet companies. Last September, an agent introduced Robert Levitan, the chief executive and co-founder of Flooz.com, which offers online gift certificates for retail Internet sites, to Whoopi Goldberg.</p>
        <p>Why? ''Everyone realizes there is no longer a distinction between marketing, branding and the experience,'' Mr. Levitan said. ''Because we had no brand equity we needed to put brand attributes around the product and service. Hollywood definitely wants a piece of that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Levitan was looking for a spokesman or spokeswoman for Flooz. Ms. Goldberg, the star of ''Sister Act'' and a past host of the Oscars ceremony, was perfect for the role, he said. She ''speaks to all groups, men, women, blacks, whites,'' Mr. Levitan said. A 15-minute conversation turned into an hour. And within a week, she had signed a contract and was shooting print ads -- becoming in the process the third-largest shareholder in the company. (Neither Mr. Levitan nor Ms. Goldberg would disclose how many options in the still-private company she holds.)</p>
        <p>''He knew what he was talking about and I was ready to start,'' Ms. Goldberg said in a recent interview.</p>
        <p>But she has influence with more than consumers. Mr. Levitan said Flooz.com, which is based in New York, recently signed a contract with Barnesandnoble.com to offer Flooz gift certificates. But Barnesandnoble.com was slow to follow through. So he asked Ms. Goldberg to give the executive in charge a nudge.</p>
        <p>''I had her call and the secretary was more than a little surprised,'' Mr. Levitan said. '' 'It sounds like her,' '' he said the secretary whispered to her boss. It was just enough to get the company moving on the project. Besides, Ms. Goldberg said, ''I think it helped him understand that this was not just a gig for me.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, what could be better than having a hard-to-reach celebrity on call? In January, Mr. Levitan made the 45-minute ride to Ms. Goldberg's home outside New York to show her the coming year's marketing plan.</p>
        <p>''What about Valentine's Day?'' Mr. Levitan said she asked him. He had no commercials in the works. ''I have time next Tuesday,'' she told him.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Goldberg the experience, so far, has been worthwhile. ''People say, 'Why did you do it?' '' she said. ''I pay homage to William Shatner because he made it viable to go to folks like me. It was an opportunity to make a little dough.''</p>
        <p>Besides, she added, it relieves some of the pressure of relying solely on movies as a source of income. ''It doesn't make you feel bad you didn't have a huge opening weekend,'' Ms. Goldberg said.</p>
        <p>But access to celebrities can only enhance success, it doesn't guarantee it. Silicon Valley and Hollywood have a lot to offer each other, said Daniel H. Case III, chairman of Chase H&amp;Q. The convergence of technology and media is real. But, he warned, ''there is a growing numbness, a disconnectedness from reality.''</p>
        <p>Jim Breyer, a partner at the venture firm Accel Partners in Palo Alto, agreed. He has talked to a number of celebrities looking to either dot-com themselves or find a company looking for a spokesman. ''Today I can't tell you whether it will pay off,'' he said. ''Anyone who has spent time putting these kinds of deals together realizes it is really hard.''</p>
        <p>One concern is that in the crush to cash in on the star of the moment, business plans will be poorly thought out. Just because a person knows how to pose for a camera, for example, doesn't mean the poser knows anything about building a Web business. Actors, too, are on location for months on end and may underestimate how much work it takes to help create a brand. And while it may be great fun to hang out with Joe Montana, Mr. Breyer said, ''it is just as important to talk about an idea.''</p>
        <p>That doesn't deter the likes of Calvin C. Lui, the 28-year-old chief executive of TheMan.com, a shopping and lifestyle Web site for men. He recently hired Karen C. Sortito, a Hollywood marketing executive from Sony Pictures Entertainment, as his chief marketing officer. He was at the Champion Ventures meeting, picking up business cards, hoping that one of the athletes would be interested in his site and willing to strike a deal.</p>
        <p>So far, he has had no takers. But Mr. Montana is a wine drinker, he mused, and maybe would be interested in writing a column about different vintages. Why not just hire a professional wine columnist? Mr. Lui grinned and sighed, as if pointing out the obvious. ''If Joe has a site there,'' he said, ''it will be read because it is Joe.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
