<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Seven Years, Couple Is Defeated</title>
    <meta content="Y06COU$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205212"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Custody and Support</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (State)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Timothy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Troxel, Gary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Troxel, Jenifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Granville, Tommie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Custody and Support</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E7D7173FF935A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Seven Years, Couple Is Defeated</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY EGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Egan, Timothy</byline>
      <dateline>MOUNT VERNON, Wash., June 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Defendants Gary and Jenifer Troxel and plaintiff Tommie Granville comment on Supreme Court decision striking down Washington State law that granted Troxels visitation rights with grandchildren; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For seven years, through three tiers of the court system, Gary and Jenifer Troxel have been trying to win the legal right to have extended visits with their grandchildren. Today, after a divided United States Supreme Court ruled against them, the Troxels were left with little but an emotional appeal.</p>
        <p>''If one afternoon a month is what we get, we'll be happy with that,'' Mrs. Troxel said. ''We miss them. They're still a part of our family.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For seven years, through three tiers of the court system, Gary and Jenifer Troxel have been trying to win the legal right to have extended visits with their grandchildren. Today, after a divided United States Supreme Court ruled against them, the Troxels were left with little but an emotional appeal.</p>
        <p>''If one afternoon a month is what we get, we'll be happy with that,'' Mrs. Troxel said. ''We miss them. They're still a part of our family.''</p>
        <p>But a few hours a month -- which was the original offer of the mother that set the Troxels off on a legal trek that galvanized retirement groups on their side and parents' rights organizations on the other -- may not even be in the offing now, the mother says.</p>
        <p>''This has been a huge waste of time, money and emotion,'' said Tommie Wynn, the mother of the two children at the center of this case. ''I'm relieved we finally won. It's a victory for every parent in the country. But I'm just not sure what we'll do as far as their request for visits.''</p>
        <p>The case that pitted a pair of 60-year-old grandparents, one of whom claims an asterisk in rock 'n' roll history, against the mother who was never legally tied to the Troxel family, dates to 1993 when Brad Troxel, father of the two children, committed suicide.</p>
        <p>Brad Troxel and the children's mother, then known as Tommie Granville, were never married; Brad lived at home with his parents. After the suicide, when the mother tried to limit the time the grandparents could spend with their two children, the Troxels went to court and were granted visits one weekend a month and for one week during the summer.</p>
        <p>The Troxels have been married 35 years, and have three other children and 10 grandchildren. Gary Troxel, a longshoreman, was a founding member of the rock band the Fleetwoods, which recorded hits like ''Come Softly to Me'' and ''Mr. Blue.'' In his house in the Skagit Valley one hour north of Seattle are two gold records for the songs, and he still performs with the group on occasion.</p>
        <p>''Gary was quite well known in the music world, and these girls have a right to know him,'' said Mrs. Troxel. The grandchildren, both girls, are 8 and 10 years old.</p>
        <p>The dispute was not about whether the grandparents had the right to visit but rather boiled down to exactly how much time they could have with their grandchildren.</p>
        <p>When Tommie Granville married, she tried to limit the visits. She offered them one afternoon a month, both sides said. But the Troxels wanted overnight stays. They were backed by a Washington State law that allows ''any person'' the right to visit when it serves a child's best interest.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Wynn said there never would have been a problem if the Troxels had not insisted on extended visits.</p>
        <p>''They were never denied visitation,'' she said. ''It was a control decision. These people became like the Elian Gonzalez relatives.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Wynn has eight children, six of whom live at home with her in Anacortes, just a few miles from the Troxels.</p>
        <p>The court, in its ruling today, said the Washington law allowing third party visits was ''breathtakingly broad.'' The Washington State Supreme Court also ruled against the Troxels, and it was the grandparents' appeal of the latest Washington state ruling that led to today's high court decision.</p>
        <p>The Troxels' lawyer, Mark D. Olson, said he was ''heartened by the decision'' because it did not throw out laws that allow grandparents the right to visit, but only knocked out the foundation of the Washington statute.</p>
        <p>However, he said the grandparents did not have a new legal strategy for enforcing visits. ''Frankly, the Troxels will take any time they can get,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
