<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush May Scoff at Polls, but Aides Call Them Reliable Predictor of Victory</title>
    <meta content="Y06BUS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5DA173FF935A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush May Scoff at Polls, but Aides Call Them Reliable Predictor of Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>AUSTIN, Tex., June 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Even though Republican presidential candidate Gov George W Bush scoffs at voter surveys showing him leading Vice Pres Al Gore for several months, his aides regard them as reliable predictor of victory; they say Bush lead is no fluke, but is instead compelling verdict on his sturdy appeal (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You could buy a Texas ranch if you had a dollar for every time Gov. George W. Bush has dismissed polls by saying that the only meaningful one is on Election Day. But his aides seem plenty attuned to the growing number of voter surveys that telegraph that moment.</p>
        <p>Today, they invited reporters to the campaign's headquarters here and, with charts, a graph and a multicolored map of the electoral college, they made the case that Mr. Bush's lead over Vice President Al Gore in most polls over the past several months was no fluke. To the contrary, they said, it is a compelling verdict on the Texas governor's sturdy appeal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You could buy a Texas ranch if you had a dollar for every time Gov. George W. Bush has dismissed polls by saying that the only meaningful one is on Election Day. But his aides seem plenty attuned to the growing number of voter surveys that telegraph that moment.</p>
        <p>Today, they invited reporters to the campaign's headquarters here and, with charts, a graph and a multicolored map of the electoral college, they made the case that Mr. Bush's lead over Vice President Al Gore in most polls over the past several months was no fluke. To the contrary, they said, it is a compelling verdict on the Texas governor's sturdy appeal.</p>
        <p>What about the two national polls released over the last week that showed Mr. Gore only a point behind? Possible anomalies, they responded, crying out for context and statistical confirmation.</p>
        <p>Or the analogy of 1988, when the challenger, Michael S. Dukakis, saw a late spring and early summer advantage over the sitting vice president, George H. W. Bush, collapse and come to naught? A poor indicator, for any number of reasons.</p>
        <p>One senior adviser drew reporters' attention to a simple, overarching reality: Mr. Bush, from the time that polls began pitting him against Mr. Gore, has frequently hit or surpassed 50 percent of voters' support, while Mr. Gore has not. In the two recent polls in which the candidates were neck and neck, Mr. Gore's support was below 45 percent.</p>
        <p>''Think about that,'' the adviser said. ''There are 182 polls. He is the vice president of the United States, with name ID well into the 90's, an incumbent administration of peace and prosperity, job approval ratings in the 50's and 60's, and this guy can get himself to 49 percent one time, and to 46-plus five times, whereas the guy on the other side can get himself to 50 percent 117 times.''</p>
        <p>Beyond its value as an engrossing reading and rearranging of political tea leaves, the briefing by Mr. Bush's advisers -- the second of its kind in less than two months -- suggested an investment in portraying Mr. Gore as a persistently unappealing loser whose retoolings have failed to reinvigorate his campaign.</p>
        <p>''This explains why they're going through their latest reinvention,'' the adviser said, citing the Gore campaign's abandonment of attack mode. ''They fundamentally gave it their best shot, and it didn't work.''</p>
        <p>Chris Lehane, a spokesman for the Gore campaign, said that he could not, off the top of his head, even confirm or dispute the Bush campaign's figures and interpretations, because the vice president ''does not waste his time and resources by analyzing polls.''</p>
        <p>''It's always a sure sign of a campaign that's starting to get very, very nervous when they have to resort to pointing to polls that support their candidacy,'' Mr. Lehane said.</p>
        <p>He nonetheless argued that polls now, as opposed to five or six months ago, made a case for Mr. Gore coming on strong and showed that Mr. Gore had eaten into Mr. Bush's once whopping lead by 15 or more percentage points.</p>
        <p>And another Gore adviser subsequently called and said that Mr. Dukakis was 12 points ahead at this point in 1988, while Mr. Bush was only 1 point up in the two recent polls.</p>
        <p>According to materials handed out today by the Bush campaign, Mr. Bush led Mr. Gore in 46 of 52 national public polls since early March. The Bush campaign also used what officials said were the latest public polls in individual states to draw a map that showed Mr. Bush in a position to garner 266 electoral votes, Mr. Gore in line to get 136 and another 136 up for grabs. It takes 270 electoral votes to win.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's advisers repeatedly rejected the model of 1988. And just last week the candidate himself offered an alternative comparison: 1960, when the vice president, Richard M. Nixon, was defeated by the challenger, John F. Kennedy. It was a telling metaphor, implying that Mr. Bush sees himself as the charismatic, fresh alternative to a perpetually striving, charm-challenged pol.</p>
        <p>''He followed a pretty successful administration,'' Mr. Bush said of Mr. Kennedy. ''His message was, 'Let's soar higher.' And that's what my message is going to be, too.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
