<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinical Studies: Choosing Ones That Can Help</title>
    <meta content="25SHER$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Women's Health" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209901"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sherman, Marcia (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E2DC133EF936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinical Studies: Choosing Ones That Can Help</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCIA SHERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sherman, Marcia (Dr)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Marcia Sherman article offers guidelines for evaluating often conflicting results of medical studies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LATE at night, bathed in the glow of your computer screen, you hit the jackpot: three medical studies discussing the latest treatment for your spouse's snoring problem. But all arrive at different conclusions.</p>
        <p>One is a case series published in a Scandinavian journal, the second is a study in the Annals of Sleep Apnea and the third is a large, randomized trial featured in the Journal of Medical Excellence. Which one should you believe? If you are going to peruse the medical Web sites, do you also need a hotline to a biostatistician, who can explain everything to you?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LATE at night, bathed in the glow of your computer screen, you hit the jackpot: three medical studies discussing the latest treatment for your spouse's snoring problem. But all arrive at different conclusions.</p>
        <p>One is a case series published in a Scandinavian journal, the second is a study in the Annals of Sleep Apnea and the third is a large, randomized trial featured in the Journal of Medical Excellence. Which one should you believe? If you are going to peruse the medical Web sites, do you also need a hotline to a biostatistician, who can explain everything to you?</p>
        <p>Ideally, yes. ''I don't want to slight anyone's intelligence, but even most medical people have a lot of difficulty interpreting clinical studies,'' said Dr. Allan S. Brett, the director of general internal medicine at the University of South Carolina School of Medicine. Dr. Brett also edits Journal Watch, a newsletter that critically reviews articles from the major medical journals.</p>
        <p>He noted that most doctors were never formally taught to read the medical literature, and that only within the last decade has medical education begun to address that deficiency.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Dr. Brett and Dr. Thomas Lee, an associate editor at Journal Watch, offered the following guidelines for the lay reader.</p>
        <p>Look at the journal source first.  ''I hate giving that advice,'' said Dr. Lee, an associate professor of medicine at Harvard Medical School. ''It's like saying you have to look at what college someone comes from. There are occasionally some good papers in poor journals, but in general the top research goes to only a few publications.'' The better journals, Dr. Brett noted, also run accompanying editorials that are more reader-friendly than the articles they discuss.</p>
        <p>Both editors rated The New England Journal of Medicine and The Journal of the American Medical Association as the best sources in general medicine. Dr. Lee, a cardiologist, added The Lancet, Annals of Internal Medicine, Circulation and the Journal of the American College of Cardiology to the list. ''If I had to choose between buying food or these journals, I'd go without the food,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Analyze the study's design.  ''You should ask, was this an experiment or simply a description of an association the authors found?'' Dr. Lee said.</p>
        <p>A prospective, random trial is a good example of an experiment: the study is designed first, then the data are collected. Observational studies may be as small as a case report or as large as the Nurses' Health Study, one of the first large studies to report an association between estrogen therapy and reduced cardiac events in postmenopausal women.</p>
        <p>''Observational studies are usually quicker and easier to do, but they cannot prove that things that appear associated with each other are actually related to each other,'' Dr. Lee said.</p>
        <p>Between the extremes of the case report and the random trial are more complicated designs, like the case-controlled study and case cohorts. ''These are much trickier to understand,'' Dr. Brett said. ''It's important to recognize that in some kinds of studies, it's much easier for the authors to twist the data to support whatever they want it to say. You have to be skeptical.''</p>
        <p>Consider the population under study.  ''If the population doesn't resemble you, then maybe the study isn't relevant to you,'' Dr. Lee noted. For example, many clinical trials exclude people with a complex disease or with multiple medical conditions.</p>
        <p>And, unless you are a rodent, use caution in applying results that are obtained with laboratory animals to your own situation.</p>
        <p>Look beyond the numbers to the human dimension of the results.  ''Really important studies talk about something that made people feel better, or made them live longer,'' Dr. Lee pointed out. ''An intervention that produces just a difference on a test, but not in the way people feel, is not as important.'' For example, he said, drugs that have been shown to slow the cognitive decline in patients with Alzheimer's dementia, but have not been shown to keep them from being placed in nursing homes.</p>
        <p>The discussion section should be where the authors talk about the limitations of their findings.  For example, a drug trial should mention side effects. If it does not, your skepticism should increase by a power of 10.</p>
        <p>Dr. Brett and Dr. Lee also proposed a few red flags:</p>
        <p>* Research financed by the manufacturers of a drug or another product might not necessarily be biased, but the lay reader should at least raise the question.</p>
        <p>* ''Investigators who own stock or get royalties from the manufacturer may have an unconscious conflict of interest,'' Dr. Lee said. ''I don't think most people are dishonest. But results might be the product of some wishful thinking.''</p>
        <p>* A brief description of scientific methods belongs in almost all credible scientific research. It's the most reader-unfriendly part of a paper, yet in some ways the most important: it tells you that the authors are willing to ''share the recipe'' for their results. ''Pages and pages of convoluted methods make me worry, though,'' Dr. Brett said. ''I start wondering why the study had to be so complicated.''</p>
        <p>* Beware of studies that report large relative differences. ''This is my pet peeve,'' Dr. Brett said. ''Let's say a given drug reduced the occurrence of stroke in the population from 2 to 1 percent. Well, even if it's at 2 percent, the event is occurring at a low frequency. But this gets reported as a 50 percent reduction.</p>
        <p>''If something -- a drug or other therapy -- improves an outcome by 50 or 75 percent, you should look at the actual numbers to see what that actually means. It may only signify a tiny difference.''</p>
        <p>* Beware of discussions with a polemical or argumentative tone. Most good researchers acknowledge opposing points of view. The discussion should place the study's results in the context of larger issues, and not simply argue for the authors' conclusions.</p>
        <p>By the way, remember that hotline to the biostatistician? That's the latest cure for your spouse's snoring: it puts you right to sleep.</p>
        <p>Marcia Sherman is an internist who practices in northern New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Marcia Sherman is an internist who practices in northern New Jersey.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
