<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Streetscapes/105 Hudson Street; A TriBeCa Taste of the Young Carrere &amp; Hastings</title>
    <meta content="25SCAP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209996"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gray, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Streetscapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E4DE1331F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1143" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Streetscapes/105 Hudson Street; A TriBeCa Taste of the Young Carrere &amp; Hastings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER GRAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gray, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>streetscapes/105 hudson street: a tribeca taste of the young</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE 1892 building at 105 Hudson Street is an uncommonly noble work for an industrial district. It was designed by the then-young firm of Carrere &amp; Hastings, who went on to become the architects of the New York Public Library at Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street. Its ground floor, once used to display chocolate, now features raw fish -- as served at Nobu, the sushi restaurant.</p>
        <p>A comprehensive exterior restoration of the building, in the TriBeCa West Historic District, is being undertaken by Bone Levine Architects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE 1892 building at 105 Hudson Street is an uncommonly noble work for an industrial district. It was designed by the then-young firm of Carrere &amp; Hastings, who went on to become the architects of the New York Public Library at Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street. Its ground floor, once used to display chocolate, now features raw fish -- as served at Nobu, the sushi restaurant.</p>
        <p>A comprehensive exterior restoration of the building, in the TriBeCa West Historic District, is being undertaken by Bone Levine Architects.</p>
        <p>In 1868, a large rail terminal was built at Hudson and Beach Streets, and the neighborhood now known as TriBeCa quickly developed from an area of polite brick houses to one of lofts and warehouses with access to both rail and river transport.  Larger and larger commercial buildings went up, most with a strictly industrial look.</p>
        <p>But in 1890 Henry L. Pierce, head of the Walter Baker Chocolate Company in Dorchester, Mass., hired Carrere &amp; Hastings to design a radically different type of building for the area. Pierce had taken over the Walter Baker concern in 1854.</p>
        <p>The company is listed in directories as having offices in New York City in the 1880's -- and even at that time their Baker's chocolate cooking product was one of the staples of the company, which is now part of Kraft Foods.</p>
        <p>Pierce was also active outside the firm, serving in the 1860's and 70's as an alderman, mayor of Boston and congressman from Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>He gave the new building his own name; although the Baker company had offices there, it appears that 105 Hudson Street was his personal investment.</p>
        <p>Carrere and Hastings had met in the offices of McKim, Mead &amp; White and established a firm together in the mid-1880's. The two had studied at the Ecole des Beaux-Arts in Paris, and brought a light, lacy, often French-inspired style to a decade typified by the heavy, dark stone of the Richardsonian Romanesque.</p>
        <p>According to research by the late architectural historian Channing Blake, their first commission in New York was a $3,000 entrance to a building at the southeast corner of 59th Street and Madison Avenue whose interior displayed a tableau of the Monitor and the Merrimac in battle in the Civil War.</p>
        <p>This was followed by a seven-story building (now demolished) on Broad Street for the Edison Electric Company, and then the Pierce building. Later projects included the Frick mansion at 70th Street and Fifth Avenue.</p>
        <p>The Pierce building was designed as a 10-story building, but wound up as seven stories, in cream colored terra cotta and light orange brick. The French neo-classic style, deeply rusticated ground-floor marble  and giant engaged columns made it appear more like a Paris office building or a London bank.</p>
        <p>AN 1892 article in the Real Estate Record &amp; Guide said it was leased to food firms. Most of what is now Nobu was used to display the Baker company's chocolate products. The upper floors were divided into smaller offices of 300 to 500 square feet.</p>
        <p>How Pierce got in touch with Carrere &amp; Hastings is not clear but in the same year the Pierce building was finished he called them back to design a fanciful templelike display pavilion for the company for the 1893 Chicago world's fair.</p>
        <p>Pierce died in 1896, and in 1903 his estate sold the building to Alexander Powell, a candy manufacturer. In 1905 Powell had his architect, Henri Fouchaux, enlarge the Pierce building to 11 stories, and also expanded it north on an additional lot on Hudson Street; bronze lettering high up on the Hudson Street front reading ''Powell Building'' was installed at that time. (These days, the building is known either as the Powell Building or by its address.)</p>
        <p>Fouchaux mimicked the original design, although its startling elegance was somewhat diluted by the addition.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1970's the developer Joseph Cazana bought 105 Hudson Street and converted it to a co-op, but with a twist. Only floors five and above were residential; the second through fourth floors were sold as offices.</p>
        <p>The upper floors were generally gutted, and a typical loft apartment on the ninth floor is expensively finished, with the heavy columns of the old office plan rising in unexpected locations. A few of the offices were left intact, with their original doors, for use as bedrooms.</p>
        <p>On the seventh floor, Susan Levine -- one of the early co-op purchasers -- has exposed the arched brick vaulting over her kitchen area, and still has the original heavy wooden windows -- perhaps two inches thick.</p>
        <p>In the commercial section, the second floor is now gutted and vacant, but long winding corridors on floors three and four look like a movie set for a detective novel, with glass-paned wooden doors. Chodosh Realty Services has left on its door old gold-leafed painting that reads ''Schwarz &amp; Ehrlich Import Agents.''</p>
        <p>Jon Chodosh, president of his firm, says that these unusual spaces rarely turn over, but that a 400-square-foot office would probably sell today for about $150,000, with a maintenance of perhaps $600 a month.</p>
        <p>The architect Kevin Bone, a partner at Bone Levine Architects, says that work is now under way on a comprehensive exterior restoration of 105 Hudson Street. This summer they plan to repoint the exterior walls and repair damaged terra-cotta units.</p>
        <p>Twenty years ago, he said, ''it was standard to throw many of them out, replacing them with fiberglass or something else.'' But Mr. Bone said that preservation techniques have advanced to a point where, with stainless-steel reinforcements and epoxy, many of the terra-cotta units can now be saved. Mr. Bone is also trying to reverse  repairs that have damaged the building. A few decades ago, when some of the terra-cotta lintels began to come loose, someone  bolted new steel supports into the brittle terra cotta -- ''pretty brutal work,'' he said.  He added that a large part of his practice is repairing earlier quick fixes.</p>
        <p>Another concern involves the cornices, where openings in the copper have provided room for pigeons to nest. ''Pigeon guano is acidic, and heavy, and creates all sorts of problems,'' he said. ''It's a major issue in cornice restoration.'</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
