<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If These Walls Could Talk</title>
    <meta content="25MERKINT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Merkin, Daphne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">gordon, emily fox</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knipfel, Jim</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">mockingbird years (book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">quitting the nairobi trio (book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E4DB113EF936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If These Walls Could Talk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Daphne Merkin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Merkin, Daphne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daphne Merkin reviews books Mockingbird Years: A Life</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mockingbird Years</p>
        <p>A Life in and Out of Therapy.</p>
        <p>By Emily Fox Gordon.</p>
        <p>243 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Basic Books. $24.</p>
        <p>Quitting</p>
        <p>the Nairobi Trio</p>
        <p>By Jim Knipfel.</p>
        <p>285 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Jeremy P. Tarcher/Putnam. $23.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mockingbird Years</p>
        <p>A Life in and Out of Therapy.</p>
        <p>By Emily Fox Gordon.</p>
        <p>243 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Basic Books. $24.</p>
        <p>Quitting</p>
        <p>the Nairobi Trio</p>
        <p>By Jim Knipfel.</p>
        <p>285 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Jeremy P. Tarcher/Putnam. $23.95.</p>
        <p>The psychotherapist's office -- whether it's decorated with archaeological finds, in tribute to one of Freud's consuming hobbies, or with selected tchotchkes, in tribute to the personal taste of the therapist -- is one of the last unstormed bastions in the Western world. What takes place behind its walls is a closely guarded secret, known only to the two people who meet for a 50-minute hour once, twice or, with increasing rarity, five times a week. Depending on the skills of the therapist and the receptivity of the patient, the drama of the enterprise known as the talking cure might prove to be be anything from a revelation to a violation; in less extreme instances it might be merely disappointing.</p>
        <p>The theoretical principles of psychotherapy, as well as the complex history of their modification and revision, have been the subject of countless texts. The practice of therapy -- how it does or doesn't work and why -- has also been extensively explored, in books that are often written in opaque professional jargon, invoking a specific set of references. You know the drill: transference, counter-transference, resistance, insight, projection, introjection. And yet few of us -- in or out of therapy -- have more than a vague sense of what it is supposed to feel like, or whether what takes place in any one office is similar to what is taking place in others. In the end, you have to accept psychotherapy on faith, because in the end it's essentially unknowable -- like other people's sex lives.</p>
        <p>Along comes Emily Fox Gordon's ''Mockingbird Years: A Life in and Out of Therapy'' to help shed some light. Written in a witty and sparkling style, Gordon's memoir tracks more than two decades of encounters with therapists who, with the exception of one remarkable healer, were variously remote, inappropriately involved or downright peculiar. ''I was formed by therapy,'' she observes, ''absorbing its influence in ways that would require most of my life to raise to consciousness. I brought into my therapies not the problems of life, but the problems of therapy.''</p>
        <p>The story begins when Emily, a ''sullen, disorganized'' 18-year-old who has flunked high school and has made a half-hearted suicide attempt (''a few swipes with a pair of nail scissors''), is packed off to Austen Riggs, the famous psychiatric hospital in Stockbridge, Mass. Far from being disturbed by this turn of events, she is delighted: ''going to Riggs was the fulfillment of an adolescent fantasy.'' But Emily is already a veteran analysand, having been through a series of comically misguided or merely inept therapies. Her first doctor, ''a classically trained Viennese psychoanalyst with a Park Avenue address,'' has one weeping eye and maintains a resolutely uncommunicative silence. Then there is Dr. G., a male therapist with a ''sober, clear-eyed gaze,'' in whose office she experiences ''the twin novelties of sitting upright and being openly addressed. And, most memorably, Dr. H., whose approach resembles Madame Defarge's: she presents Emily with a book of patterns, expertly measures her, and proceeds to knit her young patient a ''very handsome and unbecoming'' sweater. ''Given what I could see of her daily production rate,'' Gordon notes, ''it seemed strange that the sweater grew so slowly over the weeks and months of my therapy: was it possible that she unraveled it after hours, like Penelope?''</p>
        <p>Emily remains at Riggs for three years, two of them as an outpatient. A self-described ''hog for attention,'' she passes much of her time in a state of benign neglect. Along with the other patients, she lounges around in hair rollers and slippers listening to Bob Dylan and the Beatles. In reponse to the general ''apathy'' of Riggs, she stops reading, and when her I.Q. is retested after her first year, it has ''declined significantly.'' Emily is told she has a ''schizoid personality disorder with borderline trends,'' a seemingly worrisome assessment of her youthful pathology. She writes: ''This is a bad diagnosis, and an insulting one, I've been told since, but at the time I rather liked the sound of 'borderline trends.' It made me think of a stylish flourish, an extra, like piping on a jacket or whitewall tires on a car.''</p>
        <p>Emily is put under the care of a freshly minted psychologist who swamps her with ''moony empathy'' and is moved to frequent tears by her plight: ''My parents, we acknowledged in therapy, had rejected and abandoned me. I had known this for years, but pretended it was a revelation because I found his emotion too gratifying not to play on.'' Dr. S. rapidly confides his ''clammy feelings'' for her; he teaches Emily how to drive and she teaches him to smoke. Once, after an alcohol-infused dinner, Dr. S. (who is married, with a pregnant wife) puts his arm around her waist, in a gesture ''more emotional than sexual.'' Increasingly angered by his behavior, Emily casts around for another therapist.</p>
        <p>Enter Leslie Farber, who has just arrived at Riggs. ''I knew instantly,'' Gordon writes, ''that Dr. Farber was a different kind of being from the other therapists. His was not the neutral watchfulness I had become so used to; he judged, and revealed his judgment.'' Farber had already achieved some renown for the contrarian views he expressed in essays that avoided obscurantist prose in favor of a direct and colloquial style. In their very first session, Farber proceeds to ditch the formal conventions of psychotherapy; he lends her a volume of poetry and suggests that they meet the following week simply to ''talk,''one person to another. Sitting in twin red leather chairs, under ''a hazy blue lozenge of tobacco smoke,'' doctor and patient trade anecdotes, discuss their shared enthusiasm for Joanne Woodward movies, gossip about other patients, explore her childhood and his marriages, and analyze the newly ascendant 60's ''youth culture.'' Farber continues to lend Emily a wide range of books (Martin Buber, Goncharov's ''Oblomov,'' poetry by Randall Jarrell and Philip Larkin) and to hold her to his own high standards. When she goes through a promiscuous phase, he calls her ''a female jerk'' and curtly rejects her facile theorizing about the unconscious feelings that may lie behind her behavior. ''You were meant,'' he tells her, ''for the conscious life.'' Most astonishingly for someone in his profession, Farber believes in the ''inextinguishable presence of will'' as a crucial factor in human affairs.</p>
        <p>Emily's ''liberator'' steers her away from the past and toward a vision of the future; he urges her to give up on her parents (Gordon paints a subtly indicting portrait of their parenting) and to pursue a high-school equivalency diploma. When Farber moves to New York City in 1968, Emily is right behind him, even though she has no job or apartment. Although she quickly finds both, her relationship with Farber becomes problematic, gradually descending into a full-scale ''dependent collapse.'' Emily falls in love with her therapist's family as she has previously fallen in love with him. Weaving herself into the fabric of Farber's Upper West Side household, she becomes friendly with his wife (who, she discovers, was once his patient), baby-sits for his three children, and shyly sits in on the intellectual salons he holds in his living room. It's like a dream of a surrogate home come true, until her encroachment on Farber's private life gets in the way of their therapeutic alliance. Their sessions take on a distant, chilly tone, and she begins to feel like an ''interloper.'' Her involvement with Farber comes to an abrupt and undramatic end after she marries the man she has been dating. She invites Farber to the wedding, but he chooses not to come.</p>
        <p>Farber is the flawed hero of this book, a complex and tough-minded maverick who pulls his patient out of her passive, undemanding universe into the clear and sometimes unpleasant light of reality. But the Gordon we meet is remarkable too: a stunning writer whose perceptions are casually penetrating. Her guilelessly understated memoir is as good an argument for the examined life -- for the sustained construction of a coherent self that is the therapeutic ideal -- as it is a dissection of the many ways in which therapy can go wrong. Everything, it seems, hangs on the two people who sit behind a closed door, engaging in a corrective version of intimacy. With a bit of luck (which Freud thought mattered almost as much as what happened in analysis), you might find yourself with someone like Leslie Farber. More likely, you'll end up with somone who likes to knit.</p>
        <p>On a quirkier note, Jim Knipfel's ''Quitting the Nairobi Trio'' depicts the uselessness of shrinks and the virtues of a self-help approach to the disordered psyche. His memoir is set 15 years ago in a locked-door psychiatric ward -- referred to variously as ''the Bin,'' a ''madhouse'' and ''the bughouse'' -- where the author was confined for six months after having made serial suicide attempts, two of which were hilariously botched. Knipfel's first try is with a steak knife, in a scenario he has set up to look like a murder by an infatuated female stalker. But he lacks the requisite guts, not to mention skill. ''Mishima I was not,'' he ruefully observes. ''The 'wounds' on my back turned out to be little more than scratch marks, because my arm couldn't reach very well.'' He then attempts to hang himself with the belt from his trench coat, and when that doesn't work, he washes down dozens of over-the-counter sleeping pills with ''bad Scotch.'' Alas, this sure-fire technique fails as well: Knipfel is discovered by some cops after he staggers out of his apartment, and they ferry him in a police cruiser to the intensive care unit of a Minneapolis hospital.</p>
        <p>Knipfel comes to after three days of delirium to find himself, as befits a graduate student in philosophy, citing Nietzsche in rhyming ''guttural German screams.'' He is strapped to a bed, hooked up on a medley of intravenous drips and pierced from all sides: ''Something long and narrow and sharp had been inserted into the end of my penis.'' Classified as a ''mixed personality'' who has suffered a ''psychotic break,'' Knipfel is divested of his belt, shoelaces and razor, and plunked down in a unit populated by the ''lithium set.'' He receives no medication or therapy aside from a weekly 10-minute session with Dr. Spellman, who has a voice that ''sounded as if he worked hard on it, practicing for hours at home every night,'' and who has little to say other than to postpone his evaluation of his patient's condition from week to week. But with the aid of a collection of ''impenetrable'' essays by the ''wacky French psychoanalyst'' Jacques Lacan, Knipfel ambles his way back to relative mental health. Along the road, he discovers that he likes his bed and the ''pillow-soft'' food, and even feels the stirrings of affection for some of the other patients, including a woman he calls Edna Malaise, who positions herself daily inside the entrance to the unit and wears a ''sad mess of mascara and lipstick . . . like a clown who would brighten no child's birthday party.'' Then, out of the blue, Spellman promotes him to an unlocked ward, for no discernible reason other than ''the state nipping at his heels.'' After months of playing endless rounds of Go Fish with Eddie the Paranoid and waiting for the meal cart to arrive, Knipfel is sprung.</p>
        <p>''Quitting the Nairobi Trio'' is a zany lark of a read, written by someone who seems to have a hard time taking his own existential despair seriously. Knipfel, a columnist for New York Press and the author of ''Slackjaw,'' a memoir about losing his eyesight, is a gifted stylist with a truly original take on things; I felt my interest flag only when he went into lengthy descriptions of his wearyingly vivid dreams. It remains unclear whether the author considers himself to have been cured or not -- or whether, in fact, he believes he was ever unhinged. ''I was sane as stone,'' he declares, but he also talks about ''how painful madness can be.'' So, the reader wonders, was he or was he not ''jackass crazy?'' That seems to be just the teasing note of uncertainty that Knipfel wants to leave us on.</p>
        <p>Daphne Merkin is a staff writer for The New Yorker.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Daphne Merkin is a staff writer for The New Yorker.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
