<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Still Uninsured, and Still a Campaign Issue</title>
    <meta content="25PEAR0AA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Women's Health" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209900"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FAMILY CARE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E4DF123EF936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1190" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Still Uninsured, and Still a Campaign Issue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Problem of Americans who lack health insurance has been debated endlessly for decade, yet ranks of the uninsured keep growing, now standing at 44.3 million, or 16 percent of population; Clinton administration tried and failed to solve problem with sweeping health care initiative in 1993-94, and issue promises to loom large in this year's presidential campaign; several reasons why reform defies best efforts of policymakers detailed; initiatives of Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush, and their potential pitfalls, described; charts profile the uninsured (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE problem of Americans who lack health insurance has been debated endlessly for the last decade, yet theranks of the uninsured keep growing. Having risen by more than a million a year in the 1990's, the number of uninsured now stands at 44.3 million - 16 percent of the population - even though the United States is enjoying the longest period of economic growth in its history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE problem of Americans who lack health insurance has been debated endlessly for the last decade, yet theranks of the uninsured keep growing. Having risen by more than a million a year in the 1990's, the number of uninsured now stands at 44.3 million - 16 percent of the population - even though the United States is enjoying the longest period of economic growth in its history.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration tried and failed to solve the problem with its sweeping health care initiative in 1993-94. Subsequent efforts by Congress and the administration have been far more modest, and in some states (notably Massachusetts, this month) frustrated advocates are trying to force the issue with referendums.</p>
        <p>Whatever Congress does or fails to do, health care will be a significant issue in this year's presidential campaign. It is a defining issue for many Democrats, and Bill Bradley pushed it to center stage in his unsuccessful primary challenge to Vice President Al Gore. Gov. George W. Bush, the likely Republican nominee for president, has also begun to address the issue, with a proposal for tax credits to help people buy insurance.</p>
        <p>Two big choices confront patients, politicians and policy makers: Should they pursue incremental changes in the health care system or comprehensive changes? Should they seek new government spending for health care or neew tax breaks to help people buy private insurance? What follows is a look at an issue that will not go away, and at the outlines - and potential pitfalls - of the two candidates' proposals.</p>
        <p>THE PROBLEM ...</p>
        <p>Why does health care defy the best efforts of government officials and policy makers?</p>
        <p>* Any significant change in the health care system will reshuffle huge sums of money and will inevitably redistribute income, with politically explosive effects.  * Policy changes almost always have unforseen consequences, because the health care system is immensely complex. It involves not only patients, doctors, community hospitals and drug companies, but also doens of medical specialities, teaching hospitals, rural hospitals, biotechnology companies, laboratories, drugstores, nurses, physical therapists, private insurance companies, health maintenance organizations, large employers, small businesses, labor unions and countless health care businesses that fill small niches.  * Health care markets are local. What works in New York or Florida may not work in Iowa or Oregon. State legislators have struck many bipartisan compromises on issues that provoke endless squabbles in Congress.  * Health policy aggravates fundamental philosophical disagreements about the proper role of government in managing or regulating a big sector of the economy.  *Health care involves life-and-death issues, so it has a moral and ethical dimension that generates more passion than purely economic questions.</p>
        <p>... AND WHAT THE CANDIDATES SAY THEY'D DO</p>
        <p>AL GORE Rathan than remaking the health care system, Mr. Gore would build on existing programs; mindful of the 1993-94 debacle, he has said, ''We can't overhaul the system in one fell swoop.'' He would guarante access to insurance for all children by expanding eligibility for a health program that Congress created in 1997. And he would allow parents of eligible children to enroll in this program. (Most uninsured children come from families in which the parents are uninsured.)</p>
        <p>States could expand eligibility for the new Children's Health Insurance Program, so families with ncomes up to 2.5 times the official poverty level could qualify. (In most states, the ceiling on family income is set at twice the poverty level.) That program, or Medicaid, would also be open to families who could not get insurance through their employers, though they would have to pay the full premium; they would get a tax credit for 25 percent of the cost.</p>
        <p>Aides to Mr. Gore say his proposals would cover 11 million to 15 million people and would cost the federal government $146 billion over 10 years (about one-third more than health care initiatives proposed this year by President Clinton).</p>
        <p>POSSIBLE FLAWS Critics say it is unrealistic for Mr. Gore to use Medicaid and the Children's Health Insurance Program as a foundation for the future. Many people already eligible for these programs are not enrolled. About one-fourth of the uninsured are not even eligible for Medicaid.</p>
        <p>States have had difficulty enrolling children in both programs. States vary in their enthusiasm, in their financial commitment and resources, and in the effectiveness of their efforts to find and enroll children.</p>
        <p>Parents may be unaware of what is available. They may avoid Medicaid because it bears the stigma of welfare. In some states, they still face obstacles to enrolling: long application forms, or requirements to apply in person at inconvenient times and places.</p>
        <p>GEORGE W. BUSH Governor Bush, most Republicans and some Democrats support new tax breaks to help people buy health insurance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has proposed a tax credit to help individuals and families who do not receive employer-sponsored coverage and are not eligible for public programs. The government would allow a credit up to $1,000 a year for an individual and $2,000 for a family to cover up to 90 percent of the cost of health insurance.</p>
        <p>Under a bill passed by the House in October, people who buy health insurance on their own could take a tax deduction for the premiums they pay. Such deductions usually cost the government less, but provide less assitance to consumers, than tax credits do.</p>
        <p>POSSIBLE FLAWS Tax breaks are politically appealing, but they must be carefully designed if they are to promote a significant increase in the number of people with insurance coverage. Many needy people do not pay taxes, because of their low incomes. Forty-five percent of the uninsured do not owe any taxes, and 90 percent of those who do are in the 15 percent bracket, so a deduction offers only modest benefits.</p>
        <p>Under some proposals, people who already have health insurance would be allowed to take tax credits, In effect, they would be rewarded for doing what they already do. That may seem only fair, but it costs money and does not necessarily expand coverage.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Gruber, a professor of economics at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, said, ''Even very generous tax policies could not cover more than a sizable minority of the uninsured population.'' A generous refundable tax credit costing $13 billion a year would reduce the ranks of the uninsured by only four million people, he said.</p>
        <p>Prof. Mark V. Pauly, a health economist at the University of Pennsylvania, said, ''Little tax credits don't help very much,'' But, he added, larger credits could have substantial effects.</p>
        <p>FAMILY CARE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
