<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sao Paulo</title>
    <meta content="WDSAO.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209966"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S DOING IN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sao Paulo (Brazil)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/What's Doing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil/Sao Paulo</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D91531F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sao Paulo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>What's Doing In column describes upcoming events, sightseeing, accommodations and restaurants in Sao Paulo, Brazil; photos; chart; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Superlatives come quickly to mind when talking about Sao Paulo. With 18 million people in its metropolitan area, this is the largest city in Brazil, the largest in South America, indeed the largest in the Southern Hemisphere. It boasts of having the largest population of Japanese descent of any city outside Japan, the largest of Lebanese descent of any city outside the Middle East, the largest of Italian descent of any city outside Italy, and more wealth than any city in what used to be called the third world.</p>
        <p>Paulistanos, as residents of the city are known, have always taken pride in the cosmopolitan environment they have constructed around them during the past century, but rarely more so than now. All year long, Brazil is marking the 500th anniversary of the arrival of the first Portuguese expedition to the New World, and Sao Paulo, with a melting-pot population that personifies the Brazilian ideal of racial democracy, is a focal point of the commemorations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Superlatives come quickly to mind when talking about Sao Paulo. With 18 million people in its metropolitan area, this is the largest city in Brazil, the largest in South America, indeed the largest in the Southern Hemisphere. It boasts of having the largest population of Japanese descent of any city outside Japan, the largest of Lebanese descent of any city outside the Middle East, the largest of Italian descent of any city outside Italy, and more wealth than any city in what used to be called the third world.</p>
        <p>Paulistanos, as residents of the city are known, have always taken pride in the cosmopolitan environment they have constructed around them during the past century, but rarely more so than now. All year long, Brazil is marking the 500th anniversary of the arrival of the first Portuguese expedition to the New World, and Sao Paulo, with a melting-pot population that personifies the Brazilian ideal of racial democracy, is a focal point of the commemorations.</p>
        <p>Those who come to Sao Paulo expecting to find a laid-back seaside tropical resort in the style of Rio de Janeiro or Salvador are in for a shock. Sao Paulo is a very different kind of Brazil: aggressive, sprawling and resourceful, with a different climate, including temperatures that can drop to near-freezing at night during the Southern Hemisphere winter (June through September).</p>
        <p>Instead, Sao Paulo's charms are distinctly urban: restaurants, museums, concerts, nightclubs, parks and window shopping along Avenida Paulista, the main commercial boulevard. So are the problems the city confronts, including poverty, crime and police brutality. But even a confirmed Tropicalist like the pop singer Caetano Veloso was forced to confess that, as he wrote in a homage to the busiest intersection in Brazil's busiest city, ''Something happens in my heart every time I turn the corner of Ipiranga and Sao Joao.''</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>The magnificent exhibition known as ''Brazil+500'' is the largest show of Brazilian art ever assembled, spread over an area larger than the Louvre in four separate buildings. With some 15,000 pieces on display, it is hard to talk about highlights, but the sections focusing on Indian, folk and Afro-Brazilian art have drawn especially lavish praise from local and international critics. Admission is $5.75 on weekdays and $8.50 on weekends, at 1.8 real to the dollar. Telephone (55-11) 573-6073. Until  Sept. 7 at Ibirapuera Park.</p>
        <p>To mark the 500th anniversary of the Portuguese arrival, leading Brazilian and Portuguese pop musicians are offering a monthly series of free joint concerts at Ibirapuera Park. On July 30, Gilberto Gil, Maria Joao and Mario Laginha will perform together, with Ney Matogrosso and Marta Dias scheduled for Aug. 13 and Gal Costa and Madredeus closing the series on Sept. 9.</p>
        <p>Sao Paulo has numerous music halls featuring Brazil's top artists, with performance schedules published in newspapers and monthly English-language tourist guides. One winter highlight promises to be a number of shows by the brilliant pop singer Marisa Monte at the Palace, Avenida dos Jamaris 213 in Moema. She will be performing weekends from July 27 through Sept. 9, with tickets $10 and up; (55-11) 5643-2569.</p>
        <p>No rivalry in international soccer is more intense than that between Brazil, which has captured the World Cup four times, and Argentina, which has won it twice. The national teams of the two countries will play each other on July 26 at the 80,000-seat Morumbi Stadium, Sao Paulo's largest, at Praca Roberto Gomes Pedrosa 1, Jardim Leonor, as part of the qualifying round for the 2002 World Cup. Call (55-11) 3749-8000 for information about tickets (prices to be announced shortly before the match).</p>
        <p>Sightseeing</p>
        <p>Ibirapuera Park is to Sao Paulo what Central Park is to New York City: an island of green and calm amid traffic and skyscrapers. It has numerous museums and pavilions, many of them designed by the renowned Brazilian architect Oscar Niemeyer, and open spaces that include lakes and playgrounds, which draw large crowds of families on weekends. The planetarium, $2.85, is especially interesting because it displays the constellations of the Southern Hemisphere. The park is open daily, 6 a.m. to 8 p.m.; (55-11) 574-5177.</p>
        <p>Exhibitions in which venom is extracted from snakes are no longer offered to the public, but the Instituto Butantan, Avenida Vital Brasil 1500 in the Butanta area, remains perhaps the city's most popular tourist attraction. One of the world's leading reptile research centers, it has a collection of more than 60,000 animals, and its small museum features live spiders and scorpions as well as poisonous snakes with exotic names like jararaca and mussurana. Open Tuesday through Sunday, 9 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. Admission is 85 cents; 55 cents for children; (55-11) 813-7222.</p>
        <p>The Memorial to the Immigrant, at Rua Visconde de Parnaiba 1316 in Bras, is the Brazilian equivalent of Ellis Island. Nearly three million people from 60 different countries, including the United States, came through this processing center during the 91 years it operated before closing in 1978, and their contributions to Brazilian society are honored in thorough, fascinating exhibits in a somewhat nondescript complex of brick buildings done in neo-Classical style. Open Tuesday through Sunday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission $1.15, half price for children; (55-11) 6693-0917.</p>
        <p>Installed in one of the city's uglier buildings is its best museum, known as the MASP, or Museu de Arte de Sao Paulo. The collection here is said to be the largest and most impressive in Latin America, with European masters like Rembrandt, van Gogh, Goya, El Greco and Monet as well as leading Brazilian artists such as Portinari, Anita Malfatti and Tarsila do Amaral. On Sunday an antiques and arts and crafts fair is held on the square outside the museum. Open Tuesday through Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; admission $5.75. Avenida Paulista 1578; (55-11) 251-5644.</p>
        <p>Also on Sundays, the ''Discover Sao Paulo'' program offers three bus tours departing from the Praca da Republica downtown. The Green route shows visitors parks and gardens, the Cultural itinerary visits the principal museums, and the Historic tour stops at old homes and monuments. Tickets -- $2.85; $1.15 for children -- are sold at tourist offices or through (55-11) 6971-5000.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>By Brazilian standards, Sao Paulo hotels can be absurdly overpriced. Rates mimic those of New York, with service and amenities that cost half as much in Rio de Janeiro or Salvador. But on weekends, when business travelers leave, rates at major hotels can drop by 30 percent.</p>
        <p>Few of Sao Paulo's hotels are more reliable or convenient than the Crowne Plaza, just off Avenida Paulista at Rua Frei Caneca 1360 in Cerqueira Cesar. Remodeled not long ago, it has 220 rooms and large beds and bathtubs in which to sink at the end of a long day. A standard double starts at $198 a night through the chain's ''Summer Options'' program. Telephone (55-11) 253-2244 or (800) 227-6963; fax (55-11) 251-3121.</p>
        <p>In the 1970's, the Grand Hotel Ca D'Oro, Rua Augusta 129 in Consolacao, was the most elegant place to stay in Sao Paulo. The neighborhood  has fallen on hard times, but the 265 rooms, most still decorated in the same style as they were back then, are large, and the Italian restaurant on the ground floor is one of the best in town. Doubles are $150, breakfast included; (55-11) 236-4300, fax (55-11) 236-4311.</p>
        <p>Budget: Sao Paulo is awash in what are known as ''flats,'' apartment hotels aimed primarily at the long-term business visitor but also available to the tourist. One especially good option is the Parthenon chain, which operates a score of these residential hotels. Rooms at some, such as the Parthenon St. Germain on Rua Padre Joao Manuel 202 in Cerqueira Cesar, start at $60, with breakfast. The top price at this chain is $100. Call (800) 111790 for reservations; fax (55-11) 883-2476.</p>
        <p>The Best Western Porto do Sol, Rua Tutoia 77 in Cerqueira Cesar, is halfway between Avenida Paulista and Ibirapuera Park and convenient to many good restaurants. Its 198 rooms, while simple, are as clean and attractive as those of its much more expensive neighbors. A double starts at $100, with an ample breakfast buffet of tropical fruits and juices; (55-11) 3059-5000, fax (55-11) 3059-5193.</p>
        <p>Luxury: Big, swaggering, always crowded and boasting such curiosities as a restaurant specializing in Danish cuisine, the Maksoud Plaza Hotel, Alameda Campinas 150 in Bela Vista, has become something of a landmark since it opened 20 years ago. But the imposing atrium and 415 rooms are starting to show their age, and there is a certain air of snobbery that can be disconcerting. Doubles from $350; (55-11) 253-4411, fax (55-11) 253-4544.</p>
        <p>On the other side of Avenida Paulista, at Alameda Santos 1123, sits the Inter-Continental Sao Paulo. The 193 rooms here are larger than those at several other luxury hotels, the atmosphere is one of cool efficiency,  and there are many good places to eat within walking distance. Doubles are normally $400, but some are available through Sept. 15 at the ''Summer Options'' price of $200. Telephone (55-11) 3179-2600 or (800) 327-0200; fax (55-11) 3179-2669.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Year after year, Baby-Beef Rubaiyat is the runaway winner in every survey of Sao Paulo's best churrascarias, restaurants specializing in grilled meat. The cuts may seem unfamiliar to the American palate, but the meat here is extraordinarily tender and lean, perhaps because the restaurant has its own ranch where it raises cattle, hogs, sheep and chicken. Of the two branches, the more convenient is at Alameda Santos 86 in Paraiso. Dinner for two with beer, about $65; (55-11) 289-6366.</p>
        <p>In theory, Antiquarius, Alameda Lorena 1884 in Cerqueira Cesar, specializes solely in Portuguese cuisine. But one of its signature dishes is a singular mixture of Lusitanian and Brazilian ingredients: a startlingly delicate codfish moqueca, or stew, laced with coconut milk. The atmosphere is charmingly rustic. Dinner for two with a bottle of sparkling Portuguese vinho verde: about $125;  (55-11) 282-3015</p>
        <p>The menu at Amadeus, Rua Haddock Lobo 807 in Cerqueira Cesar, is devoted to seafood in all its forms, freshly caught just off the coast less than 50 miles away. Traditional Brazilian sauces, which make liberal use of coconut milk, palm oil, onions, tomato and peppers, are the main feature, but a terrific shrimp curry is also on the menu. Dinner for two with a bottle of Brazilian wine is about $110; (55-11) 3061-2859.</p>
        <p>In a city blessed with dozens of excellent Italian restaurants and cantinas, Massimo, at Alameda Santos 1826 in Cerqueira Cesar, stands at the head of the class. The osso buco is so tender it almost melts off the bone, and the cheeses, eggplant, peppers and olives used in the antipasto are extraordinarily fresh. Dinner for two is about $125 (no credit cards accepted); (55-11) 284-3011.</p>
        <p>For cheap, appetizing eating, Paulistanos often turn to restaurants offering food by the kilogram, most of which charge $4.50 to $5.50 a pound. There is a large concentration of these self-service buffet-style cafeterias in Rua Augusta. One that stands out for its varied menu and mouth-watering desserts is the Parque Avenida Grill, Avenida Paulista 1776; (55-11) 283-0201.</p>
        <p>WHAT'S DOING IN LARRY ROHTER is chief of the Rio de Janeiro bureau of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">LARRY ROHTER is chief of the Rio de Janeiro bureau of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
