<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hear Her Roar</title>
    <meta content="25STEINET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Editors' Note Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000625T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steiner, Wendy (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedan, Betty</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Life So Far (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E3DB113EF936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hear Her Roar</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Wendy Steiner</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steiner, Wendy (Prof)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prof Wendy Steiner reviews book Life So Far by Betty Friedan; photo (M))</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIFE SO FAR</p>
        <p>By Betty Friedan.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 399 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIFE SO FAR</p>
        <p>By Betty Friedan.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 399 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $26.</p>
        <p>THAT ''wonderful massive change in society'' we call Women's Liberation is in important part the brainchild of Betty Friedan, for it is no exaggeration to say that the ideas in ''The Feminine Mystique'' and the legislation urged on by the National Organization for Women have permanently altered the American psyche. She is truly a Mother of Us All. But do we have to like our mother? Acknowledging her ''reputation as a ferocious witch,'' Ms. Friedan would say no. ''I don't think it's a requirement to be sweet to be an effective leader or activist,'' she argues. In a memoirist, however, lack of sweetness is less forgivable, and the ''personal truth'' that ''Life So Far'' reveals cannot help giving us pause. To read this memoir is to grasp the labor and pain and sacrifices of one's mother without necessarily loving her for her efforts.</p>
        <p>Friedan's earliest memory is of looking in the mirror at age 3 and seeing ''a tall girl,'' though she was then and ever afterward decidedly short. ''What made me see myself as tall back then in Peoria in my mother's room?'' she wonders. Was it the nascent I.Q. of 180, her father's exorbitant praise, an infant inkling that public achievement could be pumped up to heroic proportions as a replacement for personal happiness? Whatever the cause, history proved out the accuracy of the toddler's grandiosity. In 1970, as Friedan led women in a march down Fifth Avenue, Pete Hamill reported, ''All women looked six feet tall that day.''</p>
        <p>Friedan's ''Life So Far'' is a chronicle of outstanding accomplishments: summa cum laude at Smith; top graduate fellowship at Berkeley (declined); a paradigm-shattering best seller; the founding of N.O.W.; audiences with Indira Gandhi and the pope; a university chair as ''a live history maker''; a $1 million grant from the Ford Foundation. ''What I have done with my life is already history,'' she reflects, but with this memoir, new triumphs are added to the record. ''I think I must have gotten pregnant the first night I left my diaphragm out''; ''of course, I got pregnant the first week I left the diaphragm off again''; the New Journalism had not yet been invented, ''but I'd figured out for myself what was needed''; ''I had learned to master any field enough in 24 hours to understand and ask the right questions on the cutting edge''; of her million-dollar Ford grant, she remarks, ''I think it's deserved.''</p>
        <p>Her school's principal had told the young Betty Goldstein: ''You have a great talent for leadership. You must use it for good, not evil.'' She took his advice to heart, guided by her ''Jewish existential conscience, that sense . . . that I have to use my life to make the world better.'' She might more profitably have listened to her medieval literature professor: ''Miss Goldstein, you have no humility.''</p>
        <p>False humility, of course, is nothing to admire, but neither is lack of self-knowledge. Friedan's father, she says, preserved her every school essay in his safe and declared her childhood poems masterpieces. Nevertheless he refused to come to her graduation, and his comment that if she became a psychiatrist she ''might as well be a woman'' made her so worried about not being a woman that she quit graduate school. She told everyone she was leaving in order to support the Communist movement. Aware that this was a dodge, she nevertheless did not understand why she was so afraid of being unwomanly. She reports as if truly puzzled: ''For some reason, those tight sweaters which I began to fill out and my new high heels infuriated my father.'' When she presented her research proposal for the Berkeley fellowship, she noted that the professors were embarrassed ''as the words 'oral,' 'anal,' 'genital' . . . were tossed off so blithely by me. They decided to recommend me for the biggest science fellowship at Berkeley.''</p>
        <p>Intellectual work was sexual for her; men rewarded it. But at the same time it was not womanly; her father was not pleased. When he died, ''I moved in cold calculation to sleep with someone, anyone, as my father had accused me of doing.'' Her asthma flared up, as it did psychosomatically throughout her life. She hated the very mention of the words ''penis envy,'' but obliged Freud with a classic case of hysteria.</p>
        <p>Her mother, in her eyes, was the source of her unhappiness. ''My mother, Miriam, was beautiful. . . . Everything she did, she did perfectly.'' Miriam had gone to college for two years and worked, but had quit her job to marry and have children. She was ashamed of the big nose and foreign accent of her immigrant husband and frustrated at her constrained life as a Peoria housewife. Little Betty, already six feet tall in her mother's mirror, resolved to have a job so as not to be like her miserable mother. And yet whenever a career opportunity arose, she opted instead for being a ''woman,'' identifying herself as ''housewife'' on the census form even after she had become a successful journalist. ''It was a woman, in a family, that I yearned to be, a warmer, more supportive, affectionate woman than my mother,'' she writes. ''Though I was consumed with dread of her and, I suppose, hate, and even finally a kind of revulsion, there was a desperate yearning underneath for the love she couldn't give me. And only now do I begin to understand the emptiness and fragility beneath her assumed superiority, perfectionism, and the constant unrelenting put-down of her husband, her children, her women friends.''</p>
        <p>Such insights are rare in this memoir. Throughout, Friedan fails to connect her love-hate for her mother and the sexualized desire for her father to her politics, appearing unaccountably hostile and rigid in her views and inspiring antagonism in other feminists. Rather than being moved by ''sisterhood,'' she took as her model for self-realization her immigrant relatives' search for freedom. She declares the women's movement, therefore, a further stage of the American Revolution, and defines women's rights in mainly material terms as the need for equal job opportunity, equal pay for equal work, adequate and affordable child care, access to public accommodations and control over reproduction. Sex, image and the family could be left as they were. Simone de Beauvoir was ''silly'' to insist that society be entirely reorganized to separate the home and family from female identity; Kate Millett was ''warped'' in her diatribes against men and her ''abstract sexual extremism that didn't apply to women's lives''; Germaine Greer was guilty of ''naughty-child exhibitionism.'' In contrast, Betty Friedan could boast of being as good a mother as the archconservative Phyllis Schlafly and at the same time of having won women the right to enter any profession or bar in the country.</p>
        <p>Unlike the radically chic New York feminists, she spoke for the mainstream: the women of Peoria, women like her mother! Lesbians alienated these women, endangering the movement. ''It was outrageous to question the value of heterosexual relationships''; before taking back the night for women, you needed to take back the day. Ferociously protective of the rights she valued, she declared other women's concerns peripheral and unworthy. At last she had become mainstream.</p>
        <p>The scandalous revelation of this memoir is that throughout her years of activism Betty Friedan allowed her husband to get away with beating her. Wedded to her father's approval and unable either to identify with or to separate herself from her mother, this ''two-headed lady'' remained utterly split, and yet defined the goal of feminism as healing the divide between fiery feminist and loving mother, career woman and heterosexual partner.</p>
        <p>Now 79 years old, Friedan still inhabits this duality, describing herself as ''this dignified white-haired grande dame'' who goes around swearing in public. Her memoir ends with the announcement that she and her ex-husband have become friends. One of the path-breaking chapters in ''The Feminine Mystique'' is entitled ''The Problem That Has No Name'' (a perhaps unintended echo of ''the love that dare not speak its name''). Friedan's phrase brings the lie of the happy housewife into the light of day in order to dispel its power. But in ''Life So Far,'' Betty Friedan's lies to herself remain unnamed and fearsome. She leaves us in a sad bind, aware of the public good that came of her ''mothering'' but unable to feel that her struggle was truly carried out on our behalf.</p>
        <p>Wendy Steiner, the Richard L. Fisher professor of English at the University of Pennsylvania and director of the Penn Humanities Forum, is the author of ''The Scandal of Pleasure.''</p>
        <p>Editors' Note:  June 25, 2000, Sunday  A review of ''Life So Far,'' by Betty Friedan, on Page 10 of The Times Book Review today cites the author's assertion that ''throughout her years of activism'' she ''allowed her husband to get away with beating her.''</p>
        <p>The review should have taken note of Carl Friedan's response, in a letter in The Times on May 18 and in an editors' note in this space on May 26, that the accusation is ''blatantly untrue.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Editors' Note: June 25, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A review of ''Life So Far,'' by Betty Friedan, on Page 10 of The Times Book Review today cites the author's assertion that ''throughout her years of activism'' she ''allowed her husband to get away with beating her.''</p>
        <p>The review should have taken note of Carl Friedan's response, in a letter in The Times on May 18 and in an editors' note in this space on May 26, that the accusation is ''blatantly untrue.''</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Wendy Steiner, the Richard L. Fisher professor of English at the University of Pennsylvania and director of the Penn Humanities Forum, is the author of ''The Scandal of Pleasure.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
