<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Big Decisions? They're All Yours</title>
    <meta content="25STOL$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Women's Health" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PATIENT POWER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pediatrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0DE1E3EF936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Big Decisions? They're All Yours</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sheryl Gay Stolberg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>*Women are becoming increasingly familiar with challenge, and agony, of medical decision making; revolution in patients' rights and explosion of information on Internet and elsewhere is enabling women to educate themselves as never before; doctors' attitudes have changed as well; once derided for their paternalism, many now expect patients to research their own diseases and make decisions on their own; studies show that women are gatekeepers of family health, making decisions not only for themselves, but also for their spouses, children and parents; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUSAN HOROWITZ faced the classic patient's dilemma. Three different doctors had given her three different recommendations about whether to undergo chemotherapy for her breast cancer. ''I found the idea of chemo really frightening,'' she recalled. Chemotherapy, she knew, would throw her into menopause - and she was only 45 years old.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUSAN HOROWITZ faced the classic patient's dilemma. Three different doctors had given her three different recommendations about whether to undergo chemotherapy for her breast cancer. ''I found the idea of chemo really frightening,'' she recalled. Chemotherapy, she knew, would throw her into menopause - and she was only 45 years old.</p>
        <p>It took six weeks for her to decide to do it. ''It was agonizing,'' Ms. Horowitz, now 49 and living in Los Angeles, said, referring to the decision. But she was determined not to turn it over to a doctor. ''It was a huge challenge, an intellectual challenge, to get all the information and to do the research,'' she said. ''And I actually took up that challenge.''</p>
        <p>Women today are increasingly familiar with the challenge, and the agony, of medical decision making. Over the past two decades, a revolution in patients' rights and an explosion of information in books, newspapers, magazines and cyberspace have enabled women, and men, to educate themselves as never before, Doctors' attitudes have changed, too; once derided for their paternalism, many now expect patients to research their own diseases and make decisions on their own.</p>
        <p>That is both a blessing and a burden for women, who have traditionally bee the gatekeepers of family health. Women make choices not only for themselves, studies show, but also for their husbands, children and parents. According to the Society for Women's Health Research, a nonprofit group in Washington, women, who account for 52 percent of the population, make three-quarters of the health-care decisions in the United States and spend nearly two out of three health-care dollars. About 59 percent of doctors' visits are made by women, the society says, and 59 percent of prescription drugs are purchased by women.</p>
        <p>Women also face some of medicine's thorniest questions. The plethora of alternative therapies is complicating the medical landscape for women, as well as men. And these changes are occurring within the framework of reduced reimbursements for doctors under managed care, which means that medical professionals are busier than ever, and have less time to talk through complex problems with their patients. The result, experts say, is a case of information overload among patients, particularly women, in the information age.</p>
        <p>''It is an overwhelming task for women, and consumers in general, to be able to sort through the information they find and make decisions,'' said Amy Alliana, the program director of the National Women's Health Network. ''Patients are in the position of having to do a lot of work on their own.''</p>
        <p>Not every patient is as eager as Ms. Horowit to be fully in charge. Katherine Russell Rich, whose book, ''The Red Devil: To Hell with Cancer and Back,'' recounts her experience with breast cancer, remembers the terror she felt when her oncologist explained the treatment options: ''He was trying to draw pictures of the breast. All I remember is it looked like he was drawing targets. Finally, I said, 'But what should I do?' And I remember this horrifying moment when he said, 'I can't tell you.' ''</p>
        <p>Until fairly recently, those words - ''I can't tell you,'' - rarely crossed a doctor's lips. ''Patients always used to say, 'Well, what would you do if it were your brother, or what would you do if it were you?' '' said George J. Annas, the chairman of the health law department at the Boston University School of Public Health. ''Many doctors are comfortable now saying, 'It's not me, it's you, and you're the one who has to decide.' ''</p>
        <p>To dr. Annas, that is a welcome change. ''I think people have some responsibility for their own decisions,'' he said. ''Patients should accept this as part of the price of the wonders of modern medicine.''</p>
        <p>Others see patient autonomy running amok. Carl F. Schneider, a professor of law and internal medicine at the University of Michigan who has recently written a book on medical decision-making, said that doctors have become so enamored of a patient's right to choose that they are abdicating their responsibilities as healers. He has a term for what happened to Ms Rich - ''mandatory autonomy,'' a practice that he said stems in part from fear of lawsuits. Doctors, after all, can be sued over whatever decision they make. But is the patient makes the decision, who is to blame?</p>
        <p>Yet Professor Schneider says that as patients get older, and sicker, they are less likely to want to make their own medical decisions. The same patient may want more, or less, autonomy at any given time. And he turned up this surprising tidbit: Sometimes the best-educated patients are the least likely to want to make their own medical decisions. These patients, he said, often tell him: ''Look, I'm an expert in my field; I know how difficult it is to talk about technical problems to laypeople, and how much expert thinking is passive thinking, not fully articulated. So what I try to do is pick the very best doctor I can, and then do what he or she says.''</p>
        <p>The current era of patient empowerment has its roots in the debate over whether dying people had the right to refuse life-prolonging therapies. The 1976 court case of Karen Quilan, the New Jersey woman who parents fought to withdraw her life support, established broad public support for this right, and with it the notion that sick people, not doctors, should be in charge of their medical decisions.</p>
        <p>But it was not until the 80's, said Dr. Albert Mulley, chief of general medicine at Massachusetts General Hospital, that doctors signed on to the idea. The turning point, Dr. Mulley thinks, was a series of studies that he and Dr. Jack Wennberg, of Dartmouth College, conducted on ''practice variations.'' The pair demonstrated vast differences in medical practice based on where a patient lived. Men in Washington State, for instance, were five to six times as likely to undergo surgery for prostate cancer as men in Connecticut. Two percent of breast cancer patients in Ogden, Utah, got breast-conserving surgery, compared with 35 percent in Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>The notion that geography dictated treatment ''shook the foundational belief that medicine was determined by good science,'' Dr. Mulley said. The medical establishment responded by pushing for treatment guidelines. But guidelines are based on statistics and probabilities, and experts now know that a patient's own values are as important as the numbers, if not more so.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mulley uses the example of porstate cancer: is a man with the disease willing to undergo surgery at the risk that it will cause sexual dysfunction and incontinence? Anyone who thinks the choice is an easy one need only study New York Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's televised news conference announcing that he was no longer a candidate for the Senate. Here was a man who had made decisions all his life declaring that after weeks of studying his treatment options, he was still undecided.</p>
        <p>Today the ideal is ''shared decision making,'' a concept promoted by a nonprofit organization, the Foundation for Informed Medical Decision Making, which Drs. Mulley and Wennberg founded in 1989. The idea is that doctors and patients can hash out their options together. But that takes time, and as anyone who has ever been in a doctor's office knows, time is typically in very short supply.</p>
        <p>''If they give me short shrift and don't answer my questions, then I leave the doctor,'' said Nena O'Neill, a New York City writer who was successfully treated 11 years ago for a rare cancer of the nose. This was in the days before the Internet; Ms. O'Neill said she flew to four different hospitals and hired a medical researcher to study her treatment choices.</p>
        <p>Not everyone has that opportunity, of course; 44.3 million Americans lack health insurance, and for them, questions about medical decision making a patient autonomy are academic. But Ms. O'Neill, who is 76 and still seeing doctors for painful after-effects from her cancer treatment, has sage advice for patients of all stripes: bring a short list of written queations to the doctor, and be persistent.</p>
        <p>''You just have to say, 'Look, I have a few questions,' '' she said. ''I'm not going to take a half an hour. I'm only going to take five minutes. But it's important that you listen to me.''</p>
        <p>Yet even the most sensitive doctor, and the one with all the time in the world to listen, may not have all the answers. The biomedical revolution of the past two decades has yielded a flood of life-prolonging treatments, but the boom in medical research has also created confusion within the profession. The more scientists learn about a disease, it seems, the less certain they are about the right treatment.</p>
        <p>''The sad fact of life is that as you get down into the nitty-gritty, we simply don't know enough,'' said Dr. David J. Rothman, the direct of the Center for the Study of Society and Medicine at Columbia University. ''In a world where medical technology is getting all the more powered, and often accompanied by risks, nobody can decide for you.''</p>
        <p>That, at least, was the calculation that Susan Horowitz made when she received her breast cancer diagnosis. ''My first thought when I found out I had breast cancer was, 'This is something I can't run away from; I have to deal with it,' '' she said. ''And I did. I really felt like I was in charge.''</p>
        <p>PATIENT POWER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
