<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Body With a Mind of Its Own</title>
    <meta content="25MS.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Men &amp; Health" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209891"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LIVING WITH . . ."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Multiple Sclerosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Richard M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Multiple Sclerosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Multiple Sclerosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E0DB103FF936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Body With a Mind of Its Own</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard M. Cohen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Richard M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard M Cohen article on living with multiple sclerosis; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE diagnosis came with a perfunctory phone call. There was no mention of treatment, no helpful advice. I could feel the neurologist's shrug through the wire. I sat alone and in silence. I was only 25, and did not know what to do.</p>
        <p>All these years later, I'm still not sure what to do, except to live my life. No neurologist I've come across has much to offer, beyond a few new drugs. I reach out, but with nothing to touch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE diagnosis came with a perfunctory phone call. There was no mention of treatment, no helpful advice. I could feel the neurologist's shrug through the wire. I sat alone and in silence. I was only 25, and did not know what to do.</p>
        <p>All these years later, I'm still not sure what to do, except to live my life. No neurologist I've come across has much to offer, beyond a few new drugs. I reach out, but with nothing to touch.</p>
        <p>Whatever my difficulties, I know I am fortunate. Some people with multiple sclerosis, a degenerative disease of the central nervous system, are confined to wheelchairs or to their beds, unable to fend for themselves. I move slowly, hobble a bit and sometimes stumble and fall in the street, but at least I can walk. I try to remain upbeat; my neurologist once accused me of living in denial, but I denied it.</p>
        <p>Still, there is much I cannot do. I no longer drive. I have to cede control and admit dependency. I lean on others regularly, and I hate it. Days are arduous, small tasks difficult. I take five minutes to button a shirt, five more to tie a necktie. And I can barely stay awake to go out in the evening. The betting at dinner parties these days is whether I will drop and drown in my coffee.</p>
        <p>For me, living with M.S. is all about navigating an obstacle course. Crossing the street when I cannot see the other side, finding an address when I cannot read numbers at any distance, climbing stairs with feet that drag. Shooting baskets with my kids when my right arm has no strength.</p>
        <p>And mine is a mind game, a matter of maintaining emotional equilibrium and holding onto optimism. Self-esteem suffers with the inability to perform simple tasks. I just cannot get used to admitting that I am unable to do something.</p>
        <p>Cognitive problems are on the increase. My confusion with a child's homework can be humiliating; I know the kids prefer now to do math and spelling with their mom. The black holes where there were once specific words and thoughts make up a map of frustration and anger. Why is this so difficult? What was I thinking? These questions come with greater frequency.</p>
        <p>Ambiguity and uncertainty are parts of life, of course, and I have learned to live with them. But not every worry is so manageable. I am the third generation in my family to stumble and fall with multiple sclerosis.</p>
        <p>What about my children?</p>
        <p>LIVING WITH . . . Richard M. Cohen, 52, produces television programs for Web sites and is a consultant on science and the press for the National Academy of Sciences.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Richard M. Cohen, 52, produces television programs for Web sites and is a consultant on science and the press for the National Academy of Sciences.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
