<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Pediatricians, a Struggle Against the 'New Morbidity'</title>
    <meta content="25LANG$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Women's Health" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209897"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FAMILY CARE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lang, Anne Adams</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pediatrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E0DC1E3FF936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1477" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Pediatricians, a Struggle Against the 'New Morbidity'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE ADAMS LANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lang, Anne Adams</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pediatricians are increasingly taking on responsiblity of addressing children's emotional and behavioral problems as well as their medical ones; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is a barely perceptible, almost wistful, longing for the time when his practice largely consisted of curing childhood diseases. Measles, mumps, chicken pox -- these were definable ailments that would likely go away with proper treatment. Now, Dr. Jack Swanson, a pediatrician in Ames, Iowa, spends his days dealing with more elusive problems: depressed children, anorexic and bulimic teenagers, sexually precocious tweens, young substance abusers, younger perpetrators and victims of violence.</p>
        <p>In the heartland, on the East Coast and the West, America's 55,000 pediatricians are no longer just baby doctors dispensing inoculations, cough syrups and bromides. They have become de facto psychiatrists and subspecialists. They are child welfare advocates, conduits to other social services and navigators of byzantine H.M.O.'s. They are trench warriors in the battle against the ''new morbidity.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is a barely perceptible, almost wistful, longing for the time when his practice largely consisted of curing childhood diseases. Measles, mumps, chicken pox -- these were definable ailments that would likely go away with proper treatment. Now, Dr. Jack Swanson, a pediatrician in Ames, Iowa, spends his days dealing with more elusive problems: depressed children, anorexic and bulimic teenagers, sexually precocious tweens, young substance abusers, younger perpetrators and victims of violence.</p>
        <p>In the heartland, on the East Coast and the West, America's 55,000 pediatricians are no longer just baby doctors dispensing inoculations, cough syrups and bromides. They have become de facto psychiatrists and subspecialists. They are child welfare advocates, conduits to other social services and navigators of byzantine H.M.O.'s. They are trench warriors in the battle against the ''new morbidity.''</p>
        <p>''Sex, alcohol and drugs, these problems have always been there, but they've shifted to a younger age in the last 20 years,'' Dr. Swanson observed, reflecting on two-and-a-half decades of hands-on experience. ''We find now that at ages 8 and 10, children are talking about these kinds of things.'' As a result, he said, ''There's a lot more time being spent by pediatricians on emotional, behavioral and school problems.''</p>
        <p>More and more, the psychosocial aspects of childhood and adolescence are muscling out the more traditional medical functions, making the calculus of pediatrics complex. Immunizations have reduced the number of children felled by rubella or even by flu. Advances in treatments and surgeries have turned even always-fatal diseases into more chronic conditions. As Dr. Swanson noted, ''Fortunately there aren't as many real sick children who require time in the hospital the way they used to.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, headline-grabbing tragedies -- the Columbine High School massacre, elementary-school-age rapists -- have set society's teeth on edge. Parents have an ever-tougher time distinguishing between normal bumps in the developmental road and serious disorders.</p>
        <p>''When it comes to suicidal ideation or sexual precocity, parents will, generally speaking, only raise these topics when they're in crisis,'' said Katherine Peets Grimm, a Manhattan. ''When a child seems to be doing well, they're more likely to bring up Lyme Disease.''</p>
        <p>Identifying the trouble spots is not easy. ''The first step now is that you look for the signs of distress,'' said Dr. David Kaplan, the chief director of adolescent medicine at The Children's Hospital in Denver. ''The high rates of suicide, depression, certainly violence, sexuality and substance abuse are so prevalent in society that when children and adolescents come for a 'well' visit, you inquire about signs and symptoms of depression.''</p>
        <p>Many of these problems have been around for generations. But they often went unrecognized, undiagnosed and untreated unless, or until, they could no longer be ignored. To an extent, the rise in the number of reported cases is a function of better screening, Dr. Kaplan said. Other dangerous behaviors, like eating disorders, are also on the rise.</p>
        <p>''Most of us working in the field see an increase, and it's not just a matter of recognizing it,'' said Dr. Kaplan, who works only with teenagers. ''We're seeing kids coming in at 65 percent of their ideal body weight and with heart rate in the low 30's. We are seeing more boys than we ever have. All that is very different than five years ago.''</p>
        <p>One of his patients, Dawn Foster, came into his care in September 1997, when she was hospitalized for anorexia and profound underlying depression. Her mother, Joan, a biology professor at Metropolitan State College, noticed that Dawn, then 14, was losing weight rapidly, 1 to 2 pounds a week, about 20 pounds over three months. Her pediatrician warned Dawn that more weight loss would lead to hospitalization.</p>
        <p>''My friends got me into eating disorders,'' Dawn said. ''When you have people around like that, you think about it more. I think it was a big attention-getting issue. I would sit there and say, 'I'm fat,' for the attention. But the more you say it, the more you believe it.'' She reported, too, that many of her peers use drugs -- mainly marijuana -- and are sexually active.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, she spent several months in the psychiatric unit of The Children's Hospital, where she met Dr. Kaplan. Over the past two years, Dawn has seen him once or twice a week, and relies on him to be her supporter, to protect the privacy of their conversations and serve as a bridge between her and her parents.</p>
        <p>Two-and-a-half years later, Dawn is off the antidepressants that helped put a floor under her free fall. She has put 30 pounds on her 5-foot-2-inch frame. She will graduate from high school in the Denver suburb of Wheat Ridge, and attend a Christian university nearby.</p>
        <p>She still confides in Dr. Kaplan, saying she is lucky to have found him, but suggesting that he is an anomaly. ''There's no place really to go with these kinds of issues,'' she said. ''Nobody I know would talk to their pediatrician.''</p>
        <p>What makes it especially thorny, Dawn said, is that ''independence starts in middle school, and it's not the cool thing to be with your parents a lot. Too often, parents take the approach that it's their kids' age and they'll grow out of it. But when they get to high school, it doesn't change. Parents aren't addressing reality.''</p>
        <p>She added, ''Maybe if doctors open up, and there's confidence that your doctor isn't going to tell your parents everything, kids would be more willing to talk.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the American Academy of Pediatrics, in a recent and extensive report, made it plain that pediatricians must be trained to recognize and deal with the growing percentage of children who are developing ''severe developmental-behavioral pathology, placing them in need of more intensive therapy.''</p>
        <p>That produces another quandary. ''While there's a growing recognition of the problems, of the consequences and sequelae of those problems by pediatricians, managed care isn't financing treatment,'' said Katherine Sundstrom, a pediatric psychiatrist in Brooklyn. The pressure is on primary-care doctors to put out the fires. ''I tend to get cases only after they have been inadvertently mishandled,'' Dr. Sundstrom said. ''Primary-care doctors aren't educated to treat certain problems, but they're being forced to.''</p>
        <p>A case in point: a doctor at a pediatric clinic told the mother of an aggressive, hyperactive preschool-age boy that her deficient parenting skills were to blame. There was nothing that parenting classes could not cure for her son, the mother was told.</p>
        <p>''It didn't work,'' Dr. Sundstrom said. ''She persisted and fought with the pediatrician to get a referral to me. After doing a complete history and evaluation, I found that he had a severe anxiety disorder. He's doing much better now. But the point is, pediatricians can't pick up the subtleties.''</p>
        <p>At the DeVos Children's Hospital pediatric clinic in Grand Rapids, Mich., Dr. Edward Cox administers to inner-city children and teenagers. Besides gang violence and sexually transmitted diseases, he must cope with growing poverty levels.</p>
        <p>''We've got people who don't know if they'll be living in the same apartment next month, or will have enough food on the table, let alone if they can pay for a prescription for a kid's ear infection,'' Dr. Cox said. ''Poverty, drugs, poor education, those were there a generation ago. But it's a matter of magnitude now.''</p>
        <p>It is also a matter of trying to maneuver children on Medicaid into a managed-care system. ''My colleagues want to send a child to a pediatric endocrinologist to deal with diabetes, but the H.M.O. refuses to pay for a pediatric subspecialist,'' Dr. Cox said. ''If I put down a psychiatric diagnosis, the H.M.O. won't deal with it because I'm not a psychiatrist.'' The result: he and other primary-care pediatricians are managing medications they would prefer to leave in specially trained hands.</p>
        <p>''The 'new morbidity' is not a 'reimbursable morbidity,' '' said Dr. Ramone Murphy, a Manhattan pediatrician. ''Even a family that seems to be doing well can be nailed by the costs and constraints of their health plan. It results in children not getting the medicine they need. Pediatricians are scrambling.''</p>
        <p>FAMILY CARE Anne Adams Lang is a freelance writer specializing in political, social and health care issues.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Anne Adams Lang is a freelance writer specializing in political, social and health care issues.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
