<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Divorce, Italian Style</title>
    <meta content="25NICHOLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nicholson, Geoff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parks, Tim</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Destiny (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E4DB113EF936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1135" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Divorce, Italian Style</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Geoff Nicholson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nicholson, Geoff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Geoff Nicholson reviews book Destiny by Tim Parks (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DESTINY</p>
        <p>By Tim Parks.</p>
        <p>249 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Arcade Publishing. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DESTINY</p>
        <p>By Tim Parks.</p>
        <p>249 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Arcade Publishing. $24.95.</p>
        <p>Tim Parks's new novel, his 10th, has a great opening. The narrator, Christopher Burton, learns that Marco, his schizophrenic son, has committed suicide by stabbing himself with a screwdriver. His first reaction, however, is not shock or grief; he thinks that now, at last, he can leave his hateful wife. ''Destiny'' examines how and why he arrives at this grotesque response.</p>
        <p>Burton is an English writer who is based in Italy; he has repudiated his career in journalism in order to write a magnum opus about ''national character and the predictability of human behavior.'' His Italian wife, Mara, comes from a poor and minor aristocratic family, wears lots of lipstick and has ''explosive'' hair. She is in many ways ''typically'' Italian. Their fights go along the lines of ''You're so cold and English, she said. . . . You're so fake and hysterical, I replied.'' The relationship has not been helped by Mara's refusal to learn to speak English; the language is, she says, ''hostile to my spirit.''</p>
        <p>They live in a curious economic never-never land. Burton managed to buy their daughter, Paola, an apartment without his wife knowing, and, even though he apparently hasn't worked as a journalist for some time, he and Mara are able to live in a London hotel for several months while they look, futilely, for property to buy there.</p>
        <p>Financially secure, they have plenty of energy to devote to ruining their own and, more crucially, their children's lives. Paola, we discover, was adopted from a Ukrainian orphanage, the daughter of a prostitute. The couple adopted her when it appeared they couldn't have children of their own, but Marco is soon born.</p>
        <p>There has been much warring over the children. Paola grew up plain and dull and has been neglected, while Marco has been fussed over and sent to an English-speaking school. When Marco's schizophrenia takes hold during his first year at college, he suddenly refuses to speak to his mother except in English. Other manifestations of his illness include rubbing mud in Mara's hair and locking her in a bathroom while he uses a hammer to smash the marble staircase of the family home, a place known as ''the house of ghosts.''</p>
        <p>Our narrator clearly has a great deal to mull over; he repeatedly asks himself how his troubles began, and he expresses a philosophical desire to ''go deeper.'' As his son's body is prepared for burial, he considers the children's upbringing, his own and his wife's affairs, his visits to a psychiatrist, and he frequently comes back to the ideas he's planning to use in his monumental book.</p>
        <p>''Destiny'' is written as a continuous internal monologue, one that is wandering yet repetitive and obsessive. Paragraphs go on for three or four pages and are occasionally reminiscent of Samuel Beckett or Thomas Bernhard, though Parks doesn't benefit from such comparisons. Burton's thinking can be hard to follow: ''Self is in pain and distress, I thought. That much is obvious. I decided not to buy a sandwich. Stigmata our past. Why do the Italians play with English like this? I wondered: FREE SHOP, AUTOGRILL. Pain identifies our sense of self, I thought. I must not eat or drink anything. The urine may be forced back into the kidneys.'' This may be a reasonable presentation of a mind at the end of its tether, but it's tedious to read.</p>
        <p>At first our narrator is simply unreliable, but as the book progresses we decide he's probably quite mad. At one point Burton is not sure whether he's speaking aloud or to himself. Consequently, we start to have doubts about his assessments of things. There are vague hints of sexual undercurrents between wife and son, and between son and adopted daughter, but do these exist only in Burton's mind?</p>
        <p>One is also at a loss to know whether Burton's putative masterwork is to be taken seriously. No doubt there is a nonfiction book to be written about nationality and destiny (Tim Parks appears to have written several of them), but Burton's musings are feeble and pretentious, and he seems to be interested only in the Italians and the English.</p>
        <p>In the book's final scene, following a disastrous interview with former Prime Minister Giulio Andreotti, Burton, who now seems to be demented -- among other things, he is hearing his dead son's voice -- returns to the family house and finds the place in darkness, lighted only by candles. He thinks his wife has killed herself too, and we're treated to more purple prose: ''Mara too has chosen to extinguish herself. My Mara. That's why the voice is calling. He is calling her to himself. Beyond the grave. Beyond the epiphanic veil. Beyond the stones and monuments. . . . I will fix her photograph to her tomb.'' I'm not sure whether Parks wants us to think this is just the overwrought, and perhaps comical, rambling of a madman -- or whether he wants us to take it as moving poetic prose. I suspect he wants to have it both ways.</p>
        <p>When Burton gets to the bedroom, however, his wife isn't dead at all. There's been a power outage, and she lighted the candles so he could find his way upstairs. Burton climbs in bed with her, they profess love for each other and agree they'll leave Italy and find somewhere new to live as soon as possible. And that's it.</p>
        <p>Once again, I'm not sure whether we're meant to take this bathos at face value. Do we accept that Burton's descent into madness is now over and that he's reconciled with his wife, who loved him all along, and whom he misunderstood and misrepresented because of his mad grief? The problem with this interpretation is that Burton's descent and return, by my calculation, takes place over only two and a half days -- not enough time for this journey to have the significance that Parks loads onto it. Yet if we don't accept that these characters have achieved some sort of redemption, then all we've done is read a madman's ramblings. Either way it's unsatisfactory.</p>
        <p>If we really want to think about nationality and destiny, it's worth saying that this seems a very European book rather than an English or American one. The internalization of the narrative, the plotlessness and the absence of graphic sex and violence are refreshingly alien.</p>
        <p>Reading ''Destiny'' I kept thinking of another novel that involves a father and a schizophrenic son -- Kingsley Amis's ''Stanley and the Women,'' a book that is simultaneously lighter and more profound than this one. It also seems considerably more ''English.'' I wonder if that's why it was so much more appealing to this English reviewer.</p>
        <p>Geoff Nicholson's most recent novel is ''Female Ruins.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Geoff Nicholson's most recent novel is ''Female Ruins.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
