<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Your Thyroid May Be Talking, but Is the Doctor Listening?</title>
    <meta content="25WILK$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Women's Health" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000716T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Thyroid Gland</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilkinson, Donna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE3DC1E3FF936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1313" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Your Thyroid May Be Talking, but Is the Doctor Listening?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DONNA WILKINSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilkinson, Donna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some 13 million Americans suffer from thyroid disorders, most of them women, but more than half do not know it; thyroid disorders are widely undiagnosed and misdiagnosed because symptoms can be ambiguous and doctors do not make simple blood test, particularly under managed care; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOME 13 million Americans suffer from thyroid disorders, most of them women, including Barbara Bush, Tipper Gore and the Olympic track star Gail Devers. But more than half don't know it.</p>
        <p>Thyroid disorders, experts say,  are among the most undiagnosed and misdiagnosed problems in the United States. Doctors generally don't examine the thyroid. Disorders come on slowly, and the symptoms can be ambiguous.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOME 13 million Americans suffer from thyroid disorders, most of them women, including Barbara Bush, Tipper Gore and the Olympic track star Gail Devers. But more than half don't know it.</p>
        <p>Thyroid disorders, experts say,  are among the most undiagnosed and misdiagnosed problems in the United States. Doctors generally don't examine the thyroid. Disorders come on slowly, and the symptoms can be ambiguous.</p>
        <p>''The test, which is a simple blood test, is not part of a routine exam and is becoming less so because of managed care,'' said Dr. Robert J. McConnell, a thyroid specialist and an associate attending physician at New York Presbyterian Hospital. ''Managed care groups don't like fishing expeditions. They don't like to pay for tests for no good reason.''</p>
        <p>So the test is usually ordered only if the patient demands it or if the doctor suggests it, Dr. McConnell said.</p>
        <p>Awareness is critical for women, who, for as yet unexplained reasons, are eight times more at risk than men. ''It probably has something to do with the immune system,'' said Dr. Lawrence C. Wood, the president and medical director of the Thyroid Foundation of America and a co-author of ''Your Thyroid.'' ''Thyroid inflammation is caused by a foul-up in the immune system, and women seem to be more affected by autoimmune diseases like lupus, M.S. and rheumatoid arthritis.''</p>
        <p>A woman's susceptibility is increased by certain factors, Dr. Wood said: a family history of thyroid disease; pregnancy (about 5 percent to 10 percent of women develop postpartum thyroid problems); aging (at least 1 woman in every 10 has signs of a failing thyroid by age 50); smoking; and menopause. Because symptoms are nonspecific, they are often ignored.</p>
        <p>''Many women go to doctors for years with the same coterie of symptoms and are told that they're stressed, depressed, P.M.S.-ed, getting older, menopausal or tired because they're working and have two children,'' said Mary J. Shomon, the author of ''Living Well With Hypothyroidism'' and founder of a Web site (www.thyroid.about.com) and a patient-advocacy newsletter. ''And women tend to write their symptoms off too quickly.''</p>
        <p>Several months after Susan Kane gave birth to her son, she noticed that she was starving all the time. ''I would often get up twice in the middle of the night and have a complete meal,'' she said. Ms. Kane, who lives outside New York City and is the editor of BabyTalk magazine, thought her body was signaling the need for more calories to support her breast-feeding. Then her weight plummeted to seven pounds less than before she was pregnant, and she developed heart palpitations, insomnia, muscle weakness and protruding eyes. Even then, Ms. Kane, who is in her early 40's, figured that she was out of shape and stressed from the baby.</p>
        <p>Her doctor at the time said it was anxiety. Then one day her heart was racing so wildly, she rushed to a cardiologist. ''He put two and two together and sent me to an endocrinologist,'' she said. The diagnosis? Graves' disease, an overactive thyroid condition that speeds up metabolism.</p>
        <p>Rosanna Bruno, 30, a Brooklyn artist, felt out of breath just walking up a flight of stairs. She gained weight and developed digestive problems, along with cramps in her legs and hands. But it was the hair loss that finally sent her to the doctor.</p>
        <p>She was told she was depressed and should be on medication. She went to a psychotherapist. ''I would tell her, 'Yesterday my leg felt numb.' And she would say: 'Let's talk about what it means to be numb. Are you trying to disappear?' '' Finally, Ms. Bruno saw a doctor outside her H.M.O. The diagnosis? Underactive thyroid, or hypothyroidism, which slows the metabolism.</p>
        <p>Although the thyroid has a low profile in the medical universe, it plays a major role in the body. This butterfly-shaped gland at the base of the neck manufactures key hormones, thyroxine (T4) and triiodothyronine (T3), which affect metabolism, growth, nerves, muscles and circulation. The thyroid is kept in check by the pituitary gland, which sends the thyroid-stimulating hormone.</p>
        <p>But autoimmune disease, infection, hormonal imbalance or hereditary conditions can cause the thyroid to malfunction. Thyroid problems fall into two categories: functional, like hypothyroidism and hyperthyroidism, and structural, like nodules and goiters.</p>
        <p>Hypothyroidism occurs when the gland produces too little hormone and the metabolic rate slows down; the most common cause is Hashimoto's thyroiditis, an autoimmune disease that creates antibodies that attack the thyroid gland.</p>
        <p>Hyperthyroidism results when the gland produces too much hormone and the metabolic rate speeds up; the most common cause is Graves' disease, an autoimmune condition that creates antibodies that stimulate the thyroid.</p>
        <p>Nodules are growths on the thyroid; most are noncancerous, though they should be screened. A goiter is a swelling in the throat caused by an enlarged thyroid. It is generally caused by a lack of iodine and is rare in the United States.</p>
        <p>The goal of treatment is to return thyroid hormone levels to normal; left unchecked, hypothyroidism can cause heart disease and high cholesterol. Because an underactive thyroid is not producing enough T4 hormone, hormone replacement is prescribed; common brands of synthetic thyroxine are Synthroid, Levoxyl and Levothroid. (As an alternative, Ms. Shomon said, some patients respond better to a natural thyroid hormone derived from pigs; a common brand is Armour Thyroid.)</p>
        <p>For an overactive thyroid, which produces too much hormone, there are three options: radioactive iodine, a onetime oral treatment that destroys the gland; antithyroid drugs, which have a success rate of 1 out of 3; or surgery to remove the gland.</p>
        <p>When the gland is destroyed, hyperthyroid patients become hypothyroid and need to take daily hormone medication. Left unchecked, hyperthyroidism can lead to heart failure and osteoporosis.</p>
        <p>Medication may take some fine-tuning. ''Some people who are taking just the T4 hormone may be suffering with continued symptoms,'' Ms. Shomon said. ''The conventional wisdom among more conservative endocrinologists is that your body will convert the T4 hormone into the T3 hormone. But a New England Journal study in 1999 found that some people seem to be deficient in the T3 hormone or are unable to convert it for whatever reason, and they do better with an additional T3 supplement.''</p>
        <p>For her overactive thyroid, Ms. Kane was at first given Levoxyl. ''But I was still feeling tired,'' she said. ''I happened to pick up a book by an endocrinologist who recommended lowering the Levoxyl and adding Cytomel, which is the synthetic form of T3. My doctor agreed, changed my medication, and I felt better within a week.''</p>
        <p>Since she got her diagnosis, Ms. Kane has tried to raise other people's awareness of thyroid problems. She frequently covers them in her magazine, because they can powerfully affect pregnancy and a mother's ability to function. ''Now, whenever a friend tells me she feels tired, I tell her to get her thyroid tested,'' she said.</p>
        <p>And if a doctor says it's all in your head? ''Find another doctor,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Click Here for Help</p>
        <p>These sites offer online information about thyroid disorders:</p>
        <p>WWW.TSH.ORG  Operated by the Thyroid Foundation of America, this site focuses on education and offers articles, news and doctor referrals.</p>
        <p>WWW.ENDOCRINEWEB.COM  This site, developed by doctors, offers information about thyroid disorders and surgery; it provides chat rooms, support groups and doctor referrals.</p>
        <p>WWW.THYROID.ABOUT.COM and WWW.THYROID-INFO.COM</p>
        <p>Mary J. Shomon, author of ''Living Well With Hypothyroidism,'' developed these sites, which offer articles, links to other thyroid sites, a bulletin board and a thyroid chat room.</p>
        <p>Donna Wilkinson writes about health for The New York Times and other publications.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 16, 2000, Sunday  Because of an editing error, an article in the special Women's Health section on June 25 about  thyroid disease misstated the use  of two synthetic hormones, Levoxyl and Cytomel. They are prescribed for people with underactive thyroids, not overactive ones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 16, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article in the special Women's Health section on June 25 about</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;thyroid disease misstated the use</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;of two synthetic hormones, Levoxyl and Cytomel. They are prescribed for people with underactive thyroids, not overactive ones.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Donna Wilkinson writes about health for The New York Times and other publications.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
