<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Researchers Fix Their Sights on an Elusive Silent Killer</title>
    <meta content="25LOWR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Women's Health" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209890"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ovaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Cancer Institute</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lowry, Vicky</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Ovarian Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E1DC103FF936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1276" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Researchers Fix Their Sights on an Elusive Silent Killer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VICKY LOWRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lowry, Vicky</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ovarian cancer is often called the silent killer because it is difficult to detect, but research money is at an all-time high; National Cancer Insitute initiative and other research efforts promise advances in early testing; early warning signs of disease described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OVARIAN cancer has been nicknamed the silent killer because it is difficult to detect. When found, it has often spread beyond the ovaries and is too advanced to cure. Even the symptoms are vague and easily ignored: who hasn't felt bloated and tired from time to time?</p>
        <p>But experts in the field say that a new National Cancer Institute initiative, the Ovarian Cancer Early Detection Program, promises to yield more sensitive, highly specific -- and thus accurate -- screening tests for ovarian cancer within the next five years. The program, which unites 26 comprehensive cancer centers in the United States along with more than 100 scientists worldwide, is planning to enroll more than 10,000 asymptomatic women to develop new means for accurately detecting early-stage cancer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OVARIAN cancer has been nicknamed the silent killer because it is difficult to detect. When found, it has often spread beyond the ovaries and is too advanced to cure. Even the symptoms are vague and easily ignored: who hasn't felt bloated and tired from time to time?</p>
        <p>But experts in the field say that a new National Cancer Institute initiative, the Ovarian Cancer Early Detection Program, promises to yield more sensitive, highly specific -- and thus accurate -- screening tests for ovarian cancer within the next five years. The program, which unites 26 comprehensive cancer centers in the United States along with more than 100 scientists worldwide, is planning to enroll more than 10,000 asymptomatic women to develop new means for accurately detecting early-stage cancer.</p>
        <p>''There is a clear-cut change in priority in the research community,'' said Dr. Gordon Mills at the University of Texas Anderson Cancer Institute in Houston. He is leading research on a new blood test for ovarian cancer as well as on the underlying causes of the disease. ''There is a high level of optimism that effective markers for ovarian cancer will be discovered,'' he said. ''The opportunities are greater than ever before.''</p>
        <p>The research money is at an all-time high, too. Financing for ovarian cancer has risen substantially in the last decade, to $63 million today from under $10 million in 1990, according to the National Cancer Institute.</p>
        <p>This year, 1 in 55 women will be told she has ovarian cancer. (It is rarer than breast cancer, in which the lifetime risk is 1 in 8.) That translates into 23,100 newly affected women in the United States. Thirty percent -- primarily those whose cancer is detected in its earliest stages, when it has not spread beyond the ovaries -- will survive at least five years following surgery to remove the malignant tumors and chemotherapy. For a majority, however, detection will come too late, resulting in a death toll of about 14,000 women a year.</p>
        <p>''Women need to know about the symptoms and inform their physicians so that at least the possibility of ovarian cancer is on their radar screen,'' said Patricia Goldman, a seven-year survivor of the disease and the president of the Ovarian Cancer National Alliance, a group that is trying to raise awareness of the disease. ''Unfortunately, we're accustomed to discomfort below the bellybutton.''</p>
        <p>Ovarian cancer most often strikes postmenopausal women who are over 50. Women with one or more first-degree relatives, that is, mother, sister or aunt, who have had the disease are at slightly greater risk. It is equally likely to be transmitted from the father's side as from the mother's, said Dr. Beth Karlan, the director of gynecologic oncology at Cedars-Sinai Medical Center in Los Angeles. Women with a history of breast cancer are also at higher risk.</p>
        <p>''The first step for women is to find out their own family history and discuss it with their physician,'' Dr. Karlan said. She recommended that women who are unsure about their families' medical histories complete the cancer risk assessment survey on the Web site for the Women's Cancer Network (www.wcn.org), which helps give women a sense of their own risk for various cancers.</p>
        <p>Some experts think that women who take fertility drugs, like Clomid and Pergonal, which stimulate the ovaries, may be more susceptible to ovarian cancer, because the more often a woman ovulates, the more she is at risk for ovarian abnormalities in general. This may also explain why women who have given birth more than once, or who use oral contraceptives, are much less likely to develop the disease. Indeed, some doctors prescribe the Pill to high-risk patients as a preventive measure.</p>
        <p>Ovarian cancer is difficult to detect early  because the ovaries are located deep within the pelvis: good for protecting eggs, bad for finding disease. There are some screening tools, but none are accurate enough to pick up the cancer while it is still confined to the ovaries and curable.</p>
        <p>Transvaginal ultrasound, in which a probe is inserted inside the vagina to detect ovarian abnormalities, produces too many false-positive and false-negative readings to become routine.</p>
        <p>''Before an ovary even looks abnormal on the ultrasound, there could already be widespread disease,'' Dr. Karlan warned. ''And a false-positive reading could lead a patient to unnecessary surgery and removal of the ovaries.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Jack van Nagell, who is conducting a study on transvaginal sonography at the University of Kentucky Medical School, added: ''This test is very effective in identifying ovarian tumors, but not effective in distinguishing between tumors and ovarian cancer. More operations doesn't mean better cancer care.''</p>
        <p>Another screening tool, the CA125 blood test, measures proteins in the blood that are often released by cancer cells. But researchers said that the test misses 50 percent of early cancers. So far, there is no evidence that either the blood test or the ultrasound procedure will make a difference in the outcome of the disease in the general population, which is why routine screening for ovarian cancer is not yet recommended. For now, women who have a family history, or who are at increased risk, are the only ones who should be routinely screened with transvaginal ultrasound and the CA125 test, according to the National Cancer Institute.</p>
        <p>A more promising blood test is in its final stages of research and may become available next year. This test detects a tumor marker called lysophospholipids, whose levels are significantly elevated in women with even early-stage ovarian cancer.</p>
        <p>An ovarian Pap smear may be available in five years, experts say. Developed by Dr. David Fishman, a gynecologic oncologist at Northwestern University Medical School and the director of the Ovarian Cancer Early Detection Program, this Pap smear involves inserting a hollow needle into the abdomen or vagina and collecting cells from the ovary walls. Scientists can then evaluate the cells and any gene mutations.</p>
        <p>''A woman would probably get the test once every 5 to 10 years, because genes don't change that quickly,'' Dr. Fishman said.</p>
        <p>He added, ''If we could detect ovarian cancer while it's still confined to the ovaries, 90 percent of those women would not only survive five years, but would require much less radical surgery.''</p>
        <p>Ovarian Cancer: Warning Signs</p>
        <p>The following symptoms, when persistent, are associated with ovarian cancer. Most are so common or vague  they do not arouse concern in women or their doctors.</p>
        <p>The Ovarian Cancer National Alliance, a group that is trying to raise awareness of the disease, recommends that women who experience any of these symptoms for more than two weeks should see a doctor and request a combination pelvic-rectal exam, a CA125 blood test and a transvaginal sonogram.</p>
        <p>* Persistent pressure or bloating of abdomen.</p>
        <p>* Frequent or urgent urination.</p>
        <p>* Lower back pain.</p>
        <p>* Indigestion, constipation, diarrhea, nausea.</p>
        <p>* Excessive fatigue.</p>
        <p>* Fever.</p>
        <p>* Abnormal vaginal bleeding.</p>
        <p>* Pain during intercourse.</p>
        <p>And here are the criteria for screening and exams:</p>
        <p>* Every woman should undergo annual pelvic exams.</p>
        <p>* Women who are at increased risk should get pelvic exams twice a year, as well as a transvaginal ultrasound and CA125 blood test annually. They may want to consider seeing a specialist, called a gynecologic oncologist.</p>
        <p>* For now, women who are at low risk for ovarian cancer are not advised to undergo screening tests until more studies prove their usefulness in early detection.</p>
        <p>VICKY LOWRY</p>
        <p>Vicky Lowry is a senior editor at Women's Sports &amp; Fitness magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Vicky Lowry is a senior editor at Women's Sports &amp; Fitness magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
