<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Depression Comes Out Of Hiding</title>
    <meta content="25WART$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Men &amp; Health" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wartik, Nancy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E0DC1F3EF936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Depression Comes Out Of Hiding</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nancy Wartik</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wartik, Nancy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nancy Wartik article on men and depression; some mental health experts are beginning to question whether they have given men short shrift in treatment of depression, which is twice as common among women as men but seems to take greater toll on men; some question whether depression should be approached differently in men and women, suggesting men manifest new universe of symptoms; drawing; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR much of his adult life, Beck Weathers, a Dallas pathologist, suffered from crushing depressions. ''It makes physical pain look like a cakewalk,'' he said not long ago. ''It dominates every moment of your existence. Not even a minute goes by that you don't have a sense of profound sorrow.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR much of his adult life, Beck Weathers, a Dallas pathologist, suffered from crushing depressions. ''It makes physical pain look like a cakewalk,'' he said not long ago. ''It dominates every moment of your existence. Not even a minute goes by that you don't have a sense of profound sorrow.''</p>
        <p>But Dr. Weathers, now 53, didn't discuss his depressions with anyone, not even his wife. ''I'm the John Wayne generation,'' he said. ''It's only a flesh wound': that's how you deal with it. I thought depression was a weakness - there was something disgraceful about it. A real man would just get over it.''</p>
        <p>Instead, he became a workaholic, growing more and more remote from his wife and children. He plunged passionately into sailing as a hobby. Then he discovered mountaineering.</p>
        <p>''It's the ultimate way of doing work,'' said Dr. Weathers, one of the climbers who almost died in the 1996 storm on Mount Everest chronicled in John Krakauer's best-selling book ''Into Thin Air.'' ''All you do is focus all day, because you can't think of much of anything else. It is just a wonderful way to take away thought.''</p>
        <p>To those who counsel or treat depressed men, Dr. Weathers's story is more than familiar. For years, researchers interestd in gender and depression have tended to focus on how the disease affects women, whose rate of depression is twice that of men. Men have been studied mainly to find out what ''protects'' them from the illness.</p>
        <p>But in any given year, according to the National Institute of Mental Health, three million to four million men in the United States suffer from clinical depression, and the rate may be rising slightly. And while definitives statistics are hard to come by, most experts agree that men are less likely than women to seek help.</p>
        <p>Yet depression appears to take a greater toll on men. They commit suicide at four times the rate women do (although more women try it), and a new study from Ohio State University suggests that depression increases men's - but not women's - risk of dying from heart disease.</p>
        <p>Some mental health experts have begun to ask if, in their zeal to respond to women, men have been given short shrift.</p>
        <p>''In focusing a tremendous amount on the gender gap, we may have lowered our sights for how to better identify the condition in males,'' said one research, who insisted on anonymity for fear of sounding unsympathetic toward women. ''I think we ought to pay more attention to depression in men.''</p>
        <p>Even some of those who defend the traditional emphasis wonder whether depression ought to be approached differently in men and women. Some say the mental health profession may be significantly underestimating the rate of depression in men, or it may be ignoring a new universe of symptoms of the kind Dr. Weathers displayed.</p>
        <p>''I'm convinced we're missing a lot of depression in men,'' said Dr. Jean Endicott, psychologist at the Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons, in New York. ''I do think women may have depressive disorders more frequently, but not in a 2-to-1 ratio.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Endicott believes, for example, that men's signficantly higher rates of alcoholism and drug abuse obscure their real rate of depression: ''It's often hard to diagnose depression with alcohol or drug abuse confusing the issue,'' she said. Whether men drink and use drugs because they're depressed or are depressed because of the substance abuse is uncertain. But in either case, the depression itself needs treatment.</p>
        <p>Other researchers point out that men who do seek help sometimes do not get it. ''Doctors have to see past their own bias,'' said Dr. Susan Kornstein, a psychiatrist at Virgina Commonwealth University, in Richmond. ''They tend to see depression more easily in women because they think more to the emotional side for women, more to the physical side for men. We're socialized to be much more comfortable with women crying and expressing emotional distress, than with men.''</p>
        <p>Doctors and clinicians may unintentionally rebuff male patients in other ways. Depression is diagnosed through a checklist of symptoms that include fatigue and sleep disorders, as well as feelings of sadness or hopelessness. Many researchers think that fewer men might slip through the net if examiners used different language to ask about mood.</p>
        <p>''I think there are men who will deny ever having had a period of two weeks or more where they felt sad, blue or down in the dumps,'' said Dr. Ellen Frank, a University of Pittsburgh psychologist. ''I think adding irritability to the criteria can be extremely helpful.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Ron Kessler, a professor of health care policy at Harvard, agreed. ''When you study depression among children, they don't talk about being sad, they talk about being angry and irritable,'' he said. ''Children don't have the cognitive capacity to make sense of all their feelings. There's a great similarity between children and men. Men get irritable; women get depressed.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Kessler, who is leading an international mental health survey, says he plans to ask participants if they have ever felt grumpy or discouraged for prolonged periods. If those complaints accompany traditional symptoms of depression, he says, it may suggest the need for an adjustment in the criteria for diagnosing the disease in adults.</p>
        <p>Such a change would require a relatively minor shift in how society regards depression. But a handful of experts say that the shift needs to be far more drastic - that men's high suicide rate suggests that the health profession is ignoring an epidemic of unrecognized depression.</p>
        <p>''Men are dropping like flies,'' said Dr. William Pollack, a psychologist who directs the Center for Men at McLean Hospital, the Harvard-affiliated psychiatric hospital in Belmont, Mass. ''An article in the American Journal of Psychiatry talked about how men are four to six times more likely to commit suicide, and asked why this was happening, if the men weren't depressed. If we've got psychiatrists still asking that question, we're in trouble. What we need to ask is, 'What is it about men's depression we're not seeing?' ''</p>
        <p>Dr. Pollack argues that the criteria used to diagnose depression are too ''feminized''; as a result, doctors fail to detect the illness in the 60 to 70 percent of depressed men, who, he says, are without classic symptoms. Nor do men tend to recognize depression in themselves. ''Men not only don't get treatment, they try to convince themselves they don't have an illness,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He notes that because men are typically indoctrinated with a need to appear invulnerable, they find it shameful to experience feelings of pain - and unbearably painful to experience feelings of shame.</p>
        <p>''Men will do anything not to feel shame - engage in sexual behavior that isn't really sexual, drink, even become violent,'' Dr. Pollack said. A midlife crisis? ''It's just a P.C. term for massive depression,'' he said. ''A man who suddenly divorces his wife, spends money, starts drinking - this is a midlife depression.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Pollack has devised a list of what he calls ''male-type'' symptoms, including angry outbursts, increased sexual activity, workaholism, withdrawal and risk-taking, behaviors Dr. Weathers had displayed. If used in diagnosis, Dr. Pollack contends, the list would almost eliminate the disparity in male-female depression rates.</p>
        <p>While few of Dr. Pollack's colleagues would go that far, many say his view has some validity. ''I do honestly believe women are better at feeling emotion than men,'' said Dr. Michael Thase, a University of Pittsburgh psychiatrist. ''Men may not feel depression in the same way. That's why people are suggesting variants - looking at how men act, rather than how they feel.''</p>
        <p>But others say that including too many symptoms under the rubric of depression makes the term virtually meaningless. ''I don't think everything should be lumped together as depression,'' said Dr. Kornstein, of Virginia Commonwealth. ''Men are more vulnerable to some disorders, women to others. We diagnose depression using symptoms that currently constitute the criteria for it. Then people say, 'Those are the wrong symptoms; we should be using other symptoms.' But then, those are other disorders.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Alan Romanoski, a psychiatrist at the Johns Hopkins University, in Baltimore, sounded a similar note of caution. ''I'd worry about saying, 'Show me a man who's having an affair, and I'll show you a man who's having a depression,' '' he said. ''That's trying to read something beneath what's visible. Psychiatrists aren't mind readers. We need to deal with what's conscious.''</p>
        <p>On one point, however, everyone does agree: treatment - in the form of antidepressants, psychotherapy or the two combined - is effective in 80 to 90 percent of all cases of depression, regardless of the patient's sex.</p>
        <p>MEN may find psychotherapy foreign territory at first. ''They come, somewhat bewildered, to see me,'' said Dr. Mike Jolkovski, a psychologist in private practice in Falls Church, Va. ''Someone reliable, a wife or girlfriend, has told them it's a good thing. They're going along, but literally don't know why talking about their feelings would be helpful. I say, 'I can show you better than I can tell you.' I've treated a fair number of guys- computer types, engineers - who aren't the most introspective group. Often, once they get the hang of it, they really go.''</p>
        <p>It may also turn out that some antidepressants work better for men, others for women. Dr. Kornstein's research suggests that women are more likely to respond to selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors, like Prozac, while men respond better to tricyclics, an older category of anti-depressants.</p>
        <p>The reasons are unclear, and Dr. Kornstein says taht more investigation is needed. ''But gender has never been on board as something to consider in choosing an antidepressant before,'' she said. ''It's an exciting area.''</p>
        <p>Beck Weathers, for his part, says he has never felt better, though he will forever bear the wounds of his near-fatal encounter with Mount Everest: he lost his nose, one arm and part of the other to frostbite. But the storm gave him his life back, he says, because it sent him home with a clear vision of what his family really meant to him.</p>
        <p>''All my defenses were stripped away,'' Dr. Weathers said. ''I was willing to do anything to save my relationships - I'd have stood in the road and quacked like a duck if it would help.''</p>
        <p>More practically, at his wife's urging, he saw a psychiatrist, who started him on the antidepressant Zoloft. ''I've come to think of depression much more as an organic event than a weakness,'' he said. ''But you do have to be willing to open up and deal with it.''</p>
        <p>Nancy Wartik is a writer specializing in psychology and women's health.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Nancy Wartik is a writer specializing in psychology and women's health.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
