<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Shadows Of a Stroke</title>
    <meta content="25STRO$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Women's Health" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209948"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LIVING WITH . . ."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stroke</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yoffe, Elizabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Stroke</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stroke</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE6DB1F3EF936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Shadows Of a Stroke</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Elizabeth Yoffe</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yoffe, Elizabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elizabeth Yoffe article describes experience of having a stroke; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT happened again the other night. Somehow, in my sleep, I became aware of an intensifying numbness in my left side. My brain sent a warning signal and I jerked awake with a gasp. My heart pounded, my breathing quickened and my mind flooded with a familiar panic: ''Is this it? Is it happening again?''</p>
        <p>It's been 10 years since the stroke. One minute I was sitting at the breakfast table drinking coffee and the next I lost all connection to my left hand. It was beyond numb -- as though the hand had simply vanished.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT happened again the other night. Somehow, in my sleep, I became aware of an intensifying numbness in my left side. My brain sent a warning signal and I jerked awake with a gasp. My heart pounded, my breathing quickened and my mind flooded with a familiar panic: ''Is this it? Is it happening again?''</p>
        <p>It's been 10 years since the stroke. One minute I was sitting at the breakfast table drinking coffee and the next I lost all connection to my left hand. It was beyond numb -- as though the hand had simply vanished.</p>
        <p>The numbness quickly spread up the arm, to my face and down the left leg, erasing all sense of connection to the rest of my body. I soon collapsed, unable to sit up or stand. A blood vessel, I later learned, had ruptured in the right side of my brain.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, my sister was with me. She called an ambulance and I made it to the hospital.</p>
        <p>Five hours of brain surgery saved my life; the doctors thought I might even learn to walk again, though most likely with a brace and a cane. They were less hopeful about my arm, which they believed would be useless. The surgeon suggested to my sister that I could wear it in a sling to keep it out of the way.</p>
        <p>At the age of 30, I found myself dealing with a condition most often associated with old age, yet the helplessness made me feel like a baby. It was as though I were a child, a young woman and an old one all at once.</p>
        <p>Rehabilitation is the most difficult thing I have ever had to face. I learned to sit up, stand and walk again; I learned to adjust to living with a body that was completely without sensation on one side. Eventually, I found that complementary forms of therapy helped me to regain my health. Visualization, swimming, qigong, meditation and Chinese medicine all played a significant role.</p>
        <p>Despite the predictions, I now walk without a cane or a brace. My left arm and hand, though limited, are highly functional. A small amount of feeling has returned to my affected side. But perhaps the most important shift happened recently when I spent a year working for an independent living program as a peer support specialist for people with disabilities, many of which were far more profound than mine.</p>
        <p>The people I worked with taught me to focus on living a full life with my limitations, rather than trying to appear ''normal'' in the able-bodied sense of the word. With relief, I stopped trying to hide my limp or make excuses about why I type with one hand. The acceptance of myself as I am has been as important to my recovery as my physical healing.</p>
        <p>LIVING WITH . . . Elizabeth Yoffe, 40, is a producer with First Folio Films in Los Angeles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Elizabeth Yoffe, 40, is a producer with First Folio Films in Los Angeles.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
