<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Passion That Began At the Water Hole</title>
    <meta content="25REIF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Museum of American Folk Art (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilkerson, L John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reif, Rita</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E6DA1331F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Passion That Began At the Water Hole</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RITA REIF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reif, Rita</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rita Reif profiles L John Wilkerson, who collected Indian arrowheads as child near family's ranch in Elko, Nev, and is now venture capitalist, folk art collector and president of Museum of American Folk Art in New York City; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>L. JOHN WILKERSON was 7 when he dug up a shiny stone arrowhead at a water hole near the family's small ranch in Elko, Nev. Collecting arrowheads remained a passion throughout his youth, spent among the children of ranchers and Shoshone Indians, and much later, when he returned from college to work summers as a cowboy and do research on the economics of raising cattle in the West. Yet he never dreamed that in finding that arrowhead at the water hole he had taken his first step toward becoming, 50 years later, the president of the Museum of American Folk Art in New York.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Wilkerson is a venture capitalist specializing in medical technology at Galen Associates, a New York firm of which he was a founding partner in 1995. (He had just sold the Wilkerson Group, a consulting firm on medical industry technology that he had started 20 years earlier, to I.B.M.) But he still owns the 60 stone arrowheads he amassed decades ago. ''The real jewels -- maybe 10 -- are long and skinny, shaped to travel the farthest,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>L. JOHN WILKERSON was 7 when he dug up a shiny stone arrowhead at a water hole near the family's small ranch in Elko, Nev. Collecting arrowheads remained a passion throughout his youth, spent among the children of ranchers and Shoshone Indians, and much later, when he returned from college to work summers as a cowboy and do research on the economics of raising cattle in the West. Yet he never dreamed that in finding that arrowhead at the water hole he had taken his first step toward becoming, 50 years later, the president of the Museum of American Folk Art in New York.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Wilkerson is a venture capitalist specializing in medical technology at Galen Associates, a New York firm of which he was a founding partner in 1995. (He had just sold the Wilkerson Group, a consulting firm on medical industry technology that he had started 20 years earlier, to I.B.M.) But he still owns the 60 stone arrowheads he amassed decades ago. ''The real jewels -- maybe 10 -- are long and skinny, shaped to travel the farthest,'' he said.</p>
        <p>These days, he and his wife, Barbara, are avid collectors with broader interests. Color-splashed barber poles, carousel carvings and apothecary chests enliven his office in Rockefeller Center. Boldly patterned aboriginal spirit paintings add graphic intensity to the interiors of their country home in Pennsylvania. Late-20th-century abstract sculpture fills the gardens of their home in New Jersey, while American folk art reigns supreme indoors.</p>
        <p>As the Wilkersons acquired folk art, they met other collectors at, among other places, the Museum of American Folk Art. Mr. Wilkerson became a trustee in 1994, became treasurer in 1996 and late last year was elected board president, replacing Ralph Esmerian, a pre-eminent collector of American folk art, who had been president since 1979. (He remains as board chairman.) Mr. Esmerian had helped Robert Bishop, then the director, guide the institution through turbulent times. Under their leadership, it grew from a one-room museum with a collection of 184 objects, and deeply in debt, to a formidable institution with many masterpieces among its 4,000 objects. It organizes exhibitions that travel throughout the world, and, under its current director, Gerard C. Wertkin, it is building a $22 million museum on West 53rd Street, due to open late next year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilkerson hopes to build on the success of his predecessors, placing even more emphasis on the business aspects of the museum. ''For the last 20 years, the leadership at the museum had focused 75 percent on its collections and curatorial activities and 25 percent on its business management,'' he said. ''Today with everything we have on our plate -- the building going up and an endowment being planned for major acquisitions -- it is a more balanced equation, 50-50.''</p>
        <p>The Wilkersons are already involved in the museum in other ways, lending pieces for exhibitions. Their 9-foot-long ''Angel Gabriel'' weathervane was hard to miss in the museum's show marking the millennium. And they have many articles that may be exhibited in the future. Their other weathervanes -- in the shape of horses, cows, angels and American Indians -- hang floor to ceiling in the entrance hall of their home. Pennsylvania German cabbage cutters, embellished with cutouts of hearts and hands, cover a wall in the kitchen. And painted furniture, shop signs, trade figures and watercolors are spread throughout the rest of the house. In this crowded environment, you have to look closely to see the complexity in the haunted Munchlike expression in a woman's face in a gouache by Bill Traylor.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Wilkerson had a head start on her husband as a folk-art collector: she bought her first piece -- an 1880's cherry end table -- when she was 14. But he proved a fast learner, succumbing quickly to the easy charm, optimism and diversity of folk art. They began collecting after they were married 33 years ago, and furnished their first home on a tight budget with painted chests, tables and a desk, paying less than $100 for most pieces. By the 1970's, they were buying decorative objects and weathervanes.</p>
        <p>The first vane they bought was by J. Howard &amp; Co. of West Bridgewater, Mass. ''We knew he was our guy; his vanes were the most striking,'' Mr. Wilkerson said. ''In the 1980's, we decided that we would develop the most comprehensive collection of weathervanes by Howard. We've probably done just that -- nobody else would be so crazy.''</p>
        <p>Of the 57 vanes they own, 27 are by Howard, a competitor in the 1860's of the better-known manufacturers A. L. Jewell of Waltham, Mass., and J. W. Fiske of New York. Howard specialized in using zinc and copper to achieve a better balance in his vanes. And he made stepping horses of exceptional grace, while Jewell strove for more dynamic movement in his all-copper horses. This characteristic is seen in a Wilkerson treasure, a patinated flying horse by Jewell, its tail and mane borne high by the wind.</p>
        <p>The Wilkersons also realize that their involvement in the museum is having an impact on their collecting: they are trying to upgrade what they buy and to better document the pieces that they own. But their biggest problem as collectors, they say, is that they have never sold or given away anything from their collection. ''We can't seem to say goodbye,'' Mr. Wilkerson said. ''We have a lot to learn from the curators at the museum on how to fashion and continuously refine a collection.''</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
