<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A High School Champion Who Sets, and Beats, Goals</title>
    <meta content="25DAWK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210071"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FOR THE RECORD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dawkins, Shenae</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slater, Chuck</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E2D91131F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="911" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A High School Champion Who Sets, and Beats, Goals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHUCK SLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slater, Chuck</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Shenae Dawkins, 15, of New Rochelle, who has won girls' 400-meter hurdles, 100-meter hurdles and triple jump at New York State High School Track and Field Championships; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is a moment frozen in the minds of all who saw it. Heading into the turn for home in the girls' 400-meter hurdles at the New York State High School Track and Field Championships in Liverpool two weeks ago, Shenae Dawkins of New Rochelle trailed Shevon Stoddart of Uniondale by about five yards. Making up that distance on the final straightaway was akin to a miler making up a city block on the final lap.</p>
        <p>''I didn't know if I could win, but I knew I could get closer,'' said Shenae (pronounced sh-NAY). She then did both, winning in the standout time of 60.73 seconds, more than half a second faster than her previous best.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is a moment frozen in the minds of all who saw it. Heading into the turn for home in the girls' 400-meter hurdles at the New York State High School Track and Field Championships in Liverpool two weeks ago, Shenae Dawkins of New Rochelle trailed Shevon Stoddart of Uniondale by about five yards. Making up that distance on the final straightaway was akin to a miler making up a city block on the final lap.</p>
        <p>''I didn't know if I could win, but I knew I could get closer,'' said Shenae (pronounced sh-NAY). She then did both, winning in the standout time of 60.73 seconds, more than half a second faster than her previous best.</p>
        <p>And there was more. Dawkins, 15, also won the 100-meter hurdles and the triple jump.</p>
        <p>''As a sophomore! She's incredible,'' said Dick Mann, the veteran track official who was serving at the meet. ''The coaches were talking afterward, and they said no athlete had ever won three individual events at a New York state championship. Maybe two individuals and a piece of the winning relay, but not three individuals.''</p>
        <p>Ask Shenae's high school coach, Andy Capellan, and he uses words like ''dedication'' and ''focus'' to describe his 5-foot-9 sophomore. But talk more, and a special brand of competitiveness comes out.</p>
        <p>The making of this champion began in the seventh grade.</p>
        <p>''That's when Shenae started our high school program,'' Capellan said, ''and she wasn't too impressive at first.</p>
        <p>''In fact, after a first week of very rough, very intensive practices, Shenae didn't show up for a few days. I called her house and told her we'd missed her and, like so many kids do, she said she had been sick. 'If you're not here tomorrow,' I told her, 'I'm going to assume you've quit.'</p>
        <p>''She showed up, and she's never missed a practice since. And by the time we got to the outdoor season and she learned to hurdle, you could glimpse the greatness.''</p>
        <p>And the competitiveness.</p>
        <p>''Her first year on the varsity,'' Capellan said, ''I asked her to race on our 4 x 100-meter relay team when another girl got hurt. This was in the state qualifying championships! She had never broken 60 seconds, but she turned in a 57-second leg.''</p>
        <p>At one point late this outdoor season, Shenae had the top performances in Westchester and Putnam Counties in five individual events: the two hurdles, the triple and long jump and the 400-meter run.</p>
        <p>''She just doesn't like to lose,'' Capellan said.</p>
        <p>Which means that Nubia Newsome has perhaps the most thankless job of any track and field athlete in the state. Nubia is a solid hurdler capable of winning in many competitions. She turns the 100 in the mid-15's and also long jumps more than 15 feet. But she is at New Rochelle, where every day she competes against Shenae.</p>
        <p>''Beat her? I get close,'' Nubia, 16, said.  ''There's always the possibility. Some day it would be good to win, but running against her makes me faster. And she never rubs it in.''</p>
        <p>Capellan added: ''You can see Shenae's popular with her teammates. She doesn't put on airs and she doesn't have the big ego that most sprinters have.''</p>
        <p>Kianne Dawkins, Shenae's sister and a Cheyney University student, said the same thing from a different perspective. ''Shenae is very modest,'' she said. ''Very quiet. She just comes in the house and puts her trophy down.''</p>
        <p>But, she said, Shenae is as active as she is quiet. ''As a little girl, she loved to jump on beds,'' Kiannee said. ''Always active, aways very hyper. And she liked to eat a lot of candy.''</p>
        <p>She likes track and field more.</p>
        <p>''I like the team most of all,'' Shenae said. ''We support each other, try to get each of us to do the best we can. If I train hard and do well for the team, I feel like I'm accomplishing something even if I don't win.''</p>
        <p>That does not happen very often. It did, however, last weekend at the Foot Locker national high school championships in Raleigh, N.C. In the qualifying round, Shenae was 10th in both the 100 hurdles and the triple jump; nine athletes advanced to the finals.</p>
        <p>''I'll learn from this,'' she said Sunday, ''and come back hungry to win next year.''</p>
        <p>Not that her whole life is running, jumping and hurdling. Her father, the Rev. Harry Dawkins, is minister of the nondenominational Church of the Second Chance in Brooklyn, catering to the indigent and the homeless. When not spending her weekends passing other athletes, Shenae may spend them passing out food at soup kitchens.</p>
        <p>''My dad's main goal is to help the less fortunate,'' she explained. ''He feels a lot of churches don't really do so. When you serve in a soup kitchen and people see that somebody does cares, it really changes them.''</p>
        <p>For Shenae, who plans to continue her sport in college, the changes figure to be in the level of competition.</p>
        <p>Marsha Bailey, the veteran Henrick Hudson track coach, has no doubt. ''Shenae is quite possibly the most talented female athlete I've seen in my 26 years' coaching in Westchester County,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''Olympic material? Oh, sure.''</p>
        <p>FOR THE RECORD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
