<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doyle Finds That Winning Doesn't Guarantee Celebrity</title>
    <meta content="25GOLF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210368"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E2DD1530F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doyle Finds That Winning Doesn't Guarantee Celebrity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <dateline>CLIFTON, N.J., June 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Allen Doyle will play to a huge crowd in the final round of the Cadillac N.F.L. Golf Classic on Sunday, but he does not fool himself into believing the crowd will be there to watch him. Entering the final day tied with Lee Trevino for the lead at 11 under par, the two will play with Gary McCord, who is one stroke off the lead. And Doyle will just be someone who provides a break between the applause from Trevino's adoring fans and the comic style of McCord.</p>
        <p>Winning the tournament will most likely do nothing to change that for the next tournament stop. Doyle won this tournament a year ago in his rookie season on the Senior PGA Tour, along with three other events, and he has added one more victory this season. But still, when he arrived this week he found the brochure had Tom Watson on its cover with no mention of Doyle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Allen Doyle will play to a huge crowd in the final round of the Cadillac N.F.L. Golf Classic on Sunday, but he does not fool himself into believing the crowd will be there to watch him. Entering the final day tied with Lee Trevino for the lead at 11 under par, the two will play with Gary McCord, who is one stroke off the lead. And Doyle will just be someone who provides a break between the applause from Trevino's adoring fans and the comic style of McCord.</p>
        <p>Winning the tournament will most likely do nothing to change that for the next tournament stop. Doyle won this tournament a year ago in his rookie season on the Senior PGA Tour, along with three other events, and he has added one more victory this season. But still, when he arrived this week he found the brochure had Tom Watson on its cover with no mention of Doyle.</p>
        <p>When he walked off the course as the leader this afternoon, there were just a few fans seeking his autograph. When Trevino finished, he had to make his way through a throng of fans -- those who remembered his triumphs from more than 30 years ago and children who were not yet born when he joined the Senior PGA in 1989.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't on the front page of the brochure and I'm the defending champion,'' Doyle said. ''Anybody that was human would say that irks them a little bit. If I win the tournament and play well it won't bother me one bit, and it doesn't bother me one bit. It's really an embarrassment I think to the event.''</p>
        <p>The tournament director, Dawn Bye, said: ''That's definitely not the case. I hate that he feels that way. We're thrilled that he won last year. We have him on one of the posters and there's a special article on him in the program.''</p>
        <p>Doyle posted the day's best score with an eight-under-par 64, making up ground on Trevino, who shot six under on Friday and then five under today. McCord started quickly today, with birdies on four of the first seven holes, but finished with his second straight 67. Doyle and Trevino entered the last day of the tournament paired together a year ago, too, and Trevino finished third while Doyle won in a playoff over Joe Inman.</p>
        <p>''It's great for any event to have Trevino win,'' Doyle said. ''But what he does on the course tomorrow and what I do on the course tomorrow will affect who wins, not who they want to win.''</p>
        <p>Trevino has earned his adulation, and he did today, too. On the 18th hole, trailing Doyle by one stroke, he sank a 45-foot downhill putt that raised the volume to the level of the packs that follow Tiger Woods.</p>
        <p>''I've got a good chance,'' Trevino said. ''I've got a good shot at it. I'm doing everything quite well right now. I'm driving it well, hitting good iron shots and this week I started putting.''</p>
        <p>While Trevino has been one of the most prominent players on the PGA and senior tours, Doyle spent his days running a small driving range in LaGrange, Ga., an operation that he still runs. He became the oldest rookie ever on the PGA Tour when he decided to give it a try in 1996, hoping to make some extra money to pay the college tuition for his two daughters. The driving range brings him slightly less than $30,000 in a good year. Now, he is on track to $1 million in earnings for the second straight year.</p>
        <p>But he is still more a curiosity with a strange, crouched stance and a backswing that hardly reaches his shoulder but produces eerily accurate results. ''Why complain after what's happened to me?'' Doyle said. ''Dana Quigley is quoted a lot that he's thrilled to be here, and I'm the same way. They can slight me. This is the way it's been all my career.</p>
        <p>''When I was an amateur beating Tiger Woods and David Duval and Phil Mickelson and Justin Leonard, I beat those guys for years. Then when you went to that next event two weeks later, whether I won the prior one or was the defending champ, they all wanted to talk to those guys. That's the way it is.''</p>
        <p>CHIP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Tennessee Titans punter CRAIG HENTRICH captured the National Football League players' portion of the tournament with a 75 Saturday, beating BRIAN KINCHEN of the Carolina Panthers by three strokes.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
