<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Finding Stolen Moments, Clippers in Hand</title>
    <meta content="LIGARDEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DD1430F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Finding Stolen Moments, Clippers in Hand</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH GINSBURG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PASSIONATE commitment does not lend itself to rationing. Just ask any gardener.  Most of us would gladly spend hours in our borders. In reality though, most of us are also constrained to earn our livings, raise families, and devote ourselves to the worthy causes and mundane chores that make up a full life.</p>
        <p>So what is a passionate gardener to do? The answer varies from person to person, but over all, harried gardeners tend to develop strategies that maximize the available time, minimize labor and enhance the pleasure of garden chores.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PASSIONATE commitment does not lend itself to rationing. Just ask any gardener.  Most of us would gladly spend hours in our borders. In reality though, most of us are also constrained to earn our livings, raise families, and devote ourselves to the worthy causes and mundane chores that make up a full life.</p>
        <p>So what is a passionate gardener to do? The answer varies from person to person, but over all, harried gardeners tend to develop strategies that maximize the available time, minimize labor and enhance the pleasure of garden chores.</p>
        <p>Fran Wong, who presides over a busy family and an educational foundation, keeps her garden clippers in the car. The moment she pulls into the driveway, she is ready to tend the bed that bounds it. Mrs. Wong remembers one recent day when she returned home after taking her daughter to an early morning band practice. Clad in her chauffeur's garb, bathrobe covered by raincoat, she triumphantly clipped a rose before going in the house.</p>
        <p>Lisa Redburn, an adult school administrator, also keeps her tools handy, with multiple sets of garden clogs and implements strategically positioned by her back door, front door and garden shed. As she heads out on workday mornings, she may stop in the garden to do non-messy chores such as tying up wayward clematis vines or cutting flowers.  ''I've been known to hop into the car with the pruning shears still in my pocket,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Then there is gardening at odd hours. ''A few years ago, someone gave me one of those miner's lamps,'' said Mrs. Redburn, who confessed that she not only gardens in the dark, but goes to the garden center in the evening just before closing time. ''The plants that I buy look completely different to me the next morning,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Wong has had similar experiences. ''Years ago, I ordered so many spring bulbs, that I ended up outside one night with a spotlight,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Organization helps Gail Edwards, a busy Westchester gardener, who makes lists of garden chores and also consults her garden calendar/ diary to see what she did the previous year. Mrs. Edwards gains time by ''incubating'' ideas over the winter, and writing them down for future reference. ''Sometimes,'' she said, ''when it's 20 degrees outside, things just pop into your head.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Edwards is one of many gardeners who selects plants for their ''return on investment.'' In her case, plants that increase, such as astilbes, save money as well as time. After a few years, individual specimens grow large enough to divide, providing more plants without additional expenditure of cash or time at the garden center.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Wong also buys easy-care perennials. Potentially invasive specimens are confined to pots, which she then sinks into the ground.</p>
        <p>While Mrs. Redburn admits to preferring large blocks of gardening time over small increments, she optimizes those blocks by ''focusing on one area at a time.''</p>
        <p>If work in a particular area becomes unrewarding, she feels no compunction about moving to another. ''I flow with what the garden tells me,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Proximity also saves time for Mrs. Wong, who tends the beds closest to the barbecue grill while broiling her family's dinner. ''I pull a few weeds while I watch the chicken cook,'' she said. Since weeding itself is time-consuming, she keeps crab grass and chickweed away by installing ground-covering ''shoes-and-socks'' plants such as sweet woodruff and hosta around the bases of taller plants. Mrs. Wong also saves time by using the same granular timed-release fertilizer on all her plants, except for the day lilies. The family has a pet rabbit, and Mrs. Wong makes a habit of fertilizing the lilies by rinsing out the rabbit litter tray over them. ''They're doing really well,'' she added.</p>
        <p>By and large, busy gardeners do not obsess over tidiness. ''Going with the flow'' means that Mrs. Redburn sometimes leaves piles of weeds sitting in the backyard awaiting transport to the compost heap.</p>
        <p>Individual strategies may differ, but finding ways to get out into the garden, whether for a few minutes or half a day, is essential. When it comes to finding time, said Mrs. Redburn, ''It doesn't feel like strategy, it feels like obsession.''</p>
        <p>For Gail Edwards, expanding and tending the country garden started by her mother is an essential self-indulgence. Referring to her grown offspring she added, ''People say to me, 'Why are you expanding your garden? It's going to be so much trouble for your children.' I say to them, 'Who cares what the children want. This is for me.' ''</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
