<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Filling a Niche in the Island's Health Care Industry</title>
    <meta content="25BIZ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="L.I. @ WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Therapy and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Glengariff Health Care Center (Glen Cove, Ny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strugatch, Warren</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Therapy and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Therapy and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E5DC1131F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1138" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Filling a Niche in the Island's Health Care Industry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN STRUGATCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strugatch, Warren</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Glengariff Health Care Center facility at former Frederick Pratt mansion in Glen Cove, Long Island, subacute care facility that helps hospital patients make transition from acute care to home; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER being pronounced dead by medical personnel -- twice -- Charles Lobello, 64, was feeling particularly appreciative of his current rehabilitative facility.</p>
        <p>At two hospitals ''they told me I'm a walking miracle,'' said the Flushing resident and emphysema sufferer. ''I think the people who work here are the miracles.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER being pronounced dead by medical personnel -- twice -- Charles Lobello, 64, was feeling particularly appreciative of his current rehabilitative facility.</p>
        <p>At two hospitals ''they told me I'm a walking miracle,'' said the Flushing resident and emphysema sufferer. ''I think the people who work here are the miracles.''</p>
        <p>''Here'' is the Glengariff Health Care Center, a 262-bed subacute care center housed in a former mansion in Glen Cove. Glengariff, and a 120-bed sister facility in Port Jefferson, help hospital patients make the transition from acute care to home in a resplendent setting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lobello said he does not recall the circumstances of his most recent brush with death, but when he regained consciousness last month it was not in the Flushing hospital where he was admitted, but in a sunny room of Glengariff, one of the Pratt estates and originally known as Poplar Hill.</p>
        <p>The Gold Coast mansion, built in 1907, was turned into a nursing center in 1948. In 1971 a developer, Irwin Miness, bought the property and put up a new nursing home, reserving the mansion for administrative use. A quarter century later his son Michael turned the mansion into a subacute care provider, one of a few on Long Island dedicated to that niche.</p>
        <p>The niche reflects changing medical economics: hospitals provide increasingly expensive medical care while curtailing length of stay, while community hospitals, which once provided lower levels of care for longer time periods, now focus on more lucrative specialties.</p>
        <p>Most patients are in middle- to late-middle age, suffering from neuromuscular disorders, bone fractures, brain and spinal cord injuries, and amputations. During an average stay of about 25 days, they receive medical and therapeutic services intended to support their return to independent living.</p>
        <p>The proprietor's ambitions extend far beyond Long Island. Certain that subacute care is destined to grow, and determined to speed that process, two years ago Mr. Miness launched an independent providers' organization, the New York Health Providers and Subacute Network. It has grown to 13 members who collectively provide 700 acute beds in the greater New York area. Mr. Miness, a developer's son who inherited the trade's fondness for superlatives, calls it ''the largest subacute care network in the Northeast.''</p>
        <p>While common in other parts of the country, subacute care remains unusual on Long Island and throughout New York. The state has not defined standards for subacute care centers.</p>
        <p>''At first the idea of a subacute was difficult for doctors here to accept,'' said Dr. Luigi Capobianco, a senior partner with the North Country Community Physicians, a medical practice based in Glen Cove. ''We hadn't been trained in this approach. But we see it's good for the patient. Among physicians, acceptance keeps growing.''</p>
        <p>The approach, in this case, brings a business consultant's efficiency emphasis to bear on health care delivery, where costs continue to far outpace inflation. At the Glenhaven Health Care Organization, which encompasses Mr. Miness's two facilities, costs are cut by making certain services available at nearby hospitals or clinics. For example, both centers accept patients around the clock, but neither has an emergency room. Nurses provide care that has traditionally been provided directly by doctors.</p>
        <p>Its advocates say the practice allows physicians to expand their caseload. ''The nurse practitioners are my eyes and ears,'' said Dr. Capobianco, who spends 12 to 14 hours a week at Glengariff, treating patients from his practice.</p>
        <p>Occupying a niche somewhere between the single-minded focus on medical service delivery characterized by today's hospitals and the geriatric, residential orientation of most long-term facilities, the Glengariff centers look well beyond those models, at the same time working within the restraints imposed by both regulatory agencies and third-party payers. The physical therapy area is plush enough to be the gym at a private resort; staffers are attentive and walls are decorated with calming prints of floral arrangements and evocative landscapes. Promotional materials tout the center as a ''beautiful, peaceful retreat'' offering ''a panoramic view of Long Island's Gold Coast.''</p>
        <p>It is easy to imagine Frederick B. Pratt, the original owner, returning home any day.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miness described the center as a rehabilitative and complex medical subacute health care facility catering to a niche that has previously been overlooked: too healthy for hospitals, too young for a nursing home, too ill at the moment to go home.</p>
        <p>He said the average convalescent is aged 63, although some are as young as 16. ''This is not a nursing home population,'' he said. ''These people are younger, mentally aware. They are here for a 23-day average stay. Long-term-care patients stay 18 months on average, in comparison. So this is a different population in every way, neither acute nor long-term.''</p>
        <p>While many other places offer subacute care services, only a few market to patients, insurers and hospital discharge planners as offering that specific level of service in all of their facility.</p>
        <p>''We have made an enormous adjustment, and investment, to be able to say we do this,'' Mr. Miness said. ''Staffing costs are higher. Pharmacy costs have escalated enormously. Meal costs have as well, and we have totally upgraded them in terms of quality and choice.''</p>
        <p>During a tour of Glengariff, its chief operating officer, Kenneth R. Winston, greeted many patients by name and chatted with rehab staff about their progress.</p>
        <p>''We make it a point not to have a hospital kind of environment,'' Mr. Winston said as he walked past an indoor shuffleboard court. Pointing to one of the dozens of colorful prints framed and displayed on the walls, he added, ''The worst thing in a residential environment is sterility. You won't find that feeling here.''</p>
        <p>While several other organizations on Long Island offer subacute services, the total number of beds is still well under 500, clearly below need, according to Bill Pascocello, incoming president of the New York State Health Facilities Association.</p>
        <p>''We're in discussion with the state to create a subacute category, so facilities will be able to explain to consumers clearly and precisely the level of care they are offering,'' said Ed Stafford, executive director of the industry group.</p>
        <p>On a recent afternoon, Jennie Bugge was sitting in a cozy room outfitted with a stove, oven and refrigerator. The 81-year-old Elmont resident, who suffered a stroke and was transferred to Glengariff three weeks ago, sat in a wheelchair while an occupational therapist helped her learn again how to prepare simple meals.</p>
        <p>''This is just a sandwich, but these days it takes me quite a while to do so and then clean up,'' she said with an uncomplaining smile. ''They're helping me here so when I go home I can do it by myself.''</p>
        <p>L.I. @ WORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
