<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If You're Thinking of Living In/Beekman Place; A Quiet Enclave Only Two Blocks Long</title>
    <meta content="25LIVI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210036"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Beekman Place (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Joyce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E0DF1131F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1955" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If You're Thinking of Living In/Beekman Place; A Quiet Enclave Only Two Blocks Long</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>if</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BEEKMAN PLACE, just two blocks long, is so out-of-the-way that Stanley Kohlenberg likens it to Brigadoon, the legendary Scottish town that comes to life every hundred years.</p>
        <p>''It's so removed from Manhattan and yet so much a part of it,'' said Mr. Kohlenberg, treasurer of the Beekman Place Association. ''You walk one block off First Avenue and you're in a different country. Unless you come to Beekman Place, you will not find it. We have only people who live here or who make a mistake.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BEEKMAN PLACE, just two blocks long, is so out-of-the-way that Stanley Kohlenberg likens it to Brigadoon, the legendary Scottish town that comes to life every hundred years.</p>
        <p>''It's so removed from Manhattan and yet so much a part of it,'' said Mr. Kohlenberg, treasurer of the Beekman Place Association. ''You walk one block off First Avenue and you're in a different country. Unless you come to Beekman Place, you will not find it. We have only people who live here or who make a mistake.''</p>
        <p>He's exaggerating, of course. But this quiet chip of Manhattan is tucked away, nestled between First Avenue and the East River. By car, there's only one way in (East 50th Street) and two ways out (East 49th or 51st, depending on which way you turn from 50th Street).</p>
        <p>Beekman Place sits on a kind of windy hill over the East River. ''It's a little oasis,'' said Ellen Morgan, the sales manager of the Beekman/Sutton office of the William B. May brokerage concern.''First Avenue is so busy, and you step a block away, and there's no commercial anything -- zero. You drop out from the city when you come to Beekman Place.''</p>
        <p>People who move in are ''looking for Old World charm,'' she said. But that charm  comes at New World prices, though brokers say that housing prices remain lower than those for comparable spaces on Fifth and Park Avenues.</p>
        <p>''For years, people felt the area was too far east,'' said Ms. Morgan. Residents complain about the trek to the Lexington Avenue subway. The most convenient public transportation is the No. 27 and 50 crosstown buses, which run along 49th and 50th Streets.</p>
        <p>With a few exceptions, Beekman Place apartments are prewar co-ops. One-bedrooms sell for $375,000 to $450,000, and two-bedrooms for $600,000 to $800,000, Ms. Morgan said.</p>
        <p>A two-bedroom, two-bath apartment with a garden at 420 East 51st Street -- one of the  few postwar buildings -- went for $275,000 three years ago, Ms. Morgan said. A year ago, it was resold for $550,000. ''I could sell the apartment for the high $700,000's now,'' she said.</p>
        <p>People moving to Beekman Place include ''empty nesters and couples without children, people wanting a pied-a-terre, and people who work in Midtown and like to walk to work,'' Ms. Morgan said.</p>
        <p>The area includes plenty of spectacular  homes. In September, the 16-room penthouse at 1 Beekman Place went for $8 million. ''That's the highest price I've seen,'' said Gale Rundquist, a vice president in Douglas Elliman's East Side office. The 1930 building has a garage, swimming pool, squash court, basketball court and exercise room. And until 1940, when the Franklin D. Roosevelt Drive came through, it had its own private pier.</p>
        <p>In the fall of 1924, a brochure for Beekman Terrace, a six-story building at 455 East 51st Street, advertised the largest, highest apartment -- with seven rooms, three baths and six closets -- for $20,500. A similar apartment on a lower floor is currently for sale, at a price of $1.950 million, Ms. Rundquist said.</p>
        <p>Back in 1924, the smallest ground-floor apartment, with a living room, bedroom, kitchenette and bathroom, was advertised for $3,400. The apartment is now on the market for just under $500,000, Ms. Rundquist said.</p>
        <p>Along with the prices, other things about the neighborhood have changed: the brochure also mentioned the convenience of the Second Avenue el station at 50th Street, just three blocks away.</p>
        <p>The neighborhood's one condominium is 25-27 Beekman Place. The side-by-side town houses were ''vacant and decrepit'' for years, said Elizabeth Lee Sample, a broker at Brown Harris Stevens.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, Enrico Minoli, a banker from Italy, bought the buildings. Now after an extensive renovation, all seven apartments are either sold or under contract, at prices ranging from $2.750 million to $5.2 million, Ms. Sample said. The Minoli family will live on the ground floor.</p>
        <p>Patricia Kaplan, who moved to Beekman Place 15 years ago after she married, said that for the first time in her memory, young families are moving in. ''There used to be not a lot of children,'' she said. ''Now, you see people pushing baby carriages. It's nice to see them.''</p>
        <p>The neighborhood has ''such an intimate feeling,'' she added. ''You are greeted every day by practically everybody, and you get to have a nodding acquaintance with the neighbors.''</p>
        <p>AN attraction that brings other New Yorkers to the neighborhood is Peter Detmold Park, named for a former chairman of Community Board 6 who was killed in 1972 in the vestibule of his apartment building at 230 East 49th Street. The crime has not been solved.</p>
        <p>The main entrance to the park, which runs along the East River from 49th to 52nd  Streets, is a long, steep staircase at the end  of 51st Street. The park has benches and paved walkways plus a footbridge over the F.D.R. Drive that leads to a narrow path along the East River.</p>
        <p>But the park is known far and wide for its dog run.</p>
        <p>''People drive in and spend a Sunday with the dogs,'' said Anita Inglese, the new president of P.D.P.-ARF, the nonprofit group that maintains the dog run (the initials stand for Peter Detmold Park-Animals Run Free).  Contributions pay for the dog-waste bags, there for the taking, and volunteers help with cleaning and planting. Ms. Inglese plans to put in a water fountain.</p>
        <p>''We have nearly 200 users a day,'' she said. ''There are fewer on weekends in the summer. The dogs go out of town.''</p>
        <p>The dog run draws complaints about barking and odor, but Ms. Inglese hopes to improve matters by enforcing the dog run's rules that restrict pack walkers to four dogs each.</p>
        <p>Closing the park at night helps keep down complaints. The Beekman Place Association pays for a security guard to patrol the neighborhood from dusk to dawn and to lock the park at night. The gates close at either 7, 8, or 9 p.m., depending on the season.</p>
        <p>''We pay the doorman at the two ends of the park to open the gates in the morning,'' said Buddy Radisch, the association's president.</p>
        <p>Mr. Radisch, a retired advertising-agency creative director, said he visited the area as a child with his aunt.</p>
        <p>''She was the girlfriend of Billy Rose, the showman, who lived in Beekman Place,'' he said. ''Once you walk east of First Avenue, it's a new world,'' he said. ''It's a sweet neighborhood, with friendly people who bend over to pick up discarded gum wrappers.''</p>
        <p>The street was named for the Beekman family, early Dutch settlers whose patriarch, Gerardus Beekman, lived from 1653 to 1723. The family owned three large farms. Two were downtown -- one near Beekman Street, below City Hall -- and one covered an area from what is now 49th Street to 61st Street between the river and Second Avenue.</p>
        <p>The family mansion stood at First Avenue and 51st Street from 1765 to 1874. William Howe, the British general, occupied the mansion during the American Revolution. His troops captured Nathan Hale, the American patriot, and held him there before he was executed.</p>
        <p>By the early 20th century, the neighborhood was filled with factories and slaughterhouses. Development in Beekman Place and neighboring Sutton Place started around 1920. At First Avenue and 49th Street, the Art Deco Pan-Hellenic Tower, originally built to house sorority women, is now the Beekman Tower Hotel.</p>
        <p>Several United Nations missions and consulates -- including those for Kuwait, Niger, Swaziland, Tunisia and Yemen -- dot the area. Luxembourg occupies 17 Beekman Place, the former home of Irving Berlin, who lived there for the last 42 years of his life (he died in 1989).</p>
        <p>Changes are coming to the immediate neighborhood. Just blocks to the south, against the strenuous objections of neighbors, Trump World Tower is rising. At 861 feet tall, it is being billed as the world's tallest residential building.</p>
        <p>The Beekman Regent, a 19-story condominium, is going up on the northwest corner of First Avenue and 51st Street. The building started life as Public School 35, was later used as a shelter for homeless women and now resembles a Roman ruin of eerie beauty.</p>
        <p>The building, which is being developed by  Dennis A. Herman, is scheduled for completion next summer. It will have 64 apartments, ranging in size from one to five bedrooms; a garage; and a health club.</p>
        <p>Diagonally across the street, at 400 East 51st Street, a tower called the Grand Beekman has been proposed, but no plans have yet been filed with the city's Buildings Department.</p>
        <p>THOUGH many neighborhood children attend private schools, the nearest public elementary school is P.S. 59, on 57th Street between Second and Third Avenues. It has about 320 pupils in prekindergarten through the fifth grade.</p>
        <p>The closest shops to Beekman Place are along First Avenue, where there are plenty of tailors and dry cleaners, some delis and restaurants, and the Beekman Pet Emporium.</p>
        <p>''Nine years ago, I stood on the corner for three days and counted enough dogs to say, 'I think there's enough to support my store,' '' said Dale Levinson, the owner.</p>
        <p>''The dog run provides a social outlet,'' she said. ''There are a lot of elderly people in the neighborhood, and it's a place to go to sit and talk and have companionship.''</p>
        <p>In warm weather, the store keeps a bucket of drinking water outside for the dogs, and all year long it hands out treats to its customers. ''When the store is closed,'' Ms. Levinson said, ''I am told the dogs stand outside the door and cry.''</p>
        <p>Map of New York highlighting Beekman Place; Beekman Place is tucked away on the far East Side of Manhattan, from 49th to 51st Streets. It is a leafy neighborhood, and because it is physically isolated from the rest of Manhattan, it does not get typical Midtown traffic.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
