<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out of This Hemisphere</title>
    <meta content="25DINE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Zafra (Hoboken, Nj, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Catherine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E3DB1131F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out of This Hemisphere</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHERINE JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Catherine</byline>
      <dateline>HOBOKEN</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Catherine Jones reviews Zafra, Latin American-style restaurant in Hoboken, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN Cuba the expression ''making  a zafra''  which means harvesting sugar cane -- signifies doing well. At the opening of Zafra in January, the father of Maricel Presilla, the Cuban-born chef and an owner, gave her a vibrant mural he had painted, depicting the sugar cane harvest, as a good-luck present.</p>
        <p>Ms. Presilla and her two co-owners, Clara Chaumont and Leonardo de la Sierra, have decorated the space with items from their own homes. Guests -- who include hip young Hobokenites and older Latin Americans -- feel as if they are seated in the kitchen in a Latin American house, complete with ceiling fans, flowers and music. Ms. Presilla has imparted her time-consuming recipes and techniques, and her insistence on working from scratch, to the all-woman kitchen staff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN Cuba the expression ''making  a zafra''  which means harvesting sugar cane -- signifies doing well. At the opening of Zafra in January, the father of Maricel Presilla, the Cuban-born chef and an owner, gave her a vibrant mural he had painted, depicting the sugar cane harvest, as a good-luck present.</p>
        <p>Ms. Presilla and her two co-owners, Clara Chaumont and Leonardo de la Sierra, have decorated the space with items from their own homes. Guests -- who include hip young Hobokenites and older Latin Americans -- feel as if they are seated in the kitchen in a Latin American house, complete with ceiling fans, flowers and music. Ms. Presilla has imparted her time-consuming recipes and techniques, and her insistence on working from scratch, to the all-woman kitchen staff.</p>
        <p>The result is authentic Latin American dishes like those Ms. Presilla feeds to her friends and family.  ''We have no liquor license and yet we make a lemonade made with sugar, ice and whole limes that is better than any glass of wine,'' Ms. Presilla said.</p>
        <p>While getting her Ph.D. in medieval Spanish history at N.Y.U., she apprenticed one day a week under Felipe Rojas Lombardi at the first tapas bar in Manhattan, the Ballroom. From there she headed to the French Culinary Institute to study pastry. Her first cookbook, ''The Classic Foods of Latin America,'' is being published by Scribner in 2001.</p>
        <p>Zafra is a vehicle in which she can finally show rather than tell. My advice: go often, try everything.</p>
        <p>There is the gazpacho, for example. The melon version, with hints of lime and mint, could be a refreshing drink, and the tomato version is as sweet and clean as the unadorned ripe fruit.</p>
        <p>Tamals might be next. The pleasantly creamy, sweet vegetarian version is made from grated Andean corn, fresh queso blanco cheese and sugar. The Cubano is also excellent, with a sofrito base, tomatoes and bacon and topped with a piquant lulu sauce made from Mexican chilies, pimentos, tomatillos, garlic, cilantro and onions. The chicken and red mole tamal is somewhat drier, perhaps because of the traditional masa base, but it had the note of chocolate I was looking for.</p>
        <p>There are multiple snack items to choose from. Yuca fries are fried with a light hand and served with a creamy cilantro mayonnaise redolent of garlic, allspice and cumin.  While they may have needed salt, their gratis counterpart, plantain chips, were properly seasoned and eagerly consumed. These came with both the lulu sauce and Ms. Presilla's romesco sauce, made with almonds, red peppers, guajillo peppers and fire-roasted tomatoes. Ecuadorean patties (liapingachos) intrigued me, as their center of queso blanco remained firm even while surrounded by tender mashed potatoes pan-fried in achiote-infused oil. The aji relish (tomato, red onion and cilantro) was refreshing, and the Ecuadorean tostado (toasted Andean corn called cancha in Peru) added crunch. Ms. Presilla tosses these on any dish that  ''needs something.''</p>
        <p>Patacones -- fried ''shoes'' of plantain topped with queso blanco and lulu sauce -- are another winner,  as are the regular tostones and sweeter platanos maduros. Aged slices of artisanal Manchego cheese, topped with roasted peppers and caramelized tomatoes, gave me the first taste of Ms. Presilla's mojo sauce, a mix of garlic, cumin, oregano and bitter orange juice. The pressed Cuban sandwich, whose ham is marinated in the same orange juice along with allspice, can be split into sections for the table. Hot olive oil garlic dressing, simply ladled over romaine hearts, made for a simple yet elegant dish. The ''brick layer'' chicken-cilantro soup smelled of chachucha pepper (similar in appearance to the Scotch bonnet but used for aroma rather than heat).</p>
        <p>You may never need to get to the entrees, but if you do, there are a few that clearly stand out. The chicken enchiladas are served in a tomatillo sauce with refried beans whose irresistible flavor stems from dried epazote (a coriander-like herb) and avocado leaves. The sauce, made with licorice leaves, adds yet another dimension. Or try the camarones coloraditos (shrimp in red mole sauce) over fresh corn polenta and very finely shredded kale. This mole did not contain chocolate, but rather apples, plantains, guajillo chiles and walnuts. Another feast was the large sliced skirt steak, served with a spicy chimichurri sauce loaded with herbs. A side dish of the boiled Andean tuber arracacha sauteed in a sweet mojo ereminded me of sweet potatoes, plantains and coconut all at once, and had me reconfiguring my Thanksgiving menu.</p>
        <p>There are a few missteps, at least comparatively. The ceviche is somewhat gummy, the almond gazpacho bland, and the quesadillas loose and dry. The Chino-Latino shrimp tasted like just that -- a Chinese sauce atop Latin ingredients.</p>
        <p>Still, there is so much to love here.  Which brings us back to harvesting sugar. Every item on the back of the menu is delicious. The fruit drink category boasts a corn fruit punch seasoned with pineapple, peaches, prunes and spices; sorrel wine with dried hibiscus; frozen fermented pineapple peel; Dominican milk and orange juice; batidos Latinos (try the mamey or Andean blackberry); and that Ecuadorean lemonade. Ms. Presilla is especially proud of her tea selection and labor-intensive hot chocolates (importing Venezuelan chocolate is a side business of hers).  But I'd head straight for the panqueques de dulce de leche. Haagen-Daaz is no match for these sweet-salty crepes bursting with caramelized milk. The flan is made with homemade vanilla extract (beans soaked in rum), and three-milk spongecake is porous, wet, soft and delightful.</p>
        <p>Zafra offers one departing treat: a sip of yerba mate, served in an Uruguayan gourd. This hot grass infusion has a whole ceremony to it. All I'll reveal is that you get to keep the bombilla silver straw when you leave, a token of a little place that is doing well indeed.</p>
        <p>Zafra</p>
        <p>301 Willow Street, Hoboken  (201) 610-9801</p>
        <p>EXCELLENT</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE --Festive and homey.  SERVICE -- Welcoming and cheerful.  SMOKING --Not allowed.  WINE LIST -- B.Y.O.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Gazpacho; tamals; yuca fries; liapingachos; patacones; aged Manchego; Cuban sandwich; romaine salad; chicken-cilantro soup; chicken enchiladas; camarones coloraditos (shrimp in red mole sauce); skirt steak; arracacha; corn fruit punch; lemonade; panqueques; three-milk cake; flan; yerba mate.  PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers: $3 to $10.95; sides and salads: $1.25 to $8; entrees: $9 to $18; desserts: $3 to $5.  CREDIT CARDS -- All major.  RESERVATIONS -- Not accepted for fewer than five.  HOURS -- Weekdays, 8 a.m. to 10 p.m. (to 11:30 Fridays); Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 11:30 p.m.; Sundays, 10 a.m. to 10 p.m.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- One level.</p>
        <p>RATINGS -- Poor, Fair, Satisfactory, Good, Very Good, Excellent, Extraordinary.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambiance and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
