<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Our Towns; One Community's Lawbreakers Are Another's Growth Industry</title>
    <meta content="25TOWN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Romulus (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdy, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D91430F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Our Towns; One Community's Lawbreakers Are Another's Growth Industry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW PURDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdy, Matthew</byline>
      <dateline>ROMULUS, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Romulus, NY, (pop. 3,200) welcomes Five Points state prison, which will hold 2,200 inmates, most of them from New York City and a good deal of them serving time as result of state's Rockefeller-era anti-drug laws; prison, which opens in August, will provide 638 full-time jobs and 191 spinoff jobs, and its water and sewer system will also serve the community (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FROM his front porch, Ray Zajac can hear the inmates' voices rising through the double set of glistening razor-wire fences across Main Street. The late afternoon chanting of men exercising in the drug treatment center is money to his ears.</p>
        <p>''The city is subsidizing us by producing these criminals,'' said Mr. Zajac, meaning New York City. ''It's not a nice thing to say, but it's true.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FROM his front porch, Ray Zajac can hear the inmates' voices rising through the double set of glistening razor-wire fences across Main Street. The late afternoon chanting of men exercising in the drug treatment center is money to his ears.</p>
        <p>''The city is subsidizing us by producing these criminals,'' said Mr. Zajac, meaning New York City. ''It's not a nice thing to say, but it's true.''</p>
        <p>That subsidy is about to soar. Once the state's Five Points prison opens here in August, Romulus will be home to 3,200 free-ranging souls and 2,200 inmates. The free-rangers aren't complaining.</p>
        <p>''It's a salvation to us,'' said Mr. Zajac, who has run this Finger Lakes town as the elected supervisor for 29 years.</p>
        <p>Romulus is a village saved by prisons.</p>
        <p>The state psychiatric hospital on Main Street closed in 1995, but reopened as the Department of Correctional Services' Willard Drug Treatment Campus. The 11,000-acre Seneca Army Depot began closing that same year, but the state came through with the $180 million prison now being completed on a secluded corner of the base.</p>
        <p>''It's the largest construction project ever in the Finger Lakes,'' said Michael F. Nozzolio, the local state senator and chairman of the Senate's corrections committee, who brought home this juicy morsel of bacon. Beyond the projected 638 full-time jobs and 191 spinoff jobs, the prison will also rescue Romulus from its own sewage.</p>
        <p>Waste water from about 200 homes near the prison site and Romulus's only school ran through the Army's system for decades. With the Army leaving, the hamlet would need a new system, which it could not afford. But the prison's water and sewer system will serve the town, as well, and pay the local sewer district, which will run it, an estimated $2 million a year, said the district's administrator, the same Ray Zajac.</p>
        <p>''It's a big business, crime is,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Political, too. Sentiment is growing in New York State to rethink drug laws that have helped push the prison population over 71,000, and last week the state's chief judge  announced an effort to send more addicts to treatment rather than jail. But the Legislature ended its session Friday with no action on proposals to ease the state's harshest drug statutes, the Rockefeller-era laws that mandate minimum sentences of 15 years to life for possession or sale of small amounts of drugs -- stiffer sentences than the minimums for rape or manslaughter. Fear of appearing weak on crime overcame political will.</p>
        <p>The inaction in Albany and the construction activity here, 160 miles west, demonstrate that there is just one safe political course when it comes to sentencing wrongdoers: put the pedal to the metal.</p>
        <p>But don't blame Romulus.</p>
        <p>ASIDE from some better-off folks with houses on serene Seneca Lake, Romulus is a collection of three tattered hamlets that largely lived off the state mental hospital and the cold war threat of global conflict that kept the World War II Army depot alive until the Berlin Wall fell. The world has changed, and now Romulus will have a drug treatment center, a maximum security prison and a nonprofit center for troubled youths that Gov. George E. Pataki helped inaugurate on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''We're going from government to government,'' said Dennis Aloia, the Seneca County manager. ''When you're a hungry area, like this place is, you're willing to accept things other places aren't.''</p>
        <p>Prisons are bonanzas in depressed areas, and Glenn R. Cooke, Seneca County's development director, calls Senator Nozzolio ''our rainmaker.'' The senator has six prisons in his district, and the public policy group City Project says more than a third of the state's prisons are in the districts of three senators, Mr. Nozzolio included.</p>
        <p>In Romulus, Sandy Lynd, the postmaster, is expecting business to skyrocket. Dianna LaPrade said the medical office where she works as a nurse had hired an additional doctor, anticipating an influx of prison employees. And she said the guard jobs, with good pay and benefits, will give grown children a reason to stay in town. ''It's a nice touch,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But if the world changes again and there is a move to reduce the nation's world-beating incarceration rate, it will cause economic upheaval for places like Romulus. Not that anyone is expecting, as Mr. Zajac said, ''all the criminals to find the Lord'' or for all the politicians to go soft.</p>
        <p>''I think it's less likely that will happen,'' Mr. Zajac said, ''than the Berlin Wall coming down.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
