<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="25GUID$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3DB1131F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1410" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA DELATINER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>Glen Cove holds a ''Waterfront Festival 2000'' from Friday through next Sunday at Morgan Park. To celebrate the new millennium, a dozen ships, from a 40-foot Viking long boat from Wilmington, Del., to an 80-foot schooner from Otranto, Italy, to the two-masted Californian, the only tall ship to make the trip from the West Coast, to a 455-foot United States Navy frigate, the John L. Hall, will be in port and available for boarding or viewing. On land, there will be the usual festival activities: evening concerts by the Clark Terry Quintet on Friday, Eye Contact, a ''jazz Latin'' band, on Saturday and the Big Band Association on Sunday; daytime puppet shows, clowns, jugglers and continuous performances by groups like Silver Cloud, an American Indian ensemble, and the Sean Grace Celtic Band; a classic car show and, on Sunday, fireworks (516) 759-7340.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>Glen Cove holds a ''Waterfront Festival 2000'' from Friday through next Sunday at Morgan Park. To celebrate the new millennium, a dozen ships, from a 40-foot Viking long boat from Wilmington, Del., to an 80-foot schooner from Otranto, Italy, to the two-masted Californian, the only tall ship to make the trip from the West Coast, to a 455-foot United States Navy frigate, the John L. Hall, will be in port and available for boarding or viewing. On land, there will be the usual festival activities: evening concerts by the Clark Terry Quintet on Friday, Eye Contact, a ''jazz Latin'' band, on Saturday and the Big Band Association on Sunday; daytime puppet shows, clowns, jugglers and continuous performances by groups like Silver Cloud, an American Indian ensemble, and the Sean Grace Celtic Band; a classic car show and, on Sunday, fireworks (516) 759-7340.</p>
        <p>Early Holiday</p>
        <p>Although Independence Day falls on a Tuesday this year, some typical holiday activities begin over the weekend. So if July Fourth isn't July Fourth without fireworks, you can begin celebrating Friday when the Southampton Fresh Air Fund holds its annual benefit, ''American Picnic,'' at a private home on the ocean. While activities like pony rides, carnival booths, a dinner buffet and a petting zoo are on the estate -- and require tickets to support a summer camp for children with physical disabilities -- the Grucci fireworks can be seen along the village beaches (631) 283-7596. Also out east, but on Saturday night there are fireworks at East Hampton Village's Main Beach (631) 324-0362; at the Polo Grounds in Greenport (631) 477-1943, and at Crescent Beach on Shelter Island (631) 749-0399. In Sayville, with the West Islip Symphony Orchestra performing a free concert at 7:30 p.m., there are fireworks at the Island Hills Golf Club on Lakeland Avenue (631) 661-2087.</p>
        <p>There are other traditional pursuits as well. How about an old-fashioned Fireman's Carnival? There is one from 6 to 11 p.m. Thursday through July 4 at the Greenport Polo Grounds (631) 477-9801. How about an ''1890's Summer Fair,'' complete with Victorian melodrama, musical entertainment, puppet shows and pony rides? The Unitarian Universalist Fellowship on Nicolls Road in Stony Brook has one from 11 a.m. to 7 p.m. Saturday and Sunday (631) 724-0871. The St. James General Store, on Moriches Road, has its Arts and Crafts Festival from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Saturday and Sunday, with traditional music by Tim and Mike Fitall of Sampapwan's Creek Saturday and folk tunes by Frank Hendricks and Bob Conroy on Sunday; both from noon to 4 p.m. (631) 862-8333.</p>
        <p>For a historical perspective, the Raynham Hall Museum on West Main Street in Oyster Bay, holds a mini-military encampment from noon to 5 p.m. Saturday, Sunday and July 4, inviting ''patriots'' to enlist in the Continental Army and learn how to soldier, circa 1776. The museum, based in a pre-Revolutionary house and with 1817 American flag on display, will also be open (516) 922-6808. Finally, there's even some pure entertainment in the offing, with ''Yankee Doodle Dandy: The George M. Cohan Story.'' The musical, written by David Armstrong and with music by Cohan (like ''You're a Grand Old Flag'' and ''Yankee Doodle Dandy'') has its world premiere on Wednesday at the Gateway Playhouse, on South Country Road in Bellport, and runs through July 15. A barbecue precedes the performance on July 4 (631) 286-1133.</p>
        <p>Park Concerts</p>
        <p>Get those blankets and beach chairs ready; The free summer concert music scene heats up this week as four park series make their debuts. Today, the Boardwalk Bandshell at Jones Beach State Park in Wantagh begins its six-night-a-week programming with Sundays featuring Manhattan Rhapsody, a top-40 band; Tuesdays and Thursdays showcasing square dancing with Primo; Wednesdays put aside for line dancing with Sherry Palencia and the Fugitives; Fridays highlighting Undercover, a 60's to 90's band; and Dog Soldiers, a rock and rhythm and blues group, taking over on Saturdays. The fun beings at 8 p.m. and runs through Sept. 2 (516) 785-2420.</p>
        <p>The Lakeside Theater at Eisenhower Park in East Meadow starts its prgramming tomorrow at 8 p.m. with the first of its series of ethnic nights: ''Italian-American Night'' with ''These Three Tenors,'' Michael Crouse, Rinaldo Toglia and Thomas Stallone, headlining. Ray Schinnery and his ''Blues Show'' appear in ''African-American Night: A Tribute to Youth'' on Friday, while the ''B-104 Show'' with Tommy James and the Shondells and Randy and the Rainbows, featuring Randy Safuto, take a bow Saturday (516) 572-0223. The North Fork Chorale gets things started for the ''Summer Showcase Concert Series'' at Silversmith's Corner'' in Southold at 8 p.m. on Wednesday (631) 765-3598, while North Hempstead Town's schedule begins on Friday with the Make-Believe Ballroom Orchestra at 7:30 p.m. at Manorhaven Beach Park (516) 327-3110. Saturday is when the ''2000 Music Under the Stars'' concerts begin in Long Beach with the American Concert Band at 8 p.m. at National Beach (516) 431-3890.</p>
        <p>Merman Tribute</p>
        <p>Rita McKenzie is a cabaret singer with a specialty: she can belt a song with the best of them. And since ''the best of them'' was Ethel Merman, the diva has become the object of Ms. McKenzie's performances with ''Ethel Merman's Broadway,'' a show that recreates Merman's life and celebrates her music. Ms. McKenzie brings that show to the Westhampton Beach Performing Arts Center on Main Street on Saturday at 8:30 p.m. (631) 288-1500.</p>
        <p>All Talk</p>
        <p>The spoken word dominates the East End scene this week. Today, with Barbara Goldsmith, an author, moderating, Guild Hall on Main Street in East Hampton holds a panel discussion on ''The Meaning of Celebrity.'' Peter Stone, the stage director, and Lynn Sherr, the television journalist, are among the panelists at 5 p.m. (631) 324-4050. Meanwhile, down the road a bit in the Springs section of East Hampton, also at 5 p.m., another discussion, ''The (Un)Real Thing: Fakes, Replicas, Appropriations and the Problems of Authentication,'' takes place at the Pollock-Krasner House on Fireplace Road (631) 324-4929.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Southampton College begins the public lecture part of its annual Summer Writers Conference. A panel featuring such writers as Kaylie Jones, Robert Reeves and Bob Leuci, novelists, and William Heyen and William Hathaway, poets, will discuss the conference theme, ''Writing for Love, Writing for Money'' at 8 p.m. in the Duke Lecture Hall. John Dufresne, a novelist, and Mr. Heyen talk on Thursday and Friday, respectively, while Saturday's session will be devoted to ''New Voices: June Spence and Susan Choi.'' The talks continue through July 6 (631) 287-8175. Finally, on Friday, the Hampton Library on Main Street in Bridgehampton begins its ''Fridays at Five 2000'' series of weekly author chats with the novelist Rona Jaffe. Other speakers will include Dava Sobel, July 7; Roger Rosenblatt, Aug. 4; and Robert A. Caro, Aug. 25 (631) 537-0015.</p>
        <p>'Cabaret by the Sea'</p>
        <p>Taking some literary license -- no, Guild Hall, isn't actually on the ocean -- the East Hampton Cultural Center starts a new musical series on Friday: ''Cabaret by the Sea.'' Betty Buckley is first up, appearing at 8 p.m. at the center's John Drew Theater on Main Street, and after Ms. Buckley repeats her show on Saturday, she will be followed in the series by Andrea Marcovicci, July 7 and 8; Karen Akers, July 15; Jane Olivor, July 29; Michael Feinstein, Aug. 11 and 12; and Linda Eder, Aug. 19 (631) 324-4050.</p>
        <p>Free Choices</p>
        <p>TODAY -- The Senior Pops Ensemble appears at 2 p.m. at Lake Ronkonkoma County Park (631) 854-9699.</p>
        <p>TOMORROW -- Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory holds a public seminar on ''DNA Games: From Computing to Espionage'' at 7 p.m. in Grace Auditorium. Dr. James D. Watson, president of the lab, who discovered DNA, will introduce the speakers: Viviana Risca, a senior at Schreiber High School in Port Washington who won this year's Intel Science Talent Search by encoding a message on a piece of synthetic DNA, and Dr. Laura F. Landweber of Princeton University, a pioneer in DNA computing (516) 367-8455.</p>
        <p>THURSDAY -- Two villages hold outdoor concerts: Hal Laufer and Karen Cooper, cabaret entertainers, perform at 7 p.m. at the Freeport Village Hall Courtyard on North Ocean Avenue (516) 223-2522, and Southern Grace, a contempotrary country band, appears at 7:30 p.m. on the Village Green in Rockville Centre (516) 678-9393.</p>
        <p>BARBARA DELATINER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
