<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cuban Door Will Reopen. Just Don't Ask When.</title>
    <meta content="25VIEW$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210257"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIC VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahn, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic View</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E7DD1730F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cuban Door Will Reopen. Just Don't Ask When.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH KAHN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kahn, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joseph Kahn Economic View column sees momentum building toward repeal of 38-year-old embargo on trade with Cuba, though big breakthrough remains unlikely as long as Fidel Castro is still alive; meanwhile, even the most modest relaxation to permit sales of food and medicine to Cuba faces uncertain prospects in Republican-controlled House; Cuban-American lobby is pushing to limit sales to cash-on-delivery basis only, a restriction under which trade rarely flourishes; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE United States seems to have tired of using the fruits of American labor as a weapon in global politics. In the span of a month, Congress eliminated China's annual trade review and President Clinton eased economic sanctions against North Korea. The State Department even dropped the term ''rogue state'' from its diplomatic lexicon: Libya, Iraq and Syria are now simply ''states of concern.''</p>
        <p>Could the 38-year embargo on trade with Cuba be next? There's some real momentum building, but don't bet on a big breakthrough, at least while Fidel Castro is still alive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE United States seems to have tired of using the fruits of American labor as a weapon in global politics. In the span of a month, Congress eliminated China's annual trade review and President Clinton eased economic sanctions against North Korea. The State Department even dropped the term ''rogue state'' from its diplomatic lexicon: Libya, Iraq and Syria are now simply ''states of concern.''</p>
        <p>Could the 38-year embargo on trade with Cuba be next? There's some real momentum building, but don't bet on a big breakthrough, at least while Fidel Castro is still alive.</p>
        <p>Plenty of people, including some powerful business lobbying groups, are determined to see the embargo relaxed or eliminated outright. But even the most modest easing, to permit sales of food and medicine to Cuba, faces uncertain prospects in the Republican-controlled House.</p>
        <p>Passage is closer than ever, if only because the bill's Republican sponsor, George R. Nethercutt, faces a tough re-election fight in Washington State's farm country. But the Cuban-American lobby is pushing for a compromise that would allow sales only for cash on delivery -- no credit allowed. Trade rarely flourishes under such a restriction, which is the point.</p>
        <p>Cuban-Americans, many of them passionately anti-Castro, make up less than one-half of 1 percent of the population, but they are a political law unto themselves. Cubans are concentrated in Florida, a swing state in presidential elections, and they turn out heavily for candidates who pledge not to compromise with Mr. Castro.</p>
        <p>Witness the way both Al Gore and George W. Bush opposed the Clinton administration's decision to send Elian Gonzalez back to Cuba with his father, defying opinion polls in the thick of the primary campaign.</p>
        <p>''Cubans punch way above their weight in presidential politics, and that's not changing,'' said Max Castro, a senior researcher at the North-South Center of Miami University. ''The day will come that we don't have an embargo, but I think it will have to be chipped away bit by bit.''</p>
        <p>A flurry of what Charles S. Shapiro, head of the State Department's Cuban Affairs Office, calls ''changes at the margins'' are already under way. More American are visiting Cuba. Some 135,000 Americans received official permission last year, up 10 percent from the year before. Some, including the Yale Glee Club and the Baltimore Orioles, flew on new direct air service to Havana from New York or Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>The tourist flow is still small, but not irrelevant for the United States hotel industry, which remembers Cuba as the leading Caribbean destination before the Castro era. Competitors from Spain and Canada, which do not restrict trade with Cuba, are leading a rush to invest there while American chains must watch from 90 miles away. Hotel groups are among a swelling anti-embargo lobby gathering steam in Washington.</p>
        <p>OTHER pro-trade groups are trying to make the case that Cuba's 11 million people are hungry for American goods. Paula Stern, the former chairwoman of the United States International Trade Commission who now heads her own trade consulting group, calculates that without the embargo the United States could sell $444 million of food and medicine a year in Cuba, generating 6,000 jobs.</p>
        <p>''There's a growing sense in the business community that if we're going to trade with North Korea, Vietnam, Russia and some countries in the Middle East, why aren't we trading with Cuba?'' said Thomas J. Donohue, president of the United States Chamber of Commerce. ''People are asking fundamental questions about a policy that's clearly illogical.''</p>
        <p>But Congress is listening with just one ear, at least so far. The Senate seems not to even want to study the matter: last week, it voted 59 to 41 against creating a special commission to research the effectiveness of the Cuba embargo.</p>
        <p>Part of the problem is that Cuba upends the usual political order in Washington. Democrats, usually skeptical of free trade, generally want to lift the embargo, while ordinarily trade-friendly Republicans tend to want to retain it.</p>
        <p>Larry Birns, a Cuba expert at the Council on Hemispheric Affairs in Washington, says that when the embargo finally goes, 2000 will be seen as the watershed. The Gonzalez case exposed the anti-Castro lobby as fanatical, a label that will be hard to shake, Mr. Birns said.</p>
        <p>But he thinks the political calculus still does not favor dramatic action on the embargo, and certainly not in an election year.</p>
        <p>''You can accuse people of hypocrisy and double standards all you want,'' he said. ''But they're not going to do anything about it until they see a political advantage.''</p>
        <p>ECONOMIC VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
