<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rehab Center for Addicts Runs Out of Luck and Will Close</title>
    <meta content="25CRAF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210235"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: EAST VILLAGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">All-Craft Center (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Denny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EED81630F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="474" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rehab Center for Addicts Runs Out of Luck and Will Close</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNY LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Denny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>All-Craft Center on St Marks Place in Manhattan, haven for recovering drug addicts for more than two decades, loses its mortgage and is scheduled to close on July 1 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The All-Craft Center, a sprawling complex that served as a haven for recovering drug addicts for more than two decades, has lost its mortgage and is scheduled to close on July 1.</p>
        <p>Since 1976, the nonprofit center has operated out of a block of buildings from 19 to 25 St. Marks Place, offering social services to former substance abusers, the homeless and others. But in recent years the center has accrued multimillion-dollar debts, and it filed for bankruptcy in 1995.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The All-Craft Center, a sprawling complex that served as a haven for recovering drug addicts for more than two decades, has lost its mortgage and is scheduled to close on July 1.</p>
        <p>Since 1976, the nonprofit center has operated out of a block of buildings from 19 to 25 St. Marks Place, offering social services to former substance abusers, the homeless and others. But in recent years the center has accrued multimillion-dollar debts, and it filed for bankruptcy in 1995.</p>
        <p>When the center failed to make a court-supervised payment of $3.2 million due on May 1, the United States Bankruptcy Court in Manhattan allowed the main mortgage holder, Second St. Marks, to foreclose and buy the properties.</p>
        <p>A principal with Second St. Marks said his company was undecided about the future of the property. But Arthur Steinberg, a partner at Kaye, Scholer, Fierman, Hays &amp; Handler,  which has represented All-Craft without charge, said that the intent of Second St. Marks ''was always to develop it as a commercial, revenue-generating property.''</p>
        <p>Word of the foreclosure left the center shaken.</p>
        <p>''It's inconceivable that this place could be taken away,'' said Iris Gonzalez, a counselor at the center who said she was a former cocaine user.</p>
        <p>She added that she had not used drugs since 1993, when she was escorted to the center from jail.</p>
        <p>''This place has helped so many people get their lives together,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Vanessa Babbitt is among the 26 people who call the center home. She said she was a former heroin addict, originally from Providence, R.I., who  found her way to the center after a friend abandoned her in the city seven months ago.</p>
        <p>''They took me in that night,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Joyce Hartwell, All-Craft's founder, said the center had served tens of thousands of people. It started out as the Lady Carpenter Institute, which taught woodworking and plumbing to poor women but soon expanded to include 12-step programs, an overnight homeless shelter and performance spaces.</p>
        <p>''We were the first home to Narcotics Anonymous in the city,'' Ms. Hartwell said. ''Now there are 2,000 meetings citywide.''</p>
        <p>Still, some neighborhood residents have complained of sidewalk congestion and excessive noise, especially during the dances on its alcohol-free disco nights.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hartwell, who has no plans for a new location, said she would appeal the court-approved sale. She was optimistic.</p>
        <p>''People here have been up against tremendous odds,'' Ms. Hartwell  said. ''The chance to fight is better than where we came from.''</p>
        <p>DENNY LEE</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: EAST VILLAGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
