<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Whaddaya Mean You Don't Wanna Play Here?</title>
    <meta content="25VECS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DC1530F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Whaddaya Mean You Don't Wanna Play Here?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By George Vecsey</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RANTING, apparently, is in style. Dennis Miller, the new man in the booth for ''Monday Night Football,'' is known for his rants.</p>
        <p>If ABC wanted rants, they could have hired that homeless guy near my office. All he wants is a quarter a rant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RANTING, apparently, is in style. Dennis Miller, the new man in the booth for ''Monday Night Football,'' is known for his rants.</p>
        <p>If ABC wanted rants, they could have hired that homeless guy near my office. All he wants is a quarter a rant.</p>
        <p>In the aftermath, everybody is ranting about the sacrilege of hiring a sarcastic comedian to ''Monday Night Football.'' Apparently, this will defile the dignified memory of Howard, Giff and Dandy Don, doing their Edward R. Murrow imitations.</p>
        <p>But, hey, if ranting is in, let's give it a try:</p>
        <p>I'm sick of watching the fans and the news media being played like cheap fiddles in this Sosa-Gonzalez dance. One day Sammy wants to come to New York. The next day he isn't sure. One day Juan doesn't want to come to Yankee Stadium. The next day he might consider a few months to see if he likes it.</p>
        <p>What do you mean, Juan Gonzalez doesn't want to play in New York? Is he nuts?</p>
        <p>It may only be a negotiating ploy that Gonzalez has suggested he wants to play someplace quiet, but people are not going to forget these sentiments. Doesn't he know what an honor it is to play in Yankee Stadium?</p>
        <p>Just ask Wade Boggs. Just ask David Wells. Just ask Tim Raines. Just ask Cecil Fielder. Just ask Chili Davis. Just ask Darryl and Doc. Just ask Reggie Jackson, who sat in the Orioles' bus in 1976 and sang ''New York, New York'' and other such ditties, just to tell his temporary teammates he was in a New York frame of mind. Some ballplayers have imagination and some don't.</p>
        <p>Gonzalez may have gotten the wrong idea when he had to duck some missiles from the barbarians in the right-field stands during the three losing playoff series Texas had in Yankee Stadium in 1996, '98 and '99.</p>
        <p>There is no excuse for the vile language and aerial warfare conducted from the outer seats, but hasn't Gonzalez figured out that the boos tend to stop when you put on the stripes? (Unless you've got Whitson's Disease, that is.)</p>
        <p>Maybe he got discouraged from batting 1 for 12 and 2 for 11 in the past two playoffs against the Yankees, but he has to remember the awesome feeling of hitting three homers in two games in the Stadium in 1996 and going 7 for 16 and driving in nine runs. They could hardly get him out.</p>
        <p>Anybody with that kind of series and a minimal sense of imagination would look around him and say, ''I could own this place.''</p>
        <p>Instead, the guy is using New York for leverage, or else he has got the pips. He doesn't like New York? Who does he think he is, John Rocker?</p>
        <p>By the way, that gallant spitter into toll booths is coming to town on Thursday. Somehow, Rocker has emerged as a symbol for conservatives. Apparently, it's a freedom of speech issue.</p>
        <p>Nobody said he didn't have the right to be prejudiced against whole swaths of the population. On the other hand, some of us have the obligation to reply, ''Those are our relatives and our friends and our neighbors you're talking about, young fellow.''</p>
        <p>Rocker's defenders should see the disgusted looks on the faces of his Atlanta teammates, who are athletes, not ideologues. In their pragmatism, they think he is a cancer.</p>
        <p>Now Rocker wants to indulge himself in a subway ride to Shea Stadium. He'll cost New Yorkers thousands of dollars for security by going out in public. Who does he think he is, a presidential candidate?</p>
        <p>Gonzalez has not made any anti-New York statements, but the original word was that he did not want to play here. Isn't this the same guy who said he wouldn't play in the All-Star Game if he couldn't start? Didn't Steinbrenner check his dossier?</p>
        <p>Now the Gonzalez camp is floating out the suggestion that Gonzalez wants rent-a-player status, coming to the Bronx and taking a look around.</p>
        <p>That might work, except that first impressions are not always so great. Mike Piazza had that deer-in-the-headlights look when he landed in Shea Stadium. At first, the fans booed him, sensing, in their cruelty, that he was stunned. Now they love the big gentle lug.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Gonzalez might find love at first sight. He could be like the vast majority of cool guys who have come to New York in recent years and found it much more than doable. Derek Jeter gets around. Darryl Hamilton fits in fine. Al Leiter's looking at public schools in Manhattan for one of his kids. Public schools! John Olerud rode the subway. So does Todd Zeile.</p>
        <p>Gonzalez would be a better fit for the Yankees than Sammy Sosa, but on the other hand Sammy would light up the Bronx with his smile.</p>
        <p>Doesn't Gonzalez know what a career move this could be? He has never been to the World Series. Hasn't he seen what happens to even a Jim Leyritz or a Chad Curtis or a Scott Brosius when they start playing best-of-seven in late October?</p>
        <p>This guy doesn't get it. He doesn't deserve New York. Besides, what the Yankees really need is pitching.</p>
        <p>That's it for the ranting. The ranter near my office told me everything is the C.I.A.'s fault. The guy is a loon. Everybody knows it's Nike's fault.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
