<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Nascar, the Deals Are Short-Lived, but the Memories Last Long</title>
    <meta content="25SPOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210469"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PERSPECTIVE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Huler, Scott</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E3DB1130F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1553" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Nascar, the Deals Are Short-Lived, but the Memories Last Long</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SCOTT HULER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Huler, Scott</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scott Huler article on deals made by Nascar auto racing team spotters while they are atop grandstand roof keeping drivers informed of where competition is on track; notes deals play bigger role at Talladega and Daytona, where cooperation between cars on drafting is key to winning; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every sport has its deals.</p>
        <p>In baseball, you want to make a deal, you go to spring training. Football or hockey? Try draft day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every sport has its deals.</p>
        <p>In baseball, you want to make a deal, you go to spring training. Football or hockey? Try draft day.</p>
        <p>But in Winston Cup racing, the deals go down where the guys go up -- in the spotter's stand on top of the speedway grandstand. During every race, every team sends a spotter to the roof; it's a rule. And everyone knows he spends the race telling the driver what he sees.</p>
        <p>Except the spotter has one more responsibility. He makes deals.</p>
        <p>Spotters make small deals throughout any race. They can promise later cooperation if a lapped car will give way, or they can explain why a lapped car will refuse to cooperate; perhaps it hopes to regain its lap, or perhaps the driver remembers a race two years previously when he didn't get the cooperation he asked for.</p>
        <p>If someone wants to get by a car, his spotter has to have something to offer the passed car -- help later in the race, help during another race. Sometimes it's as ineffable as a general spirit of cooperation that can grow between two teams over years; other times it's a promise to stick together until a certain point in the race.</p>
        <p>''This is no different than negotiating business contracts in a boardroom,'' said Vic Maguire, spotter for the No. 10 car driven by Johnny Benson. ''It's a give-and-take.''</p>
        <p>The spotters wheel and deal the most at the superspeedways at Daytona, where the Pepsi 400 takes place on Saturday night, and Talladega.</p>
        <p>At Talladega Superspeedway in Alabama, the real deals go down in a couple of rows of rickety aluminum bleachers high atop the grandstand at the start-finish line, almost in Turn 1. There, in a cloud of gnats in the brutal Southern sun, squinting across the 2.66-mile track through haze so thick the spotters can barely identify their own cars in Turn 3, twice-a-year spotters engage in a kind of dealing that has parallels nowhere else in Nascar -- or any other sport.</p>
        <p>Of course, Job 1 one for a spotter is to keep his driver apprised of where his competition is on the track -- when someone is coming up behind him, when he can move up or down on the track. ''Clear low!'' the spotter says into his radio, and the driver cuts down into traffic, secure that he has a space. At most tracks the spotter does little more than that eye-in-the-sky act, keeping his driver safe and his $100,000 race car in one piece. Says Danny Culler, who spots for the No. 3 car driven by Dale Earnhardt, ''It's kind of like being an air traffic controller for a race-car driver.''</p>
        <p>Except at Talladega and Daytona.</p>
        <p>At those two superspeedways, where carburetor restrictor plates limit engine output and smooth the field to a parity that renders horsepower virtually inconsequential, the aerodynamic draft is the key. In the draft, two or more cars running together outstrip even the fastest car running alone. So without a dance partner, as they say, you're sunk.</p>
        <p>Enter the spotter.</p>
        <p>If a crew chief is looking for a partner, he doesn't go running up and down pit road. ''It's easier to do it through the spotter,'' Maguire said. ''The spotters are all in one place. I'm not more than 30 feet away from a guy who might be a whole straightaway down pit road.''</p>
        <p>So late in a race at Talladega, the spotters' stand can become a cross between a boardroom and a bazaar. The only things at the speedway moving faster than the spotters are the race cars themselves.</p>
        <p>Maguire offered a look into the spotter's life at Talladega during the weekend of the Die Hard 500, which ran April 15.</p>
        <p>''The necessity, in superspeedway racing, is to be in a competitive position at the end of the race,'' Maguire said. ''If you're in a tight draft, in the top five, you've got a chance to win. So you have to create alliances that might not occur at short tracks.''</p>
        <p>All during practice, drivers run just behind and just in front of other cars. How does Benson's Pontiac handle behind a Ford? In front of a Chevy? Are there particular cars it runs with well or poorly? How does it do in a big draft? A small one? All those elements will come into play when it's time to choose a friend on race day.</p>
        <p>When this partnership of necessity is struck midrace, isn't it a little bit like the Mets calling the Dodgers with a deal? Something like: ''If you use your three weakest starters against the Phillies, we'll throw everything we've got against the Giants''?</p>
        <p>Not quite, Maguire said. ''In the first place, baseball isn't open to as many places.'' The driver Kenny Schrader agreed. ''Everything else, it's just two teams,'' he said. ''But when you got 43 cars at once, you get a buddy and say, 'Let's beat those 40 other guys first' -- then we'll lie to each other at the end.''</p>
        <p>Ah, yes -- the lie. ''Really, the deals that are set are like a fairy story,'' Benson said, shrugging and shaking his head. ''A lot of people say, 'Let's work together, let's make a deal,' but that lasts a lap and a half.'' Bart Creasman, spotter for the No. 55 car driven by Kenny Wallace, said it best: ''The real deal is there's no deal.''</p>
        <p>So deals are being broken all race long, and yet there are always more.</p>
        <p>Some spotters get reputations as dealmakers; some guys try to rough their act up to drive harder bargains. ''It's W.W.F. stuff going on up there,'' Maguire said, laughing. And if some spotter is combing the stand to make a deal, Creasman said: ''You can tell your driver, 'Hey, this guy's running up and down -- he ain't watching his car. Jump on him.' ''</p>
        <p>It truly is like a bazaar, where rational self-interest is hardly the rule of the day. Benson gave the example of a group of four or five cars drafting together not in the lead pack. ''That pack of five needs to say, 'We need to stay nose to tail,' '' and the spotters may not even need to get involved. ''That deal's going to last,'' Benson said, ''at least until you get to the lead pack.''</p>
        <p>Then things change. That draft may be the fastest draft on the track -- if they stayed together, they would not only catch but pass the lead cars. But as soon as that draft catches the leaders, someone is going to decide he can run better behind the leaders -- or is going to make a deal with one of the leaders, and everything breaks down in a hurry.</p>
        <p>The example that everyone in the garage still talks about occurred in this season's Daytona 500 on Feb. 20. With only a few laps remaining, Benson led the race, followed by Mark Martin (in the No. 6 car), Dale Jarrett and Jeff Burton (in the No. 99 car). Martin and Jarrett's teams brokered a deal for Martin and Jarrett to pass Benson on the high side, sticking together until they were by him. The spotters and teams had it all worked out.</p>
        <p>It lasted about a tenth of a second. Martin went high, Jarrett moved to follow him -- and saw in his mirror that Burton, Martin's teammate, was going low, which could have left Jarrett out in the cold, behind both cars. ''He was committed to the 6 until the 99 changed his commitment,'' Benson said. ''And he had about two-hundredths of a second to make his decision. That's how deals work. And that's among teammates, let alone the rest of the field.''</p>
        <p>Jarrett won that race; Martin, famous for sticking with his deals, said, ''I got lied to.'' Jimmy Fennig, crew chief for Martin, said at Talladega, ''We learned a lesson, and I guarantee it won't happen again.''</p>
        <p>But it's not that deals are made in bad faith, said Stevie Reeves, spotter for the No. 13 car driven by Robby Gordon, who likens the promises teams make through their spotters to those made by gamblers at a dice table. ''It's like saying, 'I'm going to roll a seven,' '' Reeves said. ''You mean it, but you don't got no control over that.''</p>
        <p>With a few laps remaining in the DieHard 500 at Talladega, which was eventually won by Jeff Gordon, Martin led the race. But he ran in the draft behind Jarrett, who was the last car on the lead lap. The teams communicated through their spotters, Jarrett asking Martin if he preferred him to move. Martin liked his position, and only very late in the race did Jarrett make a gentlemanly shift high to let the leaders by him.</p>
        <p>But don't expect that to make him best friends with Jimmy Fennig.</p>
        <p>''You never forget,'' he said of the Daytona 500. ''You never forget.''</p>
        <p>PERSPECTIVE Scott Huler is author of ''A Little Bit Sideways'' (MBI Publishing Company, 1999) about a week inside a Nascar race team.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Scott Huler is author of ''A Little Bit Sideways'' (MBI Publishing Company, 1999) about a week inside a Nascar race team.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
