<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>War Memories Temper Korean Euphoria</title>
    <meta content="25KORE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210327"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Korean War</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North Korea-International Relations-South Korea</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sims, Calvin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Korean War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EED91430F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1127" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>War Memories Temper Korean Euphoria</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CALVIN SIMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sims, Calvin</byline>
      <dateline>SEOUL, South Korea, June 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Korean War veterans in South Korea feel betrayed by their government, which has canceled all parades and other commemorative activities in observance of war's 50th anniversary because they could be offensive to North Korea, which just agreed to pursue peace and reconciliation after half century of hostilities; some American veterans who have come to Seoul to mark anniversary are as disappointed as South Koreanveterans are; North Korea also will not celebrate anniversary this year to avoid exacerbating hostilities; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a marine during the Korean War, Chang Kyong Hak saw many of his friends die and nearly lost his own life defending South Korea from invading Communist troops from the North.</p>
        <p>And like so many Korean War veterans, Mr. Chang, 66, was so looking forward to marching in a grand military parade that the South Korean government had planned for Sunday to commemorate the start of the conflict 50 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As a marine during the Korean War, Chang Kyong Hak saw many of his friends die and nearly lost his own life defending South Korea from invading Communist troops from the North.</p>
        <p>And like so many Korean War veterans, Mr. Chang, 66, was so looking forward to marching in a grand military parade that the South Korean government had planned for Sunday to commemorate the start of the conflict 50 years ago.</p>
        <p>But instead of strutting down Seoul's main avenues to the fanfare of military bands and cheering crowds as he had envisioned, Mr. Chang said he will most likely stay  home, feeling betrayed by the very country he fought to defend.</p>
        <p>Last week, North Korea agreed to pursue peace and reconciliation with the South after a half century of hostilities. And so the South Korean government has canceled all parades, battle re-enactments and other commemorative war events that could be offensive to the North.</p>
        <p>''It has been 50 years since the government told us to fight against those evil Communists, and now it wants us to accept the North Koreans as brothers and simply forget what they did,'' said Mr. Chang, a director of the Marines Corps Veterans Association, which has 800,000 members. ''Well, it's an insult that our own government doesn't even know how to properly treat those who fought and died for the nation.''</p>
        <p>Not only has the decision to tone down the anniversary celebrations brought angry denouncements from veterans, but it has also touched off a heated national debate over the significance of the Korean War and just how far the South should go to appease the North.</p>
        <p>Before the South Korean president, Kim Dae Jung, and the North Korean leader, Kim Jong Il, held historic talks in Pyongyang last week, the Communist North was widely viewed as one of the world's most bellicose nations. But after the two leaders were seen on national television here embracing and laughing and agreed to reconcile their differences, South Koreans were forced to view their decades-old nemesis in a different light.</p>
        <p>The debate over how to gauge North Korea comes as hundreds of veterans, diplomats and officials from around the world have arrived in Seoul to participate in commemoration events.</p>
        <p>The war began on June 25, 1950, after North Korea invaded the South. Russia and China took the side of the North, while the United States led a United Nations force fighting for the South. About three million people died on both sides, including an estimated 900,000 Chinese troops and 30,000 Americans. The fighting officially ended in 1953 when the North and South signed an armistice agreement, but technically the two countries are still at war.</p>
        <p>Some American veterans who came here to mark the anniversary are as disappointed as Mr. Chang.  Fred Machado, a Navy veteran from Fresno, Calif., said he was upset that South Korea had decided to scale back on the war commemorations.</p>
        <p>But Congressman Charles B. Rangel, who described his one-year tour of duty in Korea as a nightmare, had another view. ''When countries have been at war for 50 years and when they are concentrating on peace rather than war, I would think that doves and olive leaves are a little more important than parades and display of military power,'' he said. Mr. Rangel, a New York Democrat, was in Seoul as part of an official delegation for the ceremonies.</p>
        <p>South Korea had planned to spend about $40 million on commemoration events, including a parade with more than 15,000 veterans from Korea and abroad and re-enactments of major battles, including Gen. Douglas MacArthur's daring landing at Inchon. The events were to begin on Sunday and continue over three years, ending with the commemoration of the signing of the armistice.</p>
        <p>The annual parade is normally a grand display of patriotism. This will be the first time that it has been called off. South Korean officials said they had decided to scale back events as a good-will gesture toward Kim Jong Il.</p>
        <p>North Korea normally celebrates the July 24 anniversary of the signing of the armistice as War Victory Day. But the North Korean leader said during the summit meeting that North Korea would not celebrate the anniversary this year to avoid exacerbating hostilities.</p>
        <p>The South Korean government had considered canceling any commemoration of the war but decided that to do so would offend the many foreign veterans and guests who were coming to attend them. Instead of the parades and re-enactments, South Korea plans to hold what it views as more benign ceremonies -- seminars, wreath-layings, photo exhibits, and luncheons and dinner parties for veterans, the officials said.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, President Kim will address South Koreans in a ceremony to be held at the Korean War memorial. But government officials said the ceremony is to honor the memory of Korean and foreign veterans who sacrificed their lives for peace.</p>
        <p>Han Moon Koo, a factory worker whose father was taken prisoner in the war, said he is, like many South Koreans, excited about the prospects for peace on the Korean peninsula. But he and others say they are still wary of Kim Jong Il, who in the past has shown himself to be as dictatorial and warlike as his father, Kim Il Sung, the country's longtime ruler before his death in 1994.</p>
        <p>Mr. Han was 7 years old the last time he saw his father, who was preparing to go off to war and was later captured by the North. ''The war robbed me of my father while I was growing up, but oddly on this 50th anniversary, there's a real chance that I might get to see him again if he's still alive,'' Mr. Han said, referring to a prisoner exchange program that was announced during the summit meeting.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Han said that it would not be easy to divorce himself from the hatred he has long harbored against North Korea. ''I know that we are of the same race,'' he said, ''but I still consider North Koreans to be my worst enemy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
