<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>50,000 Genes, and We Know Them All (Almost)</title>
    <meta content="25BALT$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210313"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baltimore, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5DA1430F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1092" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>50,000 Genes, and We Know Them All (Almost)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Baltimore</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baltimore, David</byline>
      <dateline>PASADENA, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Baltimore Op-Ed article marvels at imminent publication of rough draft of human genome, though it will be work of many decades to sort out details; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Humans have no more genetic secrets; our genes are a book open to all to read. It is expected that the federal government and Celera Genomics will announce tomorrow that a rough draft of the total genetic constitution of the human species, its genome, has been completed. The draft information is on a Web site, available to the world.</p>
        <p>The genome is really a generic representation of our genes -- each of us actually carries small variations on the basic sequence. We already know hundreds of thousands of the major variants that occur. But our own personal genetic endowments are discoverable only at high cost, though the price is likely to descend rapidly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Humans have no more genetic secrets; our genes are a book open to all to read. It is expected that the federal government and Celera Genomics will announce tomorrow that a rough draft of the total genetic constitution of the human species, its genome, has been completed. The draft information is on a Web site, available to the world.</p>
        <p>The genome is really a generic representation of our genes -- each of us actually carries small variations on the basic sequence. We already know hundreds of thousands of the major variants that occur. But our own personal genetic endowments are discoverable only at high cost, though the price is likely to descend rapidly.</p>
        <p>How does the genome change our lives now that these secrets are laid so bare?</p>
        <p>First, it confirms something obvious and expected, yet controversial: our genes look much like those of fruit flies, worms and even plants. Should there be any doubt -- and, unfortunately, there is vehement doubt in some circles -- the genome shows that we all descended from the same humble beginnings and that the connections are written in our genes. That should be, but won't be, the end of creationism.</p>
        <p>The genome also tells us much about an organism's complexity. The differences between us and flies is poorly measured by the number of genes encoded in our DNA. Although there is much work left to do to determine the total number of human genes -- and a famous bet is in progress on the final number -- it is looking like 50,000 is a reasonable estimate.</p>
        <p>That is not that far away from our estimate of the number of genes in a fly (14,000) or a worm (18,000). Yet we are much more complex than such lowly critters. How can so few more genes generate so much more apparent complexity? The answer is partly that flies and worms have lots of genes that do specific things for them. The genes that encode the basic functions of life -- for people, flies, worms and even bacteria -- are only a few hundred to a few thousand.</p>
        <p>The other genes elaborate the specific characteristics of particular organisms. A single gene can be responsible for a great complexity of functions. Genes are just information encoded along a long string of the chemical DNA; they cannot do anything themselves. What genes encode is the structures of proteins, which are the working machinery of living beings. They let us walk and talk and think big thoughts.</p>
        <p>One gene can encode many, often 10 or more, different proteins. To carry out different activities, the proteins can vary in amount, be put in different combinations, or be modified. It is the number of proteins, not genes, that determine complexity -- and that is where the true complexity of human life will be measured.</p>
        <p>The genome will also speed up work for scientists. The information from the federal program has been placed on the Web as it was acquired and has already been very useful. It will have an increasing impact. No longer will science and medicine proceed with deep uncertainty over how many genes relate to a particular process. No longer will students and postdoctoral fellows spend long months trying to isolate genes -- they will now simply look them up on the Web. We will now have a wholly new ability: to ask scientific questions about not a single gene, but the entire genome. Now drugs can be developed for every protein to alter its function and help clear up a malfunction.</p>
        <p>However, we should not think that now biology will simply be a process of tying up loose ends. The DNA sequence tells us little about the functions of the genes or their role in the body's overall economy. At best, the sequence lets us infer a gene's capabilities, but only experiments will validate or invalidate those inferences.  Even experiments on the entire genome will generally only pose questions that need to be answered by experiments on single genes.</p>
        <p>My guess is that the next half-century will be taken up with understanding the roles of each of the human genes. And that will only happen if the projected financing for the work of the National Institutes of Health is continued. Moreover, this first draft of the genome is hardly the last word. The federal program is committed to a high-quality, virtually error-free product, and that is a year or two off. Funding for this effort needs to be maintained.</p>
        <p>Finally, the race to complete the genome tells us much about how scientific research should be conducted. There has been extensive media coverage of the acrimonious competition between the government program and that of Celera. But we should put this in perspective and recognize that the government program was centrally organized and therefore had to settle on a single strategy. This compromised a central value of science, testing multiple strategies. That is the essence of scientific competition. Thus, Celera's ability to amass the resources necessary to compete with the federal program helped move the whole effort forward in a more fluid, and ultimately, more effective way. That the two programs plan to coordinate their efforts and publish their genome findings in the same issue of a journal represents a healthier relationship.</p>
        <p>The very celebration of the completion of the human genome is a rare day in the history of science: an event of historic significance is recognized not in retrospect, but as it is happening. It shows the scientific community at its best and most modern, carrying out a program requiring elaborate collaboration, new technology and the latest computer-assisted methods.</p>
        <p>Modern biology is a science of information. The sequencing of the genome is a landmark of progress in specifying information, decoding it into its many coded meanings and learning how it goes wrong in disease. While it is a moment worthy of the attention of every human, we should not mistake progress for a solution. There is yet much hard work to be done.</p>
        <p>It will take many decades to fully comprehend the magnificence of the DNA edifice built over four billion years of evolution and held in the nucleus of each cell of the body of each organism on earth.</p>
        <p>David Baltimore, the president of the California Institute of Technology, won the Nobel prize in medicine in 1975.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Baltimore, the president of the California Institute of Technology, won the Nobel prize in medicine in 1975.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
