<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investing; Betting on a Software Lingua Franca</title>
    <meta content="25ENTE$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000702T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210243"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Lawrence M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EFD61630F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="976" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investing; Betting on a Software Lingua Franca</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE M. FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Lawrence M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Problem of integrating applications has worsened as mainframes have given way to minicomputers, which have in turn given way to client server networks; rush to e-commerce has lent new urgency to resolving integration problems and has spawned a number of new companies that offer ready-made integration software for business programs; illustration, graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BY coincidence, on May 22, Vignette announced that it was buying OnDisplay, and WebMethods trumpeted its acquisition of Active Software.</p>
        <p>The deals, both billion-dollar-plus stock swaps, put a spotlight on an obscure branch of the software industry -- enterprise application integration. It makes for an awkward phrase, but the companies in this niche could be poised for hypergrowth in the era of electronic commerce.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BY coincidence, on May 22, Vignette announced that it was buying OnDisplay, and WebMethods trumpeted its acquisition of Active Software.</p>
        <p>The deals, both billion-dollar-plus stock swaps, put a spotlight on an obscure branch of the software industry -- enterprise application integration. It makes for an awkward phrase, but the companies in this niche could be poised for hypergrowth in the era of electronic commerce.</p>
        <p>Getting one software program to talk to another has been tricky ever since a programmer created the second mainframe application and tried to connect it to the first. As mainframes gave way to minicomputers and minis to client server networks running packaged applications, the problem worsened, becoming a sort of permanent employment act for consultant armies.</p>
        <p>With the rush to conduct business online, connecting one application to another has assumed greater urgency. Now a company must not only make its own inventory program communicate with the application that enters orders, but it must also make these pieces of software connect to their counterparts at vendors and customers.</p>
        <p>Software integration has become too big a problem to address one connection at a time, with custom software from consultants or in-house programmers. So a gaggle of new companies -- including those in last month's deals as well as Tibco Software, NEON Systems, Vitria Technology and the  Software Technologies Corporation -- have emerged to offer ready-made software to help stitch together corporate America's patchwork quilt of business programs.</p>
        <p>''There are very few categories of the software business that have a greater long-term opportunity than this one,'' said Roger McNamee, a partner in Integral Capital Partners, a venture capital fund that began investing in many of these companies when they were still private and continues to hold them as publicly traded stocks. ''They have an advantage over the average tech stock in that the demand curve is vertical.''</p>
        <p>The biggest reason has been the Internet-fueled proliferation of specialized applications, all of which must be connected both to so-called legacy applications -- those that companies have been using for years to automate business processes -- and to every new Web program that comes along.</p>
        <p>While it may be too early to pick the ultimate winners, investors might consider buying a basket of these stocks. Mr. McNamee particularly likes Vitria and Software Technologies, known as S.T.C. -- two companies with very different market profiles.</p>
        <p>''Vitria is distinguished by focusing on the telecom industry,'' he said. ''The amount of legacy stuff in that industry is staggering; the amount of change in new technology is equally staggering, so it was perceived as too difficult. That's given them something of  a protected niche.''</p>
        <p>Software Technologies, one of the earliest entrants, is more horizontal, working with many industries. ''S.T.C. is sort of the everyman of the space,'' Mr. McNamee said.</p>
        <p>Most integration companies started by solving a particular problem, often for a particular industry, and now must expand their offerings in order to grow. One path is through acquisition, which explains why WebMethods, a specialist in business-to-business integration, acquired Active Software, a specialist in coordinating applications within a business. Vignette, which sells software designed to let companies personalize customers' interactions with their Web-based systems, acquired OnDisplay to bolster its business-to-business integration.</p>
        <p>The consolidation trend favors larger companies, particularly those with big market capitalizations and premium stock prices -- potential currency for new acquisitions. That is why Rehan Syed, an analyst at S. G. Cowen, has a buy recommendation on NEON and a strong buy on Tibco.</p>
        <p>''I believe all these vendors will extend their capacities, either through acquisitions or in-house development,'' Mr. Syed said. ''We think NEON, the largest company in the space, will continue to do well. Tibco, as one of the largest, with a premium market cap, is positioned well to be a consolidator.''</p>
        <p>THE spring sell-off punished integration companies severely, as technology investors gravitated toward blue-chip names like Sun Microsystems, Oracle and Cisco Systems. So while some integration companies still have sky-high price-to-earnings multiples -- or lack earnings outright -- they are generally trading 50 percent or so below their highs for the year.</p>
        <p>The main threat to the sector is that companies could change their software buying patterns, moving away from mixing and matching applications from many vendors and toward suites, which include various  applications that are designed to work together. Oracle, in particular, is pushing a suite of back-office and e-commerce applications, and Microsoft plans a technology called BizTalk.</p>
        <p>''The fact that you need these companies at all is a function of how programs were built in the past,'' said Charles Phillips, an analyst at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter. ''I think it will get easier to connect third-party applications without creating another layer of technology.''</p>
        <p>He is not alone. Jeff Wrona, portfolio manager of the $3.6 billion PBHG Technology and Communications fund, worries that integration ''is quickly becoming a commodity.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Mr. Phillips sees opportunities in the sector. He has an outperform rating on WebMethods and Software Technologies, both of which were taken public by Morgan Stanley. ''From an investment standpoint, this is a good time to look at these companies,'' he said. ''The absolute size of the companies is still quite small.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 2, 2000, Sunday  An article last Sunday about companies that make enterprise application integration software -- programs that let different software applications work with one another -- misidentified a company on which an analyst, Rehan Syed of SG Cowen, has a buy recommendation. It is New Era of Networks of Denver, commonly called NEON, not NEON Systems of Sugarland, Tex., another company in the sector; Mr. Syed does not follow NEON Systems.</p>
        <p>A chart accompanying the article, which showed the stock price of NEON Systems, was labeled correctly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 2, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about companies that make enterprise application integration software -- programs that let different software applications work with one another -- misidentified a company on which an analyst, Rehan Syed of SG Cowen, has a buy recommendation. It is New Era of Networks of Denver, commonly called NEON, not NEON Systems of Sugarland, Tex., another company in the sector; Mr. Syed does not follow NEON Systems.</p>
        <p>A chart accompanying the article, which showed the stock price of NEON Systems, was labeled correctly.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
