<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Show of Photographs Where Hope Is Channeled</title>
    <meta content="25ART.$16" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210094"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Katonah Museum of Art</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E1D81E31F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="933" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Show of Photographs Where Hope Is Channeled</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM ZIMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmer, William</byline>
      <dateline>KATONAH</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Zimmer reviews exhibition of photogaphs titled Hope on view at Katonah Museum of Art in Katonah, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PHOTOGRAPHING something as  intangible as hope  the emotion or condition -- sounds at first like photographing fairies in Victorian England. Everyone has hopes, but how do you capture them?</p>
        <p>The Katonah Museum of Art here has taken a loan exhibition of photographs titled simply ''Hope,'' and it turns out to be a meditation on very palpable subject matter. Like rising sap, hope, it seems, is channeled through these subjects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PHOTOGRAPHING something as  intangible as hope  the emotion or condition -- sounds at first like photographing fairies in Victorian England. Everyone has hopes, but how do you capture them?</p>
        <p>The Katonah Museum of Art here has taken a loan exhibition of photographs titled simply ''Hope,'' and it turns out to be a meditation on very palpable subject matter. Like rising sap, hope, it seems, is channeled through these subjects.</p>
        <p>The photographer and the viewers must at least be simpatico with the idea or potential of hope. It would be easy to be cynical, but the quality of the work here is generally strong, so viewers either receive a pleasant jolt by identifying the hope in a given picture right away, or they are led to imagine an optimistic story around a picture.</p>
        <p>Some of the subjects are almost symbols:  Robert Adams photographs two dove eggs undisturbed in a large field; Dag Alveng photographs an open gate, and William Clift has caught a rainbow arching over the flat plain of Waldo, N.M. Graham MacIndoe's ''Fortune Teller,'' meanwhile, examines an open palm that is strangely lineless.</p>
        <p>The curators, Alice Rose George and Lee Marks, must have had a fascinating time finding examples of hope, and they wisely included scientific, as well as artistic, photographs in their survey.</p>
        <p>Viewers might have to be told what they're seeing in some cases; Lennart Nilsson's amorphous blue-tinged ''Untitled (Sperm Meeting Egg)'' may be science, but it's also the quintessence of hope.</p>
        <p>Images from the American experience  include a photograph of the lift-off of the Apollo-Saturn moon mission in 1969, taken by a Japanese photographer known as Hiro, as well as a NASA photograph of man's first steps on the moon. Both pictures are suffused with communal hope, as is the grittier ''Marchers, Selma to Montgomery, Ala.,'' a 1965 document of the civil rights movement. The oldest picture in the survey, taken by Jacques-Henri Lartigue in 1910, is a relative of the space pictures: an attempt to get a primitive airplane off the ground.</p>
        <p>A second type of photograph requires viewers to rely on the photographer's word that what's in a picture is what it is purported to be. Jane Evelyn Atwood's dark photograph of a French prostitute at an upper- story window is in that category, as is Nan Goldin's large amber-colored self-portrait. The title informs us that the artist is writing in her diary during de-tox in 1989.</p>
        <p>The ostensible focus of JoAnn Verburg's ''Untitled (Chaco Culture)'' is not the mass of flaming red hair of the woman at the center of the color composition but rather the innocuous-seeming shard she holds, which might signal an archaeological find.</p>
        <p>The global scope of this exhibition is brought home in pictures set amid poverty, where hope naturally has its best chance to shine. The title of Ann Rhoney's ''Tijuana, Family Viewing California While Waiting to Run'' says it all. Mary Ellen Mark has caught a child in a travelers' camp in Ireland playing executive by talking on a discarded telephone among other items in a junk heap. Witold Krassowski photographed a tailor plying his trade in a Rwandan refugee camp, while the children in a band photographed by Rosalind Solomon in Guatemala are enthusiastic about their instruments even though they're made of paper.</p>
        <p>Other photographs wear their artiness on their sleeves. Adam Fuss's picture of a figure in a stained-glass window with some sections blocked out is labeled, ''Untitled (Faceless Prophet Preaching to the Masses).'' One might think Hiroshi Sugimoto was a Minimal artist. His ''Ionian Sea, Santa Cesarea'' appears to be a pitch-black rectangle. Closer inspection reveals some interruptions in the darkness, which are probably waves. It's hard to find a more arty place than the Uffizi Gallery in Florence. Thomas Struth's picture, set in a room devoted to the early Renaissance, almost makes a viewer feel he is there; one sinks into its large size. He focuses on tourists contemplating a madonna painted by Giotto, but the hope factor in this work is elusive.</p>
        <p>On occasion the notion of hope is reinforced by the way works are arranged. A good example involves Christopher Bucklow's silhouette of a man's torso lighted by 25,000 solar images, according to the title. On one side of this mysterious, sparkling image is a very down-to-earth picture by Christine Osinski of a young girl preparing to dive into a swimming pool. Her stance mimics the silhouette in Mr. Bucklow's picture. On its other side is the underside of the Eiffel Tower lighted at night, photographed by Michael Kenna.</p>
        <p>A few instances of several images comprising a single work are one of the exhibition's few flaws. The sense of hope in a photograph has to strike a viewer, and it dissipates in Duane Michal's, ''Grandpa Goes to Heaven,'' composed of five prints, and ''I built a Pyramid,'' which has six. Catherine Wagner's more cerebral ''Sequential Molecules Typology'' is subject to the same loss of force.</p>
        <p>A personal favorite image is Chris Killip's terse ''Girl With Hoop.'' Hope may lie in just saying ''hoop'' very fast.</p>
        <p>''Hope'' is at the Katonah Museum of Art through July 2. For further information, the number to call is (914) 232-9555.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
