<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kristen Gerard, Graham Saladino</title>
    <meta content="25GERA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210119"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GERARD, KRISTEN ROSE (KRISTEN ROSE SALADINO)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALADINO, GRAHAM HENDRICK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DE1F31F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kristen Gerard, Graham Saladino</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kristen Rose Gerard, a daughter of Charles and Terry Gerard of Northford, Conn., was married yesterday to Graham Hendrick Saladino at Robin Hill, the country home of the bridegroom's father, the interior designer John Saladino. The Rev. Ronald D'Angelo, a Roman Catholic priest, performed the ceremony.</p>
        <p>The bride, 27, and bridegroom, 28, started dating as undergraduates at Manhattanville College in Purchase, N.Y. ''Graham wasn't like any of the other guys at school,'' remembered Ms. Gerard, whose father is a service manager for Johnson Controls, a company in Hartford that installs air-conditioners and heaters. ''He could carry on a conversation about anything from his favorite film director to the next place to go in Montana. I learned a lot from him. He'd done everything I wanted to do -- he had skied down the mountains of Italy. He'd driven cross-country.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kristen Rose Gerard, a daughter of Charles and Terry Gerard of Northford, Conn., was married yesterday to Graham Hendrick Saladino at Robin Hill, the country home of the bridegroom's father, the interior designer John Saladino. The Rev. Ronald D'Angelo, a Roman Catholic priest, performed the ceremony.</p>
        <p>The bride, 27, and bridegroom, 28, started dating as undergraduates at Manhattanville College in Purchase, N.Y. ''Graham wasn't like any of the other guys at school,'' remembered Ms. Gerard, whose father is a service manager for Johnson Controls, a company in Hartford that installs air-conditioners and heaters. ''He could carry on a conversation about anything from his favorite film director to the next place to go in Montana. I learned a lot from him. He'd done everything I wanted to do -- he had skied down the mountains of Italy. He'd driven cross-country.''</p>
        <p>The couple moved to New York after graduating from Manhattanville but spent most weekends at Robin Hill, where they said they fell in love. The bridegroom's father, who designed the estate with the bridegroom's mother, the late Virginia Hendrick Saladino, describes the house as ''a palladian brick house that sits like a long train in the midst of 20 acres of woodland and gardens.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Saladino, now the director of sales for the Saladino furniture line, proposed at Robin Hill during Christmas vacation in 1998, while the couple and several of their college friends were having a reunion there. ''He got right down on his knee, with all his best guy friends around us,'' remembered Ms. Gerard, now a freelance fashion editor for magazines in New York. ''Then we busted open his dad's Champagne reserve.''</p>
        <p>That night, he gave her his mother's diamond and platinum engagement ring. ''It's like a cocktail ring,'' Ms. Gerard said. ''At first, it was a little big for me and I remember being on the subway and almost losing it. I was talking with my hand and it slipped to the end of my finger and I remember thinking, If I ever lost this ring, I'd have to hurl myself off a building. It's so irreplaceable, and it was really important to Graham that I wear his mother's ring.''</p>
        <p>In the days before the wedding, the couple and the bridegroom's father placed robin's egg-shaped soaps in the bathrooms at Robin Hill and erected white birdhouses along the roads leading there, to help guests find their way.</p>
        <p>''We worked on this wedding for a year,'' John Saladino said. ''It's an Italian Renaissance banquet. There's a custom-made, all-white tent, with an early medieval silhouette. We did two 80-foot-long banquet tables, covered in an amethyst silk with a della Robbia-style laurel-leaf garland that serpentines its way down the table, moving in and out through handblown hurricane candle lamps. It's going to be very beautiful.</p>
        <p>''The bride is beautiful and my son's handsome,'' Mr. Saladino continued. ''It's a coming together of two very sweet people. They're very serene, low profile for certain, and street smart.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''And they're good friends. That will stand them well in their old years, their golden years, when everything else begins to fade.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
