<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>June 18-24; Bumps on the Road to Nomination</title>
    <meta content="25BOXA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E6D61730F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="405" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>June 18-24; Bumps on the Road to Nomination</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Democrats were livid over a rival of Vice President Al Gore in the race for president. ''He's on an ego trip,'' said Senator Harry Reid, a Nevada Democrat. ''He has no respect for the process.''</p>
        <p>The senator was not speaking of  Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the presumptive Republican nominee, but rather of Ralph Nader, whose Green Party bid is making enough headway in some states to stir anxieties among Democrats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Democrats were livid over a rival of Vice President Al Gore in the race for president. ''He's on an ego trip,'' said Senator Harry Reid, a Nevada Democrat. ''He has no respect for the process.''</p>
        <p>The senator was not speaking of  Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the presumptive Republican nominee, but rather of Ralph Nader, whose Green Party bid is making enough headway in some states to stir anxieties among Democrats.</p>
        <p>If the election remains as close as polls indicate, Mr. Nader, the longtime consumer advocate, could be a spoiler. ''The Bush people, I'm sure, are thrilled about Nader,'' said a Gore lieutenant.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nader's potential formidability was underscored on Thursday, when he appeared in Washington with James P. Hoffa, the Teamsters president, who told reporters that on trade issues critical to labor, ''there is no distinction between Al Gore and George W. Bush.''</p>
        <p>Potential obstacles cropped up elsewhere for Mr. Gore. The head of the Justice Department's campaign finance unit recommended that Attorney General Janet Reno appoint a special counsel to examine the vice president's fund-raising activities in 1996, when he attended a Buddhist Temple event that raised $65,000 in donations that were later deemed illegal. In what prosecutors characterized as a testy encounter, Mr. Gore was questioned about that and other activities in an interview on April 18. Mr. Gore's campaign released a transcript of the interview, hoping to blunt the issue's impact.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush had his own confrontation with the legal system, albeit one with a more mournful dimension. Despite emotional protests, a flurry of last-minute court challenges and a divided Texas parole board, the governor declined to stand in the way of the execution of Gary Graham, who had been convicted in a 1981 murder in Houston.</p>
        <p>''After considering all the facts, I'm confident that justice is being done,'' Mr. Bush said shortly before Mr. Graham was given a lethal injection. It was the 135th execution of Governor Bush's term in office.</p>
        <p>With a majority of Americans supporting capital punishment, the governor's supporters predicted negligible political fallout.</p>
        <p>PETER MARKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
