<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Falling In Love With Art's Orphans</title>
    <meta content="25HAYT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Guggenheim, Solomon R, Museum (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hayt, Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenblum, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEFD91331F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Falling In Love With Art's Orphans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH HAYT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hayt, Elizabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elizabeth Hayt reviews exhibit 1900: Art at the Crossroads, conceived and curated by Robert Rosenblum at New York City's Guggenheim museum; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR years, Robert Rosenblum, a curator and scholar who likes to find connections between the curiosities of art history, visited the Church of the Ascension at 10th Street and Fifth Avenue near his Greenwich Village home. There he stood pensively in front of a strange 1899 painting depicting a monk assisting crippled, naked boys on crutches at the ocean. The picture, originally titled ''Children of Pleasure'' and then renamed ''Sad Inheritance,'' was unusual for several reasons. Its subject was not a sacred one but rather a moralizing tale of children afflicted with syphilis, a portrayal of Christian charity, an example of both church propaganda and the way religious themes were secularized in the late 19th century. The daring depiction won Joaquin Sorolla y Bastida, a Spanish artist from Valencia, a gold medal at the Paris World's Fair in 1900.</p>
        <p>But one day in 1981, when Mr. Rosenblum went to the church, the picture was gone. It had been auctioned for $240,000 at Sotheby's and repatriated after being bought by a bank in Valencia. ''If you were teaching a 50-minute survey in the history of modern art, this picture couldn't be placed,'' Mr. Rosenblum said. ''There was no cage in the zoo.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR years, Robert Rosenblum, a curator and scholar who likes to find connections between the curiosities of art history, visited the Church of the Ascension at 10th Street and Fifth Avenue near his Greenwich Village home. There he stood pensively in front of a strange 1899 painting depicting a monk assisting crippled, naked boys on crutches at the ocean. The picture, originally titled ''Children of Pleasure'' and then renamed ''Sad Inheritance,'' was unusual for several reasons. Its subject was not a sacred one but rather a moralizing tale of children afflicted with syphilis, a portrayal of Christian charity, an example of both church propaganda and the way religious themes were secularized in the late 19th century. The daring depiction won Joaquin Sorolla y Bastida, a Spanish artist from Valencia, a gold medal at the Paris World's Fair in 1900.</p>
        <p>But one day in 1981, when Mr. Rosenblum went to the church, the picture was gone. It had been auctioned for $240,000 at Sotheby's and repatriated after being bought by a bank in Valencia. ''If you were teaching a 50-minute survey in the history of modern art, this picture couldn't be placed,'' Mr. Rosenblum said. ''There was no cage in the zoo.''</p>
        <p>But now there is: ''1900: Art at the Crossroads,'' an exhibition conceived and put together by Mr. Rosenblum, which is at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum through Sept. 10, is an enormous survey of artistic crosscurrents at the turn of the century. (Previously, it was at the Royal Academy in London, where two other curators helped Mr. Rosenblum organize the show.) Roughly a third of the works were first displayed at the Paris World's Fair of 1900, where there was an international exhibition at the Grand Palais that included Japanese, Australian and American artists. The fair not only provided Mr. Rosenblum with a historical anchor for his show, but it also had modern-day relevance.</p>
        <p>''In 1996, the Guggenheim asked me to do a show for the millennium,'' Mr. Rosenblum said. ''The 1900 World's Fair was about the future and progress. There were projections that people would fly. Electricity was the new thing. Artists from all over the Western world, as well as those in ethnic pavilions, were shown. I thought this was wonderfully in sync with what is happening in terms of global culture today.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosenblum's exhibition reflects his interest in what might be considered the orphans of art history. Although the show includes modern masters like Matisse, Picasso and Mondrian, as well as academic giants like Bouguereau and Gerome, many of the 240 works are as idiosyncratic and obscure as the Sorolla.</p>
        <p>''I have spent a good part of my life trying to expand the view of late 18th- and 19th-century art, making it more ecumenical,'' said Mr. Rosenblum, who is 72 and a professor of art history at New York University and its Institute of Fine Arts, as well as the author of 14 books. ''There were paintings that I loved looking at that didn't belong to any 'ism.' ''</p>
        <p>Strolling past these waifs and strays scavenged from collections worldwide -- including offbeat maritime and city museums -- Mr. Rosenblum spoke of the works with the intimacy and sense of humor of someone flipping through a family photo album. They were a source of memories, anecdotes and inside jokes. His narrative provided a personal subtext to the cross section of art history on display.</p>
        <p>For example, about 30 years ago, visiting the Musee Calvet in Avignon, France, he saw a painting by Maurice de Vlaminck of a barmaid with a cigarette boldly dangling from her lips. Vlaminck made the work in 1900 and inscribed it with ''19'' at the lower left, completing the date by creating a visual pun of the barmaid's breasts that can be read as large 00's.</p>
        <p>Taken with the image, Mr. Rosenblum bought a postcard of it. ''I thought the painting was so precocious for 1900,'' Mr. Rosenblum said. ''I never thought I would have any use for it. I forgot all about it, but then I had a deja vu when I became fixated on the year 1900 for the show. It has turned out to be one of the hits of the show. The barmaid just has so much chutzpah.''</p>
        <p>A turbulent 1901 seascape, ''White Mark IV,'' by the Swedish playwright August Strindberg, reflects Mr. Rosenblum's knowledge of esoteric Northern Romantic painters. In the early 90's, he was invited by the Institute of Modern Art in Valencia to give a lecture on Strindberg's paintings. Although he knew nothing about them, he found that Strindberg was captivated by the idea of nature's chaos and that his paintings are much prized in Sweden. Mr. Rosenblum wound up publishing a small book on the subject, becoming something of Strindberg scholar.</p>
        <p>Although many of the works stand outside the canon of art history, their quirkiness inspired him to include them in the show. Franz von Lenbach, a trashy though popular German portraitist at the turn of the century, painted Peggy Guggenheim when she was about 5 years old. Portrayed as cherub-faced, with her fair hair in ringlets and wearing a white Victorian dress adorned with satin ribbons, the girl bears no hint of her future as a great patroness of modern art. In fact, she looks more like a child beauty-pageant contestant.</p>
        <p>Establishing relationships between works of art that are distant cousins seems to be Mr. Rosenblum's forte. In the museum's High Gallery, where the walls and carpeting are oxblood red, a favorite color for interiors at the turn of the century, Mr. Rosenblum decided to hang the paintings Salon-style, recreating part of an installation at the World's Fair. Among the campy images is a ring of frolicking nymphets by the French academician Paul Chabas. Mr. Rosenblum identified its theme and its composition as prototypes for ''The Dance'' by Matisse, who, incidentally, worked at the fair painting decorative garlands around the exhibition halls. (Both Chabas and Matisse were students of Bouguereau.)</p>
        <p>ALSO in the High Gallery is a scene of a fisher family by a Japanese artist, Ichiro Yuasa, who trained in Paris. Bathed in rosy light, Yuasa's painting of a forlorn family, set against a spare seascape, was executed in a Western style in 1898. A few years later, Picasso -- another World's Fair artist -- began his monochrome Blue and Rose period paintings of social outcasts, which, Mr. Rosenblum pointed out, are hardly singular in light of Yuasa's pink-toned picture.</p>
        <p>''My job as a historian and curator is to make unexpected connections so that things you yawn at from familiarity look different,'' Mr. Rosenblum said. ''There are some connections that are so pervasive they tell you about the spirit of the time. If you connect all the dots, you realize the period loved monochrome, and in particular blue, because it suggested something melancholy and spiritual and ethereal against the industrial, urban world. It tells you something about the mystical aspirations of the period. It's like an archaeological excavation.''</p>
        <p>In addition to collapsing the national and stylistic divide between artists working at the same historical moment, Mr. Rosenblum also views the past through the lens of the present, drawing uncanny connections between the art of then and now.</p>
        <p>History flows laterally, rather than linearly, in Mr. Rosenblum's mind. For instance, Sorolla's image of naked handicapped boys reminded the curator of the disturbing, figural, if slightly perverse, pictures by the present-day painter Eric Fischl. And a bizarre triptych of 1890-99 by the Belgian symbolist Leon Frederic, depicting throngs of rosy-cheeked, naked babies, prompted an offhand remark from Mr. Rosenblum. ''It looks like hide-and-seek in terms of the Chapman brothers,'' he said with a chuckle, referring to the hot British artists, Dinos and Jake Chapman, who create fiberglass and resin sculptures of X-rated Siamese twins and mutant children.</p>
        <p>A scholar of Mr. Rosenblum's stature might be expected to adopt a high-minded approach to art. But his attitude is surprisingly playful, even irreverent. ''About 20 years ago, I was at the Milwaukee Art Museum and I saw this version of Salome,'' Mr. Rosenblum said of an 1898 painting of Salome with the head of St. John the Baptist by Wilhelm Trubner, a minor German artist. ''Usually, Salome is veiled and exotic and an evil temptress. But here's this wacky study of a naked girl who happens to be holding a platter with a decapitated head. She looks like she's from a nudist colony. As the staff and I were installing the show, we would refer to this painting as 'Where's the Picnic Table?' ''</p>
        <p>Notwithstanding his lightheartedness, Mr. Rosenblum described his life's work as an attempt to provide a fresh perspective on both the major and minor art once lost to the past. ''I have lived with most of these for a long time,'' he said, looking at the paintings spiraling up the ramp of the Guggenheim. ''They get older and different over the years. I always think of pictures leading a life as very complicated and dependent on other pictures and people and the time we're looking at them. When newcomers appear, they get connected to the family. In the future, they'll have a different connection to us. They're like human beings that way.''</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE Elizabeth Hayt studied art history with Robert Rosenblum at the Institute of Fine Arts at New York University in the 1990's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Elizabeth Hayt studied art history with Robert Rosenblum at the Institute of Fine Arts at New York University in the 1990's.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
