<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City Is Slow In Cleaning Polluted Sites, Green Says</title>
    <meta content="25BROW$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210398"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lueck, Thomas J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Mark (Public Advocate)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harding, Robert M (Deputy Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DC1530F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City Is Slow In Cleaning Polluted Sites, Green Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lueck, Thomas J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark Green, public advocate, criticizes Giuliani administration for failing to identify and clean up thousands of brownfields, polluted sites that do not contain toxic waste, squandering a chance to attract new business to New York City and create open space for public; Robert M Harding, deputy major for economic development, says city is working very aggressively to reclaim such sites for housing and commercial use (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mark Green, the city's public advocate, sharply criticized the Giuliani administration yesterday, saying it had failed to identify and clean up thousands of blighted and polluted sites in New York City, squandering a chance to attract new business and create open space for the public.</p>
        <p>Mr. Green's criticism focused on the efforts of the city, and to a lesser extent those of New York State, in cleaning up brownfields, polluted land that does not contain toxic waste. Such space has become a high priority for economic development in several parts of the nation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mark Green, the city's public advocate, sharply criticized the Giuliani administration yesterday, saying it had failed to identify and clean up thousands of blighted and polluted sites in New York City, squandering a chance to attract new business and create open space for the public.</p>
        <p>Mr. Green's criticism focused on the efforts of the city, and to a lesser extent those of New York State, in cleaning up brownfields, polluted land that does not contain toxic waste. Such space has become a high priority for economic development in several parts of the nation.</p>
        <p>At a news conference in front of an abandoned waterfront rail yard in the Sunset Park section of Brooklyn, Mr. Green said that the city, in the midst of a real estate crunch, was risking the loss of ''hundreds of millions of dollars in federal and state aid'' and private funds that might be available to reclaim such sites.</p>
        <p>The rail yard, which community groups want to convert into a recreation area, is one of 3,300 sites in the city that might be salvaged, he said. Most of the sites, Mr. Green said, were in Brooklyn, the Bronx and industrial areas outside Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Green's criticism yesterday came at a time when City Hall was intensifying efforts to lure companies and jobs to the boroughs outside Manhattan. On Friday, legislators in Albany approved a package of incentives proposed by the mayor and the City Council that included tax credits of $3,000 per employee for companies that move above 96th Street in Manhattan or to the other boroughs.</p>
        <p>Robert M. Harding, the deputy mayor for economic development, in response to Mr. Green's criticism yesterday, said, ''His timing is pretty galling.''</p>
        <p>''He is doing this less than 24 hours after we have pushed through probably the most significant package of economic revitalization ever for the other boroughs, and with a lot of hard work by the mayor,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Although the new incentives do not provide financing to clean up polluted land, he said, the city is working ''very aggressively'' to reclaim such sites for housing or commercial use.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Green said the city had failed even to identify which of its sites meet the criteria of low-level pollution necessary to be classified as brownfields.</p>
        <p>''While other cities have accessed hundreds of millions of dollars in federal, state and private brownfield redevelopment resources, New York City has obtained almost no government money, comparatively little private funding, and has had few major brownfield redevelopment projects,'' said a report issued yesterday by Mr. Green's staff.</p>
        <p>It pointed to extensive efforts by other cities and states to develop brownfield sites, including those in New Jersey, where the new Performing Arts Center in downtown Newark and the IKEA super store in Elizabeth have been built over reclaimed brownfield sites.</p>
        <p>The report said the city and state had reached agreement with a relatively small number of private companies to analyze and reclaim brownfields through voluntary cleanup programs, which involve government subsidies.</p>
        <p>Since New York State began offering voluntary cleanup programs in 1994, the report said, 134 agreements have been signed and 200 reclamation projects begun across the state. Pennsylvania, it said, has used them to clean up more than 600 sites.</p>
        <p>The report said 22 voluntary agreements had been signed for polluted sites in the city, and only four of those cleaned up.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
