<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investing; For Battered Insurers, A Timely Turnabout</title>
    <meta content="25INSU$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Treaster, Joseph B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFDE1730F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investing; For Battered Insurers, A Timely Turnabout</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH B. TREASTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Treaster, Joseph B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shares of property-casualty insurers, which took beating in first two and a half months of year when technology stocks were soaring, have rebounded following tech stock sell-off that began in mid-March; insurance stocks have been among most oversold stocks and many still look cheap when compared with their peaks of a year or so ago; photo, graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHILE technology stocks have been careening wildly, some ugly ducklings in the insurance industry appear to be transforming themselves into market darlings.</p>
        <p>The companies that sell insurance on cars, houses and businesses, a decidedly unglamorous business, had been sputtering under the strain of poor earnings, in large part a result of natural disasters like Hurricane Floyd, and of rising interest rates since the middle of last year. And their stocks took a real beating in the first two and a half months of 2000 as technology stocks were rising sharply. But when technology shares began selling off in mid-March, the insurers rebounded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHILE technology stocks have been careening wildly, some ugly ducklings in the insurance industry appear to be transforming themselves into market darlings.</p>
        <p>The companies that sell insurance on cars, houses and businesses, a decidedly unglamorous business, had been sputtering under the strain of poor earnings, in large part a result of natural disasters like Hurricane Floyd, and of rising interest rates since the middle of last year. And their stocks took a real beating in the first two and a half months of 2000 as technology stocks were rising sharply. But when technology shares began selling off in mid-March, the insurers rebounded.</p>
        <p>There is little doubt that the insurance stocks had been oversold by many measures. Indeed, many still look relatively cheap when compared with their peaks of a year or so ago. In addition, signs of a slowing economy suggest that interest rates may begin to level off, good news for the group because higher rates can translate into smaller profits. Even more important, insurers are beginning to nudge up prices, which also bodes well for profits.</p>
        <p>''The property-casualty insurers had been among the most disfavored stocks on Wall Street,'' said Robert P. Hartwig, the chief economist at the Insurance Information Institute, an industry group in New York, adding that some had dropped below book value. ''But since the dot-com shipwreck, people have been looking to put their money in companies that are actually making a profit. And the insurance stocks have been among the greatest values on Wall Street.''</p>
        <p>As of Friday, the technology-heavy Nasdaq index was down 5.5 percent for the year, and the Standard &amp; Poor's property-casualty stock index was basically flat. Since March 10, the insurance index has gained 38.3  percent while the Nasdaq, despite its rally since May 23, is off 23.8 percent.</p>
        <p>In general, rising interest rates dampen insurance stock prices along with those of other financial services companies. So the Federal Reserve's short-term interest rate increases, which began in the middle of last year, have naturally been a drag on the group's performance. But with insurance stocks well above their March lows, investors seem to be saying that the economy is beginning to slow down -- and that the Fed may be nearly done raising rates.</p>
        <p>Financial stocks of many types have been picking up. But Alice Schroeder, an analyst at PaineWebber, says property-casualty stocks stand out because they are less sensitive to economic developments -- many people have to buy insurance whether or not prices are rising -- and ''the fundamentals of these companies are actually improving.''</p>
        <p>Auto insurers are a case in point. Shares of the Progressive Corporation closed on Friday at $77.875, up 58.1 percent from their 2000 lows on March 13, while those of the Hartford Financial Services Group closed at $53.3125, up 81.5 percent from their low on the same day.</p>
        <p>Ace, the international insurer based in Bermuda, has risen 83 percent from its March nadir, to $26.875.  The St. Paul Companies, a big commercial insurance group, is up 60.9 percent from its low on March 8, to $35, and Allstate, a leader in auto and homeowner coverage, is up 34.5 percent, to $23.875.</p>
        <p>Despite the run-up, the property-casualty stocks may have room to move higher. At the beginning of last year, for example, Progressive traded at more than twice its current price. And other stocks are well below their 1999 highs too.</p>
        <p>''It may not be the first inning of this game,'' said Doug Cliggott, the United States equities strategist for J. P. Morgan Securities. ''But I don't think it's beyond the third inning. It's still a very attractive point to get in.''</p>
        <p>Some fund managers agree. ''I think there's a long ways to go, a lot of upside, plenty of potential in these stock prices,'' said Jeff Morris, who manages the $1.3 billion Invesco Financial Services fund. Noting that the stocks have moved away from their recent highs, he added that he ''wouldn't read too much into it.''</p>
        <p>Others sounded more cautious. Ms. Schroeder says some prices of a year or two ago were historical highs that may be difficult to overtake anytime soon.</p>
        <p>Although many of the stocks may have topped out, she said, there is still money to be made on Ace; XL Ltd., another big Bermuda insurer; two of her favorites, AIG and Berkshire Hathaway; and the two biggest commercial brokers, Marsh &amp; McLennan and Aon.</p>
        <p>AFTER declining for nearly a decade, prices for commercial insurance, which offers protection to corporations for most everything from shareholder suits to plant explosions, are starting to show signs of increasing. Some of the biggest auto insurers, including Progressive and Geico, the Berkshire Hathaway unit, have also begun raising their prices after two years of declines across the industry.</p>
        <p>''You can make a pretty good case that the insurance cycle is turning in a more positive direction,'' Mr. Cliggott said.</p>
        <p>New markets are opening, too, Mr. Hartwig said, citing China and India and a whole field of coverage devoted to cyberspace problems. A handful of big insurers are entering that field with policies covering loss of data and damage from viruses.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
