<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>France Issues Tough Report On Monaco And Its Money</title>
    <meta content="Y25FRA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210251"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Money Laundering</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Monaco</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daley, Suzanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Monaco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Monaco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E2DE1730F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>France Issues Tough Report On Monaco And Its Money</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE DALEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Daley, Suzanne</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>French Parliament issues scathing 400-page report, accusing Monaco of deliberately putting in place lax banking laws to attract wealthy depositors no matter who they are; says monetary surveillance systems are so poor that even if Monaco officials want to cooperate in international efforts to prevent money laundering, they could not; report recommends that France review its accords with Monaco; says France, which supervises Monaco's lending agenices, could lose its own credibility in fight against money laundering (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The writer W. Somerset Maugham once described Monaco as ''a sunny spot for shady people.'' This week, the French Parliament offered a few more details.</p>
        <p>In a scathing 400-page report, the Parliament said that the tiny principality -- a famous refuge for wealthy tax dodgers -- was also an ideal place to launder money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The writer W. Somerset Maugham once described Monaco as ''a sunny spot for shady people.'' This week, the French Parliament offered a few more details.</p>
        <p>In a scathing 400-page report, the Parliament said that the tiny principality -- a famous refuge for wealthy tax dodgers -- was also an ideal place to launder money.</p>
        <p>It accused Monaco of having deliberately put in place lax banking laws -- including a guarantee of anonymity -- to attract wealthy depositors no matter who they were. And it said that the monetary surveillance systems were so poor that even if Monaco officials wanted to cooperate in international efforts to prevent money laundering, they could not.</p>
        <p>''Monaco is one of the most hypocritical territories when it comes to the fight against money laundering,'' said Arnaud Montebourg, one of the Socialist members of Parliament who helped to write the report. ''A loose system is not just tolerated there, it was created on purpose.''</p>
        <p>Even control systems that were in place are not functioning properly, the report said. One French auditor described inspecting more than 260 files that should have contained information about the identity of depositors. He found that a quarter of them were completely empty.</p>
        <p>The parliamentary report recommended that France review its accords with Monaco, some of which date back hundreds of years. Unless changes are made, the report said, France -- which provides Monaco with top civil servants and supervises its lending agencies -- is in danger of losing its own credibility in the fight against money laundering.</p>
        <p>The report also questioned why France should continue to contribute to the upkeep of the Mediterranean resort, especially when the principality's main goal ''appeared to be to let some of the wealthiest citizens in the world get away without paying taxes.'' At the moment, France shares its sales tax proceeds with Monaco, under a formula that most experts say favors Monaco.</p>
        <p>Money laundering and banking practices have been a hot topic in Europe lately. France's report on Monaco came only a day after members of the European Union finally reached an agreement in principle on sweeping changes to bank secrecy laws, intended to bring cross-border investment income within the net of tax authorities.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement, all 15 European Union states will exchange information on nonresident's savings. This is intended to prevent tax evasion by people who place their investments in secret accounts in another European Union member country, or elsewhere abroad.</p>
        <p>The plan, however, still faces some big hurdles. It is dependent on the cooperation of the United States, Switzerland and such tax havens as Monaco and Liechtenstein, another principality that has lately come under heavy scrutiny by an official from neighboring Austria who claims to have found evidence of money laundering. Austria itself has drawn the ire of fellow European Union members for insisting on maintaining a high degree of banking secrecy.</p>
        <p>Liechtenstein was among the top 15 countries named by a high-level international task force this week as failing to cooperate with the fight against the concealment of illegally earned funds. Other countries on the list included Russia and Israel.</p>
        <p>Monaco had also been rumored to be on the blacklist, drawn up by the 26-nation Finance Action Task Force on money laundering. But instead it was placed on the second tier ''gray'' list.</p>
        <p>The French Parliament report found that much of Monaco's surveillance system was woefully understaffed. The report also pointed out only 37 ''declarations of suspicion'' on potentially illegal transactions were filed in 1998, far less than in any other European tax haven, and despite more than $44 billion on deposit.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the report said,  Monaco had 10 times as many bank accounts as residents and about 60 percent of the 340,000 accounts belonged to nonresidents. Only about 30,000 people live in Monaco, which occupies a choice piece of Mediterranean seaside property not quite as big as Central Park.</p>
        <p>Monaco remained silent on the report. It issued a statement saying only that in time ''it would communicate the observations and comments that it believed were necessary.''</p>
        <p>The principality has a complicated relationship with France, which provides many of its top functionaries and magistrates. Monaco also uses French francs.</p>
        <p>The French report said that Monaco risks destabilizing markets through a lack of surveillance of its banking and financial sectors, and could hardly succeed in joining the Euro zone unless it mended its ways.</p>
        <p>''Monaco must choose,'' the report said. ''It is up to it to head for change.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
