<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOLLOWING UP</title>
    <meta content="25FOLL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210329"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Following Up</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E5D81430F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOLLOWING UP</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jilted Hospital Suing Doctor on the Move</p>
        <p>The case of Dr. Andrew Wiznia, a pediatric AIDS specialist formerly with Bronx-Lebanon Hospital Center, now with Jacobi Medical Center, is proceeding through the state courts. At issue: how a doctor should notify patients when changing hospitals, and whether the hospital left behind can claim damages for lost grant money and patients.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wiznia, who had worked in a Bronx-Lebanon clinic treating 180 children with H.I.V. and 250 healthy children born to H.I.V.-infected parents, moved to Jacobi in April 1999, though Bronx-Lebanon had tried unsuccessfully to keep him from seeing patients at Jacobi for six months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jilted Hospital Suing Doctor on the Move</p>
        <p>The case of Dr. Andrew Wiznia, a pediatric AIDS specialist formerly with Bronx-Lebanon Hospital Center, now with Jacobi Medical Center, is proceeding through the state courts. At issue: how a doctor should notify patients when changing hospitals, and whether the hospital left behind can claim damages for lost grant money and patients.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wiznia, who had worked in a Bronx-Lebanon clinic treating 180 children with H.I.V. and 250 healthy children born to H.I.V.-infected parents, moved to Jacobi in April 1999, though Bronx-Lebanon had tried unsuccessfully to keep him from seeing patients at Jacobi for six months.</p>
        <p>Bronx-Lebanon also said Dr. Wiznia used its records illegally in writing his patients of the move, and left them little choice but to go with him. Dr. Wiznia said he had followed standard procedure in notifying the patients, using his own records to get their addresses. The court ruled against him in December, but he is appealing.</p>
        <p>Bronx-Lebanon also charged that he had applied to transfer a federal grant supporting the unit from Bronx-Lebanon, a private hospital, to Jacobi, a public one, while still on Bronx-Lebanon's payroll.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wiznia acknowledged that he applied for the grant for Jacobi before he told Bronx-Lebanon he would be leaving, but he said Bronx-Lebanon's permission was required before the grant could be moved.</p>
        <p>Francis Carling, the lawyer for Bronx-Lebanon, countered that Dr. Wiznia left it no time to apply for grants on its own. The hospital said that because it permanently lost grants and patients, it is also suing him and his partners for damages. Dr. Wiznia said that no damages were incurred because a hospital cannot profit from research grants or Medicaid patients.</p>
        <p>Shifting Battleground For Small Harlem Stores</p>
        <p>When a white-owned clothing store in Harlem refused to renew the sublease of a popular black-owned record store in 1995, Morris Powell was at the forefront of protests as head of the 125th Street Vendors Association. The battle ended tragically. As the angry demonstrations dragged on, a man walked into the store, Freddy's clothing, began shooting and set a fire that killed seven workers and himself.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Powell's concerns echo his protests five years ago but reflect a changing Harlem. With a group called the Diallo Coalition, named for the unarmed black man killed by the police, Mr. Powell has distributed leaflets outside Harlem USA, the new mall on 125th Street that includes Disney, Old Navy and HMV.</p>
        <p>He and others are concerned by the city's recent attempts to evict Mart 125, where dozens of small businesses operate  on city-owned property. There is fear that the national chains, and the rent increases that come with them, will keep smaller vendors from enjoying the economic boom that is reaching 125th Street.</p>
        <p>''We still have them under boycott,'' Mr. Powell said of Harlem USA. ''Our community is overwhelmingly run by other people, of not the same race, and it's unfair, to say the least.''</p>
        <p>Bill Perkins, the councilman for central and east Harlem, said he disagreed with the city's desire to lease the property to the highest bidder.</p>
        <p>Mart 125 is fighting the eviction in court, he said.</p>
        <p>''Why can't Harlemites, small entrepreneurs who were here during the lean times, take advantage of the better times?'' Mr. Perkins asked. ''The so-called gentrification or whatever that people to some extent welcome can be a double-edged sword, reflected in the struggle that merchants at Mart 125 are having.''</p>
        <p>TINA KELLEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
