<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reshaping of Nets Moves Into High Gear</title>
    <meta content="25NBAA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210354"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E1DE1530F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1448" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reshaping of Nets Moves Into High Gear</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From picking No. 1 to finding a coach, Rod Thorn begins reshaping the Nets in earnest this week. Though the National Basketball Association draft on Wednesday remains a priority, the job of finding a successor to Don Casey is apparently almost done.</p>
        <p>Byron Scott, a Sacramento Kings assistant, has been interviewed by Thorn and appears to be the Nets' top choice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From picking No. 1 to finding a coach, Rod Thorn begins reshaping the Nets in earnest this week. Though the National Basketball Association draft on Wednesday remains a priority, the job of finding a successor to Don Casey is apparently almost done.</p>
        <p>Byron Scott, a Sacramento Kings assistant, has been interviewed by Thorn and appears to be the Nets' top choice.</p>
        <p>Scott is highly respected by Nets upper management, who view him much in the mold of Orlando Coach Doc Rivers: an even-keel person with a solid playing career and the respect of his peers.</p>
        <p>Scott's coming to the Meadowlands is not guaranteed. Scott, Magic Johnson's backcourt mate in the showtime years, is still in the running for the Indiana job. But with Isiah Thomas and Rick Carlisle waging campaigns to take over the Pacers, Scott may decide to leave the Kings for the Nets before taking over for the retired Larry Bird.</p>
        <p>Thorn has been tight-lipped about the candidates and does not expect to make a decision until next week. And the Nets could easily go another direction, depending on circumstances.</p>
        <p>Two of the other four candidates are Eddie Jordan, the respected assistant on Casey's staff whom Stephon Marbury has endorsed, and Tubby Smith, the University of Kentucky coach. Bob Huggins of the University of Cincinnati and Mike Fratello have also been mentioned in connection with the job.</p>
        <p>Mike Krzyzewski, the Duke University coach, was contacted by the Nets but told them he was not interested in leaving the college ranks.</p>
        <p>Thorn has other decisions to make. Kenyon Martin, the Cincinnati forward considered the top pick until he broke his right leg in the Conference USA tournament, finished his two-day visit with the Nets on Friday. Because of the injury, Martin did not work out. But he was examined closely by team doctors, and their evaluation did not deter the Nets from taking him with the first pick.</p>
        <p>Draft Possibilities</p>
        <p>With Orlando and Chicago controlling the draft -- they hold 5 of the top 13 picks and 6 of the first 24 -- the Nets are still thinking about trading the No. 1 pick. But if they don't and decide to select Cincinnati's Kenyon Martin, the rest of Wednesday's first round will probably go like this:</p>
        <p>*Vancouver likes Stromile Swift, the 6-foot-9-inch Louisiana State forward who is the second-leading shot blocker in school history, behind Shaquille O'Neal.</p>
        <p>*The Clippers, who pick third, will most likely take Iowa State's Marcus Fizer, who can score from anywhere and who should blend in well with Lamar Odom.</p>
        <p>*The Bulls, at No. 4, are contemplating trading some of their multiple first-round picks. Jerry Krause is in need of more veterans than youngsters. But they probably will not pass on Darius Miles, this year's prep phenom from East St. Louis, Ill.</p>
        <p>*That leaves Orlando at No. 5. Depending on what it does with its three first-round selections, the Magic will most likely choose between Texas center Chris Mihm or Florida's Mike Miller. If Orlando takes Mihm, then the Atlanta Hawks will take Miller.</p>
        <p>Given the lack of an impact player, finding a sleeper late in the first round is not impossible for a team like the Knicks, who pick 22nd.</p>
        <p>But as more franchises build through free agency and as the continued proliferation of early-entry candidates dilutes the talent pool, the draft continues to lose its luster.</p>
        <p>Hofstra's Speedy Claxton may be among the first point guards taken. He impressed scouts at the draft camps and worked out with the Knicks on Friday.</p>
        <p>It will be interesting to see where Ohio State's Scoonie Penn is selected. Penn, a fifth-year senior who majored in sociology, elected not to participate in the Chicago draft camp because he had to take finals the same week. Penn was determined to get his degree and passed up one of the main yardsticks for draft consideration.</p>
        <p>He reportedly also grew disenchanted with the performances of some of his peers at the Phoenix draft camp, where his stock fell. A 5-foot-11-inch point guard, Penn was moving the ball, setting screens and playing help defense, and he apparently did not fit in with the look-at-me crowd.</p>
        <p>But, really, who would want a guy who stayed in school and played team ball? In this N.B.A.?</p>
        <p>The Pacers' Choice</p>
        <p>Donnie Walsh, the Indiana Pacers' president, met for three hours Wednesday night with Rick Carlisle, a Pacers assistant, to assure him that Walsh had not yet made Isiah Thomas an offer to become the team's next coach.</p>
        <p>Carlisle assured Walsh that he still wanted the job and would go on the offensive to make sure he received the proper consideration.</p>
        <p>That apparently meant having players over to his house and telling them of his desire to work with them toward winning a title, according to an Eastern Conference coach.</p>
        <p>''With all the lobbying on both sides, it's getting ugly out there,'' the coach said, speaking on condition of anonymity. ''Isiah thinks he has the job, Rick can't believe he's not being more strongly considered and Donnie is really in a quandary, wondering what to do.''</p>
        <p>Walsh has also met with players, and from their feedback it does not appear the Pacers are leaning either way. It may come down to a gut decision by Walsh.</p>
        <p>One Eastern Conference executive said Walsh had been receiving a lot of anti-Isiah calls from N.B.A. officials who do not want Thomas to get the job. But Walsh received the same kind of feedback from Boston when Bird was up for the job and hired him anyway.</p>
        <p>Around the League</p>
        <p>Grant Hill's days in Detroit are not over but may come to an end soon. Hill, a free agent, has intimated to close friends and family that he will most likely play in another city next season, a person close to Hill said on condition of anonymity. Barring an unlikely trade to New York, Hill is considering Chicago and Orlando; both have salary-cap room to accommodate Hill. Hill is also seriously weighing playing in San Antonio if Tim Duncan stays. Hill would sign for the midlevel exception, and the Spurs would have to clear room under the salary cap the next season to sign him to an extension.</p>
        <p>Free agents can begin negotiating with teams on July 1 but cannot sign deals until Aug. 1. Some people are skeptical about how much weight those dates actually carry. One Atlantic Division official, for example, called the period a smoke screen. ''Tim Duncan knows what he's going to do, Grant Hill knows what he wants to do, and Tracy McGrady knows what he wants to do,'' the official said. McGrady, the Toronto forward, is still leaning toward the Magic or the Bulls unless the Raptors pull off a sign-and-trade with another team.</p>
        <p>After all the TV studio candidates shamelessly threw their own names around, the Knicks assistants Don Chaney and Brendan Malone have finally been receiving interest for vacant jobs. Chaney recently turned down the lead assistant position with Atlanta. Malone was contacted by Washington to be the Wizards' top assistant under Leonard Hamilton, but he chose not to pursue the job.</p>
        <p>A note on the Lakers' first title in 12 years: when Magic Johnson was directing traffic in the 1980's, there was an aura about the town and the team that could be felt when the old Forum was buzzing, as if all the problems outside the arena did not exist. Since 1988, Los Angeles has been beset with difficult times. Whether it was Johnson telling the world he had contracted H.I.V. in 1991, the fallout from Rodney King's arrest and the O. J. Simpson trial, or the devastating fires and an earthquake, the city was pelted the last decade with some kind of strife or tragedy. Since 1988, not a single pro sports team had won a title or captured the imagination of the city like the Lakers of Shaq and Kobe. A group of rioters on Monday night helped stall the healing process, but at least it's beginning. ''I'm not from L.A.,'' said Rick Fox, a Lakers forward, ''but in watching a lot of times the turmoil the city has gone through, the different riots and chaos, this would be a positive way to celebrate. And you hope in that celebration everyone stays healthy and safe. It would be something jubilant to pull the city together.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
