<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World; In Iran's Morality Play, The Moral May Be Unity</title>
    <meta content="25SCIO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210274"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sciolino, Elaine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khatami, Mohammad (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khamenei, Ali (Ayatollah)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2D61730F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World; In Iran's Morality Play, The Moral May Be Unity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sciolino, Elaine</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Symbiotic relationship between K1, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, leader of Iran's theocratic conservatives, and K2, Mohammad Khatami, Iran's reformist president, reflects political system in which people who deeply disagree and compete for power also cooperate to make whole system work; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S been years since the Clinton administration called Iran an ''international outlaw,'' and now it has decided to stop calling it a ''rogue state.'' People inside and outside the administration were saying last week that dropping such labels could open the way for Americans to think more realistically about such countries. But these labels aren't the only problem with the way the administration has been thinking about Iran.</p>
        <p>There's also the matter of K1 and K2.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S been years since the Clinton administration called Iran an ''international outlaw,'' and now it has decided to stop calling it a ''rogue state.'' People inside and outside the administration were saying last week that dropping such labels could open the way for Americans to think more realistically about such countries. But these labels aren't the only problem with the way the administration has been thinking about Iran.</p>
        <p>There's also the matter of K1 and K2.</p>
        <p>Those are the labels applied in some quarters of the American government to the two leading figures in Iran, who are often portrayed as the bad guy and the good guy in a winner-take-all morality play.</p>
        <p>K1 is Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, the dour spiritual leader and most powerful person in the country. He  ritualistically rails against Israel, rapprochement with the United States and the cultural invasion of the West. He has the support of Iran's theocratic conservatives.</p>
        <p>K2 is Mohammad Khatami, a smiling, charming president who won election in a landslide three years  ago, supported by the younger generation and women, and has called for a ''dialogue among civilizations,'' even with the United States. He continues to enjoy remarkable popular support despite his difficulty in implementing promises to create a civil society governed by the rule of law.</p>
        <p>Indeed, there are stark differences between the two men -- so stark that Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright told a Congressional committee last February, ''In some ways it looks as though there are kind of two parallel governments that are going on.''</p>
        <p>But that may miss the most intriguing point about Iranian politics: It is anything but a zero-sum game.</p>
        <p>There is, instead, a remarkable degree of overlapping authority, producing a system where people who deeply disagree and compete fiercely for power also cooperate frequently to make the whole system work.</p>
        <p>And what has emerged between K1 and K2 is an arrangement of sorts; if this were France instead of an Islamic republic, it could be called cohabitation.</p>
        <p>Despite their different roles under the constitution, different styles and different constituencies, these two  men are both clerics, and only a few years apart. Both are men of ideas who claim descent from Mohammed. And both are sworn to preserve the Islamic republic.</p>
        <p>Most surprising to anyone with a one-dimensional view of Iran, there is a lot of evidence that the two leaders know they need each other if Iran's fluid political system is to function. Ayatollah Khamenei has power on paper; President Khatami has the support of the people. They don't openly attack each other. And they seem to work well together, even having hugged each other in public.</p>
        <p>Their peculiarly symbiotic relationship has been on display repeatedly. After President Khatami announced in 1998 that he wanted to break down ''the wall of mistrust'' with the United States through cultural exchanges, Ayatollah Khamenei disagreed. But while he branded the United States ''the enemy of the Iranian nation,'' he referred to Mr. Khatami as the ''respected president'' and dismissed their differences as ''a tone of speech and difference of taste.''</p>
        <p>Then, after nationwide student demonstrations last summer deteriorated into the worst unrest since Iran's 1979 revolution, both men made it clear that their own differences were not part of that struggle. Ayatollah Khamenei announced, ''I support the respected president and the job he is doing 100 percent.'' And President Khatami never challenged the extraordinary powers of the spiritual leader, however incompatible they may be with his vision of a more democratic Iran.</p>
        <p>The president's loyalty was returned in kind four months ago, after reformers swept the elections for Iran's Parliament and conservatives who had been defeated tried to get the results in Tehran annulled.  Ayatollah Khamenei declared the election results valid and stopped a recount, paving the way for the reformist-dominated Parliament to be seated last month.</p>
        <p>IN a way, the cooperation is not surprising, considering how big a stake both men have in preserving civil order and how passionate many Iranians have become about their politics. Student leaders had  threatened to mobilize massive street demonstrations if the election results were annulled. In the last such demonstrations, a year ago, two dozen leaders of the Revolutionary Guards raised the specter of a military coup.</p>
        <p>Order is not the only tie that binds K1 and K2. The Khamenei and Khatami families have been close, a relationship that was forged when Ayatollah Khamenei, as a teenage theology student in Mashad, became a devoted disciple of Mr. Khatami's father, a beloved ayatollah.</p>
        <p>Ayatollah Khamenei has also discovered that the charm offensive of President Khatami has paid off and is struggling to change his own image. He has taken to holding small seminars with young people, women, actors and athletes. He sometimes appears on television strolling in flower-filled gardens, as soft music plays in the background, even though he once issued a ruling banning music lessons as immoral.</p>
        <p>But showing off his soft side does not mean that Ayatollah Khamenei has transformed himself into an Islamic democrat. His blunt speech in April charging that some reformist newspapers had become ''bases of the enemy'' resulted in the shutdown of 18 reformist publications. The battle was joined when one of the first acts of the new Parliament was a call for an urgent review of the country's tough press law and the reopening of the banned publications.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration is eager to see how far it can push rapprochement with Iran in this open-ended political game before President Clinton leaves office, even though Iran has not formally responded to its offer of an official dialogue.</p>
        <p>Most recently, administration officials said, they were hoping that a third country would invite Iran to a three-day Community of Democracies Conference that opens today in Warsaw. After all, countries that the administration considers less democratic in some ways than Iran -- Kuwait, Egypt, Qatar and Jordan, for example -- are expected to attend.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
