<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Alexandra Siegel, Michael Shuman</title>
    <meta content="25VOWS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210102"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS: VOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIEGEL, ALEXANDRA (ALEXANDRA SHUMAN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHUMAN, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siegel, Alexandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shuman, Michael Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/Vows</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EFD71E31F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Alexandra Siegel, Michael Shuman</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alexandra Siegel, def</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALMOST everyone describes Alexandra Siegel, the design director for the Michael Kors collection in New York, as a sensitive, detail-oriented person, someone who notices shadows and interesting leaves when walking in the woods and who sometimes spends days in the office concentrating on a design as if it were a difficult algebraic problem. ''Alex will stay up three or four nights in a row just to get a stitch right,'' Margaret Anne Baum, a friend, said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Siegel, 31, is also practically impossible to reach by phone. At work, her voice mail always seems to answer. At home, she doesn't have an answering machine. For a while, she didn't even have a telephone in her SoHo apartment, which is shaped like a bowling alley and filled with books and birds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALMOST everyone describes Alexandra Siegel, the design director for the Michael Kors collection in New York, as a sensitive, detail-oriented person, someone who notices shadows and interesting leaves when walking in the woods and who sometimes spends days in the office concentrating on a design as if it were a difficult algebraic problem. ''Alex will stay up three or four nights in a row just to get a stitch right,'' Margaret Anne Baum, a friend, said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Siegel, 31, is also practically impossible to reach by phone. At work, her voice mail always seems to answer. At home, she doesn't have an answering machine. For a while, she didn't even have a telephone in her SoHo apartment, which is shaped like a bowling alley and filled with books and birds.</p>
        <p>She is the daughter of Robert Siegel, a principal in Gwathmey &amp; Siegel Associates, the New York architecture firm, and Hazel Siegel, the president of Textus, a textile company in New York. The Siegels live on a horse farm named Meadowbrook in Bedford, N.Y., in a house filled with modern furniture as long and low as the stone walls that line local roads.</p>
        <p>Three and a half years ago at a dinner, mutual friends introduced her to Michael Adam Shuman, now 28 and a graduate student in architecture at Columbia University. Like her, he is sensitive and curious, the sort of person who turns conversations with phone operators into heart-to-heart talks.</p>
        <p>The night the couple met, they parted ways after dinner, then talked later that night by phone about everything from their shared fantasy of becoming National Geographic photographers to the importance of community service. ''It was a really beautiful, deep, stimulating conversation and before you knew it, the sun was coming up,'' Mr. Shuman said. ''It was surreal. I felt like I had met a really intriguing, mystical character out of some novel.''</p>
        <p>They soon started dating, but saw each other irregularly, as both became engulfed in their projects. ''He let me be so independent,'' she said. ''There were times I'd disappear at work for days. Then, I'd get a voice mail from him saying, 'Wherever you are, I hope you're having a beautiful time.' ''</p>
        <p>And he liked her birds. ''Michael teaches the birds to say new things,'' she said. ''One time, I came home and my African gray parrot said, 'You're so beautiful and so wise.' ''</p>
        <p>Early on, they began reading ''Don Quixote'' together and made a pact to continue dating until they had finished. As they fell more in love, they read slower and slower. They are now on page 17.</p>
        <p>He proposed last summer on the island of Majorca, while inside an old, hollowed-out olive tree overlooking the Mediterranean. ''We have photos of the tree,'' Mr. Shuman said. ''We have watercolors of it, we have rubbings from it. We have the tree fully documented.''</p>
        <p>He presented her with a temporary engagement ring. ''I gave her this piece of carob that coiled around her finger,'' Mr. Shuman said. ''And of course, being the fashion designer she is, I made her a bracelet so she had a complete carob set.''</p>
        <p>Last Sunday, they were married in a horse paddock at Meadowbrook. The bridegroom walked across the grass with his father, Stanley S. Shuman, a managing director at the investment bank Allen &amp; Company, and mother, Ruth Lande Shuman, founder of Publicolor, a nonprofit organization that repaints the interiors of public schools.</p>
        <p>The bride arrived standing in a golf cart. ''She looked like the pope -- in white, greeting the crowd, with the hand up,'' Nina Liebman, a guest, said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Siegel designed her wedding outfit: a long linen skirt embroidered with an olive branch design (inspired by the tree in Majorca), heirloom lace veil and a cashmere tank top based on the Hanes men's undershirts she wears in the office every day.</p>
        <p>Although she had recently returned from Italy, she didn't appear jet-lagged.</p>
        <p>''She's the ultimate modern bride,'' said Michael Kors, who attended the event. ''She's feminine and romantic, but she is also able to go on a business trip to Europe a week before her wedding.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS: VOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
