<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cutting the Bach Choir Down to Size</title>
    <meta content="25GRIF$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bach, Johann Sebastian (1685-1750)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parrott, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rifkin, Joshua</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Griffiths, Paul</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Essential Bach Choir, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE5D91331F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cutting the Bach Choir Down to Size</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL GRIFFITHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Griffiths, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on research by English conductor Andrew Parrott, including book The Essential Bach Choir, that backs up Joshua Rifkin's 1981 theory that what Bach's choral movements were performed by choruses consisting of four soloists; engraving; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON this 250th anniversary of the death of Bach or in any other year, there can be few musicological questions more pressing than that of how the composer's music sounded when it was being performed for the first time, week after week, under his direction in St. Thomas's Church in Leipzig, Germany. Light is now being shed on this subject by one of the leading practitioners of early music, the English conductor Andrew Parrott, in performances, recordings and a book, ''The Essential Bach Choir'' (University of Rochester Press).</p>
        <p>Mr. Parrott takes up the story from the American scholar Joshua Rifkin, who, nearly 20 years ago, caused a stir in the world of early music by suggesting that Bach's B minor Mass, ''St. Matthew Passion'' and cantatas were not the choral masterpieces everybody had always taken them to be. They were still masterpieces, for sure. What Mr. Rifkin was doubting was that they were intended to be choral music as listeners then knew it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON this 250th anniversary of the death of Bach or in any other year, there can be few musicological questions more pressing than that of how the composer's music sounded when it was being performed for the first time, week after week, under his direction in St. Thomas's Church in Leipzig, Germany. Light is now being shed on this subject by one of the leading practitioners of early music, the English conductor Andrew Parrott, in performances, recordings and a book, ''The Essential Bach Choir'' (University of Rochester Press).</p>
        <p>Mr. Parrott takes up the story from the American scholar Joshua Rifkin, who, nearly 20 years ago, caused a stir in the world of early music by suggesting that Bach's B minor Mass, ''St. Matthew Passion'' and cantatas were not the choral masterpieces everybody had always taken them to be. They were still masterpieces, for sure. What Mr. Rifkin was doubting was that they were intended to be choral music as listeners then knew it.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Rifkin's view, what Bach meant by ''chorus'' was not a throng of enthusiastic singers but rather a set of soloists. Since Bach's choral movements generally have four vocal parts -- soprano, alto, tenor and bass -- just four singers would be required to perform them. In works that have two choirs, the number would be eight.</p>
        <p>This notion that the ''St. Matthew Passion,'' for instance, might be sung by just eight singers was revolutionary when Mr. Rifkin broached it at a conference in Boston in 1981, and the controversy has rumbled on. Mr. Parrott, in his book, is out to end it. He includes Mr. Rifkin's paper -- which, astonishingly, has never been published complete before -- and adds the evidence of his own exhaustive research to present a strong and fascinating case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Parrott's argument rests principally on the primary evidence: the performance materials surviving from Bach's musical household, produced by the composer's numerous offspring and equally numerous apprentices. These young people had to copy, from Bach's score, the parts that the instrumentalists and singers would need to read as they played and sang. And it turns out that in virtually every case, only one part exists for each line in a choir.</p>
        <p>If one wants to imagine that more than four singers were involved -- or eight in works for double choir -- then one has to see these singers as clustered together, perhaps three of them reading from one part. This setup is unlikely, according to Mr. Parrott, because the parts that Bach's children and assistants wrote out do not consistently indicate changes from choral sections to solos, in which the presumed second and third singers would have had to stop singing. One might add that the parts, several of which are reproduced in Mr. Parrott's book, appear too casual, fine and detailed to have been read by more than one person.</p>
        <p>Supporting evidence includes pictorial representations of musical performance from Bach's time, none of them showing singers (or instrumentalists, for that matter) sharing copies. Mr. Parrott also cites references to choral singing in various documents, most of which suggest that choirs in Baroque Germany generally had one singer for each part or, at most, two.</p>
        <p>But the most crucial document of all is one that comes to us from the hand of Bach himself, the memorandum he lodged with the Leipzig Town Council in 1730: what he called a ''brief yet highly necessary outline of a properly constituted church musical establishment, with some sober reflections on the decline of the same.'' This, too, Mr. Parrott incorporates in his book complete, in the original German and in translation.</p>
        <p>As director of music at St. Thomas's School, Bach was responsible for the choirs of four Leipzig churches, and three of those choirs had to be musically proficient, the fourth singing only chorales. Each choir, he stipulates, ''must have at least three sopranos, three altos, three tenors and as many basses.'' Four would be better. But as he immediately explains, this was to provide for illness: a common occurrence, ''as the prescriptions written by the school doctor for the apothecary must show.''</p>
        <p>Bach was thus asking the city to provide for choirs of 12 singers (16 in his dreams), but only so that, barring epidemics, there would always be enough to perform works with eight vocal parts. What is not clear -- since Bach was writing for the councilors of Leipzig, not for musicians nearly 300 years later -- is whether he would have expected all 12 singers to perform a piece with four parts (the standard for the Sunday cantatas) at times when the apothecary was not so busy.</p>
        <p>In fact, as he miserably concludes, he had no such luxury. In 1730, when he was writing, only 17 singers under his jurisdiction were musically able, so the school could hardly have done more than send a choir of four to each of the three churches where elaborate music was performed.</p>
        <p>Of course, there is no reason for professional musicians now to be constrained by the deteriorated conditions of musical Leipzig in 1730, and Mr. Parrott risks putting the music on a fast to imitate what Bach considered starvation. The evidence of the parts and of other contemporary documents, written and pictorial, is not entirely conclusive: the pictures are too few; the documents (like Bach's statement) had their own purposes. And it seems plausible that if Bach had had what he wanted -- choirs of 12 or even 16 -- he would have wanted everybody to sing, even in a four-part composition.</p>
        <p>As always, the important support for musical choices must come not from the archives but from the sound. And the sound of Mr. Parrott's performances -- here recently with the New York Collegium, and on a Sony Classical CD with his own Taverner Consort and Players in the ''Trauer-Ode'' and two motets -- is compelling proof that his ideas work.</p>
        <p>Choirs of soloists balance and blend beautifully with a period-style chamber orchestra. They sound well, even in a relatively large church. Phrasing and texture can be lighter, the effect, as Eric Van Tassel puts it in his liner notes for the recording, ''more personal and, in a way, more human.'' And at one point in the ''Trauer-Ode,'' as recorded here, the advantage of the four-person choir becomes startling. The tenor sings a short recitative, then he alone -- not clumped into a faceless group -- leads his companions into the ensuing chorus. More than all the arguments, the moment makes the case.</p>
        <p>IT is unfortunate that Mr. Parrott, in his book, should appeal not to such musical value but instead to a merely reproductive correctness, writing that his is ''the mode of performance which . . . best reflects Bach's own practice.'' For one thing, if that were to be the criterion, then Bach choirs would have to be all male.</p>
        <p>Still, his reforming zeal is understandable. If, as he points out, the great quartets of Haydn and Beethoven had always been performed by string orchestras, performances by just four players would be revelatory. So is his gentle, touching and musicianly Bach.</p>
        <p>This is, to be sure, not the only way. Other conductors will go on using choirs on the scale Bach might have hoped for, rather than of the size he had. Most important of all, the choirs of schools, churches and amateur societies, through which most of us came to feel the glory of Bach for the first time, will go on performing the ''St. Matthew Passion'' with crowds of singers, the more the merrier.</p>
        <p>Mr. Parrott, though, is vindicating a real alternative.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
