<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Billionaires Keep 'Raising the Bar'</title>
    <meta content="25BOAT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210369"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE BOATING REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E0DD1530F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Billionaires Keep 'Raising the Bar'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERB McCORMICK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In flush times and lean ones, the America's Cup has been a historical lure to wealthy men eager to advance business or personal agendas. In the early part of the last century, the Irish merchant Sir Thomas Lipton employed numerous cup challenges to help market tea bags. Later, the railroad tycoon Harold (Mike) Vanderbilt found cup racing to be a rigorous adjunct to the joys of a Newport, R.I., summer.</p>
        <p>Although in more recent times well-heeled businessmen like Bill Koch and Ted Turner have promulgated the notion that the cup is a game for the financially gifted, other sailors with working-class backgrounds, like Dennis Conner and Paul Cayard, have also proved that campaigns can be launched -- and a handsome individual salary procured -- with a healthy input of corporate backing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In flush times and lean ones, the America's Cup has been a historical lure to wealthy men eager to advance business or personal agendas. In the early part of the last century, the Irish merchant Sir Thomas Lipton employed numerous cup challenges to help market tea bags. Later, the railroad tycoon Harold (Mike) Vanderbilt found cup racing to be a rigorous adjunct to the joys of a Newport, R.I., summer.</p>
        <p>Although in more recent times well-heeled businessmen like Bill Koch and Ted Turner have promulgated the notion that the cup is a game for the financially gifted, other sailors with working-class backgrounds, like Dennis Conner and Paul Cayard, have also proved that campaigns can be launched -- and a handsome individual salary procured -- with a healthy input of corporate backing.</p>
        <p>But the days when a sponsored sailor can run a reasonably successful effort for $12 million or even $32 million -- the budgets for Conner's Stars and Stripes team and Cayard's America One squad in the last cup -- now appear to be over.</p>
        <p>Last week, the Seattle cellular-phone billionaire Craig O. McCaw announced the formation of his OneWorld Challenge for the 2002-3 cup races. And racing personnel in the United States and New Zealand have confirmed that Oracle's software founder, Larry Ellison, whose personal fortune is a reported $47 billion, is committed to a challenge.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, in Europe, the cup newcomers Ernesto Bertarelli and Pierre-Oliver Essig, from Switzerland, have joined the Prada Challenge's Patrizio Bertelli in separate campaigns to bring the cup to the continent. And while the announced cup budgets from this group range from $50 million to $70 million, in an escalated war for talent and technology, the thought of a $100 million America's Cup campaign is no longer laughable.</p>
        <p>''Dennis Conner calls these guys the Bees, for billionaires,'' said Bob Billingham, the general manager of America One. ''They've changed the game. They're raising the bar.</p>
        <p>Billingham said the new cup order is both sad and exciting. ''We fought hard to raise $20 million in corporate funding the last time, and it's questionable if that was good value for our sponsors,'' he said. ''To ask them to double or triple that amount is unrealistic.''</p>
        <p>But if Billingham believes his team's business plan is no longer competitively viable, he also feels the injection of fresh faces and dollars could spark new interest. ''Whether you see these guys as heroes or villains, the bottom line is that they're interesting people going head to head,'' he said. ''It could give the cup a whole new personality. And their funding will create technology that advances the entire sport.''</p>
        <p>One cup rookie who plans to avoid the limelight is McCaw, who skipped last week's luncheon at the Seattle Yacht Club, which his team will represent, and who declined requests to be interviewed for this story. For several weeks, McCaw's name has arisen as the likely backer of a Seattle-based challenge that was intent on raiding the back-to-back cup-winning Team New Zealand squad.</p>
        <p>McCaw has chosen the Australian cup veteran Peter Gilmour to head his sailing team, has recruited the Kiwi yacht designer Laurie Davidson to create his boats and has signed up two dozen of Davidson's countrymen to race them and work on them. ''The reason we built it around the Kiwis is that they were talented and available,'' said Bob Ratliffe, a spokesman for McCaw.</p>
        <p>The initial roster of Kiwis, which includes the grinders Andrew Taylor and Craig Monk, is notable for its lack of marquee names. The Kiwi superstars Russell Coutts and Brad Butterworth have already cast their fates with Bertarelli's Swiss group.</p>
        <p>McCaw has also enlisted the Seattle brothers Jonathan and Charlie McKee, who will also represent the United States in the 49er dinghy class at the Olympic Games in Sydney, Australia. ''By the time we're actually out there sailing, you'll see a much more balanced team that I would guess would primarily consist of Americans,'' Charlie McKee said. ''As a sailor, I'm excited about sailing with the best team these guys can put together.''</p>
        <p>McKee also said he and his brother were intrigued by the environmental mission of the syndicate. McCaw has proclaimed that part of his motivation in mounting a challenge is to promote environmental awareness of the world's oceans. ''Jonathan and I have purposely stayed out of this arena before, and that was a significant factor in our decision to join,'' Charlie McKee said.</p>
        <p>Somewhat lost in the shuffle surrounding McCaw's announcement is the Seattle Challenge, a second local effort that represents the Corinthian Yacht Club and is spearheaded by the 26-year-old boat builder Russell Belden, who hopes to bankroll his $42 million campaign with corporate funding. Belden's aim is to field an all-American squad.</p>
        <p>THE BOATING REPORT Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
