<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No-Man's Land Where Shoppers Fear to Tread</title>
    <meta content="25DRES" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000702T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210203"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trebay, Guy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEEDA1630F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No-Man's Land Where Shoppers Fear to Tread</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUY TREBAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Trebay, Guy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manhattan retailers continue to offer dressing rooms that are inconveniently located, cleaned infrequently, tiny and poorly lit, despite important role rooms play in buying decisions; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU are standing with your pants around your ankles when a stranger pulls back a curtain and says, ''Peekaboo!'' You have been locked out in a public place wearing a single black sock and a cocktail dress with a price tag hanging off the side. You are standing in your underwear when the woman your ex dumped you for strides imperiously into the room.</p>
        <p>Pop quiz: Are you 1) trapped in a Freudian nightmare, 2) a candidate for a case study in ''The Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders'' or 3) out shopping.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU are standing with your pants around your ankles when a stranger pulls back a curtain and says, ''Peekaboo!'' You have been locked out in a public place wearing a single black sock and a cocktail dress with a price tag hanging off the side. You are standing in your underwear when the woman your ex dumped you for strides imperiously into the room.</p>
        <p>Pop quiz: Are you 1) trapped in a Freudian nightmare, 2) a candidate for a case study in ''The Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders'' or 3) out shopping.</p>
        <p>The answer, obviously, is 3. And the source of your deep-rooted anxiety is that perennial bane of the shopper, the dressing room. Strange real estate, and even weirder psychic landscape, the dressing room is part dream chamber, part orgone box and a retail no man's land. Often cramped, creepy and hard to locate, it is sometimes locked tighter than an ICBM installation and sometimes so public it could be the stage set for an ''Oh! Calcutta!'' revival.</p>
        <p>There are certain enduring mysteries that attach to the dressing room, like why there is always a fossilized Cheez Doodle in a corner, why there are never enough places to hang your clothes, what the mystery stain is on the seat of the solitary chair (assuming there is a chair) and how come the lighting seems designed for the application of F/X makeup. Let's leave the fun house mirrors aside.</p>
        <p>The dressing room is a site of particular interest just now, a time of year that may look and feel like summer but that in fact is an entirely different point in the retail calendar. For serious shoppers, late June is not the season of fireflies and view tables at Della Femina in East Hampton. By the time of the summer solstice, anyone of serious shopping purpose has posted his jitney ticket on eBay and pitched a tent in Barneys. Markdowns are in full force, spring and summer apparel being treated by retailers with all the affectionate hindsight of a drunken one-night stand. (Thirty percent off at Prada, 50 at Ermenegildo Zegna, 70 percent at Amy Chan.) The alluring first fall shipments have begun to arrive. Veterans know that all the great back-to-school clothes will be sold out long before the first maple reddens. Summer is the new winter, as they say.</p>
        <p>Which is why you might think retailers would recognize the importance of dressing rooms. ''Dressing rooms are where the rubber meets the road,'' Paco Underhill, a marketing consultant, said. ''The dressing room is critical to the conversion rate. A lot of decisions are made there.'' ''Conversion rate'' is marketing jargon for that alchemical moment when a shopper becomes a buyer.</p>
        <p>Retailers agree that the transformation takes place inside a dressing room. What's odd, though, is that this consensus is rarely reflected in the rooms themselves, which in Manhattan represent a true rarity -- real estate nobody seems to want. ''The dressing room is a very important part of forming the customer connection,'' said Mr. Underhill, the author of ''Why We Buy: The Science of Shopping'' (Simon &amp; Schuster). ''It reflects the store's ethos. Yet, they're inconveniently located, no one wants to clean them, the lights are god awful. It's almost as if the space belonged to no one.''</p>
        <p>A meandering tour, ranging from the scruffy chic of NoLIta's hole-in-the-wall fashion outposts, to the sanitarium hush of upper Madison Avenue boutiques, revealed that Mr. Underhill's diagnosis was apposite. At Mayle, a Mulberry Street favorite of fashionistas, customers dress in a tiny closet behind a scrap of fabric. At the Union Square discounter Bradlees -- whose sprayed concrete ceilings and sepulchral dim evoke the Soviet-era department store GUM -- the dressing rooms resemble shower stalls and can be entered only after garment pockets are checked for ''like, stolen bobby pins or other small stuff,'' a saleswoman said.</p>
        <p>At the Banana Republic in SoHo, the pleasure of capacious, well appointed dressing rooms is offset somewhat by self-locking doors that overplay corporate paranoia about theft. (Salesman to customer: ''You all right in there?'' Customer to salesman: ''Oh, just fine. Be out as soon as I finish concealing these khakis in a body cavity.'')</p>
        <p>At Loehmann's on lower Seventh Avenue, customers continue to dress in an infamous communal space. It's the way they prefer it, Fred Forcellati, a vice president, said. ''If someone's got a dress you want, you can say, 'Oh, that doesn't look great on you,' and then the minute they put it down, you grab,'' he explained.</p>
        <p>And at Jeffrey, the relentlessly fashion-forward store in the meat-packing district, where shoes are displayed with the devotion of reliquary fragments, customers change in an area whose general lack of amenity and privacy bring to mind a visit to the school nurse.</p>
        <p>''In a perfect world scenario,'' said Jeffrey Kalinsky, the store's owner, ''a dressing room would have a mirror, some place to sit down -- and a carpet,'' because sweaty bare feet track dirt. It would also have ample hanging bars, even bathrobes and individual makeup masks, which are provided at the original Jeffrey in Atlanta. The reality is slightly less heady. ''Who wants to try on a $3,000 dress behind a shower curtain?'' Barbara Heizer, a customer, said.</p>
        <p>The same people, presumably, who skulk behind the drapery at A.P.C. in SoHo, slithering into $300 cigarette jeans in a semipublic area where there is no place to set the clothes you just shed. Or the ones trying on $1,800 Hedi Slimane suits at Yves St. Laurent Hommes on Greene Street, where customers dress in a velvet-curtained cubicle with the feel of a coffin that won't stay shut. (It was there that a ''Peekaboo!'' interloper recently surprised me with my Nicole Farhi trousers puddled at my feet.)</p>
        <p>''In the old days, fitting rooms were big and lush,'' said Betty Halbreich, author of ''Confessions of a Retail Therapist'' (HarperCollins) and a personal shopper at Bergdorf Goodman for 23 years. ''They had bud vases and flowers. Now, they don't even bother cleaning them. There's no privacy. There are pins on the floor. There are cameras, which I suppose you have to have, because there's so much thievery.''</p>
        <p>The ideal dressing room, Ms. Halbreich said, would be the size of Staten Island and furnished with two slipper chairs, a small table, numerous clothes hooks and bars, and a three-way mirror of high quality glass. Ms. Halbreich, a realist, said she would ''settle for enough bars in the room to hang the clothes I'm showing, and enough light to see if what you're buying is black or brown or navy or mouse.''</p>
        <p>Illumination is the most often cited of the many problems related to fitting-room design. ''The basic issues are as simple as enough hooks, a good mirror and good lighting, which means incandescent and fluorescent, but masked,'' said David New, vice president for creative services at Barneys New York. Mr. Underhill considered that three light settings (day, office, evening) are a fitting-room necessity. But a dressing room should provide more than that. It should ''surprise you and make you smile,'' said Mr. New, whose designs include dressing areas with walls of vintage postcards and Tic Tac packages on Barneys's Co-op floor.</p>
        <p>It's possible that the Swedish retailer H&amp;M was making a Scandinavian light bulb joke when it designed the dressing rooms of its hugely successful new Fifth Avenue store -- where each cubicle has a toggle switch and a sign that reads: ''Would you like to change the light? If you press the button, the light will change to a colder daylight, which shows the colors of the garments in a more natural way.'' When a visitor hit the button the room went abruptly dark. Color him black.</p>
        <p>''There are three places I like to look in a store,'' Mr. Underhill said. ''The ladies' bathroom, the employee locker room and the ladies' dressing room. They're all spaces that are an important part of forming the customer connection, and that give you a sense of the corporate ethos.''</p>
        <p>Ralph Lauren Polo stores, Mr. Underhill said, display a rare conceptual follow-through, carrying brand identity from the selling floor into the dressing room. And it's true that those areas at the Ralph Lauren flagship on Madison Avenue practically clobber the customer with the aura of a private men's club: Spy prints and sepia pictures of vintage sports cars, Chippendale-style chairs with hairy knees. What matter if it's all a fantasy? Does the average shopper care that most private men's clubs are likelier to have snapshots of ancient tennis champions falling out of their frames, and flaking club chairs with springs that come at you like rectal thermometers? ''Probably not,'' Mr. Underhill said.</p>
        <p>You don't have to be Thorstein Veblen to recognize that manufactured illusion is central to consumption. Why, then, has the intoxication been allowed to leach from so many aspects of shopping, one of the the core experiences of Western life?</p>
        <p>''We realize it to be an issue,'' said Christina Johnson, chief executive of Saks Fifth Avenue, which is undergoing a five-year, $100 million renovation of its 650,000-square-foot Fifth Avenue store. ''Appropriate environment and appointments are essential to engaging with the customer. We fall short at times of the standard that we set for ourselves.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Halbreich of Bergdorf's agreed that the shopping environment counts for everything. ''Management talks about service, but rarely does anything about it,'' she said. ''In the end, what is the difference between all these stores? A little knowledge, maybe? A little taste? Service is all you really have, and it's not service putting people in cells. The dressing room is more than just a place to change your clothes. The sale is made in that room.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 2, 2000, Sunday  An article last Sunday about dressing rooms in boutiques and department stores misstated the title of a book by Betty Halbreich, a personal shopper at Bergdorf Goodman. It is ''Secrets of a Fashion Therapist,'' not ''Confessions of a Retail Therapist.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 2, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about dressing rooms in boutiques and department stores misstated the title of a book by Betty Halbreich, a personal shopper at Bergdorf Goodman. It is ''Secrets of a Fashion Therapist,'' not ''Confessions of a Retail Therapist.''</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
