<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business; In Praise of the Freedom to Take Chances</title>
    <meta content="25SBOO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210238"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Fred</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pfeffer, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sutton, Robert I</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Knowing-Doing Gap, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE2D71630F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business; In Praise of the Freedom to Take Chances</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRED ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Fred</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Stanford University prof Jeffrey Pfeffer, co-author with Robert I Sutton of book The Knowing-Doing Gap, describes how Internet companies in particular can avoid 'knowing-doing gap' and learn to put their best ideas into practice; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JEFFREY PFEFFER, co-author of ''The Knowing-Doing Gap,'' teaches organizational behavior at Stanford University, in the heart of Silicon Valley. In an interview, he described how Internet companies in particular could learn to put their best ideas into practice. Following are excerpts from the conversation.</p>
        <p>FRED ANDREWS</p>
        <p>Q. How does the knowing-doing gap apply to e-commerce? Those companies seem hell-bent on action. Do they really need prodding?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JEFFREY PFEFFER, co-author of ''The Knowing-Doing Gap,'' teaches organizational behavior at Stanford University, in the heart of Silicon Valley. In an interview, he described how Internet companies in particular could learn to put their best ideas into practice. Following are excerpts from the conversation.</p>
        <p>FRED ANDREWS</p>
        <p>Q. How does the knowing-doing gap apply to e-commerce? Those companies seem hell-bent on action. Do they really need prodding?</p>
        <p>A. I would quote David Kelley from IDEO Product Development, who said, ''Enlightened trial and error outperforms the planning of flawless intellects.'' What is often lost is the word ''enlightened.'' The knowing-doing gap is not just about taking action -- it's about turning knowledge into action. E-commerce is obviously about taking action and being fast, but it's also about being knowledgeable and enlightened. Action without knowledge doesn't get you very far.</p>
        <p>Q. Do e-commerce companies already embody what you teach? Many go to great lengths to foster cooperation and open communication.</p>
        <p>A. Some e-commerce companies have done a very good job of doing what we talk about. Some have not. There's a lot of fear at some of them, a lot of distrust. At some of them, there's a lot of internal competition.</p>
        <p>Q. But some of them do things right?</p>
        <p>A. Actually I think Amazon is pretty good on most of these dimensions. They have created a climate in which people feel secure enough to speak their mind and tell the truth.</p>
        <p>I think the paradox you uncover quickly in life is that many organizations say they want people to learn but they also don't want them to make any mistakes.</p>
        <p>Q. To whom is your book directed? The boss? The board? Just anybody?</p>
        <p>A. It is certainly directed at managers at any level who have the opportunity to create environments. And I don't really believe that an environment is created only by the C.E.O. You know, division managers, department managers, group managers, they have the opportunity in their local domain, however big or small, to create an environment that reduces internal competition, reduces fear, tries to encourage people not to get stuck in the past but to build a better future for themselves.</p>
        <p>Q. How does change get going? If bad practices are deeply embedded, how do you get the ball rolling?</p>
        <p>A. I think philosophy comes first. If you're committed to building a culture in which people really do feel free to take chances, it truly begins with philosophy and mind-set. Then you just try stuff and see what works, and you keep innovating.</p>
        <p>Q. But does uprooting the old way require breaking some bones, inflicting some pain?</p>
        <p>A. I don't know that it requires inflicting pain or breaking bones. Look at Continental Airlines. When Gordon Bethune and Greg Brenneman took it over and decided they were going to run Continental in a different way --</p>
        <p>Q. Continental Airlines was in pretty desperate straits, right?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, pretty desperate. They got rid of the senior management who had operated under what I would call a fear-based and anti-employee regime. There does come a point at which you have to say, ''This is the way we're going to operate, and people who aren't comfortable with this culture need to find another home.'' But I'm not sure I'd go so far as calling that breaking bones.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
