<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Challenge of Educating the Homeless</title>
    <meta content="25HOME$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bowles, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE6D81E31F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2220" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Challenge of Educating the Homeless</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM BOWLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bowles, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on problems of educating homeless children in Connecticut; statistics are not kept since thousands of children are in shelters that do not receive state funds and thousands more live on streets or in overcrowded homes with friends or relatives; schools are learning to adapt to children in crisis who live in chaotic conditions at shelters; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LOURDES DAVILA'S recent meeting with teachers at Mahan Elementary School in Norwich was fairly routine. Her two oldest children were struggling with class assignments and so the teachers, in line with popular educational theory, urged Ms. Davila to go home and read every night with her children.</p>
        <p>But the problem is Ms. Davila, a 23-year-old mother of three with another on the way, lives in a nearby homeless shelter where peace and quiet is a rarity and reading books is considered a luxury.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LOURDES DAVILA'S recent meeting with teachers at Mahan Elementary School in Norwich was fairly routine. Her two oldest children were struggling with class assignments and so the teachers, in line with popular educational theory, urged Ms. Davila to go home and read every night with her children.</p>
        <p>But the problem is Ms. Davila, a 23-year-old mother of three with another on the way, lives in a nearby homeless shelter where peace and quiet is a rarity and reading books is considered a luxury.</p>
        <p>''This little one keeps me so busy,'' Ms. Davila said, pointing, but not looking, at her 2-year-old son who was on a hitting tour of other children in the lounge at the Thames Valley Council for Community Action Center. ''They say, 'Mom, Mom, I need help.' I try to help for a minute, but I can do no more. It's the place. The schedule. It's crazy.''</p>
        <p>It's a scenario faced by thousands of homeless children across Connecticut and one that some educators worry is hindering their schooling and increasing the likelihood that the cycle of poverty will continue among their families.</p>
        <p>Although educational statistics on homeless children are not kept, the obstacles they face are numerous. And while some are excellent pupils, others struggle early with basic skills such as reading, writing and math.</p>
        <p>Frequent relocations create problems adjusting to new schools. The stigma associated with shelters robs them of self-confidence. Crowded living conditions make it difficult for them to concentrate on homework. And exhausted, overburdened parents struggle to help with homework.</p>
        <p>''The most important thing to remember about these children and their families is they are in crisis,'' said Mary McAtee, executive director of Connecticut Coalition to End Homelessness in Wethersfield. ''Any time we are in crisis, our regular activities are usually hampered. For both parents and children, simple daily routines like preparing for school, doing homework, returning permission slips become very difficult to manage.''</p>
        <p>From October 1998 to September 1999, there were 3,151 children in 44 shelters that received state money, a 12.5 percent increase from the same period a year before. That included 230 school-aged children at the Norwich shelter. There were also 1,393 children living with their mothers in 18 domestic violence shelters statewide in 1998-99, according to the Connecticut Coalition Against Domestic Violence.</p>
        <p>Thousands of homeless children are in shelters, such as those in churches, that do not receive state money and in other youth shelters, so no one knows exactly how many homeless children live in the state. And, experts said, thousands more live on the streets, under bridges, in cars and abandoned buildings and in overcrowded homes with friends or relatives.</p>
        <p>Connecticut Coalition, a private, nonprofit organization, has asked state legislators and social service agencies for improvements in affordable housing, employment and alcohol and drug rehabilitation services for the homeless. Ms. McAtee said improvements in these areas naturally lead to a better education for homeless children.</p>
        <p>But there are several other volunteer, federal, school and legal initiatives that help educate homeless children across the state.</p>
        <p>Ann Louise Blanchard, a lawyer with Connecticut Legal Services in Willimantic, said she helps clients understand their rights under the McKinney Act of 1987. The federal Education of Homeless Children and Youth program, created under the act, provides grants to states to ensure that all homeless children have equal access to the same free, appropriate education provided to other children.</p>
        <p>Nationwide, states received a total of $28.8 million under the act for 1999-2000. Connecticut received $256,575, which was distributed to 16 school districts for services that ranged from liaisons between the schools and homeless shelters, to homework assistance programs, to parenting programs for shelter residents.</p>
        <p>Eight years after the program began, the percentage of homeless children attending school regularly increased from 50 percent to 86 percent. The improvement was attributed partly to the fact that federal money was made available to school districts so that a homeless child could have the option of being transported back to the school district she or he had to leave.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most ambitious education program for homeless children in the state is the one run by Miriam Epstein in Manchester, a former elementary school teacher who quit that career in 1993 to devote more time to helping homeless children.</p>
        <p>The program, Books to Dreams, now in its fifth year, operates in 11 shelters, including in Hartford, New London, Danielson, Willimantic, Rockville and Norwich. From September 1998 to June 1999, she helped distribute more than 19,000 donated books to needy children.</p>
        <p>Ms. Epstein used her own money to run the program during its first year. State legislators were so impressed with her work that she received grant money through the Department of Social Services the following year. She will get $30,000 this year.</p>
        <p>''Research shows that if children read for pleasure, they become better readers and school becomes less difficult,'' Ms. Epstein said. ''They are more apt to stay in school, which gives them more choices in life, thus breaking the cycle of poverty.''</p>
        <p>Joseph Stefon, principal of Mahan Elementary School in Norwich, which children from the TVCCA shelter attend, said his school does all it can to ensure a homeless child is not at a disadvantage in class. Extra supplies and textbooks are available should a homeless child suddenly enroll at the school.</p>
        <p>Teachers and administrators work quickly to assess and register the students. A classmate is assigned to each homeless child to make the child feel welcome.</p>
        <p>But at the end of the school day, none of the teachers have control over what happens in the child's life at home.</p>
        <p>It is easy to see why things such as homework are challenges to homeless children. The noise is the first thing noticeable about the lounge at the TVCCA shelter -- at least in the evening.</p>
        <p>While Derrick Davila, 7, tried to read one recent weeknight, his 2-year-old brother, Alexander Daquan, threw a bouncy ball off the face of an older child sitting in a nearby chair. Some children watched ''The Simpsons'' on TV. A group of girls played with dolls at a table. One boy cried when another boy hit him. Another boy cried when someone took his blanket.</p>
        <p>There are 15 rooms at this one-floor brick building at the top of a hill on the grounds. Right now, there are about 40 residents. Twenty-four are children ranging in age from infants to adolescents.</p>
        <p>Ms. Davila and her family live in a small room with four beds and one crib near the end of the hallway. There is no desk for the children to do homework.</p>
        <p>After living in New London, New Jersey, New London again and Texas, Ms. Davila and her children arrived at the shelter on Dec. 22. Ms. Davila's new boyfriend joined them. Mahan Elementary School is the third school her children have attended in the past year. Moving poses academic problems because each class seems to teach the same subjects at different paces. Ms. Davila wants to move, but not too far. Her children beg her to stay. ''They say, 'Mom, that means I have to change schools, make new friends, meet new teachers and a new principal,' '' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Davila's life is full of stress, she said. She became pregnant as a young teen, dropping out of school in the eighth grade.</p>
        <p>Her oldest child, Derrick, has a brain disorder called hydrocephalus, a condition that requires frequent trips to Yale-New Haven Hospital for check-ups. She said difficulty finding child care and pains from her pregnancy prompted her to take a break from work.</p>
        <p>Her boyfriend, the one who moved in with her at the shelter, was arrested and jailed recently. Her 2-year-old doesn't understand. The boyfriend is not Alexander's father, but the boy calls him Dad. Alexander sometimes picks up the pay phone and pretends to call him. ''He's always saying, 'Where's Daddy?'' Ms. Davila said.</p>
        <p>Derrick and Tanajiah, her 6-year-old daughter, get embarrassed when the other public schools kids on the bus see where they live.</p>
        <p>Melissa DeJesus and her 7-year-old daughter, Victoria, live at the Holy Family Home and Shelter in Willimantic. Ms. DeJesus pointed to an obvious solution to her child's educational needs.</p>
        <p>''A home would help me work with her one-on-one because there would be no interruptions.' She said her child is easily distracted from her homework by other children from the shelter when they play.</p>
        <p>Still, Ms. DeJesus said she is grateful for an after-school program at the shelter where she receives help reading and uses a computer. ''The only place she might sit still long enough is with the lady at the shelter who teaches her.''</p>
        <p>It is at the shelters, where it is often chaotic, where these parents are supposed to spend time with their children, reading, dividing and writing. Experts are quite clear that parent involvement in a child's education is crucial. And the state wants success. Connecticut Mastery Tests are held every year to assess the reading, writing and math skills of every fourth, sixth and eighth grader.</p>
        <p>State education officials want to narrow the academic achievement gap between poor and rich schools and have everyone do better. So educators in primary and secondary schools are intensifying efforts for higher test scores by tightening curriculum, creating early literacy programs and encouraging parents and guardians to help their children at home. But educators struggle to fit the needs of homeless children into this picture.</p>
        <p>''We sometimes find out from kids who live at the shelter that so and so is gone, he left last night,'' said Mr. Stefon, Mahan's principal. ''We have kids we have never been able to say goodbye to.''</p>
        <p>The erratic enrollment of homeless children at Mahan affects students and staff at the school in several different ways. The impact ranges from potentially serious consequences, such as unexpectedly large classes, to the less severe, such as time spent determining what classes are best for the children.</p>
        <p>Fern Cipriani, a fourth grade teacher at Mahan, has taught a nine homeless children the past year. Two of these students loved school and excelled in their work, she said. The rest struggled.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of gaps in their education,'' she said. ''It's not that they are learning disabled, it's just the in and out of schools. They are constantly trying to catch up. When you are moving on to division and they haven't mastered multipication, it's difficult because they need to do the multiplication first. So you backtrack to get them caught up with what the rest of the class is doing.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Cipriani said she made sure she gave the homeless students extra support, either by paying extra attention to them or assigning them to one-on-one instructional times with an intern.</p>
        <p>Administrators find it difficult to evaluate homeless students for learning disabilities. At Mahan, a Planning Placement Team meets with a parent to discuss the child's needs and then administrators determine whether further academic or psychological evaluations are necessary. If so, they have 45 days to complete the testing, though it's often finished much sooner than that.</p>
        <p>The problem is, there have been times when a child has left the school two days after the meeting, leaving the pupil in limbo over his or her appropriate class level.</p>
        <p>Frustrations with similar complications prompted some shelters in the United States to provide regular classes for children. There are 40 such schools designated specifically for homeless children in 19 states, a trend that began in 1984, reported the National Law Center on Homelessness and Poverty. There is one in Connecticut, at the Bridge Youth Shelter in Hartford.</p>
        <p>But the Center argued that these permanent institutions are separate and substandard, possibly violating a federal law that guarantees access to an equal education.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, there are many testimonies of homeless children who overcome their educational odds. Ms. Epstein keeps in contact with two former homeless children originally from Willimantic who are now going to college out of state. One wants to become a lawyer. The other is taking business administration courses.</p>
        <p>''These children are bright and eager to learn,'' Ms. Epstein said. ''They need encouragement and belief in them and books in order to reach their possibilities.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
