<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>JERSEY</title>
    <meta content="25DIAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210108"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E3D61E31F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="575" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>JERSEY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>I've memorized where most items are in my supermarket in Hillsdale. So when a harried-looking man asked me where he could find the sugar, I was happy to help.</p>
        <p>We met again, and this time he was searching for mayonaise. Again I obliged. A third time we approached each other from opposite ends of the next aisle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>I've memorized where most items are in my supermarket in Hillsdale. So when a harried-looking man asked me where he could find the sugar, I was happy to help.</p>
        <p>We met again, and this time he was searching for mayonaise. Again I obliged. A third time we approached each other from opposite ends of the next aisle.</p>
        <p>''Oh hon, he called.</p>
        <p>More amused than surprised, I smiled as I came closer. Now what, I thought, as I said,''Yes?'' good-naturedly.</p>
        <p>But my amusement turned to embarrassment when I realized his remark was not addressed to me. His wife was right behind me.</p>
        <p>KATHLEEN Du HAIME</p>
        <p>Driving through Summit while taking my three young children to school, I tried to describe what a primary election was. I touched on the parties and the candidates and mentioned Jon Corzine.</p>
        <p>''Corzine is popular in this town,'' I said. ''He lives here. In fact, you may have seen his name on signs.''</p>
        <p>''Oh,'' interrupted a voice from the back of the minivan. My 9-year-old daughter had apparently made a discovery. ''I thought he was a painter.''</p>
        <p>CECELIA A. SLATER</p>
        <p>And speaking of painters . . .</p>
        <p>My husband travels frequently and has little time for home improvements, so it's my job to contract these projects out to qualified professionals. Currently I'm searching for inexpensive painters to whitewash  our back fence.</p>
        <p>While traveling through Midland Park I spotted several men in bright uniforms painting a wrought-iron fence. Eager to see their logo and telephone number, I pulled over for closer inspection. The letters across their shirts read: ''PRISONER.''</p>
        <p>DEIRDRE FLANAGAN WARD</p>
        <p>MULTITASKING</p>
        <p>As you're racing down the highway in your ultramodern Beemer</p>
        <p>One hand holds the coffee cup, the other pours the creamer</p>
        <p>One hand wields the cell phone while the other checks your e-mail</p>
        <p>One hand plies a razor (or make-up if you're female)</p>
        <p>But what I cannot spot, despite my anxious peering:</p>
        <p>Which of all those hands is the one that does the steering.</p>
        <p>BARRY DICKMAN</p>
        <p>Overheard while shopping in a Millburn gift store:</p>
        <p>An 11-year-old girl picks up a small embroidered decorative throw pillow that says, ''FIRST HONEYMOON -- NIAGARA . . . SECOND HONEYMOON -- VIAGARA'' and asked: ''Mom, I don't get this.''</p>
        <p>The mother replies: ''Never mind. I'll explain it when we're in the car.''</p>
        <p>HELEN GLASER</p>
        <p>And also overheard in Millburn, one well-heeled woman telling another while walking from the train to their cars: ''Having a house at the beach is really hard, always running from one to other . . . and neither ever looking the way you want.''</p>
        <p>(Life's a beach.)</p>
        <p>Seen on a sign in front of a church in Union: ''Well, it's official . . . only God can beat the Devils!''</p>
        <p>GABRIELE LAZZARO</p>
        <p>PARADE'S END</p>
        <p>They're a sparking lot</p>
        <p>Our New Jersey Devils</p>
        <p>But a parking lot</p>
        <p>Must do for their revels.</p>
        <p>EDMUND CONTI</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
