<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Messages That Got Away</title>
    <meta content="25ONJO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE JOB"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Van Gelder, Lawrence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/On the Job</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6D61031F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Messages That Got Away</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawrence Van Gelder On the Job column relates anecdotes that illustrate the pitfalls of communicating via telephone-answering machine, voice mail, e-mail and fax; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Without question, modern technology, notably in the form of the telephone, voice mail, e-mail and the fax, has speeded communication. Whether it has enhanced communication is another matter. As these anecdotes indicate, haste continues to make waste, chips prove no substitute for the human brain and many an ill-considered word find an unintended audience.</p>
        <p>Janice M. Cauwels, a writer and consultant in Maywood, N.J., ran into a problem when she was assisting a celebrity on a book.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Without question, modern technology, notably in the form of the telephone, voice mail, e-mail and the fax, has speeded communication. Whether it has enhanced communication is another matter. As these anecdotes indicate, haste continues to make waste, chips prove no substitute for the human brain and many an ill-considered word find an unintended audience.</p>
        <p>Janice M. Cauwels, a writer and consultant in Maywood, N.J., ran into a problem when she was assisting a celebrity on a book.</p>
        <p>''I had picked the worst possible time to contact a renowned academic psychiatrist and ask him to double-check a chapter on eating disorders that I had rewritten,'' Ms. Cauwels recalls. ''Impossibly busy anyway, he was preparing for two major conferences only a few weeks apart.</p>
        <p>''I faxed my material to the psychiatrist, then followed up with notes repeatedly apologizing for the inconvenience. Upon returning to my office a few days later, I found a long voice-mail message from him, indicating that my write-up was fine. I was one of a 'steamed group of people,' he added in what sounded like his typical vernacular, who had been trying to reach him without success.</p>
        <p>''I sent a thank-you note mentioning my surprise that he thought I was angry, despite my expressed regrets for bothering him at a bad time.</p>
        <p>''Back came a highly amused reply: more careful enunciation would have made clear that actually I belonged to 'an esteemed group,' hence his prompt attention.''</p>
        <p>''I have a business acquaintance who relies heavily on voice recognition and e-mail to do his job,'' writes Jay Vivian of Stamford, Conn. ''A year or two ago, I received a broadcast e-mail from him addressed to about seven of us, obviously a distribution list of people who shared an interest in investment risk management. After discussing some ideas, he proposed a work plan and then suggested that we get together to discuss it.</p>
        <p>''His note concluded, 'I think it would be a good idea for us to get enemas all together. Hope you agree.'</p>
        <p>''It turns out that he had said into his voice recognition microphone, 'I think it would be a good idea to get en masse, all together,' but his voice recognition software wasn't familiar with the French phrase and had replaced it with the closest match in its dictionary. He had proofread it quickly and missed the replacement.</p>
        <p>''I sent it back to him, suggesting that this was an unusual way to evaluate ideas. He was mortified.''</p>
        <p>''A colleague and I had a complicated task to complete, and our manager decided we could do it best off site, in the quiet of my colleague's home,'' writes Nancy Cheser of Naples, Fla., recalling her days as a systems analyst in Springfield, Mass.</p>
        <p>''After two days of working, I phoned my manager, who I thought was doing a particularly poor job of coordinating the project, to give him a status report on our work. He was not at his desk, so I left a message on his voice mail. I was using my colleague's cordless phone and put it down on the desk. I then proceeded to give a detailed rehashing of my complaints against my manager to my co-worker.</p>
        <p>A few days later, when Ms. Cheser returned to her office, she says: ''My manager approached me and asked me to step out into the corridor. Apparently I had not turned off the cordless phone, and my rampage was recorded, along with my status report, on his phone mail.</p>
        <p>''Though I expected him to be angry, he was more concerned that I had not approached him in person with my dissatisfaction. I still cringe when I remember our walk in the hall.''</p>
        <p>Lest all blame for miscommunication fall upon modern technology, leave it to Horace Hone, a retired aircraft engineer in Palm Coast, Fla., to note that this electronic age has no monopoly on transmissions gone wrong.</p>
        <p>''A devastating example of a garbled message occurred long before voice mail, e-mail, etc., and it ruined the day for every British subject,'' he writes. ''After the Battle of Waterloo,  a cross-Channel transmission, probably by semaphore, was received at Dover, saying 'Wellington Defeated.'</p>
        <p>''For some reason, maybe fog, no further details were forthcoming. But a one-word continuation of the message the next day changed gloom to jubilation. The word was 'Napoleon.'</p>
        <p>''There is a lesson here,'' Mr. Hone concludes. ''Be careful how you draft your communications.''</p>
        <p>ON THE JOB</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
