<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Habitats/145 Nassau Street, Near City Hall Park; Seeking Space and Quiet, Couple Move Downtown</title>
    <meta content="25HABI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hall, Trish</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Manning, Annabel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelly, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Habitats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E2D81031F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1095" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Habitats/145 Nassau Street, Near City Hall Park; Seeking Space and Quiet, Couple Move Downtown</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRISH HALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hall, Trish</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>habitats/145 nassau s</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANNABEL MANNING and Michael Kelly were expecting their first baby, and suddenly their apartment on the third floor of an East Village brownstone didn't  seem like the best place to live. Although it was large, 1,000 square feet, and charming, with two fireplaces and wide pumpkin-pine floors, it didn't have a second bedroom, and it posed the problem of stairs, which are intimidating with a baby in one arm and a stroller in the other.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly, 46, who teaches philosophy at Columbia and is the managing editor of the Journal of Philosophy,  and Ms. Manning, 41, an artist and medical translator, decided that it made sense to move to the Upper West Side, close to his work and in the heart of baby territory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANNABEL MANNING and Michael Kelly were expecting their first baby, and suddenly their apartment on the third floor of an East Village brownstone didn't  seem like the best place to live. Although it was large, 1,000 square feet, and charming, with two fireplaces and wide pumpkin-pine floors, it didn't have a second bedroom, and it posed the problem of stairs, which are intimidating with a baby in one arm and a stroller in the other.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly, 46, who teaches philosophy at Columbia and is the managing editor of the Journal of Philosophy,  and Ms. Manning, 41, an artist and medical translator, decided that it made sense to move to the Upper West Side, close to his work and in the heart of baby territory.</p>
        <p>They had settled in the East Village when they moved to New York from Boston in 1986. The East Village was filled with galleries then, and its variety of human life forms reminded Ms. Manning of Mexico City, where she had grown up, the daughter of an American mother and a Chilean father. But they were beginning to tire a bit of the neighborhood's party atmosphere. ''They call it Disneyland East,'' Mr. Kelly said.</p>
        <p>In real estate, however, as in life, what is sensible does not always make sense. With their broker, Miriam Sirota, a vice president of Bellmarc Realty, they looked at a number of places near Columbia, but they never felt at home. Ms. Sirota remembers taking them to very nice two-bedroom apartments, to open houses where there was stroller gridlock, so many families were looking. ''They would just look and say, 'um humm,' '' she said. Clearly it wasn't for them.</p>
        <p>ONE day, Mr. Kelly began browsing through the real estate Web sites and noticed that apartments downtown near Wall Street offered more space for less money than the Upper West Side. The sellers also seemed much more eager, and there was a slightly apologetic tone to their ads, he said,  especially about the lack of grocery stores and restaurants. In other neighborhoods, he said, even the listings were tough: ''It was, 'If you're not here by 7 with a bag of money, it's gone,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>He was particularly interested in a loft on Beaver Street, even though, he said, ''I had no idea where Beaver Street was.'' And so, they asked Ms. Sirota to give them a tour and introduce them to the neighborhood. The loft that was appealing on Beaver had been sold, but as they were walking up Nassau Street both Ms. Manning and Mr. Kelly stopped at No. 145, at Park Row, and told Ms. Sirota that it was the kind of building they liked.</p>
        <p>A Queen Anne-style building constructed of red brick and brownstone-colored terra cotta, the elaborately detailed structure is called the Potter Building, after the real estate investor and politician Orlando B. Potter, who commissioned its construction in the mid-1880's.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, and rather miraculously, when their broker went back to her office, she discovered that a deal on a 2,000-square-foot triplex co-op apartment there had just fallen through. Ms. Manning and Mr. Kelly quickly made a deal with the frustrated sellers, who cut their price from $825,000 to $742,000. The monthly maintenance is $2,174.</p>
        <p>Their floorthrough in their East Village co-op, on the very sought after block of 10th Street between Second and Third Avenues, sold almost immediately for their asking price of $699,000.</p>
        <p>In mid-May, they moved with their new daughter, Sonia Kelly-Manning, born on Cinco de Mayo, into the apartment. It had been renovated over the course of a year by the previous owners, who lived in it for only three weeks. The kitchen, with black appliances and cherry cupboards, opens to a large dining area, where they have placed a long, colorful tile-topped table. In addition to a living room that looks out on City Hall Park, their first floor has a small study for Mr. Kelly with an elaborately detailed arch and ceilings that are about 18 feet high.</p>
        <p>On the second floor, not much more than a landing, is a play area for children, and on the top floor, two bedrooms and an office for Ms. Manning. ''I enjoy the space,'' Ms. Manning said. ''And I enjoy a little less people, the quiet at night.'' Mr. Kelly likes all of the nooks in the apartment, which even has a perfect spot under the stairs to park a stroller.</p>
        <p>They aren't completely moved in; boxes of books still fill his office. But in the dining area, an elaborate Mexican candelabra sits on a bookshelf that holds the ''Encyclopedia of Aesthetics,'' which was published by Oxford University Press in 1988 and for which he was the editor in chief. On the facing wall is one of her paintings, a work in ink of people in a crowd, smeared with urethane to give it a ghostly quality. She often shows crowds. ''I just like the relationship of gestures when you're in a situation together,'' she said. Nearby is a framed original of a Sunday ''L'il Abner'' cartoon by Al Capp, her grandfather and playmate. ''He loved kids,'' she said. ''He got a lot of his ideas from them.''</p>
        <p>THE transition from the East Village has been easy, although the neighborhoods couldn't be more different. ''I like the newness of the neighborhood,'' Mr. Kelly said. ''It has a different kind of urbanness.'' The previous night, they had walked over to Battery Park City for an outdoor concert by Ornette Coleman. They are discovering some of the new restaurants, like the Vine on Broad Street. There are things to do, but the relatively quiet nights are a relief from the East Village.</p>
        <p>''I love to go to Montauk,'' where they have a house, Mr. Kelly said. ''But I didn't want to go to Montauk because I didn't want to be where I was.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
