<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business; In Monica's Story, a Chapter on Entrepreneurship</title>
    <meta content="25MONI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Handbags and Purses</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ellin, Abby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE2DE1730F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1346" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business; In Monica's Story, a Chapter on Entrepreneurship</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY ELLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ellin, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Monica Lewinsky, finding herself with time on her hands while White House scandal was playing out two years ago, took up knitting but could not afford the bag she wanted for carrying yarn; she sewed her own bag and launched handbag-design company, The Real Monica Inc; Lewinsky designs all the bags, though she has delegated company financial matters to one of her four partners; her bags are sold at Henri Bendel in New York and Fred Segal Melrose in West Hollywood, Calif; her Web site has more than 5 million hits since its debut in Sept 1999; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MONICA LEWINSKY breezed into her mother and stepfather's penthouse apartment in Manhattan and sighed. After apologizing for being late -- she couldn't find a cab, traffic was awful -- she kissed her stepfather goodbye as he was leaving and plopped down in a chair.</p>
        <p>''I'm so lucky,'' she murmured. It's not the sort of assessment that one might expect from Ms. Lewinsky, but she seemed to mean it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MONICA LEWINSKY breezed into her mother and stepfather's penthouse apartment in Manhattan and sighed. After apologizing for being late -- she couldn't find a cab, traffic was awful -- she kissed her stepfather goodbye as he was leaving and plopped down in a chair.</p>
        <p>''I'm so lucky,'' she murmured. It's not the sort of assessment that one might expect from Ms. Lewinsky, but she seemed to mean it.</p>
        <p>At 26, she is still young, but she seemed poised, no longer the wide-eyed White House intern. And she appeared excited about her role at the helm of her new handbag-design company, The Real Monica Inc.</p>
        <p>Her handbags, made of cloth in a ''hippie chic'' style, are sold at Henri Bendel in Manhattan, at Fred Segal Melrose in West Hollywood, Calif., and on her Web site, therealmonicainc.com. ''I originally wanted to use Monicainc.com, but that was taken,'' she said. ''A friend said, 'What about The Real Monica Inc.?' and I thought, 'O.K.' ''</p>
        <p>By now the story of how she started her business is almost as well-known as the person. Two years ago, while the White House scandal was playing out, Ms. Lewinsky had time on her hands. She knitted, but  couldn't afford the bag she wanted for carrying yarn. Having experience in sewing -- she designed costumes for high school plays -- she decided to make her own handbags.</p>
        <p>Friends loved them, and suggested that she place them in stores. With help from a few friends, she wrote a loosely detailed mission statement, which described the product line and gave guidelines for how the company would be run.</p>
        <p>''We decided that the Web would really be the best place to start,'' she said. ''We have a 24-hour store, in every city, in every state, in every country in the world. And we've had sales all over the world.''</p>
        <p>The site has had more than five million hits since its debut last September. On March 22, when the bags were first sold at Bendel's, she received 400 e-mail messages. She does not respond to such notes personally, but a small customer service department does, and she says she takes suggestions seriously.</p>
        <p>''I get tons of e-mails from young people starting out and they want advice,'' she said. ''It's a difficult situation: I don't know that I feel comfortable giving anybody advice.''</p>
        <p>MS. LEWINSKY is not in charge of company finances, having delegated the job to one of her four partners. ''I'm involved in the sense that I know what's going on, but not in the day to day,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But she designs all the bags, which are sewn by hand at an apparel manufacturer in Louisiana, where about 12 people are working for her.</p>
        <p>She buys the fabric herself from showrooms in Dallas and in the garment district of Manhattan. ''They all know me by name,'' she said, then stopped and laughed: ''Well, everyone knows me by my name, but they think of me as a different Monica, not that one.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, she said, no one seems fazed by her notoriety. ''The people with whom I've been working have been wonderful,'' she said. ''At first there was probably a slight hesitation to take what I was doing seriously, but after they spent about five minutes with me they began to treat me like they would any customer.''</p>
        <p>Like many other young Internet entrepreneurs, she readily acknowledged that she knew nothing about business before starting her company. ''If you'd said, B-to-B? B-to-C? Venture capital? I'd have thought it was a ride at Disney,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But she is learning quickly. She's had to.</p>
        <p>For starters, people were not exactly begging to be involved in a Monica Lewinsky project. And contrary to popular perception, she said, she is not a millionaire. In fact, she is working her way out of debt. Although she declined to be specific, published reports have put her legal fees at $1.5 million. She reportedly earned $500,000 for her book, ''Monica's Story,'' and had a $300,000 endorsement deal with Jenny Craig, the diet company.</p>
        <p>''People have such a misconception about my financial situation,'' she said. ''My parents aren't helping me out; I paid them back for the money they put out.''</p>
        <p>Her finances were so precarious that at first she bought fabric at retail -- partly, she said, because she wanted to keep the business a secret until it was ready, partly because she didn't think she would get credit as a young entrepreneur. ''I used to make fun of myself for that, but I recently heard from several people that a lot of people start out buying materials retail,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Now she has credit, and a viable product. She and four partners -- friends with business, Web or design experience -- are negotiating for venture capital. As for sales, she said, ''Our first quarter in 2000 is two times that of our first quarter in 1999, and we're expecting similar growth for the second quarter.''</p>
        <p>Is she exploiting herself to make a buck? After all, on the Web site are the handwritten words ''Made especially for you by Monica,'' surrounded by roses. There is also a list of questions, like ''Where can I acquire autographed books and pictures?'' (The answer: For now, you can't.) and ''What is the lipstick that Monica wore on the Barbara Walters special?'' (Club Monaco Glaze).</p>
        <p>''Quite frankly, the name is what attracts people to the product, but what's going to satisfy the customer is that it's a great product,'' she said. ''I don't want people to think I'm taking advantage of this.''</p>
        <p>Ed Burstell, the general manager at Bendel's, agreed. ''We bought 200 bags and did a blind test last Christmas, with no hype at all,'' he recalled. ''They evaporated in two weeks. They really fit in fashion.''</p>
        <p>In March, 250 bags were sold at Bendel's the day that Ms. Lewinsky appeared in the store. Mr. Burstell estimated that nearly 500 people showed up to see her bags -- or, perhaps, to see her.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky recalls that day fondly. ''To see all of the bags there, displayed so beautifully and to be in such a prominent place, I just started crying,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burstell heard about the bags from a friend who had seen them in California and told him to call Ms. Lewinsky. They met, and he was impressed. ''I was amazed at how funny she is,'' he said, ''and she comes unattended'' -- without an entourage -- ''which I found refreshing.'' Bendel's just received a summer order of 400 purses and totes, priced from $80 to $170.</p>
        <p>The fashion industry has given the bags a respectful reception. ''They're cute, almost like an anti-fashion fashion statement,'' said Karen Bressler, the editorial director of fashionwindow.com, a fashion Web site. ''Everyone in the city has a name-brand handbag. This is a nice change from all the logo-mania.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky has just finished designing  a fall-winter-holiday line that will hit the shelves at the end of summer. Other pieces -- a makeup case, messenger bag, and a ''Mommy tote'' for things like diapers -- are  in the works.</p>
        <p>She is also considering taking classes, most likely in e-commerce, to prepare for the future.</p>
        <p>And is she proud of herself?</p>
        <p>She smiled. ''When something goes from conception to opening on the Web, to selling out at Christmas and being in stores like Bendel's and Fred Segal, to then looking into getting venture capital -- all within the year -- that is something to smile about,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''Especially if you compare it to the year before.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
