<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kung Fu Buddhists Stress That Mind and Body Are One</title>
    <meta content="25TEMP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000723T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210233"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: FLUSHING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFD81630F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kung Fu Buddhists Stress That Mind and Body Are One</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM O'GRADY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a nondescript stretch of 41st Avenue, two blocks from the shopper-thronged crossroads of Main Street and Roosevelt Boulevard, sits the North American outpost of a legendary Buddhist temple.</p>
        <p>The original Songshan Shaolin Temple still exists in mountainous Hunan in China, where it was founded in the sixth century. It is known as the womb of the martial art kung fu.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a nondescript stretch of 41st Avenue, two blocks from the shopper-thronged crossroads of Main Street and Roosevelt Boulevard, sits the North American outpost of a legendary Buddhist temple.</p>
        <p>The original Songshan Shaolin Temple still exists in mountainous Hunan in China, where it was founded in the sixth century. It is known as the womb of the martial art kung fu.</p>
        <p>But what is less well known is the Shaolin tradition of marrying kung fu training to the observance of traditional Chinese Buddhism. The new temple's spiritual leader, Master  Guolin, said he was sent to the United States eight years ago to spread this blend of religious and physical discipline, which is summed up in a teaching of the old monastery: ''There is no difference between body and mind. Controlling the body is controlling the mind.''</p>
        <p>It is a teaching that Master Guolin and his staff are trying to instill in the harried shoppers of Flushing and environs.</p>
        <p>They seem to be doing modestly well. The Shaolin Temple Overseas Headquarters, as the American branch is called, recently moved from a nearby storefront to spacious new quarters where two red lacquered columns frame the front door and support a classically curved Asian roof line.</p>
        <p>In the intimate, incense-scented front room, dominated by an altar to the Buddha, Master Guolin and members of the temple gather to reflect on Buddhist scripture, receive teachings and chant prayers. In the high-ceilinged back room,  whose walls are covered with hundreds of golden carvings of Buddhist masters, kung fu training is held.</p>
        <p>Master Guolin says blending both activities in one temple is unique in the city. Jeff Wilson, author of ''The Buddhist Guide to New York,'' agreed.</p>
        <p>''Shaolin is the pinnacle of the martial arts as meditation in movement,'' he said. ''It's an expression of spiritual discipline.''</p>
        <p>Elena Che of Bayside, a 28-year-old kindergarten teacher, has been going to the temple for five years. ''Here, you have both Buddhism and the martial arts,'' she said. ''It has helped me develop a spiritual direction in my life.''</p>
        <p>As she spoke, Ms. Che stood beneath two pictures of Master Guolin. In one, he strikes a fierce kung fu pose on the grounds of the original Shaolin Monastery. In the other, he wears a monk's saffron robe as he meditates serenely on the well-trampled sands of Jones Beach.</p>
        <p>JIM O'GRADY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: FLUSHING  Correction:  July 23, 2000, Sunday  An article in the Neighborhood Report pages on June 25 about the Shaolin Temple Overseas Headquarters, a Buddhist institution in Flushing, Queens, misstated the location of the original Shaolin Temple. It is in Henan Province in China, not Hunan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 23, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article in the Neighborhood Report pages on June 25 about the Shaolin Temple Overseas Headquarters, a Buddhist institution in Flushing, Queens, misstated the location of the original Shaolin Temple. It is in Henan Province in China, not Hunan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
