<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Business Venture That Is, Well, Scary</title>
    <meta content="25BLAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210043"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Horror Garage (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Under the Volcano (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Black, Rich</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woliver, Robbie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDD1131F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Business Venture That Is, Well, Scary</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBBIE WOLIVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Woliver, Robbie</byline>
      <dateline>RONKONKOMA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Rich Black, 35, of Ronkonkoma, Long Island, former punk rocker and publisher of nationally distributed music magazine Under the Volcano whose latest publishing venture is Horror Garage; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RICH BLACK lives and works in a dank basement in his father's house in Ronkonkoma. It is a house of horrors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Black, 35, is a former punk rocker-turned-publishing entrepreneur. And his new publication, Horror Garage, is creating a buzz in the world of horror fiction and rock 'n' roll.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RICH BLACK lives and works in a dank basement in his father's house in Ronkonkoma. It is a house of horrors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Black, 35, is a former punk rocker-turned-publishing entrepreneur. And his new publication, Horror Garage, is creating a buzz in the world of horror fiction and rock 'n' roll.</p>
        <p>The former Dairy Barn employee (he worked for the company for 17 years) is a cult hero to the local underground. He has been publishing the nationally distributed music zine Under the Volcano for nine years. He is also ''the front office'' for the band Two-Man Advantage, which mixes punk and hockey themes. But now he is ready to move on to his real passion: horror fiction.</p>
        <p>The well-read, thoughtful writer-editor is not without his horror credentials. In 1997, he won the Tales of Terror writing contest at the University of California at Berkeley for ''He Ain't Heavy,'' a story about two brothers who perform a ritual that causes one of the brothers to become possessed. The possessed brother is then killed ''out of love'' by his sibling. The inspiration? ''I got drunk one night and I started thinking how much I loved my brother,'' Mr. Black recalled with a chuckle. ''I was drunk and crying and I wrote the story.''</p>
        <p>While the themes of horror might seem dark and dangerous, and its close connection to sex, violence and rock 'n' roll a bit seamy, Mr. Black is a man of strict rectitude. He will not accept lucrative phone-sex ads for Under the Volcano, which has a large underage readership and is distributed free on Long Island but is sold nationally. ''I try to be positive,'' Mr. Black said. ''The magazine isn't overly attitudinal, just a bunch of regular guys who like music from punk to ska. My biggest standard is that it is critical and constructive.''</p>
        <p>He has been determined to maintain the magazine's underground credibility. ''We talk about what is really underground, not what the corporate idea of underground is, like Korn,'' he said. ''We're looking to bring culture up, not down.''</p>
        <p>His apartment is a mess, filled with a packrat's minutiae. Until recently, his free time (he now works at a CD manufacturer in Coram) was spent coordinating advertising, distribution and editing particulars for Under the Volcano. So what does a man who has no leisure time do for fun? Create a new project that will take up even more time.</p>
        <p>Although he has been interested in reading and writing horror fiction for a long time, it wasn't until recently when he contacted Paula Guran, who runs an award-winning online newsletter, Dark Echo, that he took this on as a full-time effort.</p>
        <p>''She is a great writer, and the newsletter is very well respected, so I thought I'd throw my ideas for a new magazine by her,'' Mr. Black said. ''We talked it out and it turned out she had the same philosophy as I did. Our tastes were very similar. She's kind of like a soulmate. She has great taste.'' Ms. Guran, of Akron, Ohio, became the magazine's editor.</p>
        <p>''He's a mysterious dude,'' she said of Mr. Black, who dresses in black and refers to himself as somewhat agoraphobic. ''He's been great, very professional, and he sure comes through.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Black is very specific about the style of horror writing that he likes. His preference is fiction with a psychological bent. ''In order for it to work,'' he said, ''you have to have it change your perspective. The 'aha!' forces you to see the light.</p>
        <p>''It is not all about vampires and werewolves. It forces your reality construct to change without relying on lazy traditional scenarios.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Black takes his new horror venture very seriously. He wants it to include ''envelope-pushing dark fiction'' and to cover horror in movies, books and music. It also contains artwork by the genre's top illustrators as well as a CD compilation.</p>
        <p>The first issue includes new fiction, interviews with the film director Wes Craven and the rock band the Misfits, and a track by Alice Cooper on the CD compilation. ''I want to mix cutting-edge horror and trashy rock 'n' roll culture.'' And so the magazine has its subhead: ''sex, death and rock and roll.'' The formula evidently works, because the publication is packed with ads, mostly from record companies.</p>
        <p>He still refuses to take sex ads, although the cover girl for the debut issue is a former Penthouse Pet, Julie Strain. ''There's a difference between fun sex and lurid sex,'' he said. ''There is a difference between Julie in a bikini and ads for sex toys. I don't want to pander.</p>
        <p>''I know I'm oddly moralistic. I'm at war with myself all the time.''</p>
        <p>The first issue of Horror Garage, published last week, has become more successful than Mr. Black anticipated. Booksellers like Hellnotes Internet bookstore are on their second reorder. Hellnotes sent an E-mail message to the distributor saying, ''This is getting crazy, but the magazine is flying out the door.'' The business has increased its order by more than 150 percent. A clerk at None of the Above, a CD store in Centereach, said that the store sold out its initial order in a week.</p>
        <p>''Horror is the rock 'n' roll of fiction,'' Mr. Black said, ''and our magazine is unique, something never offered before. Fun and smart, for readers with an I.Q. one-and-a half times the room temperature.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
