<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Southern Throb In a Northern Heart</title>
    <meta content="25APPL$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Applebome, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4D71331F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2147" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Southern Throb In a Northern Heart</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Applebome column explores reasons why he, a Long Island hick who grew up listening to Beatles and Stones, became country music fan; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I'M not entirely sure how I became a hick. And, to be sure, I don't flatter myself by claiming to be anything close to the genuine item. I grew up on Long Island (O.K., Great Neck), listening to the Beatles and Stones like everyone else. I'm not unfamiliar with classical music; I know my way around Miles Davis and John Coltrane, Sonny Rollins and Thelonious Monk.</p>
        <p>But as my increasingly embarrassed children can attest, when it comes to music these days, I'm alarmingly close to all country all the time. So as I do the usual suburban dad things, with Steve Earle or the Dixie Chicks, George Jones or Emmylou Harris, pedal steel and dobro and creaky Appalachian harmonies being drowned out by the THUMP-THUMP-THUMP of the hip-hop or dance music coming from the Jeep Cherokee stopped at the same light, it's hard not to wonder what's wrong with this picture. I may be a faux hick, but I'm a committed one, and even I can't entirely explain how things worked out this way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I'M not entirely sure how I became a hick. And, to be sure, I don't flatter myself by claiming to be anything close to the genuine item. I grew up on Long Island (O.K., Great Neck), listening to the Beatles and Stones like everyone else. I'm not unfamiliar with classical music; I know my way around Miles Davis and John Coltrane, Sonny Rollins and Thelonious Monk.</p>
        <p>But as my increasingly embarrassed children can attest, when it comes to music these days, I'm alarmingly close to all country all the time. So as I do the usual suburban dad things, with Steve Earle or the Dixie Chicks, George Jones or Emmylou Harris, pedal steel and dobro and creaky Appalachian harmonies being drowned out by the THUMP-THUMP-THUMP of the hip-hop or dance music coming from the Jeep Cherokee stopped at the same light, it's hard not to wonder what's wrong with this picture. I may be a faux hick, but I'm a committed one, and even I can't entirely explain how things worked out this way.</p>
        <p>I remember the first person I ever met who listened to country music. It was my boss at my first newspaper job in Ypsilanti, Mich. Ypsi, like Bakersfield, Calif., was a mangy Southern kingdom in exile, full of expatriates working at the Ford and G.M. plants and dimly lit, famously rowdy bars full of beefy, gimlet-eyed guys named Sonny, Lester and Earl. Finding out my boss listened to country music -- Willie Nelson, Waylon Jennings, Conway Twitty, Dolly Parton -- was like finding out about some really embarrassing aspect of his sex life. I tried to put it out of my mind, but I couldn't. I'd see him walking around the newsroom and look at him as if he were some geek with three heads.</p>
        <p>If I'd thought about the music, instead of the cultural cliches, it wouldn't have seemed so odd. After all, before the Beatles changed the world, the first music I really got excited about was the sound-alike folk music of the 1960's, the Kingston Trio, the Limeliters, the Brothers Four, the Mitchell Trio. They were all preternaturally clean-cut, homogenized creatures of the interregnum between the 50's and the 60's who took the rough edges, twang and grit -- everything that made it matter -- out of acoustic Southern music and sold it for mass consumption. When the Beatles sang ''Act Naturally'' or the Stones sang ''Wild Horses,'' it sounded fine to me, even if I would have gagged at the thought of listening to Buck Owens. The group from that time that most resonated with me, and still does, was the Byrds, built around the ex-folkies Roger McGuinn, David Crosby and Gene Clark and the ex-bluegrass mandolin player Chris Hillman. From the beginning, the group's mix of rock and folk veered off naturally into hard-core country and bluegrass like Porter Wagoner's ''Satisfied Mind,'' which popped up incongruously on the group's ''Turn, Turn, Turn'' album. The Byrds looked and seemed too cool to be carrying the hick gene, so, if anything, their forays into country seemed like a knowing, hip affectation, a cool 60's goof on the inhabitants of the lower orders. Still, there was something there that spoke to richer worlds than the teenage posturing of rock 'n' roll in the rootsy jangle of McGuinn's 12-string, the ragged edges of the harmonies, the exhilarating bluegrass flourishes of Mr. Hillman's ''Time Between'' and ''Girl With No Name'' or the hilarious pop-country hybrid of ''Mr. Spaceman.''</p>
        <p>And then, somewhere along the line, I sort of got it. Like a lot of 60's types, the first real country music I listened to was the Byrds' ''Sweetheart of the Rodeo,'' a brilliant exercise in commercial suicide in which Gram Parsons took the twang from the fringes to the heart of the group's music. It included country classics like the Louvin Brothers' ''Christian Life,'' the country/soul of William Bell's ''You Don't Miss Your Water'' and memorable originals like Parsons's ''Hickory Wind.'' Three decades later, it sounds every bit as soulful and compelling as it did then. Parsons later went on to do inspired and original cosmic cowboy turns with the Flying Burrito Brothers and on his own, burn himself out and become the first alt.country martyr when he died in 1973 at the age of 26. But what the Byrds and Parsons did was to meld the restless energies and alienation of the 60's generation with the unaffected, quintessentially American longing and alienation of country. It was grown-up in a way rock could never be, rebellious in a way Nashville never wanted to be and true to something both ancient and contemporary in the American experience. Though I didn't think of it that way at the time, it was both musically and spiritually a bridge from the self-indulgent elitism of the 60's to the real world and a reminder of how fine the line was between the approved lefty music and politics of Woody Guthrie and the scorned righty music and politics of Merle Haggard.</p>
        <p>I moved to Texas in the mid-70's, picking up a stiff dose of the woozy progressive country of Jerry Jeff Walker and Ray Wylie Hubbard, the rockabilly of Joe Ely and the prairie heartache of Willie Nelson, and then to Atlanta, where learning a little about Nashville seemed a part of my job, covering the South for The New York Times. It was the time of country's biggest commercial breakthrough, with Garth Brooks selling more records than anyone in America. For a while Nashville seemed to capture, for better or worse, the moment -- the Reagan-Bush-era triumph of heartland culture over coastal culture -- much as Motown captured its moment in the 1960's. Working on a book about how much the country had been influenced by the South, I hung out in Nashville for a week or so and then drove across Mississippi, from the casinos of the Delta to the casinos of the Gulf Coast, living mostly on bottled water and Sun chips.</p>
        <p>My background music was the country smorgasbord I'd picked up in Nashville -- the pop-country of Faith Hill before she went all pop and became Shania Twain's rival for Country Super Babe; the honky-tonk of David Ball; a rockabilly album no one else seems to have heard by James House; the plaintive, literate Appalachian folk of Iris DeMent; a terrific Merle Haggard tribute album, and my favorite at the time, the cranky, Okie country rock of the Tractors. A lot of it was wretched, like Tim McGraw, Clay Walker, John Michael Montgomery and the prefabricated Nashville hunks in hats on the radio, the 90's version of the sound-alike folk acts of the 60's. But it almost didn't matter. I drove along Highway 61 in the 100-degree heat, throwing the empty water bottles in the back seat of my rental car, wondering if I'd ever have so much fun again. After that, for the first time in my life, I reflexively searched for the country station on the radio and headed straight for the country section of the record store. I was hooked.</p>
        <p>For a while I thought of my listening habits as a transitory eccentricity I'd soon outgrow. I thought it would end when I finished my book, and then when I moved back to New York a few years later. But for now, it feels like a part of the post-genetic code you pick up as you live your life. Every now and then the frequency fades out, like a too-distant radio signal, the twang just grates, and I listen mostly to jazz. But then, invariably, the signal locks back in, and I'm back to the off-the-reservation alternative country, whatever that is, of Steve Earle, Buddy Miller or Robbie Fulks or grand masters like George Jones. It's pretty eclectic fare, not the mass-produced Nashville of the radio, but one part Byrds and the Band, one part Hank Williams and Merle Haggard -- pretty much the tastes of someone who came to country through Gram Parsons, not Loretta Lynn. It's a suspect pedigree, but it's all I've got.</p>
        <p>It's hard not to see my immersion in twang as a waste of limited mental disc capacity. Here I find myself periodically forgetting familiar phone numbers and the names of people I work with, and my head is full of useless knowledge about which obscure CD's Gurf Morlux played guitar on. But maybe I shouldn't be surprised. There's not much out there for grownups to listen to. Hip-hop? Hyper-emoting tabloid divas? Horrible thrashing post-Nirvana teenage rock? Yuck. I guess we all get to choose our turf in the new Balkanized music market, and the alt.country diaspora is mine.</p>
        <p>There are probably generic and personal reasons for my predilection toward twang. Country has traditionally been music for middle-aged adults with grown-up bruises and scars. When Pete Townshend sang, ''Hope I die before I get old,'' he was mouthing the primal trope of music meant to be of, by and for kids. It no longer strikes me -- and I assume him -- as such a swell idea. When George Jones sings, ''I've had choices/ Since the day that I was born/ There were voices that told me right from wrong/ If I had listened, I wouldn't be here today/ living and dying with the choices I made,'' it rings true. I guess I could listen to Stephen Sondheim, who writes pretty smart songs about adults, too, but for now I'll stick with George Jones.</p>
        <p>And one of the triumphs of the contemporary roots/alternative-country music is to mix the frazzled, dog-eared wisdom of country with an edgy, Kerouacian energy that has made this stuff vaguely -- sigh -- hip. After all, Steve Earle, the godfather of neo-twang, was featured along with the litterateurs at the New Yorker's celebration of its 75th anniversary last month. And even the name of his new album, ''Transcendental Blues,'' bespeaks a sensibility a tad less rustic than, say, Ernest Tubb or Lefty Frizzell.</p>
        <p>IN addition, back here in the land of the enlightened, I guess I miss my time in the South. I think sometimes of an article the Texas writer Larry L. King wrote in a 1975 special issue of The Atlantic Monthly devoted entirely to the state. He reminisced about the mythic Texas of his youth, and he paid homage to an unspoiled stretch of desolate West Texas highway. Driving there, he wrote, he found himself in a mental time warp, back in Old Texas ''under a high sky where all things are again possible and the wind blows free.'' He wrote of putting the heavy spurs to his trusty Hertz or Avis steed, and flying lickety-split down the road, ''scattering roadside gravel like bursts of buckshot.''</p>
        <p>It sounds a lot like my highway satori in Mississippi. I spent much of my life wandering out to places like Wink, Alpine and Marfa, Tex., but now I'm one of the drones on the train platform, catching the 7:48 each morning from Chappaqua. Ferrying the kids around over the weekend or before school, I no longer even control the music in the car. My daughter, who for a time I brainwashed into thinking that rock 'n' roll was Mary Chapin Carpenter singing ''I Feel Lucky,'' is still ecumenical enough to appreciate the Dixie Chicks but now insists on the radio station Z-100, which means I hear Britney Spears and 'N Sync more than I hear Steve Earle. My son wants to listen to Imus in the morning, and if we're taking one of his friends along somewhere he issues a stern warning about not embarrassing him by playing any of ''that stuff'' in public. My wife's from the South, but she's anti-twang,  too. And even if suburban dads escaped to the neighborhood bar at night, I doubt there's one anywhere nearby with Patsy Cline or Ray Price, Vince Gill or George Strait on the jukebox, so that's no option either.</p>
        <p>So it's a little lonely up here, but I do my best. Scattering roadside gravel like buckshot isn't quite my thing. But when I'm alone in my trusty old Volvo, tooling around the dusty byways of Westchester County from the A&amp;P to the BJ's, from the Home Depot to the Old Navy, I crank up my twang, imagine myself under a high sky where all things are possible and go flying lickety-split down the road.</p>
        <p>MUSIC Peter Applebome, a deputy metropolitan editor of The New York Times, is the author of ''Dixie Rising: How the South Is Shaping American Values, Politics and Culture.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Peter Applebome, a deputy metropolitan editor of The New York Times, is the author of ''Dixie Rising: How the South Is Shaping American Values, Politics and Culture.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
