<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Favorites Have Feast In Tuneup for the Trials</title>
    <meta content="25TRAC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E5DD1530F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1046" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Favorites Have Feast In Tuneup for the Trials</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <dateline>EUGENE, Ore., June 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Michael Johnson crossed the finish line at 400 meters, the Hayward Field scoreboard registered 43.16 seconds, two-hundredths of a second below his world record. An excited murmur flashed like static electricity through the crowd. But the scoreboard was wrong. The posted time was like a word passed from student to student in the old classroom game until it bore no resemblance to what was actually said.</p>
        <p>Quickly, the time was adjusted to 43.92 seconds, not a record but still the fastest time in the world this year. It was that kind of beautiful, azure, windy afternoon at the Prefontaine Classic, producing nothing unprecedented but leaving the track and field world with intriguing possibility as the Olympics approach in Sydney, Australia, in September.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Michael Johnson crossed the finish line at 400 meters, the Hayward Field scoreboard registered 43.16 seconds, two-hundredths of a second below his world record. An excited murmur flashed like static electricity through the crowd. But the scoreboard was wrong. The posted time was like a word passed from student to student in the old classroom game until it bore no resemblance to what was actually said.</p>
        <p>Quickly, the time was adjusted to 43.92 seconds, not a record but still the fastest time in the world this year. It was that kind of beautiful, azure, windy afternoon at the Prefontaine Classic, producing nothing unprecedented but leaving the track and field world with intriguing possibility as the Olympics approach in Sydney, Australia, in September.</p>
        <p>Gabriela Szabo of Romania posted the world's best time of the year in the women's 1,500 meters, making 20 meters down the homestretch of the metric mile to catch Suzy Favor Hamilton at the tape in 4 minutes 0.73 seconds. The world champion Maurice Greene struggled in the curve but recovered to win a controlled victory in the 200 meters in a wind-aided 19.93 seconds. Marion Jones added another foot to her seasonal best in the long jump with a leap of 22 feet 10 1/2 inches, the fourth longest in the world this year. Her jumping remains erratic, but her improved aggressiveness on the runway has firmly restored her among the Olympic medal candidates.</p>
        <p>Less encouraging was her winning time at 100 meters. Wearing a hooded suit that covered her from head to toe and was supposed to make her more aerodynamic, Jones ran a wind-aided 10.93, far slower than the 10.84 she ran last month in Japan.</p>
        <p>Gail Devers, the two-time Olympic champion at 100 meters, made her season debut in her other specialty, the 100-meter hurdles, and posted the second-fastest time in the world at 12.64 seconds. She has been slowed by chronic injury through the years, and this season aches in her hamstring and Achilles' tendon had shelved her for much of the last seven weeks. But she is a three-time world champion in the hurdles and, with the Olympic trials only a month away, she decided it was time to run.</p>
        <p>Even with all the elite American athletes, the meet was nearly stolen by a high school runner, Don Sage of Elmhurst, Ill., who ran the fastest schoolboy mile in 33 years with a time of 4:00.29. Sage, 18, a graduate of York High School who will attend Stanford in the fall, ran splits of 58.8, 1:57.8 and 2:59.2 and appeared poised to become the first American high schooler to break four minutes since Marty Liquori in 1967.</p>
        <p>He shaved four seconds off his personal best and very nearly caught Gabe Jennings, the collegiate champion from Stanford, but Sage could not quite break four minutes as the crowd of 12,508 drew him along with expectant clapping.</p>
        <p>''I think I probably went out a little too fast, but I'm happy,'' he said. ''I could feel the energy of the crowd. It was great.''</p>
        <p>The afternoon's other riveting moment came in the women's 1,500 meters. Szabo, the Olympic silver medalist in 1996, was unbeaten at any distance since August 1998, but Favor Hamilton's career is resurgent after Achilles' tendons problems have dissipated. The two women share the same agent, who told Favor Hamilton that Szabo did not want to push the pace. Feeling obligated to run a fast time, Favor Hamilton went to the lead and began pulling away in the final backstretch. The gap reached 20 meters in the last turn, but Szabo has a blistering kick and drew ahead in the final steps as Favor Hamilton crashed to the track in 4:00.79.</p>
        <p>''I train for the finish,'' Szabo said. ''I am very happy.''</p>
        <p>Johnson, the world record-holder and Olympic champion at 200 and 400 meters, has no real threat in the 400. He grew worried when he felt a twinge in his previously injured left thigh at about 100 meters, but the pain subsided and he won easily. Dale Smith, his physical therapist, said there was no concern about a possible injury to the leg.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to run under 44 seconds and not just sneak under it,'' Johnson said.</p>
        <p>Jones won with her first long jump, fouling twice later. She still does not have a reliable technique and her landings are awkward, but she has improved by nearly two and a half feet in the last month as she prepares to try to win five Olympic gold medals. On Friday she will compete in Rome against Fiona May of Italy, this current world leader.</p>
        <p>''I've built up some confidence,'' Jones said. ''It's not the prettiest thing in the world, but who cares.''</p>
        <p>Today's meet served as a tempting appetizer for the Olympic trials, at which Johnson and Greene will meet at 200 meters. They have raced once, at this meet in 1998, and Greene won. Greene's time of 19.93 seconds today was within a hundredth of a second of the fastest sea-level time that Johnson has posted since setting a world record of 19.32 at the 1996 Atlanta Olympics.</p>
        <p>The 200 final at the trials is July 23, Greene's 26th birthday. He is the world's fastest man at 100 meters, but he also has an excitable personality. His coach, John Smith, and his agent, Emanuel Hudson, have cautioned Greene to remember that the important 200-meter race will come at the Olympics and that it could be costly emotionally and physically to run too fast too soon.</p>
        <p>''I told Maurice, 'Give Michael a gift for your birthday; don't try to beat him,' '' Hudson said, only half-jokingly.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
