<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Constant Connection In a Sea Of Choppy Currents</title>
    <meta content="08OSBY$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="JAZZ FESTIVAL REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bell Atlantic Jazz Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Osby, Greg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratliff, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7DA123FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="495" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Constant Connection In a Sea Of Choppy Currents</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Ratliff reviews alto saxophonist Greg Osby and his band performing at Knitting Factory as part of Bell Atlantic Jazz Festival; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was clear from the beginning of Greg Osby's set on Tuesday night at the Knitting Factory that he had whipped a new rhythm section into shape. Mr. Osby, the alto saxophonist, has been touring with Vashon Johnson and Derek Philips on bass and drums -- it's the fifth rhythm section New York audiences have seen in his band in four years -- and after about a dozen performances across the country they've achieved a particular rhythmic feel that seems to suit him. There's always a steady underlying pulse; Mr. Osby takes his tempos seriously. But the rhythm's emphases are jagged, and bass and drums keep up a flow of rhythmic ornamentation.</p>
        <p>This band leader likes to keep things bubbling and interactive; soloists in his music are given their moments of prominence, but they're navigating choppy currents so that a listener is forced to listen to the whole group instead of just the main improviser. In performance, Mr. Osby flows pieces together, sometimes staying with a tune only briefly. And for the last five years or so, his vision has been so commanding that no matter who's holding down the rhythm, he has had one of the freshest, most exciting groups in jazz.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was clear from the beginning of Greg Osby's set on Tuesday night at the Knitting Factory that he had whipped a new rhythm section into shape. Mr. Osby, the alto saxophonist, has been touring with Vashon Johnson and Derek Philips on bass and drums -- it's the fifth rhythm section New York audiences have seen in his band in four years -- and after about a dozen performances across the country they've achieved a particular rhythmic feel that seems to suit him. There's always a steady underlying pulse; Mr. Osby takes his tempos seriously. But the rhythm's emphases are jagged, and bass and drums keep up a flow of rhythmic ornamentation.</p>
        <p>This band leader likes to keep things bubbling and interactive; soloists in his music are given their moments of prominence, but they're navigating choppy currents so that a listener is forced to listen to the whole group instead of just the main improviser. In performance, Mr. Osby flows pieces together, sometimes staying with a tune only briefly. And for the last five years or so, his vision has been so commanding that no matter who's holding down the rhythm, he has had one of the freshest, most exciting groups in jazz.</p>
        <p>The song list of Tuesday night's set, part of the Bell Atlantic Jazz Festival, was still undetermined when the musicians started playing; as they worked, Mr. Osby provided segues by hinting at the next tune's  motif. Those tunes came to include opaque versions of the standards ''Indiana'' and ''I Didn't Know About You,'' as well as four of Mr. Osby's own pieces and one by his pianist, Jason Moran. For a few numbers, the guitarist Liberty Ellman joined the band, improvising energetically with a more classical sense of jazz harmony. But the core of the performance was the connection between band leader and pianist. Both are oriented toward the rhythmically unexpected, so that Mr. Moran might chord slowly and deliberately through an uptempo tune, and Mr. Osby might fire out brisk, declarative webs of notes in a ballad.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moran filled his playing with abstruse-harmony chords, sweet chords, intuitive sprinkles of dissonant notes, two-handed restorations of the theme. It's a dense, cumulative approach to the piano, fusing entire schools of thought about how to play jazz.</p>
        <p>Mr. Osby has his own system of phrasing, informed by bebop's lashing lines but turned inside out. It comes across the way some foreign languages do to American ears, with answers sounding like questions.</p>
        <p>Though both musicians had solos that were pretty close to extraordinary, it was the constant flow of communication between them that powered the set. And it doesn't take them very long anymore to indicate where they want to go: within five minutes of playing, the band had achieved the floating, hurtling group sound that all jazz audiences are looking for.</p>
        <p>JAZZ FESTIVAL REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
