<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leaders From Other Professions Reshape America's Schools, From Top to Bottom</title>
    <meta content="08SCHO$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205752"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">School Administration and Community Role</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewin, Tamar</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">School Administration and Community Role</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E1D9133FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2024" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leaders From Other Professions Reshape America's Schools, From Top to Bottom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TAMAR LEWIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewin, Tamar</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO, June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New breed of high-profile outsiders are taking over big-city school districts; urban districts are turning to law, business, government and military for new leadership and outside perspective; many of newcomers view leading school system as era's biggest public service challenge; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alan D. Bersin, superintendent of the San Diego schools, is talking tough with 35 student teachers: ''Our reading levels, by and large, are abysmal,'' he tells them. The dropout rate is huge, he says, and he has laid off 600 paraprofessionals because ''they have added virtually nothing to student achievement.''</p>
        <p>Since Mr. Bersin became superintendent two years ago, he has been arguing this case for a sweeping campaign to reshape the schools, with prescribed blocks of time for teaching literacy, and constant teacher training in the methods to be used.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alan D. Bersin, superintendent of the San Diego schools, is talking tough with 35 student teachers: ''Our reading levels, by and large, are abysmal,'' he tells them. The dropout rate is huge, he says, and he has laid off 600 paraprofessionals because ''they have added virtually nothing to student achievement.''</p>
        <p>Since Mr. Bersin became superintendent two years ago, he has been arguing this case for a sweeping campaign to reshape the schools, with prescribed blocks of time for teaching literacy, and constant teacher training in the methods to be used.</p>
        <p>The teachers' union objects to Mr. Bersin's approach, and his reform plan squeaked through the school board on a 3-to-2 vote in March, but his not being an educator is no longer much of an issue. Mr. Bersin is the former United States attorney for southern California, one of the first of a new breed of high-profile outsiders taking over big-city school districts.</p>
        <p>Last month, Harold O. Levy, a corporate lawyer, was chosen to lead the New York City school system, the nation's largest. They are the first non-educators ever chosen for those jobs.</p>
        <p>[On Tuesday, the Los Angeles board of education named Roy Romer, the former Colorado governor, as its new superintendent.]</p>
        <p>Other urban districts, too, have turned to  law, business, government and the military for new leadership and an outside perspective. For many of these newcomers -- often the children of immigrants who view their families' success as a direct result of public schooling -- education is the era's biggest challenge, and leading a school system is today's Everest of public service.</p>
        <p>''Public education is what distinguishes this country, both vertically, in history, and horizontally, from other societies around the world,'' Mr. Bersin said. ''For the first time, there is a real belief in this country that every child has the right to a quality education. This is the most important challenge San Diego faces. It gives reality to what is otherwise the empty myth that in this country, you can do anything you want to do.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy, in an effort to recruit teachers to the cause, said recently, ''Urban education is the equivalent of the Peace Corps of the 60's or the civil rights movement of the 50's.''</p>
        <p>Seattle has had two nontraditional superintendents in a row, one from the military, one from the private sector. Houston's superintendent is a former school board member; Chicago's a former city budget director; Kansas City's a former top federal aviation official.</p>
        <p>''These are all very smart, very talented individuals who have a clear idea of where they're going, and how to get there,'' said Michael Casserly, executive director of the Council of Great City Schools. ''What's not clear yet is whether they can produce the same academic gains as a skilled educator.''</p>
        <p>But experts in educational administration say it is precisely the sense that educators have failed the schools -- and that outsiders may have an edge in turning them around -- that is driving the trend toward nontraditional superintendents.</p>
        <p>''School districts need to change how they conduct themselves if we are to improve student achievement, and that kind of change does not usually come from those inside the system,'' said Mr. Bersin, a product of the New York City public schools.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bersin was San Diego's chief federal law enforcement officer when he was given the $165,000-a-year job of heading the nation's eighth-largest urban school district, which has 145,000 students. Now he is steeped in the language of education, talking passionately about creating a community of learners, or about children who score in the bottom quartile on the SAT 9.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't take long to understand the issues, to see the extraordinary talent of many of the people inside the system, and the ways the system has functioned as an obstacle to their growth,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Until the 1990's, it was almost unthinkable to choose a big-city superintendent from outside education. Traditionally, they were former teachers who became principals and then superintendents.</p>
        <p>Many of the nontraditional superintendents split the responsibilities of leading their districts, handling school board meetings, bond issues, union matters and politics themselves, but leaving issues of pedagogy to a deputy with educational credentials.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bersin turned to Anthony Alvarado, a New York City educator best known for his success in raising student achievement and creating innovative schools in two Manhattan districts. Mr. Alvarado's long history in New York included a difficult chapter: in 1984, his year as chancellor ended with his resignation amid accusations of personal financial irregularities.</p>
        <p>In San Diego, he is the chancellor of instruction, and head of the district's new Institute for Learning -- and, he said, delighted to be able to focus on raising the quality of instruction. Mr. Alvarado is not revered in San Diego, as he was in New York. He knows that many here see him as a brash outsider imposing heavy-handed changes on a system he does not know. But, he argues, his changes grow out of solid research, not personal whim.</p>
        <p>''We have lots of evidence about what helps kids learn,'' Mr. Alvarado said. ''We know literacy and math are the gatekeeper skills that give kids access to academic success for the rest of their lives. We know summer school helps reduce the learning loss that occurs when poor kids are out of school for a long time. It's not Tony Alvarado doing summer school, it's what works.</p>
        <p>''If you're a surgeon, visiting hospitals in different cities, there's a stunning similarity in the tools, the length of the incision, the mortality rate,'' he said. ''When we started, the elementary programs here had 200 reading programs, sometimes four or five different programs in the same school. And what all these programs generated was only 41 percent of the kids reading at or above grade level.''</p>
        <p>The commitment to systemic change is profound, according to Kimiko Fukuda, a 33-year veteran of the system who is the only one of the old assistant superintendents to remain in the new regime as an ''instructional leader,'' charged with breaking down the old system in which teachers generally went into their classrooms, closed the doors and used whatever instructional methods they chose.</p>
        <p>''I'd read Alvarado's work, and I understood the problem of every teacher being in private practice, almost an independent contractor,'' she said. ''But when I tried to change things as an assistant superintendent, it didn't have much impact because it was voluntary and the union didn't like it. You really can't make this kind of change unless it's from the top, and it covers everybody.''</p>
        <p>Now, each principal is required to spend two hours a day in classrooms helping teachers improve their work. Peer coaches in the schools help with teaching methods, too, and principals attend weekly training sessions on literacy techniques such as ''guided reading'' and ''shared reading.''</p>
        <p>Some principals love it.</p>
        <p>At Central Elementary School, a year-round school with 1,200 mostly Hispanic children crammed into a facility built for 800, Elaine Arm, the principal, praises Mr. Bersin's educational overhaul.</p>
        <p>''I've been reborn,'' she says. ''I feel powerful. I'm not just an administrator now; I'm an instructional leader; I'm in classrooms every day and I love it. There is real focus. We know what we are supposed to do, and why. It's an enormous change, all because of this superintendent.''</p>
        <p>If something as abstract as school reform can be made visible, Mr. Bersin's version is on view on the hallway bulletin boards, where sweetly childish writings -- ''I like when the frog got the peach down.'' -- are posted beneath the state learning standard that prompted the assignment.</p>
        <p>And it is visible as the fourth graders write book essays following a ''rubric'' that tells them the first paragraph should contain the title, author and theme, the second should compare the main characters, and the third should compare the problems they faced and the solutions they reached.</p>
        <p>This approach is not universally accepted. Many San Diego educators say the reforms impinge on their spontaneity and overemphasize literacy, neglecting social studies and science.</p>
        <p>''The teacher I work with is mostly hoping this will pass,'' said one of the student teachers Mr. Bersin was addressing. ''Her attitude is, 'I've been teaching for 10 years, and what the heck is guided reading?' She doesn't think the principal who's supposed to be leading it understands all this new stuff any better than she does.''</p>
        <p>The student teachers seem energized by Mr. Bersin's approach, but wary, too.</p>
        <p>''It's change, and it makes people nervous,'' said Les Henderson, who expects teacher certification next month. ''We're talking about institutionalizing education, standardizing things, and I'm on the fence about it.''</p>
        <p>Two years into Mr. Bersin's reign, some local educators question how long he can talk about the district's poor performance without being held responsible for it.</p>
        <p>''It takes three to five years to bring real change,'' said Bruce S. Cooper, a professor of educational administration at Fordham University. ''The problem is that large districts are so unmanageable and unstable that the average superintendent only lasts 2 1/2 years.''</p>
        <p>If anyone can stay the course, it may be Mr. Bersin, a Brooklyn native with an easy charm, a sharp mind, and a golden resume: Phi Beta Kappa at Harvard, All Ivy and All-East Football Teams, and Rhodes Scholar at Oxford, where he overlapped a year with Bill Clinton, and then, like the president, moved on to Yale Law School.</p>
        <p>After graduation he headed west, first as special counsel to the Los Angeles Police Commission, then handling commercial litigation at Munger, Tolles &amp; Olson. He moved to San Diego for a sabbatical teaching law school in 1992, shortly after the birth of his second daughter, now a second grader in the district. Mr. Bersin's oldest daughter is at Harvard, and his youngest is in kindergarten.</p>
        <p>''It shows you what a Republican town San Diego is that three weeks after I got here, I was the head of Clinton for President,'' Mr. Bersin said.</p>
        <p>A year later, President Clinton appointed him the U.S. attorney, and starting in 1995, he also served as Attorney General Janet Reno's border czar. Faced with the intractable problems of the border -- drug trafficking and illegal immigration -- he gained attention by reframing the issues in terms of public safety, making it possible to work with Mexico toward some common goals.</p>
        <p>These days, Mr. Bersin keeps a politician's schedule: he goes from the student teachers' visit to throwing the first ball at a San Diego Padres baseball game, from a visit to Central Elementary to teaching an eighth grade history class at Correia Middle School, and on to a staff meeting on portfolio assessment at Curie Elementary.</p>
        <p>He talks with every teacher, every administrator, asking lots of questions, listening hard and saying how much he values their ideas. He stops to ask a custodian how things are going. ''We've made everyone in the system, the bus drivers, everyone, understand that their job is to support learning in the classroom,'' Mr. Bersin said.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Clinton, he has prodigious energy, and seems to take pleasure in all the public contact. But he is not, he said, headed for political office.</p>
        <p>''If I'd wanted elective office, I'd have stayed in the U.S. attorney's office, putting bad guys in jail, which plays to the public,'' he said. ''I'm in a position to choose what I do and where I can make a difference. And this is the most important challenge.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
