<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campaigns Quickly Stake Their Ground</title>
    <meta content="08JERS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205688"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRIMARY IN NEW JERSEY: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franks, Robert D (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E2DD133FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campaigns Quickly Stake Their Ground</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, June 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses campaign strategy of Repr Robert D Franks, Republican, and his Democratic opponent Jon S Corzine in upcoming election for US Senate from New Jersey (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert D. Franks was not halfway through his victory speech early this morning when he began ripping into Jon S. Corzine, his opponent in the New Jersey Senate race, as a dangerously out-of-touch spendthrift.</p>
        <p>The race to control the wide middle of New Jersey politics began even before all the votes were counted in Tuesday's primary, which left Mr. Franks as the apparent Republican nominee. And Mr. Franks's swift attack raised a question that he clearly hoped would define the race: Can he succeed in turning the liberal proposals and record-setting spending that won Mr. Corzine the Democratic nomination into liabilities big enough to keep Mr. Corzine from winning the general election?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Robert D. Franks was not halfway through his victory speech early this morning when he began ripping into Jon S. Corzine, his opponent in the New Jersey Senate race, as a dangerously out-of-touch spendthrift.</p>
        <p>The race to control the wide middle of New Jersey politics began even before all the votes were counted in Tuesday's primary, which left Mr. Franks as the apparent Republican nominee. And Mr. Franks's swift attack raised a question that he clearly hoped would define the race: Can he succeed in turning the liberal proposals and record-setting spending that won Mr. Corzine the Democratic nomination into liabilities big enough to keep Mr. Corzine from winning the general election?</p>
        <p>''What's dangerous about Jon Corzine isn't the fact that he has spent tens of millions of his own money,'' Mr. Franks said. ''What's really dangerous is the prospect of Jon Corzine sitting in the United States Senate where he will have the power to spend your money.''</p>
        <p>In giving his own acceptance speech, Mr. Corzine, emotional and exhausted after his overwhelming but hard-won victory over former Gov. Jim Florio, seemed to be thinking more about how soon he would be able to take a vacation than about his next opponent. But his advisers suggested today that Mr. Corzine, the former co-chairman of Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company, would soon begin pointing to his Wall Street background as evidence that, for all his expansive ideas, he would understand as well as any lawmaker the importance of fiscal moderation.</p>
        <p>''Jon Corzine is a can-do, pro-jobs Democrat who understands the new economy,'' said Steven Goldstein, a top official in the Corzine campaign. ''He's running against a lifelong politician who's never had any real- world experience. And New Jersey, whether it's Frank Lautenberg or Bill Bradley, likes real-world experience in its leaders.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, aides to Mr. Corzine outlined a plan to depict Mr. Franks, who was elected to Congress in 1992, as an ideological soul mate of former  Speaker Newt Gingrich, a strategy used most successfully by President Clinton in his 1996 campaign against Senator Bob Dole, and by Senator Robert G. Torricelli in his race the same year against Representative Richard A. Zimmer.</p>
        <p>''The Franks-Gingrich agenda is hopelessly out of touch with New Jersey,'' Mr. Goldstein said. ''Bob Franks can't possibly be moderate when he voted for the Contract With America.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine is by no means the only candidate still using this ploy. In the Senate race in New York, Hillary Rodham Clinton has also tried to link her Republican rival, Representative Rick A. Lazio, to Mr. Gingrich. But it remains unclear how potent a weapon that will be more than a year after Mr. Gingrich's exit from the political stage.</p>
        <p>Charlie Smith, an aide to Mr. Franks, made clear that he would not be intimidated by Mr. Corzine's stated willingness to spend whatever it takes to win the Senate race, which he demonstrated by spending close to $35 million in the primary.</p>
        <p>''We believe we'll have the financial wherewithal to compete, with a message that's much more in tune with New Jersey's voters than Jon Corzine is with his immense wealth,'' Mr. Smith said. ''And others, around New Jersey and in Washington, will come to the same conclusion.''</p>
        <p>He added that $10 million was a decent rule-of-thumb estimate for what an effective fall campaign could cost.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Republican officials in Washington, whose help Mr. Franks will sorely need, expressed glee today at the prospect of helping him take on Mr. Corzine, whose advocacy for ambitious government programs, against the death penalty, and for affirmative action, gun control and gay rights made his campaign as left-leaning as any successful Senate primary bid in memory.</p>
        <p>''Congressman Franks is an accomplished legislator and an outstanding candidate, while all Corzine has is rich liberal guilt,'' said Steven Law, executive director of the National Republican Senatorial Committee. ''We believe in this race because Bob Franks has New Jersey common-sense values, while on the other hand, if Corzine goes any more to the left, he'll be in Pennsylvania.''</p>
        <p>Just how much more Mr. Corzine will spend in the fall campaign was the subject of much speculation today. His advisers have said they long believed that a primary campaign against Mr. Florio would be much more difficult and costly than a general election. And after an unprecedented 12-week saturation of the New York and Philadelphia television stations with Mr. Corzine's image in gauzy commercials, he enters the race with Mr. Franks, who is little known outside of his district except among Republican stalwarts, holding an incumbent's name-recognition advantage.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Franks's decision to focus on Mr. Corzine's spending was striking not only because he picked right up where Mr. Florio left off, vowing to make campaign finance reform a central issue, but because Mr. Florio's efforts in that regard had won him newspaper endorsements but failed to sway most Democratic voters. Mr. Goldstein also said that Mr. Franks was vulnerable to attack for his own acceptance of special-interest contributions.</p>
        <p>The demand among Democrats for Mr. Corzine to add to his spending record was sure to heighten with his victory Tuesday, however. After donating hundreds of thousands of dollars to county party organizations in the months leading up to the primary, Democratic officials said, Mr. Corzine now may be pressed similarly to help bankroll the party's coordinated campaign -- the grass-roots organizing efforts in which the party's presidential, Senate and Congressional candidates pool their resources and avoid putting out conflicting messages.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Vice President Al Gore, who has called New Jersey a must-win state for his presidential campaign, is expected to visit Trenton on Monday for a town hall meeting-type television show. And an official in Mr. Gore's New Jersey campaign said today that Mr. Gore also hoped to meet during his trip with Mr. Florio, Mr. Corzine and other Democratic leaders in an effort to  halt the divisive infighting between Mr. Florio's followers in South Jersey and Mr. Corzine's backers in the north.</p>
        <p>PRIMARY IN NEW JERSEY: THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
