<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foundation For the Joy Of Song And Life</title>
    <meta content="08GARL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205621"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Riverside Festival Singers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccartney, Linda (1942-98)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozinn, Allan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cha-Pyo, Helen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tavener, John (Sir)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccartney, Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DD123FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foundation For the Joy Of Song And Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Allan Kozinn reviews A Garland for Linda, cycle of choral works written by various British composers in memory of Linda McCartney, as performed by Riverside Festival Singers under direction of Helen Cha-Pyo at Riverside Church; composers include John Tavener and Paul McCartney (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After Paul McCartney's wife, Linda, died of breast cancer in 1998, Stephen Connock, a British business executive, approached him with a project that would be a memorial as well as the start of a charitable foundation. The foundation, called the Garland Appeal, would raise money for cancer research and would also support British music.</p>
        <p>That may seem an odd stretch, but for Mr. Connock, who has liver and bowel cancer, the connection is in what he regards as music's restorative power.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After Paul McCartney's wife, Linda, died of breast cancer in 1998, Stephen Connock, a British business executive, approached him with a project that would be a memorial as well as the start of a charitable foundation. The foundation, called the Garland Appeal, would raise money for cancer research and would also support British music.</p>
        <p>That may seem an odd stretch, but for Mr. Connock, who has liver and bowel cancer, the connection is in what he regards as music's restorative power.</p>
        <p>Using the 1953 ''A Garland for the Queen'' (assembled to celebrate the coronation of Queen Elizabeth) as a model, Mr. Connock proposed asking a group of British composers to provide short choral works for a new cycle, ''A Garland for Linda.'' Sir Paul agreed to lend his name to the project, and now that he is writing classical pieces, he decided to supply a work of his own, to sit beside the contributions of John Tavener, Judith Bingham, John Rutter, David Matthews, Roxanna Panufnik, Michael Berkeley, Giles Swayne and  Richard Rodney Bennett.</p>
        <p>The cycle was performed in England last year, and was released on disc by EMI. It had its American premiere at the Riverside Church on Saturday evening, as the second half of a concert that also included two other Tavener works, four Vaughan Williams settings, and a treacly medley of Lennon-McCartney songs arranged for chorus by Peter Broadbent.</p>
        <p>For the occasion, Helen Cha-Pyo, the associate director of music at the church, conducted the Riverside Festival Singers, a well-polished 28-voice choir that sang with both the robustness demanded by the Vaughan Williams works, including his contrapuntal and harmonically updated arrangement of ''Greensleeves,'' and the suppleness required by Sir John's gentle hymns.</p>
        <p>The ''Garland'' cycle was a more sober affair. Most of the works touched either directly or allegorically on illness, the memory of a lost past, farewells or faith, but a current of hope and acceptance runs through them. The Tavener work, ''Prayer for the Healing of the Sick,'' opened the cycle with a touching serenity. Sir Paul's ''Nova,'' which uses his own text, is a dialogue with God, starting with the plaintive questions ''Are you there?'' and ''Are you hiding?'' and ending with a poetic evocation of God's presence in the small details of nature that one takes for granted. The piece had a naive charm, both in its text and in the English Renaissance melodic accent of its closing verses.</p>
        <p>Particularly striking among the ''Garland'' works were ''The Doorway of Dawn'' a setting of a short Pima Indian poem by Mr. Matthews in which a melismatic solo tenor line gives way to a lovely choral harmonization, and Ms. Panufnik's ''I dream'd,'' an alluringly chromatic Tennyson setting. Ms. Bingham supplied her own text for ''Water Lilies,'' and matched its haunting imagery with musical effects that created a dreamlike atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rutter's ''Musica Dei donum'' is a smooth-flowing celebration of music as a gift of God, set in Latin and with a flute obbligato. Mr. Swayne also chose a Latin text, ''Planctus Cygni'' (''The Swan's Lament''), and presented it in a colorful setting with shimmering lines for flute and cello. Mr. Berkeley's brief ''Farewell,'' on his own text, has the melodic contours of a pop song and the gentleness of a lullaby. Sir Richard's contribution, ''A Good-Night,'' uses more elevated harmonic techniques for a similar purpose in a setting of a 17th-century poem by Francis Quarles.</p>
        <p>Demarre McGill and Pittnary Shin were the excellent flute and cello soloists.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
