<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Support Sought On Reviving Spanish-Dutch Phone Merger</title>
    <meta content="Y08TELE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205658"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Netherlands</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Telefonica Sa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Royal Kpn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Villalonga, Juan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0D8123FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Support Sought On Reviving Spanish-Dutch Phone Merger</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Executives say Telefonica chairman Juan Villalonga is seeking to rally support among board members to revive merger talks with Dutch telephone operator Royal KPN; board's recent failure to approve $58 billion merger sought by Villalonga amid pressure from Spanish government and local banks noted; opponents argued against deal in part because Dutch government would be biggest shareholder in merged company; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Juan Villalonga, the chairman of Telefonica, the Spanish telecommunications company, has been trying to rally support among company board members to revive merger talks with the Dutch telephone operator Royal KPN, executives close to Telefonica said today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Villalonga was embarrassed last month when the board, succumbing to political pressure from the Spanish government and local banks, failed to approve a $58 billion merger with KPN that Mr. Villalonga had sought. Opponents argued against the deal in part because the Dutch government would be the biggest shareholder in a merged company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Juan Villalonga, the chairman of Telefonica, the Spanish telecommunications company, has been trying to rally support among company board members to revive merger talks with the Dutch telephone operator Royal KPN, executives close to Telefonica said today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Villalonga was embarrassed last month when the board, succumbing to political pressure from the Spanish government and local banks, failed to approve a $58 billion merger with KPN that Mr. Villalonga had sought. Opponents argued against the deal in part because the Dutch government would be the biggest shareholder in a merged company.</p>
        <p>The failed merger was viewed by telecommunications industry analysts as a major setback for Telefonica, the once state-owned monopoly. With KPN, Mr. Villalonga had hoped to create a pan-European network of fixed-line, data and wireless services with the size to compete against the likes of Vodafone Airtouch P.L.C. and France Telecom, which recently agreed to buy Orange P.L.C. of Britain</p>
        <p>According to executives close to Telefonica, Mr. Villalonga has been making private overtures to several of the nine board members who voted against the merger, asking them to reconsider. The executives cautioned that Mr. Villalonga was far from winning the support needed to restart talks with KPN and might decide to abandon the effort.</p>
        <p>Eleven of Telefonica's 20 board members officially voted for the deal, nowhere near the unanimous approval regarded as necessary for such an important change in the company. Some opponents had privately voted a day earlier in favor of the merger, the executives said. Mr. Villalonga hopes to persuade them to create enough support to at least return to negotiations with KPN.</p>
        <p>For its part, KPN remains somewhat interested in combining with Telefonica, but only if the Spanish telephone company's board fully supports the deal, executives close to KPN said.</p>
        <p>After the merger talks fell apart, KPN's chairman, Paul Smits, accused the Spanish government and local banks of interfering. ''We have no interest in an internal political process,'' he said at the time. ''It's not about a merger of emotions, it's about a merger of businesses.''</p>
        <p>KPN felt that without the complete support of both management boards, no deal was possible, Mr. Smits said. ''You have to have a merger with passion con amor and with total commitment for it to work.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Smits apparently remains interested in merging with Telefonica and perhaps even more so now because of its relationship with Lycos, the United States Internet company, the executives said, though they stopped short of saying that he would necessarily endorse returning to negotiate with Telefonica because of the messy ending to their last merger attempt.</p>
        <p>Three weeks ago, Terra Networks, the Internet unit of Telefonica, acquired Lycos for $12.5 billion. If KPN and Telefonica merged, the combined group would be one of the largest Internet companies in Europe with a strong foothold in the United States.</p>
        <p>KPN and Qwest, which is based in Denver, are working together in Europe to create a high-speed network. KPN's mobile arm, KPN Mobile, also recently entered into an alliance with the Japanese mobile communications giant NTT DoCoMo, an added attraction for Mr. Villalonga.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Telefonica declined to comment on whether Mr. Villalonga was working to restart talks with KPN. A spokesman for KPN could not be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>Executives close to Telefonica stressed that it was too early to tell whether the company's board was committed enough to reaching a deal with KPN to justify new talks. One executive said he expected that a decision on whether Telefonica would try to restart talks would be made within the next several weeks.</p>
        <p>Analysts questioned whether Mr. Villalonga could revive enough interest among the board members to try to negotiate a deal with KPN and whether a deal could in fact be consummated. Nonetheless, analysts said the deal would be mutually beneficial to both companies, pointing out that shares of both companies fell significantly after the original talks collapsed.</p>
        <p>''It may not be a marriage made in heaven,'' said John Tysoe, a telecommunications analyst at West LB Panmure in London. ''But some marriages of convenience end up working out well.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
