<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times</title>
    <meta content="08ANDE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205705"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Stars</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Dallas Stars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E6DB133FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Anderson Sports of The Times column on New Jersey Devils being only one victory away from NHL Stanley Cup championship; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MEMO TO: All you Ranger fans and all the others, judging by the Nielsen ratings, who are pretending that the Devils don't exist.</p>
        <p>FROM: Dave Anderson</p>
        <p>SUBJECT: Sports of The Times, The Stanley Cup Finals</p>
        <p>ADMIT that this is the hockey team you wish were yours.</p>
        <p>When the Rangers were only one victory away from winning the Stanley Cup in 1994, you acted as if they had invented ice, that the National Hockey League had never existed until Mark Messier put on a Ranger sweater. But if the Devils dethrone the Dallas Stars in tonight's fifth game of the Stanley Cup finals, they will have won the cup twice in the last six seasons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MEMO TO: All you Ranger fans and all the others, judging by the Nielsen ratings, who are pretending that the Devils don't exist.</p>
        <p>FROM: Dave Anderson</p>
        <p>SUBJECT: Sports of The Times, The Stanley Cup Finals</p>
        <p>ADMIT that this is the hockey team you wish were yours.</p>
        <p>When the Rangers were only one victory away from winning the Stanley Cup in 1994, you acted as if they had invented ice, that the National Hockey League had never existed until Mark Messier put on a Ranger sweater. But if the Devils dethrone the Dallas Stars in tonight's fifth game of the Stanley Cup finals, they will have won the cup twice in the last six seasons.</p>
        <p>When the Rangers won the cup in 1994, they had won it twice in 55 seasons. At that rate, it will be 2048 before the Rangers win it again. All you Ranger fans should live so long.</p>
        <p>But your attitude toward the Devils is typical. When the Islanders won four consecutive Stanley Cup championships from 1980 to 1983, all you Ranger fans pretended that the Islanders didn't exist.</p>
        <p>These days, the Islanders do hardly exist, even with new owners, but stop pretending that the Devils don't exist.</p>
        <p>If the Devils win the cup again, they will have already accomplished what the Knicks have done in more than half a century and what the Mets have done in nearly 40 years: win two championships. They will have as many Stanley Cup titles as the Giants have Super Bowl trophies, and one more championship than the Jets have had in 40 seasons.</p>
        <p>You and too many others don't seem to realize that the Devils should be easy to appreciate because they possess what so few franchises in any of the four major sports possess anymore -- throwback class and charm.</p>
        <p>The owner, John McMullen, is not a corporate honcho fronting for the stockholders. He put up his own money to purchase the Colorado Rockies nearly two decades ago and move the franchise to where he lives, New Jersey. And he seldom blows up or sputters.</p>
        <p>The 82-year-old McMullen has said he now has remorse over having sold the club to the YankeeNets organization for delivery in July, but if the Devils win the cup, his name will be engraved on it again, not the name of George Steinbrenner or Lewis Katz.</p>
        <p>McMullen has been a rarity, a club owner his players not only respect but also cherish. Lou Lamoriello is a rarity, too, a general manager the players respect and fear.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, the players both cherish and fear the coach even though Larry Robinson's defining moment occurred when he yelled loudly at them after they fell behind the Philadelphia Flyers, 3-1, in the Eastern Conference finals.</p>
        <p>Even before they rallied with three straight victories, the players agreed that they deserved to be chewed out.</p>
        <p>Then again, hockey players are like that. As a group, they are the most honest and the most humble of professional athletes.</p>
        <p>Maybe it's the calmly conscientious Canadian culture that surrounded the upbringing of many N.H.L. players, but the multimillion-dollar contracts haven't spoiled them. Or changed them. With too many players in too many other sports, more money often means more nonsense. But as a group, hockey players are pretty solid citizens.</p>
        <p>If Scott Stevens and Martin Brodeur, the rocks upon which the Devils have been built, were on the Rangers, there would be statues of both outside Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>If Ken Daneyko, the bearded and burly defenseman who has played in every playoff game in Devils' history, were on the Rangers, he would be a folk hero in the Garden.</p>
        <p>If the Patrik Elias-Jason Arnott-Petr Sykora line was on the Rangers, it would already be compared to the Rod Gilbert-Jean Ratelle-Vic Hadfield line of three decades ago.</p>
        <p>What the Rangers need is what the Devils have: the warriors Bobby Holik, Randy McKay, Claude Lemieux, Scott Niedermayer and Jay Pandolfo; the Russian artistes Sergei Brylin, Alexander Mogilny, Vladimir Malakhov and Sergei Nemchinov (the only ex-Ranger); and the mature rookies: John Madden, Scott Gomez, Brian Rafalski and Colin White.</p>
        <p>Put them all together and the Devils are within a winning goal of another Stanley Cup celebration.</p>
        <p>And if the Devils skate around the ice with the Stanley Cup tonight (or Saturday night or Monday night), all you Ranger fans should break down and applaud. You can just say the Devils made you do it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
