<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Board in Talks on Global Equity Links</title>
    <meta content="Y08MARK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205656"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Stock Exchange</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berenson, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E3D8123FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Board in Talks on Global Equity Links</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX BERENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berenson, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Stock Exchange weighs creation of single global equity market with half-dozen other major exchanges from Tokyo to Toronto; proposed round-the-clock global market would electronically connect trading systems of individual markets; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York Stock Exchange is discussing the creation of a single global equity market with a half-dozen other major exchanges from Tokyo to Toronto.</p>
        <p>The proposed round-the-clock global market would electronically connect the trading systems of the individual markets, the Big Board said in a statement yesterday. Though the details of how the new market would work have not been decided, it has the potential to provide investors worldwide with one-stop access to exchanges that list companies with a total market capitalization of $20 trillion -- 60 percent of the total value of stock markets worldwide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York Stock Exchange is discussing the creation of a single global equity market with a half-dozen other major exchanges from Tokyo to Toronto.</p>
        <p>The proposed round-the-clock global market would electronically connect the trading systems of the individual markets, the Big Board said in a statement yesterday. Though the details of how the new market would work have not been decided, it has the potential to provide investors worldwide with one-stop access to exchanges that list companies with a total market capitalization of $20 trillion -- 60 percent of the total value of stock markets worldwide.</p>
        <p>About half of that valuation is on the New York exchange. In addition to the Tokyo and Toronto exchanges, the potential partners mentioned in the release yesterday are exchanges in Hong Kong, Brazil, Australia and Mexico plus Euronext, the combination of the Paris, Amsterdam and Brussels markets.</p>
        <p>But the announcement appears to leave the Big Board still trailing the Nasdaq stock market, its fierce competitor, in the race to set up a true worldwide equity market. The winner will have a giant advantage in listing new companies, offering them the chance to reach investors worldwide through a single market and to gain access to the deepest possible pool of capital.</p>
        <p>The National Association of Securities Dealers, the parent of Nasdaq, has already announced joint ventures to build markets bearing the Nasdaq name in Japan and Europe. Nasdaq Japan will begin trading later this month in a handful of stocks and expects to grow by a dozen stocks or more each month, a Nasdaq official said. With that, the Nasdaq will leap forward in its plans to offer a single, worldwide exchange.</p>
        <p>In contrast, the Big Board announcement yesterday amounts to little more than an agreement to discuss ways that the different national exchanges might link up. The Big Board appeared to rule out a merger of the exchanges in its announcement, which explained the idea of a global equity market, or GEM. ''Investors will be able to access GEM through their domestic stock exchanges, which will keep the exchanges' brand and individual standing while creating a single global pool of liquidity,'' it said.</p>
        <p>Because Big Board officials confirmed over the last several months that they had been in discussions with several of the exchanges mentioned in the announcement yesterday, the timing of the announcement puzzled some competitors.</p>
        <p>''It's talk at this point,'' said the Nasdaq official, who insisted on anonymity. ''Well, we talked for a while, but now we're actually building, and they're under pressure to respond.''</p>
        <p>But Daniel Sullivan, chairman of the Toronto Stock Exchange, said the announcement was significant. ''By making an announcement, it shows that the participating exchanges are committed to this,'' he said. ''It puts the pressure on the exchanges to be serious, because no one wants to walk away and say we failed.''</p>
        <p>The Big Board said it would make no further announcements unless a preliminary agreement was reached.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
