<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Muted Comments Avoid Criticizing the Defendant</title>
    <meta content="Y08REAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205690"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="U.S. VS. MICROSOFT: POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sun Microsystems Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Netscape Communications Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Thomas Penfield (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E7DC133FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Muted Comments Avoid Criticizing the Defendant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush of Texas and Vice President Al Gore, presumptive presidential nominees, decline comment on decision by federal Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson to break up Microsoft for violating antitrust laws; Congressional Republicans condemn ruling (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush of Texas and Vice President Al Gore, the presumptive presidential nominees, declined to comment today on the court order to break Microsoft into two companies, but Congressional Republicans condemned the ruling.</p>
        <p>Scott McClellan, a spokesman for Mr. Bush, who in February had expressed concerns that a breakup would threaten economic growth, said tonight that ''Governor Bush has said all along that it would not be appropriate for him to discuss the specifics of the case while it is still before the courts and Microsoft has indicated that they intend to appeal.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush of Texas and Vice President Al Gore, the presumptive presidential nominees, declined to comment today on the court order to break Microsoft into two companies, but Congressional Republicans condemned the ruling.</p>
        <p>Scott McClellan, a spokesman for Mr. Bush, who in February had expressed concerns that a breakup would threaten economic growth, said tonight that ''Governor Bush has said all along that it would not be appropriate for him to discuss the specifics of the case while it is still before the courts and Microsoft has indicated that they intend to appeal.''</p>
        <p>Doug Hattaway, a spokesman for Mr. Gore, said that ''since it's an ongoing legal matter, it would be inappropriate to comment.'' Mr. Hattaway declined to explain why silence was indicated in this case when Mr. Gore freely commented last month on the case involving political asylum for Elian Gonzalez, as has Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Their reluctance to comment reflected a sense among political professionals that the decision was unlikely to have much impact on the presidential election, except perhaps in Microsoft's home state, Washington, where it could hurt Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Moreover, both supporters and foes of Microsoft have contributed heavily to all sorts of candidates this year. As one Washington lobbyist put it, ''It's obvious why no one is getting too far out front -- there's too much money to be raised from both sides.''</p>
        <p>But that did not stop Republicans on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>Senator Don Nickles of Oklahoma, the assistant majority leader, said the decision marked ''a sad day for the American consumer.'' Mr. Nickles said the Clinton administration apparently wanted a ''federal department of software regulation,'' but said Congress should decide ''whether we need federal bureaucrats and federal judges writing our computer software and deciding how we surf the Internet.''</p>
        <p>Representative Dick Armey of Texas, the House majority leader, denounced the decision even before it was issued. In a statement released at 3:56 p.m., 34 minutes before the ruling was made public, Mr. Armey  said: ''Judge Jackson's ruling will divert innovative companies from creating better products. Worse, it will send the message to innovators around the world that in America we punish success.''</p>
        <p>Democrats were more hesitant in their comments. Senator Patrick J. Leahy of Vermont, the senior Democrat on the Judiciary Committee, said the implications of the ruling ''are anything but clear right now.'' Mr. Leahy urged the government and Microsoft to ''invest new urgency'' in trying to reach a settlement.</p>
        <p>Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York, said the penalty was too severe. ''Obviously,'' Mr. Schumer said, ''if Microsoft broke the law, they should be punished, But not all legal roads lead to a breakup,'' which he said should be used only as a ''last resort.''</p>
        <p>Lawmakers from Washington State were vehement in their complaints, regardless of party. Senator Patty Murray, a Democrat, called the decision disappointing, saying it would ''hobble Microsoft at a critical time in the development of our information-based economy'' and ''cripple a major technology innovator.''</p>
        <p>That was mild compared with the comments of Senator Slade Gorton, a Republican running for re-election. Calling the result a sham, Mr. Gorton said: ''Today is truly a sad day in our nation's history. Never before has our government so viciously pursued a company that has done so much good for not only Americans, but for people worldwide. Microsoft, the driving force behind the booming U.S. economy, has revolutionized how we communicate, how we educate our children and how we live.''</p>
        <p>The absence of any immediate denunciation of Microsoft, even from members of Congress who have been critical of its activities, reflected not only a desire to study the decision by Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson and weigh the politics of attacking a generally popular company, but perhaps also represented a bow to the corporation's increasing role as a campaign contributor.</p>
        <p>A study by the Center for Responsive Politics showed that while Microsoft, and individuals and political action committees connected to it, gave candidates and parties about $1.8 million from 1993 to 1998, in just the first 17 months of the current election cycle they gave $2.2 million.</p>
        <p>And while almost three-fifths of the earlier giving went to Republicans, the donations between Jan. 1, 1999, and June 1 of this year were divided with almost surgically exactness. Democrats received 50.2 percent, or $1,118,014; Republicans took in 49.8 percent, or $1,083,723.</p>
        <p>Microsoft's chairman, William H. Gates, has made strenuous efforts to cater to Democrats as well as Republicans. During his visit to Capitol Hill on Tuesday, he met at length with the all-Democratic Congressional Black Caucus and the heavily Democratic Hispanic Caucus.</p>
        <p>Still, many Microsoft officials are known to hope that if Mr. Bush is elected, his administration might be willing to settle the case on terms more generous to the company than the Clinton administration.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's spokesman, Mr. McClellan, avoided that issue, saying, ''As president, Governor Bush will fully enforce our antitrust laws to foster competition and innovation and protect consumers,'' but he declined to say whether that meant Mr. Bush would have supported government action against Microsoft.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the case seems to have little national political impact. Last month, an NBC News/ Wall Street Journal poll did find the public opposed to a breakup, by 52 percent to 35 percent. And many polls have found the company and Mr. Gates popular with the public.</p>
        <p>But there was no indication either in those surveys or elsewhere that the subject was one that could change votes. Charles Cook, editor of a highly regarded political survey, The Cook Political Report, said he had seen no impact anywhere.</p>
        <p>U.S. VS. MICROSOFT: POLITICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
