<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Candle Of Heroism In France's Dark Night</title>
    <meta content="08CHAB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205637"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS ABROAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chabannes (France)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chevrier, Felix</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gossels, Lisa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riding, Alan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">children of chabannes, the (movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2DB123FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1154" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Candle Of Heroism In France's Dark Night</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sheltering of some 400 Jewish children in a chateau in Chabannes, a village in Vichy France, from 1939 to 1943 is subject of documentary film, The Children of Chabannes, by Lisa Gossels, whose father and uncle were among the children saved from Nazis; their protectors were local teachers and villagers as well as Communist and Jewish activists, all working under leadership of Felix Chevrier, a former journalist, who believed he was defending French honor (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With France gradually and painfully reassessing its record during Germany's wartime occupation, Resistance myths have given way to deep discomfiture over the collaborationist Vichy regime's role in sending 76,000 Jews to Nazi death camps. And yet the very process of investigating a dark past has uncovered points of light, stories that are not only morally uplifting but also help to explain why at least 250,000 Jews survived World War II in France.</p>
        <p>One such point of light was a chateau in the village of Chabannes in the Creuse region of central France, where from 1939 to 1943 some 400 Jewish children found a safe haven. Their protectors were local teachers and villagers as well as Communist and Jewish activists, all working under the leadership of a portly former journalist, Felix Chevrier, who in his own way believed he was defending French honor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With France gradually and painfully reassessing its record during Germany's wartime occupation, Resistance myths have given way to deep discomfiture over the collaborationist Vichy regime's role in sending 76,000 Jews to Nazi death camps. And yet the very process of investigating a dark past has uncovered points of light, stories that are not only morally uplifting but also help to explain why at least 250,000 Jews survived World War II in France.</p>
        <p>One such point of light was a chateau in the village of Chabannes in the Creuse region of central France, where from 1939 to 1943 some 400 Jewish children found a safe haven. Their protectors were local teachers and villagers as well as Communist and Jewish activists, all working under the leadership of a portly former journalist, Felix Chevrier, who in his own way believed he was defending French honor.</p>
        <p>The moving story of this unlikely community has now been rescued in a documentary, ''The Children of Chabannes,'' which is to open on Friday at the Quad Cinema in Greenwich Village and will be shown several times this month on the HBO Signature channel, beginning on Sunday night at 7:30. As with many other newly revealed instances of French valor in face of Nazi terror, it is principally those saved who are doing the remembering. Chevrier himself died an unsung hero in 1962.</p>
        <p>Lisa Gossels, a New Yorker who produced, directed and edited this film with Dean Wetherall, did not have to look far for the story: her father, Peter, and her uncle, Werner, both born in Berlin and sent to the presumed safety of France in July 1939, were children of Chabannes until 1941, when, at ages 11 and 8 they were sent by Quakers to the United States. Their mother died at Auschwitz. ''My father does not consider himself a survivor because he was not in a camp, but he survived the war thanks to the French,'' Ms. Gossels said in a telephone interview from New York. ''It is not something he talked about a lot. It was not part of our daily existence. Yet in a sense the story gave a certain purpose to my life. In the 1980's I even met two sisters, Reine and Renee Paillassou, who had taught at Chabannes, and I thought they'd make a wonderful film.''</p>
        <p>It was a planned reunion at Chabannes in May 1996, however, that served as the catalyst for this documentary. ''The idea of honoring these people who risked their lives for the children was central to the project,'' Ms. Gossels said. ''I also thought that the occasion would probably not happen again. At first I found people reticent to speak. It was traumatic for many to go back into their memories. But we came in with love and trust, and this opened things up.''</p>
        <p>It was a story built around two points of view, two sets of memories: those of the children, now in their 60's and 70's, people like Mr. Gossels as well as Ruth Keller, Norbert Bikales and Jerry Gerard, who also ended up in the United States; and those of surviving protectors, now in their 80's and even 90's, among them the Paillassou sisters, Georges Loinger (who later helped more than 1,000 Jewish children escape into Switzerland) and Rachel Pludermacher, herself Jewish.</p>
        <p>''Most of us never saw our parents again, and these educators were our parents and they guided us to a better life,'' Mr. Bikales said of his Chabannes companions, many of whom came from Poland and Germany.</p>
        <p>Recognizing the need to avoid too many talking heads, Ms. Gossels said, she filmed the farms and hamlets around Chabannes as a way of conveying the region's quiet isolation before the hunt for Jews stepped up in the area in 1942. But her greatest stroke of fortune was to discover a 170-page journal of essays, reflections, photographs and drawings prepared by staff and children at the chateau in 1942. It was among papers donated by Chevrier to the Center for Contemporary Jewish Documentation in Paris.</p>
        <p>The journal, which provided additional illustration for the film, also had the effect of jogging memories. For instance, Ms. Gossels was able to persuade the Paillassou sisters to read aloud before a camera reflections they had written more than a half-century earlier. Frederic Pottecher, a former journalist, read from Chevrier's letters.</p>
        <p>Looking back, the children -- many already orphans in 1942 and 1943, though perhaps not yet aware of their parents' deaths -- remembered Chevrier as a jovial fatherly figure who ran something resembling a summer camp. (Many photographs show happy children.) Those who worked with him, however, spoke more of his courage and determination to shield his wards.</p>
        <p>Chevrier's motivation seemed to be political. ''He wanted to remain a true French republican,'' recalled Mr. Pottecher, who knew Chevrier well, ''and republican meant a little bit on the left but not too much. Not socialist, but a little. But in reality he was very socialist. But you couldn't say that because it was political, so he was republican. It was very French. It was in the great French tradition.''</p>
        <p>In the end Chevrier could not save all his children from deportation. In August 1942, 12 children and 2 teachers were taken away on a bus by French police. Chevrier eventually managed to obtain the freedom of six children and two teachers, but six people from the chateau were deported and, of these, only two, Wolfie Blumenreich and Mr. Gerard, managed to survive slave labor in a succession of camps.</p>
        <p>From that moment things grew steadily more difficult at Chabannes. After Germany took over the so-called unoccupied zone run by Vichy in November 1942, Chevrier began dispersing the children, smuggling some into Spain and Switzerland and placing others in homes. A few teenagers joined the Resistance. Finally, after a French gendarme tipped him off that the remaining children were about to be seized, they were taken from the chateau and never returned.</p>
        <p>''A lot of the children who had taken Chevrier for granted have now come to understand everything he did for them,'' Ms. Gossels said. ''Chevrier is also to be honored as a righteous Gentile at the Yad Vashem memorial in Jerusalem.''</p>
        <p>But France, too, has taken note. The primary school in Chabannes now carries Chevrier's name and, after the prefet, or governor, of the Creuse region saw the film, he nominated the Paillassou sisters for the Legion of Honor. The ceremony is to take place in September.</p>
        <p>ARTS ABROAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
