<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State Plans Tougher Vocational Curriculums</title>
    <meta content="08VOCA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vocational Training</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holloway, Lynette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mills, Richard P (Comr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vocational Training</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEFDB133FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="603" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State Plans Tougher Vocational Curriculums</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNETTE HOLLOWAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holloway, Lynette</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Education Commissioner Richard P Mills releases proposal intended to improve academic standards at vocational schools and make them attractive to students who would not otherwise go to four-year colleges (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>State Education Commissioner Richard P. Mills released a proposal yesterday intended to improve academic standards at vocational schools and make them attractive to students who would not otherwise go to four-year colleges.</p>
        <p>Vocational schools have long been considered dumping grounds for the school system's academically weaker students, but since the students will soon have to pass more rigorous Regents' tests in five subjects, the State Board of Regents has sought ways to improve the schools' academic content without alienating the students.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>State Education Commissioner Richard P. Mills released a proposal yesterday intended to improve academic standards at vocational schools and make them attractive to students who would not otherwise go to four-year colleges.</p>
        <p>Vocational schools have long been considered dumping grounds for the school system's academically weaker students, but since the students will soon have to pass more rigorous Regents' tests in five subjects, the State Board of Regents has sought ways to improve the schools' academic content without alienating the students.</p>
        <p>The measure, to be considered by the Regents on Monday and Tuesday, calls for vocational schools to include English, math and science material in the usual technical courses, said James A. Kadamus, state deputy education commissioner.</p>
        <p>The Regents hope that the changes make vocational programs more attractive to students by teaching them a trade and by giving them a more rounded education, Mr. Kadamus said. ''If a student wants to be a computer science major, I want one of these schools to be his first choice,'' he said. ''We want students to learn a trade.''</p>
        <p>He said the process would be seamless. ''The technical teacher and the academic teacher will be working side-by-side,'' he said. ''They will not stop and say, 'O.K. We're doing math now.' ''</p>
        <p>To graduate, students would also have to complete projects in their special trades that would be developed by the State Education Department, or by industry groups, or both. Schools would have to prepare a ''work skills and employability profile'' for students, based on their vocational and technical achievements.</p>
        <p>Graduating students who complete the integrated programs and projects would receive a ''career and technical endorsement'' on their high school diploma.</p>
        <p>New York City, with 26,500 vocational students, has 20 of the state's 35 vocational schools. Most of the 900 high schools across the state also offer vocational classes.</p>
        <p>State officials hoped the proposal would address some concerns that the new tougher academic requirements do not give vocational students enough time to learn adequate technical skills. In order to meet vocational requirements, some students attending vocational schools often take up to five periods a day in addition to their academic studies.</p>
        <p>Four years ago, the New York State Board of Regents adopted a requirement that all graduating public high school students, including vocational students, pass Regents exams in English, math, science, global studies and American history and government, by 2004. English is the only exam that is required for a diploma this year.</p>
        <p>''This might work with some kids,'' said Frank Carucci, vice president for vocational and technical high schools for the teachers' union. ''When there are some kids who can't read and write, maybe it's the hands-on experience that is motivating them to go to school. The business world needs technical workers,'' he said, and vocational schools ''are not turning out enough,'' he said. ''This is encouraging.''</p>
        <p>Carl T. Hayden, the chancellor of the Board of Regents, said he supported maintaining a vocational education system, but not one that would compromise standards.</p>
        <p>''The big fear here and the thing that I will be looking at most closely is whether this structure permits practitioners to create a trapdoor for those students who would be typically described as problem learners,'' Mr. Hayden said. ''This is intended to elevate vocation education and to imbue it with a long missing academic component. If it's a means by which we can invest technical subjects with more academic rigor, then it can prove to be a great idea.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
