<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.O.P. Says It Seeks to Avoid Partisan Vitriol at Convention</title>
    <meta content="08CONV$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205796"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hughes, Karen P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powell, Colin L (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E1D8133FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1261" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.O.P. Says It Seeks to Avoid Partisan Vitriol at Convention</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI and ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank; Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>AUSTIN, Tex., June 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karen P Hughes and other aides to Gov George W Bush, hoping to preserve upbeat tone that has served them well, say they plan Republican convention that will stress policy over partisan vitriol, interviews; want mostly postive, sustained focus on exalting Bush and his policies and oppose devoting one night to attacking Vice Pres Al Gore; favor giving Gen Colin L Powell and Sen John McCain prominent speaking roles on different nights to maximize television coverage; Bush and aides will discuss plan at retreat set for Kennebunkport, Me (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hoping to preserve and perpetuate an upbeat tone that has served them well over the last several months, advisers to Gov. George W. Bush say they are fashioning a party convention that will emphasize policy over partisan vitriol and perhaps abandon the frequent practice of devoting one night to an attack on the opposition.</p>
        <p>They say they want the second of the four nights, which has often been reserved for such sniping, to adhere to a mostly positive, sustained focus on exalting Governor Bush rather than eviscerating Vice President Al Gore. They want every night to underline a different set or area of Mr. Bush's substantive proposals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hoping to preserve and perpetuate an upbeat tone that has served them well over the last several months, advisers to Gov. George W. Bush say they are fashioning a party convention that will emphasize policy over partisan vitriol and perhaps abandon the frequent practice of devoting one night to an attack on the opposition.</p>
        <p>They say they want the second of the four nights, which has often been reserved for such sniping, to adhere to a mostly positive, sustained focus on exalting Governor Bush rather than eviscerating Vice President Al Gore. They want every night to underline a different set or area of Mr. Bush's substantive proposals.</p>
        <p>And, on a less atmospheric note, they want Gen. Colin L. Powell and Senator John McCain front and center, in prominent speaking roles on different nights, so that each of them serves as a separate lure for the fickle and finite attentions of the major television networks.</p>
        <p>These sorts of issues will be a primary focus at a retreat Mr. Bush and his aides are taking starting this weekend at his parents' compound in Kennebunkport, Me., as the campaign increasingly turns its attention to the convention, which begins in Philadelphia at the end of July.</p>
        <p>And what is most striking about their plans, at least as they were described in interviews with several of Mr. Bush's advisers over the last few days, is the campaign's stated desire to avoid harsh attacks and to try to make the intrinsically partisan proceedings seem less so.</p>
        <p>''We expect it to be a somewhat different convention,'' Karen P. Hughes, the Bush campaigns director of communications, said in an interview here today. ''There will not be the traditional Tuesday night attack night at this convention. Each night will have a positive discussion of Governor Bush's proposals.''</p>
        <p>Of course, tone is relative, and often in the ear of the beholder, and Ms. Hughes and other advisers were careful to say that the convention would still have a place for critical evaluations of Mr. Gore's record and proposals.</p>
        <p>Another adviser said the convention shared the same goal that the campaign had pursued ever since Mr. Bush effectively sealed the Republican nomination in mid-March: namely, to convince voters that the Texas governor was ''a different kind of Republican.''</p>
        <p>One clear way to do that is with a different tenor, the adviser said. Republicans toyed with that in 1996, scheduling the comments of the party's most polarizing figure, then-House Speaker Newt Gingrich, during the portion of the second night before prime-time television coverage, and putting more women into the lineup.</p>
        <p>But even during the peak of the second night, when Representative Susan Molinari of New York delivered the keynote address, there was ample venom for President Clinton. Ms. Molinari characterized him as utterly untrustworthy and Senator Kay Bailey Hutchison attacked Mr. Clinton and his ''Social-Security-taxing, health-care-socializing, drug-coddling, power-grabbing'' administration. She also bluntly ridiculed the first lady, Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>Ed Gillespie, an adviser to the Bush campaign who is helping organize the convention, said that this time around, ''We're going to continue to emphasize what Governor Bush is for, and I don't know that there's time left over for the kinds of bitter attacks that we've seen from both parties' conventions in the past.''</p>
        <p>''But there are differences between the two candidates,'' Mr. Gillespie said, referring to Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore. ''And you can't necessarily point out what they are without talking about the vice president.'' The convention, in other words, will walk a fine oratorical line, several advisers said. It will take equal care, they said, in the way it presents former President George Bush, whose position as the last Republican to reside in the White House makes him a compelling figure but whose presence could also remind voters of the advantages that helped get his son to this point.</p>
        <p>One adviser said that the former president would probably be introduced and included mainly in the context of other recent Republican presidents, like Gerald R. Ford, who would also attend the convention. Ronald Reagan, who suffers from Alzheimer's disease, might be represented by video footage or by his wife, Nancy.</p>
        <p>Along the lines of making the event seem less explicitly partisan, one adviser said, the convention may include some featured speakers who are not politicians but rather people who are grappling, in their professional or personal lives, with the very issues that Mr. Bush has discussed.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign is making its plans for this year's event with the belief that both parties' conventions may matter more than in previous years, for the simple if seemingly unrelated fact that the Summer Olympics will occur so much later than usual.</p>
        <p>In most recent presidential election cycles, the Olympics were over by the time of the conventions, and both the Republicans and Democrats could count on relatively sustained network television coverage of their candidates in September, the month after the conventions.</p>
        <p>But that is not the case for this cycle. The Republican convention runs from July 31 to Aug. 3. The Democratic convention, in Los Angeles, is from Aug. 14 to 17. The Olympics, in Sydney, Australia, take up the last two weeks of September.</p>
        <p>As a result, the television networks may pay little heed to politics for much of September, and the impressions that Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore create at their respective conventions may linger longer, unchallenged by new information, in voters' minds.</p>
        <p>Various officials with the Bush campaign have been plotting convention strategy for months, but Ms. Hughes said that the gathering of senior advisers in Kennebunkport, where Mr. Bush will head late Friday so that he can visit his parents and join his relatives in celebrating the 75th birthday of his mother, Barbara Bush, will mark the first time the campaign's senior decision makers have paid such close, vigorous attention to the coming event.</p>
        <p>Those present, in addition to Ms. Hughes and Mr. Bush, will include Karl Rove, the campaign's chief strategist, Josh Bolten, the campaign's policy director, and Michael Gerson, the chief speechwriter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush will see the first full draft of a proposed convention speech that Mr. Gerson has spent much of the last month preparing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's advisers said that they were trying to plan the convention less as a four-day event than as a 12-</p>
        <p>or 16-day one, with a preceding schedule of appearances and announcements for Mr. Bush that would build to the actual proceedings in Philadelphia. They said that they had not yet decided when they would announce Mr. Bush's vice presidential selection, and that he was not close to making a final selection yet.</p>
        <p>One aide said that each night of the convention might come under a different ''umbrella theme,'' like education or Social Security or America's role and stature in the world, that would allow for a summary of various proposals Mr. Bush has made.</p>
        <p>In addition to Mr. Powell and Mr. McCain, Elizabeth Dole is being considered for a prominent speaking role. But aides stressed that changes to their current intentions could occur.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
