<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="08PUBL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Musical Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pianos</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abyssinian Development Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waldman, Amy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lennon, John (1940-80)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barrows, Sidney Biddle</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Max, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Zachary</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pianos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Musical Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E2DE133FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="716" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON with Amy Waldman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James; Waldman, Amy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column; missing John Lennon piano has been tracked down by Sidney Biddle Barrows, Mayflower Madam of 1980's; artist Peter Max discusses his portrait of builder and philanthropist Zachary Fisher; scene at annual fund raiser for Abyssinian Development Corp described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ivory Lennon Touched</p>
        <p>The missing John Lennon piano has been tracked down by SIDNEY BIDDLE BARROWS, the Mayflower Madam of the 1980's.</p>
        <p>She was helping her husband, DARNAY HOFFMAN, who is a lawyer and represents STUART PIVAR, a former trustee of the New York Academy of Art. Last month the academy and its former director, BRUCE W. FERGUSON, were named in a lawsuit filed by the art dealer SAM GREEN, who said that he had lent the piano to the academy and that he wanted it back. Mr. Ferguson said that it had been a gift, that the academy sold it and that he did not know where it was.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Ivory Lennon Touched</p>
        <p>The missing John Lennon piano has been tracked down by SIDNEY BIDDLE BARROWS, the Mayflower Madam of the 1980's.</p>
        <p>She was helping her husband, DARNAY HOFFMAN, who is a lawyer and represents STUART PIVAR, a former trustee of the New York Academy of Art. Last month the academy and its former director, BRUCE W. FERGUSON, were named in a lawsuit filed by the art dealer SAM GREEN, who said that he had lent the piano to the academy and that he wanted it back. Mr. Ferguson said that it had been a gift, that the academy sold it and that he did not know where it was.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffman said Ms. Barrows learned that when the piano left the academy, it went to an antiques shop on East 11th Street, which sold it to BUDDY BAIN, an auction dealer in Arab, Ala.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bain said that he sold it and that the buyers wanted to sell it again. Referring to another piano, an upright Lennon used to write ''Imagine,'' which is scheduled to be sold in an online auction next month, he said, ''If that piano in Liverpool is worth a million six that belonged to John Lennon, this is a 9-foot-6 concert grand. It's worth more.''</p>
        <p>Art and a Wall For City's Flattop</p>
        <p>Ten-hut: the artist PETER MAX boarded the U.S.S. Intrepid yesterday to unveil his  portrait of Zachary Fisher, the builder and philanthropist who all but brought the Intrepid to New York by force of personality.</p>
        <p>Mr. Max said he might not have done the portrait if the German government had not given him a piece of the Berlin Wall -- not a palm-sized chunk but an 18,000-pound slab that was too heavy for his studio.</p>
        <p>''I remembered they had airplanes on top of the Intrepid,'' Mr. Max said. ''I had just met Larry Fisher, who was Zachary's brother, so I called up Larry Fisher and asked if he would take the wall. I said, 'The truck's a block away, I'll have it over to you within the hour.' That's where I met Zachary.''</p>
        <p>The portrait was not the only new thing being talked about on the Intrepid: Fleet Week, the annual celebration that gives sailors a chance to undertake search-and-enjoy missions in Manhattan while their ships are anchored in the Hudson River, has been renamed. The new name is something only a Pentagon bureaucrat could love: ''Military Salute Week.''</p>
        <p>''We had a desire to be more inclusive,'' said LT. GEN. MARTIN R. STEELE, the retired Marine who has been president and chief executive of the Intrepid Sea-Air-Space Museum since August. ''The term 'fleet week' connoted the Navy only, and perhaps the Marine Corps to some degree.''</p>
        <p>Fleet Week used to occur around Memorial Day. This year, ''Military Salute Week'' has been moved to July to coincide with OpSail 2000. Next year, General Steele said, ''Military Salute Week'' will once again coincide with Memorial Day.</p>
        <p>Rich and Powerful Dine in Harlem</p>
        <p>There may be no better sign of Harlem's resurgence than the power breakfast at City College yesterday.</p>
        <p>The gathering of the city's elite was the sixth annual fund-raiser for the Abyssinian Development Corporation. The event needed just a few tables in 1995, and this year drew 600 people and $550,000 for the corporation, which has helped spearhead Harlem's redevelopment.</p>
        <p>At one table sat HAROLD O. LEVY, the schools chancellor, and WILLIAM C. THOMPSON JR., the president of the Board of Education; JENNIFER J. RAAB, the chairwoman of the City Landmarks Commission; C. VIRGINIA FIELDS, the Manhattan borough president; and LORETTA E. LYNCH, the federal prosecutor for the eastern district.</p>
        <p>Among the organizers of the event was ANDRE LEON TALLEY, editor at large of Vogue magazine. He had invited OSCAR and ANNETTE DE LA RENTA, and had talked Prada into buying a table. But by the end of the breakfast, he and Ms. Lynch had something other than New York on their minds.</p>
        <p>''You're from Durham?'' she was heard asking the towering Mr. Talley. ''I'm from Durham, too. Where did you go to high school?''</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON with Amy Waldman</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
