<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High Spirits and Lofty Ideals at Queens</title>
    <meta content="08COMM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205701"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COMMENCEMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">Queens College</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sessoms, Allen L (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EEDC133FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="371" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High Spirits and Lofty Ideals at Queens</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Queens College holds 76th commencement; outgoing president Allen Lee Sessoms speaks; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 76th commencement of Queens College yesterday was marked by high energy and high spirits.</p>
        <p>In the calm after Tuesday's rainstorm, over 2,000 graduates of the class of 2000 pulled on black gowns, adjusted their mortarboards and  converged on the campus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 76th commencement of Queens College yesterday was marked by high energy and high spirits.</p>
        <p>In the calm after Tuesday's rainstorm, over 2,000 graduates of the class of 2000 pulled on black gowns, adjusted their mortarboards and  converged on the campus.</p>
        <p>Allen Lee Sessoms, the departing Queens College president, told the graduates on the campus quadrangle, ''The sun always shines on Queens College commencement.'' And Claire E. Shulman, the borough president of Queens, said, ''Go out there and knock 'em dead!''</p>
        <p>Joseph Brostek, the college's director of special events, said 3,800 students received degrees, with over 2,000 present at commencement.</p>
        <p>In his talk, Mr. Sessoms, expanding on remarks by George F. Will, the columnist, urged graduates to ''maintain the virtues of humanity and not confuse them with values that are subject to whim and to political manipulation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sessoms said that when he was growing up in the Bronx, ''Virtue was good; it was perhaps the only universal good. Values were a dime a dozen, and they could be an affront to our virtues.</p>
        <p>''The good in us must stick to our virtues and seek not to impose our values on others,'' he said. ''We share those virtues with the rest of humanity. They are the good that will allow us to move forward as human beings to a better collective future.''</p>
        <p>Three people also received honorary doctorates: Erika Eichhorn Bourguignon, recognized for her work in the anthropology of women;  George Perle, composer professor emeritus of the Aaron Copland School of Music at Queens College and winner of the Pulitzer Prize for music; and Arnold C. Franco, author of ''Code of Victory,'' a book about his mobile intelligence unit in World War II.</p>
        <p>COMMENCEMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
