<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>M.T.A. Said to Run Late in Answering Complaints</title>
    <meta content="08MTA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205659"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Transportation Authority</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Rail Road Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York City Transit Authority</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E0D8123FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="470" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>M.T.A. Said to Run Late in Answering Complaints</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Group on Metropolitan Transportation Authority board that represents riders finds that New York City Transit and Long Island Rail Road often do not meet their goals of answering letters quickly and not keeping those riders who phone languishing on hold (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the last several years, the Metropolitan Transportation Authority has made a habit of referring to its passengers as customers -- one way, it reasoned, to change its thinking and make itself more responsive to the millions who ride the subways, buses and commuter trains each day.</p>
        <p>But a report released yesterday by the group on the M.T.A. board that represents riders suggests that the agency still lags on at least one measure of treating riders like customers: answering their complaints and questions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the last several years, the Metropolitan Transportation Authority has made a habit of referring to its passengers as customers -- one way, it reasoned, to change its thinking and make itself more responsive to the millions who ride the subways, buses and commuter trains each day.</p>
        <p>But a report released yesterday by the group on the M.T.A. board that represents riders suggests that the agency still lags on at least one measure of treating riders like customers: answering their complaints and questions.</p>
        <p>The report found that New York City Transit and the Long Island Rail Road, by their own admission, often did not meet their goals of answering letters quickly and not keeping complainants languishing on hold.</p>
        <p>For example, while 60 seconds is the national standard for public transit agencies to get a worker on the phone with a complaining passenger, New York City Transit has set a goal of 93 seconds, and callers are kept on hold an average of 102 seconds.</p>
        <p>Additionally, of the 8,000 or so calls that New York City Transit receives every day, as many as 800 are not even included in its averages of how well it responds -- meaning that callers could be left on hold for long periods of time.</p>
        <p>When workers for the group that compiled the report -- the Permanent Citizens Advisory Committee to the M.T.A. -- tested the complaint lines, they were kept on hold in one case by New York City Transit for more than 5 minutes and by the Long Island Rail Road for 14 minutes.</p>
        <p>When the group sent complaint letters last year and used comment cards provided to passengers by the Long Island Rail Road, several letters and cards never received responses. And the group found that the Long Island Rail Road did not have bilingual workers to respond to its own Spanish language comment cards.</p>
        <p>''People should be able to expect a timely response and a correct answer, and they just can't expect that now,'' said Michael T. Doyle, the group's associate director.</p>
        <p>The Metro-North Railroad, by contrast, was consistently fast and efficient in responding, despite the fact that its self-imposed standards are more stringent than its two sister agencies -- phone calls must be answered by workers within 20 seconds and letters must be responded to within eight business days.</p>
        <p>Christopher P. Boylan, deputy executive director of the M.T.A., said yesterday that the agency would look at the report. He said the report brought up interesting points, but he added:</p>
        <p>''Sometimes the bigger the organization is, the longer it will take to find a quality answer. We could send a nice letter out saying, 'Hi, we're getting back to you.' But we want to provide a quality response and that's sometimes hard to do as fast as you would want.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
