<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Albright Tells Syrians an Accord for Palestinians Is First Goal</title>
    <meta content="Y08MID$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Israel-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Syria-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Egypt-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Egypt</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Orme, William A Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albright, Madeleine K (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mubarak, Hosni (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shara, Farouk Al- (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E0D9133FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Albright Tells Syrians an Accord for Palestinians Is First Goal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM A. ORME Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Orme, William A Jr</byline>
      <dateline>CAIRO, June 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>State Sec Madeleine K Albright, between separate meetings with Egyptian Pres Hosni Mubarak and Syrian Min Farouk al-Shara, Cairo, says Clinton administration is willing to push again for Israeli-Syrian peace talks, but that its main goal is settlement between Israel and Palestinians; says United States sticks to own timetable for Palestinian pact, despite Israeli Prime Min Ehud Barak's coalition problems; Israel pulls back from two small outposts north of provisional border with Lebanon newly demarcated by United Nations; UN cites further minor Israeli violation of withdrawal requirements (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright told Syrian and Egyptian officials today that the Clinton administration was willing to push once more for peace talks between Damascus and Israel, but that its main goal in its remaining months in office was a settlement between Israel and the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>''There is no higher foreign policy priority for the Clinton administration than an Israeli-Palestinian peace,'' Dr. Albright said between meetings with President Hosni Mubarak of Egypt and Foreign Minister Farouk Shara of Syria.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright told Syrian and Egyptian officials today that the Clinton administration was willing to push once more for peace talks between Damascus and Israel, but that its main goal in its remaining months in office was a settlement between Israel and the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>''There is no higher foreign policy priority for the Clinton administration than an Israeli-Palestinian peace,'' Dr. Albright said between meetings with President Hosni Mubarak of Egypt and Foreign Minister Farouk Shara of Syria.</p>
        <p>Capping a hastily scheduled three-day swing through the Middle East, Dr. Albright appeared to be trying to clear the rubble off both tracks of the peace effort. Arriving this morning from Israel, where she secured an agreement to resume talks with the Palestinians next week in Washington, Dr. Albright reiterated President Clinton's hopes for conclusive negotiations there this summer with Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel and the president of the Palestinian Authority, Yasir Arafat.</p>
        <p>Asked whether the troubles of Mr. Barak's coalition might disrupt the plans, Dr. Albright said Washington was sticking to ''its own timetable'' for a peace pact.</p>
        <p>''This is a rare opportunity to reach an accord, and we cannot let it slip away,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In an hourlong meeting with Mr. Shara, she stressed that ''the door is still open'' to a renewal of American-sponsored talks between Syria and Israel, a senior American official said. This was the first high-level Syrian-American encounter since Mr. Clinton's meeting with President Hafez al-Assad in Geneva in March, when the Syrians effectively ended the talks by insisting that Israel would have to surrender not just the entire Golan Heights, but also the northeastern shore of the Sea of Galilee.</p>
        <p>''We are beyond Geneva,'' a senior American official said after the meeting. ''We are looking forward. We are not looking backward.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright made it clear that the administration was aiming for a comprehensive pact between Israel and the Palestinians, not Syria. She said she believed that Israel and the Palestinian Authority could negotiate compromises on core issues like refugees and the status of Jerusalem before Sept. 13, the date that Mr. Arafat has pledged to move toward the establishment of an independent state with or without an agreement.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes deadlines focus the mind,'' Dr. Albright said. ''I would just like to announce, for those who care, we are not having a summer vacation.''</p>
        <p>Washington is also keeping a wary eye on the still volatile situation in southern Lebanon. Dr. Albright said she expected the United Nations to certify soon that Israel has fully withdrawn, following the terms of United Nations resolutions adopted after Israel occupied the zone 22 years ago. But Lebanon and Israel continue to wrangle over fragments of territory along the hilly border line, which has never been definitively negotiated or even surveyed.</p>
        <p>Israel pulled back today from two small outposts north of a provisional boundary newly demarcated by United Nations cartographers. But the United Nations mission that is supervising the pullout contends that Israel continues to violate withdrawal requirements in another pocket, of pastures, near a border kibbutz. The disagreement, though minor, may further delay official certification of the withdrawal, which is required before United nations forces can be deployed in the region.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright's discussions with Mr. Shara dealt as much with the Israeli withdrawal from Lebanon as with prospects for new bilateral talks, United States officials said. American and Israeli officials have voiced concern that violence in southern Lebanon could disrupt talks with the Palestinians, because of its political effects in Israel and the fear that it could spark outbreaks by dissidents in the West Bank and Gaza.</p>
        <p>Syria has more than 30,000 troops in Lebanon and maintains effective political and economic control over the country. Dr. Albright urged Beirut and Damascus to do more to pacify the frontier zone, Hezbollah guerrillas now largely govern.</p>
        <p>In her talks with Mr. Shara, Dr. Albright did not reiterate the demand for a Syrian withdrawal, concentrating on Syrian acceptance of the United Nations verification of Israel's withdrawal, United States officials said. Damascus and Washington are now ''pretty much in agreement'' about the certification terms, an American official said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
