<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Egyptian At Center On Rights Of Women</title>
    <meta content="Y08MUB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205714"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mubarak, Suzanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mubarak, Hosni (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E0DB133FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Egyptian At Center On Rights Of Women</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, June 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Suzanne Mubarak, wife of Pres Hosni Mubarak, who leads Egyptian delegation to United Nations conference on implementing rights for women drafted at 1995 Beijing conference; she says women must speak against false notions of Islam promoted by extremists who would deny women education and jobs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five years after thousands of women converged on Beijing to draft what amounted to a bill of rights for women, government officials and women's organizations are huddled again in conference halls here, trying to turn those promises into concrete prescriptions for action.</p>
        <p>By today, midway through the process, some cultural confrontations had kicked in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five years after thousands of women converged on Beijing to draft what amounted to a bill of rights for women, government officials and women's organizations are huddled again in conference halls here, trying to turn those promises into concrete prescriptions for action.</p>
        <p>By today, midway through the process, some cultural confrontations had kicked in.</p>
        <p>When familiar tensions between  Western delegations and conservatives led by the Vatican and supported by Catholic and Muslim nations threatened to reopen battles over abortion and family relationships, Suzanne Mubarak was dismayed. Egypt's first lady, who has worked to advance the rights of women against the background of Islamic militancy, warned in an interview today that such battles risked provoking a backlash that could impede progress.</p>
        <p>''We don't need to be pulled into all these controversies,'' said Mrs. Mubarak, who is leading the Egyptian delegation. ''We have too many problems as it is. This makes people who are not extremists become ones.''</p>
        <p>Egypt has been viewed as a pivotal country on women's rights since the 1994 international conference on population in Cairo, which put individual women, not governments, at the center of family planning and demanded that they be given the tools to determine their own reproductive lives.</p>
        <p>At the 1995 Fourth World Conference on Women in Beijing, the chairwoman was an Egyptian, Mervat Tallawy, a diplomat who is now a government minister. Since the Cairo and Beijing conferences, Egypt has outlawed genital cutting of girls and revised its civil code to make it easier for a woman to obtain a divorce, and has expanded and clarified women's rights in family law. A national council for women has been established, which leads brainstorming sessions on such issues as how to field more female candidates in elections.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Mubarak said in an interview today that Egyptian women did all this carefully, without combative claims of absolute equality, and that she believes they will have to continue this way. It is an argument heard frequently from nations on the edge of cultural conflagration.</p>
        <p>But at the same time, she said, women have to speak against false notions of Islam promoted by extremists who would deny girls an education or their mothers jobs.</p>
        <p>''If you look at the history, even the wife of the Prophet was a brave woman,'' Mrs. Mubarak said. ''She was a businesswoman. So don't come and tell me women can't go to work, if she was working.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Mubarak, who had an English mother and who married Hosni Mubarak, an air force officer who is now Egypt's president, when she was 17, decided after her two sons were in school ''that there was something more I should do in my life.'' She enrolled at the American University in Cairo, where she received a B.A. in political science and an M.A. in sociology. ''My husband supported me,'' she said. ''He said, O.K., try it out. See if you can do it, but on one condition: not at the expense of the boys.''</p>
        <p>She now urges other privileged women, many of whom she describes as ''apolitical and apathetic'' to do more for themselves and other Egyptian women through the civic organizations that are springing up around the country. Some of these owe their inceptions to United Nations conferences, she said.</p>
        <p>''In these international conferences, I think we have come a long way both on the national and international level in bringing women's issues to the forefront,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Charlotte Bunch, who directs the Center for Women's Global Leadership at Rutgers University, agrees with Mrs. Mubarak that even with disagreements, the value of a meeting like this one should not be discounted. ''Proposals and ideas are being exchanged,'' Ms. Bunch said today. ''I think a lot of good things are going to come out of this that have nothing to do with the final minutiae.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
