<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peppy Hops and Rustling, as 'Summerspace' Swamps the Senses</title>
    <meta content="08SUMM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205645"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York City Ballet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cunningham, Merce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EEDB123FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="637" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peppy Hops and Rustling, as 'Summerspace' Swamps the Senses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Anderson reviews New York City Ballet performing Merce Cunningham's Summerspace; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the balmiest of summer days on Tuesday night at the New York State Theater despite the ferocious weather outside. The New York City Ballet danced Merce Cunningham's ''Summerspace.''</p>
        <p>Like most of Mr. Cunningham's productions, this work for a cast of six is devoid of references to any specific locale, period or dramatic situation. Nevertheless its movements are so beguiling that they radiate a summery sense of well-being. And although Mr. Cunningham has sometimes puzzled dancegoers unfamiliar with his choreography, ''Summerspace'' clearly delighted the State Theater audience, which greeted it with deserved enthusiasm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was the balmiest of summer days on Tuesday night at the New York State Theater despite the ferocious weather outside. The New York City Ballet danced Merce Cunningham's ''Summerspace.''</p>
        <p>Like most of Mr. Cunningham's productions, this work for a cast of six is devoid of references to any specific locale, period or dramatic situation. Nevertheless its movements are so beguiling that they radiate a summery sense of well-being. And although Mr. Cunningham has sometimes puzzled dancegoers unfamiliar with his choreography, ''Summerspace'' clearly delighted the State Theater audience, which greeted it with deserved enthusiasm.</p>
        <p>Created in 1958 for Mr. Cunningham's modern-dance troupe, ''Summerspace'' was first performed by City Ballet in 1966. It then slipped out of the repertory. But the company revived it for a special performance of the 1999 Lincoln Center Festival. Now it has become a regular part of City Ballet's programming this season.</p>
        <p>Because many of its movements are light, the women wore point shoes in ''Summerspace'' in 1966. But this type of traditional balletic footgear slowed them down in the rapid and often unexpected changing choreographic patterns. Everyone moves deftly in slippers in this version.</p>
        <p>It is a joy to behold. Robert Rauschenberg, the designer, has spattered the backdrop and costumes with a multitude of small, brightly colored dots. Watching the action, as lighted by Aaron Copp, becomes akin to watching a Pointillist painting by Seurat come to life.</p>
        <p>The cast scurries in and out and sometimes spins in little whirls of activity. Yet never is there any sense of agitation. There are pattering runs, peppy hops and gentle skips. There also are pauses. And these moments of repose make the performers as satisfying to look at as they are when they are moving.</p>
        <p>Samantha Allen, Michelle Gifford, Benjamin Millepied, Jenifer Ringer, Alexander Ritter and Kathleen Tracey appeared always alert, and their steps were lucid. It was a pleasure to watch them cross the choreographic meadows of ''Summerspace.''</p>
        <p>Morton Feldman's accompanying score, for which John Kennedy was guest conductor, is filled with rustles, chirps and twitters. Literally imitating nothing in nature, they nevertheless may make one recall the sounds of birds and insects. As is usual in a piece by Mr. Cunningham, no attempts are made to match choreographic phrases directly with the music.</p>
        <p>Rather, the music establishes a sonic climate or atmosphere through which the dancers move. The weather of ''Summerspace'' was always pleasant.</p>
        <p>A totally different choreographic approach to music was exemplified by Jerome Robbins's ''2 &amp; 3 Part Inventions.'' In this jolly ballet, every step somehow seems to reflect something in the accompanying keyboard music by Bach, which was played on the piano by Nancy McDill. Rippling musical phrases are echoed by rippling movements, a halting melody inspires halting steps, a lilting theme prompts leaps and bounds.</p>
        <p>It could be argued that the result is merely a music visualization in which the choreography becomes the score's servant rather than its partner. But Mr. Robbins has envisioned Bach's musical counterpoint in a clever choreographically contrapuntal manner. And his visions were nimbly danced by four couples: Janie Taylor and Mr. Millepied, Rachel Rutherford and Mr. Ritter, Eva Natanya and Edward Liang, and Carrie Lee Riggins and James Fayette.</p>
        <p>The program also included a sparkling repeat performance of George Balanchine's ''Symphony in C,'' conducted by Andrea Quinn, another guest conductor this season.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
