<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="08TRAN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205806"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E5D7133FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="813" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  CLEVELAND INDIANS -- Activated RHP Paul Rigdon from the 15-day disabled list. Placed RHP Jaret Wright on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to June 3.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS -- Placed OF Todd Greene on the 15-day DL. Recalled C Josh Phelps from Knoxville of the Southern League.</p>
        <p>National League  METS -- Sent INF-OF Ryan McGuire outright to Norfolk of the International League.  PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES -- Signed RHP Taylor Buchholz, OF Brandon Caraway, 1B Reginald Griggs, OF Anthony Hensley, LHP Trevor Bullock, and C Kevin Sullivan.  SAN DIEGO PADRES -- Placed RHP Brian Boehringer on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to June 4. Recalled RHP Domingo Guzman from Las Vegas of the Pacific Coast League.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  CLEVELAND INDIANS -- Activated RHP Paul Rigdon from the 15-day disabled list. Placed RHP Jaret Wright on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to June 3.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS -- Placed OF Todd Greene on the 15-day DL. Recalled C Josh Phelps from Knoxville of the Southern League.</p>
        <p>National League  METS -- Sent INF-OF Ryan McGuire outright to Norfolk of the International League.  PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES -- Signed RHP Taylor Buchholz, OF Brandon Caraway, 1B Reginald Griggs, OF Anthony Hensley, LHP Trevor Bullock, and C Kevin Sullivan.  SAN DIEGO PADRES -- Placed RHP Brian Boehringer on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to June 4. Recalled RHP Domingo Guzman from Las Vegas of the Pacific Coast League.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  BOSTON CELTICS -- Named C.M. Newton consultant.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  CINCINNATI BENGALS -- Waived P Deone Horinek.  GREEN BAY PACKERS -- Named David Steffen executive director of Team Lambeau.  INDIANAPOLIS COLTS -- Named Tom Zupancic vice president of business development.  SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS -- Signed TE Greg Clark to a three-year contract, OT Matt Willig to a two-year contract and LB Edward Thomas to a one-year contract.  SEATTLE SEAHAWKS -- Release LB Matt Beck.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  RANGERS -- Agreed to terms with G Jason LaBarbera.  COLORADO AVALANCHE -- Traded G Marc Denis to the Columbus Blue Jackets for a second-round pick in the 2000 draft.  COLUMBUS BLUE JACKETS -- Signed F David Vyborny and F Martin Spanhel to two-year contracts.  CHICAGO BLACKHAWKS -- Signed G Erasmo Saltarelli.  MINNESOTA WILD -- Signed F Pete Gardiner and G David Brumby.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
        <p>USA BASEBALL -- Named Phil Regan, Reggie Smith and Eddie Rodriguez coaches and, Dick Cooke and Ray Tanner auxiliary coaches.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
        <p>Major League Soccer  TAMPA BAY MUTINY -- Signed F Manuel Bucuane.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>SUN BELT CONFERENCE -- Named Judy Willson assistant commissioner, effective July 1. Announced the resignation of Kevin DeRamus, service bureau director.  FAIRFIELD -- Announced the resignation of Mark Dennehy, men's ice hockey coach, to become men's assistant ice hockey coach at Massachusetts.  MISSISSIPPI -- Named Mike Bianco baseball coach.  NEBRASKA -- Reinstated QB Eric Crouch to the football team.  RUTGERS -- Named Ryan Carfley assistant offensive football coach and Kevin Kelly assistant defensive football coach.  ST. JOHN'S, N.Y. -- Named Adrienne Mullikin assistant director of media relations.  VILLANOVA -- Promoted Gina Procaccio to women's track and field and cross country coach, Jim Belzer to assistant director of facilities, Ryan Fannon to director of sales and broadcasting and Kim Rampone to assistant athletic director for corporate sponsorships.  VMI -- Announced the resignation of Scott Gines, baseball coach, effective June 30.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
