<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Government of Israel Thrown Into Tumult by Vote in Parliament to Call New Elections</title>
    <meta content="Y08ISR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E0D9133FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Government of Israel Thrown Into Tumult by Vote in Parliament to Call New Elections</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, June 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israeli Parliament, 61-48, approves preliminary bill to disperse and head toward new elections, throwing Prime Min Ehud Barak's government into turmoil; three of six parties in Barak's broad coalition vote for bill, including ultra-Orthodox Shas Party; bill requires three more hearings to become law; vote, even if it fails to spur new elections, could break up Barak's coalition and distract Barak during final peace talks with Palestinians; Barak addresses nation; urges Israelis to trust him to restore calm; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak's government was thrown into tumult today when Parliament, by a substantial margin, approved a preliminary bill to disperse and head toward new elections.</p>
        <p>Three of the six parties in Mr. Barak's broad coalition voted against him, including the ultra-Orthodox Shas Party, which has been the prime minister's most temperamental ally and today ensured his defeat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak's government was thrown into tumult today when Parliament, by a substantial margin, approved a preliminary bill to disperse and head toward new elections.</p>
        <p>Three of the six parties in Mr. Barak's broad coalition voted against him, including the ultra-Orthodox Shas Party, which has been the prime minister's most temperamental ally and today ensured his defeat.</p>
        <p>The bill requires three more hearings to become law, and it could end up derailed by political maneuvering or the more basic desire of members of Parliament to cling to their jobs and perquisites. But today's vote, even if it does not provoke new elections, could break up the governing coalition and create a chaotic interlude at a diplomatically inopportune moment.</p>
        <p>The prospect of final peace talks with the Palestinians was supposed to consume Mr. Barak's energies this summer. Instead, he may be forced to devote considerable time to domestic negotiations. ''What's next?'' said his cabinet secretary, Yitzhak Herzog. ''Poker.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak kept silent immediately after the vote, which was 61 to 48 with 11 of the 120 members absent. But this evening he addressed the nation in his unruffled manner. Saying the cabinet would meet on Sunday and figure out how to proceed, his advised all Israelis to relax, enjoy the holiday of Shavuot, which begins on Thursday evening, and trust him to restore calm.</p>
        <p>''The dust will settle,'' he said confidently. ''There aren't going to be any elections.''</p>
        <p>As he spoke, busloads of settlers were gathering outside his residence to shout: ''Barak, go home! You have no mandate!'' Carrying babies and banners, they looked exultant, and dozens of yeshiva students performed a joyful line dance.</p>
        <p>This afternoon, Nahum Barnea, the dean of Israeli newspaper columnists, shook his head as he surveyed the frenzied politicking in the bustling halls of the flat-roofed Parliament building. ''We are on the threshold of a new era,'' he said, ''and from here it looks like it will be a mess.''</p>
        <p>A former general who was elected by an overwhelming majority in May of last year, Mr. Barak went to great effort to cobble together a broad coalition of left and right, religious and secular parties in what he portrayed as an effort to heal the diverse rifts in Israeli society. He also thought that he needed a broad government to back his peacemaking plans.</p>
        <p>But from the time he took office in July, the coalition has been fractious.</p>
        <p>And today three of the six parties in the government voted against him: the National Religious Party, which was on its way to quitting anyway, the Russian immigrant party led by Interior Minister Natan Sharansky, and Shas, the party with the third-largest bloc in Parliament.</p>
        <p>All three defecting parties served in the rightist cabinet of the previous prime minister, Benjamin Netanyahu. A former chief of staff to Mr. Netanyahu, Avigdor Lieberman, who heads a second Russian immigrant party, introduced the bill. Shas members encouraged him to do so, and after the vote they surrounded him for an extended group hug.</p>
        <p>At the same time, several feet away, Ophir Pines-Paz, the chairman of Mr. Barak's party, One Israel, sat alone, looking shocked and crestfallen.</p>
        <p>Shas, which has 17 members in Parliament, represents Jews of North African and Middle Eastern origin, and it has been the balkiest party in the coalition, fighting for money and respect from the first day.</p>
        <p>The two other parties more specifically opposed Mr. Barak's peace moves and long felt out of place in a center-left government, frequently siding with the rightist opposition, which was weak without them.</p>
        <p>Asked what his party would do, Mr. Sharansky, who has complained bitterly about Mr. Barak's failure to consult his cabinet ministers, said: ''It takes two to get a divorce. But definitely this virtual coalition can't continue.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak faces several options as the bill for new elections wends its way through Parliament.</p>
        <p>He could negotiate with Mr. Sharansky and with Shas to try to save his original coalition. That seems unlikely, since Mr. Barak said tonight, ''Those ministers who voted today for early elections fired themselves.'' But leaving the door open, he also suggested that ''a coalition of similar composition to the current one'' could work if it acted more cohesively.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak could also bypass Parliament and ask the outgoing president, Ezer Weizman, to give him permission to resign. Also an unlikely scenario, such a maneuver would force elections in 90 days from the time the request was granted.</p>
        <p>That is much more quickly than if the elections came about as a result of today's bill, and it would allow Mr. Barak to seize the momentum and profit from his surge in popularity after the Israeli troop withdrawal from Lebanon last month.</p>
        <p>Or, in the most likely option, he could reshape the coalition as a narrow, minority government that would depend on Arab parties, outside the coalition, for majority votes on peacemaking issues.</p>
        <p>To do that, Mr. Barak would most likely enlist a secularist party called Shinui, with six seats in Parliament; a workers' right's party with two seats, and a leftist Russian party, also with two seats. That would give him a 52-member parliamentary coalition, with 10 votes from the Arab parties as a cushion.</p>
        <p>It would also give him a political framework similar to that of his mentor, Yitzhak Rabin. Mr. Barak aspired not to copy Mr. Rabin's governmental model because he felt it worsened the left-right, secular-religious divide in Israeli society. And it engendered a strong opposition to peace efforts, which could be recreated now.</p>
        <p>Further, it would allow the right wing to bait him as it did Mr. Rabin about relying on the Arab parties because he could not get a Jewish majority.</p>
        <p>Several government ministers wrung their hands today and asserted that the politicians who had voted to shake things up were tone-deaf to the public mood.</p>
        <p>''This vote has nothing to do with what people want,'' said Haim Ramon, a minister charged with Jerusalem affairs. ''Your desire,'' he told the lawmakers, ''is disconnected from reality.''</p>
        <p>Michael Melchior, a dovish rabbi in Mr. Barak's cabinet, said that the vote revealed the ''sectorialism'' of Parliament and that it would infuriate the public. ''What?'' he said. ''They want a period of uncertainty? No one will want this. Everyone outside this building will hate us.''</p>
        <p>Others said they feared that the country's diplomatic efforts would suffer the most. ''This is not just a government crisis,'' said Naomi Chazan, a leftist lawmaker. ''It's the future of the peace process, and everyone who voted for this is exercising maximum irresponsibility.''</p>
        <p>Leaders of the rightist Likud Party did not waste time in proclaiming Mr. Barak's days to be numbered. ''I'm running around trying to form a new coalition right now,'' said Silvan Shalom, a young lawmaker who aspires to take over the Likud.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shalom acknowledged contentedly that the peace effort, which is not his priority, might be hurt. ''Obviously the other side will understand that they are negotiating with a lame duck, and they won't want to make decisions,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Speaking from Ramallah, in the West Bank, Saeb Erekat, a senior Palestinian negotiator, said the vote was ''an internal Israeli matter,'' but one that made the Palestinians nervous. ''I hope this situation will not be used as excuse to introduce more settlements or more obstacles to peace,'' he said. ''I hope the Israeli government will not use what is happening as a pretext not to implement the third phase of redeployment or to release more prisoners.''</p>
        <p>The Shas Party, whose power base is built on a social service network that includes a large religious school system, has been battling for money to cover its schools' debts. Over financing, educational reform and power issues, its leader, Eli Yishai, has butted heads with the leftist education minister, Yossi Sarid. And its spiritual leader, Rabbi Ovadia Yosef, is under police investigation over accusations of inciting violence against Mr. Sarid in his sermons.</p>
        <p>Shas's vote today was the culmination of its threats against the government, which followed Mr. Barak's suspension of negotiations on their school system earlier this week.</p>
        <p>''We decided on Monday morning to vote in favor of Avigdor Lieberman's bill,'' said Yitzhak Suderi, the spokesman for Shas. ''When we gave him our word, he decided to introduce his bill. We warned the prime minister a few weeks ago that Lieberman was preparing the bill and that we might support it if we were to continue to be persecuted by Meretz,'' Mr. Sarid's party.</p>
        <p>''The time has come for the prime minister to make a decision,'' Mr. Suderi said. ''Does he want a narrow coalition that will endure only two or three weeks, or does he want to try to maintain his broad coalition? He can either show leadership, as we know he is capable of, given the experience with the withdrawal from Lebanon, or he can do Yossi Sarid's bidding.''</p>
        <p>The liberal, secular members of the Israeli public who voted Mr. Barak into office are hoping that he will finally turn his back on Shas. Several ministers said they imagined that he would.</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Ramon, long a liaison to Shas, sounded fed up today. ''One thing's for sure,'' he said. ''The mess is over. And the next coalition will be organized so that whoever votes against us is out the same day.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
