<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Florio, His Days as the 'Comeback Kid' May Be Over</title>
    <meta content="08FLOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRIMARY IN NEW JERSEY: THE LOSER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Florio, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6DC133FF93BA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Florio, His Days as the 'Comeback Kid' May Be Over</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, June 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses future political career of Jim Florio, following his losing Democratic primary for US Senate to Jon S Corzine (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a former boxer who once dared to fight with a broken cheekbone, Jim Florio, the politician, has endured countless analogies to his middleweight pugilist days. He lost the race for governor three times, once by 1,797 votes out of the 2.3 million cast, only to win the State House by an impressive margin in 1989.</p>
        <p>But after the knockout he suffered last night at the hands of Jon S. Corzine, Mr. Florio, a scrappy veteran of 16 political campaigns, may never again be described as a ''Comeback Kid.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As a former boxer who once dared to fight with a broken cheekbone, Jim Florio, the politician, has endured countless analogies to his middleweight pugilist days. He lost the race for governor three times, once by 1,797 votes out of the 2.3 million cast, only to win the State House by an impressive margin in 1989.</p>
        <p>But after the knockout he suffered last night at the hands of Jon S. Corzine, Mr. Florio, a scrappy veteran of 16 political campaigns, may never again be described as a ''Comeback Kid.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio has not spoken publicly about his plans for the future. And before the returns were in on Tuesday, he would not say whether he would ever run again. His friends and close associates said they thought there was little chance Mr. Florio, 62, a presence in New Jersey politics for three decades, would run again for elective office. Mr. Florio, who lost the race, 42 percent to 58 percent, spent the day with his wife, Lucinda, in their home in Metuchen.</p>
        <p>A campaign spokesman, Jim Lanard, said Mr. Florio was commiserating with friends and mulling his future. After months of media attention, Mr. Florio, he said, would not speak to the press. ''He needs some privacy,'' Mr. Lanard said. ''Besides, today is Mr. Corzine's day.''</p>
        <p>Having lost his previous two races, as well as the support of the state's Democratic organization, Mr. Florio, political analysts said, would have a hard time convincing even the most stalwart loyalists to fight with him another day. ''I can't imagine him running again,'' said Cliff Zukin, a political science professor at Rutgers University.</p>
        <p>Although he publicly conceded the race last night with graciousness and a smile, Mr. Florio, friends said, is still disappointed that his opponent spent $35 million to his $2 million. Just as disheartening, they say, is that a liberal Democrat chose to highlight the $2.8 billion tax increase Mr. Florio championed as governor. Lost in the welter of attack ads, they said, was the fact that Mr. Florio only did so because he was faced with a $600 million deficit and a court order to increase education spending in poor districts.</p>
        <p>''At one point, three different candidates were using Florio's tax in their commercials,'' said Chuck Chiarello, head of the Atlantic County Democratic Party. ''It was one man against the universe,'' he said. ''It made for pretty insurmountable odds.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio performed well in the southern portion of the state, especially in areas he represented during his 15 years in Congress. But in the more densely populated north, where Mr. Corzine enjoyed the support of the party, Mr. Florio lost badly. ''It's hard to make your voice heard when the Democratic organization is against you,'' Mr. Zukin said.</p>
        <p>His supporters said the negative tone of the race obscured Mr. Florio's accomplishments, and the media, always hungry for a good fight, helped pump up the tax issue. During his years as governor, they pointed out, Mr. Florio pushed through the nation's toughest assault weapon ban, cut insurance rates by 20 percent and solidified his reputation as a protector of the environment. During his first year as governor, there was even talk of a President Florio. But that was then.</p>
        <p>As they took stock today, campaign workers, supporters and friends said they hoped that at the very least Mr. Florio's legacy would be rehabilitated. They took heart that after years of deriding Mr. Florio for his tax hike, most newspapers in the state endorsed him for Senate, praising his record, principles and commitment to working people.</p>
        <p>Others said they thought such a high-profile loss would focus national attention on the need for campaign finance reform. Representative William Pascrell Jr. of Passaic, one of the few elected officials to stand by Mr. Florio's side last night, said he hoped the race would prod Congress to move on tougher rules for campaign finance and spending. ''If ever we needed proof, it was this election,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As for the future, Mr. Florio still has his law practice and a consulting business. He could always go back to teaching public policy, which is what he did at Rutgers University before he decided to run for the Senate. There is even talk he could be part of a Gore administration, if there is one.</p>
        <p>But one thing is sure, associates said. Mr. Florio will not spend his days in the pursuit of personal wealth. ''It might sound like puff, but Jim Florio is devoted to the public good,'' said Angelo Genova, a friend and a lawyer who worked for the Florio administration. ''He's not in it for the ego, or for the power.''</p>
        <p>Karen Kessler, who has worked as Mr. Florio's fund-raiser since 1989, said Mr. Florio is happiest as a public servant. ''After he lost the governor's race, he had no idea what he would do, and believe me, today is the same,'' she said.</p>
        <p>This time, however, things are different. He has experienced life outside politics, and at least he and his wife have a car, a home and furniture, none of which they had after Mr. Florio was voted out of Trenton in 1993. ''He's not in the same place,'' Ms. Kessler said.</p>
        <p>PRIMARY IN NEW JERSEY: THE LOSER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
