<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Both Sides Talk of Victory in Cable Ruling</title>
    <meta content="Y23NET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209572"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Portland (Ore)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">At&amp;t Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richtel, Matt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oregon/Portland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E0D81F31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1059" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Both Sides Talk of Victory in Cable Ruling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT RICHTEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richtel, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, June 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Appeals Court, reversing lower court, rules that local government cannot force cable company that offers Internet access to share its telecommunications lines with rival providers of cable modems; court, in ruling in favor of AT&amp;T in its case against City of Portland, Ore, defines cable broadband business as a 'telecommunications service,' a distinction some analysts say may ultimately force such businesses, including AT&amp;T, to open their lines to competitors nationally; decision leaves AT&amp;T, City of Portland and coalition of Internet companies seeking access to AT&amp;T's telecommunications lines each claiming victory in suit that has been closely watched by Internet industry; decision raises as many questions as it answers about how cable modem business will be regulated (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reversing a lower court, the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit ruled today that a local government could not force a cable company that offered Internet access to share its telecommunication lines with rival providers of cable modems.</p>
        <p>But in ruling in favor of AT&amp;T in its case against the City of Portland, Ore., the appeals court defined the cable broadband business as a ''telecommunications service,'' a distinction some analysts say may ultimately force such businesses, including AT&amp;T, to open their lines to competitors nationally.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reversing a lower court, the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit ruled today that a local government could not force a cable company that offered Internet access to share its telecommunication lines with rival providers of cable modems.</p>
        <p>But in ruling in favor of AT&amp;T in its case against the City of Portland, Ore., the appeals court defined the cable broadband business as a ''telecommunications service,'' a distinction some analysts say may ultimately force such businesses, including AT&amp;T, to open their lines to competitors nationally.</p>
        <p>The decision left AT&amp;T, the City of Portland and a coalition of Internet companies seeking access to AT&amp;T's telecommunications lines each claiming victory in a suit closely watched by the Internet industry.</p>
        <p>And it left industry analysts and telecommunications experts grappling with a decision they say raises as many questions as it answers about how the cable modem business will be regulated.</p>
        <p>''AT&amp;T won the battle but lost the war,'' said Scott Cleland, a regulatory analyst with the Legg Mason Precursor Group, a Washington-based market research firm. ''They lost the broader fight over whether their service is regulated or not.''</p>
        <p>But AT&amp;T executives disputed that assessment, arguing that it was premature to conclude that federal regulators would force them to open their cable lines to rivals. ''This is a complete victory,'' said Mark C. Rosenblum, an AT&amp;T vice president. ''Our point was that local authorities are not allowed to regulate telecommunication services, and we won.''</p>
        <p>Federal Communications Commission officials said the decision was likely to bring all sides in the dispute to Washington for clarification.</p>
        <p>Until now, the officials said, neither the cable industry nor its opponents had sought regulators' guidance on their view of the cable modem business. A central issue is whether cable modem operators are more like cable companies, which are not required to open their lines to rivals, or more like telephone companies, which must.</p>
        <p>''These are open questions on which the commission has not yet ruled and presumably will rule soon,'' an F.C.C. official said. ''I suspect all of this will be brought to our doorstep very soon.''</p>
        <p>More generally, the F.C.C. has embraced a policy it calls ''vigilant restraint'' with regard to Internet access, arguing that the marketplace -- not the government -- should determine which technologies prevail and which fall by the wayside.</p>
        <p>The case stemmed from a Portland City Council decision in December 1998 to make the transfer to AT&amp;T of a cable franchise owned by Tele-Communications Inc. contingent on AT&amp;T's opening access to its high-speed Internet connections. In June of last year, a federal judge in Portland upheld the move, despite objections from AT&amp;T that regulatory authority belonged to the federal government.</p>
        <p>The outcome of the case is of growing interest to major telecommunications providers, Internet access companies and a growing number of consumers seeking higher-speed Internet access.</p>
        <p>Access to the Internet over cable lines is one of the nascent technologies proffered as a high-speed alternative to the conventional dial-up Internet access, but its distribution has been held up in part by questions of whether local governments can decide who controls the lines.</p>
        <p>In light of today's decision, AT&amp;T said it would start offering the At Home cable modem service in Portland starting Friday. The company had refused to offer access previously because the Portland City Council mandated that if AT&amp;T offered its At Home service, it would have to offer service to rivals, as well.</p>
        <p>In December, AT&amp;T announced plans to give rivals access to its cable lines to deliver Internet access, asserting in a letter to the F.C.C. that access would be available by 2002. The company said it could not open the lines before that time because it had an exclusive deal to lease those lines to At Home, a high-speed cable service in which AT&amp;T holds a stake.</p>
        <p>Starting in November, AT&amp;T plans to conduct a trial in Boulder, Colo., in which rival Internet access providers will share the same cable lines. AT&amp;T says the effort will help it address unresolved technical problems with open access. But several local governments across the country, including Portland's, have sought to force AT&amp;T's hand, arguing that competition will yield faster, better-quality Internet access.</p>
        <p>Erik Sten, a Portland city commissioner, said today that the city had not decided whether to appeal the decision, in part because city officials viewed it as a partial victory. ''If the decision is interpreted as we think it will be,'' he said, AT&amp;T will be deemed to be a telecommunications service provider and thus required to open access on a national level.</p>
        <p>In its decision, the Ninth Circuit wrote that the ''principle of common carriage governs cable broadband as it does other means of Internet transmission such as telephone.''</p>
        <p>Portland, along with a coalition of Internet service providers, pointed to the language of the decision as evidence that AT&amp;T will ultimately be subject to the same regulatory requirements as local telephone companies, which must open their lines to rivals.</p>
        <p>''Open access is the law of the highest court that has reviewed this,'' said Greg Simon, co-director of the openNET Coalition, a group of Internet companies that supported Portland and other municipalities. ''The law is now open access in the Ninth Circuit.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Rosenblum of AT&amp;T said that even if the cable modem business were construed as a telecommunications service, it would not necessarily be subject to open-access requirements.</p>
        <p>The F.C.C. official said, meanwhile, that just because the Ninth Circuit defined AT&amp;T as a telecommunications service did not mean that the decision was a binding legal conclusion. The official said the question before the court was about Portland's right to regulate AT&amp;T, not about how AT&amp;T's status should be defined before the F.C.C.</p>
        <p>The official, as well as executives from AT&amp;T, also said that the court decision stated clearly that even if the cable modem business were deemed a telecommunications service, federal regulators had broad powers to exempt the technology from open-access requirements.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
