<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Statement on Travel Office Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="Y23TTE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209573"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ray, Robert W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0D81F31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Statement on Travel Office Inquiry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Transcipt of statement by independent counsel Robert W Ray on his investigation of firings at White House travel office in 1993 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following is the statement today by the independent counsel Robert W. Ray on his investigation of the firings at the White House travel office in 1993:</p>
        <p>The office of the independent counsel has concluded an investigation commonly known as the travel office matter. This matter concerned allegations that David Watkins, former assistant to the president for management and administration, and First Lady Hillary Rodham Clinton made false statements in violation of 18 U.S.C. 1001, committed perjury in violation of 18 U.S.C. 1621, or obstructed justice in violation of 18 U.S.C. 1503, in connection with their statements and testimony concerning the May 19, 1993, firing of seven employees of the White House travel office. Independent counsel has concluded that the evidence was insufficient to prove that Mr. Watkins or Mrs. Clinton made any knowingly false statements, committed perjury or obstructed justice in this matter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following is the statement today by the independent counsel Robert W. Ray on his investigation of the firings at the White House travel office in 1993:</p>
        <p>The office of the independent counsel has concluded an investigation commonly known as the travel office matter. This matter concerned allegations that David Watkins, former assistant to the president for management and administration, and First Lady Hillary Rodham Clinton made false statements in violation of 18 U.S.C. 1001, committed perjury in violation of 18 U.S.C. 1621, or obstructed justice in violation of 18 U.S.C. 1503, in connection with their statements and testimony concerning the May 19, 1993, firing of seven employees of the White House travel office. Independent counsel has concluded that the evidence was insufficient to prove that Mr. Watkins or Mrs. Clinton made any knowingly false statements, committed perjury or obstructed justice in this matter.</p>
        <p>With respect to Mr. Watkins, the evidence was insufficient to show that his statements, regarding whether Mrs. Clinton ordered him to fire the travel office employees or that she pressured him to do so, were knowingly false. Although there was some evidence that Mrs. Clinton's involvement had the effect of pressuring him to fire the travel office employees, that evidence was insufficient to prove beyond a reasonable doubt that Mr. Watkins's statements and testimony regarding that issue were knowingly false.</p>
        <p>Similarly, with respect to Mrs. Clinton, there was substantial evidence that she had a ''role'' in the decision to fire the travel office employees. She had discussions with deputy White House counsel Vince Foster, Chief of Staff Mack McLarty, and longtime friend and adviser Harry Thomason, and one direct telephone conversation with David Watkins (whose responsibilities included oversight and management of the travel office) in which she expressed her ''concerns'' regarding the travel office. These individuals discussed her concerns among themselves, which produced a momentum to take immediate action. Thus, Mrs. Clinton's concerns ultimately influenced Watkins's decision to fire the travel office employees.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the evidence was insufficient to prove to a jury beyond a reasonable doubt that any of Mrs. Clinton's statements and testimony regarding her involvement in the travel office firings were knowingly false. Accordingly, the independent counsel has declined prosecution of Mrs. Clinton as well.</p>
        <p>This office reached its conclusions only after completing an extensive investigation through the assistance of criminal investigators and F.B.I. agents already detailed to this office. These conclusions are the culmination of the investigative work of these agents and more than 10 attorneys, including assistant United States attorneys detailed by the Department of Justice to this Office, other career prosecutors, and senior O.I.C. staff. The investigation included a review of the voluminous record created by investigations by the House Committee on Government Reform and Oversight, the General Accounting Office, the Department of Justice Public Integrity Section and Office of Professional Responsibility, the inspector general for the Department of the Treasury, and the White House Management Review.</p>
        <p>In contrast to the cooperation received from the White House in the F.B.I. files investigation, concluded in March of this year, this office experienced substantial resistance in its efforts to obtain relevant evidence in the travel office matter. For example, the White House asserted unfounded privileges that were later rejected in court. White House officials also conducted inadequate searches for documents and failed to make timely production of documents, including relevant e-mails, in their possession. Despite these and other obstacles that substantially delayed the receipt of relevant evidence by this office, the independent counsel has concluded that the investigation may now be closed.</p>
        <p>This announcement, like the announcement at the conclusion of the F.B.I. files matter, is consistent with the statutory requirement relating to the conclusion of an investigation. At that time, an independent counsel is required by statute to submit a final report that ''set(s) forth fully and completely the work of the independent counsel.'' Congress has explained that the scope this provision requires ''independent counsels. . . . to provide a summary of the key steps taken in the investigatory and prosecutorial stages of their work and to explain the basis for their decisions.'' Congress described it as ''crucial'' to have ''a discussion of the conduct of the person for whom the independent counsel was appointed to office.'' This announcement serves to provide timely information to the public concerning the findings of the investigation with respect to Mr. Watkins and Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Under the independent counsel statute, a report filed with the special division remains under seal until such time, if at all, the special division authorizes its public release. Historically, public release occurs only after those persons named in a report are notified, pursuant to the statute, and have a full opportunity to read the relevant portions of the report that pertain to them and to prepare and file comments. This process typically takes several months after a report is filed.</p>
        <p>This office has now concluded its investigation into allegations relating to Mr. Watkins's and Mrs. Clinton's statements and testimony concerning the travel office firings and has fully discharged both of them from criminal liability for matters within this office's jurisdiction in the travel office matter. The matter is now closed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
