<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High Time For High Tech</title>
    <meta content="23INSI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000624T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209504"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INSIDE ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art Basel (Festival)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Miami Beach (Fla)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Getty, J Paul, Museum</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco Museum of Modern Art</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Whitney Museum of American Art</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walsh, John (Museum Director)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E0D61E31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High Time For High Tech</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>San Francisco Museum of Modern Art is mounting giant two-part show Art in Technological Times; photo; Whitney Museum will offer audio tours of permanent collection; Art Basel plans event in Miami Beach; John Walsh resigns as Gety Museum director (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, with no established exhibition like the Biennial surveys of contemporary work at the Whitney Museum of American Art, has decided to do the next best thing: take a theme, in this case technology, and take the pulse of contemporary art.</p>
        <p>''01.0.01: Art in Technological Times'' will be one giant exhibition in two parts. At one minute after midnight on Jan. 1, the museum, in collaboration with Intel, will open a show of Web-based work that will be available on the museum's Web site, www.sfmoma.org, and on a museum gallery site presented by Intel, www.Artmuseum.net.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, with no established exhibition like the Biennial surveys of contemporary work at the Whitney Museum of American Art, has decided to do the next best thing: take a theme, in this case technology, and take the pulse of contemporary art.</p>
        <p>''01.0.01: Art in Technological Times'' will be one giant exhibition in two parts. At one minute after midnight on Jan. 1, the museum, in collaboration with Intel, will open a show of Web-based work that will be available on the museum's Web site, www.sfmoma.org, and on a museum gallery site presented by Intel, www.Artmuseum.net.</p>
        <p>The second part of the show, from March 2 to July 8, consists of more than two dozen installations, video works, sound pieces and digital projects in the museum's galleries.</p>
        <p>Organized by five curatorial departments -- painting and sculpture, photography, architecture, design, and media arts and education -- the exhibition is to include about 35 artists, architects and designers whose work is responding to technology.</p>
        <p>''The Web has become the greatest venue for public art,'' said David A. Ross, the museum's director. ''It reaches directly to the viewer in a way that bypasses the museum as a physical space.''</p>
        <p>In deciding on a way of capturing what is happening in contemporary art, Mr. Ross said, ''art making in this moment is defined by technology.''</p>
        <p>Intel, the world's largest chip maker, has helped finance several art projects, notably ''American Century Art and Culture: 1900-2000'' at the Whitney last year, and the San Francisco show dovetails with the core of its business, said Kevin Teixeira, program manager for arts and technology at Intel.</p>
        <p>''Our interest is to see how artists are responding to our time and the impact technology is having,'' he said. While neither Mr. Teixeira nor Mr. Ross would say just how heavily Intel has invested in the exhibition, people involved in the project say the figure is close to $1 million.</p>
        <p>Asked if a survey exhibition would become a regularly scheduled event, Mr. Ross (who was director of the Whitney for seven years, overseeing its Biennial) said nothing had been decided.</p>
        <p>''On the West Coast there is no periodic exhibition to take the temperature of art of our time,'' he said. ''Let's see how people respond.''</p>
        <p>Listen Up</p>
        <p>The Whitney Museum never offered visitors audio guides until this spring's Biennial. But while most museums charge visitors for using audio guides, the Whitney's was free.</p>
        <p>It was also popular. About 30 percent of the 124,153 visitors to the show used it, twice the proportion who generally opt for a museum audio tour. This high success rate prompted the Whitney, with support from Cendant, the direct-marketing and hotel-franchise company, to begin offering visitors audio tours of its permanent collection.</p>
        <p>Beginning in October, visitors will be able to take an audio guide tour of the prewar work on the fifth floor and a new installation of postwar and contemporary collection on the second floor. The tour will trace the development of American art since the turn of the 20th century, with voices of critics, collectors, curators and other scholars. Visitors will also hear interviews with artists culled from the museum's archives as well as music.</p>
        <p>The tour will also be accessible at the museum's Web site, www.whitney.org, so that visitors can see images online and preview selected works from the tour before going to the museum.</p>
        <p>''We wanted this to be universally accessible,'' said Maxwell L. Anderson, the Whitney's director.</p>
        <p>The audio guides will offer new random-access equipment so visitors may view the collection in whatever order they choose. The guides will also be available in several languages yet to be determined.</p>
        <p>For tour groups, the museum will offer a new kind of audio guide system. Each person will have a unit the size of a cellular phone, and the guide will speak into a headset microphone so the group can clearly hear what is being said without disturbing other visitors.</p>
        <p>Southern Exposure</p>
        <p>Florida is becoming a hotbed of art and antiques fairs. Every February Palm Beach is the site of the International Art and Antique Fair. Now the organizers of Art Basel, the giant modern- and contemporary-art event held every June in Switzerland, are taking their show on the road. From Dec. 12 to 16 they will present a smaller version of the Basel fair in Miami Beach.</p>
        <p>This month the fair's management signed a multiyear contract with the City of Miami Beach and the Miami Beach Convention Center. About 270 dealers participate in the fair in Switzerland; in Miami the organizers expect 100 to 150. ''We also want the event to include architecture,'' said Samuel Keller, the show's manager. As a result the organizers plan to use various indoor and outdoor spaces throughout Miami Beach to show art. ''It's important to have it in a cultural context,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Miami Beach has its own contemporary-art scene, and Mr. Keller said fair organizers hoped to attract exhibitors and collectors from all over the United States as well as Latin America and Europe.</p>
        <p>Goodbye, Getty</p>
        <p>John Walsh announced this week that he was stepping down as vice president of the J. Paul Getty Trust and director of the Getty Museum after 17 years, effective on Sept. 30.</p>
        <p>The news came as no surprise in the art world. Even before the museum opened its sprawling $1 billion campus on a hilltop in Los Angeles two years ago, there were reports  that he was planning to leave once the building was completed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walsh is being replaced by Deborah Gribbon, the museum's chief curator, who has also been the Getty's deputy director for two years, overseeing the museum's day-to-day operations.</p>
        <p>INSIDE ART  Correction:  June 24, 2000, Saturday  The Inside Art column in Weekend yesterday omitted a numeral from the title of an exhibition scheduled to open on Jan. 1 at the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art. It is ''01.01.01: Art in Technological Times,'' not ''01.0.01.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 24, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>The Inside Art column in Weekend yesterday omitted a numeral from the title of an exhibition scheduled to open on Jan. 1 at the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art. It is ''01.01.01: Art in Technological Times,'' not ''01.0.01.''</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
