<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Chairman Makes Debut As Gore Camp Gets Bad News</title>
    <meta content="23DALE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209616"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEMOCRATS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daley, William M (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E0DE1630F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Chairman Makes Debut As Gore Camp Gets Bad News</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>NASHVILLE, June 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William M Daley, new chairman of Vice Pres Al Gore's presidential campaign, acknowledges on his first day at campaign headquarters that one of biggest challenges facing Gore is that Gov George W Bush, according to recent polls, is getting credit from voters for the economy, issue on which Gore has been basing his hopes; Daley photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>William M. Daley, the new chairman of Vice President Al Gore's presidential campaign, acknowledged today that one of the biggest challenges facing Mr. Gore was that Gov. George W. Bush was getting credit for the economy, the issue on which Mr. Gore had been basing his hopes.</p>
        <p>But, Mr. Daley said, that was a ''knee jerk'' reaction and he hoped to counter it by recruiting supporters from big business and labor to come to Nashville, where Mr. Gore's campaign is based.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>William M. Daley, the new chairman of Vice President Al Gore's presidential campaign, acknowledged today that one of the biggest challenges facing Mr. Gore was that Gov. George W. Bush was getting credit for the economy, the issue on which Mr. Gore had been basing his hopes.</p>
        <p>But, Mr. Daley said, that was a ''knee jerk'' reaction and he hoped to counter it by recruiting supporters from big business and labor to come to Nashville, where Mr. Gore's campaign is based.</p>
        <p>''He is right now,'' Mr. Daley said of Mr. Bush's receiving credit. ''I don't know if it's just kind of a gut thing, but Republicans have always historically got more credit for running the economy, and being good for the economy, even at the height of the deficit.</p>
        <p>''So I think we've got a challenge to remind people what things were like in 1992, and we've got a challenge to remind them that, fine, you may take this eight years of economic expansion for granted, but tough decisions were made.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Daley hastened to add that he understood the size of the task ahead of him. ''I'm not being Pollyannish about how difficult a presidential campaign is,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daley, the secretary of commerce, spoke in an interview here as he made his debut in Mr. Gore's headquarters as chairman on a day when the Gore camp had to absorb another round of bad news.</p>
        <p>A Justice Department official has recommended that an independent counsel be named to investigate Mr. Gore's role in the Democrats' questionable fund-raising activities of 1996. Two new national polls showed Mr. Gore slipping further behind Mr. Bush. And James P. Hoffa, the powerful labor leader, appeared with Ralph Nader, the Green Party candidate who could siphon enough votes from Mr. Gore to cost him a few key states.</p>
        <p>A new Wall Street Journal/NBC News poll, taken during the start of Mr. Gore's ''prosperity and progress tour,'' which was intended to showcase the booming economy, put Mr. Bush ahead of Mr. Gore 49 percent to 41 percent. A bipartisan Battleground 2000/Voter.com poll showed Mr. Bush ahead by 12 percentage points.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daley said that part of his task would be to bring business and labor interests together and urge officials to move to Nashville to dedicate themselves to Mr. Gore's candidacy. The Wall Street Journal poll showed that voters give Mr. Gore an advantage of only a single percentage point -- statistically meaningless -- on his ability to handle the economy.</p>
        <p>''We want to get people from labor and business down here,'' Mr. Daley said in an interview in his office, which will serve as his command post until the November election. ''I'm asking people, 'You want to help? Fine. When are you going to leave your job and come to Nashville?' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Daley takes the reins officially on July 15, when he leaves his cabinet post. He succeeds Tony Coelho, the campaign's former chairman, who resigned last week for health reasons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coelho said in an interview with Bloomberg.com that his health was worse than he had indicated last week. In addition to his epilepsy and inflammation of the colon, he told the news service, he has a brain cyst, though he does not know whether it is malignant.</p>
        <p>''My seizures were getting worse,'' Mr. Coelho said of his epilepsy. ''I was having stomach cramps, but I would work my way through them. I just had too much to do. Then, my sinuses above my eyes got infected and they became inflamed and shut down, basically.''</p>
        <p>After arriving from Washington, Mr. Daley met with Tennessee Democrats this morning. He then shook hands with all the campaign staff, including about 80 paid workers and 70 interns and volunteers, at their desks, and spoke to them collectively for about 15 minutes. Listeners described his comments in the meeting, which was closed to reporters, as welcoming and inspirational.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daley described his message to the staff as being ''all about grinding it out for four and a half months.''</p>
        <p>He said in the interview that it was too soon to discuss any changes he had in mind, but he cautioned that the campaign would ''not lurch this way and that.''</p>
        <p>''You just lay out a strategy and go for it, and you don't jump around,'' he said. ''It's really easy for someone who's not following the ebb and flow every day to be criticizing it. You've got to really get into it to understand what the hell's going on, and that takes a while.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEMOCRATS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
