<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House Auctions Gain Favor in an eBay World</title>
    <meta content="Y23AUC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Irvington (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Homebid.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fatato, Gloria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fatato, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E7D71F31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1449" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House Auctions Gain Favor in an eBay World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>IRVINGTON, N.Y., June 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Americans are beginning to sell their houses and apartments by means of auctions, whether in person or through Internet sites like Homebid.com; method appeals to time-pressed generation that has grown use to buying and selling things on e-Bay; was once associated with lavish estates or foreclosed homes, but is now being used for properties in between; residential auctions are more common abroad and are the norm in Australia; some traditional brokers dismiss auctions as marketing ploys or annoying competition; home of Thomas and Gloria Fatato in Irvington, NY, fetches top bid of $975,000, to which the buyer must add 10 percent for auction company; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The auction was barely under way, but already, Thomas and Gloria Fatato were feeling out of place in the Tudor-style house they had built 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>Strangers were nibbling on hors d'oeuvres and sipping on fume blanc. A ponytailed musician teased out ''Puttin' on the Ritz'' and ''Cheek to Cheek'' on a Yamaha synthesizer. A veritable army of auctioneers from the National Auction Group of Gadsden, Ala., all wearing matching American-flag ties, were doing their officious best to prod, prod, prod.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The auction was barely under way, but already, Thomas and Gloria Fatato were feeling out of place in the Tudor-style house they had built 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>Strangers were nibbling on hors d'oeuvres and sipping on fume blanc. A ponytailed musician teased out ''Puttin' on the Ritz'' and ''Cheek to Cheek'' on a Yamaha synthesizer. A veritable army of auctioneers from the National Auction Group of Gadsden, Ala., all wearing matching American-flag ties, were doing their officious best to prod, prod, prod.</p>
        <p>Then, when the bidding for the Fatatos' house stagnated at $975,000, one of the guys with the American-flag ties, Jack Ogle, rapped his knuckles on a glass shelf in the living room. In a Southern drawl, he bellowed: ''That's opportunity knocking tonight like it's never knocked before in this area!''</p>
        <p>So maybe the modus operandi was not pitch-perfect for the grizzled New York crowd. Still, for most people at the auction held here this month, this odd cocktail of one part culture clash, one part high-stakes poker, was their first taste of a national phenomenon that has proliferated in recent years: the sale of houses and apartments at auction.</p>
        <p>These slickly promoted events with the trappings of a wedding or a fund-raiser are a far cry from the enduring image of a foreclosed house being sold on the courthouse steps. Instead, the auctions appeal to a faster-paced, time-pressed society accustomed to speculating on art, stocks and everything else, in person or over the Internet -- a society, in short, with an eBay mentality.</p>
        <p>''We have a whole generation of Internet babies who love the auctions and are used to it,'' said Lee Mills, a lawyer, investment banker and powerboat racer from Key West, Fla., whose 13-acre estate in Woodstock, N.Y., was sold at auction for a higher-than-expected $2 million several years ago. ''It's a lot of entertainment, a lot of theater, and I believe it's the trend of the future.''</p>
        <p>Auctioneers and real estate brokers estimate that there are now at least 1,000 auctions of residential properties around the country each year, compared with 200 five years ago and only a handful 10 years ago. Meanwhile, the value of all forms of real estate sold at auction increased from $21 billion in 1986 to $49 billion in 1998, according to the Gwent Group, an auction-research company in Bloomington, Ind.</p>
        <p>On average the auctions can net 80 to 90 percent of the property's appraised value, which is a shade below what traditional sales can bring. But some traditional brokers dismiss the auctions as marketing ploys or annoying competition, said Jan Tarnow, manager of the auction department of the National Association of Realtors. ''There's still some of that us-versus-them mentality,'' she said.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, these auctions usually involved lavish estates of thousands of acres, owned by people like former Senator Lloyd Bentsen and the singer Kenny Rogers. On June 8, Christie's Realty International auctioned off a newly listed 2,800-square-foot brownstone on Manhattan's East Side designed by Philip Johnson and once owned by Blanchette Rockefeller. The winning bid was $11.16 million -- more than double the estimate -- and set a record for the highest sale price per square foot in Manhattan, according to Christie's. (The winning bidder was not disclosed; one of the nonwinners was Mr. Mills.)</p>
        <p>Now, though, the auctions are also becoming less stratospheric. On Sunday, Sheldon Good &amp; Company, a Chicago company, plans to auction off 50 condominiums in Battery Park City and Midtown Manhattan for $200,000 to $800,000 apiece, both in person and over the Internet, said Steven L. Good, the company's chief executive.</p>
        <p>In other countries, particularly Australia, selling real estate at auction is considered the norm. But in the United States, the word ''auction'' still conjures up bad images, dating back to the Depression era, of fast-talking hucksters preying upon vulnerable people. And the recent fiasco involving a painting's price being manipulated on eBay doesn't help.</p>
        <p>For some people, too, the packaging -- Want a mariachi band? A harpist? Some bacon-wrapped quail? -- is a distraction and a gimmick.</p>
        <p>''It was a circus,'' grumbled John Aronian III, a retired surgeon in Westchester who attended the Fatatos' auction. ''It was good ol' boys from down South. It was like a hog auction.''</p>
        <p>Then again, with prime real estate still in short supply in a good economy, more buyers and sellers are willing to gamble on an auction to create good prices.</p>
        <p>For sellers, auctions may be appealing because they can greatly accelerate the sales process, reducing the costs of a mortgage, taxes, insurance and maintenance. Buyers, who must bring a certified check to the auction -- $50,000 in the Irvington sale -- are expected to do their own inspections or buy the house on an as-is basis. They then have a set period of time, usually 30 days, to arrange financing and set a closing date.</p>
        <p>And a growing number of sellers are opting for auctions because their job or family situation has changed suddenly, or their property is unusual, said J. Craig King, president of the J. P. King Auction Company, in Gadsden, Ala.</p>
        <p>People are naturally competitive, too. At an auction, it is not just a matter of keeping up with the Joneses, but eclipsing the Joneses, and in their presence.</p>
        <p>''Watch the people sizing each other up: it's like, 'Hmm,' '' said Barbara Corcoran, president of the Corcoran Group, a Manhattan real estate company, which plans to auction properties solely on the Internet. ''It puts any French cafe to shame.''</p>
        <p>Or, as William R. Bone, president of the National Auction Group, put it: ''It reaches a point where egos take over. It's not dollars and cents; it's egos.''</p>
        <p>On a recent Tuesday, it was the Fatatos' turn. The owner of a beer distribution company in the Bronx, Mr. Fatato, 58, and his wife, 52, had tried unsuccessfully for more than a year to sell their house to move to a smaller one in Rockland County. The original price was $1.7 million, but the house was too opulent for the neighborhood, with glass-and-mirror decor that had not changed since it was designed 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, rain forced the event indoors. Still, there were 10 bidders, an unusually high number, most of whom did not want to give their names.</p>
        <p>Some were young professionals from Manhattan. At least two people were considering auctions for their own properties, one on the Hudson River, the other in Litchfield, Conn. Everyone was itching with expectation.</p>
        <p>Then, shortly after 8 p.m., show time. The auctioneer, Eddie Haynes, a member of the Oklahoma Auctioneers Hall of Fame, tried to oil the crowd with folksy charm. First, he auctioned off a bottle of Dom Perignon to Mr. Fatato for $125 for charity. Then he asked loudly: ''We having fun yet?''</p>
        <p>''I'm having fun!'' blurted another auctioneer, Wayne Thorn.</p>
        <p>The Fatatos chose perhaps the riskiest method: an absolute auction, without reserve and without a minimum bid, where the final price is the final price, even if it is $1. The Fatatos did have the option to cancel at the last minute, but they did not, and soon, Mr. Haynes started the bidding at $750,000.</p>
        <p>It was a loud and chaotic scene, with people spilling into the living, dining, kitchen and foyer areas. And slowly, tentatively, the price climbed; past $800,000, past $900,000.</p>
        <p>When the bidding halted at $975,000, Mr. Haynes tried repeatedly to whip the crowd into a frenzy, to no avail. The hammer price was $975,000, bid by a young Russian immigrant family in Manhattan, said their broker, Neil Singh.</p>
        <p>The final price, actually, was almost $1.1 million, because of the additional 10 percent charged by the auction company.</p>
        <p>The Fatatos were overwhelmed and exhausted by the experience. ''You put your whole life into their hands, and whatever they say, you believe,'' Mr. Fatato said, a few days after the auction. ''Who knows, it could have gone higher. But it happened so quick. I'm still trying to figure it out.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
