<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Steinbrenner's Brain Trust Considers Its Many Options</title>
    <meta content="23TORR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E6DD1630F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="424" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Steinbrenner's Brain Trust Considers Its Many Options</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, June 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses speculation concerning possible trades under consideration by New York Yankees (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>George Steinbrenner had lunch with Joe Torre and Don Zimmer at Suffolk Downs race track today, and the horses were obviously not the only topic that they discussed. The Yankees are contemplating improving their team by adding a pitcher or injecting a power hitter like Juan Gonzalez or Sammy Sosa, so the owner, the manager and the bench coach undoubtedly talked about numerous scenarios.</p>
        <p>But after Torre casually mentioned that he had eaten with Steinbrenner, the manager was skimpy with details of their conversation. Torre has been reluctant to answer hypothetical questions about trade possibilities since last week, and he maintained that stance today even though he was responsible for informing reporters about the interestingly timed lunch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>George Steinbrenner had lunch with Joe Torre and Don Zimmer at Suffolk Downs race track today, and the horses were obviously not the only topic that they discussed. The Yankees are contemplating improving their team by adding a pitcher or injecting a power hitter like Juan Gonzalez or Sammy Sosa, so the owner, the manager and the bench coach undoubtedly talked about numerous scenarios.</p>
        <p>But after Torre casually mentioned that he had eaten with Steinbrenner, the manager was skimpy with details of their conversation. Torre has been reluctant to answer hypothetical questions about trade possibilities since last week, and he maintained that stance today even though he was responsible for informing reporters about the interestingly timed lunch.</p>
        <p>''We talked,'' Torre said. ''Let's just say we talked about baseball.''</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner was at Fenway Park for the third straight game tonight, but, like Torre, the Yankees' principal owner has been silent about trade possibilities. Steinbrenner waved away reporters who approached him on Tuesday and deferred questions about the probability of a trade to Torre and General Manager Brian Cashman. Still, Steinbrenner said, ''We better do something, don't you think?'' after a recent loss, and it is doubtful that his feelings have changed.</p>
        <p>''He's not happy,'' Torre said about Steinbrenner. ''None of us are. Any time El Duque is a question mark and Clemens is on the disabled list, you're always looking to help your club. I think we all realize we're in pretty good shape in spite of what has happened.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees' 4-2 loss to Boston last night left them one-half game behind the Red Sox in the American League East, and there are strong indications that they will still make some kind of move to improve their team. Torre said that Steinbrenner, known for ranting when he wants to make a point, is usually mellow when they meet.</p>
        <p>Before Torre began offering brief responses to questions about possible trades, he was asked last week if it bothered him that Steinbrenner had told reporters that the two-time defending World Series champion Yankees needed to do something.</p>
        <p>''Does it bother me?'' Torre said. ''No, it doesn't bother me. I know who I work for. What seems like a negative may be a positive. He's always willing to help. He's always willing to reach into his pocket and win.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
