<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POP AND CLASSIC</title>
    <meta content="23POP.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209512"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5DF1F31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="4483" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POP AND CLASSIC</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy pop and jazz concerts in the New York metropolitan region this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended concert.</p>
        <p>TONY ALLEN, Joe's Pub, Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200. Mr. Allen was the drummer in the great band led by Fela Anikulapo Kuti through the 1970's, and his loose-limbed playing can be traced back to the style of Elvin Jones. He is basically a formidable jazz drummer from West Africa playing funk and reggae-inspired grooves -- not so hard to imagine, but he's better than you might imagine. On his latest album, ''Black Voices'' (Comet), a dub-reggae-inspired production, he creates sudden disappearances and reappearances of those hypnotic rhythms. Sunday at 8:30 p.m.; tickets are $25 (Ben Ratliff).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy pop and jazz concerts in the New York metropolitan region this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended concert.</p>
        <p>TONY ALLEN, Joe's Pub, Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200. Mr. Allen was the drummer in the great band led by Fela Anikulapo Kuti through the 1970's, and his loose-limbed playing can be traced back to the style of Elvin Jones. He is basically a formidable jazz drummer from West Africa playing funk and reggae-inspired grooves -- not so hard to imagine, but he's better than you might imagine. On his latest album, ''Black Voices'' (Comet), a dub-reggae-inspired production, he creates sudden disappearances and reappearances of those hypnotic rhythms. Sunday at 8:30 p.m.; tickets are $25 (Ben Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* BAMBOLEO, Celebrate Brooklyn, Prospect Park Band Shell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 855-7882, extension 45, and the Copacabana, 617 West 57th Street, Clinton, (212) 582-2672. Cuban dance bands hone their music through constant performing, and Bamboleo has turned itself into a feverish groove generator, with horns and percussion bearing down until the music explodes. Songs may start out as sappy salsa romantica, but sooner rather than later the groove shoves any cloying tendencies aside. Sharing the bill at Celebrate Brooklyn is Barbarito Torres, who was in the Buena Vista Social Club. His group plays courtly, old-fashioned Cuban sones, but his solos on the laud, a Cuban lute, are jagged, syncopated bursts of modern angularity. Tonight at 7:30; admission is free. At the Copacabana, Bamboleo shares the bill with the Puerto Rican cuatro (small guitar) virtuoso Yomo Toro, the flutist and band leader Johnny Pacheco and the singer Adalberto Santiago; they will perform charanga, an older style featuring flute and violin. Tomorrow around 10 p.m.; tickets are $15 before 11, $25 after (Jon Pareles).</p>
        <p>KENNY BANKS, CHOCOLATE GENIUS, Celebrate Brooklyn, Prospect Park Band Shell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 855-7882, Extension 45. Kenny Banks was a songwriter who collaborated on Kool and the Gang hits, including ''Celebration'' and ''Ladies' Night''; he now leads his own band, the Rhythm Makers. Marc Anthony Thompson, a k a Chocolate Genius, writes desolate, telling, unsparing songs about goodbyes and sings them in a glumly impassioned voice. Tomorrow at 7:30 p.m.; admission is free (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* BRIAN BLADE FELLOWSHIP, Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037. The young Mr. Blade, a former sideman for the young jazz icon Joshua Redman and one of the greatest drummers in the last decade of American music, writes for an expanded small group that doesn't sound remotely like anything else in jazz. It's sentimental, sometimes hymnlike music -- a bit cinematic, but for a very interior sort of movie. Sets through Sunday are at 9:30 and 11:30 p.m., with a 1 a.m. set tonight and tomorrow; cover charge is $20 tonight and tomorrow and $15 on Sunday, with a $10 minimum (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* RAY CHARLES, REGINA CARTER, Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500. If Ray Charles isn't the greatest American singer, he is definitely one of the top contenders. His voice is full of pain and jubilation, cockiness and despair, wisdom and impulsiveness; he knows American music from the blues to Tin Pan Alley to gospel to jazz. And with any luck, he'll let his piano-playing come through the sound system. Sharing the bill is the jazz violinist Regina Carter, who rides her vamps with ebullient, tuneful solos. Tonight at 8; tickets are $20 to $60; only $60 are left (Pareles).</p>
        <p>COMMON, TONY ALLEN, Central Park Summerstage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777. Wisdom and rhythm blend in two streams during this show. Common began his stellar rap career in Illinois, but lately he has been hanging out with righteous fellow souls, like Mos Def and the Roots, in these parts. Expect a special guest or two. The drummer Tony Allen helped invent Afrobeat as the musical director of Fela Kuti's Afrika 70's troupe; he has been experimenting in Europe for two decades, and he will bring his latest blend to Summerstage. Also on the bill is Ex-Centric Sound System, which makes Ghanaian dance music by way of Israel and the electronic universe. Tomorrow at 3 p.m.; admission is free (Ann Powers).</p>
        <p>* CONGA KINGS, CHICO HAMILTON, JVC Jazz Festival, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-1414. The Conga Kings trio was convened for a recent CD on the Chesky record label; it combines three of the greatest living congueros in Latin music: the Cubans Candido Camero and Carlos Valdes (who is known as Patato), and Giovanni Hidalgo, a Puerto Rican musician a generation younger. All three have worked extensively with jazz as well as with Latin music, and backed by a small old-fashioned conjunto including the tres, flute and bass, they'll offer virtuosity in layers. Opening is the drummer Chico Hamilton, one of the more adventuresome composers in jazz, whose career has stretched from the days when his cool chamber jazz was featured in the 1957 film ''Sweet Smell of Success.'' The concert is tonight at 8, and tickets are $31 (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* BILL FRISELL NEW QUARTET, JVC Jazz Festival, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-1414. Bill Frisell, the most widely imitated guitarist to emerge in jazz since the beginning of the 1980's, was once drawn to vaulting, heavily electrified sounds, with notes rounded into massive bubbles by an application of the volume pedal. But lately he has been making his music smaller and more homely, with a particular inclination toward the textures of country and acoustic blues. This new band includes the steel guitarist Greg Leisz, so it's bound to have a bit of honky-tonk in it. The concert is tomorrow at 8 p.m.; tickets are $31 (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* HERBIE HANCOCK GROUP, DIANNE REEVES, JVC Jazz Festival, Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 496-7070. After several years of disappointing performances in New York, Mr. Hancock gave a great one a few months back at the Blue Note. He was playing a concert geared to his latest album, ''Gershwin's World'' (Verve/Universal), as he will be this weekend, and hardly a Gershwin melody was played; instead Mr. Hancock introduced tunes as impressions, and with his unusual band (including the trumpeter Eddie Henderson, an interesting young saxophonist named Ele Gigibri and the percussionist Cyro Baptista) played with the rhythms of the songs and turned them into vamps. It worked; it was not only a playful subversion of Gershwin but also a subversion of Mr. Hancock's own album, and it was one of the memorable concerts of the year. The singer Dianne Reeves, a top-shelf professional, never seems to have a bad night; she has extraordinary control over her voice, and her material, recently arranged by her cousin George Duke, combines jazz standards with pop and Brazilian tunes, and her own compositions. The show is tomorrow at 8 p.m.; tickets are $25 and $50 (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* RALPH IRIZARRY AND TIMBALAYE, JOVENES DEL BARRIO, WAYNE GORBEA AND SALSA PICANTE, JVC Jazz Festival, Bryant Park, Avenue of the Americas at 40th Street,  Mr. Irizarry used to be the timbales player in Ruben Blades's band, and he is both percussion-minded and composition-minded, putting congas and timbales up front both literally (onstage) and metaphorically (in his well-integrated Latin-jazz arrangements). His music has impact and a lot of brains. He leads an all-Latin bill at one of JVC's free lunchtime concerts, today from noon to 2 p.m. today (Ratliff)</p>
        <p>* ELVIN JONES JAZZ MACHINE, Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 475-8592. If you're a drummer, you probably already have a reservation. Elvin Jones is one of the most important musicians in postwar jazz. He is pretty much as responsible for what we know to be the Coltrane sound as Coltrane himself; he is authoritative even playing with nothing but mallets and toms. Sets are tonight through Sunday at 9 and 11:30 p.m.; cover charge is $35 at tables or $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>*B. B. KING, B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 243 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144. B. B. King and his latest guitar called Lucille can, on a good night, summon all the tribulation and joy and resilience of the blues. He has just released an album with Eric Clapton, and he is playing one of his rare club shows in the Times Square branch of his own club. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 and 10 p.m.; cover charge is $50, with a two-drink minimum; tomorrow night is sold out but standing room is available for $30 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* LITTLE RICHARD, B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 243 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144. Rock 'n' roll wouldn't be the same without the whoops and hollers, the pounding barrelhouse piano chords and swooping glissandos that Little Richard hurled onto his singles in the 1950's. Preaching from the piano stool and belting songs like ''Tutti Frutti,'' he's still a force for creative anarchy. Sunday and Monday at 9:30 p.m.; admission is $65 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>BILLY NAYER SHOW, Fez, 380 Lafayette Street, at Great Jones Street, East Village, (212) 533-2680. Fans of Tom Waits and twisted cabaret should check out this longtime favorite from the San Francisco Bay Area. Cory McAbee inhabits the Nayer persona, which mutates into various damaged American types within clunky art-pop complemented by bizarre short films. Fun. Tomorrow at 9:30 p.m.; tickets are $10 (Powers).</p>
        <p>* NRBQ, Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 798-0406. After 30 years on the road, NRBQ still loves the same basic rock ingredients: the ingratiating melodies of 1960's pop, the twang and two-beat of rockabilly and the splashy, rowdy piano playing that links Jerry Lee Lewis to Sun Ra. The group's huge repertory includes old rhythm-and-blues, obscure pop gems, children's songs and plenty of NRBQ; if it's in the mood, the band takes requests. Tomorrow at 7:30 and 10:30 p.m.; admission is $15 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* MACEO PARKER, BRUCE HORNSBY, Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 496-7070. There was a reason James Brown used to shout ''Maceo!'' in the middle of a funk workout. Maceo Parker was the alto saxophonist who drove the horn section in James Brown's groundbreaking J. B.'s and went on to work for George Clinton's Parliament-Funkadelic. His group knows the secrets of getting on the good foot. Bruce Hornsby, who spent much of the 1990's touring as the pianist with the Grateful Dead and its spinoffs, is back with his own songs about the modern South. Tonight at 8; tickets are $25 and $40 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>EDDIE PALMIERI, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800. What was to be a summit meeting of two giants of Latin jazz -- the pianist Eddie Palmieri and the percussionist Tito Puente -- has now become a tribute to Mr. Puente, who died on May 31. Mr. Palmieri's music is brilliantly volatile, leaping from fierce dance vamps to splashy, experimental modal jazz to deep traditional rumba percussion. He is an experimenter who knows how to carry listeners wherever he wants to go. He'll be leading his aggressive big band, joined by the singers Cheo Feliciano and Domingo Quinones, along with the saxophonist David Sanchez. Tomorrow at 8 p.m.; tickets are $20 to $65 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>ZEENA PARKINS, SEBASTIAN STEINBERG, CHRIS COCHRANE, SIM CAIN, Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7503. Where but in downtown Manhattan could an experimental harpist get it on with an ex-pop star bassist, an avant-punk guitarist and a sometime-hardcore drummer? Tomorrow at 8 p.m; admission is $10 (Powers).</p>
        <p>DAVID POE, Fez, 380 Lafayette Street, at Great Jones Street, East Village, (212) 533-2680. Where did you go, David Poe? The New York-based singing-and-strumming sensitive guy is taking so long to make the follow-up to his promising debut album (four years!) that his fans are starting to wonder if he got stuck in one of the haunted houses thought up by that other Poe guy. Rumor has it the younger Mr. Poe is recording in Virginia; one hopes he will serve up some new material tonight, with a full band. With the Driver Quartet. Tonight at 9:30; tickets are $10 (Powers).</p>
        <p>SIMON SHAHEEN AND QANTARA, THE ISRAELI ANDALUSIAN ORCHESTRA, Central Park Summerstage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777. Qantara is the fusion group led by the oud and violin virtuoso Simon Shaheen in a sideline to his masterly performances of the Arabic classical repertory. The group finds the Arabic thread that runs through flamenco and jazz, with improvisations full of modal melodies and fleet hand-drum rhythms. It shares the bill with the Israeli Andalusian Orchestra, whose music harks back more than 500 years, before Jews were expelled from Spain: stately melodies with cantorial inflections, carried by string orchestra. On Sunday afternoon, Cheb I Sabbah opens with a disc-jockey set at 5 p.m., with Simon Shaheen at 6:30 and the Israeli Andalusian Orchestra at 7:45. Admission is free (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* CASSANDRA WILSON, CESARIA EVORA, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800. A double bill of contralto heaven: both Cassandra Wilson and Cesaria Evora have built repertories around deep, husky voices full of worldly experience. Ms. Wilson, who is steeped in Sarah Vaughan, Betty Carter and Joni Mitchell, moved beyond jazz purism to embrace songs from Robert Johnson to U2; her band can invoke Miles Davis modalities or slide-guitar blues. Ms. Evora walks on stage barefoot, usually with a cigarette in hand, to sing about heartache and melancholy, longing and bittersweet memories. Her music is morna, tavern songs from the Cape Verde Islands off Senegal, with melodies that are as graceful and knowing as the Mona Lisa's smile. Tonight at 8; tickets are $20 to $65 (Pareles).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
