<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Los Angeles Subway Reaches End of the Line</title>
    <meta content="Y23SUB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209576"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4D71F31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1146" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Los Angeles Subway Reaches End of the Line</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Imminent opening of last 6.3 miles of Los Angeles subway line will complete the most expensive subway in nation, 17.4 miles at cost of more than $4.5 billion; original plans were for a more extensive system were abandoned after fifteen years of construction delays, cost overruns and other problems; subway connects to 42-mile light rail line and next big proposal is for connection with express bus system; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Saturday morning the Los Angeles Red Line, long derided as the subway to nowhere, will at last be a subway to somewhere: from downtown to suburban San Fernando Valley, to be precise.</p>
        <p>The opening of the last 6.3 miles of track under the Hollywood hills will complete the most expensive subway in the nation's history, 17.4 miles at a cost of more than $4.5 billion, originally planned as the first stretch of a more extensive system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Saturday morning the Los Angeles Red Line, long derided as the subway to nowhere, will at last be a subway to somewhere: from downtown to suburban San Fernando Valley, to be precise.</p>
        <p>The opening of the last 6.3 miles of track under the Hollywood hills will complete the most expensive subway in the nation's history, 17.4 miles at a cost of more than $4.5 billion, originally planned as the first stretch of a more extensive system.</p>
        <p>But as it turns out, the start of service to North Hollywood marks an end as well as a beginning, and the city's first subway line will almost certainly be its last. Fifteen years of construction delays, accidents, cost overruns and a changed political climate have led voters to block further use of local sales tax revenue for subway construction, and forced leaders to look elsewhere for mass transit solutions to growing problems with traffic and urban sprawl.</p>
        <p>In fact, on the very day the three new subway stops open, the Metropolitan Transportation Authority will introduce the next big proposal: 80 express buses outfitted with transponders that signal wire loops in the pavement to hold green lights (or shorten red ones) so buses can speed through intersections.</p>
        <p>The new service, the most extensive use of such new technology in the nation, will begin on major thoroughfares that link up with the subway: Ventura Boulevard in the San Fernando Valley and Wilshire Boulevard from the Pacific Ocean in Santa Monica to the city of Montebello, 26 miles to the east.</p>
        <p>Transportation officials hope to lure at least 100,000 riders a day to the completed subway line, a trickle in a county that has 10 million residents and 6 million motor vehicles. Since ground was broken for the subway in 1986, bus ridership on the city's transportation system, the nation's most crowded, has fallen from about 500 million passengers a year to fewer than 400 million as money has been shifted to pay for subway construction and fares have risen to $1.35 from 50 cents.</p>
        <p>''If they get 100,000 riders a day, given the billions that have been spent, that would flunk any cost-benefit analysis that we could imagine,'' said Peter Gordon, a professor of urban and regional planning at the University of Southern California who is a longtime subway critic. ''So it's hard to take the project seriously as a transportation project. It's a pork-barrel jobs project and a political project.</p>
        <p>''The crowning insanity,'' Professor Gordon added, ''is that there are still toilet-trained adults walking around who say: 'Isn't this cool? Haven't we done a good thing?' ''</p>
        <p>The new subway is undeniably cool, with quiet, stainless-steel-skinned trains whooshing through twin tunnels in the Santa Monica Mountains, at their deepest 900 feet below Mulholland Drive.</p>
        <p>Each new station is designed to be an architectural jewel, with visual motifs representing each neighborhood's history. For example, ceilings in the North Hollywood stop are painted in concentric rings of soft yellows, orange and green, a testament to the area's citrus-growing past.</p>
        <p>A raft of dignitaries, including Mayor Richard J. Riordan, are expected at the dedication on Friday, but even the subway's biggest boosters strike an ambivalently celebratory note.</p>
        <p>''How do I feel?'' asked Representative Julian C. Dixon, an 11-term Democrat from central Los Angeles who helped win federal money for the project after some Los Angeles politicians tried to block it. ''I'm glad that we now have the beginnings of a comprehensive rail system that has meaningful transportation destinations. But I'm disappointed that there's a prohibition on local money, and I think ultimately we're going to have to re-examine that issue because cars on the streets and congestion are a growing problem that has to be dealt with.''</p>
        <p>Long a dream of former Mayor Tom Bradley, the subway was enthusiastically embraced by the establishment before falling victim to infighting, route changes and seemingly endless setbacks, from the giant sinkhole that opened on Hollywood Boulevard in 1995 to the deaths of three construction workers in 1997.</p>
        <p>When construction began, the mix of hard rock and soft shale under the mountains made digging difficult; at one point a boring machine was stuck for weeks. By 1998, cost overruns and a threatened cutoff of federal money led to the scrapping of planned extensions to East Los Angeles and central Los Angeles and a planned light rail line to Pasadena, leaving just the 17-mile Red Line.</p>
        <p>The Pasadena line has since been revived, and is to be finished by 2003. The overall system also includes two surface light rail lines.</p>
        <p>For several years, transit experts have been pressing for enhanced bus service. The new express bus, dubbed Metro Rapid, is a first test of such options; if it proves successful, officials hope to expand it.</p>
        <p>In the pilot project, which officials call a ''rubber-tire railway,'' a radio transmitter underneath special low-riding buses sends a signal that can turn a red light at an approaching intersection green, or hold a green light for up to 10 seconds.</p>
        <p>Each bus's signal identifies it by number, and the coded information is transmitted through copper wire and fiber-optic cable to the command center of the city's Department of Transportation. If a bus is late, the computer tells the light to wait.</p>
        <p>Some rider groups oppose the new bus service, contending that it is not extensive enough and that it will result in the elimination of some existing express bus service in the San Fernando Valley. Others worry about the effect on north-south cross traffic.</p>
        <p>''That's something we're definitely going to monitor,'' said John E. Fisher, an assistant general manager of the transportation department. ''It could be a possible minor problem on Wilshire, but we don't believe that an extra five seconds will be much of an impediment. And all traffic on the east-west streets will get the benefit if a green light gets lengthened for the bus.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
