<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Evidence of Water Invigorates Study of Mars</title>
    <meta content="Y23MAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Global Surveyor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Science (Journal)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malin, Michael C (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edgett, Kenneth S (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE4D81F31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1088" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Evidence of Water Invigorates Study of Mars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Warren E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Researchers say pictures taken by NASA's Mars Global Surveyor spacecraft suggest that Mars may have reservoirs of liquid water hidden under parts of its icy surface; Dr Michael C Malin and Dr Kenneth S Edgett say these water flows seem to have happened in recent geological time, and may still be occuring; finding, reported in journal Science, could profoundly effect search for life on the planet (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The standard description of Mars as cold, desolate and dry may have to be revised slightly. It now appears that Mars may have reservoirs of liquid water hidden under parts of its icy surface, a finding that could profoundly affect the search for life there, scientists said today.</p>
        <p>Pictures taken from orbit by NASA's Mars Global Surveyor spacecraft have disclosed features in numerous places that look like gullies formed by flowing water carrying rocks and debris to the bottom of craters, according to a study released today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The standard description of Mars as cold, desolate and dry may have to be revised slightly. It now appears that Mars may have reservoirs of liquid water hidden under parts of its icy surface, a finding that could profoundly affect the search for life there, scientists said today.</p>
        <p>Pictures taken from orbit by NASA's Mars Global Surveyor spacecraft have disclosed features in numerous places that look like gullies formed by flowing water carrying rocks and debris to the bottom of craters, according to a study released today.</p>
        <p>The report, by Dr. Michael C. Malin and Dr. Kenneth S. Edgett of Malin Space Science Systems in San Diego, said that evidence suggested that these water flows happened in recent geological time -- perhaps just a few hundreds, thousands or millions of years ago, instead of billions of years in the past. And the researchers said it might still be occurring.</p>
        <p>''We see features that look like gullies formed by flowing water and the deposits of soil and rocks transported by these flows,'' said Dr. Malin, whose company built the spacecraft camera that made the images. ''These features appear to be so young that they might be forming today.''</p>
        <p>At a news conference today at NASA headquarters, the researchers said there was ample evidence that water once flowed on Mars in abundance, leaving ancient river beds and the markings of huge oceans. One of the big questions about Mars, Dr. Edgett said, has been, ''Where did the water go?''</p>
        <p>''The new pictures from Global Surveyor tell us part of the answer,'' he said. ''Some of that water went underground, and quite possibly it's still there.''</p>
        <p>The researchers, whose study will be published next week in the journal Science, said that they found evidence for the flow of liquid water in 150 of 65,000 photos taken by the Surveyor's high resolution camera over the last two years. The evidence of water movement, in the form of gullies and channels terminating in fan-like deltas, appears recent because surfaces around these features are smooth and relatively light in color. Older areas on the planet are pocked with craters and covered with a dark dust, they said.</p>
        <p>Both researchers said that they were surprised by evidence of possible present-day water because the finding did not fit into current models of what Mars was like. Most of the spots that appear to be the source of flowing water are on slopes with exposed rock layers, they said, raising the possibility that liquid water is trapped below these layers and is freed by a surface shift.</p>
        <p>A specialist in possible water on Mars who was not involved with the study, Dr. Michael H. Carr, a planetary geologist with the United States Geological Survey in Menlo Park, Calif., called the images ''exciting,'' saying the gullies and channels looked like water-worn features seen from the air in the western United States. However, he said, he was skeptical about the researchers' theory that there was liquid water in layers 300 to 1,300 feet below the surface that occasionally burst out from the walls of certain craters and canyons.</p>
        <p>Dr. Carr, author of ''Water on Mars'' (Oxford, 1996), said Mars was so cold, with an average temperature of 60 degrees below zero, that any water this near the surface should have been frozen solid. While the new pictures showed important, new Martian features, he said, he was skeptical of the explanations for the apparent flows. ''Either this interpretation is wrong or there is some mechanism we don't know of to keep water liquid under these conditions,'' Dr. Carr said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Edgett said a possible explanation for the features was that water, kept liquid by an unknown means, would freeze and form an ice dam as it flowed from an underground source. The ice dam would retard the flow until there was enough force to break through the barrier, sending the water in a rapid cascade down the slope, much like a flash flood. The water would quickly freeze as its motion slowed and then would quickly boil off into gas because of the planet's low atmospheric pressure, he said, but not before spreading rocks and mud down the slope.</p>
        <p>Dr. Edward J. Weiler, NASA's chief scientist, said that if there were liquid water on Mars, it would have profound implications for the question of life on Mars, both in the past and today, and where to search for it. ''If life ever did develop there, and if it survives to the present time, then these landforms would be great places to look,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Weiler said the findings would have to be verified and explained if they were to become widely accepted. And he cautioned against exaggerating the discovery, alluding to some news reports on the find in recent days. ''There is possible evidence of liquid water,'' he said. ''They have not found lakes or rivers flowing on Mars. They have not found hot springs. They certainly have not found hot tubs with Martians in them.''</p>
        <p>If the presence of subsurface water was proved, Dr. Weiler said, it could fuel a desire to send humans to Mars. Water would make a human trip more feasible and economical because it could be used to make oxygen for astronauts to breathe and hydrogen for fuel for the return trip to Earth. But a human trip would only come after extensive robot missions to characterize the planet and find the best landing sites, he said, an effort that could take decades.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bruce Jakosky, director of the Center for Astrobiology at Colorado University, said the key to finding life on Mars was liquid water. The new findings, possibly finding water where least expected, shows that Mars will be more difficult to understand than some scientists have believed and that any life that might be there could be in unexpected places.</p>
        <p>''On Earth,'' Dr. Jakosky said, ''wherever you find liquid water below the boiling temperature, then you find life.'' The latest discovery ''doesn't tell us that life does exist on Mars, but it is the smoking gun that tells us Mars has all of the elements for life,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
