<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Draft to Be Challenge for Knicks</title>
    <meta content="23KNIC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E7D61F31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Draft to Be Challenge for Knicks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New York Knickerbockers preparing for NBA amateur player draft (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scott Layden did not generate much action in his first season as general manager of the Knicks. With little opportunity or reason to make any major transactions, he has basically left the Knicks' roster intact since Aug. 11, when he joined the franchise.</p>
        <p>But with the Knicks' run toward the title being halted in the Eastern Conference finals by the Indiana Pacers, a team the Knicks were better than a year ago, it is now time for Layden to produce. He will get his first chance Wednesday in the National Basketball Association draft.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Scott Layden did not generate much action in his first season as general manager of the Knicks. With little opportunity or reason to make any major transactions, he has basically left the Knicks' roster intact since Aug. 11, when he joined the franchise.</p>
        <p>But with the Knicks' run toward the title being halted in the Eastern Conference finals by the Indiana Pacers, a team the Knicks were better than a year ago, it is now time for Layden to produce. He will get his first chance Wednesday in the National Basketball Association draft.</p>
        <p>The Knicks have the 22nd pick in the first round and the 39th pick in the second, so the acquisition of a potential star is unlikely. But productive players can be found at such positions, and it is up to Layden to get one for the Knicks.</p>
        <p>Most draft analysts feel the Knicks' priority is to get a point guard and then a power player. The top three point guards appear to be Michigan's Mateen Cleaves, Hofstra's Speedy Claxton and St. John's Erick Barkley. Michigan's Jamal Crawford has also risen in the eyes of scouts after strong workouts. Cleaves will likely be gone before the Knicks select, but Claxton and Barkley could be available.</p>
        <p>''I'm a big fan of Speedy Claxton's,'' said Layden, who predicted that Claxton would be taken in the middle to late first round. ''I can't say enough good things about him.''</p>
        <p>There is rampant speculation throughout the league that the Knicks will be in heavy pursuit of the Detroit Pistons' Grant Hill, who is a free agent, and will probably attempt to trade Patrick Ewing, too.</p>
        <p>Hill is coveted by nearly everyone, but the Knicks are one of only a handful of teams for which he would be willing to leave Detroit. Acquiring the 6-foot-8-inch small forward would cost the Knicks either Latrell Sprewell or Allan Houston and put to an end the abnormal two shooting-guard lineup.</p>
        <p>If the Knicks are able to swing a sign-and-trade deal for Hill, Sprewell is the likely choice to be moved. He is generally regarded throughout the league as a better player than Houston, and it is improbable that Houston would return to Detroit, where he spent his first three seasons.</p>
        <p>Washington is the most likely spot for Ewing if the Knicks are able to move him. The former Georgetown star is revered in Washington, and he would not be against closing his career with the Wizards, who may be willing to offer him a front-office position upon his retirement. Any deal would probably include Juwan Howard, who has several years left on a $105 million contract.</p>
        <p>Layden said last year's first-round pick, center Frederick Weis, is scheduled to join the team's coaches at the end of this month and to play with the Knicks in a summer camp in Boston.</p>
        <p>Nets Eye Forward</p>
        <p>After spending much of the day examining Kenyon Martin's leg, the Nets' doctors determined that the star forward from Cincinnati is in good health, the team's president, Rod Thorn, said.</p>
        <p>''Our doctors said he's fine,'' Thorn said. ''I'm glad to see that because he is one of the guys we're considering.''</p>
        <p>The news could make Martin, who broke his right fibula in in the National Collegiate Athletic Association tournament, a Net. While the Nets are still considering trading their No. 1 pick, they are believed to covet the 6-9 Martin, who has great athleticism and shot-blocking ability.</p>
        <p>''I think he can be really good,'' Thorn said. ''He's such a good jumper and he's tenacious. He moves very well laterally. He can run the court. I like him a lot.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
