<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Triarc Will Spin Off Snapple Beverage Unit</title>
    <meta content="Y23SNA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209547"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Triarc Cos Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Snapple Beverage Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hays, Constance L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3DA1F31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Triarc Will Spin Off Snapple Beverage Unit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE L. HAYS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hays, Constance L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Triarc will spin off part of its beverage division, which includes Snapple, Mistic and Royal Crown brands; shares in new company, to be called Snapple Beverage Group and consisting of up to 20 percent of Triarc's soft drink holdings, will be sold during third quarter of year (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Triarc said yesterday that it would spin off a part of its beverage division, which includes the Snapple, Mistic and Royal Crown brands.</p>
        <p>Details of the plan will be filed in the next few days with the Securities and Exchange Commission, a spokeswoman said. Shares in the new company, to be called the Snapple Beverage Group and consisting of up to 20 percent of Triarc's soft drink holdings, would be sold during the third quarter of this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Triarc said yesterday that it would spin off a part of its beverage division, which includes the Snapple, Mistic and Royal Crown brands.</p>
        <p>Details of the plan will be filed in the next few days with the Securities and Exchange Commission, a spokeswoman said. Shares in the new company, to be called the Snapple Beverage Group and consisting of up to 20 percent of Triarc's soft drink holdings, would be sold during the third quarter of this year.</p>
        <p>Proceeds from the public offering, which is being underwritten by Morgan Stanley Dean Witter; Lehman Brothers; Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette; and ING Barings, would be used to pay off debt. Over time, some analysts believe, Triarc will relinquish more of the soft drink division to the new company.</p>
        <p>Shares of Triarc fell 43.8 cents, to $19.75 on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>As a separate company, Snapple could become a takeover target or an acquirer of other soft drink brands. Its namesake brand lineup, which includes noncarbonated drinks with flavors like peach, lemonade and iced tea, represents the new age beverages that consumers have been flocking to in recent years. The trend has diminished growth of colas, and the soft drink giants like Coca-Cola and PepsiCo say they are intent on widening their array of brands to capture more market share.</p>
        <p>The crown jewel of the Triarc beverage division is Snapple, which the company bought from Quaker Oats in 1997. Snapple's volume grew 6 percent last year, when the industry over all was essentially flat. Other company brands did not do as well: Royal Crown fell 13.5 percent and Mistic declined by 22 percent. A fourth brand, Stewart's, grew by 13 percent on a base far smaller than Snapple's.</p>
        <p>The division had revenue last year of $770 million and adjusted pretax earnings of $101 million. Within the highly competitive soft drink industry, Triarc's beverages are the country's sixth largest in volume, said John D. Sicher, editor of Beverage Digest, an industry newsletter.</p>
        <p>Triarc's other holdings include the Arby's restaurant franchise and two smaller franchises. At various times, the company has owned petroleum companies and textile makers, and is regarded as complex both structurally and financially. In late 1998, Triarc's chairman, Nelson W. Peltz, announced that he would take the company private for $18 a share, or $420 million, because Wall Street was underappreciating its value. Almost as abruptly, he changed his mind in March 1999.</p>
        <p>''What this deal does is, it creates a pure play,'' Mr. Sicher said. ''They are trying to unlock what they believe is some unrecognized value in the beverage business, which has been part of this complicated Triarc picture.''</p>
        <p>Michael Weinstein, Triarc's chief executive for beverages, will become chief executive of the new company. Mr. Peltz will become its chairman and Peter W. May, president and chief operating officer of Triarc, will be vice chairman. All three will become directors of Snapple, which is based in White Plains; there will also be four outside directors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sicher called Mr. Weinstein ''among the best executives in the beverage business,'' saying he had done much to rebuild Snapple after the brand was acquired from Quaker. Quaker purchased Snapple, which was then publicly traded, for $1.7 billion in 1994. After a disastrous period in which sales and market share plummeted and Wendy the Snapple Lady, the brand's distinctive, loud-mouthed spokeswoman, was fired, Quaker put the brand on the block and sold it to Triarc for $310 million. Among Mr. Weinstein's moves was bringing Wendy Kaufman back in mid-1997.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
