<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Federal Jury Convicts Pirro On All Tax-Fraud Charges</title>
    <meta content="Y23PIR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pirro, Albert J Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pirro, Anthony G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pirro, Jeanine (Dist Atty)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3DE1630F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1333" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Federal Jury Convicts Pirro On All Tax-Fraud Charges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS, June 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Albert J Pirro Jr, influential Republican businessman and husband of Jeanine F Pirro, Westchester County district attorney, is convicted of conspiracy and tax evasion; verdict imperils Pirro's business career and perhaps political future of his wife, once a strong contender for Republican nomination for US Senate; Anthony G Pirro, codefendant, is convicted with his brother; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal jury today convicted Albert J. Pirro Jr., the influential Republican businessman and husband of Jeanine F. Pirro, the Westchester County district attorney, of conspiracy and tax evasion, imperiling his business career and perhaps her political one.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Pirro, 53, the verdict, if upheld, could derail his career as Westchester's most powerful real estate development lawyer and one of New York State's most prodigious Republican fund-raisers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal jury today convicted Albert J. Pirro Jr., the influential Republican businessman and husband of Jeanine F. Pirro, the Westchester County district attorney, of conspiracy and tax evasion, imperiling his business career and perhaps her political one.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Pirro, 53, the verdict, if upheld, could derail his career as Westchester's most powerful real estate development lawyer and one of New York State's most prodigious Republican fund-raisers.</p>
        <p>For Mrs. Pirro, 49, who could have been a strong contender for the Republican nomination for the United States Senate this year were it not for her husband's legal woes, the verdict jeopardizes her immediate prospects for higher office. And for Anthony G. Pirro, Albert Pirro's brother and accountant, who was also convicted today on similar charges, the result transforms an anonymous middle-class life into one inextricably linked to a messy public scandal.</p>
        <p>Given the star quotient of the principals, the trial, at times, seemed to be more about celebrity than about conspiracy. A woman who filed a successful paternity suit against Albert Pirro threatened to confront him in court, only to be thwarted by federal authorities in Newark on an unrelated warrant. Prosecutors suggested that Albert Pirro lusted for money in much the way that Richard Nixon lusted for power. And a parade of contractors reluctantly offered intimate details about the Pirros' lavish expenditures on everything from a $13,250 Chinese rug to an $1,800 wrought-iron fence for their Vietnamese pot-bellied pigs.</p>
        <p>But when the verdict was announced today at 12:10 p.m., on the fourth day of deliberations after a four-week trial, there was no such absurdity. Instead, the jury of eight men and four women shuffled quietly into a packed and hushed courtroom without looking at either defendant. Then the foreman stood up and forcefully read out ''Guilty'' 34 times for Albert Pirro, and ''Guilty'' 23 times and ''Not Guilty'' 10 times for Anthony Pirro.</p>
        <p>Albert, Jeanine and Anthony Pirro sat motionless in the courtroom as the verdicts were read. But Anthony Pirro's wife, Donna, who attended virtually every minute of every proceeding, sobbed quietly.</p>
        <p>Federal prosecutors did not react visibly to the verdict, and they did not have any comments afterward. But throughout the trial, prosecutors argued that by improperly deducting $1.2 million of Albert Pirro's personal expenses as business write-offs, thereby reducing Albert Pirro's taxes by $413,000, the brothers had brazenly violated a fundamental tenet of the American tax system: that every taxpayer must pay his or her fair share, regardless of wealth or influence.</p>
        <p>About a half-hour after the verdict was announced, Albert and Jeanine Pirro exited the courthouse to a waiting throng of reporters and elbowing photographers. And during a 10-minute news conference, a serene and composed Albert Pirro affably fielded questions.</p>
        <p>What was his reaction? ''I'm a little surprised,'' he said, adding that he maintained his innocence. ''Disappointed. But we'll pick up and get on with our lives.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Pirro, by contrast, looked a bit stunned. ''I am disappointed in the verdict,'' she said. ''But I still believe in the process and the system. That's why we have an appellate process and an appellate system.''</p>
        <p>If the conviction withstands an all-but-certain appeal, then both brothers will probably face three or four years in jail, according to federal sentencing guidelines, said William I. Aronwald, a former federal prosecutor who is now a defense lawyer in White Plains. Moreover, Albert Pirro would almost certainly lose his law license.</p>
        <p>Until the verdict was rendered, though, many lawyers who attended the proceedings had said that the case appeared to be a tossup. And in recent days, there were strong signs of discord among jurors -- with one, William Cason, even complaining in a meeting Wednesday with Judge Barrington D. Parker Jr. about peer pressure.</p>
        <p>''I'm not a little kid,'' said Mr. Cason, who was one of at least four jurors who had been audited by the I.R.S. ''You got one person with different opinions.''</p>
        <p>In the end, Mr. Cason yielded. ''I'm not happy,'' he told reporters outside the courthouse. ''That's all I have to say.''</p>
        <p>Other jurors would not comment; some even ran away from approaching reporters. But one juror, Kenneth Kostik, said that while there were strong passions in the jury room, the only disagreements revolved around ''interpretations of the law'' and not, he suggested, around any great differences in opinions about whether the two were guilty.</p>
        <p>''I think it was cut and dry,'' Mr. Kostik said of the case.</p>
        <p>From the outset, Mr. Pirro and his legal team, led by Gustave H. Newman, had argued that Mr. Pirro was too busy and aloof a businessman to pay close attention to such mundane tasks as bookkeeping. Mr. Pirro's team also suggested that the government had overzealously pursued Mr. Pirro, since only 5 percent of his company's business deductions had been deemed improper.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Pirro's lawyers noted that he had repaid about $1 million in back taxes.</p>
        <p>But in withering, meticulous fashion, the government, led by prosecutors Elliott B. Jacobson, Cathy Seibel and Justin S. Weddle, called about 60 witnesses and referred to thousands of pages of tax returns, invoices and canceled checks in presenting their portrait of Albert Pirro as a wealthy man who simply wanted to become wealthier -- on the taxpayers' dime. Then, the final witness, John Dennehy, a revenue agent with the Internal Revenue Service, linked the expenses with the fraudulent tax returns.</p>
        <p>Along the way, jurors and the packed gallery peeked vicariously into the Pirros' private lives and spending habits on airplane tickets, country club outings, home furnishings and so much more. They heard how the Pirros would pay for personal items out of more than a dozen of Mr. Pirro's companies, even though Mr. Pirro had at least $100,000 in overdraft protection. And they heard about the Pirros' veritable fleet of luxury cars -- including a Mercedes-Benz for Mrs. Pirro's mother, who lives in Elmira, N.Y., which was deducted as an expense of a Yonkers real estate company of Mr. Pirro's.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Pirro was not charged with any wrongdoing. But she did not emerge unscathed from the torrent of personal details and insinuations that she should have known more.  Mrs. Pirro was mentioned more in testimony than her brother-in-law, Anthony Pirro, who argued that he was ''just an accountant'' doing his job.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, the testimony was numbingly repetitive and dry. But in closing arguments, Ms. Seibel unleashed enough one-liners to generate a week's worth of tabloid headlines: that Albert Pirro was a ''crook'' with ''chutzpah'' who tried to ''weasel out of his taxes''; that Albert Pirro used his corporate American Express card as a ''a personal piggybank''; that Albert and Anthony Pirro concocted a ''don't ask, don't tell'' conspiracy.</p>
        <p>And while Anthony was found not guity of 10 counts related to false tax preparation, the final tally was of little solace to either brother.</p>
        <p>The defense did not even call any witnesses, betting that the government had not met its burden of proof. After all, on many occasions during cross-examination, defense lawyers had poked holes in the government's arguments.</p>
        <p>In the end, though, the strategy did not work.</p>
        <p>''When you have a client who has no criminal record, who is as articulate and bright as Al is, basically you're chomping at the bit to put your client on the stand, especially when his defense is, 'It was an honest mistake; I didn't mean to do it,' '' Mr. Aronwald said. ''I'm sure this was a very difficult decision to make, and they obviously felt that the government didn't present enough evidence to make its case, and they guessed wrong.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
