<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Britain Charges Dutch Truck Driver in Migrants' Deaths</title>
    <meta content="Y23BRI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Amnesties and Pardons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Netherlands</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tan Wah-piow</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wacker, Perry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Roger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amnesties and Pardons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E0DB1F31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Britain Charges Dutch Truck Driver in Migrants' Deaths</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Roger</byline>
      <dateline>DOVER, England, June 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Perry Wacker, Dutch driver of a truck that became the sealed tomb of 58 illegal Chinese immigrants packed into its airtight container, is charged with manslaughter in Britain, as well as with trying to bring victims into the country and with facilitating the entry of the two survivors; none of victims have been identified, and Tan Wah-piow, London-based lawyer, calls on authorities to grant amnesty to any of victims relatives who may be in Britain illegally so that they can come forward and claim their dead; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Dutch driver of a truck that became the sealed tomb of 58 illegal Chinese immigrants packed into its airtight container was charged today with manslaughter, the police said.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the Kent police, Mark Pugash, said that the driver, Perry Wacker of Rotterdam, will be arraigned on 58 charges of manslaughter -- or unlawful killing -- when he appears in court on Friday. The driver, 32, has been held since the suffocated corpses of the young immigrants were found early Monday piled in the rear of his truck.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Dutch driver of a truck that became the sealed tomb of 58 illegal Chinese immigrants packed into its airtight container was charged today with manslaughter, the police said.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the Kent police, Mark Pugash, said that the driver, Perry Wacker of Rotterdam, will be arraigned on 58 charges of manslaughter -- or unlawful killing -- when he appears in court on Friday. The driver, 32, has been held since the suffocated corpses of the young immigrants were found early Monday piled in the rear of his truck.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wacker was also charged with trying to bring the victims into the country and with facilitating the entry into Britain of two survivors, who have been hospitalized and are being questioned by the police. His truck had made a five-hour ferry crossing from the Belgian port of Zeebrugge in unseasonable heat.</p>
        <p>The severity of the charges appeared to reflect the outrage in Britain and throughout the European Union over a case that has highlighted the unease generated by immigration. European states are deeply uncertain whether to view young immigrants as a burden or a potential benefit to their aging societies.</p>
        <p>Because legal immigration into states of the European Union is almost impossible for unskilled workers, and not easy even for the skilled, growing numbers try to enter illegally and then seek asylum.</p>
        <p>This seems to have been the goal of the 60 Chinese people packed in the truck, most of whom were in their 20's and had apparently traveled overland from China's southern Fujian Province, the police said.</p>
        <p>''The global reality now is that you cannot stop people from poorer countries aspiring for life in richer countries,'' said Tan Wah-piow, a London-based lawyer who deals with asylum cases. ''That is what drives these people from Fujian. But people in European states are not ready to confront this reality.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tan has become involved in the case because four days after the discovery of the deaths, none of the victims has been identified. He said he was outraged by this failure and contended that it reflected the refusal of British authorities to guarantee that any Chinese relatives of the dead who come forward will be granted amnesty.</p>
        <p>It appears that these relatives may themselves be in England illegally and are afraid to present themselves to the authorities for fear of detention or even expulsion.</p>
        <p>Those seeking asylum routinely destroy all their documents, so the dead are thought to have had no identification on them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pugash hinted in a radio interview today that any relatives would be treated with understanding, but he declined to offer any guarantees of immunity. ''We have said from the beginning that we will welcome anyone with any information,'' he said. ''We will treat them sympathetically. Asylum status is not an issue for us.''</p>
        <p>Britain's Labor government, under strong pressure to stem a rising flow of immigration widely seen as placing unacceptable strain on the welfare state, tightened its asylum laws earlier this year. In 1999, more than 70,000 people applied for asylum, compared to about 5,000 before the Berlin Wall fell in 1989.</p>
        <p>The Kent police have arrested two other people -- a Chinese man and woman -- in connection with the case. The Dutch police have arrested Arie van der Spek, 24, who lived at the address listed for the company registered as the owner the truck, and one other man.</p>
        <p>The case has also acquired a Belgian dimension. The police there are holding three Asian men arrested in April in connection with the illegal presence of a large group of Chinese immigrants in two villages.</p>
        <p>It is not yet clear whether these Chinese citizens, who were detained by Belgian authorities and then put unescorted on a train to Antwerp, are the same group that later died in the back of Mr. Wacker's truck. The British police are examining fingerprints of the group made by the Belgian police two months ago.</p>
        <p>Relations between Belgium and Britain have been strained over the way the Chinese were treated, with Belgian ministers curtly rebuffing British suggestions that the arrest and subsequent release of the group made little sense.</p>
        <p>These bitter exchanges have illustrated the fact that the 15 nations of the European Union have no common policy on immigration or asylum. Some, like Belgium and Germany, are members of the so-called ''Schengen area,'' a group of states that have effectively dismantled the borders between them. Others, like Britain, are not.</p>
        <p>China today called for tighter controls on immigration, suggesting some European countries were too lax. ''It is worth noting that criminal groups usually use legal loopholes in some countries to organize secret passages,'' said Zhu Bangzao, a foreign ministry spokesman. ''Countries concerned should coordinate efforts and crack down severely on these crimes.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
