<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Payton Using Month to Build Season</title>
    <meta content="23METS$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209625"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E6DD1630F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Payton Using Month to Build Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Philadelphia Phillies, 5-4; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jay Payton measures his happiness by when he is able to get to sleep. In May, it took the Mets' center fielder an extra hour -- sometimes two -- for his mind to find peace. Not so in June.</p>
        <p>''I fall asleep at 2 instead of 3 now,'' he said last night after his two-run home run put the Mets ahead to stay in a 5-4 victory over the Philadelphia Phillies. ''I probably had a couple of nights there when I fell asleep at 4.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jay Payton measures his happiness by when he is able to get to sleep. In May, it took the Mets' center fielder an extra hour -- sometimes two -- for his mind to find peace. Not so in June.</p>
        <p>''I fall asleep at 2 instead of 3 now,'' he said last night after his two-run home run put the Mets ahead to stay in a 5-4 victory over the Philadelphia Phillies. ''I probably had a couple of nights there when I fell asleep at 4.''</p>
        <p>A miserable slump produced the visions that kept Payton awake. He concluded May with 2 hits in his final 35 at-bats, and though his confidence never wavered, Payton was frustrated with his lack of playing time and seemed confused about how to win a regular job.</p>
        <p>The formula turned out to be simple: produce every day, without letting up. That is what Payton has done. He has started every game in June and is batting .400 (24 for 60) for the month. If he keeps hitting and fielding well, Payton could challenge St. Louis's Rick Ankiel and Atlanta's Rafael Furcal for the National League's rookie of the year award.</p>
        <p>The biggest change in Payton, Manager Bobby Valentine said, is his ability to recognize breaking pitches. In the sixth inning, with two outs and Robin Ventura on second after a double, Payton came to the plate. The Phillies' starter, Cliff Politte, threw two breaking pitches, and Payton let both go by for balls.</p>
        <p>''It all comes from mechanics,'' Payton said of his improved selectivity. ''When you're quiet and you don't have a lot of head movement in your swing, you're seeing the ball better. When you're jerking or waiting too long, you're not going to see the ball as well.''</p>
        <p>Catcher Mike Lieberthal set a low target, a smart call considering how well Payton hits high pitches. But Politte's pitch missed, coming in at Payton's armpits, and he smoked it to right. Bobby Abreu raced back and leaped, and the ball skimmed his glove as he collided with the fence. It skipped into the Mets' bullpen for a homer, and the Mets led, 4-2.</p>
        <p>The home run was the Mets' third -- Derek Bell and Melvin Mora had the others -- and it gave Glendon Rusch (5-5) his first lead.</p>
        <p>After walking six in his last start, Rusch walked the first batter last night. After an out, he gave up three singles in a row and he trailed, 2-0. But that was all the Phillies would get off Rusch, who permitted no more walks and just four more singles. He worked seven innings, giving up two runs on seven hits.</p>
        <p>''I'm so much more effective when I'm ahead in the count,'' said Rusch, who thinks he must do more with his final bullpen pitches to avoid starting slowly. ''I don't have anywhere near the overpowering stuff to get guys out when I'm behind.''</p>
        <p>Rusch was especially impressive in the seventh inning, when the first two Phillies reached base with no outs and Rusch escaped trouble with a groundout, strikeout and flyout.</p>
        <p>''That seventh inning showed he's really a big leaguer and a true, true competitor,'' Valentine said.</p>
        <p>Turk Wendell survived a more adventurous eighth. Protecting a 5-3 lead after an infield single by Bell had given the Mets another run, Wendell surrendered a leadoff homer to Scott Rolen, then issued a walk. A passed ball and an error by Ventura put runners at second and third, and with Kevin Jordan batting, Wendell threw a pitch behind his back.</p>
        <p>A wild pitch in that situation would have scored a run and advanced a runner to third. Catcher Todd Pratt naturally lost sight of the pitch as it zipped behind Jordan, but he stuck out his glove and snared it. Pratt did that this season on an Al Leiter pitch, but he cannot remember ever doing it before then.</p>
        <p>Jordan then drove a fly to the left-field warning track, and Joe McEwing -- a defensive replacement -- raced over for a running grab. ''I didn't think he was going to be able to get to it,'' Wendell said, ''but that's why he's Super Joe.''</p>
        <p>The Phillies scored on the sacrifice fly, but they could get nothing more off Wendell and Dennis Cook, and the Mets (38-31) avoided a sweep to the team in last place in their division.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The right-hander BOBBY J. JONES will return to the Mets' rotation tonight to face Pittsburgh, after two mediocre starts for Class AAA Norfolk. Manager BOBBY VALENTINE was vague as to how much longer Jones can struggle while still holding his spot in the rotation, but the right-hander PAT MAHOMES is not expected to be shifted to the rotation on a long-term basis. Mahomes has a 5.22 earned run average as a reliever but a 2.76 mark in three starts. . . . LENNY HARRIS had a pinch-hit double in the seventh inning for his first hit since joining the Mets in a trade from Arizona on June 2. Harris, who had been 0 for 12 with the Mets, is baseball's active career leader in pinch hits, with 120.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
