<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dramatic Revivals, Against the Odds</title>
    <meta content="23PLAY$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000703T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209496"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ford's Theater (Washington, DC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Walnut Street Theater (Phila)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wilbur Theater (Boston)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theaters (Buildings)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Buffalo (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Shea's Performing Arts Center (Buffalo)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aloff, Mindy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Buffalo</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7D71E31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dramatic Revivals, Against the Odds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MINDY ALOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Aloff, Mindy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mindy Aloff article on graceful restoration of historic theaters in Boston, Buffalo, Philadelphia and Washington; photos; reports stages are vibrant with plays, music and dance, and downtown streets around theaters are once again thronged with people (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When you want to orient yourself in a new city or to see a familiar one in a new way, it is useful to have an obsession. Just about any will do: the key is to decide how long you will yield to it, then to let it take over. Obsessions select related bits of information from the chaotic pool of data streaming into your consciousness, providing focus and structure.</p>
        <p>Over the last two years I revisited three Northeastern cities I know well: Boston, Buffalo and Philadelphia. During those visits I looked at them from the idiosyncratic standpoint of what had become of their historic theaters, those built before World War II. I also made a trip to Washington to visit the nation's most famous and sacred historic theater, Ford's; actually, it is a facsimile, as the original structure in which Abraham Lincoln was assassinated was torn down by government order soon after his death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When you want to orient yourself in a new city or to see a familiar one in a new way, it is useful to have an obsession. Just about any will do: the key is to decide how long you will yield to it, then to let it take over. Obsessions select related bits of information from the chaotic pool of data streaming into your consciousness, providing focus and structure.</p>
        <p>Over the last two years I revisited three Northeastern cities I know well: Boston, Buffalo and Philadelphia. During those visits I looked at them from the idiosyncratic standpoint of what had become of their historic theaters, those built before World War II. I also made a trip to Washington to visit the nation's most famous and sacred historic theater, Ford's; actually, it is a facsimile, as the original structure in which Abraham Lincoln was assassinated was torn down by government order soon after his death.</p>
        <p>In the course of these trips I learned much about the dynamics and histories of the cities themselves. I saw the tremendous energy and sometimes heartbreaking compromises necessary to maintain a performing-arts center today. And I learned how intensely it is possible to love a theater and to believe in a city, so much so that some people may devote most of their adult lives, sometimes as volunteers, to keeping an old theater alive.</p>
        <p>I was moved to make this pilgrimage by two developments. One was the brilliant success of renovations to several prewar theaters on 42nd Street just off Times Square.</p>
        <p>Not only were the buildings gracefully remodeled or restored, but their stages are also vibrant, with plays, music and dance; and the street is thronged with people. Was this kind of renewal possible only in New York, or have other cities revived their downtowns by renovating theaters from earlier eras? Could they go forward by, in some respect, going back? The other motivation was my sadness over what had happened to many theaters in my hometown, Philadelphia. A city of flourishing theaters during the 19th and early 20th centuries, it has suffered from a declining tax base, civic mismanagement and the depredations of unplanned real estate development. Most of the theaters I grew up with, including the sumptuous movie palaces, appointed for kings and priced for laborers, are now gone, are boarded-up ruins or have been transformed into other commercial uses.</p>
        <p>Philadelphia</p>
        <p>New theaters have been built in Philadelphia, but they are small, and their designs reflect ruthless cost cutting. Only a handful of historic theaters survive as working theaters in Center City. In trying to bring its decaying downtown back to health, Philadelphia has chosen to knock down much of its business district, once lovely and humanely scaled, and build aggressively new and much higher buildings.</p>
        <p>Complicating the situation has been the city's longtime hope of establishing an Avenue of the Arts in its downtown core. Its hub is to be a new concert hall for the Philadelphia Orchestra, which musicians argue has outgrown the compromised acoustics and restricted production space of the Academy of Music, its home for most of the past century. (The new hall, partially completed, is projected to open in September 2001. The Academy, with its old-fashioned raked stage, will be remodeled to accommodate more dance and opera.)</p>
        <p>One heartening new theater opened last year in the completely gutted ''picture palace'' that was built in 1921 as the Karlton and that I used to attend when it was called the Midtown. This is the Prince Music, a producing and presenting house for films and live performance, operated by a visionary organization founded in 1984 as the American Musical Theater Festival.</p>
        <p>The Prince is named for the director-producer Harold Prince, a longtime festival board member and mentor of the festival co-founders, Eric Salzman, Ron Kaiserman and Marjorie Samoff (who is also the theater's producing director). It has two auditoriums: a 450-seat hall, which includes an orchestra pit for dance and musicals as well as equipment for the screening of films; and a 150-seat black-box space in what was one of the Karlton's two ballrooms.</p>
        <p>As it happens, the oldest theater in the United States in continuous use as such is in Philadelphia: the Walnut Street, founded in 1809 as a circus for equestrian shows. When I was growing up, it was the main showcase for traveling modern-dance companies. Although the facade of the building was refurbished to approach its early, simple elegance, the interior has suffered from nearly a century of modernization. Two years ago the main auditorium was completely gutted, rehabilitated and repainted a light gray; the results are austere and impersonal compared to my memories of the graciously ornamented house of the 1950's.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, over the last two decades, the Walnut's nonprofit organization managed to achieve seasonal programming based on new plays and musicals, along with some revivals. These are performed in its main auditorium and in a smaller studio space; at least 70 percent of the audience members are subscribers. Under its current artistic director, Bernard Havard, the Walnut functions as a producing theater and as a theater school.</p>
        <p>In the company of the historic Academy of Music; the Merriam (once the Shubert), where the Pennsylvania Ballet dances; and the Forrest, a house used primarily for musicals but too frequently dark these days, the Walnut keeps the flame of a theatrical Philadelphia, whose larger memory is still cherished by many writers, historians, librarians and natives.</p>
        <p>Boston</p>
        <p>In contrast to Philadelphia, Boston has made an extraordinary civic effort to light up its downtown with the original chandeliers of a number of carefully restored and maintained historic theaters and playhouses, most of them within walking distance of one another in the historic district. Some are excellent houses for theatrical dance.</p>
        <p>Among these are the sumptuous Italianate Wang Center for the Performing Arts (1925), where the Boston Ballet performs; the Emerson Majestic (1903, owned by Emerson College), whose proscenium is especially well proportioned for dancers, although many kinds of shows are presented there; the elaborately ornamented Colonial (1900), a gilded wonder where Fred and Adele Astaire performed; the snow-and-gold Shubert (1910); and the Charles Playhouse (1843), built originally as a church.</p>
        <p>The spoken word is also accommodated beautifully in the pristinely restored Wilbur (1914), site of the world premieres of ''Our Town'' and ''A Streetcar Named Desire,'' and, a little way across town, my favorite Boston theater, the arboreal Huntington (1925, owned by Boston University), which is decorated with quotations from Shakespeare and houses its own nonprofit resident company.</p>
        <p>In conjunction with newer theaters and playhouses in Boston and adjacent Cambridge, such historic structures help to provide city residents with a sense that, here, history is valued.</p>
        <p>Although no individual can be credited completely with leadership in a citywide effort to maintain the life of any art, Boston's theatrical legacy would not be what it is today without the commitment and enlightened voice of Elliot Norton, the 97-year-old drama critic and historian. His prodigious memory and beneficial open-mindedness, developed over 48 years as a drama critic for Boston newspapers and more than 25 years as host of a program devoted to theater on WGBH-TV, has provided Bostonians with a model of intellectual perspective and beneficial passion for the subject.</p>
        <p>Washington</p>
        <p>Ford's, one of two theaters in the United States overseen by the Department of the Interior (the other is at Wolf Trap in Virginia), attracts thousands of tourists yearly. They come because of its unfortunate notoriety: it is the place where the actor John Wilkes Booth burst through a door and fired the shot that killed Lincoln. From the auditorium travelers can descend to a museum devoted to the assassination and its aftermath; they can then walk across the street to the house where Lincoln was carried and spent his final hours.</p>
        <p>Still, Ford's is an energetic producing theater as well as a national memorial. Its artistic director, Frankie Hewitt, has been associated with it since it was rebuilt and reopened in 1968. She recently noted that in addition to serving adult theatergoers with plays like Steve Martin's ''Picasso at the Lapin Agile,''  Ford's also presents shows for young people, many of whom visit the theater on school trips.</p>
        <p>Ford's is the perfect place for plays with a historical basis, like ''Give 'Em Hell, Harry'' about Harry S. Truman and ''Will Rogers's U.S.A.'' Ford's has a yearly production of ''A Christmas Carol,'' based on the story by Charles Dickens, who declaimed it himself in Carroll Hall in Washington.</p>
        <p>Ford's is the only theater I've been to in the United States, outside the New Victory in Manhattan, where each member of the audience downstairs is offered an individual upholstered chair. (And after visiting the theater museum, I can tell you that today's audiences at Ford's are much more cossetted than those of the 19th-century original.)</p>
        <p>Buffalo</p>
        <p>Of all the theaters I visited, however, the most affecting was Shea's Performing Arts Center, a jewel of a civic heirloom in the heart of Buffalo's downtown. Built as a movie palace in 1926 by Paramount, it was immediately nicknamed Shea's after its manager, Michael Shea. Today it is a nonprofit institution that houses touring commercial shows.</p>
        <p>Its interior, designed in the Spanish Baroque style by Louis Comfort Tiffany, is glowing burgundy and gold with cooling touches of aquamarine. It is a wonderful place, full of light and warmth; and its human story is wonderful, too.</p>
        <p>For the fact that Shea's still exists, in a tenderly renovated condition, is directly attributable to the continuing determination by many Buffalonians over the last 30 years not to let it go. Even a fire that destroyed much of the surrounding downtown in 1986, rendering the block on which the theater stands a ghost town, did not daunt its supporters.</p>
        <p>The walls of the handsome entrance lobby, clad partly in real marble and partly in a laboriously manufactured artificial marble known as scagliola, have been painstakingly repaired and repolished. The original swirling, marbelized abstractions once again seem to corruscate under the light of four crystal-beaded chandeliers, each nearly 10 feet long. Their renewed brilliance alone represents 350 man-hours of restoration, cleaning and rewiring, all of it performed by volunteers, who since 1997 have worked under the leadership of Doris Collins, director of the docent program.</p>
        <p>Volunteers have been central to the survival of Shea's since the day in 1975 when a group of them interposed themselves between the building and the wrecking ball that was to reduce it to rubble.</p>
        <p>Shea's is not currently a producing theater: it houses touring Broadway shows, mostly, as well as some pop music groups and other prepackaged entertainment. But Patrick Fagan, its president for the last 14 years and the person most strongly identified with the community's efforts to keep the theater alive, said Shea's was operating reasonably well. In 1999 it offered some 200 events for some 300,000 theatergoers. And it recently completed a backstage expansion.</p>
        <p>Further construction is needed: a second lobby, more bathrooms, a decent coat check, more room for concession stands. The city has contributed $2 million of the $13 million required. The remainder will be sought from corporate sponsors and private patrons.</p>
        <p>Buffalo is a city with a distinguished history of private patronage of the arts; corporate support is comparatively recent. Over the last few years, for example, the Buffalo Philharmonic, once sustained largely by private patrons, has been actively looking to corporations as well. The Philharmonic's home theater is another prized historic structure: Kleinhans Music Hall, a W.P.A. project that opened in 1940 with a modernist design by Eliel Saarinen, first-rate acoustics by Charles C. Potwin and poetic lighting by Stanley McCandless.</p>
        <p>Still, the city has suffered economically for many decades, and both its audiences and its leading arts patrons are aging. Neither group seems to be readily replaced by a younger generation, even though artists themselves keep trying to renew the Buffalo scene.</p>
        <p>Across Main Street from Shea's, for instance, is a newly designed arena theater in a former store. It serves the Irish Classical Theater Company, founded in 1990 by two young Irish actor-brothers, Vincent and Christopher O'Neill, and by Dr. James Warde. A recent season consisted of plays by Brecht, Ibsen, Eugene O'Neill, Shakespeare and Martin McDonagh. I found out about the Irish Rep when Ms. Collins, who was guiding me around Shea's, spoke proudly of it as a neighbor.</p>
        <p>Terrance L. Demas, the executive director of the League of Historic American Theaters, based in Baltimore, said that many historic theaters in the United States were restored with some sweat equity. Shea's, though, is singular in its continuing program to train volunteers in restoration jobs, like fine painting, for which craftsmen are usually hired.</p>
        <p>''You have to make choices about what historic theaters you save, because you can't save them all,'' Mr. Demas said. ''People turned to theater restoration in the 1960's and 70's. It was a time when cities were trying to save their downtowns. Theater restoration revives an interest in the downtown, and anecdotal studies show that their economic impact on cities is quite substantial.''</p>
        <p>Restoration can also be more economical than building new.</p>
        <p>''Take the Palace Theater in Chicago, where Elton John's 'Aida' opened,'' Mr. Demas said. ''That took $25 to $30 million to restore; to build it new today, in a comparable space, would cost $100 million, at least.''</p>
        <p>''They say that we can't build theaters like the old ones anymore,'' he continued. ''Well, we do have the craftsmen; we do have the artisans. It's the cost. Our field is one where a lot of these theaters get saved not because it's economically feasible but because the people there want them to happen. They believe in them. With the theaters they will get an important piece of their history.''</p>
        <p>Stages of History</p>
        <p>Here are details about attending performances at the historic theaters mentioned in Mindy Aloff's article:</p>
        <p>Philadelphia</p>
        <p>FORREST THEATER, -- 1114 Walnut Street, at 11th Street, (800) 447-7400 or (215) 923-1515. Performances resume Nov. 15 with ''Fosse.''</p>
        <p>MERRIAM THEATER, -- 250 South Broad Street, between Locust and Spruce Streets, (215) 336-1234. ''Woman Thou Art Loosed,'' a gospel show by T. D. Jakes, through June 25. Tuesdays through Sundays at 8 p.m.; Saturdays at 2 p.m.; Sundays at 3 p.m. Ticket: $23.50 to 35.50.</p>
        <p>PRINCE MUSIC THEATER,-- 1412 Chestnut Street, at Broad Street, (215) 569-9700. ''St. Louis Woman,'' starring Vernel Bagneris, through June 25. Wednesdays through Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 p.m. Tickets: $30 and $36. ''The Eyes Have It: The Films of Elizabeth Taylor,'' June 24-29. Tickets: $7.</p>
        <p>WALNUT STREET THEATER, -- 825 Walnut Street, at Ninth Street, (215) 574-3550. ''La Cage aux Folles,'' through July 2. Tuesdays through Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Thursdays and Saturdays at 2 p.m.; Sundays at 2 and 7 p.m. Tickets: $8 to $50.</p>
        <p>Buffalo</p>
        <p>IRISH CLASSICAL THEATER COMPANY, -- 625 Main Street, (716) 853-4282. ''Intimate Exchanges,'' two one-act plays by Alan Ayckbourn. Through July 2. Thursdays through Sundays at 7:30 p.m.; Wednesdays at 2 p.m. Tickets: $10 to $21.</p>
        <p>KLEINHANS MUSIC HALL, -- 370 Pennsylvania Avenue, (800) 699-3168 or (716) 885-5000. The Buffalo Philharmonic Orchestra begins its season on Sept. 15 with Peter Nero as guest.</p>
        <p>SHEA'S PERFORMING ARTS CENTER, -- 646 Main Street, (716) 852-5000. ''Tea Party,'' at 8 p.m. on July 2 only. Tickets: $22 and $17.50. ''Miss Saigon'' opens on July 27 and runs for 16 performances, through Aug. 6. Tickets : $25 to $62.50.</p>
        <p>Boston</p>
        <p>CHARLES PLAYHOUSE, -- 74 Warrenton Street, (617) 931-2787. For the last four and a half years, Blue Man Group has held exclusive court here; its tenure continues indefinitely. Wednesdays and Thursdays at 8 p.m.; Fridays at 7 and 10 p.m.; Saturdays at 4, 7 and 10 p.m.; Sundays at 3 and 6 p.m. Tickets: $39 and $49.</p>
        <p>COLONIAL THEATER, -- 100 Boylston Street, (617) 426-9366. The season begins on Aug. 27 with ''Seussical'' (through Sept. 17) and will include ''Fiddler on the Roof'' and ''Les Miserables.''</p>
        <p>EMERSON MAJESTIC THEATER, -- 219 Tremont Street, (617) 824-8000. The season begins on Sept. 22 with ''The Crutchmaster'' a dance production.</p>
        <p>HUNTINGTON THEATER, -- 264 Huntington Avenue (at Massachusetts Avenue), (617) 266-7900. The season begins on Sept. 8 with ''Dead End,'' a play by Sidney Kingsley.</p>
        <p>SHUBERT THEATER, -- 265 Tremont Street, (617) 482-9393; tickets, (800) 447-7400. The season begins on Sept. 19 with ''Copacabana.'' The Boston Lyric Opera's ''Madama Butterfly'' opens on Oct. 4.</p>
        <p>WANG CENTER FOR THE PERFORMING ARTS, -- 270 Tremont Street, (617) 482-9393; tickets: (800) 447-7400. ''Miss Saigon,'' through June 25. Tuesdays through Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 7:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays at 2 p.m. Tickets: $15 to $65. ''Eric Idle Exploits Monty Python,'' at 8 p.m. on June 29. Tickets: $26 to $56. ''The Music of Andrew Lloyd Webber,'' with Michael Bolton, July 13-16. Thursdays and Fridays at 8 p.m.; Saturdays at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sundays at 1 and 7 p.m. Tickets: $35 to $65.</p>
        <p>WILBUR THEATER, -- 246 Tremont Street, (617) 423-4008. The season begins on Sept. 22 with ''Little Women,'' and includes ''Fully Committed'' and ''Dame Edna.''</p>
        <p>Washington</p>
        <p>FORD'S THEATER, -- 511 10 Street N.W., (800) 955-5566 or (703) 218-6500. The season begins on Sept. 26 with ''Inherit the Wind,'' starring James Whitmore; it will be followed by ''A Christmas Carol.''</p>
        <p>Mindy Aloff is the dance critic for The New Republic.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 3, 2000, Monday  An article in Weekend on June 23 about historic theaters misstated the history of Ford's Theater in Washington. The building was not torn down after the assassination of President Abraham Lincoln. It was gutted and the interior became office space in the 1930's, but the walls were left standing. A restoration of the theater began in 1965, based on photographs taken by Mathew Brady, and the new Ford's opened in 1968.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 3, 2000, Monday</p>
        <p>An article in Weekend on June 23 about historic theaters misstated the history of Ford's Theater in Washington. The building was not torn down after the assassination of President Abraham Lincoln. It was gutted and the interior became office space in the 1930's, but the walls were left standing. A restoration of the theater began in 1965, based on photographs taken by Mathew Brady, and the new Ford's opened in 1968.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Mindy Aloff is the dance critic for The New Republic.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
