<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yanks Want Gonzalez, but Does He Want Yanks?</title>
    <meta content="23PINS$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209640"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Detroit Tigers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzalez, Juan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E4DC1630F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1203" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yanks Want Gonzalez, but Does He Want Yanks?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, June 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees agree to trade in principle for Detroit Tigers player Juan Gonzalez and have until Sunday to negotiate contract extension with him; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees have agreed to a trade in principle for the Detroit slugger Juan Gonzalez and have until Sunday to negotiate a contract extension with the two-time most valuable player, numerous baseball officials said today.</p>
        <p>In return for Gonzalez, the Yankees have agreed to swap Drew Henson, their best prospect, as well as outfielder Ricky Ledee and the left-handed pitcher Randy Keisler, currently in Class AA.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees have agreed to a trade in principle for the Detroit slugger Juan Gonzalez and have until Sunday to negotiate a contract extension with the two-time most valuable player, numerous baseball officials said today.</p>
        <p>In return for Gonzalez, the Yankees have agreed to swap Drew Henson, their best prospect, as well as outfielder Ricky Ledee and the left-handed pitcher Randy Keisler, currently in Class AA.</p>
        <p>The Yankees are still negotiating with the Chicago Cubs for Sammy Sosa, but have found the asking price of five or more players to be high. The Yankees will not complete trades for both players.</p>
        <p>The 30-year-old Gonzalez, who drove in more than 100 runs seven times with the Texas Rangers, controls his future because a limited no-trade clause in his contract allows him to veto any proposed trade to a New York team. He could say no to the Yankees, flatly, because he does not want to play in New York. Luis Mayoral, a long-time friend of Gonzalez and the Tigers' Latin American liaison, told The Detroit Free Press today: ''New York is too fast for Juan's persona. He likes Arlington and Detroit.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees contacted Gonzalez's agent, Jim Bronner, today, but made no immediate progress toward securing the player's approval either for the trade or for a contract extension.</p>
        <p>Gonzalez said after tonight's game in Toronto that he knows his response to the Yankees' initial overture, but wouldn't say what it is.</p>
        <p>Gonzalez would not reveal his feelings about staying or leaving Detroit. Playing for a winning team, he said, ''is very important to me.''</p>
        <p>''I played with Texas and we won three of the last four years,'' he said. ''When you win, everything is exciting.''</p>
        <p>Referring to Yankee Stadium, Gonzalez said, ''There are a lot of legends there and a great winning attitude.''</p>
        <p>Bernie Williams, the Yankees' center fielder, has known Gonzalez for years, and he nodded slightly, knowingly, when it was mentioned that Gonzalez might have reservations about playing in New York. ''I think he had an impression of coming into the city and being bombarded by the media and the fans, and the fans were very rowdy towards him,'' Williams said. ''I think that's probably the impression he has of New York.</p>
        <p>''It's like every other player who refuses to come here because they have a bad impression of what it is to play with the Yankees. I don't think any of the players who have played with us the last four or five years have anything bad to say about playing in New York. He certainly would help us -- a two-time m.v.p. He can hit in the clutch, and he can have stretches where he can carry the club all by himself. He's the kind of offensive player that cannot hurt a team.''</p>
        <p>Gonzalez, who is in the last year of his contract, could agree to play for the Yankees, but refuse to sign a contract extension. This would give the slugger a stage with a contending team in the months before he can become a free agent. But the Yankees probably wouldn't be interested because they don't want to give up top prospects for what would essentially be a three-month rental.</p>
        <p>Gonzalez could agree to a contract extension, although he has already rejected a huge offer from the Tigers -- something in the range of eight years for $140 million, or about $17.5 million per year -- and, reportedly, Bronner asked the Tigers for $148 million over eight years. The Yankees presumably would have to make a similar commitment to Gonzalez to sign him.</p>
        <p>With the Tigers and Yankees on the cusp of a deal Wednesday, Detroit officials went to Toronto, where the Tigers were playing, and are believed to have met with Gonzalez. Whatever Gonzalez told them did not discourage the Tigers.</p>
        <p>Getting the 20-year-old Henson could be a huge coup for Detroit. He attended high school in Michigan and expects to be the starting quarterback for the University of Michigan this fall. There remains a question of whether Henson will play baseball or football professionally.</p>
        <p>In return for Sosa, the officials said, the Cubs have asked the Yankees for at least five players, among a group that includes the Class AAA shortstop Alfonso Soriano; Henson; Ledee; Keisler; the recently promoted pitcher Jake Westbrook and the Class AA right-hander David Walling. The market for Sosa has not been robust, and the Yankees may be trying to use the Gonzalez negotiations to push the Cubs. Many of the advisers to George Steinbrenner, the Yankees' principal owner, have told him that Gonzalez is a better all-around player, but Sosa possesses more marquee value.</p>
        <p>Signing Gonzalez would propel the Yankees' payroll to astronomical levels. If an agreement were reached, the Yankees would most likely have to pay Gonzalez about $17 million per year. They already have to pay Bernie Williams $12.5 million a year through the 2006 season. Derek Jeter is making $10 million this year and will make much more than that in the future; negotiations for a $118.5 million deal have fallen apart and Jeter's long-term deal could eventually approach $20 million per season. Mariano Rivera, the closer, is making $7.25 million this year and soon could command in excess of $20 million per season.</p>
        <p>The Yankees are paying second baseman Chuck Knoblauch $6 million for this year and next, and at the time they traded for him in 1998, they agreed to give him a two-year, $18 million extension that has never been announced. Similarly, Roger Clemens is expected to receive a two-year extension for about $14 million to $15 million per year for 2001-2002. The Yankees' payroll, now at $92 million, could approach $140 million to $150 million in two years. But the Yankees can expect a significant increase in television revenue because their cable deal expires after this year.</p>
        <p>The Yankees would not acquire Gonzalez or Sosa and then stick him in the sixth or seventh spot in the lineup. Either would be jammed right into the middle.</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre could use Gonzalez or Sosa as the cleanup hitter, behind Paul O'Neill, and bump the rest of the hitters down one spot, Williams from fourth to fifth, Tino Martinez from fifth to sixth, and so on. Gonzalez or Sosa could bat third, with Williams remaining in the cleanup spot and O'Neill hitting fifth, but that would create a logjam of right-handed hitters at the top and bottom of the order.</p>
        <p>The lineup that might force a manager to make the most difficult decisions would be to bat Williams third, Gonzalez or Sosa fourth, O'Neill fifth, Jorge Posada sixth and Martinez seventh: In order, a switch-hitter, a right-handed hitter, a left-handed hitter, a switch-hitter and a left-handed hitter.</p>
        <p>The Yankees continue to search for pitching help. They had a scout watch the Rangers righthander Esteban Loaiza on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
