<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Icahn Increases Nabisco Bid For Second Time in 2 Days</title>
    <meta content="Y23FOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209536"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nabisco Group Holdings</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Danone Sa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cadbury Schweppes Plc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philip Morris Cos</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Icahn, Carl C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E6DB1F31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="603" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Icahn Increases Nabisco Bid For Second Time in 2 Days</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carl C Icahn, who owns about 10 percent of Nabisco Group, sweetens his offer for company, second time in two days he raises bid; Philip Morris Companies and joint venture of Danone SA and Cadbury Schweppes PLC submit bids for food company; Wall Street Journal says Philip Morris has bid close to $55 a share and that Danone-Cadbury bid is close to $50 a share; Ichan offered $28 a share on June 22, but increased bid next day (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carl C. Icahn, the financier who owns about 10 percent of Nabisco Group, sweetened his offer for the company yesterday, the second time in two days he has raised his bid.</p>
        <p>Mr. Icahn's revised offer was disclosed in a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission after the stock market closed. It came after a telephone conversation he had yesterday morning with Steven F. Goldstone, chairman of Nabisco Holdings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Carl C. Icahn, the financier who owns about 10 percent of Nabisco Group, sweetened his offer for the company yesterday, the second time in two days he has raised his bid.</p>
        <p>Mr. Icahn's revised offer was disclosed in a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission after the stock market closed. It came after a telephone conversation he had yesterday morning with Steven F. Goldstone, chairman of Nabisco Holdings.</p>
        <p>The discussion took place less than a day after the Nabisco Group received bids for its 80.4 percent stake in Nabisco Holdings, and an offer from Mr. Icahn to buy the holding company.</p>
        <p>The Philip Morris Companies and a joint venture of Danone S.A. and Cadbury Schweppes P.L.C. submitted bids for the food company, The Wall Street Journal reported yesterday. The Journal said that Philip Morris had bid close to $55 a share and that the Danone-Cadbury bid was close to $50 a share. Shares of Nabisco Holdings fell $1.6875 yesterday, to $51.5625.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Mr. Icahn offered $28 a share for Nabisco Group, $19 a share in cash and $9 in two-year 14 percent notes. Mr. Icahn then revised and increased that bid yesterday. Shares of Nabisco Group Holdings rose 6.25 cents, to $25.</p>
        <p>In his letter to Mr. Goldstone, Mr. Icahn said he was prepared to pay 88 percent of the after-tax cash price that Nabisco Group received for the food company.</p>
        <p>The revised offer is structured along the lines of an offer that R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Holdings reportedly made for Nabisco Group.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, The Wall Street Journal said Reynolds had submitted a bid that would price the holding company at a 20 percent discount to the net proceeds received from the sale of the food company.</p>
        <p>Jan Smith, a spokeswoman for R. J. Reynolds, declined to comment. Spokesmen for Philip Morris and Danone declined to comment. Nabisco also declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Icahn's offer is not fixed in stone, analysts said it was clearly superior to the bid he made on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''By offering to buy Nabisco Group Holdings at a 12 percent discount to net asset value, Mr. Icahn has raised substantially his bid,'' said Martin Feldman, a tobacco analyst at Salomon Smith Barney. ''The impact of this bid is that it has raised the bar materially for other bidders for Nabisco Group Holdings, including R. J. Reynolds.''</p>
        <p>Board members of Nabisco Group  are expected to meet this morning to consider the offers.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Feldman and others said they did not consider the bids submitted thus far to be the final offers the company would receive.</p>
        <p>They pointed to the fact that Mr. Goldstone called Mr. Icahn and encouraged him to raise his bid as evidence that the bidding was not over. If Mr. Goldstone spoke with Mr. Icahn, the analysts reasoned, he most likely placed similar calls to executives at Philip Morris and Danone.</p>
        <p>''Steven Goldstone is going to do everything he can to grow the sale price between now and the time the holding company and the food company are eventually sold,'' Mr. Feldman said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
