<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CABARET GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="23CABA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7DE1F31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2310" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CABARET GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stephen Holden</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing of new or noteworthy cabaret shows in Manhattan this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>BARBARA CARROLL, Bemelmans Bar, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, (212) 744-1600. This agelessly chic red-haired pianist and singer seems to know every important popular song ever written and to be able to perform from memory in any key. Her elegant, lyrical pianism is a compendium of 20th-century jazz styles, from Count Basie to Erroll Garner to Bill Evans and beyond. And her clipped, understated vocals, which verge on speech-song, approach lyrics from a wry but warmhearted point of view. Through July 22. Tuesday through Saturday nights, beginning at 9:30. From 5:30 to 8, Michael Devine. No cover for early show; cover for late show: $15. No minimum; $5 cover at the bar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing of new or noteworthy cabaret shows in Manhattan this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>BARBARA CARROLL, Bemelmans Bar, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, (212) 744-1600. This agelessly chic red-haired pianist and singer seems to know every important popular song ever written and to be able to perform from memory in any key. Her elegant, lyrical pianism is a compendium of 20th-century jazz styles, from Count Basie to Erroll Garner to Bill Evans and beyond. And her clipped, understated vocals, which verge on speech-song, approach lyrics from a wry but warmhearted point of view. Through July 22. Tuesday through Saturday nights, beginning at 9:30. From 5:30 to 8, Michael Devine. No cover for early show; cover for late show: $15. No minimum; $5 cover at the bar.</p>
        <p>* HOWARD FISHMAN QUARTET, Sardi's, 234 West 44th Street, (212) 221-8440. Powerful echoes of Stephane Grappelli and Bix Beiderbecke are among the influences rippling through the Howard Fishman Quartet's seamless swing. The group -- Mr. Fishman on guitar, banjo and vocals; Russell Farhang playing virtuosic Grappelli-style violin; Peter Ecklund on cornet; Andrew Hall on bass -- folds elements of vintage jazz, swing and early bluegrass into rhythmically animated, richly allusive jazz chamber music. Whether the music is Stephen Foster (a bubbly ''Old Folks at Home''), Gershwin (''Soon'') or Romberg (''When I Grow Too Old to Dream''), it is all translated into lilting, fine-tuned ensemble music that transcends time and idiom. Fridays at 10:30 p.m. No cover charge, but $15 minimum at tables.</p>
        <p>* ''OUR SINATRA,'' Blue Angel Theater, 323 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. The rising young cabaret star Eric Comstock is the mastermind behind this utterly winning tribute to Ol' Blue Eyes, which focuses on what Mr. Comstock calls the hidden gems and orphan songs that Sinatra made popular. Joined by Christopher Gines, a creamy baritone who echoes Dick Haymes and Steve Lawrence in their prime, and Hilary Kole, a perky swinger, Mr. Comstock conducts a witty and knowledgeable survey of the Sinatra canon. Mr. Comstock focuses on the mature Sinatra and Mr. Gines on the dreamy 1940's balladeer, with Ms. Kole bridging the gap. The memorable show proves that there are still young singers good enough to keep the tradition alive. Today, tomorrow, Monday and Thursday at 8 p.m.; Sunday at 3 and 7:30 p.m.; Wednesday at 2:30 and 8 p.m. Tickets: $50 and $55 (premium ringside seating, $75 and $80).</p>
        <p>* MICHAEL WINTHER, Triad, 158 West 72nd Street, (212) 362-2590. Mr. Winther, a tasteful folk-pop tenor with the range and discipline of a trained theater singer, offers a generous sampling of recent American theater music (some of it from works in progress) in a sophisticated post-Sondheim mode. Among the composers are Adam Guettel, Ricky Ian Gordon, Debra Barsha and Jenny Giering (who accompanies on piano). The musical styles range from formalized folk-pop to funny 80's pop parodies to lush neo-romantic ballads. The abundance of burgeoning talent offers reason for hope. Tomorrow and Sunday at 10 p.m. Cover: $12; two-drink minimum. Also at the Triad, tonight at 8, Lee Truesdale, singer, in ''A Tribute to Love.'' Mondays at 7 p.m. through July 24, Mari Eileen O'Brien, singer, in ''Romance: Something About Love.'' Cover: $15; two-drink minimum.</p>
        <p>FIREBIRD CAFE, 363 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 586-0244. Tonight at 9 and 11, Sian Phillips. Cover: $30; $15 minimum. Tomorrow night at 7, Randa McNamara, singer; at 9 and 11, Kane Alexander, singer. Cover: $25; $15 minimum. Sunday night at 7, Julie Gold, singer-songwriter (part of Firebird Songwriters series); at 9, Martha Lorin, singer. Cover: $20; $15 minimum.</p>
        <p>* BOBBY SHORT, Cafe Carlyle, at the Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, (212) 744-1600. Although his voice has its ups and downs, Mr. Short, now 75, still gives the best cabaret party in New York. For his 32nd spring season at the Cafe Carlyle, he is joined by a small, top-notch swing band, and he struts his bluesier pianism in the instrumental ''Moten Swing.'' Nobody puts a more vivacious spin on Cole Porter than Mr. Short, whose new show includes a boyishly wistful version of ''Why Shouldn't I?'' and the hilariously tongue-twisting, double-entendre-laden title song from ''Can-Can.'' Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:45 and 10:45. Cover: $60 at tables, no minimum; $30 cover at the bar.</p>
        <p>ARCI'S PLACE, 450 Park Avenue South, at 30th Street, (212) 532-4370. Tom Postilio, singer, in ''This Time Around,'' directed by Thommie Walsh. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30 and 11; Tuesday through Thursday at 9. Through July 1. Monday at 8 p.m., Steven Lutvak, singer. Cover: $25; $15 minimum.</p>
        <p>LAURIE BEECHMAN THEATER, West Bank Cafe, 407 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 695-6909. Monday at 8 p.m., ''The Kleinbort Collection,'' presented by Jamie deRoy, featuring songs by Barry Kleinbort, with Brent Barrett, Banny Burstein, Rita Gardner, Eric Michael Gillett, Marcia Lewis, Karen Mason, Mary Testa and Melanie Vaughan. Cover: $12; one-drink minimum.</p>
        <p>DANNY'S SKYLIGHT ROOM, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133. Tonight from 9 to 1 in the piano bar, Jerry Scott; at 9:15, Carolyn Maye, singer. Tomorrow from 5 to 9 p.m. in the piano bar, Chuck Musone; at 7, Jude Treder-Wolff, singer, in ''Evolving at the Speed of Life''; from 9 to 1 in the piano bar, Mr. Scott; at 9:15, Ms. Maye. Sunday night at 6:15, Terrence Kennedy, singer; from 7 to 11, Sol Yaged and friends. Cover: free to $15; $10 minimum.</p>
        <p>DON'T TELL MAMA, 343 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 757-0788. Tonight at 7, Chris Puckett, singer, with Vadim Feichtner, pianist; at 9, Mary Liz McNamara, singer, songwriter and pianist; at 9:30, Beth Valenti, singer, with Rick Jensen, pianist. Tomorrow night at 6, Lisa Asher, singer, with Jeff Waxman, pianist; at 6:30, Elyn Trilby, singer, with Robert Wagner, pianist; at 8:30, ''Poole Party!,'' comedy with Ron Poole; also at 8:30, Peg Winter, singer, with band; at 11, Tommy Femia impersonates Judy Garland. Sunday night at 8, Keith Lawrence, singer, songwriter and pianist. Cover: Free to $15. Two-drink minimum. No credit cards.</p>
        <p>FEINSTEIN'S, at the Regency, 540 Park Avenue, at 61st Street, (212) 339-4095. Vikki Carr. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30 and 11. Cover: $60; dinner required for early show, with seating beginning at 6; a la carte supper menu with $25 minimum for late show. Also at Feinstein's, on Monday nights, Eric Comstock. Beginning Tuesday, Marc Salem, singer.</p>
        <p>JOE'S PUB, Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778 or (212) 239-6200. Harvey Fierstein in ''This Is Not Going to Be Pretty,'' comedy, music and drama in celebration of Gay Pride Week. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30. Tickets: $25.</p>
        <p>OAK ROOM, Algonquin Hotel, 59 West 44th Street, (212) 840-6800. Buddy Greco. Tonight and tomorrow night at 9 and 11:30. Cover: $50, with $50 prix fixe dinner required for early shows Saturdays and Sundays; $15 food or drink minimum for late shows; suggested dinner arrival for early show is 7. Julie Budd opens on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>UPSTAIRS AT ROSE'S TURN, 55 Grove Street, West Village, (212) 366-5438. Tonight at 7, Mike Van Allen Trio; at 9, ''The Elephant Man: The Musical''; at 11, ''Candy Comedy,'' stand-up. Tomorrow night at 7, Tom Kraft, singer; at 11, ''Candy Comedy.'' Sunday night at 7, Karyn Larson. Cover: $5 to $12; two-drink minimum. No credit cards.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
