<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Zimbabwe's Voter Registration in Turmoil</title>
    <meta content="Y23ZIM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209544"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Registration of Voters</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zimbabwe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cauvin, Henri E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Voter Registration and Requirements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E5DA1F31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="605" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Zimbabwe's Voter Registration in Turmoil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRI E. CAUVIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cauvin, Henri E</byline>
      <dateline>HARARE, Zimbabwe, June 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Election monitors in Zimbabwe report that large-scale problems with registration of voters could lead to significant confusion during coming weekend of elections; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Overshadowed by the political violence that has dogged this country for months, large-scale problems with registration of voters remain unresolved and could lead to significant confusion when voters arrive at the polls this weekend, election monitors say.</p>
        <p>More than two million people registered to vote for the first time in this year's election, swelling the national rolls to nearly 6 million, but inexplicably many newcomers' names have not made it onto the books, the monitors say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Overshadowed by the political violence that has dogged this country for months, large-scale problems with registration of voters remain unresolved and could lead to significant confusion when voters arrive at the polls this weekend, election monitors say.</p>
        <p>More than two million people registered to vote for the first time in this year's election, swelling the national rolls to nearly 6 million, but inexplicably many newcomers' names have not made it onto the books, the monitors say.</p>
        <p>While the central government has acknowledged the problem, exactly what is being done to correct it is unclear, the monitors say. They fear that many voters will only discover they are not registered when they show up at polling stations.</p>
        <p>Complicating the matter, voters were not given receipts when they registered, as was done in the past,  leaving them no recourse if they discover on election day that their names were omitted.</p>
        <p>But adding voters to the rolls has not been the only registration problem. Removing them has been similarly troublesome. A study earlier this year by the United Nations Development Program found that anywhere from 10 to 25 percent of the people registered to vote were dead, raising the possibility of fraud.</p>
        <p>''To be honest, the process was handled in a very unfortunate way,'' said Phil Matsheza, chairman of the Zimbabwe Election Support Network, an umbrella organization of civic groups involved in election monitoring. ''These things will definitely affect the vote.''</p>
        <p>With so many unanswered, unresolved questions, voters here might think that the problems are the result of something more than benign neglect, Mr. Matsheza said. ''You want people to believe there's transparency in an electoral process,'' he said. ''But we're all going into the election with one question. Why? Why has the government handled it this way?''</p>
        <p>Jonathan Moyo, a spokesman for President Robert Mugabe's ruling party, the Zimbabwe African National Union-Patriotic Front, said the concerns that have been raised are unfounded, fueled by biased Western international observers who favor the opposition and have turned their jobs into a ''partisan exercise.''</p>
        <p>''We didn't invite them,'' Mr. Moyo said. ''They expressed an interest and we said fine, but they are getting carried away, acting like we are East Timor or Somalia with no constitution and a breakdown in the social order.''</p>
        <p>With the country's economy suffering and many of its people weary of the old guard, the ruling party and its leader, President Mugabe, are facing their first bona fide political challenge in the 20 years since they took control of this former British colony. A new opposition party has drawn widespread support, and the ensuing struggle between them has been ugly, and often bloody.</p>
        <p>The fight to lead the country has drawn considerable international attention, and how the government has handled independent election monitoring has been another source of  concern in recent days, as both local and international observers have faced new limitations and considerable scrutiny by the central government.</p>
        <p>The most restrictive step would have prohibited civic groups from assigning more than one observer to a polling station. The organizations, which had been planning to send four observers to each site, complained that the strain for one monitor to shoulder the responsibility alone during two 12-hour days of voting would undermine the effort. Today, in a sharp turnabout, the government said it would ease the policy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
