<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ART GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="23D02SPT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01EFDF1630F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="4631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ART GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The New York Times of new or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most gallieres are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery Admission is free.  *denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The New York Times of new or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most gallieres are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery Admission is free.  *denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* ANN ALBERS, Jewish Museum, Fifth Avenue at 92nd Street, (212)423-3200 (through Aug. 20). This survey of arguably the most influential textile artist of the 20th century is part retrospective, part weaving seminar, part biography - and altogether fascinating. It traces the development of Albers's work from her student days at the Bauhaus to Black Mountain College where she taught with her husband, Josef. It contrasts her designs for commercial fabrics, which emphasized structure and materials in new ways, with her pictorially striking handloomed pieces. A gallery of photographs, letters, personal memorabilia and pre-Columbian textile fragments she collected reflects her character and quietly glamorous personal style. Hours; Sundays through Thursdays, 11 a.m. to 5:45 p.m.; Tuesdays to 8 p.m. Admission: $8; $5.50, students and senior citizens; free for children under 12 (Roberta Smith).</p>
        <p>* ''THE ART OF WILLIAM EDMONDSON,'' Museum of American Folk Art, 2 Lincoln Square, (212)595-9533 (through Aug. 27). All creatures, celestial, human and animal, find their way into the limestone sculpture of Edmondson (1874-1951) and the results feel like an epic folk oepra: score by Scott Joplin, libretto by Aesop, choreography by the great master dancers of Yorubaland. This exhibition also includes photographs of the artist by Edward Weston, Consuelo Kanaga and Louise Dahl-Wolfe, showing him at home in Nashville, where, at 59, he began to carve gravestones and garden ornaments for the local African-American community. In 1937 he made a solo debutat the Museum of Modern Art, and he has been part of the American pantheon ever since. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11:30 a.m. to 7:30 p.m. Free (Holland Cotter).</p>
        <p>&amp; ''ART AND ORACLE: SPIRIT VOICES OF AFRICA,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street, (212)535-7710 (through July 30). This is the first big international loan exhibition of African art to appear at the Met outside the Michael C. Rockefeller wing, and it is gorgeous. The subject is divination, the practice of channeling superhuman knowledge to predictthe future, diagnose illness and promote social harmony. Nearly every object here has a role in that process or reflects its effects, from a ''power figure'' that looks as explosive as a stick of dynamite to a Yoruba divination tray believed to be the oldest African wood sculpture in the West, to the portrait of a king who was warned by diviners to beware of water and had himself depicted a half-fish. (He ended up in exile far across the Atlantic in Martinique.) Hours: Sundays and Tuesdays through Thursdays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:15 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays until 8:45 p.m. Admission: $10; $5, students and the elderly (Cotter).</p>
        <p>''THE CHANGING FACE OF LIBERTY: FEMALE ALLEGORIES OF AMERICA,'' New-York Historical Society, 2 West 77th street, (212)873-3400 (through Sept. 3). Uncle Sam, the allegorical male representative of the United States, has always had a female counterpart, the damsel dressed in flowing robes who came to symbolize Liberty. As a sequel to who came to symbolize Liberty. As a sequel to its ''Uncle Sam'' show, the historical society mounted this very lively display of his iconic sister in her many guises, from ''L'Amerique,'' an Indian princess with feathers in her hair who represented the New World in post-Columbus maps, to the matronly Lady Liberty protrayed in the Bartholdi statue that stands in New York Harbor. The fascinating story of Liberty's evolution is told in posters, cartoons, illustrations and photographs. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $5; $3, students over 12 and the elderly (Grce Glueck)</p>
        <p>* WILLIAM MERRITT CHASE, ''Modern American Landscapes, 1886-1890,'' Brooklyn Museum of Art, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718)638-5000 (through Aug. 13). Chase (1849-1916) had a long, distinguished run as a painter, teacher and art politician. But this show zeroes in on the five-year period when, in a transitional phase between the brown, murky tones of his Munich training and his arrival at a lighter style based on French Impressionism, he painted genteel views of park landscapes in Brooklyn and Manhattan. Aside from their engaging scenic content, the 35 oils and pastels in the show are important because they are the first paintings in which an Impressionist style was used to depict American subjects. Recent examination corrected some errors about their locales. And new scholarly speculation on Chase's motives for painting them suggest that he wanted them to serve as examples of ''civilized urban landscapes'' that accorded with the European avant-garde model of modern life. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m (to 11 p.m. on the first Saturday of each month). Admission: $4; $2, students and the elderly (Glueck).</p>
        <p>VIVIAN CHERRY, ''A Working Street Photographer, 1940's-1990's,'' Brooklyn Museum of Art, 200 Eastern Parkway at Prospect Park, (718)638-5000 (through Aug. 6). A fast eye, a quick mind and a speedy shutter are essentials for a good street photographer, a breed of picture-taker with which Ms. Cherry proudly identifies. Over the last half-century she has taken her lens from Depression-era Harlem to Mexico and the rural South, and this show of more than 70 works, organized from the museum's own collection, has some real strengths. Among them is a troubling 1948 series on small boys in New York City playing at adult violence, menacing each oter with authentic-looking toy guns and staging ''lynchings.'' Most of the photographs are in vintage black-and-white, with more edge to them that her recent color photographs of Mexico and Times Square. Hours and admission: See above (Glueck).</p>
        <p>''STUART DAVIS IN GLOUCESTER,'' National Academy of Design, 1083 Fifth Avenue, at 90th Street, (212)369-4880 (through July 30). The quaint fishing port of Gloucester, Mass., seemed an unlikely hangout for the jazy city painter Davis (1894-1964). But he actually loved the place, and in the summers he spent there, from 1915 to 1934, he used motifs drawn from the rocky coast, the townscape and the maritime activity as he worked toward a more progressive style of painting. This show, with some 45 oils, watercolors and drawings, gives a good account of his struggles in assimilating Modernist ideas to arrive at the innovative American Cubist style for which he is celebrated. But in the end, Davis's art had more to do with his own genius: his gift for paring line and shape to essences and uniting them with scintillating color. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m.; Fridays to 6 p.m. Admission: $8; $4.50, children 6 to 16, students and the elderly (Glueck).</p>
        <p>* ''EDWARD HOPPER, PRINTMAKER,'' Whitney Museum of American Art, 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212)570-3676 (through July 16). Before concentrating on paintings, Hopper (1882-1967) made prints from 1913 to 1923. In that decade he produced his first mature work, a wonderful body of etchings that brought realism, emotion and a strong sense of the medium's potential to a field that had become more decorative than challenging. Using many of the motifs he was to pursue in his later paintings - nudes, loners, decrepit houses, night scenes, railraod trains - Hopper took full advantage of the intense moodiness a black-and-white etching can convey. The pervasive theme of loneliness and isolation for which he was noted is very much present in this show. The nearly 50 works here are a fine introduction to Hopper's basic themes, and give a splendid idea of what he accomplished in the demanding medium. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays, and Fridays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Thursdays, 1 to 8 p.m. Admision: $12.50; $10.50, students and the elderly (Glueck).</p>
        <p>* ''MAKING CHOICES, 1920-1960,'' Museum of Modern Art, 11 West 53rd Street, (212)708-9480 (through Sept. 26). The main event at the Modern these days is the museum itself. This has been the case since last fall, when the project ''MOMA 2000'' began the first of what will be three successive top-to-bottom re-installations of the permanent collection galleries. The affair has been billed as a test drive for the future, a chance for an institution to rethink the modern art tradition that it helped invent and to consider its own identity in what is often called a postmodern world. This second installment, which looks denser, weirder, messier and more truly modern (or maybe post modern) than the first, is a big leap in the right direction. Hours; Thursdays through Tuesdays, 10:30 a.m. to 5:45 p.m.; Fridays, to 8:15 p.m. Admission: $10; $6.50, students and the elderly (Cotter).</p>
        <p>* ''OTHER PICTURES: VERNACULAR PHOTOGRAPHS FROM THE THOMAS WALTHER COLLECTION,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth avenue at 82nd Street, (212)535-7710 (through Aug. 27). A deceptively modest and sublimely endearing exhibtion of several dozen photographs by anonymous amateurs, shot between the 1910's and 1960's, the heyday of the black-and-white snapshot, Surrealism and New Vision photography. They're a catalog of aspiring masterpieces in a modernist mode and serendipitous catastrophes. In the extraordinary way such things happen, these pictures traveled from drug-store to family album to attic to Dumpster to flea market into the hands of some scavenging dealer-collector, whereupon they became items on the art market, until finally wending their way to their present location. Isn't life amazing sometimes? And don't miss ''The Snapshot'' (through July 21), a companion show at the excellent Ubu Gallery, nearby at 16 East 78th street, which includes several dozen more amateurs' gems, equally lovable. Hours and admission: See above (Michael Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>* ''PAINTERS IN PARIS: 1895-1950,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street, (212)535-7710 (through Dec 31). This show of more than 100 paintings celebrates the Met's acquisitions of works by School of Paris painters, going back to 1946 when Gertrude Stein bequeathed her portrait, done by Picasso in 1906. The portrait served as a cornerstone for later acquisitons in the field, particularly over the last 20 years. The museum's increasing interest and diligent wooing of collectors have not only brought single works but also groups and entire holdings, like the major objects bequeathed by Florene M Schoenborn in 1995 and the Jaques and Natasha Gelman trove of 85 masterpieces accessioned in 1998. The treasureson view include works by some of the 20th century's greatest: Bonnard, Braque, Chagall, de Chirico, Derain, Gris, Leger, Matisse, Miro, Modigliani and Picasso, in an animated arrangement that should beguile the most jaded Metgoer. Hours and admission: See above (Glueck).</p>
        <p>''1900: ART AT THE CROSSROADS,'' Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212)423-3500 (through Sept. 10). A wacky exercise in historical simulation, the excuse being a new century. It is hard to remember the last time so many bad pictures were in one place at one time, unless you consider eBay a place. There is also a good deal of excellent art mixed in among the dogs, and sometimes what is best is not what you would expect, which is partly the show's point. We're meant to look anew at a moment 100 years ago when it was not yet clear who would be the pioneers in the 20th century and who would be forgotten. The show provides just enough compensatory rewards for its schlock quotient. The weak-hearted and modern-day cultural Pharisees may never get past the shock of confronting so much of the art that the abstractionists were rebelling against in a museum created as a shrine to 20th-century abstraction. Hours: Sundays through Wednesdays, 9 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 8 p.m. Admission: $12; $7, students and the elderly (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>JOHN BOWMAN, Winston Wachter Mayer, 39 East 78th Street, (212)327-2526 (through June 30). Since the 1980's, Mr. Bowman has been using traditional painting styles to allegorie postmodernist historical and philosophical conundrums. More interesting conceptually than formally, his new paintings include mysterious images of Renaissance-style theater prosceniums teeming with Ensoresquefaces, masks and gargoyles. In one we look out from the stage over a serene, autumnal forest. Maybe the empty stage signifies the end of master narratives (Ken Johnson).</p>
        <p>WILLEM DE KOONING, ''Mostly Women,'' Gagosian Gallery, 980 Madison Avenue, at 76th Street, (212)744-2313 (through June 30). Dominated by deKooning's lush, disheveled paintings and drawings of women frm the middle 1960's, this show has the intimacy and excitement of a visit to the artist's studio. The works, from the collection of John Kimiko Powers, come in all shapes and sizes and are executed on whatever's-handy surfaces - from paper towels to hollow-core doors. They are often affectionately inscribed by the artist (Smith).</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>* ''EXTRA ORDINARY,'' James Cohan, 41 West 57th Street, (212)755-7171 (through July 7) This excellent group exhibition presents avariety of ways of defamiliarizing the familiar. Outstanding works include a near-hallucinatory sculptural portrait of an elderly woman by Ron Mueck, Tom Friedman's actual-size ladybug, Roxy Paine's mushroom field, Michael Combs's carved and painted dead duck, FrancisCape's mysterious cabinet, Vija Celmins's velvety starry sky painting, Robert Gober's folded door and glamorous floor polishers appropriated by Jeff Koons (Johnson).</p>
        <p>ANDY GOLDSWORTHY, ''A Line and a Wall,'' Galerie Lelong, 20 West 57th Street, (212)315-0470 (through June 28). Two impressive installations set up an engaging dialogue of opposites. In one, a loopy line of thin rush reeds wanders all over the ceilings and walls of the gallery, and in and out of doorways. The other piece is an inches-thick wall of mud that has dried into a deep crawuelure pattern. A face-off, you might say, between the Mercurial and the Saturnine (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>''ARTISTS OF YADDO: 1965-2000,'' Claudia Carr, 478 Broadway, at Spring Street, (212)673-5518 (through June 30). This seven-artist show presents intimate works on paper made at Yaddo, bucolic artists' retreat in upstate New York. The exhibition includes pastel color field swith cosmic sprials by Jason Stewart, sketchy Mondrianesque studies by Ward Jackson, Tantric-style mandalas by Jeanne Miles, richly colored biomorphic abstractions by Garth Evans, fields of gestural knots by Melissa Meyer and essays in sensuous layering by Garry Mitchell and Darra Keeton. (Johnson).</p>
        <p>JEFFREY STURGES, Spencer Brownstone, 39 Wooster Street, (212)334-3455 (through June 30). Photography of corporate, industrial or otherwise anonymous functional architecture is a common genre now, but Mr. Sturges gives it a compelling beauty in large, richly colored prints. Pictures of a brick wall sandwiched between deep blue sky and intensely green grass or of a well-lighted and clean pedestrian tunnel in Zurich are compositionally perfect and dreamily vivid (Johnson).</p>
        <p>PHILIP TRAGER, ''Changing Paris: A Tour Along the Seine,'' Julie Saul, 560 Broadway, at Prince Street, (212)431-0747 (through June 30). Mr. Trager has been photographing architecture since the 1970's. His perfectly composed, richly printed views of Paris have a sober, self-effacing clarity; but they are animated, too, by subtly romantic or dreamy feelings, as in a wide-angle shot of I. M. Pei's glass pyramid rising in the Louvre courtyard or a study of neo-classical armor carved in stone on an 18th-century hotel rooftop (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>''AMBIENT FICTION,'' Pat Hearn, 530 West 22ndf Street, (212)727-7366 (through July 1). This three-artist show proves that paintings and electronically activated art should be kept separate. Monique Prieto used a computer to generate the bulbous forms in her buoyant, Neo-Color Field painting; Jeff Elrod used a mouse to make the sketchy, mechanical doodle on which he based a wall-painting. But these artist's nonmoving, nonilluminated works fade next to Jeff Zilm's hypnotic video projection of a stripe that rapidly changes color to the sound of digital music (Johnson).</p>
        <p>ERICA BAUM, D'Amelio Terras, 525 West 22nd Street, (212)352-9460 (through June 30). This conceptual photographer makes visually nondescript, digitally processed pictures of enlarged sections of book indices. The books are unnamed, the lists like poetry. One reads (leaving out the page numbers), ''Somebody, somehow, someone, speak,'' Another, ''Elastic air, electric girl'' (Johnson).</p>
        <p>GREG CHANN, Margaret Thatcher, 529 West 20th Street, (212)675-0222 (through June 30). At first Mr. Chann's elegant graphite-on-vellum abstractions look like amorphous clouds of dark smoke. On closer examination one sees that they are pieced together from differnt rectangular sections, setting up a subtle dialogue between planar constructivism and natural flux (Johnson)</p>
        <p>WALTON FORD, Paul Kasmin, 293 10th Avenue, at 27th Street, (212)563-4474 (through June 30). An impressive life-size watercolor of a rampaging Indian elephant dominates this exhibition. The galloping, sexually aroused pachyderm is rendered in faux-antique style on 22 separately framed pages assembled into one looming 12-by-18-foot rectangle. Curiously, the elephant has attracted dozens of birds - owls, starlings, goldfinches, vultures, larks; they are meant to sympbolize Western efforts to colonize India (Johnson).</p>
        <p>PAUL GEORGES, ''The Big Idea,'' Center for Figurative Painting, 115 West 30th Street, (212)868-3452 (through June 30). Although he has stayed with traditional subject matter - self-portraits, nudes, landscapes, flowers and mythological scenes - Mr. Georges brings a modernist outlook to it. This mini-retrospective of nearly 20 paintings in diverse styles reveals how he has brightened and lightened his palette over the years, tempering his affection for the old masters with the here and now. An example is an inviting self-portrait of 1989-90 whose welcoming informality is conveyed in a dazzlement of light and color. He is also amaster at flower painting; his colorful blooms, in gardens or in vases, have a lusty freshness few contemporary painters can match (Glueck).</p>
        <p>EMIL LUKAS, ''The Use of Evidence,'' Gorney Bravin + Lee, 534 West 26th Street, (212)352-8872 (through June 30). Mr. Lukas's eccentric experiments with processes and materials are intellectually engaging if not aesthetically appealing. He puddles paint into the convexities of deformed canvases; he drops a sheet of glass onto wet plaster, which dries into a remarkable, all-over bubble pattern; he put live maggots into a hole in a block of plaster, poured ink over them and watched them crawl out, creating an abstract composition of linear trails (Johnson).</p>
        <p>THOM LUSSIER, Paul Morris, 465 West 23rd Street, (212)727-2752 (through June 30). For his large color photographs, Mr. Lussier shoots men in public places so that they appear as dark, enigmatic silhouettes. The shadow figure may be a gimmick but the men, their features entirely submerged in darkness, have an unsettling, vaguely menacing, yet seductive presence (Johnson).</p>
        <p>HELEN MIRRA, Gasser &amp; Grunert, 524 West 19th Street, (212)807-9494 (through July 1) This Chicago-based artist's first New York solo is spare and oblique, but it has a warm and subtle wit. Long narrow text on fabric works describe scenes from Buster Keaton's movie ''The Navigator,'' while a little wooden ship plies the gallery floor; longitudinal, dyed fabric strips map the world and striped, handwoven wool rugs over thick planks allude to railroad beds and, maybe, Carl Andre's floor-bound Minimalism (Johnson).</p>
        <p>RICHARD PRINCE, Barbara Gladstone Gallery, 515 West 24th Street, (212)206-9300 (through June 30). After 20 years, Mr. Prince continues to produce work that disturbs, resists assimilation as art, questions authorship and effectively uses photo appropriation to expose some of the weirder corners of American pop culture. Here he takes (mostly) real publicity photographs of rock n' roll, screen and television stars, supplies signatures himself and adds bits of art, his own included. Grouping personalities according to genre, role or appearance, the pieces are about different stereotypes and pop cultural camouflage. They present the artist as ultimate fan, but as the images are all dedicated to him, they also suggest the fan as ultimate star (Smith).</p>
        <p>BARBARA SCHWARTZ, Andre Zarre, 515 West 20th Street, (212)255-0202. (throug June 30). Known for her energetic abstract wall sculpture, Ms. Schwart here shows a series of lively glazed tile paintings made at a ceramics factory in Italy. Ovals and cruciform shapes bearing expressionistically singly or fitted together into complex emblematic configurations that have a certain gaudy, Mediterranean decorative appeal (Johnson).</p>
        <p>JIM TOIA, Kim Foster, 529 West 20th Street, (212)229-0044 (through July 1). This New Jersey-based sculptor subjects natural objects to unnatural procedures. He cut a slender tree truck into sections, which he hinged back together and now displays in a snaky pile; he arranged scores of short tree-limb segments into an elaborate, ritualistic wall-scale grid; and he paints Modernist abstract images on big, dried bracket mushrooms (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>''AT THE EDGE: A PORTUGUESE FUTURIST - AMADEO DE SOUZA CARDOSO,'' AXA Gallery, 787 Seventh Avenue, at 51st Street, (212)554-1704 (through Sept. 16). One of those perfect, dropped-from-the-sky retrospectives, this show introduces a talented and ambitious Portuguese modernist who died in 1918 at the age of 30. In the previous 10 years he had absorbed several budding modern art movements in Paris, especially Cubism and Futurism, combined them with references to things Portuguese and produced vividly-colored, carefully calibrated paintings. They seem ahead of their time in their missing of styles, images, materials and cultural references. His exceptional draftsmanship is shown in a series of ultra-refined drawings that suggest Ingres high on Cubism (Smith).</p>
        <p>BRENDA JOY LEM, Museum of Chinese in the Americas, 70 Mulberry Street, Chinatown, (212)619-4785 (through June 30). It is always a moving experience to visit this small institution. the lantern-shaped central gallery is filled with relics of immigrant life. A second gallery holds new art. On view is work by Ms. Lem, a Chinese-Canadian artist: banners silk-screened with family photographs and hand-written books about the artist's childhood. The spare installation is the visual equivalent of oral history (Cotter).</p>
        <p>ROBERT LOBE, Senior &amp; Shopmaker, 21 East 26th Street, (212)213-6767 (through June 30). His first show in New York since 1992 finds Mr. Lobe still copying trees and boulders by wrapping sheets of aluminum around them and hammering the metal to conform to their shapes and textures. Freestanding or wall hung, the sculptures hover between naturalism and Minimalism. They have rough yet fragile presence, but you wonder what would happen if Mr. Lobe tried something different - like, say, painting them (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''SHASTA SIKANDER: ACTS OF BALANCE,'' Whitney Museum of American Art at Philip Morris, 120 Park Avenue, at 42nd Street, (917)663-2453 (through July 7). Ms. Sikander has received well-deserved attention for her vivid, complex paintings, which infuse the traditional miniatures of India with a new cross-cultural content. For this exhibition she has expanded her themes into wall paintings veiled with sheets of opaque paper. The results, though ambitious, look obscurant rather than revealing. More successful are three large paintings hung high in the adjoining atrium, which suggest that this gifted artist is trying to move beyond the miniaturist label in what feels like a transitional show (Cotter).</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>''AT THE EDGE: A PORTUGUESE FUTURIST - AMADEO DE SOUZA CARDOSO,'' AXA Gallery, 787 Seventh Avenue, at 51st Street, (212)554-1704 (through Sept. 16). One of those perfect, dropped-from-the-sky retrospectives, this show introduces a talented and ambitious Portuguese modernist who died in 1918 at the age of 30. In the previous 10 years he had absorbed several budding modern art movements in Paris, especially Cubism and Futurism, combined them with references to things Portuguese and produced vividly-colored, carefully calibrated paintings. They seem ahead of their time in their missing of styles, images, materials and cultural references. His exceptional draftsmanship is shown in a series of ultra-refined drawings that suggest Ingres high on Cubism (Smith).</p>
        <p>BRENDA JOY LEM, Museum of Chinese in the Americas, 70 Mulberry Street, Chinatown, (212)619-4785 (through June 30). It is always a moving experience to visit this small institution. The lantern-shaped central gallery is filled with relics of immigrant life. A second gallery holds new art. On view is work by Ms. Lem, a Chinese-Canadian artist: banners silk-screened with family photographs and hand-written books about the artist's childhood. The spare installation is the visual equivalnt of oral history (Cotter).</p>
        <p>ROBERT LOBE, Senior &amp; Shopmaker, 21 East 26th Street, (212)213-6767 (through June 30). His first show in New York since 1992 finds Mr. Lobe still copying trees and boulders by wrapping sheets of aluminum around them and hammering the metal to conform to their shapes and textures. Freestanding or wall hung, the sculputres hover between naturalism and Minimalism. They have rough yet fragile presence, but you wonder what would happen if Mr. Lobe tried something different - like, say, painting them (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''SHAHZIA SIKANDER: ACTS BALANCE,'' Whitney Museum of American Art at Philip Morris, 120 Park Avenue, at 42nd Street, (917)663-2453 (through July 7). Ms. Sikander has received well-deserved attention for her vivid, complex paintings, which infuse the traditional miniatures of India with a new cross-cultural content. For this exhibition she has expanded her themes into wall paintings veiled with sheets of opaque paper. The results, though ambitious, look obscurant rather than revealing. More successful are three large paintings hung high in the adjoining atrium, which suggest that this gifted artist is trying to move beyond the miniaturist label in what feels like a transitional show (Cotter).</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>ELENA CLIMENT, Mary-Anne Martin, 23 East 73rd Street, (212)288-2213 (through Thursday). A mostly self-taught painter who lives in Mexico and Chicago, Ms. Climent presents studiously detailed, altar like images of personal momentos arranged before windows with expansive outdoor views. The painting is technically nondescript, but at their best the pictures have autobiographical resonance, intriguing spatial complexity and magic luminosity (Johnson).</p>
        <p>THORNTON DIAL/MORTON BARTLETT, Ricco/Maresca, 529 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212)627-4819 (through tomorrow). Mr. Dial, the self-taught Alabaman, shows wildly gestural linear charcoal drawings, mostly of figures and mostly charged with hyperkinetic eroticism. They are a refreshing change from his heavily layered and constructed paintings. Bartlett (1909-1992) was a Harvard-educated businessman who secretly made amazingly lifelike, half-size female dolls, clothes and all, and took intensely suggestive photographs of them. This show offers two of those magical sculptures and 16 photographs that are full of unrequited, possibly pedophiliac yearning (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* ''MASTERPIECES OF JAPANESE ART FROM THE MARY GRIGGS BURKE COLLECTION,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street, (212)535-7710 (through Sunday). The good news is this ravishing exhibition of Japanese art, ranging from Neolithic pottery to knee-weakening Edo-period screens with a breadth and depth rarely seen in New York. Even better news is that a large part of the collection from which these 200 works are drawn is a promised gift to the Met, placing it suddenly among the top five museums for Japanese art in the United States. The show includes Buddhist sculptures and mandalas, monochrome ink paintings and calligraphy, hand scrolls and hanging scrolls as well as occasional but outstanding examples of ceramics and lacquerware. A specific Japanese sensibility, alternately refined and earthy, descreet and rambunctious, spiritual and cosmopolitan, and always astoundingly attuned to materials, is revealed here. Hours and admission: See above (Smith).</p>
        <p>''PICTURING THE MODERN AMAON,'' New Museum of Contemporary Art, 583 Broadway, near Prince Street, SoHo, (212)219-1222 (through Sunday). Especially in its outstanding catalog, this exhibition delivers everything anyone could want to know about the relatively invisible, characteristically obsessive subculture of female body-building. It ushers the visitor into a world of high-definition muscles, low-definition sex-linked characteristics and gender-bending ambiguity; surveys 60 years of newspaper cartoons and comic books, videotapes of competitions and photographs galore. There are paintings, sculptures and other artworks here, too, but they do not have much impact. This is art show as archive, as sociological document, as lifestyle tourism. Aesthetically challenged it may be, and indicative of curatorial flabbiness, but one leaves feeling that one's preconceptions about gender, beauty and power have had a more than decent workout. Hours Wednesdays and Sundays, noon to 6 p.m.; Thursdays through Saturdays, noon to 8 p.m. Admission: $6; $3, students, artists and the elderly (Smith).</p>
        <p>LISL STEINER, Leica, 670 Broadway, at Houston Street, SoHo, (212)777-3051 (through tomorrow). This retrospective of a photojournalist who started out in the 1940's is full of amusing and interesting pictures of famous people. It includes an image of Henry Kissinger talking to a couple of soccer players who are sitting in a hot tub; portraits of Henri Cartier Bresson, Camera in Hand, looking for a perfect moment in New York; and a wonderful shot of Norman Mailer and his mother, who studies him with anxious, maternal concern (Johsnon).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
