<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Bad Taste for All and Charity for None</title>
    <meta content="23IREN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zellweger, Renee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carrey, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Farrelly, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Farrelly, Bobby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A O</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Me, Myself and Irene (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By A. O. Scott</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E6DF1F31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1135" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Bad Taste for All and Charity for None</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A O</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A O Scott reviews Me, Myself and Irene, movie directed by Bobby and Peter Farrelly; Jim Carrey and Renee Zellweger star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With ''Me, Myself and Irene,'' Peter and Bobby Farrelly, proud sons of Cumberland, R.I., extend the string of heartfelt, stomach-turning comedies that began with ''Kingpin,'' still the greatest Amish-bowler road picture ever made, and continued with ''Dumb and Dumber'' and the seminal gross-out masterpiece, ''There's Something About Mary.'' Their characteristic preoccupations are much in evidence here: characters gratuitously named Dick or Dickie; animals in medical distress; and an almost connoisseurial regard for onanism, scatology and -- how to put it? -- placing things (in this case, an oversize sex toy and a live chicken) where they don't belong.</p>
        <p>If ''There's Something About Mary'' disgusted you with its callous mockery of hair and pet care and its whimsical views of stalking and serial killing, ''Me, Myself and Irene'' will make you miserable indeed. As a character squats down to defecate on a neighbor's lawn, the brothers (who directed from a script they wrote with Mike Cerrone) cut to a shot of chocolate soft-serve ice cream swirling into a cup. They serve up bodily fluids with all the gusto of deranged sommeliers proffering rare vintage wines. But ''Me, Myself and Irene'' shares with the Farrelly brothers' earlier movies a kind of dopey, boyish sincerity and a good-natured sympathy for the underdog that may prove capable of winning over even the dourest spirits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With ''Me, Myself and Irene,'' Peter and Bobby Farrelly, proud sons of Cumberland, R.I., extend the string of heartfelt, stomach-turning comedies that began with ''Kingpin,'' still the greatest Amish-bowler road picture ever made, and continued with ''Dumb and Dumber'' and the seminal gross-out masterpiece, ''There's Something About Mary.'' Their characteristic preoccupations are much in evidence here: characters gratuitously named Dick or Dickie; animals in medical distress; and an almost connoisseurial regard for onanism, scatology and -- how to put it? -- placing things (in this case, an oversize sex toy and a live chicken) where they don't belong.</p>
        <p>If ''There's Something About Mary'' disgusted you with its callous mockery of hair and pet care and its whimsical views of stalking and serial killing, ''Me, Myself and Irene'' will make you miserable indeed. As a character squats down to defecate on a neighbor's lawn, the brothers (who directed from a script they wrote with Mike Cerrone) cut to a shot of chocolate soft-serve ice cream swirling into a cup. They serve up bodily fluids with all the gusto of deranged sommeliers proffering rare vintage wines. But ''Me, Myself and Irene'' shares with the Farrelly brothers' earlier movies a kind of dopey, boyish sincerity and a good-natured sympathy for the underdog that may prove capable of winning over even the dourest spirits.</p>
        <p>The superior ''Mary,'' it's true, had a more inventive story, the indelible presence of Jonathan Richman as a guitar-strumming narrator and a range of inspired comic performances, notably Cameron Diaz's sweet-tempered spitfire and Matt Dillon's besotted private investigator. What ''Me, Myself and Irene'' has is Jim Carrey, whose rubberized body and latex fright-mask face  dominate the screen, making the rest of the cast look like well-meaning, ordinary folk.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carrey plays Charlie Baileygates, a proud member of ''the greatest law enforcement organization in the land'' (the Rhode Island State Police, naturally), who lives with his three sons in a modest waterfront bungalow. Because of a plot twist I'll refrain from divulging, Charlie's triplets are African-American academic prodigies. They humor their adoring dad in his attempts to speak their language: ''I don't want to have to bust a cap,'' he says, reminding them to clean up their rooms and do their homework.</p>
        <p>The Farrellys like to poke at cultural sensitivities, daring the audience to take offense and at the same time daring it not to. Charlie's sons are obvious racial stereotypes but they also mock the very idea of racial identity. Growing up in a suburban backwater in one of the whitest little states in the union, Jamaal (Anthony Anderson), Lee Harvey (Mongo Brownlee) and Shonte Junior (Jerod Mixon) talk like characters in one of Ice Cube's ''Friday'' movies, a result of their youthful exposure to the stand-up comedy of Richard Pryor. The most striking thing about this family, though, is not the color of its members but how loving and loyal they are to one another.</p>
        <p>Some literal-minded souls have objected to this movie's portrayal of mental illness, since its shambling plot turns on Charlie's affliction with ''advanced hallucinatory schizophrenia'' accompanied by ''involuntary narcissistic rage.'' Yes, the etiology of Charlie's disorder is flagrantly inaccurate, but the movie's message, to the extent that it has one, is one of compassion, self-awareness and emotional balance. Or maybe I'm crazy.</p>
        <p>Anyway, in layman's terms, Charlie's diagnosis arises from the fact that after enduring 18 years of milquetoast humiliation at the hands of his first wife, his neighbors and the good people of southern Rhode Island, he suddenly turns into Hank, a lustful sociopath who expresses himself in skewed tough-guy catch phrases. ''Just because I rock doesn't mean I'm made of stone,'' he tells Irene, a fugitive golf-course superintendent played with the right mixture of moxie and bewilderment by Renee Zellweger.</p>
        <p>As Hank, Mr. Carrey shows the edge of creepiness that made him so repellent, and so fascinating, in the underrated ''Cable Guy.'' As Charlie he manifests a dorky sincerity somewhere between ''The Truman Show'' and ''Dumb and Dumber.'' The two performances become less distinct as the movie careens toward its climax -- the most amazing one-man wrestling match since Steve Martin grappled with the ghost of Lily Tomlin in ''All of Me'' -- but somehow add up to a credible romantic lead. It's a rare comedian who can be so completely repulsive and at the same time so lovable.</p>
        <p>The plot of ''Me, Myself and Irene'' doesn't really bear thinking about; at any rate, Mr. Cerrone and the Farrellys don't seem to have given it much thought. Something about crooked dealings between an upstate New York golf course developer and the Environmental Protection Agency, and a clutch of standard-issue bad guys (notably Richard Jenkins and Chris Cooper, in a succession of Hawaiian shirt and blazer ensembles) -- just enough to send Hank, Charlie and Irene on a scenic ramble from gag to gag.</p>
        <p>Along the way, they acquire an albino sidekick named Whitey, a character whose treatment is a perfect illustration of the Farrellys' comic sensibilities. When Hank first meets Whitey (Michael Bowman), he subjects him to a torrent of unprovoked, and hilarious, abuse, which turns to tears of remorse when he realizes he has hurt the young man's feelings. The audience's feelings after this sudden tonal shift lie somewhere between guilt and bewilderment, but they are soon swept away by the next round of jokes. The humor in ''Me, Myself and Irene'' is often outrageous but rarely cruel. I hope I don't embarrass the filmmakers, who work so hard to give offense, by pointing out the streak of tender humanity that runs through their work. They commit acts of flagrant bad taste in the service of decency.</p>
        <p>''Me, Myself and Irene'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes -- where to begin?</p>
        <p>ME, MYSELF AND IRENE</p>
        <p>Directed by Bobby Farrelly and Peter Farrelly; written by Peter Farrelly, Mike Cerrone and Bobby Farrelly; director of photography, Mark Irwin; edited by Christopher Greenbury; music by Peter Yorn and Lee Scott; production designer, Sidney J. Bartholomew Jr.; produced by Bradley Thomas, Bobby Farrelly and Peter Farrelly; released by 20th Century Fox. Running time: 100 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Jim Carrey (Charlie/Hank), Renee Zellweger (Irene), Anthony Anderson (Jamaal), Mongo Brownlee (Lee Harvey), Jerod Mixon (Shonte Junior), Chris Cooper (Lieutenant Gerke), Michael Bowman (Whitey), Richard Jenkins (Agent Boshane) and Robert Forster (Colonel Partington).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
