<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israel's Ruling Coalition Narrowly Averts a Breakup, Just as Mideast Peace Talks Near</title>
    <meta content="Y23ISRA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209550"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E0DA1F31F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1367" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israel's Ruling Coalition Narrowly Averts a Breakup, Just as Mideast Peace Talks Near</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, June 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shas party retracts its resignation from Israel's government after forcing leftist Meretz party out of cabinet; Prime Minister Ehud Barak, whose broad coalition is battered but intact as it head into a crucial stage of peacemaking with the Palestinians, appeals to nation to reflect and rise above recent internal turmoil, which he says threatens to sour everything that Israel has fought for and dreamed of; photo fo Shas leaders (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The linchpin political party Shas retracted its resignation from Israel's government this afternoon, leaving Prime Minister Ehud Barak's broad coalition battered but intact to head into a crucial stage of peacemaking with the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>In one of his strongest speeches since taking office, Mr. Barak then appealed to his nation to reflect on and rise above the recent internal turmoil, which, he said, threatened to sour ''everything that the Jewish nation fought for and dreamed of.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The linchpin political party Shas retracted its resignation from Israel's government this afternoon, leaving Prime Minister Ehud Barak's broad coalition battered but intact to head into a crucial stage of peacemaking with the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>In one of his strongest speeches since taking office, Mr. Barak then appealed to his nation to reflect on and rise above the recent internal turmoil, which, he said, threatened to sour ''everything that the Jewish nation fought for and dreamed of.''</p>
        <p>''What sort of Israel do we want?'' Mr. Barak said in a live radio broadcast from a Labor Party meeting. ''Do we want an Israel of violence and division?</p>
        <p>''Do we want an Israel of hatred? Where will this lead? I am afraid that we all know and I believe that we are all afraid.</p>
        <p>''Friends, we cannot make peace with our neighbors without making peace first among ourselves.''</p>
        <p>In the midst of this gut-wrenching day for many Israelis, when their country was spared the immediate turmoil of a government's collapse but witnessed the denouement of what many considered a sad spectacle, Dennis Ross, the American peace envoy, arrived here to tackle the external peace issue.</p>
        <p>Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright will follow next Tuesday as part of the Americans' intensifying effort to lay the foundation for a successful retreat-style summit meeting in July. The meeting's goal would be a final peace agreement and an end to the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, although a partial solution is considered more feasible.</p>
        <p>Those peace talks are the backdrop for today's political events.</p>
        <p>Shas officials, in fact, specifically noted that their re-enlistment in the government would permit Mr. Barak to proceed with the negotiations that are his central project.</p>
        <p>''We gave the prime minister, first of all, the umbrella that he has a government,'' said Shlomo Benizri, a Shas official and Health Minister.  ''And with this government, he will be able to travel to the United States in the near future, within two weeks, to continue with the peace process.''</p>
        <p>After nearly a year of tense coexistence with the leftists in Mr. Barak's government, Shas, an ultra-Orthodox party, won a primary battle by forcing the leftist Meretz party out of the cabinet so that it could remain.</p>
        <p>Meretz's three ministers, including Education Minister Yossi Sarid, a staunch secularist who has become Shas's nemesis, quit their posts on Wednesday night. Meretz will stay in the government to support the peace effort that they champion, but the leaders relinquished their ministries to end the uncertainty about whether the government would survive, they said.</p>
        <p>''The prime minister agreed, maybe against his true wishes, to give up Meretz,'' Mr. Sarid said. ''And Meretz agreed to lie down over the fence for him.'' He was using a well-known army expression, referring to a soldier who throws himself over barbed wire so that others can walk over him to safety.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak, who now has a cabinet similar to that of his rightist predecessor, Benjamin Netanyahu, did not try to convince the Meretz ministers to stay. He did say that he appreciated their ''concession,'' but he seemed to cast blame widely, calling on all parties to ''stop with the invective and the arm-twisting.''</p>
        <p>''The country is not the toy of any party or any individual,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Soon, Mr. Barak will learn whether the political crisis has been worth it: whether Shas, indeed, backs him and the peace effort or whether they continue to act like an opposition party that sits in the government. He originally included Shas in his coalition, and withstood its full-time balkiness, in order to have the party's backing for a peace deal with the Palestinians. But that support is not guaranteed.</p>
        <p>The overt issues in contention between Shas and Mr. Barak concerned the finances and oversight of the religious party's indebted school system and the legalization of its pirate radio stations, which have been nicknamed ''the holy channels.''</p>
        <p>But when Shas's rabbis instructed their politicians to resign from the coalition last week, they also cited as an incentive Mr. Barak's plan ''to forsake'' the West Bank. There is a deeply embedded resistance inside the party to territorial concessions, despite a one-time ruling by Shas's spiritual leader, Rabbi Ovadia Yosef, that it is valid to give up land if it serves to end the violence and save Jewish lives.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak's party, One Israel, ''has not discounted the possibility that in a month or two, if he presents an agreement with the Palestinians, Shas will stick a knife in his back,'' Yossi Verter wrote in Haaretz today.</p>
        <p>Formed a year ago, Mr. Barak's broad coalition was his effort to learn from the mistakes of his mentor, the late Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin, and to forge a national consensus for his peacemaking. But the rifts between various segments of Israeli society go deep, and they are probably even more intense at the leadership level. Instead of bridging differences, the broad government has seemed to exacerbate them.</p>
        <p>A demonstration of the deep-seated enmity between Mr. Sarid and Eli Yishai, the Shas leader, played out like hostile theater in Israel's Parliament, known as the Knesset, on Wednesday. Mr. Sarid mocked what he said was Mr. Yishai's weakness as a party leader, repeatedly saying, ''Try to refrain from lying. I know it's not easy.'' Mr. Yishai accused Mr. Sarid of persecuting Shas in a obsessed way, and referred to him as ''wicked.''</p>
        <p>Responding to the bickering, Mr. Barak sighed: ''You hear the argument,'' he said, ''and you really understand why, when the teacher in the second grade sees her pupils misbehaving, she says to them: 'This isn't the Knesset, get a hold of yourselves.' ''</p>
        <p>Many Israelis have been disgusted and disillusioned by the political crisis. Nahum Barnea, a senior columnist for Yediot Ahronot, compared the politicians' displays of rage to a recent rash of impulse murders. ''The ministers are no better than the drivers who kick each other to death because of a quarrel over the right of way at a traffic light,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Gabi Lalouche, who is the right-wing mayor of Dimona, a poor town, noted that he strongly opposed Mr. Sarid's views on the peace effort. ''But I've been mayor for 11 years, and what Sarid and Ran Cohen,'' another Meretz minister, ''have done in the last year for the development towns has not been done in many years. Their exit is a dirge for generations.''</p>
        <p>Political experts heaped a lot of blame on Mr. Barak, a former general, for handling the situation like an inexperienced politician. They said he ended up doing belatedly and publicly what he could have done much earlier and more quietly: pressuring Meretz and capitulating to Shas's demands.</p>
        <p>But the same experts said that the political world in general is to blame; politicians have become so hermetically sealed in their air-conditioned Parliament that they don't seem to understand the Israeli public's desire for peace with its Arab neighbors and peace at home, they said.</p>
        <p>''Madmen, get down from the roof!'' Sima Kadmon, another columnist, wrote to the lawmakers.</p>
        <p>For the Shas school system, Mr. Barak offered millions in debt relief as well as tax forgiveness. He also proposed that the system's problems be administered by a special team reporting to him and taken out of the Education Ministry's hands. The radio stations will come under the umbrella of Israel's second broadcasting authority, where they have been promised almost complete independence.</p>
        <p>In return, Shas will withdraw its support for early elections, killing the idea for the time being.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
