<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ilya and Emilia Kabakov 'The Palace of Projects'</title>
    <meta content="RV011251" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209648"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Art Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kabakov, Ilya</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kabakov, Emilia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kimmelman, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E2DC1630F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="522" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ilya and Emilia Kabakov 'The Palace of Projects'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL KIMMELMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kimmelman, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Kimmelman reviews The Palace of Projects, created by Ilya and Emilia Kabakov and installed at 69th Regiment Armory under auspices of Public Art Fund; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>69th Regiment Armory  Lexington Avenue at 26th Street  Manhattan  Through July 10</p>
        <p>Ilya Kabakov's latest installation, a collaboration with his wife, Emilia, which is something new, comes to New York after much hoopla at its stops in Madrid and London. The local sponsor is the Public Art Fund, which has been getting conspicuously more ambitious in its efforts to do projects by significant artists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>69th Regiment Armory  Lexington Avenue at 26th Street  Manhattan  Through July 10</p>
        <p>Ilya Kabakov's latest installation, a collaboration with his wife, Emilia, which is something new, comes to New York after much hoopla at its stops in Madrid and London. The local sponsor is the Public Art Fund, which has been getting conspicuously more ambitious in its efforts to do projects by significant artists.</p>
        <p>This project, commissioned by ArtAngel in London, is not Mr. Kabakov's best by a long shot, but it is big, elaborate and worth a close look anyway. It is a spiraling temporary pavilion, translucent fabric stretched over a wood frame, 40 feet tall and 80 feet in diameter. Its nautilus shape recalls Tatlin's utopian monument, not coincidentally. The pavilion sits in the middle of the vast armory, where it happens that the great 1913 show that introduced America to European modernism took place, a neat coincidence. The pavilion glows white in the dark space, its most striking effect. (Hours: Daily except Tuesday, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m. Admission is free.)</p>
        <p>Inside, the Kabakovs have installed around 65 ''projects,'' fictive plans in the form of texts, accompanied by models, sculptures, slide projections and so on. The result is vaguely like a vast 4-H Club booth at a country fair. The projects are for improving the world, and are attributed to imaginary characters. A plan by a writer named V. Korneichuk, for example, promotes concentration and privacy through living environments made of clothing closets (shades of Andrea Zittel). A secretary named B. Borden proposes constructing a ladder 1,200 meters high in a remote agricultural area from which to see angels.</p>
        <p>Borrowing something of Mr. Kabakov's installation at the 1997 Whitney Biennial, which was a post-Soviet hospital ward for recovering memory, there is also a plan, attributed to an N. Selikhova, a pensioner, to relieve sick and elderly patients of their misery through soporific slide projections of family snapshots.</p>
        <p>We find the familiar Kabakovian attributes in abundance: the wry absurdist literary ambition, linked to the great Russian tradition; the deceptive visual nonchalance; the allusions to Russian avant-gardists like Tatlin, reinterpreted as lost empires of the imagination; the melancholic and humanely nostalgic recall of Soviet life, mingled with dreams for escape -- art based on political opposition manifested as a kind of Proustian fantasy.</p>
        <p>The problems have to do with rehashing old themes, combined with the increasing distance between the Soviet past and the postcommunist present, making the work less specific and urgent. The abundance is a drawback, too, even if an intentional effect: too many projects, too much reading, installed in a pavilion that, unlike Mr. Kabakov's previous and artfully dilapidated installations, looks almost too sleek, despite its simple materials.</p>
        <p>There is still something notable, as always with him, about the scope of the imagination. Even when not at his most striking, Mr. Kabakov, now teamed with his wife, operates on a creative level that few other artists can.</p>
        <p>MICHAEL KIMMELMAN</p>
        <p>ART IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
