<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE NUCLEAR SHIELD: Looking for Cover; Politics Mixes With Strategy In Plan for Antimissile System</title>
    <meta content="Y23MIS$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209606"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Grand Forks (Nd)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Grand Forks (Nd)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alaska</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Aleutian Islands</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Michael R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myers, Steven Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, Ted (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/North Dakota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Dakota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DE1630F930A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE NUCLEAR SHIELD: Looking for Cover; Politics Mixes With Strategy In Plan for Antimissile System</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON with STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Michael R; Myers, Steven Lee</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Domestic political calculations have weighed enormously with both Clinton administration and its Republican rivals in their maneuvering over missile defense system; an example is how administration was forced to abandon plans to locate system in Grand Forks, ND, which would not require renegotiation of Antiballistic Missile Treaty, because a system built there could not protect westernmost islands of the Aleutians, something sure to run afoul of Sen Ted Stevens of Alaska; a major aim of administration's plan has been to protect Pres Clinton--and more important, Vice Pres Al Gore--against Republican charges that Democrats have been soft on defense; a missile defense system was little more than a footnote to history when Clinton took office in 1992, but it has emerged as political litmus test since then as result of raw partisan politics, bitter fights over secret intelligence reports and an evolving missile threat; photos; maps (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton's aides initially thought that they had the perfect plan for building a missile shield over the United States, a system that would guard against nuclear, biological and chemical threats without plunging the United States into a bitter tug of war with the Russians.</p>
        <p>To ease Moscow's concerns, the system would be built at Grand Forks, N.D., the only place where a limited defense could be deployed under an exception carved out in the Antiballistic Missile Treaty that the United States signed with the Soviet Union in 1972.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton's aides initially thought that they had the perfect plan for building a missile shield over the United States, a system that would guard against nuclear, biological and chemical threats without plunging the United States into a bitter tug of war with the Russians.</p>
        <p>To ease Moscow's concerns, the system would be built at Grand Forks, N.D., the only place where a limited defense could be deployed under an exception carved out in the Antiballistic Missile Treaty that the United States signed with the Soviet Union in 1972.</p>
        <p>But then computer simulations demonstrated that the system could not cover the westernmost islands in the Aleutians. And while only several thousand people lived on these remote reaches of Alaska, no one in the Clinton administration was about to tell Senator Ted Stevens, the powerful Alaska Republican who is chairman of the Senate Appropriations Subcommittee on Defense, that the world's most elaborate missile defense system would not protect some of his constituents.</p>
        <p>''Every computer run we ran showed that we could not get to the four westernmost islands of the Aleutians or two westernmost uninhabited in Hawaii,'' a former administration official said. ''The Pentagon charts had red on Alaska and Hawaii, meaning we could not cover all parts of those states.''</p>
        <p>Those red spots, and a complex debate among government lawyers over how to interpret the treaty, killed the Grand Forks option. Soon plans were approved to put 100 missile interceptors and a new battle-management radar in Alaska, raising the projected cost by $2 billion. The administration began pushing to amend the ABM treaty, and Washington found itself enmeshed in a debate that has soured relations with Russia, unnerved America's allies in Europe and provoked fears of a new arms race in Asia.</p>
        <p>The administration has long argued that its plan to build a limited missile defense was a response to emerging missile threats from countries like North Korea, Iran and Iraq. But a reconstruction of the decision-making involved in the plan shows that as with the decision to protect the Aleutian Islands, both the administration and its Republican rivals have long been motivated by domestic political calculations as well as by strategic concerns.</p>
        <p>A major aim of the administration plan has been to protect Mr. Clinton -- and more important, Vice President Al Gore, the presumed Democratic presidential candidate -- against Republican charges that the Democrats have been soft on defense, according to administration officials and lawmakers.</p>
        <p>The administration's initial antimissile plan was forged in negotiations with Congressional leaders as the White House sought to defuse the missile defense issue before the 1996 presidential election. This year, Mr. Gore and Governor George W. Bush of Texas have both called for some version of a missile shield even before crucial tests of the technology, and before American intelligence experts had completed an assessment of how Russia, China, North Korea and other nations would be likely to respond to such a system.</p>
        <p>As American diplomats have been sent around the world to discuss the worries of the Russians, Chinese and Western Europeans, they are trying to make the best case for an American decision that appears to be all but made.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton may defer the deployment decision to a successor, but there seems to be too much political momentum behind the idea of an antimissile system for the United States to abandon it now. While there is still intense debate among scientists about the feasibility of the administration's plan, the guiding assumption in the Pentagon is that sooner or later the technology can work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's national security adviser, Samuel R. Berger, insists that political considerations have played no role in the decision and that the administration is tackling a complex and thankless issue.</p>
        <p>''Our proposal is based on our analysis of the emerging threat and our commitment to maintain the core of the ABM treaty, which contributes to stability and to the efforts of the U.S. and Russia to control the process of reducing nuclear weapons,'' Mr. Berger said.</p>
        <p>But veterans of Washington's bare-knuckled battles over arms control say politics has played an enormous role in the debate over whether to deploy such a system. In their view, it is politics that is stampeding the United States into a decision.</p>
        <p>''Russian, China and the NATO allies have become virtual bystanders in this debate,'' said Thomas Graham Jr., an arms control specialist who served as Mr. Clinton's special ambassador on proliferation issues. ''The real fight is being waged in Washington, and it is much more about politics than the threat.''</p>
        <p>The Politics -- Stealing Thunder Of Republicans</p>
        <p>How support for a missile defense system became a political litmus test of is a tale of raw partisan politics, bitter fights over secret intelligence reports and an evolving missile threat.</p>
        <p>Missile defense seemed to be little more than a footnote to history when Mr. Clinton took office in 1992. The Soviet Union had collapsed and seemingly with it President Ronald Reagan's bold dream of a ''Star Wars'' defense against ballistic missiles.</p>
        <p>With the encouragement of the military, the Clinton administration reorganized the Pentagon's research on antimissile systems, giving priority to systems for protecting American troops from attack by short-range and medium-range rockets and playing down  defenses to protect the United States.</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Clinton prepared for the 1996 re-election campaign, the politics of missile defense intensified. Republicans, after winning control of the House in the 1994 election, pressed to revive a version of Mr. Reagan's proposal.</p>
        <p>Faced with that challenge, Mr. Clinton used one of his time-tested tactics: He stole the Republicans' thunder by co-opting their position.</p>
        <p>In 1995, seeking to hammer out a bipartisan compromise, the White House opened negotiations with four Senate leaders: Sam Nunn, a Georgia Democrat; Carl Levin, a Democrat from Michigan; John W. Warner, a Virginia Republican; and William S. Cohen, the Maine Republican whom Mr. Clinton later appointed secretary of defense.</p>
        <p>The administration promised to develop the technology for an antimissile system within three years. That would put the United States in position actually to deploy an antimissile system within a second three-year period if new missile threats emerged, or so the White House argued. Hence, the plan became known as ''three plus three.''</p>
        <p>''We sort of created the Pentagon program,'' Senator Levin said in an interview. ''We tried to encapsulate where we were going on development.''</p>
        <p>There was another important assumption behind the strategy: The first phase of any missile defense would be based at Grand Forks, consistent with the ABM treaty. That would enable Washington to avoid a diplomatic rupture with the Kremlin.</p>
        <p>In the end, Senate Republicans signed off on the deal, but their more hard-line colleagues in the House balked, and the effort to forge a bipartisan consensus on missile defense fell apart.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Clinton had signaled that he was prepared to consider a limited missile defense to blunt his Republican critics, and conservative Republicans had indicated that they were prepared to one-up the Democrats by pushing for a more ambitious system.</p>
        <p>''It was both a classic example of how the Congress could drive the defense debate and an example of Clinton's 'New Democrat' approach to defense,'' said Joseph Cirincione, a senior associate at the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace. ''Clinton was able to say that he was all for missile defense and put the tough decisions off to the future.''</p>
        <p>The Intelligence -- A Second Review Sounds the Alarm</p>
        <p>As it turned out, missile defense was not a big issue during Mr. Clinton's re-election fight; Bob Dole, his Republican challenger, barely mentioned it.</p>
        <p>But it did not take long before the debate re-emerged. This time intelligence was the battleground.</p>
        <p>The administration had drawn comfort from a 1995 National Intelligence Estimate, coordinated by the Central Intelligence Agency, that concluded that nations like North Korea would need at least 15 years to develop a missile that could strike the continental United States.</p>
        <p>Republican lawmakers, however, objected to the implication that there was no need to speed development of a missile shield, and they set out to challenge it.</p>
        <p>Their first attempt failed. To review the intelligence report, they established a panel whose chairman was Robert M. Gates, the director of central intelligence during the Bush administration. But its 1996 report basically supported the view of American intelligence experts.</p>
        <p>Two years later, however, the Republicans tried again. This time Congress set up a panel headed by Donald Rumsfeld, who was defense secretary under President Gerald R. Ford and was at Governor Bush's side recently when he unveiled his plan to build a more expansive missile defense system if elected this fall.</p>
        <p>Three of the nine members of the commission were picked by Democrats, including Richard Garwin, a renowned physicist who is a Republican but is known for his fierce independence. Mr. Garwin recalled in an interview that while Mr. Rumsfeld conducted the review in a fair-minded manner, the panel's mandate was carefully drafted to boost the case for antimissile defenses.</p>
        <p>''The charge was cooked,'' Mr. Garwin said. ''We were not asked what where the most likely ways in which the U.S. might be attacked and how they compared to an ICBM. We were only asked to study the long-range missile threat. Nor did they ask us what to do about it. If they asked us about that, we would never have reached agreement in six months.''</p>
        <p>The scope of the commission's mandate was particularly important because American intelligence has concluded that there is a greater risk that a foe would try to sneak a nuclear bomb or biological weapons into the United States than attack it with a long-range missile.</p>
        <p>The Rumsfeld panel report was published in July 1998, and soon became one of the most influential documents in modern American military planning. India and Pakistan had recently exploded nuclear bombs, catching the United States by surprise. It was a period when military experts were particularly anxious about both the quality of United States intelligence and third world threats.</p>
        <p>In a sharp critique, the Rumsfeld panel concluded that American intelligence officials had been far too relaxed about missile threats and noted that there were shortcuts that could be used to develop such a weapon.</p>
        <p>For instance, time-consuming Russian or American-style test programs could be eliminated and a crude, inaccurate missile could be developed to lob a nuclear weapon or a biological warhead at the United States.</p>
        <p>''This is not a distant threat,'' the panel said.</p>
        <p>Stung by the criticism, American intelligence later revised its intelligence estimate, reflecting many of the Rumsfeld panel's arguments.</p>
        <p>The North Koreans -- A Missile Test Surprises the U.S.</p>
        <p>If the Republicans had based their crusade for missile defense on the Rumsfeld report alone, however, they might still be fighting an uphill battle. But just a month after the report came out, on Aug. 31, 1998, they gained additional ammunition when the North Koreans sent a satellite hurtling toward space on a Taepo Dong-1 missile.</p>
        <p>For days, the North Koreans insisted that the satellite was broadcasting ''immortal revolutionary hymns'' in honor of their late leader, Kim Il Sung, and his son, Kim Jong Il. Only later would it become clear that the satellite had never gone into orbit and had fallen into the Pacific Ocean.</p>
        <p>''They said it was up there broadcasting music, but we never found the music,'' a Defense Department official said.</p>
        <p>The Taepo Dong-1 was not the most sophisticated system. Its first two stages consisted of relatively primitive systems: a liquid-fueled Scud and a liquid-fueled No Dong missile.</p>
        <p>But it was the third stage that surprised the United States. It consisted of a small solid-fueled motor designed to thrust the satellite into space. The use of the third stage reflected an important milestone in North Korea's attempt to develop an intercontinental-range missile.</p>
        <p>''That they were doing this at all suggests they were farther along than the intelligence community had anticipated they would be,'' Walter B. Slocombe, the under secretary of defense for policy, said in an interview. ''It would be as if you were watching a diver who you think can only do a simple one somersault, and she tries a three-and-half reverse, but screws up the half part. The fact she tried it at all indicates she is better than you thought she was, and the fact she got most of the way through indicates she is a lot farther along than you thought she was.''</p>
        <p>Even so, American intelligence says the North Korean missile has considerable limitations: It is not powerful enough to carry a nuclear warhead to the United States, though it could carry a lighter biological warhead. Nor is it particularly accurate.</p>
        <p>''It would be very inaccurate, so inaccurate that if aimed at Honolulu it would probably land in the water,'' said a senior American official who is familiar with intelligence on the missile. ''If it was aimed at Alaska, it would probably hit land mass but might not land anywhere near a city.''</p>
        <p>More recently, American intelligence has concluded that the North Koreans have abandoned work on that missile in favor of the Taepo Dong-2, a two-stage missile that uses a cluster of No Dong engines as a first stage and a No Dong missile as a second stage. The Taepo Dong-2 has never been flight-tested, a vital step in developing a missile, and cannot be test-launched under a accord that the United States has negotiated with North Korea. The North Koreans, however, have continued work on the program.</p>
        <p>If North Korea did conduct a flight test and built another Taepo Dong-2, it might have a rudimentary long-range missile in a matter of months, according to American intelligence officials. While such a missile could deliver a nuclear-size payload to Alaska and Hawaii, it could not reach the continental United States unless the North Koreans added a third stage. But a third stage would make it less accurate, American officials say.</p>
        <p>Even if North Korea did violate the test ban and developed an effective intercontinental-range missile, it would have enough nuclear material only for two warheads at most, according to United States intelligence, compared with more than 6,000 missile warheads for the United States.</p>
        <p>The missile threat from other nations is more distant, and American specialists are divided over whether Iran can field an intercontinental-range ballistic missile by 2010. As for Iraq, American intelligence experts cannot agree on whether it can could develop a long-range ballistic missile by 2015.</p>
        <p>Because the United States' overwhelming military might has deterred North Korea in the past, some senior American officials say there is no reason to think that Pyongyang would act irrationally in the future and threaten the world's sole remaining superpower with a missile strike.</p>
        <p>''North Korea has not used its artillery against Seoul for decades, and it could do a real number on it,'' a senior American official said. ''It has not used its Scud missiles against the rest of South Korea. It has not used its No Dong missiles against Japan. So you have to argue they have been deterred.''</p>
        <p>Still, in making their case for a missile defense, advocates say even a rudimentary ability to deliver a biological or nuclear warhead might give North Korea a weapon it might brandish to try to prevent Washington from coming to the aid of South Korea or Japan in a future conflict. Although deterrence has worked in the past, the proponents argue, there is no guarantee that it will in the future. And if the United States has the money and technology to develop a missile defense, it should do so, they insist.</p>
        <p>''The threat is that nations with aggressive ambitions could come to believe that because of their missile capability, we could be deterred from intervening in their region,'' said Barry M. Blechman, a member of the Rumsfeld panel and chairman of the Henry L. Stimson Center, a Washington-based research organization. ''That is the whole reason for defense.''</p>
        <p>With the White House seeking to protect its right flank during the election year, however, the complex debate over deterrence has received relatively short shrift.</p>
        <p>''Eighty percent of my colleagues in the Congress are not really paying attention,'' said Senator Joseph R. Biden Jr., a Delaware Democrat. ''They think they need to be for some kind of defense, but they don't really know anything about it. We have not really had a debate.''</p>
        <p>The Site -- From the Dakotas North to Alaska</p>
        <p>Eager to demonstrate a new seriousness on missile defense, the administration moved into high gear last year. It developed a new goal: The United States should be able to build a limited antimissile defense by late 2005.</p>
        <p>Officially, Mr. Clinton insisted that he had not yet decided whether to build a limited defense. He says his decision will depend on the antimissile technology that is to be tested on July 7 and on evaluations of the threat and the implications for arms control. He may defer a decision about deploying the system, but there is virtually no chance that he will decide a missile defense is unnecessary.</p>
        <p>Even as it moved forward on the issue, however, the White House wanted to avoid a diplomatic confrontation with Moscow. The hope was that the initial phase of a missile defense might be deployed at Grand Forks, which was the only American site permitted for such a defense under the ABM treaty.</p>
        <p>But that hope was dashed when Republicans insisted that even a limited system had to protect all 50 states, and the Joint Chiefs of Staff made this a military requirement.</p>
        <p>No matter how hard they tried, American military experts could not cover all of the United States from Grand Forks.</p>
        <p>The Western Aleutians and some uninhabited islands in Hawaii were outside the sphere of coverage. The White House pressed the Pentagon to re-examine the problem, but it only seemed to get worse. That was a huge political obstacle since Senator Stevens headed the Appropriations Subcommittee on Defense and Senator Daniel K. Inouye of Hawaii was the ranking Democrat on the panel.</p>
        <p>Another problem was how to interpret the ABM treaty with the Russians. While Reagan administration lawyers had ruled that a ''thin defense'' at Grand Forks would not violate the treaty, now lawyers in the State Department were insisting that a nationwide defense would run afoul of the accord.</p>
        <p>Faced with these obstacles, the Clinton  administration scrapped its Grand Forks plan in early 1999, and resigned itself to deploying 100 interceptors in central Alaska and erecting a powerful battle-management radar on Shemya, a remote island in the Aleutians. That would entail difficult negotiations with Moscow.</p>
        <p>And unlike the situation in 1996, it became difficult for Mr. Clinton to endorse the idea of missile defense while putting off tough decisions until after the next election. In the winter of 1998, an earnest Air Force lieutenant colonel who worked for the Joint Chiefs of Staff gave several national security aides at White House a dose of bad news: The administration was running out of time.</p>
        <p>To meet the administration's goal of deploying the first phase of its system by 2005, the colonel explained, Mr. Clinton would have to give the final go-ahead for some of work by November 2000, on the eve of the presidential election.</p>
        <p>The briefing struck the White House like a thunderclap. The administration had thought that it could balance politics, diplomacy and security by simply exploring the idea of a limited defense. Now, after years of maneuvering, it was boxed into a corner.</p>
        <p>The administration had not yet carried out crucial tests of the system. It did not have the latest intelligence on how China, Russia and North Korea might respond. Nor had it prepared its European allies or the Russians for such a dramatic change in defense policy.</p>
        <p>But it could wait no longer. It would have to open negotiations with the Russians and conduct them during an American election campaign.</p>
        <p>Recently, to provide Mr. Clinton with more flexibility, administration lawyers came up with a ruling that some initial work could be done without violating the treaty. But arms control supporters have criticized this move, and the Russians are opposed.</p>
        <p>Despite all the headaches, it is not clear that the administration's plan will even provide the political benefits the White House had hoped for. While its defense plan is too much for the Russians, Republicans are assailing it as too limited.</p>
        <p>Looking back on the debate, Senator Biden said the administration had erred by trying to steal the missile defense issue from Republicans. That, he said, has simply prompted the Republicans to propose an even grander defense and committed the Democrats to a premature decision on the issue.</p>
        <p>''I told Berger he had made a big mistake,'' he recalls telling the national security adviser. ''If you think 'thin defense' plays well politically, well guess what, thick plays better.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
