<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Win Now, or Lose Forever</title>
    <meta content="03GABL$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196480"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Time Warner Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Disney, Walt, Company</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garber, Neal</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EEDB1039F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Win Now, or Lose Forever</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Neal Gabler</byline>
      <dateline>AMAGANSETT, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Neal Gabler Op-Ed column on dispute between Time Warner and Disney that resulted in removal of Disney television subsidiary ABC from Time Warner's cable system for 39 hours in New York and other areas; says dispute is not only about money, but about hegemony and that brinkmanship demonstrates that media companies are no longer rivals jockeying for position, but behemoths locked in deadly power struggle; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For now the doomsday clock has stopped ticking. ABC is back on the air, at least temporarily, while Time Warner and Walt Disney, the parent company of ABC, restart talks over whether Time Warner's cable systems will carry ABC programming. Some 3.5 million cable subscribers will no longer be deprived of ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire,'' ''Dharma and Greg'' and ''N.Y.P.D. Blue.''</p>
        <p>A national crisis has temporarily been averted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For now the doomsday clock has stopped ticking. ABC is back on the air, at least temporarily, while Time Warner and Walt Disney, the parent company of ABC, restart talks over whether Time Warner's cable systems will carry ABC programming. Some 3.5 million cable subscribers will no longer be deprived of ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire,'' ''Dharma and Greg'' and ''N.Y.P.D. Blue.''</p>
        <p>A national crisis has temporarily been averted.</p>
        <p>Yes, it's easy to be sarcastic. On its face this is a dispute about money. In exchange for letting it carry ABC programming, Time Warner says Disney is insisting that the cable operator convert the Disney Channel from a premium service to a basic cable service and that it add two Disney-owned channels to its systems -- and that it pay what it believes is an extortionate fee for doing so. Thus the Orwellian ''Disney Has Taken ABC Away from You'' sign that had appeared on cable screens in the affected communities.</p>
        <p>For its part, Disney insists that the pending AOL-Time Warner merger has changed the negotiating context and says it wants the same access to new, highly profitable interactive technologies that Time Warner's own channels feature.</p>
        <p>But while money is certainly at issue, it is not the whole story or even the main story -- at least not the relatively small amounts being quibbled over. This is about hegemony. The brinkmanship demonstrates that media companies are no longer rivals jockeying for position, but behemoths locked in a deadly power struggle to become the lone king of a rapacious world.</p>
        <p>Rivalry among media giants is nothing new. Back in the 1920's, for example, when the movie companies were integrating production, distribution and exhibition, Paramount, Fox, Warner Brothers and Loew's, the parent company of MGM, were all building or buying theaters -- the movie equivalent of cable -- to deliver their films to the public.</p>
        <p>Fierce battles often ensued. Companies even instigated labor troubles at rivals' sites and promoted disinformation campaigns charging that a rival's theater was carelessly constructed and the balcony would collapse. Paramount was so enthusiastic in its efforts to subvert its competitors that the Federal Trade Commission even opened an investigation of its practices.</p>
        <p>But once the construction dust settled, the movie companies realized that not only could they co-exist, they could make money from one another. Why fight? A Loew's first-run theater could show a Warner Brothers movie and a Warner Brothers theater could show an MGM film if the theater's location and the situation warranted it.</p>
        <p>Before the Depression, the idea was that the movies were an ever-expanding pie with plenty for everyone. After the Depression hit, the idea was that the rivals had to find ways of dividing the pie, profiting off one another. In either case, there was a grudging collegiality.</p>
        <p>As the dispute between Time Warner and Disney illustrates, the days of cooperation, grudging or otherwise, are long gone -- the casualty of two factors. One is the Internet, which has created unparalleled opportunity and uncertainty in equal measure. Everyone assumes that eventually hundreds of billions of dollars will be made off Internet technology, which is why America Online could acquire Time Warner in the first place, but no one knows exactly how this windfall will be reaped. Each company sees the unprecedented chance to be the Internet Almighty and thus reduce opponents to irrelevance -- the fear that Disney has expressed in the wake of the AOL-Time Warner merger.</p>
        <p>In this situation, there is no ever-expanding pie to be divided but only one to be eaten whole by the company that gets the jump on the Internet and the billions of dollars that go with it.</p>
        <p>That leads to the second factor that has turned media competition into hostility: a monopolist mentality.</p>
        <p>The old movie moguls may have been megalomaniacs but they didn't think like monopolists. They thought like heated competitors trying to be the biggest and the best, but never believing that they could be the only one. They knew they couldn't.</p>
        <p>Kept in check in part by the threat of government antitrust actions, Louis B. Mayer, the chieftain of MGM, realized that the 50 or so films his studio made each year couldn't satisfy some 80 million weekly viewers. In effect, he needed the other studios to keep slaking the movie-going habit, just as they needed him. Together they constituted a film industry that could never have been congruent with just a single company.</p>
        <p>Today's media conglomerates, however, have an opportunity that those old movie companies didn't have. Microsoft notwithstanding, the government seems less zealous in enforcing antitrust law, and the financial system encourages vast new economies of scale and the mergers that help provide them.</p>
        <p>The new media companies are full-service entertainers that can provide everything an audience might want -- not only movies but television, videocassettes, CD's, books, interactive games, theater and, yes, the Internet.</p>
        <p>When you can provide for every entertainment need an audience might have, the industry and the company can be congruent, which creates an entirely different mindset, as we can see from the Time Warner-Disney dust-up.</p>
        <p>Competitors are no longer an unavoidable part of doing business; they have actually become an impediment to doing business.</p>
        <p>In a sense, then, the skirmishes among Time Warner, Disney, Fox, Sony, Bertelsmann and the other pretenders to media pre-eminence have less to do with traditional economics than with dynastic politics. These companies are modern warriors that don't believe they have to live with one another. As they see it, the world may be big enough for only  one of them -- one king of the media hill and a group of vassals.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, we still have Regis.</p>
        <p>Neal Gabler is the author, most recently, of ''Life the Movie: How Entertainment Conquered Reality.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Neal Gabler is the author, most recently, of ''Life the Movie: How Entertainment Conquered Reality.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
