<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y03BRIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000505T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196463"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E4DC1039F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>NETHERLANDS: LOCKERBIE TRIAL  Two Libyans go on trial today at a Scottish court in the Netherlands, charged with murder and other crimes in the bombing of a Pan Am plane in 1988 that killed 259 passengers and 11 people on the ground in Lockerbie, Scotland. About a dozen American relatives visited the courtroom at Camp Zeist, an old United States air base deemed Scottish territory for the trial. The defendants, Abdel Basset Ali al-Megrahi and Lamen Khalifa Fhimah, are described by prosecutors as intelligence agents.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>NETHERLANDS: LOCKERBIE TRIAL  Two Libyans go on trial today at a Scottish court in the Netherlands, charged with murder and other crimes in the bombing of a Pan Am plane in 1988 that killed 259 passengers and 11 people on the ground in Lockerbie, Scotland. About a dozen American relatives visited the courtroom at Camp Zeist, an old United States air base deemed Scottish territory for the trial. The defendants, Abdel Basset Ali al-Megrahi and Lamen Khalifa Fhimah, are described by prosecutors as intelligence agents.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NORTHERN IRELAND: TALKS CONTINUE  After inconsequential meetings with Ulster's Catholic and Protestant political leaders at 10 Downing Street, Prime Minister Tony Blair and his Irish counterpart, Bertie Ahern, scheduled more talks in Belfast tomorrow. The sessions are seeking to restart the power-sharing government suspended by Britain, which said it acted because of the failure of the Irish Republican Army to make expected moves on disarmament.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>IRELAND: BODY SEARCH  Working with new information from the Irish Republican Army, diggers searched in County Louth for the remains of Jean McConville, a mother of 10 who was killed by the I.R.A. in 1972 after she comforted a wounded British soldier. Digging for the bodies of nine I.R.A. victims from the 1970's began at the end of last May; three bodies were found before excavation was suspended.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: EXTRADITION ORDER  A court ordered the extradition of two Egyptians to the United States to face charges of conspiring with the Saudi dissident Osama bin Laden in the 1998 bombings of the American embassies in Kenya and Tanzania. Ibrahim Hussein Abdel Hadi Eidarous and Adel Mohammed Abdul Almagid Bary can appeal the order, a Bow Street Magistrates' Court official said.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>MEXICO: NEW CHIAPAS BISHOP  Felipe Arizmendi Esquivel, 60, the new bishop in a turbulent diocese in Chiapas state, said he is opposed to the armed tactics of the Zapatista guerrillas but also warned that poverty and inequality breed violence. Thousands of Indian worshippers thronged San Cristobal de las Casas when Bishop Arizmendi, above, took over from Bishop Samuel Ruiz Garcia, who retired after 40 years. Bishop Ruiz was revered by many Indians but was accused by the government of preaching Marxism.</p>
        <p>Julia Preston (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>SIERRA LEONE: U.N. SOLDIERS SEIZED  Seventeen United Nations peacekeepers from India and Kenya were taken hostage in northern and eastern Sierra Leone by rebels who have yet to disarm despite a nine-month-old peace accord. Negotiations with the rebel leader Foday Sankoh were under way to obtain the release of the hostages. Meanwhile, a Nigerian officer died from wounds received in a clash with rebels on Monday.</p>
        <p>Norimitsu Onishi (NYT)</p>
        <p>ZIMBABWE: COMMONWEALTH CONDEMNATION  Seeking increased diplomatic pressure on President Robert Mugabe, Britain won support from the 54-nation Commonwealth in condemning political violence, lawlessness and the occupation by squatters of white-owned farms in Zimbabwe. A statement from an influential Commonwealth panel in London coincided with reports that a 15th opponent of Mr. Mugabe had died in violence linked to coming elections.</p>
        <p>Alan Cowell (NYT)</p>
        <p>CONGO: BELGIUM AND LUMUMBA  A Belgian commission opened an investigation into Belgium's role in the 1961 assassination of Patrice Lumumba, the first head of government of an independent Congo. The inquiry was ordered by Foreign Minister Louis Michel after a book by a Belgian sociologist suggested that Belgium bore ''the greatest share of responsibility'' for his death. Congo, a Belgian colony from 1885, became independent on June 30, 1960. Mr. Lumumba was killed seven months later.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>INDIA: REBELS FREED  The government continued to release jailed leaders of the Hurriyat Conference, an alliance of anti-India groups in Kashmir. Shakeel Bakasi of the Jammu and Kashmir Liberation Front was the latest to be set free. Home Minister L. K. Advani said India is willing to engage Hurriyat in talks aimed at ending a decade of strife.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>ARMENIA: PREMIER FIRED  President Robert Kocharyan, left, fired Prime Minister Aram Sargsyan and his government over what he said were intrigues aimed against him. Under the constitution, the entire government must resign when a prime minister is dismissed. The decision appeared linked to an investigation of a shooting in Parliament last October in which Prime Minister Vazgen Sargsyan, Aram Sargsyan's brother, the speaker and five other top officials were slain.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>SYRIA: ARABS MEET  The foreign ministers of Syria, Egypt and Saudi Arabia will meet in Palmyra, Syria. today to coordinate their stand on Arab-Israeli peace talks, officials said. They said Farouq al-Shara of Syria, Amr Moussa of Egypt and Prince Saud al-Faisal of Saudi Arabia would also discuss Israel's planned withdrawal from southern Lebanon.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>IRAQ: ALLIED BOMBING  Iraq said American and British planes attacked civilian targets in the north and south before being driven off by ground defenses. The United States military command said allied planes in the no-flight zones set up after the gulf war had responded to threats from antiaircraft artillery sites. Iraq says 296 people have been killed and 860 wounded since the almost daily attacks began in December 1998.</p>
        <p>(Reuters, Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 5, 2000, Friday  A report in the World Briefing column on Wednesday about United Nations peacekeepers who were taken hostage by rebels in Sierra Leone referred incorrectly to a Nigerian officer wounded in a clash with the rebels on Monday. He did not later die; he was sent home for treatment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 5, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>A report in the World Briefing column on Wednesday about United Nations peacekeepers who were taken hostage by rebels in Sierra Leone referred incorrectly to a Nigerian officer wounded in a clash with the rebels on Monday. He did not later die; he was sent home for treatment.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
