<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Awaiting Heat, Ewing Displays His Confidence</title>
    <meta content="03KNIC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196532"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="N.B.A. PLAYOFFS: KNICKS VS. HEAT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ewing, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E2DF1139F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Awaiting Heat, Ewing Displays His Confidence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knickerbockers center Patrick Ewing discusses his preparations for playoff series against Miami Heat; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last February, when his average hovered around 13 points, Patrick Ewing admitted that Alonzo Mourning, his good friend and protege, was the premier big man in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>A couple of days later, in a nationally televised game at Madison Square Garden, Ewing destroyed Mourning, leading the Knicks to a 14-point victory over the Heat by outscoring him, 25-12, and outrebounding him, 14-5. From that game on, Ewing hit nearly 50 percent of his shots and scored 20 or more points every third or fourth game, and his mentality began to change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last February, when his average hovered around 13 points, Patrick Ewing admitted that Alonzo Mourning, his good friend and protege, was the premier big man in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>A couple of days later, in a nationally televised game at Madison Square Garden, Ewing destroyed Mourning, leading the Knicks to a 14-point victory over the Heat by outscoring him, 25-12, and outrebounding him, 14-5. From that game on, Ewing hit nearly 50 percent of his shots and scored 20 or more points every third or fourth game, and his mentality began to change.</p>
        <p>While the proud Ewing had maintained that greatness still resided in his creaky, surgically repaired body, the tangible proof on the court began to pile up like sand in an hourglass, convincing Ewing that he had surrendered his supremacy too soon.</p>
        <p>So yesterday, with the Knicks and the Heat preparing to meet for the fourth consecutive year in the playoffs, Ewing ate his words and said he was still the ultimate post player in the East.</p>
        <p>''He's definitely the best center in the East,'' Ewing said of Mourning, before pausing for dramatic effect and adding, ''next to me.''</p>
        <p>The smile the horde of reporters expected to crack upon Ewing's 37-year-old face never came, and it became evident that the longtime warrior was serious.</p>
        <p>''I'll believe what I want to believe,'' Ewing said. ''You all believe what you want to believe and that's it. Of course, Alonzo's going to think that he's the best center in the East. He knows he's great, and I know I'm great.''</p>
        <p>Whether he is engaging in gamesmanship or is truly convinced that he is the better player, Ewing is entering his showdown with Mourning with supreme confidence, not only in his team, but in himself.</p>
        <p>Ewing has the superior regular-season numbers (21.7 points, 9.5 rebounds and 3.7 blocks per game), and he has fared surprisingly well in their one-on-one matchups.</p>
        <p>Before Mourning dominated Ewing with a 33-point, 11-rebound, 6-block performance in Miami's 95-94 victory on April 9, Ewing had outscored his fellow Georgetown alumnus in six straight regular season games. And while Mourning outscored Ewing in the first four contests of last year's first-round playoff series, Ewing outrebounded him consistently and outplayed him in the decisive Game 5, which ended with Allan Houston's soft-bouncing game-winner in Miami.</p>
        <p>In that 78-77 victory, Ewing recorded 22 points and 11 rebounds against Mourning's 21 points and 5 rebounds.</p>
        <p>That performance in particular may have bolstered Ewing's faith because it came on the aching Achilles' tendon that eventually tore and ended his season in the conference finals against Indiana.</p>
        <p>''I was hurting a lot,'' Ewing said. ''But that was last year. This is a new year. To tell you the truth, I'm not even thinking about last year. Last year's in the past. I'm just concentrating on the future, trying to get myself and my team ready to play against the Heat on Sunday.''</p>
        <p>While Ewing clearly has plenty of game left, the 30-year-old Mourning, the league's most fearsome center this side of Shaquille O'Neal, is at the height of his career and is unquestionably the better player at this stage.</p>
        <p>Observers have opined that Mourning subconsciously plays with less fire against Ewing, whom he has looked up to since the two met at a summer camp during Mourning's senior year in high school. They say the tenacity, brutality and devilishness that characterize Mourning's play against everyone else are missing, or at least decreased, when he locks up with Ewing.</p>
        <p>Of course, Ewing, who works out with Mourning and Atlanta's Dikembe Mutombo, another Georgetown alumnus, in the summer, does not agree.</p>
        <p>''He's always aggressive against me, even in the summertime,'' Ewing said. ''I feel the elbows. I feel everything.''</p>
        <p>At the conclusion of the series, when all the games have been played and all the venom has been released, it should not matter which center was dominant, for the Knicks do not need Ewing to outplay Mourning.</p>
        <p>With Latrell Sprewell and Houston able to slice through Miami's aged and average guards for midrange jumpers and with Marcus Camby able to fly above all of the Heat's personnel, Ewing must simply play well for the Knicks to emerge victorious. His surrounding pieces are superior to Mourning's, so if indeed his protege surpasses him individually, a close second should be good enough for Ewing and the Knicks to win the series, the only battle that counts.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>The Knicks say they will not be fooled by Miami's secretiveness regarding the health of TIM HARDAWAY. Miami Coach PAT RILEY has said that neither he nor his players will discuss his point guard's status for Sunday's Game 1. The Knicks, however, are preparing as if Hardaway, who missed the Heat's first-round sweep of Detroit with a sprained left foot, will play. ''We would like to catch them without Hardaway, but realistically he's going to play,'' the Knicks assistant DON CHANEY said. ''Even if he's hurt, he's going to play. He's not going to miss this series. I would be surprised if he didn't play because he's such a competitive guy. But if he's not there, you still have to give them respect because they still have solid players.''</p>
        <p>N.B.A. PLAYOFFS: KNICKS VS. HEAT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
