<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Auto Sales Keep to Torrid Pace Even as Loan Costs Rise</title>
    <meta content="Y03AUTO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196505"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimlerchrysler Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Honda Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toyota Motor Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nissan Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mitsubishi Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bayerische Motorenwerke Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Volkswagen Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EFD81039F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1150" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Auto Sales Keep to Torrid Pace Even as Loan Costs Rise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, May 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Big domestic and foreign automakers announce that sales in April exceeded even last year's brisk pace even as loan costs rose; General Motors Corp reports 2.2 percent gain overall as 7.1 percent rise in sales of sport vehicles, pickup trucks and vans more than offset 2.5 percent decline in car sales; Ford Motor Co reports 15.4 percent increase in car sales, while sales of light trucks rose 9.9 percent; DaimlerChrysler's sales rose 5.3 percent, led by sport utilities, pickup trucks and Mercedes cars; Asian companies thrived last month, with Honda's sales rising 14.7 percent from year ago; Toyota's sales, up 15.7 percent; Nissan's, up 31.8 percent and Mitsubishi's, up 55.2 percent; BMW posts 12.1 percent increase, while Volkswagen reports gain of 19.3 percent; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rising interest rates, a volatile stock market and higher gasoline prices were expected to be slowing the American economy by now, especially the highly cyclical auto industry. Yet the stampede into the showrooms continues across the country, with every big domestic and foreign automaker announcing today that sales last month exceeded even last year's brisk pace.</p>
        <p>The buyers are people like Frank DiBernardino, a 52-year-old human resources consultant in Glen Mills, Pa., who bought a huge, indigo blue GMC Yukon for $42,300 last month. Interest rate increases did not affect him, he said, because he wrote a check for the entire cost of the full-sized sport utility vehicle, using the proceeds from stock he sold in February. Nor was he troubled by the high price of gasoline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rising interest rates, a volatile stock market and higher gasoline prices were expected to be slowing the American economy by now, especially the highly cyclical auto industry. Yet the stampede into the showrooms continues across the country, with every big domestic and foreign automaker announcing today that sales last month exceeded even last year's brisk pace.</p>
        <p>The buyers are people like Frank DiBernardino, a 52-year-old human resources consultant in Glen Mills, Pa., who bought a huge, indigo blue GMC Yukon for $42,300 last month. Interest rate increases did not affect him, he said, because he wrote a check for the entire cost of the full-sized sport utility vehicle, using the proceeds from stock he sold in February. Nor was he troubled by the high price of gasoline.</p>
        <p>''There's a certain size requirement we needed for the family,'' he said, noting that his three grandchildren frequently visit him and his wife.</p>
        <p>Economists and auto executives have been predicting for the last several months that sales would soon slow significantly. That has not happened. Sales did dip very slightly in April from the record-setting pace of the first quarter of this year. But after adjusting for seasonal variations, they were still up 10.5 percent from the extremely strong levels of April last year. In fact, last month was the auto industry's best April ever, according to Ward's Auto Infobank, a data service.</p>
        <p>Other economic indicators are also showing surprising strength: the Commerce Department said today that new-home sales leaped 4.5 percent in March, while the Conference Board in New York announced today that its index of leading indicators rose a tenth of a percent in March after edging down in February.</p>
        <p>The auto sales report is a clear sign that robust economic growth continued into the second quarter. Auto executives and economists said the biggest reason was that buyers were still feeling confident about the economy and still had plenty of money to spend.</p>
        <p>''Real wages are really strong and it's hard to stop this train,'' said Diane C. Swonk, a senior vice president and chief economist at Bank One in Chicago. ''You don't need any more gains from the stock market.''</p>
        <p>Another reason for the booming business at dealerships is that automakers are still piling on rebates, discounted interest rates and other incentives in a frantic struggle to increase or maintain market share. They are using their enormous profits to subsidize prices and keep monthly payments from rising for the 80 percent of their customers who obtain loans or leases instead of paying cash.</p>
        <p>''The fly in the ointment is that the incentives for everybody are very tough,'' said James Holden, the president of the Chrysler division of DaimlerChrysler. ''With interest rates escalating, trying to hold payments constant is getting expensive.''</p>
        <p>Paul Ballew, general director of global market and industry analysis at General Motors, said that his company actually hoped that sales would slow soon, because factories were struggling to keep up with demand, and the torrid sales now might hurt future sales.</p>
        <p>''We would like and expect to see some moderation -- it's not in our interest to have an exaggerated cycle,'' said Mr. Ballew, who was the Federal Reserve's top expert on the auto industry in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>There are a few signs that the sweltering pace of sales might be cooling. Frank Ursomarso, a car dealer with many franchises in Wilmington, Del., said he had noticed a slightly slower tempo lately. He has charted a pattern over the last 44 years in which his sales trends tended to precede the overall industry's increases and declines.</p>
        <p>''The floor traffic has been trending down a little each month,'' he said. ''At least in this market, there's beginning to be a slower pace.''</p>
        <p>DaimlerChrysler said on Friday that it was cutting production slightly of the Jeep Grand Cherokee, which faces ever-growing competition from other midsize sport utility vehicles. Mr. Holden said the company had decided that it was better to lose a little market share than to keep increasing incentives.</p>
        <p>William Lovejoy, G.M.'s group vice president for vehicle sales, service and marketing, also complained about the discounting. ''Some of the incentives really are, we believe, extreme,'' he said.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s market share was 28.3 percent in April, down from 30.6 percent a year ago. But almost all of the decline came from the company's continued weakness in the unprofitable small-car market, in which it faces competition from low-cost Korean imports. G.M. has gained share in sales of profitable full-sized sport utility vehicles, as recently redesigned models like the Chevrolet Suburban and Mr. DiBernardino's Yukon have enjoyed vibrant sales.</p>
        <p>G.M. reported the smallest sales increase among the big automakers last month: a 2.2 percent gain overall as a 7.1 percent rise in sales of sport utilities, pickup trucks and vans more than offset a 2.5 percent decline in car sales.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s archrival, Ford Motor, reported a different pattern. Its 15.4 percent increase in car sales led the company to an overall sparkling increase of 12.1 percent, while its sales of light trucks -- sport utilities, pickups and vans -- rose 9.9 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ballew said that this might be the first full year in which light trucks inched ahead of cars. That so far has happened only for a few months during the last three winters, which invigorated the sales of four-wheel-drive vehicles.</p>
        <p>Market share gains for light trucks have slowed sharply from the mid-1990's, and are increasingly a result of rising sales of all-wheel-drive wagons, like the Chrysler PT Cruiser, which the auto industry chooses to classify as light trucks because of preferential regulatory treatment for such vehicles.</p>
        <p>DaimlerChrysler's sales rose 5.3 percent, led by ever-popular sport utilities, pickup trucks and Mercedes cars.</p>
        <p>Among other automakers announcing results today, Asian companies thrived last month, with Honda's sales rising 14.7 percent from a year ago; Toyota's sales, up 15.7 percent; Nissan's, up 31.8 percent; and Mitsubishi's up 55.2 percent.</p>
        <p>European automakers also prospered, with BMW posting a 12.1 percent increase, while Volkswagen reported a gain of 19.3 percent.</p>
        <p>Jamie Jameson, DaimlerChrysler's vice president for sales and marketing, said that with 25 to 30 percent of customers now leasing their automobiles, sales would not drop too quickly.</p>
        <p>''Those people are coming back to the dealership every two or three years and they don't walk home -- they drive home in a new vehicle,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
