<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trapped in a Maze, but Sharing the Space</title>
    <meta content="03NOTE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Steppenwolf Theater Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Wharf Theater</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sinise, Gary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Plimpton, Martha</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hedda Gabler (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Critic's Notebooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E5DE1039F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1518" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trapped in a Maze, but Sharing the Space</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, April 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Weber Critic's Notebook column focuses on stars nurtured by Steppenwolf Theater Company, Chicago ensemble, in light of performances by Gary Sinise in company's production of One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest and of Martha Plimpton in Hedda Gabler at Long Wharf Theater, New Haven; holds both lead actors are giving ensemble-oriented performances in roles often played as tours de force; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Steppenwolf Theater Company, which will celebrate its 25th birthday next season, has become known, somewhat paradoxically, for both its ensemble ethos and the stars that have emerged from its ranks.</p>
        <p>On the one hand the company is, in many ways, emblematic of the thriving and close-knit theater world here, a city where a surprising number of actors manage to work and live without making the pilgrimage to either coast and where a de facto performance style has arisen as a result. Chicago actors tend to be less career-oriented offstage and thus less audience-oriented on. They play to one another here; they don't mind turning upstage. Actors here speak of this as liberating, a license to challenge their colleagues with a vigor that isn't necessarily appreciated elsewhere. The physically robust quality that many critics have attributed generally to Chicago actors is a manifestation of this.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Steppenwolf Theater Company, which will celebrate its 25th birthday next season, has become known, somewhat paradoxically, for both its ensemble ethos and the stars that have emerged from its ranks.</p>
        <p>On the one hand the company is, in many ways, emblematic of the thriving and close-knit theater world here, a city where a surprising number of actors manage to work and live without making the pilgrimage to either coast and where a de facto performance style has arisen as a result. Chicago actors tend to be less career-oriented offstage and thus less audience-oriented on. They play to one another here; they don't mind turning upstage. Actors here speak of this as liberating, a license to challenge their colleagues with a vigor that isn't necessarily appreciated elsewhere. The physically robust quality that many critics have attributed generally to Chicago actors is a manifestation of this.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, the fame and reputation of Steppenwolf rests largely on the individuals who have leapt from here to celebrity: John Malkovich, Gary Sinise, Laurie Metcalf, John Mahoney and Joan Allen are among the company's 33 current members, many of whom no longer live in Chicago. And even though most return periodically for company productions, the traditional definition of an ensemble troupe is not really applicable to Steppenwolf any longer; star-studded ensemble is something of an oxymoron.</p>
        <p>Two current productions provide an interesting illustration of this peculiar dynamic at work. One is at Steppenwolf, where Mr. Sinise, a founding member of the company, is starring as McMurphy in Dale Wasserman's adaptation of the Ken Kesey novel ''One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest.'' The other is at the Long Wharf Theater in New Haven, where Martha Plimpton, a Steppenwolf member for the last two years, is performing the title role in ''Hedda Gabler.'' Both lead actors are giving ensemble-oriented performances in roles that are often played as tours de force. Why ''Cuckoo's Nest'' is the more satisfying has to do with the productions that contain them.</p>
        <p>Directed by Doug Hughes, the Long Wharf's artistic director, from his own script adaptation, this ''Hedda'' is a chilly one. Played against a curving ice-blue wall conspicuously in need of a paint job, with minimal furnishings and only the ominous portrait of Hedda's military father as a decorative touch, the production is devoid of the sumptuous affluence that Hedda, the manipulative and unsatisfiable new wife, insists on exhibiting in her new home and that her weak-kneed scholarly husband, Tesman, cannot afford. The directorial idea -- a home that is warmthless and barren -- puts obvious emphasis on Hedda's tortured sexuality, but it also places huge demands on all the actors, leaving an enormous vacancy onstage for the characters to fill with their collective anxieties.</p>
        <p>The production, which is scheduled for a reprise at Steppenwolf next season, begins with Ms. Plimpton, wraithlike in a long white dress, entering alone, running back and forth across the stage as if in flight from an invisible demon. It's an effective introduction to the powerlessness Hedda can neither escape nor abide. She's a trapped rat in an oversize maze, and for the rest of the play, you can't forget the image; her wheedlings and plottings loom as an ever more desperate search for an exit. The best moment of this production is the first.</p>
        <p>But from then on, with the entrance of the other characters, the production creaks like uncarpeted floorboards. These are tough roles in any case, with inbred ambiguities that should swell as the play proceeds. But here, only Quentin Mare as Lovborg, Tesman's rival scholar and a self-destructive, charismatic man with a discomforting hold on Hedda's heart, has found the weight in his character that can command the stage.</p>
        <p>Graham Winton plays Tesman as a man oblivious to the most evident innuendo; Jenny Bacon, as Thea Elvsted, the woman who has fallen for Lovborg, seems purely feckless. By the end, after Lovborg's death, they seem remarkably untouched by the action around them, simply getting out of the way so Hedda can get on with her suicide.</p>
        <p>Best known as a film actress, Ms. Plimpton has nonetheless established her stage chops; as Pegeen Mike in ''The Playboy of the Western World'' and Laura in ''The Glass Menagerie,'' both at Steppenwolf during the last two seasons, she demonstrated a wide-ranging gift. But with her reedy voice and slight build, as Hedda she never exudes real potency, never swells to a near triumph. Hedda's feigned self-possession is unpersuasive; she's straining to assume authority rather than creating a mask and hiding behind it, and as a result, Hedda's self-inflicted demise is no dramatic fall, just a closing event. In the end, this is a production that could have used, from her, a bit more diva.</p>
        <p>In contrast, here in ''Cuckoo's Nest,'' which is the city's hottest ticket right now, Mr. Sinise is being buoyed and challenged by a company of actors in strong character turns, and by a director, the Steppenwolf member Terry Kinney, who has made sure his star never has to seek the spotlight. It's a mediocre play -- the stage version extracts the theme of righteous rebellion against injustice without the Faulkneresque darkness of the Kesey novel -- but the production is a crowd pleaser, played in the first act for laughs and the second for tears. It will travel to London for a brief sojourn this summer, and, with a commercial producer, Fox Theatricals, behind it, Broadway may beckon, particularly if Mr. Sinise is willing to stick around.</p>
        <p>''Cuckoo's Nest'' is the story, of course, of Randle Patrick McMurphy, a gregarious prisoner who is transferred to a mental asylum, where he becomes a doomed messiah, bringing life and hope to the inmates as he disrupts the emasculating ward routine. Mr. Sinise, a burly man with a natural swagger (he's physically closer to the Kesey description of the character than was Jack Nicholson, who won an Oscar for the role in Milos Forman's 1975 film), exudes here the capability of physical threat and an instinctive sympathy for the downtrodden.</p>
        <p>He plays the part for the melodrama the play insists on -- the renegade with the heart of gold -- and it is a winning performance, not least because it isn't overdone. In an admirably modest star turn, he's willing to share the stage, and happily, he has worthy colleagues here.</p>
        <p>Nurse Ratched, his nemesis, is played here with stony unrufflability by Amy Morton, one of many Steppenwolf actors of deserving local renown in the cast. They include Mariann Mayberry as a riotously salacious prostitute McMurphy smuggles into the ward; Rick Snyder as Cheswick, a patient who behaves, a pathetic and hilarious amalgam of bravado and retreat; and K. Todd Freeman as a doctor caught between McMurphy's charm and Nurse Ratched's punishing authority. They are joined by Ross Lehman, marvelous as the patient Harding, whose erudition is no salve for his crippling sexual inadequacy, and Eric Johner, well cast as the stammering, suicidal Billy Bibbit; his gentle good looks make Billy's unbearable insecurity especially touching.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the play's most difficult role is that of Chief Bromden, the belittled Indian giant who feigns being deaf and dumb to survive on the ward and whose long-buried sense of self is restored by McMurphy. He is played with effective lumbering sadness by Tim Sampson, an Oklahoman whose father, Will, played the part in the film. But it's a role that suffers in translation from page to stage.</p>
        <p>In the novel, it is the Chief who narrates; his strange and moving voice combines shrewd observation with the deranged fantasies of a man who wants only to hide in plain sight. This is what the play misses, the sense of organic misery that soaks the ward and that gives the novel its earned tragedy. The Chief's paranoid inner monologues are illustrated here with interludes of stagecraft: the Chief standing and speaking in a shaft of light, with huge projections of machineworks on the white institutional walls and steel-latticed windows of Robert Brill's set. The projections, by Sage Carter, are dramatic, but anyone who has read the novel will feel them as a makeshift ploy.</p>
        <p>In any case, the actors are the heart of the production. Their firm characterizations seize the sympathy of the audience without ever stealing its attention, allowing Mr. Sinise to play off them without undue clamor. And though there are moments when Mr. Kinney calls the jittery energy on the ward to an awkward halt to allow McMurphy to linger in the spotlight, this is, by and large, a highly successful example of ensemble power. It's what Steppenwolf has always done best.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
