<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>12 Companies to Bid for Billions in German Wireless Licenses</title>
    <meta content="Y03AUC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196504"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mci Worldcom Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Deutsche Telekom</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mannesmann Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">E-Plus Mobilfunk Gmbh</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Royal Kpn Nv</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bellsouth Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mobilcom</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">France Telecom</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EFD81039F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>12 Companies to Bid for Billions in German Wireless Licenses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>FRANKFURT, May 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>German government officials announce that 12 companies, including MCI Worldcom, have signed up for auction of as many as six licenses for so-called third-generation wireless voice and data services; these licenses will be made available for advanced new series of high-speed services that could make it possible to transmit video or surf World Wide Web in full color using mobile devices; other bidders include Deutsche Telekom, Mannesmann AG, E-Plus, a German mobile phone carrier controlled by Royal KPN of Netherlands and BellSouth of US, and MobilCom AG, fast-growing German rival to Deutsche Telekom that has backing from France Telecom (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With barely any time to relax after companies bid $35 billion for five new wireless communications licenses in Britain, many of the same competitors lined up today for a potentially bigger auction in Germany.</p>
        <p>German government officials announced that 12 companies, including MCI WorldCom, have signed up for an auction of as many as six licenses for so-called third-generation wireless voice and data services. These licenses will be made available for an advanced new series of high-speed services that could make it possible to transmit video or surf the World Wide Web in full color using mobile devices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With barely any time to relax after companies bid $35 billion for five new wireless communications licenses in Britain, many of the same competitors lined up today for a potentially bigger auction in Germany.</p>
        <p>German government officials announced that 12 companies, including MCI WorldCom, have signed up for an auction of as many as six licenses for so-called third-generation wireless voice and data services. These licenses will be made available for an advanced new series of high-speed services that could make it possible to transmit video or surf the World Wide Web in full color using mobile devices.</p>
        <p>But the staggering amounts of money offered in the British auction, which ended last week, have raised new worries among some industry analysts about the billions of dollars many companies will have to borrow if they bid for licenses across Europe.</p>
        <p>Besides MCI, the list of bidders in Germany includes Deutsche Telekom, which won a license in Britain through its British wireless carrier One2One; Mannesmann A.G., which is being acquired by Vodafone AirTouch of Britain; E-Plus, a German mobile phone carrier controlled by Royal KPN of the Netherlands and BellSouth of the United States; and MobilCom A.G., a fast-growing German rival to Deutsche Telekom that has backing from France Telecom.</p>
        <p>All European Union countries plan to issue similar new licenses in the next year or so, but there is a growing debate about whether the licenses should be auctioned to the highest bidders or awarded free through what amounts to a beauty contest.</p>
        <p>The supercharged bidding in Britain, which reached levels seven times those officials originally predicted, has strengthened the arguments on both sides.</p>
        <p>Many governments, like Germany's, have been mesmerized by the prospect of windfalls that would enable them to either reduce budget deficits or shore up existing programs.</p>
        <p>But others are worried that the billions paid for licenses will translate into higher costs for users and could destroy companies that miscalculate the potential benefits and bid too much.</p>
        <p>Many analysts now believe that the bidding for licenses in Germany -- which with 82 million people is a significantly larger market than Britain with 60 million -- could reach as high as $50 billion.</p>
        <p>Germany is crucial for any company bent on providing services across Europe. Companies like Deutsche Telekom, France Telecom, Vodafone and KPN want to build up pan-European networks and acquire licenses in at least the biggest markets.</p>
        <p>Other competitors appear to have more limited ambitions. Orange P.L.C., the British carrier soon to be sold by Mannesmann, was a successful bidder in Britain and has teamed up with the Sonera Corporation of Finland and Telefonica of Spain.</p>
        <p>The bidding strategies have inevitably become intertwined with strategies for mergers and acquisitions.  Telefonica is now in talks to acquire KPN, and one of the two would presumably drop out if they reach an agreement.</p>
        <p>Vodafone is in a particularly complex situation. Having won a brutal takeover battle for Mannesmann, Germany's biggest wireless carrier, it must raise billions just to pay for its British license and additional billions for anything it wins in Germany or other countries.</p>
        <p>In order to gain antitrust approval for the takeover of Mannesmann, Vodafone is disposing of Orange. It had been expected to do that through taking Orange public, but it now appears to be leaning toward an all-cash sale to another telecommunications company.</p>
        <p>On Monday, the U.M.T.S. Forum -- for Universal Mobile Telephone Standard -- an industry association aimed at promoting the third-generation services, declared that countries would be better off awarding licenses through beauty contests rather than through auctions that could send the costs of new services to prohibitive levels.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
