<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lush Wine From A Pacific Breeze</title>
    <meta content="03BARB$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196458"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Santa Barbara County (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asimov, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3DD1039F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lush Wine From A Pacific Breeze</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC ASIMOV</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>LOMPOC, Calif., May 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Number of wineries in Santa Barbara County, Calif, has grown rapidly in recent years; small growers in western Santa Ynez Valley are planting pinot noir and chardonnay grapes, which they expect to flourish in cool, moist climate; passionate young winemakers are planting syrah and other Rhone varietals in warmer central part of valley; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Santa Ynez Valley stretches west through central Santa Barbara County, reaching toward this small city and the Pacific Ocean beyond. It's a land of relaxed beauty, where narrow roads curl through the knobby, windswept Santa Rita Hills, through rows of walnut trees and strawberry fields, past acres of cabbage and broccoli and, here and there, a few sparse vineyards. It's certainly not Burgundy, where grapevines are planted everywhere, right to the edge of the highway, or Napa Valley, where the wineries are as densely packed as a suburb full of split-levels, but make no mistake: this is wine country.</p>
        <p>And in the last few years, the Santa Barbara wine region has grown astonishingly. Since 1997, the amount of land planted with grapes has shot up to more than 18,000 acres, from about 10,000, and the number of wineries in the county has almost doubled in the last decade, to about 50. Most of that acreage was planted by big wineries like Beringer, Robert Mondavi and Kendall-Jackson, which, recognizing the quality of Santa Barbara grapes and the relative affordability of the land, bought up huge tracts in the Los Alamos Valley and the Santa Maria Valley to the north.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Santa Ynez Valley stretches west through central Santa Barbara County, reaching toward this small city and the Pacific Ocean beyond. It's a land of relaxed beauty, where narrow roads curl through the knobby, windswept Santa Rita Hills, through rows of walnut trees and strawberry fields, past acres of cabbage and broccoli and, here and there, a few sparse vineyards. It's certainly not Burgundy, where grapevines are planted everywhere, right to the edge of the highway, or Napa Valley, where the wineries are as densely packed as a suburb full of split-levels, but make no mistake: this is wine country.</p>
        <p>And in the last few years, the Santa Barbara wine region has grown astonishingly. Since 1997, the amount of land planted with grapes has shot up to more than 18,000 acres, from about 10,000, and the number of wineries in the county has almost doubled in the last decade, to about 50. Most of that acreage was planted by big wineries like Beringer, Robert Mondavi and Kendall-Jackson, which, recognizing the quality of Santa Barbara grapes and the relative affordability of the land, bought up huge tracts in the Los Alamos Valley and the Santa Maria Valley to the north.</p>
        <p>But the true measure of excitement here is focused a little farther south, on the western Santa Ynez Valley, where smaller parcels of land, ranging from just a couple of acres to a few hundred, have been planted with pinot noir and chardonnay grapes. Growers expect these Burgundian varietals to flourish in the cool climate that is moistened by fogs blowing in almost daily off the Pacific Ocean, and the first wines, made from vines planted three years ago, show excellent potential. The chardonnays are almost crisp with citrus flavors, while the pinot noirs, flamboyant in their youth, should achieve elegance as the vines mature.</p>
        <p>''You're going to see some brilliant wines coming out of Santa Barbara,'' said Alan Phillips, the winemaker and general manager of both Foley Estate and LinCourt Vineyards, which have planted about 250 acres, mostly of chardonnay and pinot noir, on undulating slopes facing south and west. ''The cool climate wines are absolutely stunning.''</p>
        <p>Equally exciting are the passionate young winemakers like Steve Beckmen, 31, of Beckmen Vineyards and Andrew Murray, 28, of Andrew Murray Vineyards, who have seized on Rhone varietals, particularly syrah, and have planted new hillside vineyards in the warmer central part of the valley.</p>
        <p>THE best Santa Barbara syrahs are rich and complex wines, layered with nuances as in the northern Rhone Valley of France, syrah's home territory, rather than lightly likable, as so many California syrahs have been.</p>
        <p>''When I started making syrah, I think there were four other people in the state who were doing it,'' said Bob Lindquist of Qupe, who made his first syrah for Zaca Mesa in 1982 and who saw the potential for Rhone grapes early on in the Santa Ynez Valley. ''Now, I think there are 25 syrah makers in Santa Barbara County alone.''</p>
        <p>Santa Barbara is not the only booming region in California. San Luis Obispo County, the Monterey Bay region and Sonoma County have all experienced similar rapid development. But this sleepy county about 100 miles north of Los Angeles may be the most unlikely California region to be joining the top echelon of wine producers. It's far better known for the relaxed city of Santa Barbara, for its beautiful hills that have offered refuge to the likes of Ronald Reagan and Michael Jackson and for its 18th-century adobe missions. In fact, the missions were the first in the county to make wine, a sweet and sturdy beverage that no doubt had its secular as well as its sacramental uses. Wine was made in the county right up through Prohibition but seemed to die out after World War II.</p>
        <p>Not until the late 1960's and early 70's, well after the California wine industry began to take off, did Santa Barbara again try its hand at grape growing and winemaking. Pioneers like Firestone Vineyards, Zaca Mesa and Sanford &amp; Benedict arrived, with little idea of what grapes to plant and where.</p>
        <p>Many early arrivals planted cabernet sauvignon in areas ill suited for the grap, producing weedy, vegetal wines. Others planted chenin blanc and riesling, noble grapes that have never achieved much popularity in California. But some got it right almost immediately. The 130-acre Sanford &amp; Benedict vineyard, the first planted in the western part of the Santa Ynez, has been a superior source of pinot noir and chardonnay grapes for 25 years, while the 900-acre Bien Nacido vineyard, first planted 30 years ago, graces the labels of many of the county's finest bottles.</p>
        <p>By the mid-80's, acclaimed wineries like Au Bon Climat, Qupe, Babcock Vineyards and Sanford Winery were firmly established, soon to be joined by others like Foxen Vineyard, the Lane Tanner Winery and Fess Parker Winery and Vineyard. Big organizations like Beringer had begun to make inroads, but the winemakers were largely a small, close-knit community, many of whom had learned their craft together, and the county reflected their irreverence.</p>
        <p>By most accounts, Jim Clendinen of Au Bon Climat, an iconoclastic winemaker who wore long, shaggy hair after it had been stylish and a goatee before goatees came back, worked feverishly to draw attention to Santa Barbara wines, traveling the world to tout their quality. In Santa Barbara County, he and Mr. Lindquist of Qupe had a cooperative agreement to share production facilities at the Bien Nacido vineyard, an arrangement that has set a collegial standard for the county.</p>
        <p>''Jim Clendinen has been huge, as far as his ambassadorial role in bringing attention to the area and paving the way for others to follow, and to illustrate what the potential of Santa Barbara County could be,'' said Greg Brewer, 31, of Brewer-Clifton, one of the county's hottest winemakers today. ''In the late 80's and early 90's, he was a larger-than-life figure here.''</p>
        <p>Though they had eked out a reputation for seductive, elegant pinot noirs and ripe yet nicely acidic chardonnays as well as a few good syrahs, Santa Barbara wines were still largely a footnote in California.</p>
        <p>BUT that made Santa Barbara all the more attractive to wealthy wine lovers in Southern California, who saw greater opportunities to make an immediate mark in the wine industry nearby, rather than in Northern California, where they would be greeted with yawns, if they were noticed at all. That and the fact that prime Santa Ynez vineyard sites are a relative bargain, under $20,000 an acre, compared with $35,000 to $45,000 an acre in the Carneros district of Napa Valley, by one winemaker's estimate.</p>
        <p>Ron Melville, who owns a securities firm in Los Angeles, actually bought land in Napa Valley before settling on several hundred acres in the Santa Rita Hills, where he built Melville Vineyards and Winery. He hired Mr. Brewer to oversee his operations. Melville will release its first bottles, from the 1999 vintage, later this year. The families of both Mr. Beckmen and Mr. Murray moved up from Los Angeles, choosing Santa Barbara over Northern California to build wineries. Fess Parker, the Hollywood actor who played Davy Crockett and Daniel Boone in the 50's and 60's, opted for elbow room and wide open spaces in Santa Barbara County in the late 80's, over densely populated Northern California.</p>
        <p>Like many in the county, Mr. Parker points to great untapped potential in the region, and with recent purchases in both the western Santa Rita Hills and the central Santa Ynez, he is doing his best to tap it. He owns hotels in Santa Barbara and in Los Olivos, a quiet town of cafes, galleries and wine-tasting rooms, where Mr. Parker is trying to develop a world-class restaurant.</p>
        <p>''My goals here are not modest,'' he said. ''I want this to be the French Laundry of Santa Barbara County. Napa Valley wasn't any fun until the restaurants came in.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Parker's winery, a sprawling ranch-style building with a rambling veranda, is on Foxen Canyon Road, a winding country lane of stunning vistas of hills and valleys, sprawling coastal oak trees and wildflowers, with hawks and vultures drifting overhead. While most of the small wineries on this route that links the Santa Ynez Valley with the Santa Maria Valley welcome visitors, Mr. Parker's is one of the few equipped to handle big groups, complete with a large tasting room, a smiling staff and a gift shop where you can buy wines, local foods and of course, coonskin caps.</p>
        <p>Such an operation sends cold chills through many in the county, who see wineries as harbingers of the kind of large-scale development they detest. Traffic jams are unknown in Santa Ynez, short of the tourists who slow to gawk at the twirling windmills in the town of Solvang, where the main draw is not wineries but a quaint and kitschy Scandinavian theme with plenty of clogs and shoppes.</p>
        <p>''This is kind of where Napa was 25 years ago,'' said Gary Burk, a marketing and production executive with Au Bon Climat and Qupe, who incidentally makes very good pinot noirs and chardonnays under his own label, Costa de Oro. ''Are we going to stay a little country place that makes wines, or are there going to be wine trains and bed-and-breakfasts all up and down Foxen Canyon Road? I don't know if everybody wants that. Some people will welcome that, I think especially the newer people. The older people prefer making wines in a more casual environment.''</p>
        <p>In an effort to slow development, the county has put up numerous regulatory hurdles -- ''the madness,'' Mr. Phillips, the Foley winemaker, calls it. Well-financed concerns like Foley Estate can battle their way through the obstacles, but some smaller winemakers are opting out.</p>
        <p>Brewer-Clifton, which makes minute quantities of pinot noir and chardonnay from purchased grapes, is moving its winemaking operation to a warehouse in the city of Lompoc, which is within the county lines but is not bound by its rules.</p>
        <p>''Lompoc is a funny town that's screaming for business,'' Mr. Brewer said. ''Santa Barbara County is very resistant to more wineries going in. There are all kinds of regulations, permits and delays. It's a long, arduous process.''</p>
        <p>Though the regulatory tensions are bound to continue (the latest debate was over a rare salamander that received an emergency listing as an endangered species, grinding several winery projects to a halt), one thing the wineries seem to be figuring out is to how to use the climate for the maximum advantage of each particular grape.</p>
        <p>THE Santa Ynez Valley is blessed with long growing seasons with plenty of sunshine, offset by natural, fog-induced maritime air-conditioning, a product of the east-west valleys that are a peculiar feature of the jutting coastline below Santa Barbara. ''It's a unique combination,'' said Mr. Lindquist of Qupe. ''We're far enough south so that we don't get hit by the rains that come down from the northwest, and yet because the coastline is turned around we have this tremendous cooling effect. The soils are important, but not nearly as important as the climate.''</p>
        <p>That moderate climate, Mr. Murray of Andrew Murray Vineyards said, is what gives the Rhone varietals such potential in the central Santa Ynez. ''Too warm and you might get a more insipid-style syrah,'' he said. ''Too cool and it might be too lean. Somewhere right in the middle, you get your darkest, richest wines, full-bodied but still elegant.''</p>
        <p>Other places in California make good syrahs, too, Mr. Murray admited, but he believes that the long Santa Barbara growing season is a definite advantage. ''We were picking syrah at the end of November,'' he said. ''That's when you can really eke out not only those fruit flavors, but those flavors of earth and spices and violets, the real pretty side of syrah, which you find often in the syrahs of this area.''</p>
        <p>The California wine boom has sent the demand for grapes soaring, forcing many winemakers to seek new supplies or to grow their own. Chris Whitcraft, who has been buying grapes to make small quantities of pinot noir and chardonnay since 1985, had to get his pinot noir from Sonoma County in 1999. When the demand exceeds the supply, the small winemakers are the first to lose out, one of the reasons that Mr. Beckmen of Beckmen Vineyards feels more secure with his own supply of grapes.</p>
        <p>''Believe me, having 80 acres of syrah, I get calls every day asking if I have syrah grapes available to sell,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Some fear that the expansion can be too rapid, and that a fall will be inevitable. ''Will there be a home for all these grapes, especially if the economy takes a dip?'' Mr. Lindquist asked. ''Both '98 and '99 were small crop years. But in '97, there were more grapes than we could handle. A lot of winemakers have short memories.''</p>
        <p>As far as the wines themselves are concerned, a Santa Barbara signature has been elusive. The future looks very good for syrahs, which can be spicy, nuanced and elegant. Some optimistic winemakers even expect that the eastern end of the Santa Ynez, the warmest part of the valley, will one day produce good Bordeaux varietals like cabernet sauvignon and merlot, grapes that have failed miserably in other parts of the valley.</p>
        <p>But most people agree that the county's greatest successes have been its richly textured, sweet pinot noirs and its chardonnays, some of which resemble Chablis in their blend of citrus and mineral flavors.</p>
        <p>For some like Mr. Brewer, who can sound almost mystical discussing how Brewer-Clifton wines reflect the soil from which the vines emerge, this is a noble challenge. Others like Richard Dore, an owner of Foxen Vineyards, seem to say, slow down and catch your breath.</p>
        <p>''We've been doing this for 30 years, and we're just figuring out where to plant stuff, let alone how to make it,'' Mr. Dore said. ''In Burgundy they've had 3,000 years to get it right.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
