<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leafs Discover Brodeur Is a Vexing Puzzle</title>
    <meta content="03DEVI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196536"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toronto Maple Leafs</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brodeur, Martin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Toronto Maple Leafs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFDF1139F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leafs Discover Brodeur Is a Vexing Puzzle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., May 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses play of New Jersey Devils goaltender Martin Brodeur in playoff series against Toronto Maple Leafs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everybody involved in the Stanley Cup playoff series between the Devils and Toronto has Martin Brodeur's name on the tip of his tongue. Brodeur, the Devils' goaltender, has been so brilliant preventing goals and so effective distributing the puck that he has intimidated the Maple Leafs.</p>
        <p>''He's the most mentally tough goaltender I've ever worked with,'' said the Devils' goaltending coach, Jacques Caron. ''He's so confident, and what he does is that he usually gets into opponents' minds when he plays well.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everybody involved in the Stanley Cup playoff series between the Devils and Toronto has Martin Brodeur's name on the tip of his tongue. Brodeur, the Devils' goaltender, has been so brilliant preventing goals and so effective distributing the puck that he has intimidated the Maple Leafs.</p>
        <p>''He's the most mentally tough goaltender I've ever worked with,'' said the Devils' goaltending coach, Jacques Caron. ''He's so confident, and what he does is that he usually gets into opponents' minds when he plays well.''</p>
        <p>Brodeur certainly infiltrated the minds of the Panthers in the Devils' first-round four-game sweep of Florida. Not a moment seemed to go by that the Panthers did not mention Brodeur's ability to come up with an outlet pass to his forwards that could lead to an offensive opportunity for the Devils.</p>
        <p>Now, the Leafs are the ones bestowing the verbal bouquets on Brodeur, who is arguably the most effective goaltender in the league when it comes to handling and clearing the puck out of his zone. ''We're facing a great goaltender who is essentially an extra guy who moves the puck like a defenseman,'' Toronto's Steve Thomas said.</p>
        <p>And even when the Leafs' remarks are in defense of their own goaltender, Curtis Joseph, they seem to backfire. When Toronto Coach Pat Quinn pointed out that the Devils were running into Joseph, the officials became more aware of players interfering with both goaltenders. Now, Quinn's players are afraid to hit Brodeur for fear of being penalized.</p>
        <p>With help from Caron, the goaltending coach, Brodeur spends a great deal of time in practice working on controlling and distributing the puck. Brodeur also enjoys playing forward in intrasquad scrimmages so he can score goals.</p>
        <p>''It's a great feeling when you score,'' Brodeur said. ''Sometimes I enjoy scoring even when I play with my kids in the basement. But I also make them earn a save. My kids come to the games and wave at me from the stands. They know that Daddy cannot wave back during a game.''</p>
        <p>Brodeur's forte is making spectacular saves at the most opportune time. He is notorious for making the big save to turn a game to the Devils' advantage. He did it in the 1-0 victory in Game 2 in Toronto Saturday night. And he did it again here Monday night with 11 saves in the scoreless first period as the Devils went on to a 5-1 triumph and a 2-1 lead in the four-of-seven-game Eastern Conference semifinal series.</p>
        <p>''There isn't much to say about Marty,'' said Scott Gomez, who scored a goal for the first time since the opening game of the series against Florida. ''He bailed us out in the first period like he has done so many times.''</p>
        <p>Inspired by Brodeur's first-period heroics, the Devils came out with enthusiasm and confidence, scoring three times in the second period and twice in the third. Before Toronto's Kevyn Adams scored with 4 minutes 17 seconds left in the game, Brodeur had gone 134:25 without allowing a goal.</p>
        <p>The Maple Leafs will go into Game 4 Wednesday night with only three goals in three games against Brodeur. His goals-against average in this year's playoffs is 1.29, much lower than his career-playoff average of 1.95 goals against.</p>
        <p>Brodeur was not at his best in the playoffs the past two springs and the Devils made an early exit. This spring, he has been better than in 1995, when he backstopped the Devils to the Stanley Cup title with a goals-against average of 1.67.</p>
        <p>''I didn't play well in the playoffs the last two years,'' Brodeur said before the Florida series. ''This year, I put myself under a lot of pressure to do well because it's what you do in the playoffs that people judge you the most.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Comments by Toronto Coach PAT QUINN that were critical of SCOTT STEVENS have been noticed by the Devils' captain. ''Sure it bothers me a bit,'' Stevens said, responding to a charge that he is a dirty player. ''But I know what kind of a player I am. I am not going to make a comment about what he said. I'll just go out and play my game.'' . . . Coach LARRY ROBINSON excused SCOTT NIEDERMAYER, JAY PANDOLFO and JASON ARNOTT from Tuesday's practice. . . . SERGEI BRYLIN practiced with the team, but Robinson ruled out the possibility of using Brylin in Game 4. Brylin has been out with a bruised right knee since the second game of the series with Florida. ''The knee is fine,'' Brylin said, ''but I'm a little out of shape.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
