<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Food, Please, It's Foodieville</title>
    <meta content="03MEDI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="This column will appear monthly, looking at food on television, on radio, on the&#10;&lt;br&gt;Internet and in magazines." name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MIXED MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Foodie Magazine</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slatalla, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E4D71339F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1000" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Food, Please, It's Foodieville</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michelle Slatalla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slatalla, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Slatalla Mixed Media column on new magazine Foodie, which contains no recipes; sees magazine geared toward young men who do not cook, but who embrace celebrity culture that surrounds food these days; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I HAVE to say that if I were the editor of the brand-new Foodie Magazine, I probably would have put Stephen Baldwin on the cover of the first issue.</p>
        <p>After all, Mr. Baldwin epitomizes the reader that this food magazine wants to reach. He's a man, in his mid-30's and he doesn't cook. And in a short question-and-answer interview inside that avoided discussion of how bad the food really was at Alaia, his short-lived Manhattan restaurant, Mr. Baldwin eloquently summed up the appeal of a trendy, buzz-driven eatery: ''It can be a hell of a lot of fun.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I HAVE to say that if I were the editor of the brand-new Foodie Magazine, I probably would have put Stephen Baldwin on the cover of the first issue.</p>
        <p>After all, Mr. Baldwin epitomizes the reader that this food magazine wants to reach. He's a man, in his mid-30's and he doesn't cook. And in a short question-and-answer interview inside that avoided discussion of how bad the food really was at Alaia, his short-lived Manhattan restaurant, Mr. Baldwin eloquently summed up the appeal of a trendy, buzz-driven eatery: ''It can be a hell of a lot of fun.''</p>
        <p>That's also the rallying cry for Foodie Magazine, which arrived in the last two weeks. More and more glossy food magazines are being crammed onto newsstands in these flush times; in the first three months of this year, a dozen joined the 50 or so mainstream food titles already vying for the attention of the eating obsessed.</p>
        <p>But Foodie manages to stand out. For one thing, it has no recipes: not for Foodie the prosaic coverage of, say, the best way to insert raw chicken into an oven to achieve an edible result, the sort of topic to which magazines like Gourmet and Fine Cooking -- and yes, even Mr. Food's Easy Cooking -- have devoted pages in recent issues.</p>
        <p>With most food magazines, I know where I stand. When I see Gourmet, I think of my mother-in-law and her friends, all fine cooks, who learned in the 1960's the value of adding red wine to their pate -- and who still keep back issues on their coffee tables. Bon Appetit reminds me (again) that it's time to visit Italy, and Saveur nudges me to add more butter to that sauce -- O.K., cream, too -- because we should be good to ourselves.</p>
        <p>Instead, everything about Foodie is a call to unite a new generation of groupies (the young, the hip, the testosterone-and-cash-laden) who avidly embrace the celebrity culture that surrounds food these days. I think this might explain the big photo of a tattooed chef who cooks for rock stars. And a spread on sushi that features more photos of scary, sharp knives than of actual food. And one hopes, the item extolling the virtues of a Web site called Chowhound.com, which Foodie describes as a ''boundless, stream-of-consciousness dining diary,'' recounting eating excursions around the New York area.</p>
        <p>I called Foodie's editor, Gus Floris, who confirmed the masculine slant. ''More and more, men are into food today,'' he said. ''They dig it because celebrity chefs like Bobby Flay and Emeril are making it cool.''</p>
        <p>Apparently, they crave details of Steven Spielberg's breakfast routine in the Hamptons (he speed-walks to a local gourmet shop), or Frank Sinatra's tipping habits (he'd give $100 to the bartender). And don't get me wrong. I am as interested as the next eater to learn that a former fashion editor at Elle magazine is the one to thank for the chichi swimming club decor at Isla, the hip Cuban restaurant in Greenwich Village. But is this sort of information -- a curious blend of People magazine meets Hulk Hogan -- enough to sustain a long-term audience?</p>
        <p>Quite possibly, said Samir Husni, a professor of journalism at the University of Mississippi who specialized in the magazine industry. ''This is a good time for magazines,'' he said. ''The unprofessional approach may work for them, if they can find enough people in the world who belong to the swinging club of food people.''</p>
        <p>The club president, Mr. Floris, is a former associate publisher of Sportswear International, an industry magazine, where he worked for 10 years. Mr. Floris, whose father owned Greek diners in New York City, said he yearned to create a magazine that would combine the glamour of the fashion industry with the hype surrounding the latest hot restaurants. In fact, he said he got the idea for the magazine's name four years ago. He recalled: ''I was sitting in a bar with a friend of mine who's a certified chef. He said, 'Call it Foodie, because that's what's happening now.' ''</p>
        <p>It may be a cultural phenomenon, but Mr. Floris is content to start small. After founding Morpheus Publishing Inc., and obtaining private financing, he hired a skeleton staff of five and put together the first issue of what he plans as a quarterly. With a print run of 52,000 copies, Mr. Floris said he expected to sell no more than 4,000 on newsstands at $3.95 a copy. He will mail another 25,000 to ''a list of names I rented,'' and has also struck a deal with the online food retailer Fultonstreet .com to distribute 15,000 to customers.</p>
        <p>With the second issue, scheduled for Aug. 21, Mr. Floris plans to print 100,000 copies. The staff, he said, will remain lean. Not to sound picky, but he might consider hiring an additional copy editor: the first issue is riddled with misspellings and factual errors, like describing Quisp cereal as ''long gone.'' (It lives, Foodie, and it's a cult favorite among your target audience.)</p>
        <p>But in the end, I couldn't quibble with Mr. Floris's decision to put the rock star Sarah McLachlan and her hunky, peroxide-blond chef on the cover. He explained his logic: ''It's a perfect fit -- she's a celebrity and she's a lover of food. And they definitely appeal to the target audience.''</p>
        <p>Or put another way: She's a famous person who eats. And he's a tattooed person who cooks. In a culture obsessed with style and with eating, they cover almost all the angles. The only thing missing is food.</p>
        <p>MIXED MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
