<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why Are These Commuters Smiling?</title>
    <meta content="03COMM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Workplace" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196424"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Management Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Brien, Kathleen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E6D91239F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1276" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why Are These Commuters Smiling?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA LAWLOR</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American Management Association survey shows number of companies that engaged in at least one form of surveillance of workers' use of e-mail and Internet surged to 66 percent this year from 45 percent in 1999; more companies are tracking Internet use than any other office activity, perhaps because potential for visiting inappropriate sites is so great; graphs; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Terry Murray feels most alive when he is on the move -- which is why he spent five years making the two-hour one-way hike to and from his job as an engineering manager at Bio-Rad Laboratories in Cambridge, Mass. It wasn't until he strapped on a pair of in-line skates and headed out the door one morning last year, though, that his commute became really interesting.</p>
        <p>''I feel like a warrior on my way to work,'' said Mr. Murray, who cuts a striking figure in black stretch pants, fluorescent green-and-yellow top and helmet with red blinking lights fore and aft. It takes him 40 minutes to skate 10 miles from his home in Winchester to his workplace, past woods, lakes, streams and throngs of trenchcoat-clad 9-to-5ers waiting forlornly at the train station. For fun, he plows through puddles, throwing up a wake behind him, or jumps over recyclable containers left on sidewalks. ''Every commute is like a day of skiing,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Terry Murray feels most alive when he is on the move -- which is why he spent five years making the two-hour one-way hike to and from his job as an engineering manager at Bio-Rad Laboratories in Cambridge, Mass. It wasn't until he strapped on a pair of in-line skates and headed out the door one morning last year, though, that his commute became really interesting.</p>
        <p>''I feel like a warrior on my way to work,'' said Mr. Murray, who cuts a striking figure in black stretch pants, fluorescent green-and-yellow top and helmet with red blinking lights fore and aft. It takes him 40 minutes to skate 10 miles from his home in Winchester to his workplace, past woods, lakes, streams and throngs of trenchcoat-clad 9-to-5ers waiting forlornly at the train station. For fun, he plows through puddles, throwing up a wake behind him, or jumps over recyclable containers left on sidewalks. ''Every commute is like a day of skiing,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mention the word ''commute,'' and most people make a face. And no wonder. An overwhelming majority of Americans drive to work, and according to a study of 68 urban areas by the Texas Transportation Institute in 1997, they spent an average of 45 hours a year sitting in traffic, up from 16 hours in 1982. Los Angeles had the highest average delay, at 82 hours.</p>
        <p>Users of mass transportation, though smaller in number, tell horror stories of delayed trains and overcrowded subway platforms. Yet, a breed of worker is flourishing that actually likes the daily commute. Some simply sit back and enjoy the ride; others have figured out ways to make the ride more interesting, and still others -- like Mr. Murray -- have switched from cars or trains to more exotic forms of transport. The common theme is to try, somehow, to make one of life's great frustrations one of the day's great rewards.</p>
        <p>Jacqueline Skinner, a travel consultant in Manhattan, is a traditionalist who has commuted by train since 1959. Her favorite commute, she says, began on ''the day Elvis died'' in 1977 when she first took the 8:03 a.m. Metro North train from New Canaan, Conn., to Grand Central. ''Everybody knows everybody,'' said Mrs. Skinner, who recently got a cake for her 70th birthday from the train's engineer and conductor. ''In the morning, it's like a kaffeeklatsch.''</p>
        <p>In the 60's and 70's, she rode the 6:10 p.m. ''party train'' home and luxuriated in the smoky bar car, where bartenders hired three-piece combos on holidays. Every Christmas, Mrs. Skinner dressed up as Santa and handed out gifts. Though she has since switched to the more sedate 5:05 p.m. train, she still considers the ride a high point of her day.</p>
        <p>The three-piece combos are long gone, but long-running card games and bar cars endure as institutions on the Metro North line. Two years ago, Tom Skinner (no relation to Jacqueline), executive producer for Touchscreen Media Group, an Internet company based in New York, started the Web site www.barcar.com to give commuters a way to keep in touch once they left the train. Contributors post jokes and photos and comment on just about everything. One popular section, named ''The Blue Lagoon'' after a blue disinfectant used to clean the toilets, invites visitors to submit opinions of the train's restrooms.</p>
        <p>New Canaan bar-car riders have posted their own Web page on the site, decorate their bar car with lights each Christmas, are fiercely loyal to their bartender, Vinnie, and tend to be a little cliquish. ''If someone new walks in, they have to tell one good joke that offends at least one person, or sing their alma mater,'' said Linda Hinckley, an advertising account supervisor and regular on the 6:05 p.m. bar car to New Canaan. ''The more timid personalities tend to turn around and leave.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Skinner, a regular on the West Port line for 20 years, typically stands at the end of his bar car with a can of beer and a bag of peanuts, chatting with old friends. ''It's the only social life I have during the week,'' he said. ''I see people on the train sitting with their laptops playing solitaire, and I feel pity for them.''</p>
        <p>Even fighting highway traffic can be enjoyable -- if you have company. Derrick D. Mitchell, a San Diego city employee, organized a van pool with seven other commuters not long ago and says the hour's drive into the city now slips by almost unnoticed. ''We are literally laughing all the time,'' he said. ''Wednesday is doughnut day. On the way home, sometimes we go to a truckers' stop called Messy's Burger for hamburgers. At Christmas, we all get together with our spouses and go out to dinner. When someone is having a personal problem with a child or a spouse or a job, we support them. We are very close -- like family.''</p>
        <p>Joe Brown, the owner of a restaurant in Cherry Hill, N.J., also found a way to ease the angst of fighting his state's notorious traffic jams. Five years ago, he began taking his son, Jordan, with him and dropping him off at a day-care center near the restaurant. ''He demonstrates his karate moves for me, and we sing Motown songs,'' Mr. Brown said. ''It's our best time together.''</p>
        <p>Some drivers take extreme measures to relieve ennui. On a crawl along 25 miles of California Highway 17, Emil Gallant of Soquel said he and a friend used to ''take pictures of people doing stupid stuff while they were driving -- like putting on makeup, eating breakfast, talking on cell phones, reading books.'' They would post the photos on a Web site they entitled ''The Highway 17 Page of Shame.'' Mr. Gallant has since found a job closer to home and zips over country roads to his new workplace on his Triumph motorcycle. ''I love it,'' he gloated.</p>
        <p>Terry Head loves riding two-wheelers, too. Ms. Head, a postal worker in Carrollton, Ga., gave up her Chevrolet Suburban for a bicycle when gasoline hit $1.44 a gallon. Now, her 30-minute ride to work past flowering dogwood and apple trees, a lake, a river and all kinds of wildlife ''has turned into more of a pleasure than a protest for me,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''It's the best part of the day. The kids aren't bothering me, and the telephone isn't ringing.''</p>
        <p>If she thinks her commute is serene, she ought to meet Pat Doud, general manager of the Scuttlebutt Brewing Company in Everett, Wash. He paddles a kayak across Puget Sound from his home in Marysville. Though the ride takes up to an hour, versus 15 minutes by car, it gives him an unhindered view of the Cascade and Olympic mountains, bald eagles, seals, osprey, blue herons and spectacular sunsets on the way home.</p>
        <p>Besides, ''it's a great upper-shoulder and arm workout,'' Mr. Doud said. ''I bring an extra set of clothes, and when I get to work I hose off with one of the brewery hoses -- a quick cold shower. Invigorating.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
