<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shuberts Turn to Union In Dispute With Stewart</title>
    <meta content="03MORG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Actors Equity Association</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Shubert Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stewart, Patrick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Arthur</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schoenfeld, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pogrebin, Robin</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ride Down Mount Morgan, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Shubert Organization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Actors Equity Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Arthur Miller</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DD1039F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shuberts Turn to Union In Dispute With Stewart</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Producers of play The Ride Down Mount Morgan complain to Actors Equity Association about speech actor Patrick Stewart made from stage accusing producers of failing to promote play adequately; speech, which Stewart made on behalf of himself and author Arthur Miller, stunned Broadway by taking on powerful Shubert Organization; Shubert chairman Gerald Schoenfeld says Shubert and other producers spend over $1 million on advertising and promotion; show has playing to nearly full houses, but most of</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The producers of the Broadway play ''The Ride Down Mount Morgan'' have filed charges with the stage actors union against the show's star, Patrick Stewart, citing a speech he made from the stage on Saturday accusing the producers of failing to promote the play adequately.</p>
        <p>The complaint of unprofessional conduct, filed with the Actors Equity Association, could result in Mr. Stewart's expulsion from the union, which would be a professional blight but would not bar him from Broadway productions. The union rarely expels a member, but Mr. Stewart could be reprimanded or fined if the union agrees with the producers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The producers of the Broadway play ''The Ride Down Mount Morgan'' have filed charges with the stage actors union against the show's star, Patrick Stewart, citing a speech he made from the stage on Saturday accusing the producers of failing to promote the play adequately.</p>
        <p>The complaint of unprofessional conduct, filed with the Actors Equity Association, could result in Mr. Stewart's expulsion from the union, which would be a professional blight but would not bar him from Broadway productions. The union rarely expels a member, but Mr. Stewart could be reprimanded or fined if the union agrees with the producers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stewart and one of the producers will each have the opportunity to speak before a hearing committee of four Equity actors. The hearing has yet to be scheduled. Under Equity rules, agreeing to this procedure means that the producers have waived their right to take other legal action.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stewart declined through a spokeswoman to comment on the charges yesterday. The spokeswoman, Kelly Bush, said that Mr. Stewart had not yet been notified of the action.</p>
        <p>Gerald Schoenfeld, chairman of the Shubert Organization, along with the other producers of the show, said simply, ''In our opinion we thought the matter should be brought to Equity's attention.'' Mr. Schoenfeld said that the producers had spent more than $1 million on advertising and promotion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stewart's speech -- which he made on behalf of himself and the play's author, Arthur Miller, nine days before Tony nominations are to be decided -- stunned Broadway, not only because they could not recall a precedent, but because Mr. Stewart publicly took on the powerful and legendarily tough-minded Shuberts, as the organization is commonly known.</p>
        <p>The actor, who agreed to take a lower salary than usual for ''Mount Morgan'' in exchange for a percentage of the show's profits, had until then had a close relationship with Mr. Schoenfeld, having worked with him on ''A Christmas Carol'' and ''The Tempest,'' both of which were produced in Shubert theaters.</p>
        <p>''Mount Morgan,'' which received positive reviews, has been running at nearly full capacity, according to Variety, but most of the tickets have been heavily discounted, selling for about $40, down from the top ticket price of $80. As a result the play has been taking in 61 percent of its optimum gross. The producers would not say how much revenue the show needed to take in to make money.</p>
        <p>In an interview on Monday Mr. Stewart said that Mr. Schoenfeld had rejected requests to meet with him and Mr. Miller and that Mr. Stewart's agent, Sam Cohn, relayed a message from Mr. Schoenfeld demanding a written apology. ''Of course I have no reason to make an apology of any kind,'' Mr. Stewart said.</p>
        <p>He said he was driven to deliver his statement -- which he made standing alone onstage after the curtain call at Saturday's matinee and evening performances -- because he felt that the concerns he had voiced to Mr. Schoenfeld were being ignored. ''It's not as if I were trying to create a controversy around a failed production,'' Mr. Stewart said. ''The production is a success. The reviews are excellent. But people are not being told that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stewart said he believed that other nonmusicals like ''The Real Thing'' and ''A Moon for the Misbegotten'' were being advertised more aggressively. ''We are all in competition for audiences and for awards and nominations when they come around,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stewart said he had received assurances from Mr. Schoenfeld last week over the telephone that an advertisement for the play would run the following Sunday in the Arts &amp; Leisure section of The New York Times. The ad appeared in less than half of the copies -- 700,000 of 1.8 million, advertising personnel at The Times said, because it arrived at the Times after the deadline. He also said he had assurances that the exterior of the Ambassador Theater would be decorated with signs quoting the positive reviews, but that these never materialized.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schoenfeld said the signs would be forthcoming.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stewart said that before he made the speech, he alerted Mr. Miller; the play's director, David Esbjornson; Ms. Bush; and the rest of the cast. The actors declined through a secret ballot to join Mr. Stewart onstage.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Stewart had initially vowed to continue making his speech, he said he changed his mind because of the wide attention his comments attracted.</p>
        <p>''It's a disturbing thing for an audience to experience that,'' Mr. Stewart said. ''And I was disturbed at having to do it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
