<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Painting Contractor Charged With 1989 Murder in Queens</title>
    <meta content="03MURD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershaw, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romano, Ralph Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spensieri, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD61039F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Painting Contractor Charged With 1989 Murder in Queens</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH KERSHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershaw, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City police arrest Ralph Romano Jr for second-degree murder eleven years after Queens businessman John Spensieri was shot to death in his lavish Astoria home; case reviewed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eleven years after a Queens businessman was shot to death in his lavish Astoria home, the authorities yesterday charged the owner of a major bridge-painting company, which has worked on the Verrazano, Whitestone and Triborough bridges and has been linked to organized crime, with the murder of the Queens man, his former business partner.</p>
        <p>The police charged Ralph Romano Jr., 36, with second-degree murder in the June 7, 1989, killing of John Spensieri, 51, who had previously run a trash hauling company with Mr. Romano in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, officials said yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eleven years after a Queens businessman was shot to death in his lavish Astoria home, the authorities yesterday charged the owner of a major bridge-painting company, which has worked on the Verrazano, Whitestone and Triborough bridges and has been linked to organized crime, with the murder of the Queens man, his former business partner.</p>
        <p>The police charged Ralph Romano Jr., 36, with second-degree murder in the June 7, 1989, killing of John Spensieri, 51, who had previously run a trash hauling company with Mr. Romano in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spensieri was shot nine times with a 9-millimeter handgun in the basement of his home, the authorities said, adding that they were still unsure of a motive. Mr. Spensieri had been romantically involved with Mr. Romano's mother, Linda Romano, and was living with her at the time of his murder, officials said.</p>
        <p>Evidence implicating Mr. Romano in the killing was discovered during an investigation by Manhattan law enforcement officials into Mafia corruption in the garbage hauling industry, officials said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romano started his own garbage company after parting ways with Mr. Spensieri. He later joined his father's bridge painting business, Romano Enterprises, in Queens.</p>
        <p>His father, Ralph Romano Sr., had started the bridge painting company and worked for the Lucchese crime family as a bid estimator, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>During a federal bid-rigging trial in 1994, the elder Mr. Romano was named by a witness as a member of the so-called painters club, a group of Mafia leaders and associates who controlled major bridge painting contracts in the city.</p>
        <p>Ralph Romano Sr. was neither tried nor convicted in the painters club trial, but the Queens company was barred by the Department of Transportation from further work on city bridges.</p>
        <p>Since then, under the ownership of the younger Romano, the company  has completed multimillion-dollar jobs for the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, including a $13.8 million job on the Whitestone Bridge that was finished in 1998. The company is on the verge of completing a $15.7 million paint job on the North Grand Island Bridge near Buffalo.</p>
        <p>The company has recently tried to get city business again, making two bids with the Department of Transportation. The bids are under review by the city's Department of Investigations, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The authorities said the elder Romano was still involved in running the company, but a Romano Enterprises employee who answered the telephone yesterday said he was not and that he was out of town.</p>
        <p>The younger Mr. Romano, who was arraigned late yesterday on second-degree murder charges and was being held without bail, faces up to 25 years in prison. He has not been  charged with illegal activities involving either his trash hauling company or the bridge painting company.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romano's lawyer, Kenneth J. Schreiber, said his client would plead not guilty to the charges.</p>
        <p>''He is totally unaware of the nature of his involvement because he was not involved,'' he said. Mr. Schreiber added that Mr. Romano had no connection to organized crime.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spensieri's wife, Jean, who was separated at the time of the murder, said last night that she was relieved, mostly for the couple's two sons, that there was an arrest in the case after the family waited more than a decade. ''After 11 years, I'm glad that it's over with,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
