<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Papa's To-Do List: Hunt, Fish, Drink. More of Same.</title>
    <meta content="03WERT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Palin, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wertheimer, Ron</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Michael Palin's Hemingway Adventure (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E7DE1039F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Papa's To-Do List: Hunt, Fish, Drink. More of Same.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RON WERTHEIMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wertheimer, Ron</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ron Wertheimer reviews 2-part PBS television program Michael Palin's Hemingway Adventure, written and hosted by Palin; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Michael Palin's Hemingway Adventure'' is an engrossing travelogue. But there are two things it is not. Even though Mr. Palin, the program's host and writer, is an alumnus of the Monty Python comedy troupe, this is no manic Pythonian romp. Nor is it a colloquy on the life and work of Ernest Hemingway.</p>
        <p>In the spirit of Mr. Palin's two earlier globe-trotting series, this four-hour ''Adventure'' -- which PBS is showing in two chunks, tonight and next Wednesday -- gives Mr. Palin wide latitude (not to mention longitude) for his wry observations. They are often delightful. And that's lucky because while the series visits Hemingway's birthplace, grave and many of the places that were most significant in between, he remains a shadowy presence along the way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Michael Palin's Hemingway Adventure'' is an engrossing travelogue. But there are two things it is not. Even though Mr. Palin, the program's host and writer, is an alumnus of the Monty Python comedy troupe, this is no manic Pythonian romp. Nor is it a colloquy on the life and work of Ernest Hemingway.</p>
        <p>In the spirit of Mr. Palin's two earlier globe-trotting series, this four-hour ''Adventure'' -- which PBS is showing in two chunks, tonight and next Wednesday -- gives Mr. Palin wide latitude (not to mention longitude) for his wry observations. They are often delightful. And that's lucky because while the series visits Hemingway's birthplace, grave and many of the places that were most significant in between, he remains a shadowy presence along the way.</p>
        <p>You'll hear some memorable factoids about the great man: he once shot himself while fishing; he loved cats; he hated underwear; he ate Spam; he and Orson Welles once bashed each other with chairs. But to seek his essence as a man or a writer, you'll have to book another kind of passage. Or pass time with a book.</p>
        <p>For now, though, you can enjoy the trip that Mr. Palin is conducting. He is an imaginative tour guide, both knowledgeable and curious about the places through which he leads you. He has a knack for creating the illusion of intimacy as he speaks wittily to you and to the people he meets along the way, rarely acknowledging the film crew that is shadowing him and capturing dozens of memorable images, from the snows of Kilimanjaro to Mr. Palin's own farewell to arms after he tries firing a pistol and shotgun.</p>
        <p>Tonight, after recalling his delight in discovering Hemingway's books as a teenager, Mr. Palin is off to Spain: to Pamplona, where Hemingway described the annual running of the bulls, and to Valencia, where he started his first novel, ''The Sun Also Rises.'' At a bullring, Mr. Palin makes the first of many discoveries of his own distaste for things Hemingway loved.</p>
        <p>''I think I know better what drew Hemingway to the bullfight,'' he says. ''For him, to confront death was to experience life at its most intense. For me, well, it's a Spanish thing.''</p>
        <p>Tonight's other stops include Kenya, where, instead of hunting, Mr. Palin views animals with rangers who protect them, and to Hemingway's birthplace in Oak Park, Ill., where Mr. Palin learns that he shares a hometown -- Sheffield, England -- with Hemingway's maternal grandfather.</p>
        <p>Next week's jaunt includes stops in Key West, Fla., for the annual Hemingway look-alike contest; Uganda, where he survived two plane crashes within 48 hours; and Venice, where he gleefully read in The Daily Mirror of New York that he had died in the second crash. Before reaching Ketchum, Idaho, site of Hemingway's suicide in 1961, Mr. Palin stops in Cuba for the series's best sequence.</p>
        <p>He visits Hemingway's favorite hotel room in Havana and his house outside the city, both lovingly maintained as shrines. At the house, ''every object is cleaned religiously,'' including Hemingway's record collection, ''which can never be played, as they've run out of needles.''</p>
        <p>At the end, when he concludes that Hemingway has been a good traveling companion, you'll think the same of Mr. Palin. He has gamely failed in his attempts at Hemingway-style fishing, shooting and drinking. But except for a moment's jotting in a notebook, he is never shown trying that most Hemingwayesque pursuit, writing. Maybe that's why Papa never quite comes into focus.</p>
        <p>Besides his scripts, Mr. Palin has written several books, including a novel called ''Hemingway's Chair,'' which he never mentions. Still, he was probably wise to keep such efforts off screen. If you've ever seen someone actually writing, you'll know: it is not a pretty sight.</p>
        <p>MICHAEL PALIN'S HEMINGWAY ADVENTURE  PBS, tonight  (Channel 13, New York, at 9)</p>
        <p>Produced by Prominent Television Productions for the BBC and PBS. Martha Wailes, series producer; David F. Turnbull, director; Anne James and Edward Mirzoeff, executive producers.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
