<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>About 16, the Year Of Living Furiously</title>
    <meta content="03LESS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196522"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LESSONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herring, Hubert B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5DF1139F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>About 16, the Year Of Living Furiously</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Hubert B. Herring</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herring, Hubert B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lessons column discusses educational pressures facing 16-year old and his parents (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I WAS 16 once. My mother, in the midst of tearing her hair out, used to mutter, ''When you have a 16-year-old, you'll understand.''</p>
        <p>Well, suddenly I do, and I'm starting to.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I WAS 16 once. My mother, in the midst of tearing her hair out, used to mutter, ''When you have a 16-year-old, you'll understand.''</p>
        <p>Well, suddenly I do, and I'm starting to.</p>
        <p>The thing is, though, that being 16 isn't what it used to be. As I've quickly come to realize, it's worse. I'd love to be able to harrumph to my son, ''Why, in my day . . . ,'' and then reel off the horrors of coming of age in the early 60's. But once I told him I grew up without a VCR (''You're kidding!'') or had to learn to drive a stick shift (''What's that?''), I would have to admit that the pressures now are far greater.</p>
        <p>For those out of the teenage loop, 16 might seem just another number on the steady climb from 0 to 21. But just look at the pressures that our society, in its infinite mischief, has conspired to load onto children -- or are they young adults? or what? -- in the year following their 16th birthday.</p>
        <p>Educational pressure is surely the worst. It used to be that we wandered into the College Boards without much thought, looked at a few colleges and sent in our applications. But these days, high school juniors -- who are typically 16 -- often go to tutors or special classes for the tests. My wife and I tried to resist this, thinking of such prepping as a gimmick, a low-cal short cut, but since most students do it, the playing field would be tilted against our son without it. We succumbed, and off he went each week to two tutors, one for English, one for math -- preparing to submit himself to the tests ordeal not once but twice this spring.</p>
        <p>This time-consuming process came just as high-pressure advanced-placement exams loomed, along with -- in his case -- Regents and International Baccalaureate exams. That last program, as I understand it, gets students both to learn more rigorously and to approach learning in a new way -- noble goals indeed. It's still fairly rare in this country, but I was glad to hear at least one college admissions officer speak of it with respect. Innovative as it is, it adds yet another round of exams and another layer of pressure.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, in the day-to-day classroom, it has been drilled into these students that solid junior-year grades are vital for getting into a good college, and they feel this pressure daily, test by test, paper by paper. To top it off, many sports-minded teenagers have hit the varsity level -- for our son, it's tennis -- and the endless practices and bus trips gobble a big slice of time. Since such activities are essential for college admission, what parent will say no?</p>
        <p>Even as all this is happening, guidance counselors are telling students they really need to start getting a sense of what the college scene is all about. So we, like many other parents, dutifully tried to find little pockets of time this spring to squeeze in college visits -- to a chorus of ''No, the SAT's are that weekend'' or ''That's just before the A.P.'' or ''That's the prom'' or ''I've got to work that weekend to get money to buy clothes.'' Or, perhaps, the day came and he was simply exhausted. (Do these people ever sleep?)</p>
        <p>We did manage to visit several colleges this spring, but were flying a little blind until we knew our son's SAT scores -- and thus which colleges would be realistic choices.</p>
        <p>Then there's tuition. A generation ago, a middle-class family could probably just write the check; now, unless there's a new dot-com or some old money in the family, that's unlikely. So, like many other parents, we've had to give our son a crash course in matters financial: there's this much money, and beyond that you have to play a part in making the numbers add up, whether through scholarships, loans, or opting for a less expensive school.</p>
        <p>And in a cruel quirk of timing, all this often coincides with a host of extracurricular pressures, notably that liberating, get-out-of-my-way-world moment: getting a driver's license. One moment they're children, suffering the indignity of having bald, badly dressed parents chauffeur them around; the next they're full-fledged members of an on-the-go society.</p>
        <p>A driver's license, in turn, expands the social possibilities exponentially, and these, in turn, create a dire need for cash, which means an intense desire to earn money even as all the other distractions mount.</p>
        <p>Any one of these pressures could be heavy going; when they all converge in the spring of junior year -- well, it makes my head spin, and I'm mainly just watching in awe from the sidelines.</p>
        <p>But I wonder: Does it put too much stress on students and parents alike to have childhood rattle over so many bumps simultaneously? Can any tinkering be done to spread these pressures out?</p>
        <p>LESSONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
