<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Across the Atlantic, the Microsoft Case Attracts Curiosity</title>
    <meta content="Y03EURO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196499"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Liberation (Newspaper)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE6D81039F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Across the Atlantic, the Microsoft Case Attracts Curiosity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <dateline>CAMBRIDGE, England, May 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>In Britain and on European Continent, lastest chapter in Microsoft Corp antitrust case--government's proposal to break company in two--has received prominent attention in media; French daily newspaper Liberation has even set up forum on its Web site for Parisian readers to weigh in their views; European Commission, executive unit of European Union, has kept careful eye on Microsoft's practices, working with US Justice Department in some instances to curb Microsoft's behavior (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This university town has been transformed in the last decade by the arrival of companies like Microsoft, along with a bevy of start-ups hoping to follow in its footsteps. Now it is watching intently to see whether Microsoft's path will be divided.</p>
        <p>''For us, Microsoft is viewed as the archetypical high-tech success story,'' said John Cornish, director of product marketing for ARM Holdings, a designer of microchips for hand-held devices based in Cambridge that itself has become a hometown success story. ''The antitrust issues are a function of antitrust laws based on U.S. history, which differs very much from the U.K. and Europe.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This university town has been transformed in the last decade by the arrival of companies like Microsoft, along with a bevy of start-ups hoping to follow in its footsteps. Now it is watching intently to see whether Microsoft's path will be divided.</p>
        <p>''For us, Microsoft is viewed as the archetypical high-tech success story,'' said John Cornish, director of product marketing for ARM Holdings, a designer of microchips for hand-held devices based in Cambridge that itself has become a hometown success story. ''The antitrust issues are a function of antitrust laws based on U.S. history, which differs very much from the U.K. and Europe.''</p>
        <p>In Britain and on the Continent, the latest chapter in the Microsoft tale -- the government's proposal last week to break the company in two -- has received prominent attention in the media. The French daily newspaper Liberation has even set up a forum on its Web site for Parisian readers to weigh in with their views.</p>
        <p>''We're a bit further removed, but I think there is as much interest here as there is in the States,'' said Derek McAuley, the assistant director of Microsoft's research lab in Cambridge, Microsoft Research Ltd. ''When I talk to my friends at the pub, there is an understanding of the principles of antitrust, but there is some confusion as to why this litigation is being brought to bear against us.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, for many of the new-economy start-ups in Europe, Microsoft has served as the ultimate example of an entrepreneurial success story. William H. Gates, Microsoft's chairman, has achieved a celebrity status in Europe that rivals the Spice Girls. And while most Europeans have watched the breakup of state-owned monopolies through deregulation, most have never seen the breakup of a self-made company.</p>
        <p>But the European Commission, the executive unit of the European Union, has kept a careful eye on Microsoft's practices, working with the Justice Department in some instances to curb the software giant's behavior. The Brussels-based commission is investigating Microsoft's integration of certain server-related software technology that has been integrated or bundled into Windows 2000. The European Commission is also examining Microsoft's agreement to acquire 29.7 percent of Telewest, the British cable TV operator, from MediaOne.</p>
        <p>''This is not a competition between antitrust authorities,'' a spokeswoman for the European Commission said. ''At this stage, we trust the Justice Department. Obviously, the bottom line is that we're talking about a global marketplace and whatever happens in the U.S. will have an impact everywhere.''</p>
        <p>In 1995, the European Commission and the United States Justice Department cooperated in an antitrust investigation that Microsoft settled by changing contracts with personal computer producers and eliminating some restrictions on software makers.</p>
        <p>Today, neither party is willing to settle, and this time around the stakes are much higher. And so is the attention the company is getting across the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>''Microsoft has used its operating system as a marketing vehicle to the disadvantage of the customers,'' said a column in the German business daily Handelsblat. ''At a time when the trend goes toward software that is integrated into servers on the Internet, a voluntary or a forced split-up would offer the chance for a new beginning.''</p>
        <p>Readers of Liberation have been posting messages to its Web site about the Microsoft case all week. ''The dismantlement of Microsoft is not a cure-all to break the monopoly of Windows, but at least it sheds light on the general contempt for Microsoft's practices,'' wrote a user identified as Erion.</p>
        <p>Not many companies in Europe compete head-on with Microsoft. More often than not, the high-tech companies in Europe that have prospered have been allied with Microsoft. From computers to hand-held devices to set-top boxes for digital television, it is hard to find a European version of Sun Microsystems or Oracle, two American companies that have lobbied hard for a breakup of Microsoft.</p>
        <p>Even British Telecommunications P.L.C., the once state-owned telephone monopoly, has several alliances with the software maker.</p>
        <p>''On one hand it does seem strange to try to break them up because they are the ultimate start-up made good,'' said Peter Bonfield, chief executive of British Telecom. ''But who am I to judge the Justice Department? In terms of a company, we deal with them. We don't feel threatened by them at all.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
