<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Enjoy a Glass, Lessons Are Not Needed</title>
    <meta content="03WINE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196450"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WINE TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prial, Frank J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Wine Talk</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E6DE1039F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="980" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Enjoy a Glass, Lessons Are Not Needed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank J. Prial</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Prial, Frank J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank J Prial Wine Talk column discusses difference between true wine tasting and party at which wine is drunk, often also called tasting; holds people do not have to take course to enjoy wine; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DRINKING wine is fun. Tasting wine is work.</p>
        <p>And yet for some reason, Americans love to talk about wine tasting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DRINKING wine is fun. Tasting wine is work.</p>
        <p>And yet for some reason, Americans love to talk about wine tasting.</p>
        <p>''The meeting will be followed by a wine tasting.'' ''After the candidate speaks, there will be a wine tasting in the library.'' ''Join us for a wine and cheese tasting.''</p>
        <p>The wine broker in Bordeaux, who prowls the cold damp cellars trying to guess what the raw young wines will be like in another 10 years, is a true taster. The importer confronted with, and probably confounded by, an array of seemingly identical bottles is a taster. So is the judge at a wine competition, facing 100 cabernets. So is the winery owner, making the final crucial blend of the vintage. They all know what they're looking for.</p>
        <p>These people are professionals who spend years developing their skills. They taste often and they taste seriously, because many thousands of dollars ride on their decisions.</p>
        <p>Wine-tasting classes abound, particularly in the big cities, and they are serious enough -- but mostly about meeting other tasters. As for all those other so-called tastings, they are mostly, to use the diplomat's term, drinkings. In other words, parties at which wine is served.</p>
        <p>How can you tell a real tasting from a fashionable one? Simple: At a professional tasting, nobody -- at least nobody with any sense -- drinks anything. Since the nose is a far better judge of wine than the mouth, the pros spend as much time smelling wine as they do tasting it. And what they do taste, they spit out. Spitting is no fun. It's awkward, it's messy and it's frustrating. After all, one's instinct is to swallow, particularly if the wine is any good.</p>
        <p>Characterizing a wine and cheese party as a tasting is harmless enough, except for the fact that it conveys the idea of something educational, of a learning process. It implies that wine is something for the initiated; that to drink and enjoy it, you have to go through -- yes -- tastings.</p>
        <p>I'd like to have a bottle of good Burgundy for every time someone has said to me, ''I like wine, but I don't know anything about it.'' Why is it that no one ever says, ''I like rye bread, but I don't know anything about it''? Why are so many so intimidated? Why do people think they have to take a course to be able to enjoy a glass of wine?</p>
        <p>The industry bears much of the responsibility. How many kinds of rye bread confront the consumer every day? A dozen, if that? How many zinfandels? A couple of hundred. How many chardonnays? Probably close to a thousand. For all their vaunted marketing skills, the people who sell wine can't seem to do much about this confusion.</p>
        <p>The idea behind ''tastings'' appears to be that you will learn to distinguish among various wines. But who can make a choice among 1,000 chardonnays? The wine publications are not much help. ''We tasted 350 chardonnays for you,'' they trumpet, ''and picked the 30 best.'' Thanks a lot.</p>
        <p>A colleague came to me 20 years or so ago and asked: ''Is Chateau X supposed to be a good wine?'' He had had a bottle the night before and liked it. I don't remember the chateau name, but it was a good wine and at a good price. Years later, he said it was the only wine he ever drank. ''I still like it,'' he said. ''Why change?''</p>
        <p>Why indeed?</p>
        <p>If everyone had half a dozen wines he or she knew and enjoyed, much of the insecurity that accompanies wine drinking and wine buying would disappear, along with the lucrative ''wine education'' business that profits from it. Rare and expensive wines would continue to attract the relatively small market of collectors and connoisseurs, but a vast new market would open up for all the people who would like to drink wine but are put off by the confusion and elitism that plague the wine trade.</p>
        <p>Almost lost in the approach to wine as something exotic is the idea of wine as food. The typical wine advertisement shows a handsome couple relaxing by the fire, sipping wine. To me, there is no greater waste of a good red wine than drinking it like a cocktail, either at home or at a bar.</p>
        <p>In traditional wine drinking countries, wine is almost never served as an aperitif or an after-dinner drink unless it is fortified. If you're just having a drink, have a martini or a beer or a sherry. Or -- the one exception -- an oaky, sweetish California chardonnay. But save the red wine, or the dry white wine, for dinner.</p>
        <p>Wine is meant to go with food. When Baron Eric de Rothschild took over Chateau Lafite-Rothschild in 1977, he invited a few people to come to the chateau for a long weekend to sample every vintage produced since the Rothschilds bought Lafite in the 19th century. As many of the wines as possible were tasted at the table, with meals.</p>
        <p>Once or twice a year, Bipin Desai, a California collector, puts on extensive tastings of famous wines -- every vintage of Ridge Vineyards' Monte Bello cabernet, for example -- for other collectors. Mr. Desai's tastings, usually spaced over three or four days, are always done in restaurant settings. Like Baron Rothschild's weekend, they are not really tastings but a succession of resplendent meals.</p>
        <p>Good wine and good food. Now that's what I would call fun.</p>
        <p>WINE TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
