<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arrest May End Slovakia Ex-Premier's Influence</title>
    <meta content="Y03SLO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Slovakia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meciar, Vladimir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Slovakia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Slovakia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E4DA1039F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arrest May End Slovakia Ex-Premier's Influence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>BRATISLAVA, Slovakia, April 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Violent arrest by commandos of Vladimir Meciar, former Prime Minister of Slovakia, may finally end his extraordinary influence over Slovak politics; he governed Slovakia from independence in 1993 when it split from Czech Republic until September 1998, when he was defeated by coalition of four parties; his government was widely considered illiberal, discriminatory and corrupt, practicing crony politics; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bold or bizarre, the violent arrest of former Prime Minister Vladimir Meciar may finally, the government hopes, put an end to his extraordinary influence over Slovak politics.</p>
        <p>On April 20, masked commandos from the organized-crime unit blew down the back door of Mr. Meciar's villa with dynamite and took him away at gunpoint for questioning. He was quickly released. But the raid raised new questions about a bruising politician who, polls show, may be both the most popular and the most unpopular in Slovakia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bold or bizarre, the violent arrest of former Prime Minister Vladimir Meciar may finally, the government hopes, put an end to his extraordinary influence over Slovak politics.</p>
        <p>On April 20, masked commandos from the organized-crime unit blew down the back door of Mr. Meciar's villa with dynamite and took him away at gunpoint for questioning. He was quickly released. But the raid raised new questions about a bruising politician who, polls show, may be both the most popular and the most unpopular in Slovakia.</p>
        <p>Populist, nationalist and hyperbolic in his language, Mr. Meciar, a former boxer, ran Slovakia from its independence in 1993, after the divorce from the Czech Republic, until September 1998, when he was defeated by a coalition of four diverse parties.</p>
        <p>His government was widely considered illiberal, discriminatory and corrupt, practicing crony politics. So much so that Slovakia became a pariah, left out of the first round of NATO expansion and shunned for entry negotiations by the European Union.</p>
        <p>Only a year ago, Mr. Meciar won 43 percent of the vote in the presidential election, losing to a former Communist, and his party remains the most popular, winning 25 percent support in polls.</p>
        <p>More recently, despite difficult economic times because of a long-delayed restructuring and reform, including a 22 percent unemployment rate, Mr. Meciar's popularity has been dropping enough that the government of Prime Minister Mikulas Dzurinda was able, quietly, to  sanction the raid on Mr. Meciar's villa.</p>
        <p>The next day, several thousand supporters rallied here to protest his arrest and scream epithets at Mr. Dzurinda.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meciar was seized because he had refused to cooperate with investigators. Although he was quickly released, he is being investigated for paying $350,000 in bribes, called ''illegal bonuses,'' to cabinet members, and he faces questioning about the kidnapping of the son of the president of Slovakia in 1995. The kidnapping is widely believed to have been carried out by the secret police on Mr. Meciar's orders.</p>
        <p>''The case is formally about the bribes but informally about the kidnapping,'' said Grigorij Meseznikov, president of the Institute for Public Affairs, a research group. ''Everyone knows he was involved in this.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Meciar's party had dropped,  from 32 percent in the polls to 25, Mr. Meseznikov said, and the criminal accusations will hurt him. ''I don't think he can return to power,'' Mr. Meseznikov said. ''It's hard to imagine that any of the democratic parties will go into coalition with him.''</p>
        <p>He paused and added: ''Of course, since 1990, people have been saying that Meciar was finished. But he keeps coming back.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dzurinda is widely admired in the West for trying to bring Slovakia back, as quickly as he can, to the prescribed route of reform for former Communist states. With a smart young economist, Ivan Miklos, as deputy prime minister, he has moved rapidly to cut the budget, trade deficits and foreign debt and to restart a more open process of privatization that will include banks, energy and telecommunications.</p>
        <p>But ''because of Mr. Meciar, we've lost time, nearly 10 years,'' Mr. Miklos said. ''The Meciar legacy is lack of investor confidence.''</p>
        <p>That is most visible in comparison with the Czech Republic, which has some of the same problems of cronyism and corruption. Last year, the Czech Republic attracted $4 billion in direct foreign investment, and Slovakia just $350 million. And as usual, restructuring has led to higher unemployment and a drop in the government's popularity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dzurinda has also promised new respect for human rights and a fairer deal for Slovakia's Gypsies, who make up 8 percent of the population and who face widespread discrimination and joblessness. He is pushing Slovakia for the next round of NATO expansion, whenever that will come, trying to get President Clinton to stop here next month.</p>
        <p>Slovakia is about to join the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, and the European Union has invited the new government to talks.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Dzurinda expressed some concern over the cohesion of his broad coalition. His center-right party is itself a merger of five smaller parties. A new populist party called Smer, or Direction, run by a young lawyer and former Communist, Robert Fico, has quickly emerged from nothing to become the second most popular.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fico is described by experts and diplomats as purposefully vague, making broad populist comments that criticize crime, corruption, the Russian and Slovak mafias and the Gypsies, but maintaining a pro-European stance and saying he will never cooperate with Mr. Meciar.</p>
        <p>''I hold the door open for Fico,'' Mr. Dzurinda said. ''On the one hand, I'm not so happy with his party. He's a bit populist. But he's not Meciar.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
