<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Antonio Reid Is New Chief In Power Shift at Arista</title>
    <meta content="03ARIS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196453"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arista Records</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bmg Entertainment</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carvajal, Doreen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reid, Antonio</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Clive</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E1DE1039F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="508" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Antonio Reid Is New Chief In Power Shift at Arista</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOREEN CARVAJAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carvajal, Doreen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>BMG Entertainment names Antonio Reid chief executive of its Arista Records unit, succeeding unit founder Clive Davis; move follows unusually public struggle over replacement for Davis, 67; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a long-expected power shift, Antonio Reid was formally named yesterday as the new chief executive of Arista Records, the 25-year-old pop powerhouse that for months has been bracing for the departure of its founder and longtime leader, Clive Davis.</p>
        <p>The announcement by the record label's parent, BMG Entertainment, endedwhat has been a long-running and uncommonly public struggle over the replacement of Mr. Davis, 67, an old-fashioned music industry titan who has nurtured artists from Janis Joplin and Barry Manilow to Whitney Houston and Carlos Santana.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a long-expected power shift, Antonio Reid was formally named yesterday as the new chief executive of Arista Records, the 25-year-old pop powerhouse that for months has been bracing for the departure of its founder and longtime leader, Clive Davis.</p>
        <p>The announcement by the record label's parent, BMG Entertainment, endedwhat has been a long-running and uncommonly public struggle over the replacement of Mr. Davis, 67, an old-fashioned music industry titan who has nurtured artists from Janis Joplin and Barry Manilow to Whitney Houston and Carlos Santana.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reid, 43, chief of his own Atlanta-based label, LaFace Records, said yesterday that he had discussed his appointment with Mr. Davis. It remained unclear what sort of role Mr. Davis would play in a transition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis was noticeably muted yesterday in his comments about his replacement, who will take over in early July after Mr. Davis's own contract ends.</p>
        <p>''Though I regret the imposition of the Bertelsmann retirement age policy, it's time now to turn to a new and vital chapter in this fast-changing world of music,'' Mr. Davis said in a statement he issued after declining to be interviewed. He added that he  was looking at offers to start his own record label, including a potential deal with BMG.</p>
        <p>BMG Entertainment said that LaFace Records would be consolidated with Arista through BMG's purchase of the remaining 50 percent of LaFace that it did not own.</p>
        <p>Consolidation could lead to expansion because of plans to increase Arista's reach into genres like Latin music, said Mr. Reid and Strauss Zelnick, chief executive of BMG Entertainment.  ''Neither one of us expects to go through the unfortunately typical process of roster reduction and consolidation that new label presidents often go through,'' Mr. Zelnick said.</p>
        <p>With gross revenues of about $425 million, Arista is expected to achieve record profits by the end of its fiscal year in June, partly on the strength of Santana's best-selling album ''Supernatural.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Reid said that Arista could probably improve its performance. ''We intend to make Arista the home for many Latin artists, record producers and Latin superstars,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reid, the son of a Cincinnati seamstress who got his musical start as a drummer for a group called the Deele, helped create LaFace Records 11 years ago, cultivating Atlanta's thriving hip-hop and urban music scene with performers like Toni Braxton, TLC, Usher and OutKast. He founded that label with Babyface Edmonds, a left-handed guitarist from the Deele. Mr. Edmonds is to head his own record label, which will be called Joe Lies Music.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
