<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rock Faithful's Intrepid, Ruminative Guide</title>
    <meta content="03PROF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196487"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Broadcasting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Vin Scelsa</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffman, Jan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scelsa, Vin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEEDA1039F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rock Faithful's Intrepid, Ruminative Guide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN HOFFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoffman, Jan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column discusses career of radio disc jockey Vin Scelsa; he discusses his new role with Internet DJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VIN SCELSA'S baby-round cheeks are smooth, his smile easy, as he relaxes in the sunroom of his suburban New Jersey home, which looks onto a protective barrier of thick woods. His commute to the new job that officially began yesterday, in a broadcast studio lined with his 10,000 CD's and 10,000 LP's, is the fastest imaginable: through the kitchen and down the hall.</p>
        <p>''I have a relatively stress-free life,'' he says. ''I haven't worked full time since 1982. This is going to be a culture shock.'' He is laughing. If you're a New York radio fan of a certain order, you know that rich, rolling, deeply self-regarding and self-amused chuckle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VIN SCELSA'S baby-round cheeks are smooth, his smile easy, as he relaxes in the sunroom of his suburban New Jersey home, which looks onto a protective barrier of thick woods. His commute to the new job that officially began yesterday, in a broadcast studio lined with his 10,000 CD's and 10,000 LP's, is the fastest imaginable: through the kitchen and down the hall.</p>
        <p>''I have a relatively stress-free life,'' he says. ''I haven't worked full time since 1982. This is going to be a culture shock.'' He is laughing. If you're a New York radio fan of a certain order, you know that rich, rolling, deeply self-regarding and self-amused chuckle.</p>
        <p>And he is also not kidding.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scelsa has been treated for obsessive-compulsive disorder, bulimia and manic depression, and does not like change. Though ''Live at Lunch,'' his new, thrice-weekly program expressly for an Internet audience, is being sent from the controllable confines of home, computers give him anxiety jags, and he's both eager and uneasy about doing nine more hours a week of his signature aural painting with music and monologues.</p>
        <p>''Last night I was wired and up,'' he says, referring to ''Idiot's Delight,'' his Sunday show from 8 p.m. to 2 a.m., or thereabouts, that has been parked at WNEW-FM since 1996. ''I was boom, boom, boom! But the manic highs aren't the danger zones for me. The lows are.''</p>
        <p>What's surprising is that after more than 30 years as New York commercial radio's free-format doodlebug, an increasing anachronism in a tightly programmed market, Mr. Scelsa has found a way to be a pioneer again. Although to his critics, he is yammering and self-absorbed, to generations of listeners, he is a gifted storyteller who brings aboard gold-standard musicians.</p>
        <p>''I got to be friendly with Lou Reed because of the show,'' Mr. Scelsa says. ''Now he gives me a hug! Lou? Can you imagine that?''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Scelsa is at his most articulate when expressing the moody ineffable through recordings, from Billie Holiday to Leadbelly to Kurt Cobain to the next young, hungry band he discovered the other day. He's the ultimate music fan: passionately faithful to the old, yet always poised to fall in love.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scelsa's listeners have heard his dark riffs about aging -- he's 52 -- and his dinosaurlike presence in an Internet culture. But his new show on ArtistEnt.com, a Web site started by Danny Goldberg, the music industry executive, almost brings him back to the late 60's, when he was a student founder of WFMU, the pre-eminent renegade station, at Upsala College in East Orange, N.J.</p>
        <p>FOR where once he astonished by broadcasting ''Heroin,'' the Velvet Underground's malevolent drug dance, now, in unrestricted cyberspace, Mr. Scelsa can even play music with forbidden words. So far, his program is uninterrupted by commercials, unconstrained by programming policy.</p>
        <p>''I'm alone at my end and the listener is alone at his or her end,'' says Mr. Scelsa, petting his dachshund and describing the surreal allure of a life in radio, the solipsistic performer in a dimly lighted room, overheard by thousands.</p>
        <p>Things were not always this serene. In the late 70's when he and his colleagues at WNEW-FM were kings of the rock world, snorting and swaggering in their satiny baseball jackets, Mr. Scelsa, nicknamed Bayonne Butch -- he's New Jersey Italian,  Catholic schools, even, briefly, the seminary -- was more of a public character, introducing Bruuuucce at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>For him, the radio rock world died with John Lennon. On Dec. 8, 1980, his voice quavering, Mr. Scelsa announced the terrible news and held an on-air wake. Two years later, as radio formats narrowed, he was out of a job.</p>
        <p>With his wife, Freddie, working in the jewelry business, Mr. Scelsa became a stay-at-home dad to toddler Kate, and had time to go a little mad.</p>
        <p>His body consumed him. He lost 100 pounds and spent three hours a day exercising. ''It was my full-time job,'' he says ruefully. He hid, he binged, he got diagnoses, therapy and antidepressants.</p>
        <p>''I learned that as dark as it gets, you can work your way out of it,'' he says. ''You can survive. But in the middle, you think you're dying.''</p>
        <p>Even now, when he has stretches without Prozac, a mournfulness occasionally wells up. ''My daughter is turning 20,'' he says. ''I miss my child, although I love who she's become. It's not that I want another kid, it's about Little Her. I used to meet her bus every day.'' Kate's toddler swing set still stands in the backyard.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scelsa went back to work in 1985 at WXRK. In the early 90's, he began moderating ''In Their Own Words,'' a gathering at the Bottom Line of singer-songwriters like David Byrne, Rosanne Cash, Natalie Merchant.</p>
        <p>Although he did radio without a net, Mr. Scelsa found that similar prospect, in front of an audience he could actually see, unbearable. After five years, the nausea, diarrhea and sweats of stage fright bested him. He retreated to his Sunday show, which had returned to WNEW.</p>
        <p>''Even as a kid I had the Sunday blues,'' he says, ''that sense of loss that the weekend was almost over. It's why I like working Sundays. I never have to face it.</p>
        <p>''Besides, listeners tell me I help them get through,'' he adds, smiling. ''That tickles me.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
