<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sather's Oiler Contract an Obstacle in Rangers' Path</title>
    <meta content="03RANG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sather, Glen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DF1139F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sather's Oiler Contract an Obstacle in Rangers' Path</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses speculation concerning Glen Sather becoming New York Rangers general manager (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Glen Sather is indeed willing to listen to overtures from the Rangers about taking over control of the team, it may come after a long wait.</p>
        <p>Sather acknowledged recently that he had a window of opportunity to leave Edmonton, where he is president and general manager. But Cal Nichols, the chairman of the Edmonton Investors Group, which owns the Oilers, said yesterday that opportunity to leave the Oilers takes place in mid-July. The window, which Sather had written into his contract, is believed to be two weeks. ''There is a time limit,'' Nichols said, declining to elaborate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If Glen Sather is indeed willing to listen to overtures from the Rangers about taking over control of the team, it may come after a long wait.</p>
        <p>Sather acknowledged recently that he had a window of opportunity to leave Edmonton, where he is president and general manager. But Cal Nichols, the chairman of the Edmonton Investors Group, which owns the Oilers, said yesterday that opportunity to leave the Oilers takes place in mid-July. The window, which Sather had written into his contract, is believed to be two weeks. ''There is a time limit,'' Nichols said, declining to elaborate.</p>
        <p>Nichols also said that Sather's status with the Oilers was tied to their payroll, and how competitive that payroll was with the rest of the league. ''It's tied to our player budget,'' Nichols said. ''It has to meet a percentage of the league average.''</p>
        <p>By that he meant that the Oilers' payroll must remain within a certain percentage -- he would not say how much -- of the league average. If it does not, Sather is free to leave during the escape window. Sather had that clause written into his contract to protect his interests in case the cash-poor Oilers began slashing the payroll by trading top players.</p>
        <p>It is no secret that the Edmonton ownership group, made up of 37 partners, is strapped for cash, and Nichols acknowledged their economic concerns. ''I don't know where the league is going,'' Nichols said, alluding to salaries. ''We know where we're going to go. And we're not going to try to keep up with the league. We will have a player budget that we can afford.''</p>
        <p>A person in hockey familiar with Sather's thinking said that because of the Oilers' current budget situation, he may be less inclined than ever to stay in Edmonton, where he has worked with the Oilers for 24 years.</p>
        <p>If Sather is unable contractually to use the escape clause, the Rangers could presumably try to negotiate with the Oilers for his services. When asked if the Rangers would need to contact the Oilers before talking to Sather, Nichols said: ''They certainly have to talk to us. Otherwise, it would be tampering. He has two years left on his current contract. We intend to fulfill our part. If he decides to leave, that will certainly be his decision.''</p>
        <p>When reached on the golf course near his Palm Springs, Calif., home on Monday, Sather had no desire to reveal the contents of the clause. ''I have zero comments to make,'' he said.</p>
        <p>According to Alan Adams, a hockey expert who writes for The National Post of Canada, the Oilers had a payroll this season of $25.2 million, 22nd in the 28-team league. The Rangers, who missed the playoffs for the third straight year, had a payroll of $61.2 million, tops in the league by almost $14 million.</p>
        <p>The dilemma for the Rangers, of course, is that if they wait until mid-July to begin speaking with Sather, they will likely miss out on some of the other candidates they may be interested in, and who may be interested in the job. Without a general manager until mid-July, the hiring of a coach would have to be delayed until late summer, as well. Training camp begins in early September.</p>
        <p>The Rangers have been without a general manager and coach since the Madison Square Garden president Dave Checketts fired Neil Smith and John Muckler on March 28. The Rangers have two possible in-house candidates for the general manager's job to fall back on should they wait in vain for Sather. They are the assistant general manager Don Maloney, who is basically serving as the interim general manager; and John Davidson, the longtime television analyst. Both Maloney and Davidson played for the Rangers, as did Sather, which makes all three all the more attractive as candidates to Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>The more likely scenario, then, is the Rangers' asking for permission to speak with Sather before his window of opportunity opens. If so, the Rangers would have to work out some sort of deal with the Edmonton ownership group involving any possible package that would include money, draft picks and players.</p>
        <p>Checketts was not available for comment yesterday. When asked if the Rangers have already asked for permission to speak with Sather, Nichols said, ''No, they have not.''</p>
        <p>But Nichols did not rule out the possibility that he would listen if the Rangers came calling. ''It can happen,'' Nichols said, when asked if the Rangers could seek permission before mid-July. ''But we're not inviting it.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
