<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Six Runs and One Inning Add Up to Loss for Mets</title>
    <meta content="03METS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EEDC1139F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Six Runs and One Inning Add Up to Loss for Mets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, May 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>San Francisco Giants defeat New York Mets, 7-1 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are a lot of unusual things about Pacific Bell Park, the quirky yard that has played host to 10 games by the San Francisco Bay.</p>
        <p>An 80-foot Coca-Cola bottle, doubling as a children's slide, looms over left field. Next to that is a giant old-fashioned baseball mitt. A robot named Rusty emerges from a shed in right field now and then, waving goodbye to opposing pitchers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are a lot of unusual things about Pacific Bell Park, the quirky yard that has played host to 10 games by the San Francisco Bay.</p>
        <p>An 80-foot Coca-Cola bottle, doubling as a children's slide, looms over left field. Next to that is a giant old-fashioned baseball mitt. A robot named Rusty emerges from a shed in right field now and then, waving goodbye to opposing pitchers.</p>
        <p>And sometimes, the unusual can be found on the scoreboard. The Mets have seen a lot of crooked numbers on this road trip, and the San Francisco Giants posted another in the fourth inning tonight: 6.</p>
        <p>The Mets' starter, Glendon Rusch, was undone by one big inning, and the Giants defeated the Mets, 7-1. Rusch allowed six runs in the fourth -- the third six-run inning the Mets have allowed in five games on this trip. Four other times, an opponent has scored at least three runs in an inning.</p>
        <p>It was the first unsuccessful start for Rusch out of four he has made this season. He had been virtually invincible until tonight, permitting just five runs in 22 2/3 innings, walking just two. He walked no Giants tonight, but five hits and a hit batsman ruined his evening.</p>
        <p>With the score tied, 1-1, Barry Bonds doubled to lead off the fourth. Two singles gave the Giants a 2-1 lead, and Rusch faced J. T. Snow. With a 2-2 count, the left-handed-hitting Snow leaned into a curveball with his front shoulder, a hit-by-pitch.</p>
        <p>Mets Manager Bobby Valentine argued, suggesting Snow made no effort to get out of the way of the pitch. Two weeks ago, the Mets had gotten such a call, when the Cubs' Eric Young was not awarded a hit-by-pitch after leaning his shoulder into a John Franco pitch. But Valentine was unsuccessful this time, and the bases were loaded.</p>
        <p>The next hitter, Rich Aurilia, poked a single to right field to increase the Giants' lead to 3-1. Catcher Bobby Estalella then came up and ripped a line drive to left that never stopped carrying until it had barely cleared the eight-foot wall in left-center field. Suddenly the Giants had a 7-1 lead on the grand slam, and the Mets never got close off Livan Hernandez.</p>
        <p>Rush was lifted after six innings, having allowed seven runs on 11 hits. His record dropped to 1-2.</p>
        <p>The Mets did score off Hernandez in the first inning, but they could have had more than one run.</p>
        <p>The right-field corner is only 307 feet from home plate here, because the Giants wanted space for a public walkway between the fence and the bay.</p>
        <p>But they also wanted a field that would play fairly for pitchers and hitters. Heeding the advice of their broadcaster and former pitcher, Mike Krukow, designers made the right-center-field gap a distant 421 feet from the plate.</p>
        <p>That dimension sometimes inspires extra-base hits at the expense of home runs, as the Mets' Robin Ventura discovered in the first inning. Hernandez struck out the first two Mets on breaking balls, and he got ahead of Edgardo Alfonzo. But Alfonzo walked, and Ventura followed by slamming a pitch high off the brick wall in right-center. It would have been a homer almost anywhere else, but it went for a double here.</p>
        <p>No Mets runner got farther than second for the rest of the game. Hernandez, who was 0-5 against the Mets last season and has gone 19-28 since winning the most valuable player award for Florida in the 1997 World Series, beat the Mets for his first victory this season. He worked all nine innings, allowing eight hits on three walks and five strikeouts.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Outfielder DARRYL HAMILTON, who has not played since April 6 because of a sprained left foot, decided Tuesday to have surgery on his left big toe after visiting a specialist in Oakland, Calif. Hamilton will miss at least three more weeks, said the Mets' trainer, FRED HINA, and possibly as many as eight depending on the extent of the surgery and Hamilton's ability to recover.</p>
        <p>Hamilton, who had bone chips removed from the right side of the arthritic toe in November, will have them removed from the left side of the toe. He will return to New York in the next couple of days and hopes to have the surgery by Monday.</p>
        <p>''It was definitely important to get back this year,'' said Hamilton, who had feared he would miss the rest of the season. ''I didn't want to waste a year being lame and basically bedridden. That would have been a huge loss for me personally.''</p>
        <p>Catcher MIKE PIAZZA hit and threw on Tuesday with no pain, said Manager BOBBY VALENTINE, who expects Piazza to start on Thursday. Piazza, who hyperextended his right elbow in a home-plate collision on Friday, may be available to pinch-hit on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>In his first start at Class AAA Norfolk on Tuesday, the right-hander PAUL WILSON threw three and a third innings, allowing seven earned runs on six hits, with four walks and six strikeouts. Wilson, who missed all of 1999 after elbow surgery, threw his fastball 91 miles an hour, about 5 to 6 m.p.h. harder than he did at the beginning of spring training. . . . BILL PULSIPHER had impressed the Mets with his concentration and resilience in his two starts at Norfolk. But the left-hander experienced the same old problems in his first start for the Mets on Monday, allowing four runs on three hits and four walks in three and a third innings. The Mets plan for Pulsipher to stay in the rotation until BOBBY J. JONES can return from a calf strain. Jones threw about 80 pitches in a simulated game Tuesday and may be ready for a rehabilitation assignment this weekend.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
