<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An agency moves to consolidate its media services in a diversifying consumer market.</title>
    <meta content="Y03ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">B Com3 Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Starcom Worldwide</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mediavest Worldwide</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Starcom Mediavest Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7DB1039F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An agency moves to consolidate its media services in a diversifying consumer market.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>B Com3 Group will merge its media services agencies, Starcom Worldwide and Mediavest Worldwide, to form media planning and buying giant named Starcom Mediavest Group; merger points to intensified focus on media services as critical tool for agencies in trying to sell goods and services to increasingly choosy customers (Advertising column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JUST when Madison Avenue was looking for the latest merger developments from Young &amp; Rubicam Inc., another giant agency company, the B Com3  Group in Chicago, generated some merger news of its own.</p>
        <p>B Com3  -- formed this year when the Leo Group and the MacManus Group combined and then sold a 20 percent interest to Dentsu in Tokyo -- said yesterday that it would merge its media services agencies, Starcom Worldwide and Mediavest Worldwide, to form a media planning and buying behemoth named the Starcom Mediavest Group. (The name may be prosaic, but at least it's not puzzling like B Com3 ).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JUST when Madison Avenue was looking for the latest merger developments from Young &amp; Rubicam Inc., another giant agency company, the B Com3  Group in Chicago, generated some merger news of its own.</p>
        <p>B Com3  -- formed this year when the Leo Group and the MacManus Group combined and then sold a 20 percent interest to Dentsu in Tokyo -- said yesterday that it would merge its media services agencies, Starcom Worldwide and Mediavest Worldwide, to form a media planning and buying behemoth named the Starcom Mediavest Group. (The name may be prosaic, but at least it's not puzzling like B Com3 ).</p>
        <p>Starcom Mediavest will handle media services for accounts with billings estimated at $16.6 billion. That figure would place the newly merged agency second among all media brands in worldwide billings handled, behind only Mindshare, part of the WPP Group, at $17 billion. Among the major multinational clients of Starcom Mediavest are blue-chip marketers like Coca-Cola, General Motors, Kellogg, Mars, Philip Morris and Procter &amp; Gamble.</p>
        <p>The merger points to the intensified focus on media services as a critical tool for agencies in trying to sell goods and services to increasingly choosy consumers. Media planning and buying were not so important in the days when the choice of big television networks on which to run a commercial was limited to ABC, CBS and NBC, and the choice of large national magazines in which to run an advertisement was limited to Collier's, Life, Look and The Saturday Evening Post.</p>
        <p>''Without the right media, you won't get the message through,'' said Bob Brennan, 41, the chief operating officer at Starcom who will hold that post at Starcom Mediavest.</p>
        <p>''Jack and I often talk how we're on the verge of a nuclear arms race among media agencies,'' Mr. Brennan said, referring to Jack Klues, 45, the chief executive at Starcom who will become chief executive at Starcom Mediavest. ''This industry is going to consolidate rapidly and war is going to begin. We want to go into the war with as big an arsenal as we can find.''</p>
        <p>Coming soon to a theater near you, will be ''Dr. Strangead or: How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Love the Infomercial.''</p>
        <p>In most countries, the separate offices of Starcom, formed in 1997 by Leo, and Mediavest, formed by MacManus last year, will be combined by Jan. 1, 2001, and operate under the Starcom moniker. That has already taken place in Mexico. In others, including China and Greece, joint ventures were formed to handle media duties for P.&amp; G.</p>
        <p>In some markets, however, Mediavest and Starcom will operate separately, either because of conflicts preventing a merger or the success of the individual media brands. In North America, for instance, Mediavest will continue handling media for the Burger King unit of Diageo and Continental Airlines, while Starcom will continue handling media for McDonald's and Delta Air Lines.</p>
        <p>If those conflicts were ever to be resolved, ''we can instantly consolidate,'' Mr. Brennan said.</p>
        <p>And in markets like Britain, where ''there's tremendous opportunity to grow the two brands,'' he added, ''we can always consolidate systems and nonproprietary research.''</p>
        <p>Starcom Mediavest will be run by a chief executive team of Mr. Klues, Mr. Brennan and Kevin Malloy, 36, the chief operating officer at Mediavest. Mr. Malloy will become executive vice president for international operations at Starcom Mediavest and the chief executive at Mediavest North America.</p>
        <p>Mike Moore, who had come out of retirement to lead Mediavest after Irwin Gotlieb, its president, left to join Mindshare last summer, will relinquish the reins again, as of July 1. Mr. Moore, 62, will remain on the Starcom Mediavest board.</p>
        <p>The merger of Mediavest and Starcom brings the Leo-MacManus saga full circle. The two had initially met in 1998 to discuss merging only their media agencies, but the talks bogged down primarily because of disagreements between Mr. Gotlieb and his counterparts at Starcom.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Gotlieb defected to Mindshare, Roger Haupt, the incoming chief executive at Leo, contacted Roy J. Bostock, chairman and chief executive at MacManus, to propose merging the holding companies.</p>
        <p>''Good things come to those who wait, I guess,'' Mr. Brennan said, laughing, then pausing to add: ''And plan and fight and are tenacious about their futures.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
