<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.O.P. PANEL SEEKS TO ALTER SCHEDULE OF PRIMARY VOTING</title>
    <meta content="03RELEC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196548"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE PRIMARY SCHEDULE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brock, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EFDE1139F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1396" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.O.P. PANEL SEEKS TO ALTER SCHEDULE OF PRIMARY VOTING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>High-level Republican committee proposes new presidential nominating system aimed at building suspense and interest from March through June, with smaller states voting first and larger states casting decisive final votes; proposal is sharp reaction to current system, in which both party nominations were effectively decided by March 7, first day with several major primaries, before millions of Americans knew much about candidates; under proposed plan, 12 least populous states, District of Columbia and territories would be allowed to hold primaries or caucuses no earlier than first Tuesday in March; 13 slightly more-populous states would hold primaries first Tuesday in April; 13 middle size states would hold primaries on first Tuesday in May; remaining states, including New York, California, New Jersey, Texas and Florida, would hold primaries on first Tuesday in June; Bill Brock, former Republican National Committee chairman and leader of committee offering proposal comments; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A high-level Republican committee proposed a new presidential nominating system today intended to build suspense and interest from March through June, with smaller states voting first and larger states casting the decisive final votes.</p>
        <p>The proposal was a sharp reaction to the current system in which both party nominations were effectively decided by March 7, the first day with several major primaries, before millions of Americans knew much about the candidates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A high-level Republican committee proposed a new presidential nominating system today intended to build suspense and interest from March through June, with smaller states voting first and larger states casting the decisive final votes.</p>
        <p>The proposal was a sharp reaction to the current system in which both party nominations were effectively decided by March 7, the first day with several major primaries, before millions of Americans knew much about the candidates.</p>
        <p>Bill Brock, former Republican Party chairman, who led the committee that offered the plan, said, ''Too many people in too many states have no voice in the electoral process that names our candidates.''</p>
        <p>Jim Nicholson, the Republican national chairman, said he expected the party to adopt the plan.</p>
        <p>The Republican willingness to scrap the system seems likely to open up a national debate, even though the Democratic Party's reaction was to point out that the present system had elected Bill Clinton twice and therefore ''at this point, there is little incentive to change.''</p>
        <p>But if Republicans adopt the plan at the convention in August, Democrats might be willing to discuss changing the primary process. A crucial provision would give the Republican National Committee the authority, which it now lacks and the Democratic National Committee has, to alter delegate selection rules between conventions.</p>
        <p>James Roosevelt, co-chairman of the Democratic Rules and By-Laws Committee, said, ''If the Republicans can get that kind of flexibility, then between cycles we could have some real substantive discussions about this.''</p>
        <p>Potential opposition from large states is a major obstacle to the Brock plan. So is traditional Republican reluctance to impose national rules on state parties. Democratic opposition, if it persists, would be another hurdle, and even if both parties agreed on a plan, getting almost every state to change its primary or caucus date would be difficult.</p>
        <p>Under the plan, the 12 least-populous states, the District of Columbia and the territories would be allowed to hold primaries or caucuses no earlier than the first Tuesday in March. Another group of 13 slightly more-populous states, from Connecticut to New Mexico, could go on the first Tuesday in April. Thirteen middle-size states, including Kentucky and Massachusetts, could go on the first Tuesday in May.</p>
        <p>The rest, including New York, New Jersey, California, Florida and Texas, could have primaries on the first Tuesday in June. Any state could go later, and in the early stages, some might do so to get a Tuesday that was less crowded. The plan makes no allowance for early votes in Iowa and New Hampshire, but that might be adjusted by the Republican National Committee.</p>
        <p>State legislatures would have to vote to adopt new primary dates. To pressure them, the Republican National Committee would have the power to deny state parties 50 percent to 90 percent of their delegates.</p>
        <p>That degree of central control may be an issue, at the convention if not earlier, at next week's meeting of the Republican rules committee.</p>
        <p>John Deardourff, a Republican consultant whose first primary was in 1964, said today, ''The unwillingness to impose Washington-based decisions and the unwillingness to accept them is pretty strongly ingrained in Republican theology, and whether it's the government doing it, or the party, it just doesn't sit well.''</p>
        <p>The first hurdle is clearly within the party.</p>
        <p>Bill Jones, the California secretary of state, said the plan was ''absolutely not'' in his state's best interest because it would mean that California always came in the last group. He said the majority of members on the Brock commission on which he served were mistaken in their belief that because nearly half the delegates would not be chosen before June, a contest would keep going.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jones, who had pushed to move the California primary up to March 7, said he did not think the suggested changes would be enough to overcome the current way of nominating a candidate, which he called ''raise a lot of money, get it over quick.'' He said he thought a system of regional primaries, in which different regions each got their chance to go first, would be better.</p>
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the presumptive Republican presidential nominee, could play a decisive role on the plan at the convention. But his campaign had no comment tonight, saying Mr. Bush looked forward to studying the report.</p>
        <p>The report was issued on the day when North Carolina and Indiana, the 11th and 14th most populous states, held presidential primaries that drew virtually no interest. Early in the campaign, primary turnout was high, at least among Republicans, but by March 7, known as Super Tuesday, two-fifths of Republican delegates and one-third of Democratic delegates had been picked.</p>
        <p>Curtis Gans, head of the Committee for the Study of the American Electorate, who cheered the Brock report as ''the best thing since sliced bread,'' said turnout since March 7 ''has been abysmally low, and the citizens in the states which were after Super Tuesday have felt left out of the process.''</p>
        <p>A study by the Joan Shorenstein Barone Center at Harvard, known as the Vanishing Voter project, found both interest in and knowledge of the candidates had declined in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>The Brock report said the plan that it recommended could ease ''many of the problems that have come to plague the current nominating process: front-loading, compression, low voter turnout, early media frenzy, excessive 'tarmac and media ad' campaigning.''</p>
        <p>If Republicans do adopt the plan, the process of getting legislatures to alter primary dates (and abolish winner-take-all contests), would be simplified if some agreement was reached with the Democrats. Republicans might not press ahead without such cooperation.</p>
        <p>Today Mr. Roosevelt complained that the Republican plan gave too prominent a place to ''states with no diversity.'' Mr. Brock acknowledged that blacks made up only 6.2 percent of the population in the first group of states. But he said the existing system, with pre-eminence to Iowa and New Hampshire, rewarded two even-less-diverse states, since Iowa is 2 percent black and New Hampshire is 0.7 percent black.</p>
        <p>In the 1970's, when Democrats were establishing new rules for choosing delegates, most legislatures went along. The bipartisan good feelings more typical in state capitals than Washington frequently persuaded Republicans to let the Democrats have the new procedures they needed to stay out of trouble with their national party. Democrats could well do the same for Republicans over the next couple of years.</p>
        <p>Prof. Thomas Patterson, a leading researcher in the  Vanishing Voter project at Harvard, said he doubted the plan would accomplish its goals. Mr. Patterson said he believed if one candidate won most of the primaries in the first two months, he would be acclaimed as the likely nominee, even if most delegates had not been selected.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brock did not argue that the plan, if in force this year, might have produced a different candidate. But he noted that a shortage of money had forced several Republicans out of the contest even before the first votes had been cast. He argued that a calendar that began with primaries in lightly populated, relatively inexpensive states would have let them continue longer and ''bring their ideas'' to the process.</p>
        <p>John Weaver, political director for Senator John McCain, said he had no idea how a different calendar would have affected Mr. McCain.</p>
        <p>''We've not been reflective about that,'' Mr. Weaver said. ''We were pleased with the calendar. Why look back?''</p>
        <p>On the Democratic side, the national committee's satisfaction with the existing system reflected the position of the campaign of Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Doug Berman, campaign manager for former Senator Bill Bradley, said that having both parties hold primaries at the same time would have helped Mr. Bradley, since interest in the Democratic race evaporated when only Republicans were voting in February.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE PRIMARY SCHEDULE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
