<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="03DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196547"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE0DE1139F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1085" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Time Warner and Disney Agree to a Temporary Truce  Under increasing pressure, Time Warner restored the signals of ABC television stations to 3.5 million homes after agreeing to a temporary truce with Walt Disney.</p>
        <p>The settlement ended a 39-hour blackout and put off until July 15 a deadline for Time Warner Cable and Disney to agree on how much Time Warner would pay Disney for use of three of its cable channels. Time Warner had sought an eight-month extension. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Time Warner and Disney Agree to a Temporary Truce  Under increasing pressure, Time Warner restored the signals of ABC television stations to 3.5 million homes after agreeing to a temporary truce with Walt Disney.</p>
        <p>The settlement ended a 39-hour blackout and put off until July 15 a deadline for Time Warner Cable and Disney to agree on how much Time Warner would pay Disney for use of three of its cable channels. Time Warner had sought an eight-month extension. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Auto Sales Boom Despite Naysayers  Economists and auto executives have been predicting for the last several months that auto sales would soon slow significantly. That has not happened. Adjusting for seasonal variations, sales were up 10.5 percent from the extremely strong level of April last year. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Adventure, the Chinese Way  In business school, you write your thesis on how to manage for-profit schools. After more research, you take your idea and a 20-year plan to a developing country on the other side of the planet. Are you crazy? Many thought he was, says Seth Kaplan, who is in Shanghai, with 16 1/2 years left to go on his plan to develop a chain of universities in China. ''In China, you must be ready to create and take opportunities the Chinese way,'' he says. His stories bear him out. The Boss. [C8.]</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T Comments Send Stocks Down  Stocks fell broadly yesterday after AT&amp;T delivered a cautious profit outlook and investors took profits from a three-day rally in technology shares. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 80.66 points, to 10,731.12. The Nasdaq composite index slipped 172.63 points, or 4.4 percent, to 3,785.45. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index dropped 21.96 points, or 1.5 percent, to 1,446.29. [C16.]</p>
        <p>A Power Shift at Arista Records  In a long-expected power shift, Antonio Reid was formally named the new chief executive of Arista Records, the 25-year-old pop powerhouse that for months has been bracing for the departure of its founder and longtime leader, Clive Davis. [E3.]</p>
        <p>Clinton Focuses on China Trade Bill  President Clinton and his top aides, acknowledging that they lack enough votes to pass a crucial China trade measure later this month, increased pressure on Congress by emphasizing national security issues. [A1.]</p>
        <p>New-Home Sales Up 4.5% in March  Sales of new single-family homes unexpectedly rose 4.5 percent in March, to a seasonally adjusted annual rate of 966,000 units, after falling 0.6 percent in February. The sales rate was the largest since the 995,000 units reported in November 1998. The median price of a new home rose 3.1 percent, to $165,000 in March from $160,000 a month earlier. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Media Service Agencies to Merge  B Com3 is merging its media services agencies, Starcom Worldwide and Mediavest Worldwide, to form a media planning and buying behemoth, the Starcom Mediavest Group. Stuart Elliott: Advertising. [C11.]</p>
        <p>Corporate Jets Make a Comeback  The corporate jet business has come back at full throttle, thanks to a booming economy, a reaction against the delays and frustrations of commercial airlines, and a pronounced change in attitudes as corporate managers justify the expense of a company plane as a business tool. Business Travel: Joe Sharkey. [C12.]</p>
        <p>Gannett's Succession Plan Set  The chief executive of Gannett, John J. Curley, is stepping down in June but will remain chairman until he retires next year. Douglas H. McCorkindale, who has been the company's president since 1997, will succeed him. [C11.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
