<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bestfoods Gets Unilever Bid And Says No</title>
    <meta content="03BEST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bestfoods</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Unilever</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shoemate, Charles R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0DC1139F930A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bestfoods Gets Unilever Bid And Says No</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Unilever announces unsolicited bid to acquire Bestfoods for $18.4 billion, or $66 a share, in cash; Bestfoods rejects offer as 'financially inadequate'; Bestfoods chairman-chief executive Charles R Shoemate, in letter rejecting offer, discloses that Unilever first offered to buy Bestfoods on April 20 for $61 to $64 a share (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Unilever, the Dutch-British consumer products giant that agreed to buy Ben &amp; Jerry's Homemade and Slim-Fast last month, announced an unsolicited bid yesterday to acquire Bestfoods for $18.4 billion, or $66 a share, in cash.</p>
        <p>Bestfoods, the maker of Skippy peanut butter, Hellmann's mayonnaise, Entenmann's cakes and Knorr soups, rejected the offer as ''financially inadequate.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Unilever, the Dutch-British consumer products giant that agreed to buy Ben &amp; Jerry's Homemade and Slim-Fast last month, announced an unsolicited bid yesterday to acquire Bestfoods for $18.4 billion, or $66 a share, in cash.</p>
        <p>Bestfoods, the maker of Skippy peanut butter, Hellmann's mayonnaise, Entenmann's cakes and Knorr soups, rejected the offer as ''financially inadequate.''</p>
        <p>In a letter to Unilever rejecting the offer, Charles R. Shoemate, the chairman and chief executive of Bestfoods, disclosed that Unilever had first offered to buy Bestfoods on April 20 for $61 to $64 a share.</p>
        <p>That offer was considered at a Bestfoods board meeting yesterday along with the sweetened offer of $66 a share, which Mr. Shoemate said was ''subject to certain conditions.''</p>
        <p>In the letter to Antony Burgmans and Niall FitzGerald, Unilever's co-chairmen, rejecting the offer, Mr. Shoemate called Unilever's interest a ''validation of Bestfoods' global strategy in the consumer foods industry.''</p>
        <p>He said, however, that the board had decided that the bid was ''not in the best interests of Bestfoods, its shareholders and other constituents; and it is not opportune to consider a sale of the company.''</p>
        <p>The offer was the second time in less than a year that Bestfoods' name had come up as a possible merger partner in an industry that analysts say direly needs to consolidate.</p>
        <p>Last fall it was widely reported that Bestfoods was in talks with H.J. Heinz. At the time, Bestfoods denied any conversations were in progress.</p>
        <p>Moreover, in the very recent past Mr. Shoemate did not rule out a combination. In the company's 1999 annual report, which was published in March, Mr. Shoemate addressed the topic by first saying he would prefer to remain independent.</p>
        <p>''However, if we were to identify a partner with whom we could truly create even stronger profit growth and enhanced value for our shareholders, we would certainly be open to the opportunity,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>''The annual report was almost an invitation,'' said John M. McMillin, a food analyst at Prudential Securities. ''Looking at the success of Kraft/General Foods in North America, it is hard to argue against the benefits of consolidation. The issue is, what is Bestfoods worth?''</p>
        <p>Jeffrey G. Kanter, who works with Mr. McMillin at Prudential, said that on a cash flow basis the $66 a share offer represented a premium of ''about 33 percent'' over the average food industry multiple. Over the last year investors have been very unkind to food stocks, discarding their predictable cash flows and earnings for wild rides in technology shares.</p>
        <p>The stocks have done a bit better recently. On the New York Stock Exchange yesterday, Bestfoods closed at $50.56, down 75 cents a share.</p>
        <p>The stock has traded as high as $60 a share over the last 52 weeks, and as low as $35.75.</p>
        <p>The $66-a-share offer ''is a start,'' Mr. Kanter said.</p>
        <p>The analysts said the combination would make a good fit for both companies.</p>
        <p>Unilever, which has Breyers ice cream and Gorton's fish sticks in its stable of food brands, as well as Lipton teas, has been digging deep to augment and improve its offerings lately.</p>
        <p>Last month the company spent about $2.6 billion to buy Slim-Fast Foods and Ben &amp; Jerry's Homemade.</p>
        <p>In 1999 Unilever had sales of $43.7 billion. About half of its revenues come from food, Mr. McMillin said.</p>
        <p>A purchase of Bestfoods would make sense, the analysts said, because of the strength of its brands and its global reach.</p>
        <p>The company, which is based in Englewood Cliffs, N.J., has operations in 65 countries and sells products in many more.</p>
        <p>''These companies overlap in a lot of emerging markets,'' Mr. McMillin said. ''At the end of the day, a Bestfoods takeover was just a matter of time. It is the prettiest girl at the dance, and it has a chief executive who is 60 years old.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McMillan predicted that Bestfoods would hold out for a higher price. And he mentioned only one other company that might consider making its own bid for Bestfoods.</p>
        <p>''If the offer price gets into the $70-a-share range I don't know how they can fight it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''And there are not many companies that have as big a pocketbook as Unilever. Only Nestle has one as large.''</p>
        <p>Bestfoods has operations in more than 60 countries of North America, Europe, Latin America, Asia, the Mideast and Africa. It is one of the most international of the United States food companies, measured by its percentage of sales and earnings coming from outside the United States. In 1999, about 60 percent of its sales came from international operations, the company says.</p>
        <p>Last year Bestfoods had revenue of $8.6 billion and earnings of $717 million.</p>
        <p>Unilever had 1999 earnings of $3.1 billion.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
