<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>American Influences Help Redefine Practice of Yoga</title>
    <meta content="01YOGA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219197"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yoga</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kripalu Center for Yoga and Health (Lenox, Mass)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yoga Alliance</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Fitness and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Yoga</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E7D8163DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1587" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>American Influences Help Redefine Practice of Yoga</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN POWERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powers, Ann</byline>
      <dateline>LENOX, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American masters of yoga are devising their own styles, mixing knowledge gained from Indian masters with native experience to create a ecumenical approach with a practical, world-friendly character; American yoga is nonsectarian and does not follow guru paradigm; conference on American yoga was recently held at Kripalu Center for Yoga and Health in Lenox, Mass; Yoga Alliance has been formed by group of leading practitioners to explore criteria for certification (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many of America's masters recently descended upon the Kripalu Center for Yoga and Health here for a conference on ''The New American Yoga.''</p>
        <p>Virtually anyone who has bought a book or video, attended a workshop, or unfurled a mat in a major studio would have recognized someone here. This was as close to a summit meeting as yoga has come.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Many of America's masters recently descended upon the Kripalu Center for Yoga and Health here for a conference on ''The New American Yoga.''</p>
        <p>Virtually anyone who has bought a book or video, attended a workshop, or unfurled a mat in a major studio would have recognized someone here. This was as close to a summit meeting as yoga has come.</p>
        <p>Erich Schiffmann of Los Angeles, the star of a best-selling yoga video featuring Ali McGraw, declared the conference a ''power spot.'' Sharon Gannon and David Life, the founders of the favored rock star hangout, Jivamukti Yoga in Manhattan, came to teach and stump for animal rights.</p>
        <p>Veterans like the Bay Area's Rama Jyoti Vernon mingled with younger masters like Baron Baptiste, who teaches power yoga on ESPN. Other yoga teaching stars included Rod Stryker, Don Stapleton, Judith Lasater, Todd Norian and John Friend.</p>
        <p>The group represented the scope of approaches, from sweaty ''strong'' yoga to tension-melting restorative poses, that are taking yoga beyond the confines of the counterculture to the mainstream of American fitness. They came to stretch and breathe with eager students in the weekend's daily classes, but more important, they came to discover what their approaches had in common, and how they might add up to a definition of American yoga.</p>
        <p>These leading lights had one thing in common: none were of Indian descent. Most had studied with Indian masters, including the now-elderly triumvirate of B. K. S. Iyengar, K. Pattabhi Jois, and Sri T. K. V. Desikachar, whose principles of precision, heat and healing still dominate the discipline. But as they devised their own styles, the Americans mixed their knowledge with native experience to create the wide-ranging approach that has caught on today.</p>
        <p>''In the 60's and 70's, a number of swamis came to the U.S., and there was an emphasis on the spiritual side of yoga,'' said Kathryn Arnold, editor of Yoga Journal, the unofficial organ of American yoga, in an interview during the conference. ''The philosophy was more integrated into the asana practice,'' she said, referring to posture. ''They've all gone away, basically, or they've really aged. And there's been this inheritance of the yoga by the Americans themselves. And so we are redefining it. ''</p>
        <p>Indian teachers still influence American yoga. Integral, the school led by Swami Satchidananda from his ashram in Yogaville, Va., has dozens of schools nationwide. Bikram Choudhury's hot yoga technique is popular in Hollywood. Yet like American Buddhism, the yoga shaped by Western-born teachers has its own attributes. Its practical, world-friendly character is having an impact on Americans who would never visit an ashram.</p>
        <p>Yoga Journal says that 12 million people practice hatha yoga, the physical limb of a system that also includes ethics, breath work and meditation. Instructors here have combined different strains of Indian yoga to suit modern American tastes. Many have been drawn by the athletic ashtanga-based styles that have become popular here.</p>
        <p>Others prefer gentler therapeutic styles like Kripalu. Americans are sticking to their yoga mats long after tae-bo videos have been buried in the closet. Indeed, yoga is so popular that a group of longtime leading practitioners, the Yoga Alliance, has formed to explore criteria for certification.</p>
        <p>To say American yoga is just aerobics with chanting misses a large reason for its popularity. For many, the practice is spiritual, or at least psychological. Books like Mr. Schiffmann's ''Yoga: The Spirit and Practice of Moving Into Stillness'' are as popular as old-fashioned self-help tomes. People who once turned to therapy now seek inner peace from teachers who simultaneously help them tone their abs.</p>
        <p>''There's a bifurcation in the psychotherapy world, as a result of managed care in this country,'' said Stephen Cope, a Kripalu teacher, psychotherapist and the author of  ''Yoga and the Quest for the True Self.'' ''You've got managed care, very focused on medication, with short-term time limits on psychotherapy. Then you have this whole stream of people, the so-called worried well, with their spiritual quests, their desire to be fully alive, their attempts to be in better relationships. Where are they taking that? They're not taking it to psychotherapy any more, because they can't afford it.''</p>
        <p>Americans use the yoga mat as a therapist's couch, and often, as a church pew.</p>
        <p>''Our culture really likes the physical stuff,'' said John Abbott, the publisher of Yoga Journal. ''We're all ingrained from the earliest age that it's good to do exercise. And then you find this, wow, this is more than exercise. This is something about living.''</p>
        <p>The ecumenical approach that so well serves American attitudes is new in yoga. In the 1960's and 1970's, yoga practitioners came in two varieties. Either they were health nuts at the Y.M.C.A., uninterested in yogic philosophy, or they were serious disciples who took Indian names, wore bright or white robes, and followed gurus.</p>
        <p>But the guru paradigm has largely crashed and burned. Communities like Kripalu, whose guru, Amrit Desai, left in scandal in 1995 after 20 years, are having to reinvent themselves. Kripalu has thrived as a self-defined post-guru community, training hundreds of nonsectarian teachers per year. The model based around a charismatic leader often led to egotism and corruption and students fled disillusioned. In addition, many Americans grew wary of adopting a culture that was not their own. ''Most of the major ashrams did fall,'' said Sudhir Jonathan Foust, Kripalu's director of curriculum. ''Maybe because of the sensitivity of these particular cultures, they were the first to fall. But they weren't the only ones. In the Catholic Church, in synagogues, in schools, no question in government -- it's almost like our society won't tolerate that structure any more. Which has set us up for this new paradigm of experimentation.''</p>
        <p>As secular America has opened up to new notions of the inner life, through therapeutic practices and New Age conjectures, the seekers of the counterculture have been coming down to earth. These two paths met in the middle in the physical practice of yoga, especially as it was transmitted to today's leading teachers by Indians like B. K. S. Iyengar.</p>
        <p>''We were just coming out of the 60's change-your-consciousness thing, and many of us were in our heads, and wanting to meditate, and reach samadhi,'' said Patricia Walden, a renowned teacher and longtime student of Mr. Iyengar, referring to enlightenment. ''Iyengar was like, 'Stand on your feet. Feel your feet.' He was so practical. His famous quote was, 'How can you know God if you don't know your big toe?' ''</p>
        <p>The major question for American yoga is how to reconnect God and that big toe.</p>
        <p>The Kripalu conference often felt like a strictly religious gathering, with chanting, meditation, and talks like Mr. Schiffmann's, which extrapolated on basic Eastern ideas of nonduality, and Ms. Gannon's, a discourse on the relationship between ahimsa, the Hindu ethic of nonharming, and animal rights. The last question Mr. Foust asked the gathered teachers, at a closing panel, was, ''Do you believe enlightenment is possible?'' Everyone answered yes.</p>
        <p>Yet the teachers stood united in anti-sectarianism. ''There's more of a cross-pollination of the practices,'' Mr. Abbott said. ''In the Indian tradition, gurus have their yoga and only their yoga. Here, there's good communication among teachers, and the students feel comfortable going from one place to the other. That's very American, I think.''</p>
        <p>Traditionalists may consider the turn away from ashrams and gurus a caveat to the capitalist truism that whatever sells is good. Mr. Friend addressed this accusation in his keynote speech, standing up for eclecticism on the grounds that any spiritual influence is better than none at all. Yet he pointed out that teachers and students both needed to challenge themselves to go deeper.</p>
        <p>''If you wear a deity on your T-shirt or have one in your home, maybe find out what it means,'' Mr. Friend joked, hinting at the proliferation of blue-skinned Krishna prints on today's fashion runways.</p>
        <p>It is still unclear whether most Americans exploring yoga will find a life path or simply an optimal conditioning method. But as the medical establishment continues to accept the mind-body connection, the more room American yogis are finding to develop their plain view of the divine within the hamstrings.</p>
        <p>The next conference to be organized by Yoga Journal, this month, will be aimed at  gym owners and aerobics instructors as part of the World Fitness Convention in San Diego, and cardiovascular flow will undoubtedly get more attention than the lessons of the sacred yoga sutras. Yogis bringing the practice into the secular arena are working hard to make sure its metaphysics do not get lost.</p>
        <p>''I think an American trait is, What's the bottom line?'' Mr. Foust said. ''How can I get the best results the fastest? Through all these techniques you can get these different results. As each tradition presents itself, people can choose.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
