<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Griffey's Homecoming Is Half-Empty</title>
    <meta content="01ARAT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219297"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cincinnati Reds</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Griffey, Ken Jr</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cincinnati Reds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0D7103DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Griffey's Homecoming Is Half-Empty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times column on Cincinnati Reds outfielder Ken Griffey Jr and his desire play for team; discusses Griffey's slow start in 2000; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAYBE you can't go home again, as Ken Griffey Jr. seemed to be saying yesterday, but Barry Larkin was having no second thoughts about staying home after refusing to come play shortstop for the Mets.</p>
        <p>''If they had offered me a multiyear contract, I would have been here,'' Larkin said, still and perhaps forever a Cincinnati Red, before the Mets had their six-game winning streak snapped at soggy Shea Stadium, 6-0. ''But it worked out for me. Yes, it did.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAYBE you can't go home again, as Ken Griffey Jr. seemed to be saying yesterday, but Barry Larkin was having no second thoughts about staying home after refusing to come play shortstop for the Mets.</p>
        <p>''If they had offered me a multiyear contract, I would have been here,'' Larkin said, still and perhaps forever a Cincinnati Red, before the Mets had their six-game winning streak snapped at soggy Shea Stadium, 6-0. ''But it worked out for me. Yes, it did.''</p>
        <p>On the day the major league trade deadline mercifully arrived, sparing paper mills potential inventory depletion from servicing baseball's rumor mill, Larkin arrived to say, hey, no hard feelings, the Mets got Mike Bordick, while he secured the three-year contract extension he'd all but given up on.</p>
        <p>He stayed put, which is all he wanted after a lifetime in Cincinnati and 14 terrific years with the Reds and what's wrong with that? Larkin was still booed all night by those unmistakably sophisticated New York baseball fans, even louder than Griffey, who spurned the Mets without so much as sleeping on it last December. Then Griffey forced Seattle to ship him to the team in whose uniform his father of the same name enjoyed his best days. Junior signed for less money, a mere $116.5 million, than the open market would have paid.</p>
        <p>It was supposed to be a modern-day triumph of homespun values, loyalty over abject greed, at least until Griffey started slowly, the Reds sank under .500 and stuffed their best pitcher, Denny Neagle, into George Steinbrenner's bottomless pocket. Next came the attempted trading of Larkin to the Mets, who wanted to send him a plane full of welcoming teammates, which he called ''flattering,'' but not the point.</p>
        <p>Asked what Griffey had to say during the time it seemed he might be leaving, Larkin said: ''His response was, 'I didn't travel 3,000 miles to come home and play with you for one year.' He told me he was going, too.''</p>
        <p>That sounded like a threat, but Griffey said one place he never went was to the Reds' new owner, Carl Lindner. ''I didn't express that to management,'' he said, though he also insisted: ''I wouldn't have deferred as much money as I did to have someone sell off my teammates. I didn't come here to lose.''</p>
        <p>Quite the contrast to the ebullient Larkin, Griffey seemed so weary in the pregame clubhouse, so dour, you almost hoped it was all an act. No one with his gifts and grace should look that unhappy, feel as unappreciated, wallow in such self-pity, as Griffey appeared to be doing when he stared vacantly and whispered his answers as if he were on death row.</p>
        <p>He began the game with 32 home runs and 91 runs batted in, better power numbers than Mike Piazza's. Yet even after two hits last night, Griffey was hitting only .243, and though the Reds have climbed over .500 and back into the National League Central race, they hadn't exactly been the Seattle Mariners. That's another rub. Junior's old team took the money it saved by not keeping him to hire some pitchers, make itself a more balanced team. The Mariners are in first place without him and, no matter how logical baseball minds avoid casting this as a reflection on him, he is a sensitive soul who tends to see half-empty glasses.</p>
        <p>''Everything that's been said this season has been negative,'' he said. ''If I go 4 for 4 and hit three home runs and didn't hit the fourth one out, it's like I didn't do anything.''</p>
        <p>He doesn't seem to recall the positive responses to his signing with the Reds. He believes the news media have dogged him for eight months, accusing him of everything from signing with the Reds only so his father, a coach, would become manager to calling a cable sports network to complain that another center fielder's highlights were being shown more often than his.</p>
        <p>The best thing about playing baseball in Cincinnati? ''Hanging out with my family,'' he said.</p>
        <p>It sounded heartfelt except he didn't have one good thing to say about playing baseball with the Reds, a small-market team that, under fan fire, dug deep to keep Larkin, its longtime linchpin. Though in all likelihood, not without budgetary consequences.</p>
        <p>Junior had better get used to it. While he said he might have considered the Mets had he not been given 15 minutes to make up his mind, team officials in Seattle have said no such ultimatum was ever delivered. For Larkin, at 35, the proud owner of a 1990 World Series ring, staying put was a storybook ending he had earned. Griffey's another story. If he didn't leave Seattle to lose, he would have been better off flying that Mets plane, with Piazza as his co-pilot.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
