<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>I Can See the Eye Chart Now, and Even the Letters!</title>
    <meta content="01ESSA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Eyes and Eyesight</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Laser (Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyall, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Laser (Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Eyes and Eyesight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E1D7133DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1083" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>I Can See the Eye Chart Now, and Even the Letters!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyall, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sarah Lyall article on Lasik treatment that ended her years of dependence on corrective eyeglasses (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Surgery that would let me give up my glasses forever had always sounded too good to be true, like one of those ads promising that you can earn $10,000 a month by sitting around the house doing nothing. I had been discussing it with my eye doctor for years, and for years, the doctor had told me the technology was not yet advanced enough.</p>
        <p>But he changed his mind because of improvements in the technology. ''We can do it, if you're ready,'' he said last summer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Surgery that would let me give up my glasses forever had always sounded too good to be true, like one of those ads promising that you can earn $10,000 a month by sitting around the house doing nothing. I had been discussing it with my eye doctor for years, and for years, the doctor had told me the technology was not yet advanced enough.</p>
        <p>But he changed his mind because of improvements in the technology. ''We can do it, if you're ready,'' he said last summer.</p>
        <p>I directed my unfiltered gaze to the eye chart on the wall. It was silly to bother. As usual, I couldn't make out any of the letters. In truth, I couldn't even tell that there was an eye chart.</p>
        <p>Yes, I told him, I'm ready.</p>
        <p>Sure, I had my concerns. I worried that it would smell like burning eyeball, or feel as if someone were taking an X-acto knife to Jell-O. I worried that I would go blind, develop a disfiguring infection or have to spend the rest of my life wearing tinted, oversized double-thick aviator glasses.</p>
        <p>There is no question that I was severely nearsighted and a good candidate for Lasik treatment. I'd worn glasses since I was 7 and, according to family legend, failed to see the beautiful wild goat silhouetted against the sunset while we were on vacation in Greece.</p>
        <p>Those first glasses -- bulbous tortoise-shell ones that clashed with my Dorothy Hamill haircut -- were followed by other, equally dismaying ones, and then some years later by contact lenses, which tended to become dry, scratchy and unbearable, forcing me back into the glasses.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, my eyesight kept spiraling downward, finally settling at a miserable -8.5. This is roughly equivalent to having 20-1,600 vision, meaning that what a perfectly sighted person could see from 1,600 feet away, I could see at 20 feet. But I wore my disability, which included considerable astigmatism, with perverse pride, happily using it to explain a number of my most glaring personal failures, including a pathological fear of heights, an inability to remember what people looked like, and a tendency to drive in a way that made my passengers want to take the bus.</p>
        <p>What would happen, I wondered, when I lost the ability to not see?</p>
        <p>It happened last fall, at a laser lab in the gold-encrusted Trump Tower on Fifth Avenue and 57th Street. Fortified with the drugs I'd been prescribed, Valium and Percocet, I took my seat along with a half-dozen other laser patients, all of them men in their mid-30's. They had brought their wives. I brought my mother. We were all dead nervous.</p>
        <p>We swapped stories about lifetimes hobbled by corrective lenses, and then it was my turn. I sat down, surrounded by nurses whose job, it seemed, was to prevent me from running from the room. And then the doctor began, one eye after the other.</p>
        <p>He gave me some numbing drops. And then he clamped my eyelid open to prevent me from blinking, and put a suction ring around my eye. Then he took the microkeratone -- which looks like a mini-version of a butcher's meat-slicing machine -- and moved it across the eye, cutting a tiny flap in the cornea.</p>
        <p>After that, which made everything go dark for about a minute, the actual laser was not that bad. The suction ring was removed, and I could see again. My job was not to flail erratically, not to sob pitiably, and, most frighteningly, not to divert my eye from a light blinking overhead.</p>
        <p>''Whatever you do, DON'T LOOK AWAY,'' my doctor said ominously. I did not smell burning, of fresh eyeball or singed flesh or anything else. And I didn't feel any pain, only a lot of discomfort and a strong desire to shout, ''Get your finger out of my eye!''</p>
        <p>The doctor flooded my eye with liquid, taking what felt like a mini-paintbrush and stroked my eyeball over and over, to get the flap to re-attach itself over the cornea. And then he did the same thing to the other eye.</p>
        <p>It didn't hurt, but by the end, my eyes felt so dry and scratchy that all I wanted to do was close them and crawl away somewhere dark. Which is what I did next, in a dimly lighted communal recovery room along with several patients who had already had the surgery.</p>
        <p>The other patients' wives (and my mother) asked anxiously how we felt. We felt as though someone were blowing sand into our eyes with a straw. But when I left the laser lab, wearing a pair of goggles and an enormous pair of surgical sunglasses, I had enough vanity left to make it clear to those who joined us on the Trump Tower elevator that, No, I had not had a face lift, but an important, medically necessary ocular procedure. (My insurance company didn't think it was medically necessary, of course: it cost $5,000, out of pocket).</p>
        <p>The next few weeks were strange ones, as my eyes healed and I began to realize that, in fact, I could see again in a way that I had never imagined.</p>
        <p>It's a hard feeling to describe, because it's not as if I'd been actually blind before. But I'd always taken my fragile sight to be a precarious commodity, a favor that, having been granted, could easily be snatched away. And then there was the ever-present fear of being caught in a thunderstorm in the middle of the woods, losing my contact lenses, breaking my glasses and starving to death when I could not find my way home.</p>
        <p>Now, I've almost forgotten all those years of gray, all those lenses and inchoate worries. My eyes are better than 20-20: I can see the tiny little line of letters at the bottom of the eye chart, the optional ones. And when I wake up, it's just me facing the world without any distorting layers, with eyes that seem sharper and brighter and more alive than they ever have before.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
