<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Disability Ruling Limits Nets' Maneuverability</title>
    <meta content="01NETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219275"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Jayson</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kittles, Kerry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905EED9103DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Disability Ruling Limits Nets' Maneuverability</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Basketball Assn denies request by New Jersey Nets for disabled player exemptions for Jayson Williams and Kerry Kittles, each worth about $3.8 million; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nets had hoped to have deeper pockets entering today's free-agency signing period. Instead, they have been reduced to counting their loose change.</p>
        <p>The Nets sustained their first loss of the season yesterday when the National Basketball Association did not grant either of two disabled-player exceptions the team had sought, each worth about $3.8 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Nets had hoped to have deeper pockets entering today's free-agency signing period. Instead, they have been reduced to counting their loose change.</p>
        <p>The Nets sustained their first loss of the season yesterday when the National Basketball Association did not grant either of two disabled-player exceptions the team had sought, each worth about $3.8 million.</p>
        <p>The league determined that the Nets missed the deadline to apply for the exception for center Jayson Williams, who retired June 28 because of a career-ending leg injury originally sustained in April 1999. And the league's medical staff disagreed with the Nets' doctors by determining that the shooting guard Kerry Kittles, who had knee surgery in June, could return this season.</p>
        <p>Because of the ruling, the Nets now have only the $2.25 million midlevel exception that is available to teams over the salary cap, as well as the biannual $1.2 million exception, which cannot be combined.</p>
        <p>Without the extra cash, the Nets can most likely forget about signing the shooting guard Ron Mercer, or even a player such as Jon Barry. While they will continue to work toward resigning the veteran Kendall Gill, the Nets will see where the market prices the available second-tier shooting guards and how far the first tier drops within the first week.</p>
        <p>''That's what the process is, and now we're going to have to find out if there's someone out there who can help us,'' Nets President Rod Thorn said. ''We were hoping there was a chance to get either of those exceptions, and it turns out there isn't. But we will not just sign somebody to be signing somebody.''</p>
        <p>The Nets were caught in a no-win situation with both applications. The league determined the team had missed the window to apply for an exception for Williams, who broke his right leg when he collided with point guard Stephon Marbury on April 1, 1999. The Nets held out hope that Williams would return last season, so they did not apply for the exception, which must be filed within six months of an injury, according to the collective bargaining agreement.</p>
        <p>Williams did return for three practices last March, but he broke his foot and his knee swelled inordinately, forcing him to retire on draft night. The Nets applied for his salary exception then.</p>
        <p>While the team will still pay the rest of Williams's four-year, $59.6 million salary, the Nets waived him yesterday, a formality that enables them to erase his salary from the cap next April.</p>
        <p>''Obviously it's an injury that will preclude him from ever playing, and we did it just to clean the slate and get on with what we're doing,'' Thorn said.</p>
        <p>Thorn, formerly the N.B.A.'s senior vice president for basketball operations, pleaded with the league, saying that the Nets would have applied earlier had they known Williams's injury would be career ending.</p>
        <p>With Kittles, the Nets did not want to make the same mistake of missing the window again. ''We believed there was a good chance he would not play this year, and it's not an exact science, as they say,'' Nets General Manager John Nash said. ''We were preceding as if we are going to be without, just based on our experience of a year ago. We recognize that we're going into the season without him and expect to be without him for a significant period and maybe even the whole season.''</p>
        <p>Even if Kittles does return late in the second half of the season, the Nets are without a starting shooting guard and without the money to lure a better one.</p>
        <p>''Chicago is the real player right now,'' Thorn said of the Bulls, a team that is roughly $19 million under the cap. ''If they want a player, they're going to get it. In the case of Mercer, there is a definite possibility that Chicago might have an interest in him.''</p>
        <p>The league rarely approves injury exceptions, especially for orthopedic-related reasons. Two years ago, the league granted the San Antonio Spurs the exception for Sean Elliott, who had a kidney transplant. But he returned last season.</p>
        <p>The N.B.A. declined comment yesterday.</p>
        <p>''The league looks very closely any time there is this sort of exception,'' said Thorn, who added that he would not take any further action. ''They don't want to do something today that would haunt them five years ago.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
