<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Image and Reality on Education</title>
    <meta content="01TUE1$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E4D6103DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Image and Reality on Education</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says Gov George Bush's focus on education as signature issue at Republican National Convention in Philadelphia is wise choice in terms of giving convention softer and more inclusive feel, but also illuminates its central paradox; says same delegates who cheered Bush's vision of providing education especially for poor and disadvantaged, also ratified platform that defines narrower, less generous world in which federal government has virtually no role to play in shaping country's educational future (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first of four theme nights at the Republican Party's meticulously planned national convention focused on what has become George W. Bush's signature issue -- education, particularly education for young, poor children. In terms of giving this convention a softer and more inclusive feel, this was a wise choice. Yet it also illuminated the central paradox of a conclave marking Mr. Bush's emergence as the party's trend-setter. On the one hand, the vast convention hall was positively awash in soaring language and inspiring individual success stories designed to highlight Mr. Bush's signature promise that no child, no matter how disadvantaged, would be left behind. On the other hand, the same delegates who cheered this vision in prime time had earlier ratified a platform that defines a narrower, less generous world in which the federal government has virtually no role to play in shaping the country's educational future.</p>
        <p>This paradox revolves around a fundamental question about Mr. Bush's candidacy, a question he can go a long way toward answering in his acceptance speech Thursday night. Does his noble rhetoric about compassionate conservatism spring from a genuine determination to lead his party toward a more activist role in education, or is it just empty salesmanship? Based on the numbers, the rank-and-file seems willing to be led. In a New York Times survey of delegates to this convention, 26 percent ranked education the No. 1 issue in their states, whereas four years ago the economy was No. 1 for the same number and education received a measly 2 percent. Yet it was not clear whether they were prepared to spend more money on the problem than their leaders in Congress, who for the last eight years have often tried to cut education spending.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first of four theme nights at the Republican Party's meticulously planned national convention focused on what has become George W. Bush's signature issue -- education, particularly education for young, poor children. In terms of giving this convention a softer and more inclusive feel, this was a wise choice. Yet it also illuminated the central paradox of a conclave marking Mr. Bush's emergence as the party's trend-setter. On the one hand, the vast convention hall was positively awash in soaring language and inspiring individual success stories designed to highlight Mr. Bush's signature promise that no child, no matter how disadvantaged, would be left behind. On the other hand, the same delegates who cheered this vision in prime time had earlier ratified a platform that defines a narrower, less generous world in which the federal government has virtually no role to play in shaping the country's educational future.</p>
        <p>This paradox revolves around a fundamental question about Mr. Bush's candidacy, a question he can go a long way toward answering in his acceptance speech Thursday night. Does his noble rhetoric about compassionate conservatism spring from a genuine determination to lead his party toward a more activist role in education, or is it just empty salesmanship? Based on the numbers, the rank-and-file seems willing to be led. In a New York Times survey of delegates to this convention, 26 percent ranked education the No. 1 issue in their states, whereas four years ago the economy was No. 1 for the same number and education received a measly 2 percent. Yet it was not clear whether they were prepared to spend more money on the problem than their leaders in Congress, who for the last eight years have often tried to cut education spending.</p>
        <p>True to Mr. Bush's desire to convey optimism on even the most difficult issues, last night's menu of speeches and visuals was relentlessly upbeat and demographically inclusive -- a fourth-grade teacher from North Carolina discussing math and science, a video from a largely Hispanic school in El Paso, brief testimonials to the virtues of parental involvement and after-school enrichment, and a speech by his wife, Laura, about her experience as a teacher and their joint commitment to education. The evening was topped off by an inspirational testimonial to racial fairness and educational opportunity from probably the most popular Republican in America, Gen. Colin Powell.</p>
        <p>The reality of the platform was quite different. At Governor Bush's insistence, the committee dropped a harsh and longstanding provision calling for the abolition of the Department of Education. The document also quoted lofty pledges that under a Bush presidency no American child would be ''segregated by low expectations, imprisoned by illiteracy, abandoned to frustration and the darkness of self-doubt.'' Yet when the document turned to substance, it pointed in a direction opposite to that proclaimed in Mr. Bush's oratory. The platform insisted that ''the role of the federal government must be progressively limited as we return control to parents, teachers and local school boards.'' The  platform then goes on to extol remedies like those celebrated in last night's displays -- charter schools, parental involvement and the like -- while writing off Title I, the main federal program aimed at disadvantaged children, as a $120 billion failure.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush is the only person in Philadelphia who can fix this disconnect. This is a nation in which a lot of children are in trouble -- 11 million with no health insurance and nearly 13 million, one in five, living in poverty, untouched by the present prosperity. Head Start could handle a million more eligible children with more generous financing. It may be too much to expect Mr. Bush to redesign his proposed $1.3 trillion in tax cuts in order to pay for these and similarly worthy ventures. But even those who no longer doubt the sincerity of his belief that no child should be left behind have a perfect right to ask him how he means to balance the scales.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
