<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees Stay in Dugout At the Trading Deadline</title>
    <meta content="01YANK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219265"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Texas Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFDA103DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1075" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees Stay in Dugout At the Trading Deadline</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees discuss ultimately passing on all of trade options they discussed before yesterday's deadline; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the Yankees ultimately passed on all of the trade options they discussed before yesterday's deadline, their general manager compared the decisions to surfing: sometimes you go with the wave, Brian Cashman said, and sometimes you don't.</p>
        <p>What Cashman and the other Yankees executives determined is that the big waves they have ridden in the past five weeks -- the trades for the slugger David Justice, pitcher Denny Neagle, outfielder Glenallen Hill and infielder Jose Vizcaino -- have improved the team to the point where they did not absolutely have to make a trade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After the Yankees ultimately passed on all of the trade options they discussed before yesterday's deadline, their general manager compared the decisions to surfing: sometimes you go with the wave, Brian Cashman said, and sometimes you don't.</p>
        <p>What Cashman and the other Yankees executives determined is that the big waves they have ridden in the past five weeks -- the trades for the slugger David Justice, pitcher Denny Neagle, outfielder Glenallen Hill and infielder Jose Vizcaino -- have improved the team to the point where they did not absolutely have to make a trade.</p>
        <p>Sure, they considered proposals for outfielders B. J. Surhoff, Rondell White, Jeromy Burnitz and pitchers Matt Clement and Pedro Astacio. Each of those players would probably have improved the team. But either the cost for those players was too high -- especially since the first-place Yankees harvested some of their best prospects for the earlier trades -- or the risk was too great.</p>
        <p>''I'm comfortable that we pursued things vigorously,'' Cashman said, ''and I'm comfortable with the team that we have.''</p>
        <p>Now waivers will greatly complicate any effort to make trades, and although there is a chance the Yankees can make an incremental deal before the end of the regular season, they will probably have to rely on players in their farm system.</p>
        <p>Justice is probably going to have to play more in left field than the Yankees would like. He is adept defensively, but the team would prefer that he be used primarily as a designated hitter, to save him the wear and tear. Justice will play left field against many left-handed starting pitchers, with Hill in the role of designated hitter. When the Yankees face right-handed starters, Justice could be in left, with Chuck Knoblauch as the D.H. and Vizcaino at second. Sometimes, Ryan Thompson will play left, with Justice at D.H.</p>
        <p>If the Yankees need an upgrade in pitching, it will probably have to come from Orlando Hernandez and Allen Watson, both working their way back from injuries, or from David Cone, whose next chance to reverse his stunning decline will come Saturday against the Seattle Mariners.</p>
        <p>Adrian Hernandez, a Cuban defector who signed with the Yankees earlier this summer, has moved quickly through the minor leagues, and there is a chance he could be a factor before the end of the season. The top infield prospect, Alfonso Soriano, is remarkably still in the organization after being included in dozens of trade proposals in recent months, and there is no telling if he may somehow develop a role with the team.</p>
        <p>The Yankees could have traded Soriano and others to San Diego for Clement and outfielder Eric Owens, but club officials were not sure exactly how good Clement would be. There were questions about whether his erratic control is a chronic problem, or why the Padres would be willing to trade a highly touted, homegrown pitcher.</p>
        <p>The Yankees might have pieced together a deal for Astacio, but the cost was going to be steep -- Soriano and perhaps pitcher Ramiro Mendoza -- and Astacio would have had the right to demand a trade after the season.</p>
        <p>The Yankees wanted Surhoff, and were in the process of sorting through a three-team blockbuster deal Sunday that would have netted Surhoff and Clement. But the Orioles, who had rejected many proposals from the Yankees for Surhoff, backed out, wanting to deal with the Yankees directly.</p>
        <p>The Yankees were under the impression that they could count on a trade for outfielder Chad Curtis, at the least. But Texas executives changed their minds Sunday, wary of the impression that they were conceding the division race. The Rangers had lost catcher Ivan Rodriguez to injury and had traded first baseman David Segui.</p>
        <p>''We proposed a lot of interesting things, and had a lot of interesting things proposed to us, and ultimately we didn't do anything,'' Cashman said.</p>
        <p>Now that the deadline has passed, a trade can be made only under two circumstances. First, a player can be traded if he clears waivers, meaning that 29 teams could conceivably block proposed deals by merely agreeing to pay a minimal waiver fee and assume the remainder of the player's contract. Second, a trade can be worked out with a team that is awarded a waiver claim.</p>
        <p>Hypothetically, if the Yankees wanted to trade shortstop Derek Jeter for Cincinnati center fielder Ken Griffey Jr., both players would have to clear waivers without any other team making a claim. Or the trade could be made if the Yankees were awarded a waiver claim to Griffey and the Reds to Jeter. It used to be that general managers allowed the coveted players of other teams -- even those belonging to division rivals -- to pass through waivers unclaimed, a kind of gentlemen's agreement.</p>
        <p>But in recent years, some of the younger general managers began ignoring that practice. Mets General Manager Steve Phillips and Cashman have been two of the most aggressive at making waiver claims in anticipation of possible moves made by rivals. If the Rangers try to pass closer John Wetteland through waivers, then Phillips and Cashman will most likely make claims. Phillips might do so because of Atlanta's recurring need for relief help, and Cashman because any number of American League contenders could use Wetteland.</p>
        <p>Many players will clear waivers, including high-salaried players like Albert Belle, whose contract would scare away potential suitors, along with mediocre or subpar players. Given Curtis's salary, $2 million for next year, and the fact that the Rangers are loaded with outfielders, there is a chance Curtis can get through waivers and be available in a deal.</p>
        <p>The Yankees will continue to look for a left fielder. Corner outfielders tend to get through waivers far more easily than front-line pitchers, so the Yankees could make a trade before the postseason.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
