<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrat's Exit a Relief for New Jersey Republicans</title>
    <meta content="01JERS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219264"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torricelli, Robert G (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE1DA103DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="695" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrat's Exit a Relief for New Jersey Republicans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <dateline>CHERRY HILL, N.J., July 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Republicans attending national convention in Philadelphia discuss Senator Robert G Torricelli's sudden withdrawal from Democratic race for governor (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Jersey Republicans attending the national convention in Philadelphia today were so stunned by Senator Robert G. Torricelli's sudden withdrawal from the Democratic race for governor that they seemed not to know whether to celebrate or lament his exit.</p>
        <p>''Going to Mass yesterday morning really helped,'' joked Donald T. DiFrancesco, the president of the State Senate and a contender for the Republican gubernatorial nomination, who had widely been seen as the underdog in a contest with Mr. Torricelli.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New Jersey Republicans attending the national convention in Philadelphia today were so stunned by Senator Robert G. Torricelli's sudden withdrawal from the Democratic race for governor that they seemed not to know whether to celebrate or lament his exit.</p>
        <p>''Going to Mass yesterday morning really helped,'' joked Donald T. DiFrancesco, the president of the State Senate and a contender for the Republican gubernatorial nomination, who had widely been seen as the underdog in a contest with Mr. Torricelli.</p>
        <p>But Mr. DiFrancesco quickly added that James E. McGreevey, the Democrat whose endorsement today by the mayor of Newark, Sharpe James, and other officials prompted Mr. Torricelli to bow out, could prove no less formidable an opponent. ''He's a tough candidate,'' Mr. DiFrancesco said. ''He almost beat Christie Whitman, he's been campaigning every day for four years -- he says that openly -- he's got labor support, he's got African-American support, he's got cities, he's got Sharpe James.</p>
        <p>''Democrats rallying around Jim McGreevey is not good for Republicans,'' he added. ''I'd rather see them fighting -- fisticuffs, punching, scream, bite, yell, curse.''</p>
        <p>If Mr. Torricelli's monthlong candidacy had divided New Jersey Democrats, it had distracted Republicans as well, overshadowing Representative Robert D. Franks's uphill run for the United States Senate and giving party leaders reason to think twice about their field of potential gubernatorial candidates for next year's election.</p>
        <p>Besides Mr. DiFrancesco, of Union County, the leading Republican contenders are Jack Collins, the Assembly speaker, who is from rural Salem County at the southern end of the state, and Bret D. Schundler, the mayor of Jersey City. None has the statewide name recognition that Mr. Torricelli enjoys.</p>
        <p>Until today, some Republicans were even promoting the idea of enticing former Gov. Thomas H. Kean to make another run -- a notion Mr. Kean did nothing to discourage -- as if only a popular former governor had the electoral heft to trump a Torricelli candidacy.</p>
        <p>''There did seem to be that juggernaut feeling coming at people,'' said Robert Stears, a Republican lobbyist attending a fund-raiser tonight in Camden.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks, the fund-raiser's beneficiary, said, ''The 800-pound gorilla is back in his cage.''</p>
        <p>He had his own reasons to exult, of course. With little chance of matching the advertising budget of his Democratic opponent in the Senate race, the multimillionaire Jon S. Corzine, Mr. Franks is almost wholly dependent on journalists for publicity, and the Senate race was essentially ignored during the commotion surrounding the Torricelli-McGreevey matchup.</p>
        <p>''I'm delighted that the New Jersey media will now be available to spend more time with the Senate campaign,'' Mr. Franks said.</p>
        <p>Other Republicans suggested that while Mr. Torricelli's departure would cement Mr. McGreevey's status as the presumptive nominee, it would also deepen the fissures among New Jersey Democrats. They noted that the rebellious faction of South Jersey Democrats led by George E. Norcross III of Camden County had promoted Mr. Torricelli's gubernatorial bid to compete with Mr. McGreevey's supporters in the central and northern parts of the state.</p>
        <p>''Torricelli's pulling out only makes the rift even worse,'' said Gregg Edwards, Mr. DiFrancesco's top aide in the Senate. ''Some of these folks, particularly George Norcross, will be very bitter people. They'll just look for one more fight to get into.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Collins, the Assembly speaker, emerged today from his hotel room here, where the New Jersey Republican delegation is staying, and broke into a broad smile when he was told that Mr. Torricelli had quit the race without endorsing Mr. McGreevey.</p>
        <p>''He's the man who will be the senior senator from New Jersey, and the assumed leader of the Democratic Party, and he's not for Jim McGreevey?'' Mr. Collins said. ''How can anything be better for Republicans?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
