<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Company Seeking Donors Of DNA for a 'Gene Trust'</title>
    <meta content="01DNA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219281"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deoxyribonucleic Acid</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dna Sciences (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Watson, James D (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, James H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D8103DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Company Seeking Donors Of DNA for a 'Gene Trust'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>DNA Sciences, California start-up company, is introducing Web site to recruit people to donate their DNA to help find genes that cause disease; company, which has DNA double helix discoverer James D Watson as director and Netscape founder James H Clark as investor, hopes to get 50,000 to 100,000 people to contribute to its 'gene trust' by appealing to their altruism; new effort underscores change taking place in genetics; studies to link genes to disease are beginning to be done on unparalleled scale, involving far more people than ever before; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wanted: your genes.</p>
        <p>A California start-up called DNA Sciences is introducing a Web site today that will recruit people to donate their DNA to help find genes that cause disease. The company, which has James D. Watson, a discoverer of the DNA double helix, as a director and James H. Clark, Netscape's founder, as an investor, hopes to get 50,000 to 100,000 people to contribute to its ''gene trust'' by appealing to their altruism.</p>
        <p>''The knowledge we gain from the gene trust has the potential to change medicine forever,'' the site, DNA.com, intones. ''But we can't do it without your help.''</p>
        <p>The new effort reflects a big change taking place in genetics. Studies to link genes to disease are starting to be done on an unparalleled scale, involving far more people than ever before.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wanted: your genes.</p>
        <p>A California start-up called DNA Sciences is introducing a Web site today that will recruit people to donate their DNA to help find genes that cause disease. The company, which has James D. Watson, a discoverer of the DNA double helix, as a director and James H. Clark, Netscape's founder, as an investor, hopes to get 50,000 to 100,000 people to contribute to its ''gene trust'' by appealing to their altruism.</p>
        <p>''The knowledge we gain from the gene trust has the potential to change medicine forever,'' the site, DNA.com, intones. ''But we can't do it without your help.''</p>
        <p>The new effort reflects a big change taking place in genetics. Studies to link genes to disease are starting to be done on an unparalleled scale, involving far more people than ever before.</p>
        <p>While such studies promise to lead to big medical advances, the collection of genetic data on such a wide scale is also raising ethical and privacy issues, particularly that genetic information -- if not kept confidential -- could be used to deny people or their family members insurance or employment.</p>
        <p>''It is essentially being developed and hitting the spotlight without a sense of rules, ethics and social norms,'' said Janlori Goldman, director of the health privacy project at Georgetown University.</p>
        <p>With the recent unraveling of the human genome, scientists are cataloging hundreds of thousands of differences in the genetic makeup of different individuals.</p>
        <p>Figuring out which genes contribute to disease could help in developing drugs. In the future people might have their genes tested to know if they are susceptible to certain diseases. And instead of the current practice of one drug fits all, patients might have their genes tested to see which drug would work best for them, a field known as pharmacogenetics.</p>
        <p>But to get to that point, scientists must first determine which of hundreds of thousands of genetic variations contribute to which disease or to the effectiveness of a particular drug. And that will require ''disease association studies'' -- surveying many people to find statistical correlations.</p>
        <p>In the past, scientists usually found disease-causing genes by studying a few families or some isolated village with a high prevalence of a disease. Such genes have often been for rare inherited diseases, in which a defect in a single gene is at fault.</p>
        <p>But that technique is becoming less effective, said Neil J. Risch, professor of genetics at Stanford University. The diseases of most interest to drug companies and the public health, he said, are common ones like cancer, heart disease, diabetes, Alzheimer's and schizophrenia. It is believed many genes contribute to such diseases, with each one having a small effect. To find these genes, hundreds or thousands of patients might be needed.</p>
        <p>''This is not going to happen in some esoteric studies with a couple of families here and there,'' said Mihael Polymeropoulos, a vice president of Novartis, the Swiss drug company. ''We're going to need lots of people.''</p>
        <p>Just how many will be needed is a matter of debate. Some skeptics say the statistical links might be too weak to ever detect. ''It's a blind leap of faith that this approach is going to work at all,'' said Joseph D. Terwilliger, an assistant professor at Columbia University's genome center.</p>
        <p>Others say that even if the technique works in some situations, knowing the gene is often not enough to develop a drug. ''You're asking why someone gets a disease, not what to do about it,'' said William A. Haseltine, chief executive of Human Genome Sciences, who said there were many cases, like cystic fibrosis, in which the gene has long been known but there is still no good treatment.</p>
        <p>Yet Glaxo Wellcome says it has already found genes associated with migraines, psoriasis, diabetes and Parkinson's disease. Genset, a French company specializing in studies on diverse populations, says it has found genes linked to prostate cancer and schizophrenia.</p>
        <p>DNA Sciences, based in Mountain View, Calif. is just one of the companies springing up to try to gather patients and do studies. Two companies had initial public stock offerings in the last two weeks: deCODE Genetics, which is making a database using medical records and DNA samples from most of Iceland's 275,000 people, and Gemini Genomics, a British company that has DNA samples and extensive medical records from thousands of pairs of twins.</p>
        <p>Another company, Framingham Genomic Medicine, was formed in June by Boston University and venture capitalists to analyze data from a project that has collected data and DNA samples from thousands of people in Framingham, Mass.</p>
        <p>The Baltic nation of Estonia is also looking to set up a genetic database of nearly all its 1.4 million citizens.</p>
        <p>Genomics Collaborative, a private company in Cambridge, Mass., has a network of 250 doctors with the goal of getting as many as a million patients. It just signed an agreement with Ameripath, which performs pathology services for 170 hospitals and analyzes nearly three million biopsies a year. Under the agreement, hundreds of thousands of those tissue samples will go into a tissue bank for genetic studies.</p>
        <p>The companies all say they obtain the informed consent of patients to have their DNA used and operate under the purview of institutional review boards or ethics committees. They also say they ''anonymize'' the data, so it cannot be linked to a particular person.</p>
        <p>But critics say hackers could gain access to the identity of patients stored in computers. They say assurances that data will not be sold to others, like insurance companies, are not ironclad. Questions have already arisen about the ethics of getting private profit from the Framingham data, which was collected in a federally financed project. And deCODE's activities in Iceland have also provoked a controversy about privacy.</p>
        <p>Kari Stefansson, chief executive of deCODE, argues that privacy advocates are retarding progress. ''It is considered by some a right to deny science the ability to use information about us to help future generations,'' he said at a public forum on medical privacy in Washington recently.</p>
        <p>He and others involved in such companies say many people are happy to help search for cures for diseases from which they or their descendants might suffer.</p>
        <p>''This is the first opportunity for Six-Pack Joe in the heartland who has diabetes to participate in a study,'' said Hugh Y. Rienhoff Jr., a physician and former venture capitalist who heads DNA Sciences.</p>
        <p>Under DNA Sciences' program, volunteers answer on-line questionnaires about their medical history, and their family's. The company will then send someone to their homes or offices to collect blood samples. Healtheon/WebMD, the medical Web site, owns a stake in DNA Sciences and will be used to help recruit patients.</p>
        <p>Donors will not be paid, as is true with the other companies as well. There have been controversies in which doctors or companies have profited from developing a diagnostic test or cell line from a patient's tissue without compensating the patient. But in this case, the companies say, huge statistical studies are being done in which the contribution of any one patient is insignificant. Dr. Rienhoff said that if the company developed any diagnostic tests for diseases, the volunteers would be given the tests free.</p>
        <p>Experts see two potential problems with DNA Sciences' approach. One is that volunteers' description of their medical histories might not be accurate. ''There's garbage in and garbage out,'' said Jonathan M. Rothberg, chairman and chief executive of Curagen, a company looking for disease genes. He said the company used data from Gemini Genomics because the twins in the Gemini database had undergone hours of standardized medical tests.</p>
        <p>The second problem is that the people recruited by DNA Sciences might be too heterogeneous. Although large numbers are needed, there is still some advantage to relatively homogeneous populations like Iceland's.</p>
        <p>But DNA Sciences and some others say that a broader population is better. ''That gene might be great for Iceland but it's not the gene for New York City, and we sell far more drugs in New York City than Iceland,'' said Allen D. Roses, worldwide director of genetics for Glaxo Wellcome.</p>
        <p>DNA Sciences and most other companies want to find some disease genes themselves. Merely providing patients for others might not be a great business because some academic scientists studying particular diseases already have large collections of patients and samples. And some drug companies will do it themselves.</p>
        <p>Glaxo Wellcome enlists about 10 academic scientists per disease to recruit several hundred families for each study, Dr. Roses said. The company is spending $22 million a year on this, because it pays the scientists' institutions, which will also be entitled to royalties from any drugs that result.</p>
        <p>Novartis intends to get patients from its clinical trials, since those patients have the disease and well-documented medical records, Dr. Polymeropoulos said. Novartis intends to get controls -- the DNA of people who do not have the disease -- from blood banks, which have thousands of anonymous samples.</p>
        <p>Besides recruiting patients, the biggest obstacle to the studies is cost. It costs about $1 to test one patient for one variation of a single letter in the genetic code. Scientists have already found hundreds of thousands of variations, known as single nucleotide polymorphisms, or SNP's (pronounced ''snips''). Testing 100,000 SNP's in 1,000 patients would cost a prohibitive $100 million.</p>
        <p>But companies like Orchid Biosciences of Princeton, N.J.; Sequenom of San Diego; and Third Wave Technologies of Madison, Wis., are developing techniques for high-speed SNP testing that experts hope will bring the cost down sharply in a couple of years.</p>
        <p>One of the first big disease association studies will take place in Japan. Third Wave and PE Biosystems, a genomics equipment company, just won an $80 million contract to jointly develop tests for 150,000 SNP's for a Japanese government project. About 800 people will be tested for all 150,000 SNP's, said Yusuke Nakamura, director of the Human Genome Center at the University of Tokyo.</p>
        <p>How many SNP's must be tested on how many people depends on how homogeneous the population being studied is, how many genes contribute to a particular disease, how frequent a particular genetic variation is, and how strong the effect of a particular gene is. Scientists do not have all the answers yet.</p>
        <p>If a particular variation is found in 10 to 50 percent of people and doubles the chance of getting a disease, then several thousand patients would have to be tested to find this variation, said Leonid Kruglyak, a geneticist at the Fred Hutchison Cancer Research Center in Seattle. If a variation increases the risk of disease fivefold or tenfold, far fewer patients would be needed, but Dr. Kruglyak said he doubted there were many such variations. ''If there are tenfold or fivefold effects out there we probably would have found them by now,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Glaxo and others say they can effectively narrow the search. Millennium Pharmaceuticals, for instance, uses biological knowledge and other techniques to first estimate what genes are likely to be involved in a disease. It then studies only the 1,000 or so SNP's in those genes, allowing it to get by with fewer than 100 patients, said Michael G. Kauffman, vice president for medicine of Millennium Predictive Medicine.</p>
        <p>Curagen is also limiting its search to particular SNP's, Dr. Rothberg said. ''The bottom line is you just do it, and that gets rid of the cynics,'' he added.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
