<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tale of Bad Timing at AMF: Silk Stockings and Bowling Shows</title>
    <meta content="Y01PLA$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET PLACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bowling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Amf Bowling Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Goldman Sachs Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bowling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EED7103DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1299" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tale of Bad Timing at AMF: Silk Stockings and Bowling Shows</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>AMF Bowling has racked up losses and its stock price has sunk since Goldman, Sachs led buyout in 1996; directors reportedly weigh range of revamping options, including prepackaged bankruptcy; company has been hurt by drop in popularity of league bowling, lifeblood of bowling business; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Goldman, Sachs led a buyout of AMF Bowling in 1996, some analysts wondered why a silk-stocking investment bank would risk sullying its image in such a pedestrian pursuit. But, after four years under Goldman's control, it is AMF's image that has suffered as the company has racked up losses and its stock price has sunk to 75 cents a share.</p>
        <p>Having traded for less than $1 a share for more than 30 consecutive days, AMF -- arguably the biggest name in bowling -- is in danger of being delisted from the New York Stock Exchange and investors are wondering if the company will have to sort out its financial troubles in bankruptcy court. People close to the company, which is based in Richmond, Va., said that AMF's board discussed a range of revamping options, including a prepackaged bankruptcy filing, last week in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Goldman, Sachs led a buyout of AMF Bowling in 1996, some analysts wondered why a silk-stocking investment bank would risk sullying its image in such a pedestrian pursuit. But, after four years under Goldman's control, it is AMF's image that has suffered as the company has racked up losses and its stock price has sunk to 75 cents a share.</p>
        <p>Having traded for less than $1 a share for more than 30 consecutive days, AMF -- arguably the biggest name in bowling -- is in danger of being delisted from the New York Stock Exchange and investors are wondering if the company will have to sort out its financial troubles in bankruptcy court. People close to the company, which is based in Richmond, Va., said that AMF's board discussed a range of revamping options, including a prepackaged bankruptcy filing, last week in New York.</p>
        <p>AMF is saddled with about $1.2 billion in debt. Its bonds have been trading for 20 percent to 30 percent of their face value.</p>
        <p>When the company releases its second-quarter earnings within the next two weeks, those investors who still are paying attention will focus less on what happened in the traditionally slower spring season than on what the company has to say about its future plans. After all, the earnings cannot surprise analysts because nobody on Wall Street follows AMF's stock any more.</p>
        <p>Ronald Baron, chief executive of Baron Capital, once was one of AMF's biggest boosters, predicting that the stock price would soar to $100 by 2003. Now, with his company and its mutual funds holding more than 11 million shares of AMF, Mr. Baron will not discuss AMF. Through a spokesman, he denied that his funds, the biggest investor in the company after Goldman, were among the sellers when AMF shares dropped to a record low of 18.75 cents on June 30.</p>
        <p>Stephen E. Hare, AMF's chief financial officer, said in an interview that ''the capital structure needs to be fixed'' but the company has not settled on a solution. He declined to discuss the possibility of a voluntary bankruptcy filing and said that the company had not started negotiating with its creditors. But it is clear that changes must be made before AMF has to start making much bigger payments to bondholders in about a year.</p>
        <p>''The meter is running,'' Mr. Hare said ''It's fair for the markets to say, 'Show us the plan.' When we have a plan that we're comfortable with, you'll see us announce it.''</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Mr. Hare acknowledged, the company, its industry and its employees are all suffering. ''Just the fact that the stock has not been successful in the last year, I don't think speaks well for the industry,'' he said, ''We feel a certain obligation to be successful for the industry at large.''</p>
        <p>Goldman officials declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hare said that company officials have talked to representatives of the New York Stock Exchange about how to get back into compliance with the exchange's listing standards. AMF has less than 30 days to come up with a plan. One possibility: a reverse stock split that would reduce the number of shares outstanding to push up their price and buy management more time to realign the company.</p>
        <p>How AMF, under Goldman's control, got into such a bind is a complicated story that involves Asian economics, American social trends and the ways of Wall Street.</p>
        <p>In 1996, Goldman led a leveraged buyout of AMF. A year later, the firm took the company public again, raising $263 million by selling shares for $19.50 each.</p>
        <p>The pitch for the 1997 initial offering was that AMF would buy bowling alleys around the United States and would capitalize on a growing craze for bowling in China and other parts of Asia. AMF would make money two ways: by operating a chain of bowling centers and by selling the equipment to outfit new ones overseas.</p>
        <p>But while AMF was gobbling up alleys and trying to run them more efficiently, league bowling -- the lifeblood of the bowling business -- was dying. Leagues, which represent a predictable stream of revenue from September through March, once accounted for as much as 80 percent of a bowling center's business, said Sandy Hansell, a bowling consultant in Southfield, Mich. That share has dropped to about 50 percent, he said.</p>
        <p>Then in the summer of 1998, an economic crisis swept across Asia, wiping out demand for capital-intensive leisure activities like bowling.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, Goldman was the majority owner of a heavily indebted company in a slow-growth business. The bowling products business, which had generated about $70 million in cash flow in 1997, produced less than $10 million in cash flow last year, Mr. Hare said. He said demand for bowling is still growing in some countries, including England, but ''what we don't see right now are any markets that have that boom potential.''</p>
        <p>AMF's board -- which has Richard A. Friedman, who runs Goldman's merchant-banking operations, as chairman -- removed the company's management. Last year, the directors hired Roland Smith, who formerly ran the Arby's fast-food chain, as chief executive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith is slowing the pace of acquisitions while the company devises a strategy for marketing its 417 United States bowling centers as a national chain, Mr. Hare said. The company is spending about $10 million to gear all of its centers for what it calls Xtreme bowling, a nighttime activity aimed at teenagers and other recreational bowlers, and is considering an extensive ad campaign, he said.</p>
        <p>Without a big increase in revenue, the bowling centers are quite profitable on an operating basis, Mr. Hansell, the consultant, said. And, despite its slower growth, the bowling business is healthy, with most lane operators making more money than they ever have, he said.</p>
        <p>The tough question for AMF and Goldman is how they can relieve the company of some of its debt burden before it snuffs the life out of bowling-center operations. It is a rare problem for Mr. Friedman and Goldman's other merchant bankers, who have rolled their share of strikes, most recently in having a big stake in VoiceStream Wireless when Deutsche Telekom agreed to buy that company for a huge premium.</p>
        <p>In May 1996, Goldman and its merchant-banking funds put up $260 million for a majority stake in the buyout of AMF. Two other investment banks, Blackstone Group and Kelso &amp; Company, bought smaller stakes, and the company borrowed about $1 billion through bank loans and bond sales.</p>
        <p>Along the way, Goldman received about $50 million in fees for advising the company and underwriting securities, including its initial public offering of stock. Now its 45 million shares are worth less than that, about $34 million. Goldman officials will not say how much the firm has lost on its AMF investment, but a person close to the matter said the firm is feeling ''a lot of pain.''</p>
        <p>No matter what happens to AMF, Mr. Hansell said, the bowling business will survive.</p>
        <p>''If AMF went belly up, would it be a problem?'' he said. ''It would hurt, but it wouldn't be cataclysmic. The other 5,000 bowling centers in this country would roll along.''</p>
        <p>MARKET PLACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
