<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Convention's Magic Hour Stays Tuned to Major Networks</title>
    <meta content="Y01STA$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: THE TV COVERAGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cable News Network</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E5DF113DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1098" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Convention's Magic Hour Stays Tuned to Major Networks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, July 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coverage of opening night of Republican National Convention in Philadelphia by major television networks appraised; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jeff Zucker, the executive producer of convention coverage for NBC News, wanted a live interview tonight from the First Union Center with one of the event's most sought-after guests: George P. Bush, the telegenic 23-year-old nephew of the Texas governor.</p>
        <p>But to the dismay of NBC officials, the Republicans turned down the request, and not because young Mr. Bush is camera-shy. No, Mr. Zucker contended, NBC was spurned because it was covering the proceedings in prime time tonight only on its cable channel, MSNBC, which garners substantially lower ratings than the broadcast network.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jeff Zucker, the executive producer of convention coverage for NBC News, wanted a live interview tonight from the First Union Center with one of the event's most sought-after guests: George P. Bush, the telegenic 23-year-old nephew of the Texas governor.</p>
        <p>But to the dismay of NBC officials, the Republicans turned down the request, and not because young Mr. Bush is camera-shy. No, Mr. Zucker contended, NBC was spurned because it was covering the proceedings in prime time tonight only on its cable channel, MSNBC, which garners substantially lower ratings than the broadcast network.</p>
        <p>The fact that ABC News was to provide a full hour and CBS News about 30 minutes of prime-time coverage starting at 10 tonight knocked NBC down a few notches in the pecking order, Mr. Zucker said. ''It's a game,'' he observed. ''They have divvied out guests accordingly.''</p>
        <p>Later in the day, after a reporter inquired about Mr. Zucker's complaint, the Republicans informed NBC that they could have the young man on the air, and spokesmen for both NBC and the convention sought to play down the episode. But the incident was instructive about a reality of the media hierarchy here: cable television may provide more coverage, but the broadcast networks are still the kings.</p>
        <p>That truism is reflected in the way the convention program is structured. Virtually all the major speeches this week, from those of Laura Bush and Gen. Colin L. Powell tonight and continuing with Senator John McCain and Elizabeth Dole on Tuesday, the vice-presidential nominee, Dick Cheney, on Wednesday, and Gov. George W. Bush on Thursday, are to take place between 10 p.m. and 11 p.m. That just happens to be the hour each night that one or more of the over-the-air networks will be covering the Philadelphia proceedings live.</p>
        <p>''Everything is geared for the 10 to 11 o'clock hour,'' said Tom Hannon, the political director of CNN. ''They're obsessed about getting their message across in the 10 to 11 hour, and that is their driving concern. People say that the conventions are for cable, but as far as the parties are concerned, the conventions are for the most eyeballs they can get.''</p>
        <p>Tonight, the Republicans got those eyeballs, at least on ABC, but not exactly the program they had concocted. Like clockwork, the preseason football game -- begun an hour early to accommodate the convention coverage -- ended a few minutes before 10 p.m., paving the way for Peter Jennings to introduce several minutes of highlights before seguing about a third of the way into a speech by Laura Bush. CBS broke into its ''48 Hours'' program early with an update and returned at 10:30 to cover the final half-hour.</p>
        <p>Viewers of ABC got a taste of what cable and PBS broadcast all night: an unusual showcase for multiculturalism. It was certainly the ''different'' sort of Republican evening the planners promised: videos of Gospel choirs and vignettes of inner-city school students, who were used at times to underline the Bush campaign's promises of a more inclusive kind of Republicanism and to reinvigorate education reform.</p>
        <p>Governor and Mrs. Bush -- the  former appearing by satellite from a classroom in Westerville, Ohio -- both spoke with backdrops consisting of children seated at desks. For Mrs. Bush's remarks, ABC even spliced in footage from a graduation ceremony in Crawford, Tex., that the Bushes had attended.</p>
        <p>The conflicting aims of the parties and the networks have led to an odd  standoff: as the conventions become ever more scripted and ever less newsworthy in the strictest journalistic sense, the networks become ever less interested in covering them. Yet the conventions vie for the network cameras as vigorously as ever, and the networks still show up in vast numbers, but with scaled-back prime-time coverage plans. As for the needs of the print media, well, that institution does not come up much in conversations with convention planners.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zucker seemed a bit underwhelmed at the prospect of supplying four nights of coverage, principally on MSNBC, the network's cable channel. NBC will also cover the proceedings on its flagship channel on Wednesday and Thursday nights.</p>
        <p>At a meeting this afternoon in an air-conditioned trailer, Mr. Zucker and Elizabeth O'Connell, the news executive producer of special events, gave out assignments for the night of cable coverage.</p>
        <p>Reporters were to fan out and report on the conservative bent of the delegates, and try to score interviews with more coveted Republican luminaries. (George P. is widely considered a significant ''get,'' as is former President Bush, who spoke exclusively to Maria Shriver on MSNBC about 10 p.m.)</p>
        <p>Still, the event does not exactly enthrall Mr. Zucker. ''I'm not sure it's not a colossal waste of time and money,'' he said after the meeting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zucker is not a lone voice. Many in the news business, both in print and broadcast, mutter to one another about the gargantuan size of the press corps here -- 15,000 plus, or more than seven for every delegate -- and the puniness of the story.</p>
        <p>''Great drama and great TV and great journalism are built on conflict,'' Mr. Zucker said.</p>
        <p>In fact, the news vacuum is already something of a joke among reporters. On Sunday, Sam Donaldson of ABC News came bounding into a work station in one of the media pavilions here and breathlessly exclaimed, ''It's Cheney!''</p>
        <p>The Republicans seem unfazed about the lack of drama. Their big worry is to keep up the pace and make sure they exploit the television moment. On the convention floor today, Ed Gillespie, a Bush adviser who had been working on the convention for six weeks, was preoccupied with the endless logistics. Between cell phone calls placed to find one of the evening program's participants, he explained that the schedule was merely the most rational use of time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hannon said that the convention organizers''are in the business of knowing who their audience is,''  even if their focus on packaging may be overblown. ''Bob Dole lost in '96,'' he added, ''but they still think they had a great convention.''</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: THE TV COVERAGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
