<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Big City; Paper Profits That Failed To Materialize</title>
    <meta content="01BIG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219270"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newsprint</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tierney, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershkowitz, Allen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/John Tierney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E1D9103DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="789" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Big City; Paper Profits That Failed To Materialize</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TIERNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tierney, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Tierney The Big City column discusses reasons for abandonment after 8 years of plans by Allen Hershkowitz to build mill in Bronx for recycled newsprint (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was hailed by President Clinton as a model for the nation. State and city politicians enthusiastically offered praise and money. There were ready customers for its product. Allen Hershkowitz's dream of building a mill in the Bronx for recycled newsprint was nothing if not appealing.</p>
        <p>It evoked a certain admiration even from his professional enemies, a group I joined in 1996 by writing an article for The New York Times Magazine titled ''Recycling Is Garbage.'' Dr. Hershkowitz, a senior scientist at the Natural Resources Defense Council, responded with a line-by-line rebuttal in an 86-page report, ''Too Good to Throw Away: Recycling's Proven Record.'' For a while we were condemned to a television road show of vitriolic debates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was hailed by President Clinton as a model for the nation. State and city politicians enthusiastically offered praise and money. There were ready customers for its product. Allen Hershkowitz's dream of building a mill in the Bronx for recycled newsprint was nothing if not appealing.</p>
        <p>It evoked a certain admiration even from his professional enemies, a group I joined in 1996 by writing an article for The New York Times Magazine titled ''Recycling Is Garbage.'' Dr. Hershkowitz, a senior scientist at the Natural Resources Defense Council, responded with a line-by-line rebuttal in an 86-page report, ''Too Good to Throw Away: Recycling's Proven Record.'' For a while we were condemned to a television road show of vitriolic debates.</p>
        <p>But we also managed, during the commercial breaks, to have civil conversations about the scheme for the Bronx that he had been promoting since 1992. It was a refreshing change of pace for environmentalism. Instead of preaching about the morality of recycling, Dr. Hershkowitz was looking at the market for it.</p>
        <p>He was proposing to help capitalists turn New York City's waste paper into newsprint. He wanted, as he liked to say, to build ''the sustainable economy of the future.''</p>
        <p>''We have spent years stopping projects and we are still not saving the forests,'' he told a reporter in 1997. ''So we decided to do something more pro-active to improve the way we use resources. And we also think if you can find a project that does something positive and produces a good financial return, industry will jump all over it.''</p>
        <p>The economics seemed plausible, or at least not inherently impractical, even if you knew how much money had been lost in other recycling efforts. Paper tended to be more valuable for recycling than most other materials collected in curbside programs, and New York seemed to have some special comparative advantages in this business.</p>
        <p>The city's office buildings made it the ''Saudi Arabia of wastepaper,'' as Dr. Hershkowitz said, a place with more cellular fiber per acre than the Amazon. And the city was willing to provide a reliable stream of that raw material at favorable prices.</p>
        <p>Its citizens were required by law to sort out this raw material from their garbage, providing the mill with what might be described as free labor. There was also a reliable market for the finished product, in part because local newspapers had signed a pledge (under pressure from politicians and environmentalists) to buy more recyled newsprint.</p>
        <p>Using more than $2 million of his organization's money, Dr. Hershkowitz helped plan the mill, secure environmental permits and gather political support. Local newspapers agreed to buy its products; the city and state promised a variety of tax breaks and subsidies, and paid for a two-mile-long rail line to the industrial yard where it would share space with other companies.</p>
        <p>PAPER companies and developers seemed close to building at several points, but ultimately no one was willing to put up the money. After eight years, the project was formally abandoned last month. Private investors decided the returns from the mill would not be high enough.</p>
        <p>They realized that, contrary to some expectations of paper shortages, the supply of newsprint has been high enough in recent years to keep the price down. That makes it especially hard to justify a new mill in New York, where the high costs of construction and labor make it difficult to manufacture anything economically.</p>
        <p>''It's a lot cheaper to build a paper mill out in the sticks than in New York,'' said Jerry Powell, the editor of Resource Recycling, a trade magazine. ''And this is not a great time to be building any kind of new mill. The original idea for the Bronx mill looked great, but since then the industry has become much more efficient, and there's too much capacity.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Hershkowitz said he was not discouraged. ''We environmentalists are regularly criticized for not taking the market seriously,'' he said. ''We tried working with business and got extraordinarily close to achieving our vision. Now we have a more refined understanding of the obstacles in front of us. This is just the beginning.''</p>
        <p>That's one way to look at the results. Here's another: even after extraordinary subsidies and interventions by environmentalists and public officials, recycling has failed an important test in New York. These results, along with other recent developments, raise questions about the entire recycling program. More on that next week.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
