<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>I.N.S. Cited for Poor Checks on Citizenship</title>
    <meta content="01IMMI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000802T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Citizenship</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Immigration and Naturalization Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alvarez, Lizette</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Citizenship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EED9103DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="981" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>I.N.S. Cited for Poor Checks on Citizenship</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZETTE ALVAREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alvarez, Lizette</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Justice Department's inspector general issues report detailing litany of errors committed by Immigration and Naturalization Service as it rushed to naturalize one million citizens in 1995 and 1996; says agency's eagerness to shorten its backlog of citizenship applications led it to naturalize at least 180,000 immigrants, or 18 percent, without proper criminal background checks (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Justice Department's inspector general issued a report today detailing the litany of errors committed by the Immigration and Naturalization Service as it rushed to naturalize one million citizens in 1995 and 1996.</p>
        <p>The agency's eagerness to shorten its backlog of citizenship applications during that time led it to naturalize at least 180,000 immigrants -- or 18 percent -- without proper criminal background checks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Justice Department's inspector general issued a report today detailing the litany of errors committed by the Immigration and Naturalization Service as it rushed to naturalize one million citizens in 1995 and 1996.</p>
        <p>The agency's eagerness to shorten its backlog of citizenship applications during that time led it to naturalize at least 180,000 immigrants -- or 18 percent -- without proper criminal background checks.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department has acknowledged that the errors allowed several hundred immigrants with criminal convictions to obtain American citizenship, and that it is in the process of reviewing many of those cases to determine if the citizenship should be revoked.</p>
        <p>The investigation, which the inspector general's office described as the largest it had ever undertaken, found that the immigration agency ignored a number of warnings, including its own, as it pressed to meet its goal of naturalizing one million applicants by Sept. 30, 1996.</p>
        <p>''I.N.S. failed to address known system weaknesses before implementing a program that they knew would tax that system as it never had been taxed before,'' said Robert L. Ashbaugh, acting inspector general. ''The results were predictable.''</p>
        <p>Saying the agency has fixed much of what was broken, an observation that is underscored in the report, the immigration agency played down the findings today and called many of them outdated.</p>
        <p>''There is nothing in this report that is new,'' said Maria Cardona, an agency spokeswoman. ''This is a report about a system that is no longer applicable. That was then, this is now.''</p>
        <p>While the report chronicles a series of missteps by the immigration agency -- including hiring improperly trained workers and failing to wait for Federal Bureau of Investigation background checks on applicants who had been fingerprinted -- it cleared the White House of accusations that it manipulated the citizenship program to boost voter rolls for the 1996 election. The agency and its commissioner, Doris M. Meissner, ''were not acting out of partisan political motives,'' the report states.</p>
        <p>The actions of Vice President Al Gore came under review because he and his ''reinventing government'' operation had suggested ways for the immigration agency to decrease the citizenship backlog. Jim Kennedy, a spokesman for Mr. Gore, said the report backs what the vice president and the White House have been saying about the naturalization program all along, ''namely that it was an effort designed to reduce the backlog of citizenship applications and not to further any inappropriate political end.''</p>
        <p>In written answers to questions from the inspector general, Mr. Gore denied any political motive to the effort to reduce the backlog. But the report makes it clear that the Clinton administration took an interest in the program's progress.</p>
        <p>''We found evidence that White House officials were interested in I.N.S.'s naturalization program for a variety of reasons, including 'political' reasons that related to the November 1996 election,'' the report states, ''but from the evidence we did not find those interests resulted in improper actions.''</p>
        <p>Those interests, however, ''added to the significant pressure that already existed on I.N.S.,'' the report states.</p>
        <p>At least one White House aide, Douglas Farbrother, who was assigned to work on Mr. Gore's reinventing government team, reported to the inspector general that he was told by Elaine Karmack, Mr. Gore's senior policy adviser, that the citizenship program was linked to the upcoming election.</p>
        <p>Mr. Farbrother's own electronic mail messages to Mr. Gore and Ms. Karmack show that he was keenly aware of the link as he criticized the agency for falling down on the job of producing ''a million new citizens before election day.''</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Farbrother, Ms. Karmack said President Clinton had heard about a backlog in citizenship applications in Southern California. ''The president was interested in naturalization because he thought this group would mostly vote for him,'' Mr. Farbrother said he was told.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton then asked Mr. Gore to have the reinventing government program ''take a look'' at the backlog, Mr. Farbrother said Ms. Karmack told him.</p>
        <p>Ms. Karmack denied making these statements, the report says.</p>
        <p>Representative Lamar Smith, the Texas Republican who chairs the subcommittee on immigration, said he was troubled by the implications of the report and plans to hold hearings on its findings when Congress reconvenes in September. ''The American people have a right to know that this agency will bow to political pressure from the Clinton administration,'' Senator Smith said.</p>
        <p>The report also chronicles how the immigration agency mishandled the job of processing a million citizens, permitting unqualified people to become naturalized. But the inspector general said it was impossible to come up with a figure of how many citizens were wrongly approved or rejected.</p>
        <p>An auditor hired by the government found in 1997 that 180,000 immigrants did not undergo background checks, mostly because the system for fingerprinting people and verifying the results was not working.</p>
        <p>The agency said its own audit uncovered 8,400 immigrants who could have been ''wrongly naturalized'' because they had criminal records or for other reasons. Of those, the agency's general counsel winnowed the list to 600 who had criminal convictions and had lied about them on their citizenship applications. So far, 140 have had their citizenship revoked. The rest are being reviewed.</p>
        <p>While the report praises the agency for revamping its background check system, it concludes that the I.N.S. must create uniform standards for citizenship applicants. There are no standards for determining whether an applicant can speak English or is of ''good moral character,'' which leads to inconsistencies and unfairness in the treatment of applicants.</p>
        <p>The federal agency now faces a backlog of 1.1 million citizenship applications, down from its high of nearly 2 million early last year.</p>
        <p>''I.N.S. has made little progress toward ensuring that adjudicators, once they have the requisite tools -- like the results of criminal history checks or the applicant's file -- know how to use them,'' the report states.</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 2, 2000, Wednesday  An article yesterday about a Justice Department report on the Immigration Service's 1996 citizenship program referred incorrectly in some copies to the cases of immigrants with criminal convictions. Four such immigrants -- not 140 -- have lost their citizenship. The service says it has sent 140 cases -- out of 600 known -- to the Justice Department; the rest of the 140 are pending.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 2, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about a Justice Department report on the Immigration Service's 1996 citizenship program referred incorrectly in some copies to the cases of immigrants with criminal convictions. Four such immigrants -- not 140 -- have lost their citizenship. The service says it has sent 140 cases -- out of 600 known -- to the Justice Department; the rest of the 140 are pending.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
