<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Replacing Mary Fisher, And Pushing Abstinence</title>
    <meta content="Y01DIA$19" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000808T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219332"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: PHILADELPHIA DIARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuczynski, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdy, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE6DF113DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1168" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Replacing Mary Fisher, And Pushing Abstinence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alex Kuczynski and Matthew Purdy</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdy, Matthew; Kuczynski, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vignettes of behind-the-scenes goings-on at National Convention in Philadelphia; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mary Fisher speech had become a fixture at Republican conventions. She spoke passionately in 1992 and 1996 about living with H.I.V., and offered to do a repeat performance in Philadelphia. The response from the Bush campaign was, well, no direct response.</p>
        <p>Instead, a short speech about AIDS will be delivered by Patricia Funderburk Ware, the president of the Preserving Family Well-Being Foundation, who favors abstinence-only sex education programs. It's a more conservative message than the one Ms. Fisher would have delivered. Ms. Fisher finances an AIDS research and education fund, and advocates a broader range of preventive measures. ''I think it's more important to save lives than virginity,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mary Fisher speech had become a fixture at Republican conventions. She spoke passionately in 1992 and 1996 about living with H.I.V., and offered to do a repeat performance in Philadelphia. The response from the Bush campaign was, well, no direct response.</p>
        <p>Instead, a short speech about AIDS will be delivered by Patricia Funderburk Ware, the president of the Preserving Family Well-Being Foundation, who favors abstinence-only sex education programs. It's a more conservative message than the one Ms. Fisher would have delivered. Ms. Fisher finances an AIDS research and education fund, and advocates a broader range of preventive measures. ''I think it's more important to save lives than virginity,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But there's another difference. Ms. Fisher, whose father, Max, has given generously of his auto body fortune to the Republican Party, is white. Ms. Ware, who worked in the administration of President Bush, is black.</p>
        <p>''I think it was important that it be an African-American,'' said Carl E. Schmid, a leading gay supporter of Governor Bush, citing the disease's demographics.</p>
        <p>Tim Fitzpatrick, a spokesman, said simply that Ms. Ware ''is reflective of Governor Bush's call for soldiers in the army of compassion.'' Ms. Ware did not return calls.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fisher said she thought it would be more powerful for the delegates to hear from someone with AIDS. ''Having someone with the disease puts a face on it,'' she said. ''Maybe it brings it too close to them.''</p>
        <p>So Ms. Fisher stayed away from the convention, but her noninvitation was on the minds of some at a reception yesterday for gay and lesbian Republicans. Like Ms. Fisher, they were struggling to find their place under the Republican tent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schmid, addressing a room of about 200, praised the draft platform, which was in line with many policies favored by gays. ''Unfortunately,'' he said, ''the very conservative platform committee'' changed the language. ''We have a long road ahead in our own party,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One step on that road, Mr. Schmid said, will be a speech by Representative Jim Kolbe of Arizona, who will be the first openly gay person to address a Republican convention.</p>
        <p>His topic? International trade policy.</p>
        <p>Surprise Rehearsal</p>
        <p>Anyone who happened to be milling around the convention hall yesterday afternoon caught something unusual: Laura Bush, unvarnished and unpracticed.</p>
        <p>The wife of the Republican presidential candidate turned up unannounced on stage for a sound check and a run-through of her speech, with a crowd of Bush aides. And Mrs. Bush made the most of it.</p>
        <p>''I'm honored and overwhelmed to open the convention that will nominate my husband to run for president of the United States,'' she said, and then provided her own chorus of cheers: ''YEA!'' The smattering of delegates, technicians and reporters in the hall looked up in surprise to realize who was at the microphone.</p>
        <p>''You know I'm completely objective when I say, you've made a great choice!'' she continued. And then again, ''YEA!'' This time, a few delegates joined in the cheering.</p>
        <p>Aides offered advice about speaking to the cameras, but Mrs. Bush was confident. ''This will be great,'' she said, heading off stage.</p>
        <p>An Unwelcome Distraction</p>
        <p>The message of inclusion and diversity was wafting from the dais, but on the floor, tolerance found its limits.</p>
        <p>As Colin Powell was giving a rousing speech about unifying diverse communities, Hideya Sugio, a correspondent for Tokyo Broadcasting, was conducting a rather loud stand-up, telling the folks back home about the party's new moderation. Mr. Sugio chattered on, growing louder and drawing stares from the delegates trying to listen to Mr. Powell.</p>
        <p>''Someone ought to tell that guy to stop,'' one delegate said.</p>
        <p>Finally, a man turned around an emphatically shussed Mr. Sugio. Then another delegate joined in, muttering with a smile, ''Sayonara!''</p>
        <p>A Somber Tea</p>
        <p>Republican ladies who usually do not have time for lunch -- about 200  women, including members of the House and Senate -- sat down to an afternoon tea, given by Lifetime Television for Women, in honor of Elizabeth Dole.</p>
        <p>But a dolorous air had settled in at the ballroom in the Four Seasons Hotel, over the tables, some empty, set with crumpets, cream and crystal flutes of Champagne.</p>
        <p>After all, many women attending the tea had hoped that it would be Mrs. Dole making her acceptance speech here in Philadelphia, for either spot on the ticket.</p>
        <p>Nancy G. Brinker, the founder of the Susan G. Komen Breast Cancer Foundation, stopped to pose for a photograph with Mrs. Dole and said that she was disappointed that there was no woman on the Republican ticket. Mrs. Brinker, though, remained hopeful that there would be  in the future.</p>
        <p>Asked if she was disappointed not to see Mrs. Dole on the ticket, Representative Tillie Fowler of Florida said, ''Oh my, yes. She's been my friend for 30 years.'' The two once worked together in the Lyndon Johnson White House.</p>
        <p>But Representative Jennifer Dunn of Washington, a member of the Republican House leadership and a deputy convention co-chair, was positively buoyant. She said George W. Bush was strong on issues that deal with women, citing his plans for Social Security reform as an example.</p>
        <p>''Husbands tend to die seven or eight years earlier than their wives, so Social Security reform is beneficial for women,'' she said. She was also a big fan of Dick Cheney. ''He is married to a powerful woman, and he knows he needs to listen to a powerful woman,'' she said.</p>
        <p>A Not-So-Republican Alert</p>
        <p>Larry Rockefeller, an environmental lawyer, stalked the corridors of the Republican convention yesterday with an escort from the Democratic National Committee, spreading his gospel, a ''Statement by Larry Rockefeller'' that warns darkly of Republican extremism.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rockefeller, whose uncle Nelson A. Rockefeller was the original Rockefeller Republican, said that he was making the rounds to sound an alert.</p>
        <p>''We must look beyond the gauze and the haze and the happy promises and look at Bush's record in Texas,'' he said, his leather satchel leaking manifestos. ''He is not, despite what some voters think, a mainstream Republican. As a Republican, I personally feel I ought to let voters know.'' Mr. Rockefeller, a self-described ''mainstream Republican,'' contributed $2,000 to Al Gore's campaign last year.</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: PHILADELPHIA DIARY  Correction:  August 8, 2000, Tuesday  A report in the Philadelphia Diary column last Tuesday about a speech on AIDS at the Republican National Convention misstated the source of the fortune made by Max Fisher, a Republican donor whose daughter Mary Fisher spoke about AIDS at the 1992 and 1996 conventions. He made his fortune in the oil business and as an investor, not in the auto body business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 8, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A report in the Philadelphia Diary column last Tuesday about a speech on AIDS at the Republican National Convention misstated the source of the fortune made by Max Fisher, a Republican donor whose daughter Mary Fisher spoke about AIDS at the 1992 and 1996 conventions. He made his fortune in the oil business and as an investor, not in the auto body business.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
