<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Demonstrators, Denied Permission, March Anyway and Even Gain a Police Escort</title>
    <meta content="Y01PHI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219283"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: THE PROTESTERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E0D8103DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="870" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Demonstrators, Denied Permission, March Anyway and Even Gain a Police Escort</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, July 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Demonstrators stage protests outside Republican National Convention in Philadelphia amid massive police presence; successful efforts of police bike squad in maintaining peace by avoiding confrontations and being helpful to demonstrators discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Slowly and strategically, a thick blue line of city police officers retreated from downtown toward the Republican National Convention today, yielding before an illegal protest parade rather than facing a potentially violent street confrontation with the world watching.</p>
        <p>''We're not going to stop them,'' the deputy police chief, Sylvester Johnson, decided on Broad Street as a parade of welfare protesters, denied a permit to march, stepped off from City Hall nevertheless and headed south toward the convention.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Slowly and strategically, a thick blue line of city police officers retreated from downtown toward the Republican National Convention today, yielding before an illegal protest parade rather than facing a potentially violent street confrontation with the world watching.</p>
        <p>''We're not going to stop them,'' the deputy police chief, Sylvester Johnson, decided on Broad Street as a parade of welfare protesters, denied a permit to march, stepped off from City Hall nevertheless and headed south toward the convention.</p>
        <p>The protesters were no less strategic than the police as they made sure that their parade began with a phalanx of toddlers and infants backed up by paraplegics in wheelchairs.</p>
        <p>''I'll be marching with them,'' Chief Johnson added, emphasizing that flexibility had to be the watchword for this tense convention week.</p>
        <p>Indeed the chief did march the full three miles through the hot sun. He converted his large stationary force of officers, who stood at first as a line in the sand that attracted a mass of news media, into a mobile escort. They cleared traffic before the parading demonstrators, who happily won their point and chanted: ''Whose streets? Our streets!''</p>
        <p>The marchers, in turn, cooperated by finally veering off into a park near the convention site rather than confronting the large backup force of police officers, equipped with hundreds of sets of plastic handcuffs tucked in their gunbelts, firmly ringing the arena behind barricades.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, eight arrests had been made at a much smaller demonstration outside City Hall as protesters denounced the Army's School of the Americas and blocked traffic by lying down in the street. The school, at Fort Benning, Ga., has long been the subject of complaints that it trains Latin American soldiers in combat methods often used in human rights abuses to protect dictatorships. The demonstrators, opting for nonviolent civil disobedience, were accommodated by the police, who made fast arrests.</p>
        <p>The larger welfare protest, which eventually attracted several thousand marchers, drew initial warnings of arrest but apparently proved too sizable and peaceful for police confrontation.</p>
        <p>''We feel this is a big victory in giving a voice to the words and power of poor people,'' said Jonathan M. Blazer, a lawyer for the Kensington Welfare Rights Union, a North Philadelphia civic group that sponsored the march and prevailed in taking over Broad Street, despite being denied a permit.</p>
        <p>No arrests were made during the march and no injuries were reported. But traffic was disrupted on one of the main routes to the convention arena as the opening gavel was summoning the Republican delegates.</p>
        <p>''I don't care about the traffic,'' declared Femi Johnson, a cab driver trapped by the protesters. ''This march is letting the people express themselves. I'm from Nigeria and one day I wish to go back and deliver a lesson in democracy like this.''</p>
        <p>For all the uniformed police and gold stars in evidence along the march, the pivotal police figures were plainclothes officers from the civil affairs unit who negotiated with demonstration leaders and even supplied them with cold drinks from police buckets as the day unfolded.</p>
        <p>Capt. William V. Fisher, the unit commander, stayed at the head of the march, a sweat-soaked study in navigating around confrontation. He conferred repeatedly with protest negotiators, then with Police Chief John Timoney, who would suddenly pedal to the scene at strategic turnings with members of the police bike squad.</p>
        <p>With the convention site sealed off and the Republican agenda a rosy model of nondissent, the marchers, bolstered by assorted other protesters, sought to instigate the only untoward event of the day for the 15,000 visiting news workers. Once the chance of confrontation passed, the event turned into an unsensational three-hour trudge but for a flurry of alarm at a passing coincidence: Newt Gingrich was sighted down a side street.</p>
        <p>A thicket of television camera crews instantly sprang off in pursuit, as if the former House speaker were one of the promised ''anarchists'' who have been threatening to haunt the convention proceedings.</p>
        <p>''Newt came out of that Dunkin' Donuts, I think,'' one foreign journalist announced as reporters hurried after this white-haired specter of Republican victories past.</p>
        <p>''No, it was a White Castle!'' a stickler corrected breathlessly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gingrich, on his way to a neighborhood photo op, turned and looked bewildered at receiving the largest amount of media scrutiny since Republicans purged him from leadership.</p>
        <p>Before yielding to the marchers, Chief Johnson received contrary advice from an aide who could be heard telling him, ''If we don't move, they don't move.'' But the police moved first, backward. As the march proceeded, a large, ever-changing electronic message sign at a construction site at Spruce and Broad came forth almost eerily with what seemed apt advice for the passing scene: ''Using force to stop force is absurd.'' And: ''To disagree presupposes moral integrity.''</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: THE PROTESTERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
