<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Riley to Get Mason In the Deal For Jones</title>
    <meta content="01NBAA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219298"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Charlotte Hornets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Eddie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mason, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, P J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Washburn, Jamal</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Orleans Hornets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0D7103DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Riley to Get Mason In the Deal For Jones</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charlotte Hornets and Miami Heat reportedly are close to nine-player trade in which Anthony Mason and Eddie Jones would join Heat in return for P J Brown and Jamal Washburn; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the chagrin of the Chicago Bulls, Pat Riley appears to have gotten his man.</p>
        <p>On the eve of the National Basketball Association free-agent signing period, the Charlotte Hornets and the Miami Heat were on the cusp of completing a nine-player trade, with the Hornets sending Eddie Jones and Anthony Mason to South Florida for the Heat's Jamal Mashburn and P. J. Brown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the chagrin of the Chicago Bulls, Pat Riley appears to have gotten his man.</p>
        <p>On the eve of the National Basketball Association free-agent signing period, the Charlotte Hornets and the Miami Heat were on the cusp of completing a nine-player trade, with the Hornets sending Eddie Jones and Anthony Mason to South Florida for the Heat's Jamal Mashburn and P. J. Brown.</p>
        <p>Throughout the off-season, Riley, the Heat's coach and team president, has pursued Jones, the athletic All-Star shooting guard his team desperately needs. And the trade would reunite Mason with Riley, his former coach with the Knicks.</p>
        <p>Riley has seen the Heat eliminated by the Knicks the past three postseasons. He was hoping to announce the deal as early as today, an Eastern Conference team official said on the condition of anonymity last night.</p>
        <p>The other players involved in the trade were believed to be Ricky Davis and Dale Ellis of Charlotte and Otis Thorpe, Rodney Buford and Tim James of Miami. There were still contract details to be worked out, and it was unclear whether the assortment of role players would change.</p>
        <p>Last night, a Hornets team official said the deal was ''almost done.''</p>
        <p>In Miami last night, fans on talk shows were wondering whether Riley had given up too much for Jones. The Heat had to acquire Mason, the player Riley feuded with and suspended while with the Knicks, to shore up the deal.</p>
        <p>It is unclear whether the Heat will pursue a deal for Lakers small forward Glen Rice while using Mason as trade bait. But another Eastern Conference team official would not rule out further trades involving Miami. The Heat did not want to part with Brown, the consummate role player Riley has often kept out of deals.</p>
        <p>The only news the Knicks made yesterday was orally agreeing to terms with Kurt Thomas. Thomas, a free-agent forward, will most likely sign a multiyear extension with the club in the next two days, a team official said.</p>
        <p>Jones, whom the Chicago Bulls coveted, and the rest of the 2000 free-agent class can begin signing contracts today. In a sign-and-trade deal, he could earn more than $86 million over seven seasons.</p>
        <p>While Orlando officially overhauls its roster today with the signings of Grant Hill and Tracy McGrady -- two of the top five free agents -- the Bulls are left with $19 million in salary-cap room and not a single All-Star left to bid on.</p>
        <p>After Tim Thomas spurned the Bulls last month to remain in Milwaukee, their only hope is to perhaps overpay Ron Mercer or Rice.</p>
        <p>Indiana is going to re-sign Jalen Rose and is working out contract extensions for Reggie Miller and Mark Jackson. Philadelphia's Toni Kukoc, Seattle's Rashard Lewis and Houston's Cuttino Mobley are also expected to sign with their current teams.</p>
        <p>The Magic did well, but it missed out on the top prize. Tim Duncan decided to stay in San Antonio, where he is expected to sign a three-deal with a fourth-year option for more than $45 million.</p>
        <p>Before most deals were signed, teams were waiting to hear from the league office what the adjusted salary cap number would be for next season. A league official said the salary cap would total approximately $35.5 million -- meaning a team's aggregate annual salaries for their 2000-1 players under contract must add up to that number or less.</p>
        <p>A player with one to six years of experience can sign for 25 percent of the total unadjusted salary cap. The union and the league agreed last night that such a player's maximum salary the first year would be $9.658 million. A player with six to nine years' experience can sign for $11.589 million in his first year, and a player with 10 years' experience or more cannot earn more than $14 million in the first season of a new contract.</p>
        <p>While several players were still undecided as to where they would go, the Miami-Charlotte deal became the buzz of the league yesterday afternoon.</p>
        <p>The Hornets were ecstatic to acquire Mashburn and Brown. Faced with the possibility of losing Jones for nothing if he signed with another team, the Hornets dramatically altered their lineup as well.</p>
        <p>The only real intrigue left around the league is what is going to happen to Portland's Brian Grant. Grant has said he wants to play in New York, and the Trail Blazers have even mentioned Patrick Ewing's name in discussions between the teams. But it is doubtful the Knicks will part with their center for Grant, a power forward.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
