<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From General Powell's Address to Republicans</title>
    <meta content="01CTEX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219348"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powell, Colin L (Gen) (Ret)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E1DF113DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1535" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From General Powell's Address to Republicans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from address by Retired Gen Colin Powell before Republican National Convention (M),</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from Retired Gen. Colin Powell's speech at the Republican National Convention yesterday, as recorded by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>During the almost seven years since I retired from the Army I've traveled all across America. I've seen people hard at work providing for their families, giving of themselves, taking care of each other. I've seen them creating wealth for the nation, I've seen an economy transforming itself to seize the promise of the information revolution. . . .</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from Retired Gen. Colin Powell's speech at the Republican National Convention yesterday, as recorded by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>During the almost seven years since I retired from the Army I've traveled all across America. I've seen people hard at work providing for their families, giving of themselves, taking care of each other. I've seen them creating wealth for the nation, I've seen an economy transforming itself to seize the promise of the information revolution. . . .</p>
        <p>I've been moved yet again to stand in awe of the American dream, which was given birth in this city over 200 years ago. A dream that I have been privileged to live. I've met so many young people who believe in the dream. They're on a road to success. . . .</p>
        <p>There is so much that is so good and right in America tonight my friends that we ought to be very, very proud of this wonderful country of ours. And yet I cannot ignore and we cannot ignore other things I've seen in my travels. I've seen poverty. I've seen failing communities. I've seen people who've lost hope. Tragically, I've seen too many young Americans who were overwhelmed by the daily struggle just to survive. I've seen kids destroying themselves with drugs. Kids who see violence and crime as the answer to their hopelessness. Kids who no longer believe in themselves and who don't see a reason to believe in America. I've seen kids in utter despair. I've visited kids in jail doing adult time for the crimes they've committed. They are part of a growing population of over two million Americans behind bars. . . . Most of them are men and the majority of those men are minorities.</p>
        <p>The issue of race still casts a shadow over our society. Despite the impressive progress we have made over the last 40 years to overcome this legacy of our troubled past, it is still with us.</p>
        <p>So with all the success we have enjoyed and with all the wealth we have created we have much more work to do and a long way to go to bring the promise of America to every single American.</p>
        <p>And with all we have to do in our national agenda, I am convinced that to deliver on that promise we must begin with our children. So many of the problems we worry about go back to how we raised our children. The problem is as simple and as direct as this: we either get back to the task of building our children the way we know how or we're going to keep building jails in America. And it's time to stop building jails in America and get back to the task of building our children.</p>
        <p>Listen. Listen. And listen, listen, listen very carefully. Our children are not the problem. They are our future. They are America's promise. The problem is us if we've failed to give them what they need to be successful in life. The burden is on us, not on our children.</p>
        <p>That mission of providing for our children has become the passion of my life. Because what I've seen over the last several years convinces me of the following truths:</p>
        <p>That if you want to solve our drug problem, you won't do it by trying to cut off supply and arresting pushers on the street corners alone. It will only be solved when we place into the heart of every child growing up in America the moral strength never to fall for the destructive lure of drugs, the strength -- only -- we will only solve and cure this plague of drugs is when we have given to each and every one of our children the strength to just say, and you've heard it before, just say no, not me, I won't do it, I've got too much to live for, I'll never do drugs. . . .</p>
        <p>Tonight we focus on education, the keystone to it all. Governor Bush has rightly made children and education the centerpiece of his campaign for president. . . . Every child deserves and must receive a quality education. Because when you give a quality education to a child who believes in himself or herself then even with the bleakest beginning in life that child can make it. And once that child makes it and gets out into the work place and is earning a decent living, you have broken the cycle of poverty and failure for that family forever. Education is the key to breaking that cycle of poverty and failure.</p>
        <p>So many, many of our public schools are doing a fine job preparing our youngsters. . . .  But I've also seen too many schools that are failing. They are trapped in fossilized bureaucracies. Bureaucracies that have low expectations for children and consequently set low standards for them. These schools are failing our children and they must be fixed and they must be fixed now.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush has shown in Texas in just a few short years what can be done for education. As governor, he ended social promotions for kids, he increased state funding by $8 billion, he put new text books in every school in the state of Texas, he strengthened standardized testing in all Texas public schools, he insisted on teacher competency and he expanded the charter school movement. Seventeen thousand Texas kids are now in charter school. Seventy-eight percent of those kids are minorities. Their parents had a choice and they decided what was best for their children. And the results, the results in Texas have been dramatic. . . .</p>
        <p>He hasn't stopped there. To ensure a diverse college population with the loss of affirmative action, Governor Bush has guaranteed acceptance at public universities for the top 10 percent of every high school graduating class in the state. . . .</p>
        <p>Governor Bush now offers the leadership that he has demonstrated in Texas to the nation. In pursuing educational reform as well as in all other parts of his agenda for Texas, Governor Bush as reached out to all Texans -- white, black, Latino, Asian, Native American. He has been successful in bringing more and more minorities into the tent by responding to their deepest needs. Some call it compassionate conservatism, to me it's just caring about people.</p>
        <p>I believe he can do the same thing as president. I am convinced he will bring to the White House that same passion for inclusion. I know that he can help bridge our racial divides. I know that.</p>
        <p>Recently, Governor Bush addressed the annual meeting of the N.A.A.C.P. He spoke to the delegates about his plans for housing and health and educational programs to help all Americans. He also spoke the truth to the delegates when he said that the party of Lincoln has not always carried the mantle of Lincoln. I talked with him again today and I know that with all his heart, Governor Bush welcomes the challenge. He wants the Republican party to wear that mantle again.</p>
        <p>But he knows and I know and all of you must know that it's going to take hard work. He knows that that mantle will not simply be handed over. That it will have to be earned. The party must follow the governor's lead in reaching out to minority communities. And particularly the African-American community. And not just during an election year campaign. My friends, if we're serious about this, it has to be a sustained effort. It must be every day and it must be for real. The party must listen to and speak with all leaders of the black community regardless of political affiliation or philosophy.</p>
        <p>We must understand, my friends, we must understand that there is a problem for us out there. We must understand the cynicism that exists in the black community. The kind of cynicism that is created when, for example, some in our party miss no opportunity to roundly and loudly condemn affirmative action that helped a few thousand black kids get an education. But you hardly hear a whimper when it's affirmative action for lobbyists who load our federal tax code with preferences for special interests. It doesn't work. It doesn't work. You can't make that case.</p>
        <p>Overcoming the cynicism and mistrust that exists and raising up that mantle of Lincoln is about more, it's much more about than just winning votes. It is about giving all minorities a competitive choice. They deserve that choice. And if we give them that choice it will be good for our party but above all it will be good for America. And we need to work to give them that choice.</p>
        <p>Good for America, that must be the measure for all that we do. I believe that's the measure that Governor Bush will use to guide his actions as president. Whether it's economic policy or military strategy or seeing what we can do to make our American family more inclusive, he will always try to do that which is good and right for America.</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
