<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="01MBRF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219284"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EFD8103DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1857" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: DEMOLITION BLOCKED  The demolition of a row of historic buildings on West Third Street, including a former home of Edgar Allan Poe and Judson House, a Greek Revival town house on the corner of Third and Thompson Streets, has been stopped for now by a temporary restraining order signed yesterday by Justice Robert D. Lippman of the State Supreme Court. Two city preservation groups sought the injunction to prevent the New York University School of Law from tearing down the buildings until a hearing on Aug. 8.</p>
        <p>Nina Siegal (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: DEMOLITION BLOCKED  The demolition of a row of historic buildings on West Third Street, including a former home of Edgar Allan Poe and Judson House, a Greek Revival town house on the corner of Third and Thompson Streets, has been stopped for now by a temporary restraining order signed yesterday by Justice Robert D. Lippman of the State Supreme Court. Two city preservation groups sought the injunction to prevent the New York University School of Law from tearing down the buildings until a hearing on Aug. 8.</p>
        <p>Nina Siegal (NYT)</p>
        <p>QUEENS: TEENAGER INJURED  A 13-year-old Queens boy was struck in a hit-and-run accident at noon yesterday while crossing Conduit Boulevard near Hemlock Street, the police said. The boy, whose name was not immediately released, was taken to Jamaica Hospital Medical Center, where he was in critical but stable condition with no apparent brain injuries, said Ole Pedersen, a hospital spokesman. The police were searching for the driver of a 1990's dark blue Toyota Camry or Cressida with dark tinted windows.</p>
        <p>Elissa Gootman (NYT)</p>
        <p>MINEOLA: UNDERSHERIFF CRITICIZED  Two Nassau County legislators yesterday demanded the resignation of Undersheriff Jerome Donahue after a federal jury found that his department discriminated against gays. The legislators, Joseph K. Scannell and Lisanne Altmann, both Democrats, called for the resignation in a letter to Sheriff Ed Reilly. On July 18, a jury awarded $1.55 million in damages to a former correction officer in the Sheriff's Department who testified that Mr. Donahue and Sheriff Joseph Jablonsky, now retired, had ignored his complaints. Mr. Donahue has denied the existence of an anti-gay policy.</p>
        <p>Stacy Albin (NYT)</p>
        <p>ITHACA: DEER POPULATION CONTROL  Contraceptive injections could help curb an exploding deer population in areas of upstate New York, researchers say, although the contraceptives' effectiveness is limited by the difficulty of catching the deer to administer the medication. A four-year study at the former Seneca Army Depot on a captive herd vaccinated with darts showed an 85 percent decrease in fawns, said Paul Curtis, a wildlife biologist at Cornell University. Scientists also are researching the possibility of putting contraceptive drugs into deer food.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: OFFICER REINSTATED  A New York police detective who spent nine months in jail before being cleared of corruption charges has been reinstated to the rank of detective after a period of modified duty, his lawyer said. The detective, Zaher Zahrey, left, was reinstated on July 21, said the lawyer, Joel Rudin, who received formal notification yesterday. Mr. Zahrey, a decorated undercover narcotics detective, was acquitted by a federal jury on June 27, 1997. He had been accused of helping members of a drug gang in two robberies, one of which ended in a murder.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: CRIME RATE DROPS  Connecticut's overall crime rate dropped 10.4 percent from 1998 to 1999, according to new figures released by the Department of Public Safety. The 111,039 crimes reported last year -- including 107 murders, 19,231 burglaries and 11,357 auto thefts -- represented the lowest cumulative figure since 1977, when the state began compiling an annual crime index, the department said yesterday. Last year, the total number of violent crimes reported -- 11,380 -- was 5.2 percent lower than in 1998. The state's crime index peaked in 1980, when 179,618 crimes were reported statewide.</p>
        <p>Paul Zielbauer (NYT)</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: BUDGET SURPLUS DETAILED  Gov. John G. Rowland explained yesterday how a state law would split up a predicted $530 million budget surplus. About $316 million would pay for school construction projects, and $53 million would be used to wire school systems, invest in open space and update the state's financial systems. The surplus also would help bail out the cash-strapped University of Connecticut Health Center, which needs $20 million to cover operating losses.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>WEST HARTFORD: CRACKDOWN ON LOUD RADIOS  The West Hartford Town Council is considering a law that would impose a $30 fine on those who play their car stereos too loudly. Under the proposed ordinance, any car stereo that could be heard more than 50 feet away would be considered too loud. The town already prohibits loud music from residential buildings and restaurants. Officials say loud music erodes the town's charm.</p>
        <p>Theresa Crapanzano (NYT)</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: HEART SURGERY FOR REPRESENTATIVE  Robert Farr, a 10-term Republican representative running for re-election in West Hartford, said yesterday that he would undergo open-heart surgery to replace a defective valve. He said he should be able to do ''some light campaigning'' by the end of September. Mr. Farr, the ranking member of the General Assembly's Judiciary Committee, said he had known about his heart problem a few days before receiving the nomination at the state Republican convention on July 22, but did not know the severity of it until an angiogram a week later.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW HAVEN: INMATE NUMBERS UP  The inmate population in Connecticut has soared 86 percent to 17,700 since 1990, but the number of prison guards and other staff members has risen only 55 percent, to 7,000. The disparity means more guards are at risk for assault, the correction officers union said. A Department of Correction spokeswoman, Capt. Heather Ziemba, said the staff has grown proportionately with inmate growth.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>TRENTON: COLLEGE TUITION TO RISE  College students can expect to pay more this fall at every four-year college and university in New Jersey, according to figures supplied by the state Commission on Higher Education. The tuition increases, which do not include room and board, will range from about 3 to 10 percent. Princeton University posted the smallest increase at 3.2 percent, while Rowan University had the highest at 10.4 percent. Tuition will range from $3,375 at Richard Stockton College of New Jersey to $25,430 at Princeton.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
