<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Decisions, No Drama</title>
    <meta content="01ASSE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000817T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: NEWS ANALYSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Apple, R W Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E1D6103DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1413" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Decisions, No Drama</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Apple, R W Jr</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, July 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis by R W Apple of opening night of Republican National Convention in Philadelphia, characterized by tightly choreographed display of unity and lack of discord; says drama and eccentricity that characterized conventions of yesteryear have been drained from modern political conventions by adoption of new and unspoken guiding principle to 'do no harm' as both parties are confronted with uncomfortable realization that Americans hate partisanship and discord; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ronald Reagan used to preach what he called the 11th commandment: Speak no evil of other Republicans.</p>
        <p>But now his party, and the other one, too, have gone him one better, appropriating the physician's Hippocratic oath as the unspoken guiding principle for their quadrennial gatherings: First, do no harm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ronald Reagan used to preach what he called the 11th commandment: Speak no evil of other Republicans.</p>
        <p>But now his party, and the other one, too, have gone him one better, appropriating the physician's Hippocratic oath as the unspoken guiding principle for their quadrennial gatherings: First, do no harm.</p>
        <p>It is that thought, more than anything, that has drained all of the drama and much of the meaning from modern political conventions. No surprises are wanted these days. No sore losers. No floor fights. So long, eccentricity. Farewell, spontaneity; hello, choreography. No more smoke-filled rooms -- unless you count the convention hall, which is to be filled with artificial, politically correct smoke as part of the entertainment here.</p>
        <p>The Republicans, who began their national convention this morning, and the Democrats, who meet in Los Angeles next month, have been reading the polls and reflecting on the past. Partisans all, they are confronted with the uncomfortable finding that Americans, a few of whom may actually be watching on television, hate partisanship and discord.</p>
        <p>Perhaps it is the times. Perhaps it is because most people are happy with their lot, with the economy and with the course of the ship of state. If that is the reason for voters' aversion to conflict, feel-good conventions could be a passing phase. Hard times pose hard questions, and those questions get thrashed out not only in campaigns but also in the conventions preceding them.</p>
        <p>This year, though, it is pablum for breakfast, lunch and dinner.</p>
        <p>The original raison d'etre of conventions -- nominating candidates -- vanished a quarter-century ago. Not since the Republican gathering in Kansas City in 1976, when Gerald R. Ford barely held off Ronald Reagan, has there been a genuine contest for the presidential nomination at a convention of a major party. It was well past midnight when West Virginia finally gave Mr. Ford the votes he needed to go over the top.</p>
        <p>Not since 1940 has an outsider captured the nomination. At the Republican convention that year, Wendell L. Willkie finished third on the first ballot; it took his handlers many hours to put together the deals that gave him the nomination on the sixth.</p>
        <p>There will probably never again be a spectacle even remotely resembling the epic struggle between rural and urban interests at the 1924 Democratic convention in the first Madison Square Garden. John W. Davis of New York was chosen by exhausted delegates on the 103rd ballot, but the party had next to nothing left for the fall campaign, and Davis was trounced by Calvin Coolidge.</p>
        <p>The new reality is the consequence of the 1968 Democratic convention in Chicago, which was so rowdy, with spiteful oral combat inside the hall and a police riot outside, that the parties tore up their old rule books.</p>
        <p>Today almost all the delegates are chosen by voters in primaries and caucuses, not, as of old, by the political bosses. The delegates know months before they come to town whom they will vote for. They are bit players now, with no power.</p>
        <p>George W. Bush, the man they have come here to nominate, told The National Journal the other day that conventions have become an anachronism. But that, he insisted, does not -- should not -- mean they are on the way out.</p>
        <p>''The convention provides a system of rewards for hardworking, grass-roots people who end up being delegates,'' Mr. Bush said. ''I view it as an opportunity for these people to go back home, energized to help me get elected.''</p>
        <p>Fair enough. It also provides an excuse for a lot of parties, mostly paid for by big corporations, and yet another setting to raise money.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also said that the convention has become ''a place to showcase ideas more than in the past.'' Not exactly. To be precise, it has become a place to talk in muted terms about ideas that the nominee wishes to be heard. If there are abortion rights supporters at the podium this week, for example, they will talk about something else, thanks to what Mr. Bush calls his ''iron-fist'' control of the proceedings. But there will be no oratorical fire on the other side of the issue, either, and few attacks on the Democrats.</p>
        <p>That was the lesson that politicians drew from the contrasting conventions of 1992. The Republicans, nominating George Bush the elder, permitted the clergyman who delivered the opening-night invocation to compare abortion to the Holocaust and allowed Patrick J. Buchanan to issue a shrill call to arms for the ''religious war going on in our country for the soul of America.''</p>
        <p>Gov. Tom Ridge of Pennsylvania said this week, ''I felt absolutely terrible that night.'' Just like a lot of other people in the hall and out across the country.</p>
        <p>The Democrats, on the other hand, staged a pageant of unity behind Bill Clinton, denying Robert J. Casey, then the governor of Pennsylvania, a chance to state his anti-abortion position from the podium. Mr. Clinton won, of course, and a new bit of conventional political wisdom was born: Trouble in August means trouble in November.</p>
        <p>So there will be no echoes here of Barry Goldwater's belligerence in accepting the Republican presidential nomination in 1964.</p>
        <p>Quoting Cicero, Mr. Goldwater, senator from Arizona, told the delegates that ''extremism in defense of liberty is no vice,'' and that ''moderation in pursuit of justice is no virtue.'' He lost, as did William Jennings Bryan of Nebraska in 1896 after perhaps the most spellbinding of convention speeches. Siding with the Western populists against Eastern bankers, Bryan cried out, ''You shall not crucify mankind upon a cross of gold!''</p>
        <p>Nor will there be a surprise vice-presidential nominee. In 1956, Gov. Adlai E. Stevenson of Illinois left the choice to the delegates at the Democratic convention, and a youngster named John F. Kennedy, then a senator from Massachusetts, though narrowly defeated by Senator Estes Kefauver of Tennessee, set himself up for 1960. Kennedy, in turn, stunned the country by choosing Senator Lyndon B. Johnson of Texas as a running mate. And George Bush chose Dan Quayle, a senator from Indiana.</p>
        <p>Now a new tradition is emerging: choose the running mate before the convention, so as to eliminate that, too, as a potential disruption.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the drama of conventions has lain in credentials disputes.  At Chicago in 1952, Dwight D. Eisenhower's managers mounted a campaign of dubious legitimacy under the slogan ''Fair Play'' and succeeded in stripping Robert A. Taft of enough delegates to assure the general's nomination.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the drama has lain in the rules. At Miami Beach in 1972, the brain trust of Senator George McGovern of South Dakota deftly manipulated the rules to guarantee his victory.</p>
        <p>And sometimes -- often, in fact -- the drama has lain in the platform debate, where conflicting ideas on major issues were thrashed out.</p>
        <p>Here in Philadelphia 52 years ago this summer, Hubert H. Humphrey led a passionate campaign for civil rights. He told the delegates, assembled to nominate Harry S. Truman: ''There are those who say we are rushing this issue of civil rights. I say we are 172 years too late.''</p>
        <p>The Dixiecrats walked out, nominated Strom Thurmond for president and carried five states. But Truman won -- a reminder that it has by no means always been politically suicidal to stage a contentious and divisive convention.</p>
        <p>This year, neither convention is likely to tackle such important issues as drugs, campaign finance and the gulf between the rich and the poor. The Republicans, deeply divided on the issue of abortion, will display no prime time dissent; abortion-rights forces, who had enough votes in the platform committee to take a minority plank to the floor, decided to pass up that chance in the name of unity.</p>
        <p>''It's all propaganda,'' the chairman of the Republican National Committee in the 1996 convention, Haley Barbour, said. ''It's all a TV show. It's not news, but it's hugely important information for the American people.''</p>
        <p>Yet the question remains whether these carefully packaged four-day Republican and Democratic infomercials will influence the unaligned, uncommitted voters whom both parties say they want to reach.  With dissent muffled, with debate defunct, will they be stirred? The low turnouts in recent presidential elections suggest that all the staging in the world will not do the trick.</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: NEWS ANALYSIS  Correction:  August 17, 2000, Thursday  A front-page news analysis article on Aug. 1 about the effect of the Republican Party's efforts to keep its national convention free of discord misstated the source of the phrase ''do no harm.'' It is from Hippocrates' work ''Epidemics,'' not from the Hippocratic oath.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 17, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>A front-page news analysis article on Aug. 1 about the effect of the Republican Party's efforts to keep its national convention free of discord misstated the source of the phrase ''do no harm.'' It is from Hippocrates' work ''Epidemics,'' not from the Hippocratic oath.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
