<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Republicans Open Convention, Emphasizing Unity</title>
    <meta content="01CONV$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219344"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powell, Colin L (Gen) (Ret)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, Laura (Mrs George W Bush)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Diversity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E1DF113DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Republicans Open Convention, Emphasizing Unity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, July 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican National Convention opens in Philadelphia with keynote speeches by Gen Colin Powell and Laura Bush, wife of Gov George W Bush, forming centerpiece of tightly choreographed presentation that seems aimed at convincing public at large that its rightful place is in Republican Party; Powell challenges delegates to rally behind Bush's genuine commitment to minorities and appeals for inclusiveness; says party must make sustained effort to reach out to minority communities, particularly African-Americans; criticizes party's record on affirmative action; Laura Bush delivers warm testimonial about husband's values, extolling his commitment to education and literacy; says his core values will not change with with winds of polls or politics or 'fame, fortune or misfortune;' Bush addresses convention by satellite from Westerville, Ohio; applauds wife's speech; his effort to reach out to blacks is seen as part of determination to portray party as tolerant and inclusive, in hopes of appealing to independents and moderate Democrats; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Republican Party put on its newly moderate and disciplined face at the opening of its national convention today as one of the party's most compelling figures, Colin L. Powell, challenged delegates to rally behind Gov. George W. Bush with a genuine commitment to minorities.</p>
        <p>At the party's last convention in San Diego four years ago, General Powell appealed for inclusiveness and spoke of his support for affirmative action and abortion rights. Tonight, he repeated much of his rallying cry for inclusion -- but dropped any reference to abortion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Republican Party put on its newly moderate and disciplined face at the opening of its national convention today as one of the party's most compelling figures, Colin L. Powell, challenged delegates to rally behind Gov. George W. Bush with a genuine commitment to minorities.</p>
        <p>At the party's last convention in San Diego four years ago, General Powell appealed for inclusiveness and spoke of his support for affirmative action and abortion rights. Tonight, he repeated much of his rallying cry for inclusion -- but dropped any reference to abortion.</p>
        <p>''The party must follow Governor Bush's lead and reach out to minority communities and particularly the African-American community -- and not just during an election-year campaign,'' General Powell said pointedly. ''It must be a sustained effort. It must be every day. It must be for real.''</p>
        <p>He did not spare the party for its record on affirmative action. There was ''cynicism in the black community,'' he said, because ''some in our party miss no opportunity to roundly and loudly condemn affirmative action that helped a few thousands black kids get an education.''</p>
        <p>But, he added, ''hardly a whimper is heard from them over affirmative action for lobbyists who load our federal tax codes with preferences for special interests.''</p>
        <p>The address by General Powell, and a warm testimonial by Mr. Bush's wife, Laura, about education and her husband's values, formed the centerpiece tonight of a tightly and painstakingly choreographed presentation by the Bush campaign and by the Republican Party that was aimed far beyond the First Union Center. It was intended to convince the public at large -- particularly women, independents and even Democrats -- that their rightful place was in the Republican Party.</p>
        <p>The drive to put blacks out front tonight was especially striking, and persistent, and included things as diverse as the line-up of entertainers and the choice of General Powell as the keynote speaker. There was a live remote of a black preacher from a gospel church in South Philadelphia, followed by a performance of a gospel choir on stage in the hall.</p>
        <p>It made for a particularly sharp contrast with the audience because only 4 percent of convention delegates identify themselves as black, according to a survey by The New York Times and CBS News.</p>
        <p>For the Republicans, it was not so much a matter of reaching out for the black vote, but part of Mr. Bush's determination to portray his party as tolerant and inclusive, in hopes of appealing to independents and moderate Democrats.</p>
        <p>This image of a remade party was also unlikely given that many delegates seemed stirred by two famous faces of the past in the audience: Mr. Bush's mother and father.</p>
        <p>After the Bush campaign decreed there would be no searing swipes at Democrats, Mrs. Bush, in describing her husband, confined herself to an implict comparison with Bill Clinton and Al Gore, whom the campaign often portrays as obsessed by bald political calculations.</p>
        <p>''His core principles will not change with the winds of polls or politics or fame or fortune or misfortune,'' Mrs. Bush said of her husband. ''I know because I've known him through big legislative successes and a few defeats. I sat by his side during some winning and many losing baseball seasons. But George never loses sight of home plate.''</p>
        <p>In the testimonial to her husband of 22 years, she went on: ''He shares credit and doesn't cast blame. He sets a tone that's positive and constructive, a tone that is very different from the bitterness and division that too often characterizes Washington, D.C.''</p>
        <p>Her best-received line was when she declared that people tell her, ''I want my son or daughter to respect the president of the United States of America.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Bush, a former teacher and librarian, extolled her husband's commitment to education and literacy. And she said Mr. Bush was devoted to Head Start, a subject upon which the Republican ticket has become suddenly vulnerable because of votes cast against it by Dick Cheney, the vice-presidential candidate, when he was a congressman.</p>
        <p>''As first lady, I will make early childhood development one of my priorities,'' she said, ''and George will strengthen Head Start to make sure it's an early reading and early learning program.''</p>
        <p>While the party's new standard bearer was still wending his way eastward to Philadelphia as part of a six-day tour of swing states, Mr. Bush dominated the convention today. In a play on his nickname -- and an appeal to women -- the letter W  was emblazoned big and red on signs throughout the arena. Underneath, in smaller letters, were the words, ''Stands for women.''</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Bush was not entirely absent. Shortly after his wife's speech, he paid a surprise visit to the convention via satellite, from Westerville, Ohio, where he spoke from a classroom. Appearing on a giant screen, he applauded his wife's speech, and said, ''I can't wait to stand before you on Thursday night and tell America how I want to use these good times for great purposes.''</p>
        <p>Then he introduced General Powell with a hint that he would appoint him to serve in a Bush administration, declaring, ''I hope his greatest service to America still lies ahead.''</p>
        <p>While General Powell has been mentioned as a possible secretary of state, it was notable that Mr. Bush made those comments from a classroom and that General Powell spoke only about domestic issues. That may be, of course, that education was the dominant theme tonight.</p>
        <p>The remarks by General Powell, the former chairman of the joint chiefs of staff, were far more partisan than four years ago, when he had recently revealed that he was a Republican.</p>
        <p>When he addressed the convention in 1996, he also spoke of compassion and people in need. But in that speech, he reminded delegates of his support for abortion rights and, while he then saluted Bob Dole as a war hero, he was much more effusive this year about Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Bush appeared before the N.A.A.C.P. earlier this month, General Powell said, it was not mere window dressing. He quoted Mr. Bush's declaration that ''the party of Lincoln has not always carried the mantle of Lincoln.'' And he said that he spoke with Mr. Bush today and that ''he wants the Republican Party to wear that mantle again. But he knows that it will take hard work.''</p>
        <p>But the effort by General Powell to avoid saying anything that could stoke unrest among the roughly 22,000 people who crammed into the hall, including 2,066 delegates and 2,066 alternates, underscored the degree to which Republicans are united behind Mr. Bush in their determination to win back the White House. The program ran so tightly that at one point it was 20 minutes ahead of the minute-by-minute schedule.</p>
        <p>In his remarks, General Powell focused on Mr. Bush's achievements in Texas; he emphasized the ''compassion'' in the governor's ''compassionate conservative'' slogan.</p>
        <p>''For Texas, Governor Bush has reached out to all Texans -- white, black, Latino, Asian, native American,'' he said. ''He has been successful in bringing more and more minorities into the tent by responding to their deepest needs. Some call it compassionate conservatism. To me, it's just about caring about people.''</p>
        <p>The 37th Republican convention opened when Erik Weihenmayer, a blind mountain climber, led the delegates in the Pledge of Allegiance. Throughout the day, a parade of women, blacks, Latinos and recovered Democrats marched to the rostrum in a show that more resembled an Up With People jamboree than a hard-driving, calculated effort to retake the White House. Despite the understated references to the current administration, the words ''Clinton,'' ''abortion'' and ''impeachment'' appeared to have been banished from the scripts today. Even Newt Gingrich was far removed from the action; his role tonight was as a commentator for Fox News.</p>
        <p>That left those tuning in on television with a buffed view of the Republican Party -- and Mr. Bush -- far more moderate than the delegates in the hall who voted today for a platform that hewed to some fiercely conservative tenets, like the party's call for a ban on abortion. With the usual internecine maneuvering largely absent, and Mr. Cheney already selected as the running mate, there was little suspense.</p>
        <p>That was reflected in the lack of enthusiasm in a roll call to make Mr. Bush's nomination official -- the party's first three-day rolling roll call -- that drew only the most perfunctory rounds of cheers by delegates.</p>
        <p>Karl Rove, Mr. Bush's chief strategist, said he did not believe there was a contradiction between the moderate, inclusive message tonight and the fact that polls of the delegates show that they are notably conservative.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there's a gap between what Republicans believe and what their candidate does,'' said Mr. Rove, in an interview on ''Political Points,'' The New York Times/ABC News Webcast. ''Otherwise, they wouldn't have nominated him. And let me correct. You said inclusive and moderate. What we're saying is it's inclusive and compassionately conservative.''</p>
        <p>Despite all the stage managing, convention organizers had an easy job because delegate after delegate said the party had not been so unified since 1984, when Ronald Reagan cruised to a second term. On the opening night of that convention, in Detroit, Republicans bashed Walter F. Mondale relentlessly. But tonight, party officials expressed such confidence with Mr. Bush's positioning that they said they felt they could go easy on Vice President Gore.</p>
        <p>It was no accident that the party met here this week, the first Republican gathering in Philadelphia since Thomas E. Dewey won the nomination in 1948. The party this year was determined to underscore its commitment to a state that is not reliably Republican.</p>
        <p>In keeping with the effort to portray Mr. Bush as a leader who could work across party lines, his name was placed in nomination by his lieutenant governor, Rick Perry. Mr. Perry told reporters that Mr. Bush helped persuade him to defect from the Democratic Party to the Republicans more than a decade ago.</p>
        <p>''I proudly place the name of the current governor of the great state of Texas and the next president of the United States into nomination, George W. Bush,'' Mr. Perry said.</p>
        <p>While cable networks and Websites covered the evening's events extensively, coverage on the big three broadcast networks was fleeting and confined to the 10 o'clock hour at best. Only ABC covered any part of Mrs. Bush's address; CBS and ABC covered General Powell's speech virtually in its entirety. NBC relegated its prime-time coverage to MSNBC, its cable sister.</p>
        <p>Breaking from tradition, the Republicans abandoned their one-night roll calls of states, which officials said has become too interminable for a single sitting of prime-time television, and tonight began a rolling state-by-state tally that will be spread over three nights. The party was careful to juggle which states cast their votes so that Mr. Bush would not be officially nominated before Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's father and mother strode into the hall at 8:40 P.M. Their arrival was not announced. But as delegates began catching sight of these most famous of Republicans, a swell of applause came from the floor. When they were announced moments later, they were greeted with a 30-second standing ovation and chants of ''Bush! Bush! Bush!''</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
