<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State to Sue Over Uncertified Teachers</title>
    <meta content="01SUIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219268"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodnough, Abby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mills, Richard P (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O (Chancellor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2D9103DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="594" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State to Sue Over Uncertified Teachers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodnough, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Education Comr Richard P Mills surprises NYC Schools Chancellor Harold O Levy by announcing that he will go to court to ask judge to enforce his order prohibiting Levy from allowing uncertified teachers to work in failing schools (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York State's top education official surprised Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy yesterday by announcing that he would go to court today to ask a judge to enforce his order prohibiting Mr. Levy from allowing uncertified teachers to work in failing schools.</p>
        <p>Richard P. Mills, the state education commissioner, called reporters yesterday to inform them that he was taking legal action against Mr. Levy. Mr. Mills is angry because New York City last year violated a new state policy requiring that, after September 1999, only certified teachers be hired in 99 troubled schools known as schools under registration review.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York State's top education official surprised Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy yesterday by announcing that he would go to court today to ask a judge to enforce his order prohibiting Mr. Levy from allowing uncertified teachers to work in failing schools.</p>
        <p>Richard P. Mills, the state education commissioner, called reporters yesterday to inform them that he was taking legal action against Mr. Levy. Mr. Mills is angry because New York City last year violated a new state policy requiring that, after September 1999, only certified teachers be hired in 99 troubled schools known as schools under registration review.</p>
        <p>The city hired nearly 600 uncertified teachers to work in those schools last year because it could not find enough qualified teachers. Mr. Mills has repeatedly asked for assurance that Mr. Levy will reassign those teachers this year and hire only certified teachers for the 99 schools this fall. Mr. Mills said yesterday that he was going to take legal action in State Supreme Court in Brooklyn because Mr. Levy had not promised to do so.</p>
        <p>''The reason I am going to court to enforce the order is that I haven't received any assurance that this problem will be solved,'' Mr. Mills said. ''I see many good efforts under way, but good effort is not the point. It's good results that we need, and a qualified teacher for all the lowest-performing children.''</p>
        <p>Of the 585 uncertified teachers hired last year to work in underperforming schools, roughly 250 had been reassigned as of mid-July. The Board of Education has urged the remaining 335 to apply to a new alternative certification program that the State Board of Regents approved last month. But to participate, they would have to pass two state certification exams and take 200 hours of intensive training this summer.</p>
        <p>Many of these teachers have repeatedly failed the certification exams, and Mr. Mills said yesterday that the alternative certification program would not begin to solve the problem.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy said that he learned of Mr. Mills's plan to go to court only at the last minute. Mr. Levy said that he anticipated needing to hire at least several hundred certified teachers to comply with the order, but he added, ''I'm still hopeful that we can comply.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy's hands are at least partly tied, because the teachers' union contract prohibits him from transferring certified teachers against their will. The board has tried to get experienced teachers to transfer to failing schools, but with only moderate success. The union has warned that experienced teachers would abandon the city schools if they were forced to teach in schools where they did not want to work.</p>
        <p>The board will hold a recruitment fair for the 99 failing schools next week, Mr. Levy said. He would not say whether he was trying to negotiate new salary incentives for certified teachers who agree to work in failing schools, but he said that he was working on  last-minute recruitment plans. ''I have not given the commissioner a legal assurance because I am not convinced with legal certainty that we will be able to do this,'' he said. ''But I've got a couple more tricks up my sleeve. Stay tuned.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
