<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Griffey and Larkin Say No to the Mets Once Again</title>
    <meta content="01METS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cincinnati Reds</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cincinnati Reds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E2DF113DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="982" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Griffey and Larkin Say No to the Mets Once Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cincinnati Reds defeat New York Mets, 6-0; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rumors became reality three hours before the Mets played the Cincinnati Reds last night, and in their clubhouse at Shea Stadium, Mets players chatted about the comings and goings around the majors. They did not add or lose any teammates yesterday at the nonwaiver trading deadline, and this, they hope, is the group that will carry them into the postseason.</p>
        <p>When they took the field, on a damp, misty night, they encountered a Reds team with two players who could have been a part of their group. Ken Griffey Jr. and Barry Larkin both vetoed potential deals to the Mets within the last year, and they were pivotal in leading the Reds to a 6-0 victory last night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The rumors became reality three hours before the Mets played the Cincinnati Reds last night, and in their clubhouse at Shea Stadium, Mets players chatted about the comings and goings around the majors. They did not add or lose any teammates yesterday at the nonwaiver trading deadline, and this, they hope, is the group that will carry them into the postseason.</p>
        <p>When they took the field, on a damp, misty night, they encountered a Reds team with two players who could have been a part of their group. Ken Griffey Jr. and Barry Larkin both vetoed potential deals to the Mets within the last year, and they were pivotal in leading the Reds to a 6-0 victory last night.</p>
        <p>The loss was the first for the Mets on this homestand, which opened with six victories that had made the miserable weather easy to ignore.</p>
        <p>''It was a little gloomy out there tonight, but it's been gloomy the whole homestand,'' Mets starter Glendon Rusch said. ''But we've been winning, so it's all right.''</p>
        <p>The Mets' streak stopped last night, and not just because Griffey went 2 for 5 with two runs scored, Larkin singled home a run in the seventh and Dante Bichette drove in three runs. Reds starter Scott Williamson held the Mets scoreless for six innings, the reliever Larry Luebbers completed the shutout.</p>
        <p>The right-handed Williamson (4-7) had men on base in all of his innings, but the Mets were 0 for 6 off him with runners in scoring position. He gave up six hits, walking two and striking out three and outpitching Rusch, who fell to 7-8.</p>
        <p>''He'd throw one wild and then come in and hit the corner with it,'' said right fielder Bubba Trammell, one of three players the Mets acquired Friday, when they completed both of their predeadline deals. ''Effectively wild.''</p>
        <p>That was the popular term to describe Williamson, who threw two wild pitches last night to give him 19 for the season, tying a Cincinnati record. He came into the game averaging 6.5 walks per nine innings.</p>
        <p>Williamson, the National League's rookie of the year as a reliever last year, survived mainly with two pitches, a slider and a fastball. But they were enough.</p>
        <p>''He was on,'' Mets Manager Bobby Valentine said.</p>
        <p>So was Rusch, at least after a single by Griffey and a double by Bichette led to a three-run first inning for the Reds. Griffey doubled in the third and scored on Bichette's single, putting the Reds ahead, 4-0, but Rusch settled in, throwing three hitless, scoreless innings from the fourth through the sixth.</p>
        <p>Rusch found some comfort in his effectiveness after a rough beginning, a trait he has shown before this year.</p>
        <p>''Maybe early in my career, I'd let an inning like that take me out of the ballgame,'' Rusch said. ''I can't do that anymore. I need to be my own reliever, in a sense, erase that inning and do your job as long as you can.''</p>
        <p>Rusch left in the seventh inning after Pokey Reese reached on a fielding error by third baseman Robin Ventura. Larkin singled off Rick White to bring in that run, the first unearned run Rusch has allowed this year. Larkin, Cincinnati's shortstop, who nixed a deal to the Mets on July 22, leading to their successful pursuit of Mike Bordick from Baltimore, was razzed by the crowd of 42,774.</p>
        <p>''This crowd takes the team personally, and I think they felt a little personal attack there,'' Valentine said. ''But they know he's a tremendous player and respect him for that.''</p>
        <p>The Reds' seventh-inning rally managed to take Williamson from the game; the pitcher had a spasm in his left hamstring running the bases. But Luebbers came in to pitch three innings, earn a save and end a forgettable game.</p>
        <p>''It was an overcast, coolish night,'' Valentine said. ''The crowd didn't get into it, we didn't get into it. Just one of those nights.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Shortstop REY ORDONEZ, who was expected to be lost for the season, said he might be able to return next month. ''The doctor said everything is O.K., and I could maybe play in September,'' said Ordonez, who broke his left forearm on May 29 and had a metal plate and screws inserted in June. ''I'm not sure, but my arm is doing great. No pain, nothing.''</p>
        <p>Despite internal discussions about replacing Ordonez as the Mets' long-term shortstop -- with either MIKE BORDICK or Seattle's ALEX RODRIGUEZ, both potential free agents -- Ordonez said he was not concerned and had no questions for Manager BOBBY VALENTINE when the two spoke.</p>
        <p>''The last five years, it's the same thing: they're saying Alex Rodriguez is coming to New York,'' Ordonez said. ''It never happened. I can only worry about my arm now. I like New York. I'm waiting for my arm and I'll see what happens next year.''</p>
        <p>The left-handed reliever RICH RODRIGUEZ accepted a demotion to Class AAA Norfolk. He was designated for assignment on Friday and is off the 40-man roster, but General Manager STEVE PHILLIPS promised Rodriguez he would be promoted to the Mets in September, if not sooner. Rodriguez, who will earn $900,000 next season, has a 7.71 earned run average in 28 games this year.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
