<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Interests; G.O.P.'s Summer Of Love</title>
    <meta content="01COLL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Gail</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Gail Collins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2D6103DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Interests; G.O.P.'s Summer Of Love</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GAIL COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Gail</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gail Collins Op-Ed column on Republican National Convention in Philadelphia says that in producing convention that looks like America, George W Bush has manufactured one that looks nothing like his party (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thousands of Republican activists walked into the maw of the Philadelphia convention yesterday to begin their reprocessing. They arrived here as well-to-do white conservatives, a number of whom think trigger locks are unconstitutional and Social Security is a socialist scheme. But by Thursday night they are going to be nothing but a big, squishy bowl of inclusion that likes big hugs all around.</p>
        <p>Their reorientation program, otherwise known as the Republican National Convention, consists mainly of listening to: (a) blacks and Latinos talking about upward mobility; (b) white women talking about tax cuts; (c) the kinds of celebrities Bob Dole was complaining about in 1996; and (d) single moms, people who have overcome disabilities, people who are at least taking regular medication.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thousands of Republican activists walked into the maw of the Philadelphia convention yesterday to begin their reprocessing. They arrived here as well-to-do white conservatives, a number of whom think trigger locks are unconstitutional and Social Security is a socialist scheme. But by Thursday night they are going to be nothing but a big, squishy bowl of inclusion that likes big hugs all around.</p>
        <p>Their reorientation program, otherwise known as the Republican National Convention, consists mainly of listening to: (a) blacks and Latinos talking about upward mobility; (b) white women talking about tax cuts; (c) the kinds of celebrities Bob Dole was complaining about in 1996; and (d) single moms, people who have overcome disabilities, people who are at least taking regular medication.</p>
        <p>After an opening program that included a blind man who recited the Pledge of Allegiance (''He has climbed four of the world's highest mountains.''), a black woman who sang ''The Star-Spangled Banner'' (''Gloria is a well-known and forceful advocate for the homeless.'') and a Latino party activist who cried ''Puerto Rico I love you!,'' the delegates settled back to wait for the evening's big prime-time hour, which differed from what preceded mainly in that the people on the platform were famous women and minorities.</p>
        <p>In producing a convention that looks like America, George W. Bush has manufactured one that looks nothing whatsoever like his party. It's going to be hard to top the woman who ''won the Miss America pageant with an insulin pump under her evening gown.''</p>
        <p>The convention did grudgingly provide a few minutes of cable-only air time yesterday to some of the Republican candidates from hotly contested districts. The Senate hopefuls were totally off-message -- middle-aged white men in suits complaining about their opponents, liberal judges and Hillary Clinton's health care plan.</p>
        <p>Outside of abortion and gun control, the platform has been rewritten to cover all bases while offending no feelings. In one stroke of genius, the framers scrapped the old, non-inclusive call for elimination of the Department of Education and the National Endowment for the Arts in favor of: ''There are too many departments and agencies.'' Who could argue with that? And who could not agree with Tommy Thompson, the platform committee chairman, who told the convention, ''Our title says it all: Renewing America's Purpose Together.''</p>
        <p>In their drive to refashion themselves into non-threatening winners, Republicans are laying waste to anything that's left of the English language as a meaningful political tool. As a public speaker, Mr. Bush is naturally incoherent, and his genius is his ability to sound both sincere and indecipherable. ''If you don't know what you're supposed to know, we'll make sure you do early before it's too late,'' he said the other day, discussing education policy in Kentucky. He's still out campaigning in the heartland, making his way slowly, slowly toward Philadelphia. The crowds are enthusiastic, and the message is invariable: If you breathe, here's your man.</p>
        <p>''There are some people who think power resides in Washington and that's where the most important people are,'' said Representative Anne Northup at a rally in Louisville. ''But the truth is, the most important people are every American, up and down every street. These are the people that go to work every day. They care about their children.''</p>
        <p>This seems a little tough on the important people who live in Washington. (None of whom, of course, have anything whatsoever to do with this convention. The skyboxes are reserved solely for the homeless.) Do high-priced lobbyists not bleed? Do they not get up and go to work every day, and hug their children at night?</p>
        <p>Actually, the convention hasn't had much to say about lobbyists -- except one really nifty swipe by Gen. Colin Powell. They've been lumped in with the Christian right's agenda as the Reality That Dare Not Speak Its Name.</p>
        <p>There are still a few people worried about John McCain's prime-time moment tonight. Mr. McCain has fallen in the tank for the Bush campaign so often over the last few days that his suit is shrinking. But what would happen if his evil spirit took over and he launched into a bout of truth-telling about the relationship between the Republican Party and big money?</p>
        <p>At this convention, not much. Everybody would probably start singing ''Michael, Row the Boat Ashore,'' and drown him out.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
