<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. to Field A Dream Team</title>
    <meta content="02B06NWS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PLUS: TENNIS -- OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2DA1E3DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. to Field A Dream Team</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lindsay Davenport, Monica Seles and Venus and Serena Williams were named by the United States Tennis Association yesterday to the American women's team for the Olympics in Sydney, Australia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lindsay Davenport, Monica Seles and Venus and Serena Williams were named by the United States Tennis Association yesterday to the American women's team for the Olympics in Sydney, Australia.</p>
        <p>Davenport, Seles and Venus Williams will compete in singles play, while the Williams sisters will team for doubles competition. Last month, the U.S.T.A. named the Hall of Famer Billie Jean King to coach the team. The competition is scheduled for Sept. 19-28 at the New South Wales Tennis Center.</p>
        <p>Davenport, 24, is the defending gold medalist in women's singles, having defeated Spain's Arantxa Sanchez Vicario in Atlanta in 1996. Seles, 26, reached the quarterfinals of the 1996 games, losing to the eventual bronze medalist Jana Novotna.</p>
        <p>(Bloomberg News)</p>
        <p>BARCELONA TO HOST DAVIS CUP FINAL: Barcelona's Palau Sant Jordi Arena will be the site fo the Davis Cup final between Spain and Australia, Dec. 8-10, the Spanish Tennis Federation said yesterday. Spain completed a 5-0 thrashing of the United States in Santander on July 23 while Australia beat Brazil by the same score on July 15 in Brisbane.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)  EARLY EXIT FOR NORMAN: Magnus Norman of Sweden, who said he wanted to prove he deserved the world's No. 1 ranking heading to the United States Open, was beaten by Richard Krajicek yesterday in the first round of the Tennis Masters Series-Canada in Toronto.</p>
        <p>Norman, seeded third in the ATP hardcourt tournament behind Andre Agassi and Pete Sampras, did not hide his disgust after a 7-5, 7-6 (7) loss.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, I had bigger hopes than going out in the first round here,'' said Norman, whose six-week tenure stop the ranking will probably end after the event. ''But I didn't lose to Mr. Nobody. I lost to a good player.''</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>EARLY EXIT FOR NORMAN: Magnus Norman of Sweden, who said he wanted to prove he deserved the world's No. 1 ranking heading to the United States Open, was beated by Richard Krajicek yesterday in the first round of the Tennis Masters Series-Canada in Toronto.</p>
        <p>Norman, seeded third in the ATP hardcourt tournament behind Andre Agassi and Pete Sampras, did not hide his disgust after a 7-5, 7-6 (7) loss.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, I had bigger hopes than going out I the first round here,'' said Norman, whose six-week tenure atop the ranking will probably end after the event. ''But I didn't lose to Mr. Nobody. I lost to a good player.''</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>VAN ROOST TRIUMPHS: Dominique Van Roost scored a 6-2, 7-6, (4) victory over Ai Sugiyama in the first round of the $535,000 Acura Classic yesterday in Carlsbad, Calif. Van Roost, ranked 15th in the world, broke Sugiyana's serve four times in the first set, and she broke Sugiyama again to go ahead by 4-2 in the second set. She then struggled before taking control in the tie breaker.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>PLUS: TENNIS -- OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
