<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Interloper Ants Keep It All in the Family</title>
    <meta content="01ANT.$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219216"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Argentina</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Christensen, Jon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E2D6133DF932A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Interloper Ants Keep It All in the Family</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON CHRISTENSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Christensen, Jon</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Argentine ants are overwhelming native California ants while forming what scientists believe may be a supercolony stretching from San Diego to north of San Francisco; are are so genetically similar that different colonies do not fight with one another, as they do with fierceness in Argentina, and present a united family front to win territory from native California ants, which are vital to survival of certain plant and lizard species; supercolony also poses unsolved riddle about the evolution of so-called unicolonial insects and even raises possibility of an insect world dominated by invasive unicolonial species; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a quirk of evolution and genetics, Argentine ants are overwhelming native California ants while forming what scientists believe may be the biggest ant colony in the world, stretching more than 600 miles from San Diego to north of San Francisco.</p>
        <p>The ants in this so-called supercolony are so genetically similar that different colonies do not fight with one another the way they do in their homeland. As a result, they are using a united family front to win territory from native ants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a quirk of evolution and genetics, Argentine ants are overwhelming native California ants while forming what scientists believe may be the biggest ant colony in the world, stretching more than 600 miles from San Diego to north of San Francisco.</p>
        <p>The ants in this so-called supercolony are so genetically similar that different colonies do not fight with one another the way they do in their homeland. As a result, they are using a united family front to win territory from native ants.</p>
        <p>In Argentina, where they are known as sugar ants, different nests of the fiercely territorial ants fight with one another, competing for food and space. An ant that wanders into the territory of another colony just 50 yards away will quickly be torn apart by workers, which recognize the peculiar odor of a rival. But in California, scientists found that they could take a worker from San Diego and put it in a colony from San Francisco and it would be welcomed like a kissing cousin.</p>
        <p>Using the same DNA fingerprinting techniques used in paternity cases, scientists at the University of California at San Diego looked at the genetic differences between ants in Argentina and California. They discovered more than twice as much genetic diversity among Argentine ants in their native range compared with those in California.</p>
        <p>Published reports and museum samples showed that Argentine ants first came to the United States aboard ships carrying coffee and sugar from South America during the 1890's. The scientists concluded that the relatively small immigrant populations created a ''genetic bottleneck,'' choking off genetic diversity. The small founding populations represented less than half the genetic diversity of the species.</p>
        <p>That has made almost all Argentine ants in California similar enough that they can no longer distinguish between close kin and ants from other nests, a critical mechanism in the evolution of social insects. So instead of defending separate territories, the ants behave like a single fluid colony in their new territory.</p>
        <p>And though the Argentine ants appear to have mel-  lowed out  among themselves in California and are mostly just a nuisance to humans, they ruthlessly kill and displace native ants, some of which are 20 times as large as the Argentines. The effects of the invasion ripple through the ecosystem. Some plants, like tree poppies, depend on native ants for seed dispersal. And large native harvester ants make up more than 90 percent of the diet of coastal horned lizards, commonly known as horny toads and a candidate for the endangered species list.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ted J. Case, a biologist at the University of California at San Diego, has spent much of his career studying population changes among reptiles on islands and in isolated patches of natural habitat like parks in suburban California.</p>
        <p>When a statewide survey of reptiles and amphibians found a precipitous decline in the population of coastal horned lizards, Dr. Case thought that changes in the lizard's food base might be involved. So he pulled together a team of scientists and students to study the tiny Argentine ants, which are about a fifth of an inch long.</p>
        <p>The DNA detective work capped a five-year investigation of the ecology, behavior and genetics of the ants. By comparing Argentine ants in their native and invaded ranges, the scientists solved an intriguing puzzle in the increasingly important field of invasion biology, which is the study of invasive species. Most invasive species move into a territory that has been opened up by changes in habitat and local extinction of native species, Dr. Case said. But in the case of Argentine ants, a genetic change set off changes in behavior and colony structure that enabled the invader to conquer new territory by eliminating native species.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the huge supercolony of Argentine ants in California continues to pose an unsolved riddle about the evolution of so-called unicolonial insects, which act as single colonies over large areas. And it raises the creepy possibility of an insect world dominated by invasive unicolonial species.</p>
        <p>Scientists play down that possibility. The loss of genetic diversity is generally considered to be detrimental to the survival of a species, said Neil Tsutsui, a graduate student who did the genetics research in Dr. Case's laboratory. The loss of kinship recognition is an even bigger problem for social insects, he said. The only way female workers, which make up the bulk of the colony, can ensure that their genes are passed on to future generations is by protecting closely related queens. So it is assumed that workers work only for queens that share their genes. But if workers cannot distinguish between their kin and any other ants, they end up working for the whole supercolony. And then there is no way for natural selection to favor any one queen and her workers over any other in the colony.</p>
        <p>If unicolonial insects were successful in the grand sweep of evolutionary time, Dr. Case said, they would probably appear more often. Unicoloniality may be useful in the short term, as it is for Argentine ants and some other invasive ants, he said, but in the long run it appears to be an evolutionary dead end because social behavior could not evolve.</p>
        <p>That is little consolation for residents of Southern California, where the small, dark brown and black Argentine ants are the No. 1 pest that extermination companies are called upon to eliminate.</p>
        <p>In contrast, it took a week for researchers to even find the ants in Argentina. ''It was eye-opening to see how inconspicuous they were in Argentina,'' Dr. Case said. ''Even in areas where they're relatively common, they're not dominant. They're not a pest. So then the question was, what has enabled them to be so successful here?''</p>
        <p>In California, the researchers have no trouble finding ants to study. There are Argentine ants invading the chaparral-covered ocean bluffs around the University of California at San Diego. There are Argentine ants scurrying along cracks in sidewalks on campus. And there are Argentine ants swarming by the elevator on the ground floor of the biology building.</p>
        <p>Although colleagues have joked that the researchers have aided and abetted the invasion, Dr. Case's lab keeps its ants under strict control, in plastic tubs coated with a slippery Teflon-like substance that ants cannot climb. The lips of tubs are coated with a sticky substance that traps any ants that might find a trail to the top. In the lab, different colonies of Argentine ants are connected by plastic tubing to common foraging areas -- tubs with water and food.</p>
        <p>By not fighting among themselves, Argentine ants in the supercolony gain a competitive advantage over other ants, said Dr. David Holway, a postdoctoral researcher who designed experiments to test the supercolony's advantage over colonies that fight with one another. The experiments showed that Argentine ants that cooperated with one another produced more than three times the brood and more than twice as many workers as colonies that fought with one another.</p>
        <p>The experiments also showed the advantage the supercolony ants had over native ants. The Argentine ants get to food faster, overwhelm rivals with sheer numbers of workers, and defend their territory with chemical weapons they spray on opponents. ''The Argentine ants win in a few days,'' Andrew Suarez, a graduate student, said with grim admiration. Mr. Suarez's family came from Argentina, and his grandmother put up the research team members when they studied the ants there.</p>
        <p>He said the experimental results helped explain why some parts of California that were once home to as many as 20 different species of ants now contained as few as two: Argentine ants and a native species that is active in the winter, when the Argentine ants are less active.</p>
        <p>''Some people say, 'Big deal; you're just replacing some ants with others,' '' Mr. Suarez said. ''But the thing is, you're displacing 20 species. And all the roles they play are wiped out: dispersing seeds, pollinating plants, providing food for other animals. All the functions are totally lost when Argentine ants move in.''</p>
        <p>Friends and neighbors often ask the researchers how to deal with Argentine ants in their homes. Because their research indicates that lack of moisture is the only factor that seems to limit the spread of Argentine ants, they suggest a simple solution: replacing lush lawns with desert landscaping. ''You wouldn't have them if there were native plants and cactus and San Diego looked like it should,'' Mr. Suarez said.</p>
        <p>In their research papers, the scientists have also suggested that more Argentine ants could be introduced to California to increase their genetic diversity so that the ants would again fight with one another and contain their own populations. But they conceded that it was an academic idea unlikely to be practical. Any introduced populations would probably be quickly wiped out by the supercolony, Mr. Tsutsui said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Case's laboratory is now collaborating with scientists at Clorox who are studying the chemicals that ants smell to identify nest mates. If they could create a chemical that identifies ants as enemies of the supercolony, then they might be able to spray the chemical on half of the colony and let the Argentine ants fight to the death.</p>
        <p>Another more grim possibility is that another invasive species could offer some competition for the Argentine ants. In the Southeastern United States, imported red fire ants seem to have limited the spread of Argentine ants. The fire ants come from the same South American habitat as the Argentine ants. And they are also an invasive unicolonial species. But unlike Argentine ants, which spread slowly without help from humans and took a century to spread throughout most of coastal California, fire ant queens and winged males take nuptial flights and establish new far-flung colonies. They have invaded California just in the last few years. And they are even meaner than Argentine ants.</p>
        <p>Dr. Case is chagrined to see another invasive species come to California. Especially one that bites, he said. But he and his colleagues are also students of invasions and species change. And the coming showdown between Argentine and fire ants will offer another opportunity to study an invasion as it happens.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
