<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>European Cities Of Two Minds On One Bourse</title>
    <meta content="Y20BOU$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200827"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Frankfurt Stock Exchange</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">London Stock Exchange</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EEDF133AF933A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="892" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>European Cities Of Two Minds On One Bourse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>FRANKFURT, May 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pioneering merger of London and Frankfurt stock exchanges is running into heavy resistance in both cities; German regulators and state-owned banks fear Frankfurt will lose control over market for small growth companies, which has been huge success in last three years; British officials fear Frankfurt will take all good business and that London traders will be left with little except costs of switching over to Frankfurt's system for electronic trading; some British executives also complain that merger has been engineered by big American investment banks that want lower trading costs even if London is diminished as financial center; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The pioneering merger of the London and Frankfurt stock exchanges is running into heavy resistance in both cities.</p>
        <p>In Germany, regulators and the nation's state-owned banks fear that Frankfurt will lose control over the market for small growth companies, which has been a huge success here in the last three years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The pioneering merger of the London and Frankfurt stock exchanges is running into heavy resistance in both cities.</p>
        <p>In Germany, regulators and the nation's state-owned banks fear that Frankfurt will lose control over the market for small growth companies, which has been a huge success here in the last three years.</p>
        <p>In Britain, the fear is that Frankfurt will grab all the good business and that London traders will be left with little except the costs of switching over to Frankfurt's system for electronic trading.</p>
        <p>Some British executives also complain that the merger has been engineered by big American investment banks that want lower trading costs even if London is diminished as a financial center.</p>
        <p>But even some of Europe's biggest trading institutions, which badly want a more efficient pan-European stock market, are complaining that the deal announced two weeks ago has serious problems.</p>
        <p>''Everyone is in favor of getting a single trading system, but this isn't the way to do it,'' said an executive at a London trading institution. ''This is two exchanges that are trying to carve up everything for themselves and monopolize the market.''</p>
        <p>Under the deal, the market for smaller growth stocks is to be based in Frankfurt while London assumes responsibility for blue-chip stocks.</p>
        <p>But the two exchanges also plan to form a joint venture with Nasdaq, which is focused on the same kinds of small technology stocks in the United States. The joint venture will be incorporated in London.</p>
        <p>Executives at both exchanges say their merger plans are still on track. The supervisory board of Deutsche Borse, the parent of the Frankfurt exchange, will vote next Tuesday on the plan, which needs support from three-quarters of the members.</p>
        <p>But at least 2 of the 21 board members have publicly criticized the plan. More ominously, the economics minister for the state of Hesse, who regulates the Frankfurt exchange, is raising pointed questions as well.</p>
        <p>And Donald Cruickshank, chairman of the London Stock Exchange, acknowledged on Wednesday that members of the London exchange would not approve the merger until they received more detailed information. That will not be coming until July, because many details remain to be negotiated.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Dieter Posch, the economics minister of Hesse, the state that includes Frankfurt, has demanded that the Deutsche Borse answer a list of 14 detailed questions.</p>
        <p>Addressing Werner G. Seifert, chairman of Deutsche Borse, Mr. Posch questioned whether it was even realistic to create a system that would operate under two regulatory regimes -- a British one for blue-chip stocks, and the German one for small growth stocks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Posch also demanded to know whether the Nasdaq venture would be managed from London; why the parent company of the new exchange, called iX, will be based in London; and whether German investors might end up paying higher transaction fees if they had to buy German blue-chip stocks in London.</p>
        <p>Germany's powerful Bundesbank, whose board members heard a presentation by Mr. Seifert on Thursday, seems to cautiously support the merger.</p>
        <p>At a news conference today, a Bundesbank board member, Hans Reckers, warned that Frankfurt had to keep control of trading in small growth stocks but said that the merger was fundamentally positive.</p>
        <p>The main opposition in Germany appears to be coming from publicly owned savings banks and cooperative banks. Manfred Zass, head of the DGZ Dekabank in Frankfurt and a member of the German stock exchange's supervisory board, said on Wednesday that he would not agree to a merger that amounted to a ''takeover'' of the Frankfurt market.</p>
        <p>Heinz Hilgert, a managing director at SGZ Bank, a cooperative bank in Frankfurt, said today that the overriding fear of smaller banks was of losing control of the market for growth stocks -- the ''neue markt.''</p>
        <p>''This is clearly the domain of cooperative and public-sector savings banks, in both I.P.O.'s and in trading,'' Mr. Hilgert said. ''The growth of this growth market has been in German, not Spanish, not French and certainly not British,'' he added, referring to companies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hilgert predicted that Nasdaq's American executives would inevitably view London rather than Frankfurt as their European center.</p>
        <p>But some British executives are worried that London will lose its primacy, noting that Mr. Seifert is to become chief executive of the combined entity.</p>
        <p>''The proposed takeover of the London Stock Exchange -- for that is effectively what it is -- by the Deutsche Borse has serious implications for London's continued role,'' wrote George Cox, director general of a British business association called the Institute of Directors.</p>
        <p>In a letter to The Financial Times, Mr. Cox said that Mr. Seifert ''is hardly likely to have London's interests as his main concern'' and that the merger was being promoted by a small group of ''powerful stock exchange members, all of whom appear to be American.''</p>
        <p>Goldman Sachs was the lead investment bank advising Deutsche Borse, while Merrill Lynch was among the banks advising the London Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
