<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="20FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200874"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EFD9133AF933A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1169" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>A G.O.P. Senator Blocks Money for Peacekeepers  Senator Judd Gregg of New Hampshire has used his power as chairman of a Senate appropriations subcommittee to singlehandedly stop the United States from paying $368 million it owes the United Nations for peacekeeping missions in Congo, East Timor, Kosovo and Sierra Leone, infuriating the Clinton administration and some of its allies.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>A G.O.P. Senator Blocks Money for Peacekeepers  Senator Judd Gregg of New Hampshire has used his power as chairman of a Senate appropriations subcommittee to singlehandedly stop the United States from paying $368 million it owes the United Nations for peacekeeping missions in Congo, East Timor, Kosovo and Sierra Leone, infuriating the Clinton administration and some of its allies.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>More U.N. Troops for Africa  The Security Council increased the number of troops allowed in the United Nations peacekeeping force in Sierra Leone by 2,000 and was expected to expand the force further.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>New Era Begins in Taiwan  Chen Shui-bian was sworn in as president, ending 50 years of rule by the Nationalist Party.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Europe and China Trade Talks  Negotiators agreed on terms for China's entry into the World Trade Organization.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Renewed Violence in Mideast  Bloody clashes occurred in the West Bank and Gaza, and fighting intensified in southern Lebanon. The Israeli prime minister, Ehud Barak, considered canceling his departure for the United States, where he had planned to meet with President Clinton and Jewish-American leaders.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Step Toward Irish Peace Stalls  David Trimble, the Ulster Unionist leader, postponed a meeting of his ruling council set for today to gain time to persuade the party to endorse an I.R.A. offer to permit international inspections of its secret arms dumps. But the debate is also turning on issues like what flag flies atop government buildings and what symbols end up on officers' uniforms.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Serb Opposition Seeks Help  Political opposition leaders said they would go to Moscow to seek help in getting President Slobodan Milosevic to moderate his policies.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Voter Boycott Urged in Peru  Alejandro Toledo, who dropped out of the presidential race, urged people not to vote in the second round, on May 28, and to stage peaceful protests to discredit the vote.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A9-13, 16</p>
        <p>N.R.A. Members Gather, Vowing to Fight New Limits  Thousands of gun owners gathered in Charlotte, N.C., for the N.R.A.'s annual convention, vowing to fight new firearms restrictions and, with encouragement from the group's president, Charlton Heston, to take their pro-gun sentiments into voting booths this fall. The group also announced plans to open a theme store and restaurant in Times Square.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Fire Renews Concern Over Lab  The fires that consumed nearly 50,000 acres of northern New Mexico, including parts of the Los Alamos National Laboratory, have raised new concerns over the buildup of nuclear and hazardous waste at the laboratory. Officials said the fires were 70 percent under control.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Recreating an Army Institution  The Army's School of the Americas, which has trained generations of soldiers from Central and South America, is on the verge of getting a new charter, a new curriculum and a new name -- the Defense Institute for Hemispheric Security Cooperation. But critics who have linked the school and some of its graduates to human rights violations are not expected to abandon their protests.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>U.S. Classifies a Criticism  The Pentagon has classified as secret an antimissile critic's letter to the White House, even though it has been widely distributed and is available on the Internet, leaving the critic, Theodore A. Postol, an M.I.T. professor, crying foul.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Bitter House Debate on Census  Republicans suggested the Clinton administration was trying to manipulate the count to benefit Democrats, and Democrats insinuated that Republicans did not want to count members of minority groups.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Director Apologizes for Ad  Ridley Scott, whose ''Gladiator'' is No. 1 at the box office, has apologized for a trade publication ad that heightened tensions in a three-week-old actors' strike. The ad depicts a black woman's bare breasts.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>The Other Jackpot Winner  A Chicago-area family that owns a small brewery and a medical supply company collected their half of the $363 million Big Game lottery prize. They chose a lump sum, worth about $61 million after taxes.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Beliefs</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>Giuliani Bows Out of Race; G.O.P. Backs Congressman  Mayor Giuliani withdrew from the Senate race, saying his health and treatment for prostate cancer were more important to him than running against Hillary Rodham Clinton. The state Republican Party immediately pledged support for Representative Rick A. Lazio of Long Island. Mr. Giuliani said he would devote his remaining 18 months in office to being a better person and mayor, one who reaches out to minority residents.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's supporters see his lack of name recognition as a potential plus: He does not arouse the strong antipathy that both Mr. Giuliani and Mrs. Clinton do in various quarters.</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton wished the mayor a ''full and speedy recovery,'' but deflected questions about how his withdrawal affected her campaign.</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Insurgent Loses Support  Assemblyman Michael J. Bragman admitted his effort to depose Speaker Sheldon Silver had sputtered, though he intended to press on.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Inducements for Film Studio  New York State, New Jersey and Connecticut are competing for a film studio that would be built by Robert De Niro and Miramax Films. A tentative deal with New York City collapsed seven months ago.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>$50 Million Scholarship Offer  An organization co-founded by the financier Theodore J. Forstmann offered $50 million in aid to underprivileged children to try to fill all 7,500 empty seats in parochial and private schools in New York City.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B13-24</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Warning on Diabetes Drugs  Doctors at an F.D.A. meeting on the withdrawn drug Rezulin warned that people taking two newer drugs, Avandia and Actos, should be checked for signs of liver trouble.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14</p>
        <p>Stock Markets Head Lower  The Nasdaq dropped 148.31 points, or 4.2 percent, to 3,390.40; the Dow fell 150.43 points, or 1.4 percent, to 10,626.85; and the S.&amp; P. 500 lost 30.26 points, or 2.1 percent, to 1,406.95. Investors expressed concern about further interest rate increases.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Trouble for Markets' Merger  The pioneering merger of the London and Frankfurt stock exchanges is running into heavy resistance.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Variation of Malicious Program  Antivirus software companies warned of a program circulating on the Net, similar to but more malicious than the one that disrupted computer systems this month.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Knicks Hang On  The Knicks beat the Heat, 72-70, tying the Eastern Conference semifinals at 3-3. New York will play Miami Sunday in Miami.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>The winner of Sunday's game will face Indiana, who beat the Philadelphia 76ers, 106-90.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A14-15</p>
        <p>Editorials: Mr. Giuliani stays at City Hall; obviating affirmative action; trials for the Khmer Rouge.</p>
        <p>Columns: Frank Rich, Anthony Lewis.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B22</p>
        <p>TV Listings</p>
        <p>B24</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>B20</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Public Lives</p>
        <p>A9</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
