<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Siblings of Starved Boy Taken From Mother</title>
    <meta content="20STAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200861"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Administration for Children's Services (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barnes, Julian E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Renee C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, David (Abuse Victim)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E5DA133AF933A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="556" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Siblings of Starved Boy Taken From Mother</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIAN E. BARNES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barnes, Julian E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Social workers take custody of Renee C Jones' two surviving children after New York City medical examiner rules that her 10-year-old son, David Jones, died of starvation and dehydration; two surviving children are placed together in a foster home according to spokeswoman for Administration for Children's Services; investigators have not determined if charges will be filed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Social workers took custody of a Brooklyn woman's two surviving children this week after the New York City medical examiner ruled that her 10-year-old son had died of starvation and dehydration.</p>
        <p>The child who died, David Jones, was one of triplets, and the two other children were placed together in a foster home, said Jennifer Falk, a spokeswoman for the Administration for Children's Services. The agency had been monitoring the family since David died on Feb. 17, but did not take the children until shortly after the Medical Examiner's office ruled on Monday that the boy's death was a homicide, she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Social workers took custody of a Brooklyn woman's two surviving children this week after the New York City medical examiner ruled that her 10-year-old son had died of starvation and dehydration.</p>
        <p>The child who died, David Jones, was one of triplets, and the two other children were placed together in a foster home, said Jennifer Falk, a spokeswoman for the Administration for Children's Services. The agency had been monitoring the family since David died on Feb. 17, but did not take the children until shortly after the Medical Examiner's office ruled on Monday that the boy's death was a homicide, she said.</p>
        <p>The Administration for Children's Services has no other abuse reports against the woman, Renee C. Jones, either before or after the boy's death, Ms. Falk said.</p>
        <p>Kevin Davitt, a spokesman for the Brooklyn district attorney's office, said his office was investigating the case but had not yet decided what charges, if any, to bring.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jones called the police on Feb. 17, when her son fell unconscious in their Cobble Hill apartment after saying he felt sick, police officers said. The boy was taken to Long Island College Hospital, where he was pronounced dead upon his arrival.</p>
        <p>Although doctors at first thought the cause of death might be a viral infection, the medical examiner's office, the police and children's services all began investigating the case, officials said.</p>
        <p>Daniel was 4 feet 6 inches tall but weighed just 50 pounds at the time of his death, the medical examiner's spokeswoman, Ellen Borakove, said yesterday. Most boys that height and age weigh about 70 pounds, she said.</p>
        <p>In an interview Thursday evening, Ms. Jones denied that she had abused her son and that he was malnourished. Ms. Jones did not respond to a phone message left at her home yesterday. Her lawyer, Brian Dworkin, also would not comment. ''In these kinds of cases, there are always a lot of questions,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A few neighbors said the mother and children appeared thin to them. But most said they never suspected anything was wrong until rumors began circulating around the building recently.</p>
        <p>Although the determination on Monday that David had died of malnutrition came almost three months after his death, investigators said they could not find fault with the medical examiner. Starvation is more difficult to diagnose than other types of abuse, investigators said.</p>
        <p>The medical examiner's office interviewed people who knew David, reviewed his medical records, screened for toxins, examined brain tissue and conducted other tests.</p>
        <p>''When there is no obvious cause of death you have to look harder and do more work,'' Ms. Borakove said.</p>
        <p>Starvation cases are also more difficult to prosecute, and detectives are moving carefully, law enforcement officials said. Detectives have questioned Ms. Jones but are seeking to talk to her further, officers said.</p>
        <p>Investigators said that before they decide whether to file charges, several questions must be answered, including why David's siblings appear to be in good health while their brother starved to death.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
