<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Clean Bill of Fare</title>
    <meta content="20ZAGA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200813"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sanitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Health Department (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zagat, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFD6123AF933A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="546" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Clean Bill of Fare</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tim Zagat</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zagat, Tim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tim Zagat Op-Ed article reports that New York City Health Department's new Web site listing restaurant sanitation violations gives out information to which public is entitled, but also highlights problems with city's inspection and reporting system (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York City Health Department's new Web site listing restaurants' sanitary  violations gives the public information it has a right to know. Making it available to everyone should help force restaurants to become more vigilant in maintaining high standards of cleanliness. But the Web site also highlights problems with the city's inspection and reporting system.</p>
        <p>The site does not make clear what many of the reported violations represent and how serious they really are. La Caravelle, for example, is cited as having ''vermin,'' but the vermin in question was a fly that was found during an inspection last summer -- hardly a cause for panic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York City Health Department's new Web site listing restaurants' sanitary  violations gives the public information it has a right to know. Making it available to everyone should help force restaurants to become more vigilant in maintaining high standards of cleanliness. But the Web site also highlights problems with the city's inspection and reporting system.</p>
        <p>The site does not make clear what many of the reported violations represent and how serious they really are. La Caravelle, for example, is cited as having ''vermin,'' but the vermin in question was a fly that was found during an inspection last summer -- hardly a cause for panic.</p>
        <p>Le Bernardin is also cited for vermin -- one bag of flour, which was never used and was eventually returned to the distributor, was found to have mouse droppings inside. But in fact Le Bernardin's kitchen is one of the city's cleanest, as any patron can see: from the dining room, the kitchen is visible through a glass wall.</p>
        <p>The city's inspection system needs to be re-evaluated to make sure that the most honest and important information is made available but does not cause unnecessary public fear. It is fair to ask a number of questions:  How many inspectors are there, and how often do they inspect? What are the inspectors' qualifications?</p>
        <p>Some restaurants appear to have had numerous violations in a review period and yet remained open. If a restaurant is in a dangerous condition, what kind of violation is necessary to close it? If the Health Department has chosen not to close a restaurant, does that mean the restaurant has been determined to be essentially safe?</p>
        <p>Health inspections are a sensitive subject in the city's restaurant industry, given what happened in the 1980's,  when nearly 40 inspectors were convicted for taking payoffs from restaurants that feared the publication of violations. This should not prevent the Health Department from providing greater disclosure, but it does suggest the need for extreme care. Perhaps the city should follow the example of Los Angeles, where each restaurant is given an A, B or C rating for overall cleanliness and then required to post it at the front entrance.</p>
        <p>Given the importance of this subject, the serious business implications for restaurants and the good intentions of the Health Department, it would be wise for the department to get together with leading restaurateurs to discuss what system would best serve the public's interest in health and disclosure.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, anyone who is really interested in how food is being prepared in a restaurant need only ask to see the kitchen. I do this frequently. Believe me, these visits can be very revealing. Should a restaurant refuse to show you its kitchen, you would be well advised to eat elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Tim Zagat is publisher of Zagat's restaurant guides.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Tim Zagat is publisher of Zagat's restaurant guides.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
