<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Second Half of $363 Million Lottery Is Claimed</title>
    <meta content="20LOTT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200832"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lotteries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Illinois</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kainz, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lotteries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EFDE133AF933A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="668" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Second Half of $363 Million Lottery Is Claimed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, May 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joe Kainz, 64, whose family operates small brewery in Chicago area, claims second half of $363-million Big Game lottery jackpot (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A brewer and his family collected their half of the $363 million Big Game lottery jackpot here today, after waiting nearly two weeks to identify themselves as one of two winners of the largest lottery prize ever awarded in America.</p>
        <p>Joe Kainz, 64, and his wife, Sue, 62, of Tower Lakes, a northwest suburb of Chicago, accepted their winnings today with their three sons and daughter-in-law. The other winner, the owner of a swimming pool company from suburban Detroit, stepped forward last week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A brewer and his family collected their half of the $363 million Big Game lottery jackpot here today, after waiting nearly two weeks to identify themselves as one of two winners of the largest lottery prize ever awarded in America.</p>
        <p>Joe Kainz, 64, and his wife, Sue, 62, of Tower Lakes, a northwest suburb of Chicago, accepted their winnings today with their three sons and daughter-in-law. The other winner, the owner of a swimming pool company from suburban Detroit, stepped forward last week.</p>
        <p>The Kainz family owns and operates a small brewery and a medical supply company in the Chicago suburbs. The Kainzes, along with their sons, Michael, 34, Patrick, 29, and John, 26, and Michael's wife, Jennifer, 29, had pooled money to buy 50 $1 tickets for the May 9 drawing. They opted to take their money in a lump sum, worth about $61 million after taxes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kainz, a regular lottery player, had purchased the tickets while stopping by a service station in the nearby suburb of Mount Prospect, to buy gas. The winning number was on the third line of the fifth ticket he matched against the numbers printed in a newspaper on the day after the drawing.</p>
        <p>''My stomach retreated to the lower portion of my body,'' he said, when he realized that he had won. He and his wife immediately locked the ticket in a safe deposit box at a bank.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kainz today compared his family to that of the other prize winner, Larry Ross, 47, whose children also work for the family business. Mr. Ross also took his prize in a lump sum payment of about $61 million, after taxes.</p>
        <p>In the nine weeks leading up to the winning drawing, 565 million tickets were sold in Georgia, Illinois, Maryland, Massachusetts, Michigan, New Jersey and Virginia, the seven states that participate in the Big Game.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kainz said he and his wife had no intention of retiring, but instead would use some of their money to improve their businesses, including the Wild Onion Brewing Company, which Mr. Kainz said is on schedule to ''just break even'' this year. They will also replace the leaky roof on their home and travel to Ireland and France, and they said they planned to give away a lot of the money to charity.</p>
        <p>''When you win something of this size -- I mean this is sheer luck, any one of you could have won this,'' Mr. Kainz said, ''you've got an obligation. Certainly we will be considering the many, many things we can do for humanity.''</p>
        <p>Family members said they had had difficulty keeping their win a secret, especially once officials revealed that the ticket had been sold locally. Mrs. Kainz had a particularly difficult time when, on a visit to her dentist, he jokingly asked if ''she had picked up her lottery winnings yet.''</p>
        <p>''I nearly bit off his hand,'' Mrs. Kainz said.</p>
        <p>In fact, the couple went to Sweeney's Oil the day after the drawing, when it was announced that the ticket had been sold there. They were even approached by a television reporter, but declined to be interviewed.</p>
        <p>''They have known they were winners all along, and have enjoyed watching what has been going on,'' said Lori Montana, an Illinois Lottery official.</p>
        <p>''I didn't mean to put any of you through any anguish,'' Mr. Kainz told reporters, adding that he was trying to protect his family's privacy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kainz was also standing in the crowd when lottery officials awarded a $1.8 million commission check to John Sweeney, owner of the station that sold the winning ticket.</p>
        <p>Patrick and John Kainz, who are both single, joked that they would probably be hearing from many of their old girlfriends.</p>
        <p>But John Kainz had this message for them: ''Too bad, suckers.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
