<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Three States After Plum Role: Hollywood East; De Niro and Miramax Scout Locations for a Studio</title>
    <meta content="20STUD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200871"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miramax</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foderaro, Lisa W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Niro, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Studios</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Studios/Miramax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE2D9133AF933A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Three States After Plum Role: Hollywood East; De Niro and Miramax Scout Locations for a Studio</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA W. FODERARO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Foderaro, Lisa W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York, New Jersey and Connecticut vie for new motion picture studio being developed by Robert De Niro and Miramax; states are offering tax incentives and other enticements to the venture; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They are the bouquets and bonbons of the economic-development world, and these days they are raining down on Robert De Niro, the Academy Award-winning actor, and Harvey Weinstein of Miramax Films, who are still looking for a place to build a sprawling film studio.</p>
        <p>New York State is down on one knee, pledging a road and perhaps even a sewer system. New Jersey is whispering sweet nothings about sales tax exemptions and possibly a direct capital investment. And Connecticut, though hush-hush about its exact courtship strategy, is also dangling tax incentives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They are the bouquets and bonbons of the economic-development world, and these days they are raining down on Robert De Niro, the Academy Award-winning actor, and Harvey Weinstein of Miramax Films, who are still looking for a place to build a sprawling film studio.</p>
        <p>New York State is down on one knee, pledging a road and perhaps even a sewer system. New Jersey is whispering sweet nothings about sales tax exemptions and possibly a direct capital investment. And Connecticut, though hush-hush about its exact courtship strategy, is also dangling tax incentives.</p>
        <p>In the seven months since a tentative film studio deal between New York City, Mr. De Niro and Miramax Films collapsed, the three states have wasted no time in wooing the taciturn film star and his influential partner, Mr. Weinstein, co-chairman of Miramax. Officials say they are eager to pick up the ball they believe Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani dropped.</p>
        <p>It was no secret that the partners felt burned when the Giuliani administration announced in October that it had chosen another set of developers to build studios at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. Mayor Giuliani had, after all, tried out his best Godfather imitation for Mr. De Niro and then held a glittering news conference in Brooklyn about their collective vision for a sound stage complex there.</p>
        <p>But the city's sudden shift in favor of other developers (after administration members decided that that group would build the studios faster and require less city money) apparently did not dim the interest of Mr. De Niro in creating a film studio in the New York region. Although a record number of films and television shows have been shot in New York and New Jersey in recent years, members of the movie industry and state officials have long complained about the area's shortage of sound stages, which has forced filmmakers to go to Los Angeles and Toronto for indoor photography.</p>
        <p>The leading studio site contenders appear to be properties in the city of Yonkers in southern Westchester County and in the Hudson County town of Harrison, N.J., two municipalities desperate to redevelop their industrial waterfronts with the sort of sexy centerpiece that the movie partners could provide. Mr. De Niro and Mr. Weinstein had briefly considered sites in New York City, but they have zeroed in on those two tracts, according to someone who went on some of the tours.</p>
        <p>Neither Miramax, a subsidiary of the Walt Disney Company, nor Mr. De Niro's company, TriBeCa Productions, would comment on their quest for a parcel. But people who have met with the actor and Mr. Weinstein and seen architects' sketches for the two sites say their plan goes beyond a large film studio to include housing and possibly stores and restaurants. Such elements could make the proposal more attractive to investors skittish about the possibility of studios sitting empty between productions.</p>
        <p>''There's a dire need for studios in New York,'' said Charles A. Gargano, chairman of the Empire State Development Corporation, New York State's economic development agency. ''The problem is these things do not work by themselves. They do not generate enough money, so they have to have some additional development with them.''</p>
        <p>Some developers and film executives doubt whether Miramax and TriBeCa Productions will ever get a shovel in the ground. They cite a series of grand plans for film studios in recent years that either evaporated or were drastically scaled back, mostly for lack of financing.</p>
        <p>Abandoned late last year, for instance, was an ambitious plan to build a television and movie studio complex on top of a Manhattan office building at Houston and West Streets. The $160 million project, called Hudson River Studios, was to include five sound stages. But the developers lost their financing after two soap operas that had committed to using the space pulled out.</p>
        <p>In addition, after years of robust growth, the number of feature films shot in New York City actually fell by 12 last year to 209. The Mayor's Office of Film, Theater and Broadcasting is quick to point out that film production was down slightly nationwide as well. But the office still contends that there is not enough studio space in New York to meet demand.</p>
        <p>Others disagree. They cite a glut of studio space in Los Angeles and fear an eventual glut in the New York region, too, especially if the developer selected for the Brooklyn Navy Yard, New York Studios, realizes its plan for 11 sound stages. The development group, led by Douglas C. Steiner, is demolishing buildings at the site.</p>
        <p>And Kaufman Astoria Studios in Queens is adding a seventh studio, but its president, Hal G. Rosenbluth, said: ''We're pushing the envelope to believe you can build dozens of stages and actually fill them. We're never going to displace Hollywood. All the creative decisions to green-light things are still in Los Angeles, and the majority of the actors, directors and producers live in L.A.''</p>
        <p>But officials in New York and New Jersey are downright bubbly, promoting the superiority of their respective sites as they assemble incentive packages for Mr. De Niro and Mr. Weinstein.</p>
        <p>Connecticut is more coy. Edward Dombroskas, executive director of the state's film office, said the filmmakers ''are looking at a couple of different sites, but I can't reveal where they are.'' Mr. Dombroskas was also circumspect about incentives, but did say breaks on sales and property taxes were available to companies locating in so-called entertainment zones.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, the filmmakers are looking at a former steel plant on the Passaic River in Harrison, according to local and state officials. In 1998, an independent film production company in Manhattan, the Shooting Gallery, settled on the same 41-acre site for a grandiose studio plan with 15 sound stages and a $75 million price tag. That plan was abandoned for a much smaller project in Manhattan, on Leroy Street in the West Village.</p>
        <p>Harrison officials think a Miramax-De Niro studio would have a better chance of succeeding given the principals' track records. The mayor of Harrison, Raymond J. McDonough, said he met with representatives of TriBeCa Productions and Miramax in April, and ''they asked me how they could obtain all the property in the redevelopment area.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, officials are offering several lures, from financing through the Hudson County Improvement Authority to annual payments to the studio company over 10 years that would represent a portion of the state income tax revenue generated by the new jobs.</p>
        <p>Gualberto Medina, New Jersey's secretary of commerce, said the state was also considering a direct investment of money in the project and was working with the filmmakers on a ''joint request for proposals'' from potential real estate developers.</p>
        <p>Local and state officials said the Harrison property would be perfect for a studio complex: it has a cavernous column-free building with 103,000 square feet and a 100-foot-high ceiling, and it is across the street from a PATH train station. Gregory J. Castano, the lawyer for the Harrison Redevelopment Agency, said, ''No other site offers a building like that.''</p>
        <p>The Yonkers site, a former wire factory, also has a building with a 100-foot ceiling, sans columns, although it is smaller, at 30,000 square feet. The 13-acre parcel may be a bit cramped for a mixed-used development, but it is a striking location, sitting alongside the Hudson River, with the wooded cliffs of the Palisades across the way and the Manhattan skyline to the south. It, too, is convenient to public transportation, with a Metro-North Railroad stop only a couple of hundred yards away.</p>
        <p>The soaring main building, which is clad in unfortunate powder-blue panels, was recently used to film a scene from ''Sleepy Hollow'' -- a nighttime shot of a cornfield that entailed hauling in 600 tons of dirt.</p>
        <p>''The girth of the walls, the thickness of the floors, the enormity of the space -- it's got such character,'' said Paul W. Adler, the general manager of commercial services for Prudential Rand Realty, which represents the property's owner, BICC P.L.C. ''Some of the offices look like something you could film a Bogart movie in.''</p>
        <p>BICC, a transportation and development company in London, is talking to Mr. Weinstein and Mr. De Niro about a joint venture, Mr. Adler said. That would also enable the company to oversee a necessary environmental cleanup of the site, estimated to cost $7.5 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gargano, the economic development chairman in New York State, said the state reached out to the filmmakers after learning that they were looking in New Jersey last fall. While New York would not contribute ''seed money'' to the studio project, the state could help with infrastructure improvements and savings on sales tax, he said.</p>
        <p>''The key thing here is to get them to build studios in New York,'' Mr. Gargano said. ''That's a very important industry, and it's good for New York State. New Jersey is ahead of us because they've been dealing with them longer.''</p>
        <p>So are Mr. De Niro and Mr. Weinstein stringing along New Jersey and New York, the same way that the Giuliani administration treated them? State and local officials say their eyes are open. ''They've been candid that they're looking at other areas,'' said Mr. Castano, the lawyer for the Harrison Redevelopment Agency, ''and we've known that from the beginning.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
