<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fire Renews Safety Concern Over Los Alamos Lab Waste</title>
    <meta content="Y20ALA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200840"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Mexico</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Alamos National Laboratory</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E0DD133AF933A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="952" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fire Renews Safety Concern Over Los Alamos Lab Waste</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>SANTA FE, N.M., May 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fires that have consumed nearly 50,000 acres of northern New Mexico, including parts of Los Alamos National Laboratory site, raise new concerns about buildup of nuclear and hazardous waste stored at facility; government officials say fires, now 70 percenet under control, did not get close enough to threaten thousands of containers filled with contaminated equipment, but scientists and environmentalists warn that dry conditions in nearby forests could create more dangerous situation; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The fires that consumed nearly 50,000 acres of northern New Mexico, including parts of the Los Alamos National Laboratory, have raised new concerns over the buildup of nuclear and hazardous waste stored at the laboratory.</p>
        <p>State and federal officials have insisted that the fires, which were 70 percent under control by late today, did not get close enough to threaten thousands of containers filled with used gloves, rags, booties and other combustible items contaminated by low-level radioactive waste, like plutonium. By some estimates, the nearest flames remained half a mile away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The fires that consumed nearly 50,000 acres of northern New Mexico, including parts of the Los Alamos National Laboratory, have raised new concerns over the buildup of nuclear and hazardous waste stored at the laboratory.</p>
        <p>State and federal officials have insisted that the fires, which were 70 percent under control by late today, did not get close enough to threaten thousands of containers filled with used gloves, rags, booties and other combustible items contaminated by low-level radioactive waste, like plutonium. By some estimates, the nearest flames remained half a mile away.</p>
        <p>But scientists and environmental advocates said today that dry conditions in forests adjacent to the storage site made the forests ripe for another fire, and a potentially more dangerous situation because of the increasing quantity of stored waste.</p>
        <p>Typically, the laboratory generates 150 cubic meters of waste a year, which is stored above ground under a fabric dome in 55-gallon steel drums and smaller wooden boxes. About 4,808 cubic meters, the equivalent of 14,000 drums, is currently in storage.</p>
        <p>''The problem is just sitting there, just waiting for another incident to happen,'' said a Los Alamos scientist familiar with the storage site. ''And there are a lot of people at the lab who share that concern.''</p>
        <p>Greg Mello, director of the Los Alamos Study Group, a nuclear watchdog organization, said: ''It's a dangerous situation. If they could get that stuff out of there, everyone would be better served.''</p>
        <p>Officials from the energy department and the laboratory have disputed the contention that anything at the storage site, a mesa surrounded by canyons known as Technical Area 54, is vulnerable to fire.</p>
        <p>They cited an environmental study of the laboratory conducted four years ago in which officials created a theoretical worst-case fire and found that the waste would survive unaffected.</p>
        <p>But even if conditions grew so grave that the drums overheated and exploded, sending toxic plumes skyward, the study concluded that no one living within a 50-mile radius would suffer ill effects.</p>
        <p>Those views are not shared by many scientists, who contend that the department's worst-case test was not worst case at all. While the department model assumed a breach of 62 drums, Edwin Lyman, scientific director of the Nuclear Control Institute, a nonprofit research organization in Washington, said an intense fire would more likely breach ''closer to hundreds'' of drums, causing a much greater potential for illness than the study provides.</p>
        <p>''The department,'' Dr. Lyman said, ''has refused to look at the real worst-case scenario.''</p>
        <p>Efforts are under way to remove the waste at Los Alamos to the Waste Isolation Pilot Plant outside Carlsbad, N.M., which opened last year after a decade of delays. For now, the rate of removal is but a trickle.</p>
        <p>With cleanup at the Rocky Flats nuclear weapons plant outside Denver, which is scheduled to close by 2006, and three other facilities producing nuclear waste for disposal, the competition for removal has grown intense.</p>
        <p>For Los Alamos, the pace has been further delayed by lawsuits challenging the environmental impact of the disposal and a dispute between the state government, which requires that the contents of every container be itemized, and the Energy Department, which does not agree that detailed inventories are necessary.</p>
        <p>Energy Department officials said today that Los Alamos shipped 714 drums of waste last year, with 252 scheduled to go this year, 1,176 next year, 2,940 in 2002 and increasing numbers in the following years.</p>
        <p>While that leaves the majority of the drums on site for the foreseeable future, officials from the laboratory and the Energy Department insisted that the containers were well protected, largely as a result of following recommendations of the environmental impact study. To add layers of protection, dry timber was removed from the perimeter of the laboratory, the tree line was moved back and dirt pathways were built as a buffer against fires from the canyons below.</p>
        <p>Still, critics are not convinced that enough safeguards are in place, especially with the unpredictable updrafts from the canyons, which the current fires demonstrated, and the ever present possibility of sparks during an intense fire.</p>
        <p>Representative Tom Udall, a Democrat whose district includes the laboratory, said today that a recent tour of the laboratory convinced him that the fire ''was too close for comfort,'' and that rebuilding efforts -- some older buildings were destroyed -- should emphasize greater protections against fires or other disasters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Udall also said the waste removal from Los Alamos was part of a larger national problem for which Congress had traditionally authorized only limited spending.</p>
        <p>''On a national scale,'' he said, ''this is not regarded as a high risk. But we need to get to the job of cleaning up all over the country.''</p>
        <p>The Los Alamos scientist familiar with the storage site added one further regret. He said he and his colleagues were eager to return to work next week, when the laboratory reopened. But they were anxious as well, he said.</p>
        <p>''The lab is tucked away in what was some of the most beautiful scenery you've ever seen,'' he said. ''Since the fire, it looks terrible, and you can't just go out there with a bucket of paint and fix it. That was slow-growth forest that burned. It will take a long time to come back to what it was.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
