<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Saul Bellow on Birth, Death and All That Stuff in Between</title>
    <meta content="13CONN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198980"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CONNECTIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rothstein, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tolstoy, Leo (1828-1910)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellow, Saul</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ravelstein (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Connections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EFDC153BF930A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1071" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Saul Bellow on Birth, Death and All That Stuff in Between</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edward Rothstein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rothstein, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Edward Rothstein discusses author Saul Bellow's process in conceiving themes for his books with emphasis on lastest book Ravelstein; theme is death, invoking spirit of Tolstoy's Ivan Ilyich; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sitting in the office that the art critic Harold Rosenberg once used (his poster of a beautiful Nautilus shell still hangs there), Saul Bellow is leaning back slightly, fingertips touching, pausing before beginning to speak. For a listener whose education was shaped in part by Augie March and Henderson and Mr. Sammler, Mr. Bellow's meditations can seem a creation of his characters' pungent imaginations. Now his surgically shaped phrases and dreamlike imagery make it sound as if he were reciting one of Herzog's letters to the famous dead.</p>
        <p>Tolstoy is the recipient of this one, or perhaps Mr. Bellow is addressing himself. In the office, whose fading light comes from the small Gothic leaded windows of the University of Chicago, Mr. Bellow asks what is to be made of Ivan Ilych's death. That was Tolstoy's project in his famous short story: to reveal how death, with all its ruthlessness, strips away the creaturely surface of life, as vain pleasures and social climbings give way to final things.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sitting in the office that the art critic Harold Rosenberg once used (his poster of a beautiful Nautilus shell still hangs there), Saul Bellow is leaning back slightly, fingertips touching, pausing before beginning to speak. For a listener whose education was shaped in part by Augie March and Henderson and Mr. Sammler, Mr. Bellow's meditations can seem a creation of his characters' pungent imaginations. Now his surgically shaped phrases and dreamlike imagery make it sound as if he were reciting one of Herzog's letters to the famous dead.</p>
        <p>Tolstoy is the recipient of this one, or perhaps Mr. Bellow is addressing himself. In the office, whose fading light comes from the small Gothic leaded windows of the University of Chicago, Mr. Bellow asks what is to be made of Ivan Ilych's death. That was Tolstoy's project in his famous short story: to reveal how death, with all its ruthlessness, strips away the creaturely surface of life, as vain pleasures and social climbings give way to final things.</p>
        <p>But what, then, is a novelist to do? If material life is an illusion and a distraction, it is also where the writer dwells. The surface cannot be avoided; its sensuous transience is of the essence. The novelist honors it with meticulous description, straining to take note of the rush of human sensations. So doesn't the world-dwelling novelist resist the otherworldly insistence of the religious believer?</p>
        <p>Bellow's meditations returned to me while reading his new novel, ''Ravelstein,''  and not just because I was acquainted with the model for Ravelstein; he is, of course,  the political philosopher Allan Bloom, who also taught seminars with Mr. Bellow in Chicago. Ivan Ilych is invoked in ''Ravelstein'' as well, for this too is a portrait of a man headed toward death. Ravelstein is a version of Ilych without the hypocrisy, possessing an almost rabid sensuality, a devotion to luxury, unsated erotic longings and nervously trembling fingers. Ravelstein relishes sensation and desire. ''A human soul devoid of longing,'' he suggests, ''was a soul deformed, deprived of its highest good, sick unto death.''</p>
        <p>But what happens to these material  tastes as death steals away his strength and mind? Ravelstein believes that ''nothing is more bourgeois than the fear of death'' and that nothing much exists after death. So the essence of things is to be found only in the material world, which, in Ravelstein's view, can lead to philosophic knowledge as well as to sensual pleasure. It is an answer that might have pleased Tolstoy the novelist but dismayed Tolstoy the Christian believer.</p>
        <p>Chick, the chronicler of Ravelstein's death, also relishes the texture of the material world, believing, in fact, that ''the heart of things is shown in the surface of those things.'' Chick is devoted to pictorial detail. Death, he says, is when the pictures come to an end, though he eventually wonders if there may be something to see after life's images fade.</p>
        <p>Such themes have often preoccupied Mr. Bellow, but Augie March, Henderson and Herzog test their desires against the wide world, wrestling against its bounds. Their ambition is American, their tragic sense, Jewish. Here possibilities have shrunk as the problems have grown: the world is the size of a man's soul. The desires are as great, but the natural limits greater. If death can strip away all surfaces and we are fated to live in death's shadow, then by what guidelines are we to live? How are we to shape our lives? ''The soul of another is a dark forest,'' says Ravelstein.</p>
        <p>There was a time when Mr. Bellow was called (along with Philip Roth and Bernard Malamud) an ''American Jewish novelist,'' a label he mocked as resembling a haberdashery, the writers as the Hart, Schaffner &amp; Marx of literature. But the label also identified a temperament: the Jewish novelists of the 1950's and 60's were new inheritors of the American estate, intoxicated with its personalities and possibilities. Recently Mr. Roth was asked whether it was necessary for the main character of his 1997 novel ''American Pastoral,'' Swede Levov, to be Jewish.</p>
        <p>''It was for me,'' he responded. It is through knowledge of the particular that the universal is perceived.</p>
        <p>But now, in this Bellow novel, and in Mr. Roth's new novel, ''The Human Stain,'' the particular is itself unreliable. Mr. Bellow wonders about the stability of the material world. Mr. Roth wonders about the stability of character and identity. Mr. Roth's alter mind, Nathan Zuckerman, like Mr. Bellow's Chick, is ailing and aging, trying to comprehend the life of a friend, Coleman Silk, after being shaken by his death.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Roth's political canvas is large -- racial identity, the Vietnam War, political correctness -- but the focus is concentrated. How can a soul's dark forests be illuminated? Mr. Roth never forgets our animal being, the sensual habits and desires that are cloaked by our public selves. Still, what do we know of another or of ourselves? There is, of course, the public persona we put forward. (''Everyone Knows'' is the title of the first chapter.)</p>
        <p>But as Zuckerman learned in ''American Pastoral,'' interpreting appearances is  an impossible task. He will always get it wrong, always misinterpret. However much he may be devoted to understanding the human, reality is always ready to ''slip a punch,'' showing that what was taken for surety is little more than illusion. ''The entanglement with life'' is never untangled. Silk presented himself as Jewish; but he was actually black. ''I don't know what to think about anything,'' Nathan concludes. Nothing is known because nothing can be.</p>
        <p>It is only in death, when all appearances are stripped away, that something is disclosed. It is after Levov's death that Nathan begins to learn the truth; it is after Silk's death that Nathan learns his secrets. Otherwise, appearances and identities are all we have. Mr. Bellow sees them as a code to be read; Mr. Roth sees them as a code to be misread. And both writers, in these late American Jewish novels, treat their fragile existence with melancholic tenderness.</p>
        <p>CONNECTIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
