<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abroad at Home; Cruelty Without Mercy</title>
    <meta content="13LEWI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198981"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yemen</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">al-Jailani, Ashraf</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swensen, Michelle</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEFDC153BF930A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abroad at Home; Cruelty Without Mercy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Anthony</byline>
      <dateline>KENT, Ohio</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Lewis Op-Ed column criticizes harshness of US immigration policies; cites case of Ohio couple, Michelle Swensen and Ashraf al-Jailani; al-Jailani, from Yemen, faces deportation because of no-contest plea in domestic violence case brought after two had minor argument in mall (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michelle Swensen was a zoology student at Kent State University when in 1994 she won a scholarship to go to Japan for a year and learn the language. At Shimane University there she met a student from Yemen, Ashraf al-Jailani. They were married in 1996.</p>
        <p>The al-Jailanis live in Kent now; I met them here recently. They have two small daughters, and Michelle is expecting another child next month. It is an appealing family. There is just one trouble. The family is about to be destroyed by the harsh provisions of the Immigration Act of 1996.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Michelle Swensen was a zoology student at Kent State University when in 1994 she won a scholarship to go to Japan for a year and learn the language. At Shimane University there she met a student from Yemen, Ashraf al-Jailani. They were married in 1996.</p>
        <p>The al-Jailanis live in Kent now; I met them here recently. They have two small daughters, and Michelle is expecting another child next month. It is an appealing family. There is just one trouble. The family is about to be destroyed by the harsh provisions of the Immigration Act of 1996.</p>
        <p>Why? Because Ashraf knocked Michelle's glasses off -- accidentally, they both say. In a series of events worthy of Kafka, he was advised to plead no contest to a charge of domestic violence. Under the rigid terms of the 1996 act, that made him deportable -- without a chance of mercy. But let Michelle tell how it happened.</p>
        <p>''We were arguing in the mall about which treadmill to buy,'' she told me. ''It was December a year ago.</p>
        <p>''We went out to the car and put the kids in the back. We were yelling at each other. They were crying.</p>
        <p>''I turned around to talk to the kids. When I turned back, Ashraf apparently reached for something on the dashboard and knocked my glasses off. I was extremely angry. I thought he did it on purpose.''</p>
        <p>Michelle ran into the mall, saw a policeman and asked him to find her a place to stay. Her husband had knocked her glasses off, she said, and she did not want to go with him. The policeman asked if she wanted to press charges. ''Definitely not,'' she says she replied. But the policeman did. Mr. al-Jailani was charged with domestic violence.</p>
        <p>In court a young man met him 10 minutes before the trial and advised him to plead no contest. The young man was not a lawyer, the al-Jailanis found out later, but an intern in the Public Defender's office. Under Ohio law, a judge has to warn alien defendants of immigration consequences. The intern, Mrs. al-Jailani said, told them not to worry about that -- ''It's just a formality. The chance of you getting deported is one in a million.''</p>
        <p>Mr. al-Jailani was found guilty. ''Next thing we know,'' his wife said, ''he gets a paper from the Immigration and Naturalization Service saying he is to be deported because of his conviction for domestic violence. My husband never committed an act of domestic violence! We argued -- that's all.''</p>
        <p>The al-Jailanis now have a lawyer, and he has tried to have the conviction vacated. But a judge rejected the motion, saying that Mr. al-Jailani should have understood the consequences of his plea. But he knew nothing about the law, and he was badly advised. Moreover, because of the plea of no contest, the court never examined the facts of the incident.</p>
        <p>Domestic violence is serious, and Americans have come to realize that victims may go on suffering it too long. But sometimes -- many times -- marital tension leads to misunderstanding, and then both parties really want to repair the difficulty and renew their love. I'm convinced that this is such a case. I do not believe that anyone could meet Michelle al-Jailani and not understand that she loves her husband.</p>
        <p>But the 1996 Immigration Act makes a conviction for domestic violence an automatic, unreviewable ground for deportation. An immigration judge can consider only the fact of a conviction, not the circumstances of it or the humane argument for keeping a family together. The statute removed judges' right to withhold deportation if it would cause extreme hardship.</p>
        <p>''What upsets me,'' Mrs. al-Jailani said, ''is that you get before an immigration judge and have no real chance to defend yourself. Who's going to support my kids when their father is gone?''</p>
        <p>The principal authors of the 1996 Act, Representative Lamar Smith of Texas and Senator Spencer Abraham of Michigan, have said that the I.N.S. should alleviate the law's harshness by using prosecutorial discretion. But in this case the I.N.S. says it has no legal choice: it is doing what the law requires.</p>
        <p>If they care about the human consequences of their legislation, Representative Smith and Senator Abraham should meet Michelle and Ashraf al-Jailani. In just a few minutes I believe they would understand the urgent need to amend the act. Before the law destroys a family, there has to be room for judgment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
