<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Big City; Parting Ways With His Hero And His Wife</title>
    <meta content="13BIG.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199071"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tierney, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanover, Donna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/John Tierney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DB123BF930A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Big City; Parting Ways With His Hero And His Wife</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TIERNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tierney, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Tierney, The Big City column, discusses marital problems between Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani and his wife Donna Hanover; says Giuliani should have warned Hanover of substance of announcement; concedes Giuliani may have been acting in familiar role as nonpolitician who rejects the rules; refers to announcement as personal whim of mayor (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN September 1995, Donna Hanover sat down with me for an interview that must have struck her as awkwardly timed. New York magazine was on the newsstands with a cover story, ''The Woman Behind the Mayor,'' and the woman was not Ms. Hanover. The story was about Cristyne Lategano, the communications director and constant companion to Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>I dutifully dredged up the topic, and she tersely avoided it. She spent the rest of the interview lavishly praising her husband's fine qualities as a mayor, a father and a husband. She smiled as she talked of her love for him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN September 1995, Donna Hanover sat down with me for an interview that must have struck her as awkwardly timed. New York magazine was on the newsstands with a cover story, ''The Woman Behind the Mayor,'' and the woman was not Ms. Hanover. The story was about Cristyne Lategano, the communications director and constant companion to Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>I dutifully dredged up the topic, and she tersely avoided it. She spent the rest of the interview lavishly praising her husband's fine qualities as a mayor, a father and a husband. She smiled as she talked of her love for him.</p>
        <p>At the time it seemed a game performance; in retrospect it strikes me as a triumph of the dramatic arts. Until this week, I assumed that Ms. Hanover and her husband had peacefully reconciled themselves to separate lives. They seemed to have reached some sort of Clintonian understanding to remain in the executive mansion. But the couple who went before the cameras this week was not at peace.</p>
        <p>In some ways, the dueling arias before the cameras made for a refreshing contrast to the Clintons' pious pronouncements. They weren't denying the undeniable or smearing innocent people or blaming an outside conspiracy for their troubles.</p>
        <p>But the news conferences were an embarrassment for Ms. Hanover and a public relations disaster for Mr. Giuliani. He violated a couple of rules that he could have heard from any political consultant or couples therapist:</p>
        <p>If you're going to announce a separation from your wife of 16 years, clear it with her first. And do not use the news conference to proclaim your need for the new woman in your life.</p>
        <p>How could Mr. Giuliani not have foreseen the angry response from his wife? Why would any politician running for the Senate publicly flaunt his relationship with another woman and prod his wife into denouncing him for destroying their marriage? Is he trying to force himself out of the race, or at least out of the marriage?</p>
        <p>Maybe. Mr. Giuliani could be like a wayward husband who leaves a hotel receipt lying around rather than facing his wife directly. And perhaps Mr. Giuliani was spurred into action by the diagnosis of prostate cancer.</p>
        <p>But it's also possible that Mr. Giuliani was just acting out his familiar role as the nonpolitician who rejects the rules. He has kept talking about being ''honest'' and ''decent'' and ''honorable'' -- all of which he defines for himself. He has always shunned ideological labels and party doctrines, styling himself as an iconoclastic moralist like his hero, Fiorello La Guardia.</p>
        <p>STUBBORN independence can be a wonderful quality -- Mr. Giuliani succeeded precisely because he disdained conventional politics and what he referred to as New York's ''so-called intellectuals.'' But when you're not guided by public opinion or a consistent ideology, the alternative is liable to be personal whim, which can get dangerous the longer you're in power.</p>
        <p>Fiorello La Guardia took office denouncing Tammany Hall's fiscal scams, but by the end of his mayoralty he was resorting to similar ploys.</p>
        <p>''La Guardia was always very willful,'' said his biographer, Thomas Kessner, a historian at the Graduate School of the City University of New York. ''But as the years went by he became more irascible, more brittle, more insistent on doing things his way.''</p>
        <p>Not even La Guardia, though, flouted conventional standards for sexual behavior. He remained faithful to his stolid, un glamorous wife, and he disciplined city workers for having extramarital affairs on the grounds that their conduct was ''prejudicial to the good name and interest of the city.''</p>
        <p>La Guardia was appalled by Mayor Jimmy Walker, a married man who moved out of his home to carry on a public affair with a young actress. During his campaign against Mayor Walker in 1929, La Guardia called Walker a ''Paris gigolo'' and urged voters to elect ''a mayor who will sleep at night and work in the daytime.''</p>
        <p>Walker's adultery apparently didn't bother the voters. He was re-elected in a landslide. Whatever relevance that has to the 2000 Senate race, Mr. Giuliani might at least take comfort from an incident in the 1929 campaign, during a speech La Guardia made at a church in Harlem.</p>
        <p>Thank God, La Guardia pointedly told the congregation, that some men go home at night to sleep with their own wives.</p>
        <p>''And that ain't so good either,'' someone shouted back.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
