<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jeter Hopes a Week Is All It Takes to Heal</title>
    <meta content="13PINS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jeter, Derek</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DB123BF930A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="745" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jeter Hopes a Week Is All It Takes to Heal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, May 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Yankees Notebook article focuses on player Derek Jeter, who is expected to miss at least week with strained abdominal muscle (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Derek Jeter is expected to miss at least a week with a strained abdominal muscle, and he is hoping to avoid a stint on the 15-day disabled list. But Jeter knows how conservatively the Yankees treat their injuries.</p>
        <p>''You break a toenail around here'' and you find your name on the disabled list, Jeter said before tonight's game against the Tigers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Derek Jeter is expected to miss at least a week with a strained abdominal muscle, and he is hoping to avoid a stint on the 15-day disabled list. But Jeter knows how conservatively the Yankees treat their injuries.</p>
        <p>''You break a toenail around here'' and you find your name on the disabled list, Jeter said before tonight's game against the Tigers.</p>
        <p>Clay Bellinger started at shortstop in place of Jeter, and Scott Brosius batted in Jeter's No. 2 slot in the lineup tonight against the Tigers left-hander C. J. Nitkowski.</p>
        <p>On those days when the Yankees face a right-hander, Manager Joe Torre figures to use the left-handed-hitting Ricky Ledee in Jeter's spot.</p>
        <p>Jeter felt pain after taking extended batting practice Wednesday, and he experienced even more pain early in Thursday's game against Tampa Bay when he apparently aggravated the strain. Jeter said it probably would have been smarter if he had kept himself out of the lineup altogether Thursday. As it was, he lasted only a couple of innings.</p>
        <p>But the injury, Jeter thinks, is not as severe as the rib-cage strain that forced him to the disabled list in 1998.</p>
        <p>''I think it's one of those things where you've got to wait a couple of days to see how it feels,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Torre said, ''I'd say it's going to be a week anyway.''</p>
        <p>Jeter batted .349 last year, with 24 homers and 102 runs batted in, and was the team's best and most consistent offensive player. The Yanks have mostly won without his offense this year. He is batting .266 and has not had a hit in his last 13 at-bats.</p>
        <p>Torre thought that Jeter's recovery from his rib-cage strain two years ago was the fastest he had ever seen for that type of injury. But in spring training, Jeter acknowledged that maybe he had not been as healthy as he claimed to be at the time, that perhaps he had played in pain just so he could play.</p>
        <p>All-Star Potential</p>
        <p>The All-Star teams will not be selected for nearly two months, but catcher Jorge Posada and reliever Jeff Nelson have placed themselves in a position to be considered. Posada ranked fifth in the American League with a .362 average, and Nelson was 6-0 with a 1.35 earned run average before tonight's game.</p>
        <p>But while Posada would seem to have an excellent chance, because most All-Star teams consist of three catchers, Nelson knows middle relievers are rarely considered.</p>
        <p>''It would be unbelievable, but it wouldn't break my heart if it didn't happen,'' he said.</p>
        <p>What Nelson does think about constantly, he acknowledged, is his next contract. He is eligible for free agency after this year and wants an extension from the Yankees. An All-Star Game invitation would look good on his resume.</p>
        <p>The manager of the American League All-Star team is Joe Torre.</p>
        <p>Prospect Slow to Heal</p>
        <p>When Nick Johnson, a top prospect at first base, sprained a hand in an exhibition game March 10, the Yankees expected him to miss a few days or a week.</p>
        <p>But Johnson, who appeared to be the heir apparent to Tino Martinez next season, has not swung a bat since. Although there are indications that he is healing, Johnson's progress has been so slow that he will see another hand specialist on Monday for another opinion. It will be the fourth one he has received.</p>
        <p>''It's going too slow for us,'' General Manager Brian Cashman said. ''While we'll have patience, we want to make sure we're doing everything we can to get him back.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees have received some more bad news about another top prospect, outfielder Donzell McDonald, who had a .442 on-base percentage and 11 stolen bases at Class AAA Columbus. He has torn a ligament in a thumb and is expected to be out for an extended period of time.</p>
        <p>Outfielder on the Mend</p>
        <p>Felix Jose, a veteran outfielder who strained his groin after getting hits in his only two at-bats for the Yankees, is getting closer to returning. When he is ready, however, the Yankees will have some roster issues. Jose is out of options and cannot be sent back to Class AAA unless he is passed through waivers.</p>
        <p>Chris Turner, who was called up to replace Jose, is also out of options and the Yankees may not want to risk losing him at a time when they lack depth at catcher.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
