<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ford's Admission Perplexes the Neighbors in Henry's Hometown</title>
    <meta content="Y13FOR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199013"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Efficiency</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dearborn (Mich)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Motoring</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEFD7153BF930A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="849" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ford's Admission Perplexes the Neighbors in Henry's Hometown</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DEARBORN, Mich., May 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents of Dearborn, Mich, town with close ties to Ford Motor Co, express little shock at Ford's admission that sport utility vehicles cause serious safety and environmental problems; focus on Ford's vow to improve emissions and fuel economy and find ways to make vehicles less dangerous in crashes with cars; Detroit's news media seem mystified by Ford's frankness; environmental groups seem perplexed about how to respond; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The doors and floor mats at City Hall here proudly bear the logo, ''Home Town of Henry Ford.'' The Ford Motor Company's headquarters, an immense rectangle of glass and steel in a community of two-story homes, is a mile down the street, and the company's endless office parks, factories and test tracks cover most of the landscape.</p>
        <p>So people in this southwest suburb of Detroit tend to support Ford, and they expressed little shock at the company's frank admission on Thursday that sport utility vehicles cause serious safety and environmental problems. They focused on Ford's vow to improve the big vehicles' tailpipe emissions and fuel economy and find ways to make them less dangerous in crashes with cars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The doors and floor mats at City Hall here proudly bear the logo, ''Home Town of Henry Ford.'' The Ford Motor Company's headquarters, an immense rectangle of glass and steel in a community of two-story homes, is a mile down the street, and the company's endless office parks, factories and test tracks cover most of the landscape.</p>
        <p>So people in this southwest suburb of Detroit tend to support Ford, and they expressed little shock at the company's frank admission on Thursday that sport utility vehicles cause serious safety and environmental problems. They focused on Ford's vow to improve the big vehicles' tailpipe emissions and fuel economy and find ways to make them less dangerous in crashes with cars.</p>
        <p>''They should if it's the vehicle you're buying -- it's a lot of money you're investing,'' said Natasha Lintz, who works for a trucking company that carries steel to Ford factories. She drives a sport utility vehicle, a dark red GMC Jimmy.</p>
        <p>Across the Detroit area and in Washington, people were trying today to interpret Ford's acknowledgment that it faced an awkward situation in balancing sales of highly profitable sport utilities with the company's desire to be a good corporate citizen. In an industry with a long history of resisting safety and environmental advances like seat belts, air bags and catalytic converters, Ford's forthright stance took many by surprise.</p>
        <p>Some in Michigan's Congressional delegation were concerned that the company might have strengthened its longtime political enemies in regulatory and legislative battles. ''It does make it more difficult for us to propose reasonable standards,'' said Paul F. Welday, the chief of staff for Representative Joe Knollenberg, a Michigan Republican on the Appropriations Committee. ''The company is trying to find itself right now, and we're not sure where it is.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Knollenberg has led efforts to freeze fuel-economy regulations, locking in more lenient treatment for sport utilities and other light trucks than for cars. Each federal budget since 1995 has included a rider barring the Clinton administration from spending any money to tighten the standards.</p>
        <p>Detroit's news media seemed mystified by Ford Motor's stance. ''Ford admits its trucks hurt Earth,'' was the large headline leading the business section of The Detroit Free Press, although the article below it from The Associated Press was just seven paragraphs long. ''Ford admits dilemma: SUVs vs. environment,'' was the headline on the front page of the business section of the more conservative Detroit News, next to a column warning of the dangers of providing help to critics of the auto industry.</p>
        <p>The environmental groups to which Ford wants to build ties were particularly perplexed about how to respond. Some saw the ''corporate citizenship report'' issued by the company as ammunition to use against Ford and the rest of the auto industry in pursuing tighter regulations in Congress.</p>
        <p>''The timing is useful in terms of the likely discussions that are going to be taking place in Washington,'' said Brian Dunkiel, a lawyer for Friends of the Earth.</p>
        <p>But some environmental groups were reluctant to use Ford's arguments in lobbying, for fear of discouraging Ford and other companies from taking a more cooperative approach to the environment. ''There will probably be some groups that will use it to make more trouble, but others will want to work with them,'' said Frank J. O'Donnell, the executive director of the Clean Air Trust, a Washington group that has lobbied for tighter emissions rules on sport utilities.</p>
        <p>William C. Ford Jr., the automaker's chairman, and Jacques Nasser, its chief executive, said at the company's annual meeting on Thursday that they believed it was best to be open about the company's problems. Mr. Nasser said consumers are increasingly influenced in their buying decisions by their overall perceptions of companies. Ford Motor executives have long been envious of the reputation of the General Motors Saturn division, which had considerable success for many years in using its strong public image to sell cars that tended to draw poor reviews from experts.</p>
        <p>Debbie Zemke, a longtime friend of Mr. Ford who is now Ford Motor's director of corporate governance, drafted the report with the forthright discussion of sport utility vehicles' drawbacks. ''We just said: 'For heaven's sake, everybody else is talking about it, so why shouldn't we?' '' she said.</p>
        <p>At lunchtime today on the streets of Dearborn, there was even a sense of relief at the company's remarks among some car owners. Marie Conrad, a homemaker and the wife of a retired Chrysler auto worker, drives a 15-year-old white Chrysler Fifth Avenue with plush red seats and feels nervous around big sport utilities.</p>
        <p>''I'm glad they're doing something about it,'' she said. ''But why couldn't they catch it sooner?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
