<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani Decision on Senate Expected in Days</title>
    <meta content="13MAYO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199078"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipton, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanover, Donna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nathan, Judith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFDB123BF930A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1135" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani Decision on Senate Expected in Days</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani is considering his decision whether to stay in or drop out of race for United States Senate; extraordinary events of last two weeks--cancer diagnosis, revelation of extramarital relationship and plans to separate from his wife--make this 'a difficult time' as Giuliani said on his weekly radio show; announcement of decision expected in next several days; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani spent yesterday afternoon behind closed doors as he began what his advisers said would be a weekend-long effort to consider treatment options for his prostate cancer and to try to decide whether to stay in -- or drop out of -- his supercharged race for the United States Senate.</p>
        <p>Aides indicated that he would probably cancel a fund-raising trip to California on Tuesday and Wednesday, with an announcement of his decision on his political future expected within the next several days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani spent yesterday afternoon behind closed doors as he began what his advisers said would be a weekend-long effort to consider treatment options for his prostate cancer and to try to decide whether to stay in -- or drop out of -- his supercharged race for the United States Senate.</p>
        <p>Aides indicated that he would probably cancel a fund-raising trip to California on Tuesday and Wednesday, with an announcement of his decision on his political future expected within the next several days.</p>
        <p>The deliberations took place after a morning in which the mayor strained to re-establish a hint of normality at City Hall, presiding over a bill-signing ceremony and fielding calls on his weekly radio show about topics as mundane as parking spaces for the handicapped and a sinkhole on a Brooklyn street.</p>
        <p>But the extraordinary events of the last two weeks -- his announcements of his cancer diagnosis, of his relationship with an Upper East Side woman and of his plans to separate from his wife -- never faded too far into the background.</p>
        <p>''It is a difficult time; I would be less than honest and candid if I didn't say that,'' Mr. Giuliani said during his WABC radio show, a weekly event in which the mayor more typically is combative and sarcastic with callers. ''It is a difficult time not just for me, but for all the different people who are involved in these situations.''</p>
        <p>There was as much confusion among Mr. Giuliani's aides yesterday as there was across the city itself over whether Mr. Giuliani would proceed with the Senate campaign. Some said they thought he would, though it might have been as much wishful thinking as informed speculation.</p>
        <p>''I feel confident he is going to run,'' said one close adviser, who like others interviewed did not want to be named because their discussions with the mayor were confidential. ''I think that is what he wants to do and I think he can handle it.''</p>
        <p>But another close aide was not so sure. ''It is just too much stuff,'' the aide said.</p>
        <p>The mayor at one point yesterday called himself ''a possible candidate'' in the Senate race against Hillary Rodham Clinton. And while he declined to set a date for his decision, he agreed that he owed it to the Republican Party to make up his mind soon. The state party meets on May 30 to nominate its Senate candidate, and party leaders have grown increasingly anxious that Mr. Giuliani might drop out, leaving them no obvious replacement.</p>
        <p>''I am going to make the decision as quickly as I can responsibly make it,'' the mayor said. ''I do feel like I have an obligation to the party.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's advisers said yesterday that Mr. Giuliani had also postponed a long-scheduled meeting with Representative Rick A. Lazio, a Long Island Republican  who has been mentioned as a replacement candidate if the mayor decides not to run.  Mr. Giuliani's aides said he decided to put the meeting off because of conflicting pressures next week.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Giuliani urged the public not to assume that his cancellation of events in the coming week, probably including the California trip and perhaps a speech to Republicans he is scheduled to give tonight in Oneonta, N.Y., was a sign that he was dropping out of the race, saying instead that he needed time to make up his mind about his medical treatment.</p>
        <p>The unusual public display of emotion that first surfaced this week in Mr. Giuliani was again evident yesterday as he acknowledged to reporters and on his radio show how difficult the recent days had been. The Republican mayor was also gentle and friendly with Democratic City Council leaders. ''Victor, once again, great job,'' he said to Victor L. Robles, a Brooklyn Democrat who was a lead sponsor on one of the bills before the mayor yesterday.</p>
        <p>Before signing a bill that will require that most dogs and cats be sterilized before they are sold at city pet shops or adopted from animal shelters, Mr. Giuliani held a 7-week-old mixed Labrador puppy named Oreo on his lap, allowing the dog to lick his chin and his cheek. But Mr. Giuliani also at times appeared to be anxious, as he repeatedly rearranged sheets of paper in front of him, rechecked his bill-signing pens to see if they worked and tapped his fingernails on the glass table top.</p>
        <p>Asked by one reporter after the bill signing if he was having a midlife crisis, the 55-year-old mayor ruminated, not ruling out the possibility.</p>
        <p>''That is an interesting way to put it,'' the mayor said, chuckling at first at the suggestion. ''I don't know exactly how I would describe it. When you are going through it I don't know that you are able to describe it, you just try to figure out the best answers you are capable of. And try, despite all of the pain and difficulties and emotion and feelings about it, you try to grow from it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani also acknowledged that some people might not be willing to forgive him for his actions, referring indirectly to his relationship with Judith Nathan and his plan to separate from his wife of 16 years, Donna Hanover.</p>
        <p>Some ''will be sympathetic and empathetic and understand the kind of human situation that is going on,'' the mayor said. ''And then there are people who would be very angry and very upset and have a different view of it. And I understand that.''</p>
        <p>Many of the callers to Mr. Giuliani's radio show expressed sympathy, but they were split as to whether he should stay in the race.</p>
        <p>One man from New Jersey, after wishing the mayor a complete recovery, said he should drop out of the Senate race, serve out his term as mayor and then make a future bid  for governor of New York.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani did not entirely dismiss the suggestion.</p>
        <p>''What you say is certainly a reasonable, rational analysis and people have privately offered me the same analysis,'' he said, although he also explained why he wanted to serve in the Senate. ''But the main focus that I have to have is the first part of what you said, about my health, and whether I am going to have the physical wherewithal and stamina to do it, and I am hopeful that I will.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
