<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="13DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199038"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E4DE123BF930A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1103" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International Paper Wins Contest to Buy Champion  International Paper emerged the victor in a bidding war to acquire Champion International after a Finnish paper company declined to increase its offer. International Paper agreed to pay about $7.3 billion, or $75 a share in cash and stock.</p>
        <p>UPM of Finland had reached a merger deal with Champion in February for $6.6 billion, or $56.50 a share. International Paper made a surprise cash-and-stock bid of $64 a share two weeks ago. UPM raised its bid to $70 in cash, but failed to match International's highest offer as the deadline passed. [Page C4.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International Paper Wins Contest to Buy Champion  International Paper emerged the victor in a bidding war to acquire Champion International after a Finnish paper company declined to increase its offer. International Paper agreed to pay about $7.3 billion, or $75 a share in cash and stock.</p>
        <p>UPM of Finland had reached a merger deal with Champion in February for $6.6 billion, or $56.50 a share. International Paper made a surprise cash-and-stock bid of $64 a share two weeks ago. UPM raised its bid to $70 in cash, but failed to match International's highest offer as the deadline passed. [Page C4.]</p>
        <p>The Ascent of WPP and Its Leader  It was not so long ago that Sir Martin Sorrell was on the brink of ruin, nearly bankrupting the British advertising conglomerate WPP Group that he was trying to build. But as Sir Martin announced that WPP had formally agreed to acquire Young &amp; Rubicam for stock worth $4.7 billion, it is clear that not only is Sir Martin back, he has vaulted to the top of Madison Avenue's short list. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Clinton Takes China Fight to Midwest  President Clinton took his campaign to elevate trade relations with China to the Midwest, arguing that if Congress rejects the measure it will deny troubled farmers a chance to tap a giant new market. Standing on hay bales at a Minnesota family farm, the president said soybean and corn producers could expect an ''almost incalculable'' increase in exports if China opens its markets to American agriculture the way other Asian nations have. [A6.]</p>
        <p>Ford Plans to Close Plant in Britain  Ford announced that it would close its biggest car assembly plant in Britain early in 2002, eliminating 1,900 jobs. Ford attributed the move to what it called the company's ''totally unacceptable'' financial performance in the whole of Europe. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Wholesale Prices Declined in April  Wholesale prices fell in April for the first time in 14 months as energy costs took their biggest plunge in nine years, more than outweighing a sharp jump in food prices. The Producer Price Index, which measures inflation pressures before they reach consumers, dipped an expected 0.3 percent last month. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Dow Ends Week on Positive Note  The blue-chip Dow Jones industrial average gained 63.40 points, or 0.60 percent, to close at 10,609.37 in light trading. Among the biggest gainers were General Motors and General Electric. The Nasdaq composite index rose 29.48 points, or 0.8 percent, to 3,529.06, while the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index jumped 13.15 points, or 0.9 percent, to 1,420.96. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Telefonica Is in Talks With Lycos  Terra Networks, an Internet company controlled by the Spanish phone giant Telefonica, told market regulators in Madrid that it was in talks with the Web search company, Lycos. Officials of Terra and Lycos would not comment further, but Spanish newspapers have reported that the companies were in talks to merge part or all of their activities. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Ingersoll-Rand in $1.55 Billion Deal  Ingersoll-Rand, a diversified industrial company, agreed to acquire Hussmann International, a maker of commercial refrigeration products, for $1.55 billion in cash. Ingersoll-Rand will also assume $275 million of Hussmann's debt. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Preussag May Buy Thomson Travel  Europe's largest travel company, Preussag of Germany, is said to be buying shares in Thomson Travel and to be considering an outright buyout. Preussag's German rival C&amp;N Touristic valued Thomson about $2.4 billion during buyout talks and has been pursuing a deal since April. Thomson said it had been contacted by another party, which may be interested in making a bid. [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
