<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="13FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199051"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EEDD123BF930A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1234" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>U.N. Leader Chides U.S. For Holding Back on Troops  Secretary General Kofi Annan, faced with war on several fronts in Africa, criticized the Clinton administration for a reluctance to put American troops on the ground in United Nations peacekeeping efforts.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>U.N. Leader Chides U.S. For Holding Back on Troops  Secretary General Kofi Annan, faced with war on several fronts in Africa, criticized the Clinton administration for a reluctance to put American troops on the ground in United Nations peacekeeping efforts.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Three hundred Jordanian peacekeepers arrived in Sierra Leone, and 100 United Nations civilian employees who had been evacuated returned to Freetown, the capital.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Heavy fighting erupted along the Ethiopia-Eritrea border. Although there have been occasional skirmishes recently, this appeared to be the worst fighting in nearly a year.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Debate on Kosovo Force  The Pentagon and a bipartisan group of senators criticized legislation setting a deadline for withdrawing Nato-led American peacekeepers.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Questions on Korea Massacre  New evidence has been published that appears to undermine the testimony of two witnesses who said American soldiers were ordered to kill civilians near the No Gun Ri bridge during the Korean War.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>China Official Dies After Fall  Officials confirmed that China's top foreign exchange regulator, Li Fuxiang, died on Wednesday, after falling from a hospital window. Hong Kong newspapers called the death a suicide.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Clinton Presses China Trade  President Clinton took his campaign to elevate trade relations with China to the Midwest, arguing that if Congress rejected the measure it would deny troubled farmers a chance to tap a giant new market.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Pakistan Coup Ruled Legal  The Supreme Court ruled that the coup last October was legal and justified because of corrupt and ineffective rule by Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif, but it set a three-year deadline for a return to civilian rule.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Russian Police Raid Defended  President Vladimir V. Putin gave a backhanded defense of a police raid on the corporate headquarters of a private media empire, saying, ''All are equal before the law, no matter what business they are in.''</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A9-14, 20</p>
        <p>Officer in Harassment Case Breaks Her Public Silence  Lieut. Gen. Claudia J. Kennedy, who has accused a fellow Army general of making unwanted sexual advances toward her in 1996, said women in uniform who face harassment need to report it immediately to friends and superiors or ''misconduct will continue to harm us.''</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>League Fights Costly Verdict  Lawyers for the Anti-Defamation League filed motions in a federal court in Denver asking a judge to set aside a defamation verdict against it or at least reduce the $10.5 million in damages that the jury awarded a couple who were called anti-Semites by a local league official.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Suit Against Islamic Charities  The parents of an Israeli-American teenager, David Boim, who died in a 1996 terrorist attack in Jerusalem, sued several Islamic charities, nonprofit groups and individuals that the Boims say raised money in the United States for Hamas, the militant Palestinian group. The Boims, who are seeking $600 million in damages, say the groups are legally responsible for their son's death.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Respite for New Mexico Fire  Better weather stabilized the fire that destroyed much of Los Alamos and threatened the nation's main weapons laboratory. But high winds were expected this weekend.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Lottery Winner Steps Forward  A 47-year-old owner of a Michigan swimming pool company claimed half the record $363 million Big Game lottery prize; after taxes, he will pocket about $61 million. Officials in Illinois were still seeking the other winning-ticket holder.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Recasting G.O.P. Primaries  The Rules Committee of the Republican National Committee voted, 36 to 13, for a new primary system in which the smallest states would hold their contests in February while the biggest states would have to wait until May. The plan must be approved by the full committee and then the national convention this summer.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Bush to Offer Trigger Locks  Gov. George W. Bush said he would spend $1 million a year to provide free trigger locks for handgun owners in Texas and, if elected president, would push for a national initiative, at a cost of $65 million a year.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Religion Journal</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Mayor to Devote Weekend To Health and Politics  Advisers said Mayor Giuliani would spend today and tomorrow considering treatment options for his prostate cancer and whether to stay in the Senate race. The mayor said he owed it to Republicans to make his plans known soon, and aides indicated an announcement by midweek.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Judge Allows Water Plant  A federal judge dismissed three lawsuits against a planned water-filtration plant in Van Cortlandt Park in the Bronx, allowing the city to go forward with a project that has been assailed by community groups and environmentalists.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Stolen Cyanide Trailer Found  Police officers in Queens found a stolen truck trailer that had held 20 drums of potassium cyanide, a highly poisonous chemical, on a deserted street. The chemical can be used for making bombs, but there was no indication that terrorists were involved in the theft.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Way Clear for Interim Chancellor  Harold O. Levy's last two competitors for the chancellor's position dropped out, a day before they were to be interviewed by the New York City Board of Education.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B7-16</p>
        <p>Auction Houses Disclose Data  Sotheby's and Christie's have given confidential company information to lawyers representing customers who accuse them of price-fixing in the wake of a federal inquiry. The move was a sign that the houses may be exploring a possible settlement of a potentially vast class-action suit.</p>
        <p>B13</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Miami Beats Knicks  The Miami Heat beat the Knicks, 77-76, in overtime. Miami holds a 2-1 lead the NBA Eastern Conference semifinals.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Scion of Racing Family Is Killed  Adam Petty, 19, a fourth-generation Nascar driver, died after crashing in practice in New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14</p>
        <p>Icahn's Nabisco Proposal  Carl C. Icahn said in a regulatory filing that he would pay Nabisco Group shareholders $19 in cash and $3 a share in short-term debt, which Mr. Icahn said he would retire within two years through a refinancing or the sale of Nabisco's assets. Stock analysts called the price fair, given bids for other food companies, but said the bidding could go higher. Nabisco Group closed at $19.69, up $2.13.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Wholesale Prices Ease  The Producer Price Index, which measures inflation pressures before they reach consumers, dipped 0.3 percent last month, after shooting up in February and March. Nonetheless, economists expect the Fed to push rates higher on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Stocks Markets Rise Slightly  The Dow gained 63.40 points, to 10,609.37; the Nasdaq rose 29.48 points, to 3,529.06; and the S.&amp; P. 500 climbed 13.15 points, to 1,420.96.</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Ford Closing Dagenham Plant  Ford said it would close its biggest car assembly plant in Britain by early 2002, with a loss of 1,900 jobs. Ford cited poor financial performance in the whole of Europe.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A14-15</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: New York's new archbishop; controlled burning, out of control; insuring a fair vote in Peru; a real New Jersey debate.  Columns: Anthony Lewis.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B15  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B16  Crossword</p>
        <p>B14  Weather</p>
        <p>D8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A9</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
