<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Near-Ruin to King of the Ad World</title>
    <meta content="Y13YOUN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199018"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wpp Group Plc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Young &amp; Rubicam Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorrell, Martin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E5D6153BF930A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1103" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Near-Ruin to King of the Ad World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, May 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>WPP Group chief executive Sir Martin Sorrell comments on his success in building an advertising gian in light of company's planned acquisition of Young &amp; Rubicam (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was not so long ago that Sir Martin Sorrell was on the brink of ruin, having nearly bankrupted the British advertising conglomerate, the WPP Group, that he was trying to build.</p>
        <p>But as Sir Martin announced today that WPP had formally agreed to acquire Young &amp; Rubicam for stock worth $4.7 billion, it was clear that he not only was back but had vaulted to the top of Madison Avenue's short list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was not so long ago that Sir Martin Sorrell was on the brink of ruin, having nearly bankrupted the British advertising conglomerate, the WPP Group, that he was trying to build.</p>
        <p>But as Sir Martin announced today that WPP had formally agreed to acquire Young &amp; Rubicam for stock worth $4.7 billion, it was clear that he not only was back but had vaulted to the top of Madison Avenue's short list.</p>
        <p>''If you told me 15 years ago that I would assemble this treasure trove of brands, I'd tell you to have your head examined,'' Sir Martin, the chief executive of WPP, said in an interview after a nearly all-night marathon to make official the biggest advertising acquisition in history. ''I can say that I am very proud of what we have achieved.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Sir Martin has poached one of the most influential and last major independent advertising companies in the world, adding to WPP's already bulging roster of holdings, which includes J. Walter Thompson and Ogilvy &amp; Mather as well as the public relations agencies Hill &amp; Knowlton and Cohn &amp; Wolfe.</p>
        <p>For one who has always said ''I don't claim to be an advertising man,'' Sir Martin has achieved the ultimate ad man's dream, assembling a prestigious list of clients that covers household brands like Ford Motor, I.B.M., American Express, AT&amp;T, Kraft and Sony.</p>
        <p>To Sir Martin, 55, it is still strictly business. ''I find the prospect of doing a deal like this daunting,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But he has always been known for hard-charging business tactics. He took over both J. Walter Thompson and Ogilvy &amp; Mather by force, successfully making bids that were less than friendly for both, in an industry where the assets of a company can literally walk out the front door. And many did.</p>
        <p>His fight for Ogilvy &amp; Mather, completed in 1989, was particularly vitriolic. In what has become lore in the advertising world, the legendary ad man David Ogilvy referred to Sir Martin as an ''odious little jerk.''</p>
        <p>Though the deal with Young &amp; Rubicam was considered friendly, Sir Martin's negotiating tactics were no different. The two companies broke off talks twice in a corporate brawl that at some points took on the dimensions of hostile bidding.</p>
        <p>Sir Martin and Thomas D. Bell Jr., Young &amp; Rubicam's chief executive, dislike each other, and the tension between them was partly why it took them so long to complete the deal, executives close to the talks said. Still, in the end, Mr. Bell capitulated to Sir Martin.</p>
        <p>''I guess he's very demanding, but you have to respect it,'' Lorna Tilbian, an analyst at the London office of West LB Panmure, an investment banking firm, said of Sir Martin. ''People who have achieved this level of success are not pussycats.''</p>
        <p>Both Sir Martin and Mr. Bell played friendly today in a conference call with reporters. ''We've always gotten along better than you thought,'' Mr. Bell said. Sir Martin chimed in after many of Mr. Bell's comments, adding, ''You're right on the button.''</p>
        <p>Despite that show of collegiality, Mr. Bell will be leaving the combined company once the merger is completed and the integration of the two parts is successful.</p>
        <p>''Two cooks spoil the broth,'' Mr. Bell said of his decision to step down. In the interim, he will serve as chairman of Y.&amp; R. and on a special four-member integration committee.</p>
        <p>''A company needs one clear designated leader,'' Mr. Bell said, ''and I can't think of anyone better to lead this combination than Sorrell.''</p>
        <p>Sir Martin has always wanted to be a leader, and with this deal he has transformed the company he turned from a maker of shopping-basket wire into the largest advertising company in the world, leapfrogging rivals like the Omnicom Group and the Interpublic Group of Companies.</p>
        <p>Sir Martin, who went to Cambridge and later to Harvard Business School, first made his name in the late 1970's and early 1980's, rising through the ranks of Saatchi &amp; Saatchi to become the company's financial director.</p>
        <p>He struck out on his own in 1986 by taking over Wire and Plastic Products, which effectively became a shell company for WPP. He immediately set out to build a worldwide advertising holding company, first by acquiring the venerable J. Walter Thompson in 1987 and then Ogilvy &amp; Mather in 1989.</p>
        <p>But his ambition to gain such size and muscle so fast cost him dearly as a recession hit in the early 1990's. WPP's buying spree pushed the conglomerate within an eyelash of going broke as debts taken on during the acquisition binge were aggravated by the markets' downturn. ''It was my mistake,'' Sir Martin said today of that period. Faced with the threat of bankruptcy in 1992, WPP underwent an extensive revamping.</p>
        <p>Without cash or even borrowing capacity to make further acquisitions, Sir Martin was forced to sit on the sidelines during most of the 1990's as he watched Omnicom, now the parent of BBDO Worldwide and DDB Worldwide, and Interpublic Group, now the parent of McCann-Erickson WorldGroup and the Lowe Group, gobble up a bevy of competitors in a rash of consolidation.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tilbian said Sir Martin's acquisition of Young &amp; Rubicam was a triumph for him. ''He was absolutely on a crusade to regain the respect of the industry and he did,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In the process, he has also made a lot of money. Last August, Sir Martin received about $:35 million ($53.1 million) in shares of WPP as part of a compensation package that raised eyebrows but that he recently extended to 14 other top executives. ''I have virtually my entire net worth committed to WPP for the next three to four years,'' Sir Martin said.</p>
        <p>Since Sir Martin received his $:35 million bonus last summer and reinvested it in WPP, the company's stock price has nearly doubled. It is unclear if Sir Martin will get an additional bonus from this deal. But he jokingly told Mr. Bell, ''Let's make sure you're not on the remuneration committee.''</p>
        <p>In the deal, WPP will pay 0.835 American depository receipt for every Y.&amp; R. share. The value of the acquisition has dropped precipitously this week, falling even lower today. In London, shares of WPP fell 42 pence, or 5 percent, to 803 ($12.16). Its American depository receipts, each worth five ordinary WPP shares, fell $3.50, or 5.5 percent, to $60 on Nasdaq. Young &amp; Rubicam shares fell 62.5 cents, to $47.75, on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
