<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Love Keeps Making Birdies; Woods Makes the Cut</title>
    <meta content="13GOLF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199043"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gte Byron Nelson Classic</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Love, Davis 3d</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E1DE123BF930A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Love Keeps Making Birdies; Woods Makes the Cut</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>IRVING, Tex., May 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>love keeps making birdies; woods makes the</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While Davis Love III thought about winning the tournament, Tiger Woods was thankful today just to make the cut.</p>
        <p>With a blistering round in sweltering 95-degree heat, Love shot a seven-under-par 63, propelling him into a four-stroke lead after the second round of the GTE Byron Nelson Classic. Love was 11 under par for the tournament (129), four strokes in front of John Huston, who was seven under par after shooting a 65 today. Six players were tied for third place at five under par: Mark Brooks, Glen Day, Neal Lancaster, Blaine McCallister, Jesper Parnevik and Kevin Sutherland.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While Davis Love III thought about winning the tournament, Tiger Woods was thankful today just to make the cut.</p>
        <p>With a blistering round in sweltering 95-degree heat, Love shot a seven-under-par 63, propelling him into a four-stroke lead after the second round of the GTE Byron Nelson Classic. Love was 11 under par for the tournament (129), four strokes in front of John Huston, who was seven under par after shooting a 65 today. Six players were tied for third place at five under par: Mark Brooks, Glen Day, Neal Lancaster, Blaine McCallister, Jesper Parnevik and Kevin Sutherland.</p>
        <p>Woods avoided the embarrassment of missing the weekend cut by making three birdies over his final five holes to reach even par for the tournament (140), safely within the cut line of three over par. Woods has made 48 consecutive cuts, the longest current streak on the PGA Tour, and he admitted feeling pressure to keep that streak alive.</p>
        <p>''I was definitely thinking about it,'' said Woods, who admitted he felt rusty after taking a four-week break. ''That cut streak means you're fighting all the time. Even when you're playing badly, you have the mental tenacity to hang in there on those bad days and make cuts. I'm not going to dog it out there. That's not my style.''</p>
        <p>Both Woods and Love played at Cottonwood Valley, the easier of the tournament's two courses. After opening with a 66 at the Four Seasons TPC to tie McCallister for the first-round lead, Love used his length to overpower Cottonwood during a round that included nine birdies and just two bogeys. Love birdied Nos. 3, 4, 6 and 7, and then added birdies at Nos. 10, 14, 15, 16 and 18. Love hit his approach shots so close to the pin that the longest birdie putt he made all day was 10 feet.</p>
        <p>After starting with a bogey on each of his first two holes, Love regrouped and turned a potentially tough day into a memorable one. That is the kind of resilience he has not always shown during the last two years, one reason he has failed to win since April 1998. That 25-month stretch without a victory is the longest dry spell Love has endured in more than 10 years. So after his poor start, he was pleased that he found a way to regroup.</p>
        <p>''After the way I started, I said to myself, 'It's time to start playing the way you've been playing,' '' said Love, who has 13 career victories, including the 1997 P.G.A. Championship. ''The last two years, I play good for a while, then I have a bad patch and let it ruin my tournament. I didn't let it ruin today. On this course, if you drive it in the fairway, you have a lot of opportunities. Today, I took advantage.''</p>
        <p>The weather also cooperated. After 38 mile-an-hour wind gusts on Thursday, the wind subsided to 25 m.p.h. this morning, and by this afternoon had fallen to 10 m.p.h. or less. With Love on top of his game, and the wind not causing major problems, he made birdies in bunches. And he said he planned to remain aggressive this weekend.</p>
        <p>Asked if he thought Woods was too far behind to be a threat in the tournament, Love said: ''I don't know if he's ever far enough behind. I need to keep doing what I've been doing the last couple of days. Hopefully that will be good enough. I've been in the lead a lot. I just haven't won. I've been feeling for a long time that if I could just get one or two good things to happen, I could get going again. I'm not happy with getting to the top of the career money list, then falling back, getting to No. 2 in the world, then falling back. I want to start moving back up to the top. And the only way to do that is to win.''</p>
        <p>CHIP SHOTS</p>
        <p>BEN CRENSHAW, who had missed 24 consecutive cuts, made the three-over-par cut by finishing the day exactly three over par for the tournament. Among those who missed the cut were JEFF SLUMAN (4 over), JUSTIN LEONARD (9 over) and MARK CALCAVECCHIA (12 over). Leonard, the 1997 British Open champion, is fighting a troublesome slump. He does not have a top 10 finish this year. ''It's hard to think that the hard work is worth it, because it's not paying off,'' Leonard said. ''But hopefully it will soon.'' . . . PHIL MICKELSON shot a 63 at Cottonwood to equal DAVIS LOVE III for the best round of the day. Mickelson was four under par for the tournament.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
