<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abducted and Then Shot, Student at Seton Hall Dies</title>
    <meta content="13ABDU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westfield, NJ</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seton Hall University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Honrath, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Massachi, Sohayla</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE3DE123BF930A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1074" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abducted and Then Shot, Student at Seton Hall Dies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, May 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seton Hall University student Sohayla Massachi is abducted near campus and killed by boyfriend Christopher Honrath at his apartment in Westfield, NJ; Honrath then takes his own life; two teenage girls witnessed abduction and attempted to report incident to campus security guard who directed them to local police station several blocks away; couple met 15 months ago on Internet but relationship has been fraught with abuse, each obtaining restraining orders against other (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 23-year-old Seton Hall University student died this afternoon, two days after she was abducted from a street near the campus and shot in the head by a former boyfriend, who then took his own life.</p>
        <p>The midday abduction had been witnessed by two teenage girls, but their frantic pleas to a campus security guard to help or call the police had been rejected, the police said. Today, Seton Hall officials said the guard, who works for a private agency hired by the university, was no longer assigned to the campus, and the university employee who supervised him had resigned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 23-year-old Seton Hall University student died this afternoon, two days after she was abducted from a street near the campus and shot in the head by a former boyfriend, who then took his own life.</p>
        <p>The midday abduction had been witnessed by two teenage girls, but their frantic pleas to a campus security guard to help or call the police had been rejected, the police said. Today, Seton Hall officials said the guard, who works for a private agency hired by the university, was no longer assigned to the campus, and the university employee who supervised him had resigned.</p>
        <p>The police in Westfield, N.J., where the shootings took place, said they were investigating the account of the girls, who had been walking home from high school. The girls said they  saw a man dragging a screaming woman to his car with a necktie tied around her neck, and when one sought a campus guard's help, he told her to walk two blocks to the police station and file a report.</p>
        <p>The police said they were exploring whether charges could be filed against the guard, but state officials said New Jersey law does not appear to apply to those who fail to report a crime. Neither the police nor the university would identify the guard.</p>
        <p>The victim, Sohayla Massachi of Union Township, was abducted about 2 p.m. Wednesday near the South Orange campus by her former boyfriend, Christopher Honrath, 24, who then drove her to his apartment in Westfield, where he shot her around 3 p.m., the police said. She never regained consciousness, said Rogers Ramsey, a spokesman for University Hospital here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Honrath died in his apartment, apparently shooting himself with a .38-caliber revolver moments after he shot Ms. Massachi, just as the police arrived after being summoned by a neighbor reporting a domestic quarrel, Lt. Francis Brunelle of the Westfield Police Department said. Fearing a hostage situation, he said, the officers waited for backup, which arrived 30 to 45 minutes later. They then entered the apartment.</p>
        <p>The deaths followed months of charges and countercharges of harassment and physical abuse between the couple, who met 15 months ago over the Internet, police investigators said.</p>
        <p>On the morning of the shootings, the couple had a court appearance in  State Superior Court in Elizabeth, where Mr. Honrath withdrew his March request for a restraining order against Ms. Massachi, who earlier in the year had obtained one against him.</p>
        <p>''He came to us in March as a victim claiming that he was being stalked by his girlfriend,'' said Detective Matthew Cassidy of the Westfield police, who before that complaint had interviewed a fearful Ms. Massachi about her own complaints against Mr. Honrath. ''But there were too many inconsistencies in what he said, and we concluded that he was making up stories.''</p>
        <p>The police said that according to the two girls who saw the abduction, Mr. Honrath jumped from his parked car just off the Seton Hall campus as Ms. Massachi left the grounds. Wrapping what appeared to be a necktie around her neck, Mr. Honrath -- who was 5 feet 11 inches tall and weighed about 300 pounds -- dragged her into his car as she screamed for help and the two girls shouted for him to stop.</p>
        <p>''The man was choking her and she was turning red and screaming, 'Help me, help me!' '' said one girl, Chituru Iromuanya, who spoke to  reporters outside her house in South Orange.</p>
        <p>Ms. Iromuanya, 17, said that as she stood there ''in shock and not knowing what to do,'' her friend Asia Davis, 17, ran about half a block to the security guard's post.</p>
        <p>Ms. Iromuanya said she noted the car's license number as it sped off.</p>
        <p>The police said the girls told them that the security guard, rather than helping or calling the police, told Ms. Davis to walk two blocks to the police station and file a report.</p>
        <p>''Those two girls were outstanding in what they did,'' Lieutenant Brunelle said. ''As for the security guard, we are looking into whether he can be charged under any state law.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the state attorney general, John Farmer Jr., said that the state's Good Samaritan Law allows the police to charge those who fail to provide medical assistance to a victim of a crime or an accident.  But it does not cover those who fail to  report a crime or to intervene to stop one, the spokesman said.</p>
        <p>The president of Seton Hall, Msgr. Robert Sheeran, said that all campus security guards are employees of  USA Security/Argentbright, a Hackensack company under contract with the university. The guard's supervisor, he said, was a university employee.</p>
        <p>A manager at the security company refused to comment today.</p>
        <p>Ms. Massachi, who grew up in Westfield, was an undergraduate student with a major in education. Mr. Honrath, a former roommate told The Star-Ledger in Newark, worked as a chef for a number of halfway houses in Jersey City.</p>
        <p>Detective Cassidy said the two met in February 1999 and dated until that April, when Ms. Massachi, charging that Mr. Honrath was physically abusive, went to Superior Court in Elizabeth seeking a restraining order against him.</p>
        <p>Later that month she withdrew the request, said the detective, who quoted her as saying later that she had ''hoped it would all go away.''</p>
        <p>The harassment apparently continued until December, when Ms. Massachi filed a complaint of harassment and physical abuse against Mr. Honrath at Westfield police headquarters. A month later, she sought a restraining order, and on Feb. 24 Westfield officers arrested Mr. Honrath, charging him with sending e-mail threats to Ms. Massachi.</p>
        <p>It was after that, said Detective Cassidy, that Mr. Honrath filed his request for a restraining order against Ms. Massachi and began filing complaints with at least nine New Jersey police agencies that she was harassing and stalking him.</p>
        <p>The detective said that all of the police agencies determined that his claims were unfounded.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
