<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Michigan, a Lunch Break Leads to $181 Million</title>
    <meta content="Y13LOT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lotteries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Michigan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Illinois</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ross, Larry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Christian, Nichole M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lotteries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD8153BF930A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Michigan, a Lunch Break Leads to $181 Million</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLE M. CHRISTIAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Christian, Nichole M</byline>
      <dateline>LANSING, Mich., May 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Larry Ross, 47-year-old owner of Michigan swimming pool company, wins half of $363-million Big Game jackpot, on 98 tickets he bought with lunchtime change; photo; other winning ticket was sold at gas station in Lake Zurich, Illinois (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A man walks into a convenience store, buys a hot dog with a $100 bill, spends the change on 98 lottery tickets and a few hours later, wins half of the nation's richest jackpot ever.</p>
        <p>It's a true story. Really. Ask Larry Ross, the 47-year-old owner of a Michigan swimming pool company, who bought one of the two winning tickets in the seven-state drawing called the Big Game. Mr. Ross and his family came out of hiding today to collect a check for half of the record $363 million prize. After taxes, he will pocket about $61 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A man walks into a convenience store, buys a hot dog with a $100 bill, spends the change on 98 lottery tickets and a few hours later, wins half of the nation's richest jackpot ever.</p>
        <p>It's a true story. Really. Ask Larry Ross, the 47-year-old owner of a Michigan swimming pool company, who bought one of the two winning tickets in the seven-state drawing called the Big Game. Mr. Ross and his family came out of hiding today to collect a check for half of the record $363 million prize. After taxes, he will pocket about $61 million.</p>
        <p>It took nine weeks for someone among the hundreds of thousands of people who bought reams of $1 tickets in Georgia, Illinois, Maryland,  Massachusetts, Michigan, New Jersey and Virginia to match the six numbers selected on Tuesday night. Illinois lottery officials were still seeking the only other person to pick the winning numbers. That ticket was bought at a gas station in Lake Zurich, Ill., a northwest suburb of Chicago. All told, the seven states sold more than 565 million $1 Big Game tickets over the nine weeks.</p>
        <p>Even with the check in hand yesterday, Mr. Ross said he still could not believe how a simple lunch-break whim turned him into a multimillionaire. He tried to appear composed, to ignore the beads of sweat on his brow, as he and his family stood with Gov. John Engler of Michigan in their first news conference.</p>
        <p>''My wife told me to buy some tickets,'' he said, glancing at his wife, Nancy, 46, who clutched a bouquet of peach roses and appeared dazed by the throng of reporters studying her family: their sons Eric, 24, and Ian, 21; their daughter, Shannon, 12; Eric's wife, Jamie; and Ian's fiancee, Katie Niemasz.</p>
        <p>''I asked the guy to give me the change in lotto tickets,'' Mr. Ross continued, referring to the clerk at Mr. K's Party Shoppe, a suburban Detroit store near his family's home where Mr. Ross sometimes buys sodas and sandwiches, and where he bought the hot dog and tickets.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ross added: ''Nobody ever expects to win. You hope, you dream you could win.''</p>
        <p>Since Tuesday night, anonymity is what Mr. Ross has hoped for most. After learning he had matched all six numbers, Mr. Ross whisked his family from their modest four-bedroom ranch-style house in Shelby Township, Mich., to a nearby hotel.</p>
        <p>But the pressure of trying to protect his winning ticket, which he wrapped in plastic, became too much to bear, he said, adding: ''I haven't slept in three days. It's a great diet program, win the lotto and lose weight. I haven't eaten in three days.''</p>
        <p>He has been far too busy worrying about his family's new status. ''You have the ecstasy of winning,'' Mr. Ross said. ''Then you start realizing the agony of what might happen. You worry about your family and who's at risk. We live in a nice middle-class neighborhood, but we don't have security like rich people have.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ross said he had hired lawyers, financial planners and real estate agents to allay some of those fears. ''We are going to put the money to use for something good,'' he said. ''We're going to wait 90 days before we buy anything.''</p>
        <p>After that, the search begins for a purple Jaguar, the one thing Nancy has wanted, he said, since they married. The family will also take its first vacation in 13 years, once everyone agrees on a destination.</p>
        <p>Equally important, Mr. Ross said, would be finding time to continue servicing pools for the customers who helped him put food on the table before he became a millionaire.</p>
        <p>''I'd like them all to know we will take care of them,'' said Mr. Ross, who typically works 80 to 100 hours a week during the spring and summer.</p>
        <p>He said he would eventually hand the business to Eric, adding, ''I'd like to start a new job playing golf.''</p>
        <p>A bit of controversy intruded upon today's celebration. Don Gilmer, Michigan's lottery commissioner, said that George Kassab, the owner of Mr. K's Party Shoppe, was suing the state, contending that retailers who sell winning tickets are not fairly rewarded. Mr. Kassab received a bonus check of only $2,000. In Illinois, the vendor who sold the other winning ticket received $1.8 million, or 1 percent of that winner's share of the jackpot. Mr. Kassab did not return telephone calls seeking comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gilmer described Michigan's commission as one of the country's more generous. No other state, he said, offers lottery retailers a six percent commission plus a two percent bonus up to $2,000 on winning tickets that exceed $600. Most states offer rewards only on tickets that win more than $1,000, he said.</p>
        <p>''The Michigan retailers in the last fiscal year got $121 million in commissions,'' Mr. Gilmer said. ''If we would have had the Illinois system, with the big super bonus thing, they  would have received $25 million less in commissions.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ross, a frequent customer at the store, called the dispute unfortunate, but he said he had not decided whether to offer Mr. Kassab any of his winnings. ''We're still in a daze,'' he explained.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
