<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>REPORT DISCLOSING MASSACRE BY G.I.'S IS UNDER QUESTION</title>
    <meta content="13KORE$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199075"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Korean War</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Associated Press</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">US News &amp; World Report (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stars and Stripes (Pub)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Becker, Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barringer, Felicity</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daily, Edward L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flint, Delos</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Korean War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E0DB123BF930A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1577" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>REPORT DISCLOSING MASSACRE BY G.I.'S IS UNDER QUESTION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH BECKER and FELICITY BARRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Becker, Elizabeth; Barringer, Felicity</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New evidence undermines testimony of two witnesses who have charged that American soldiers were ordered to fire on civilians during Korean War, and that hundreds were killed in July 1950; Associated Press investigation won two major awards, was featured by many newspapers including The New York Times and prompted Pentagon investigation which confirmed that refugees were fired on; Army documents retrieved by Stars.com (Stars and Stripes) and US News &amp; World Report indicate that neither Edward Daily nor Delos Flint were at scene; Daily was in maintenance unit miles away from No Gun Ri bridge, and Flint had been wounded and evacuated; Flint sticks by story, but says he does not remember much; contradictory accounts reviewed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New evidence has been published that appears to undermine the testimony of two witnesses who said that American soldiers were ordered to kill civilians during the Korean War.</p>
        <p>Their charge was featured in a prominent and detailed news report last September by The Associated Press, which concluded for the first time that American soldiers killed hundreds of Korean civilians in July 1950. It also quoted veterans who said they were at the scene, some of whom said they were given orders to shoot. Other soldiers quoted by the news agency said they did not remember such orders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New evidence has been published that appears to undermine the testimony of two witnesses who said that American soldiers were ordered to kill civilians during the Korean War.</p>
        <p>Their charge was featured in a prominent and detailed news report last September by The Associated Press, which concluded for the first time that American soldiers killed hundreds of Korean civilians in July 1950. It also quoted veterans who said they were at the scene, some of whom said they were given orders to shoot. Other soldiers quoted by the news agency said they did not remember such orders.</p>
        <p>The investigation by The Associated Press won two of journalism's most prestigious awards, a Pulitzer and the Polk. Numerous newspapers, including The New York Times, carried the report on their front pages. And it prompted an investigation by the Pentagon, concerned about the impact on relations with an important Asian ally, South Korea.</p>
        <p>Despite the new questions, senior Defense Department officials said yesterday that an Army investigation has confirmed the central element of the report, that American troops fired on refugees, resulting in what the Pentagon calls the ''tragic death of hundreds of civilians.''</p>
        <p>Army documents retrieved by Stripes.com, an electronic edition of The Stars and Stripes, which covers the military, and an investigation by U.S. News &amp; World Report, question the credibility of Edward Daily, a witness interviewed in the original Associated Press investigation of the deaths.</p>
        <p>The new reports state that he was not at the site, the No Gun Ri bridge, when the refugees were killed, but instead was serving with a maintenance unit miles away.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daily was among those who told the news agency that the shootings of civilians at No Gun Ri were carried out under orders.</p>
        <p>''The command looked at it as getting rid of the problem in the easiest way,'' he said. ''That was to shoot them in a group.''</p>
        <p>A second of the dozen witnesses quoted in the original report, Delos Flint, also was not at the bridge on July 26, 1950, when the shooting reportedly began, according to the new reports; they found he had been wounded and was already ferried off the battlefield.</p>
        <p>Reached by telephone yesterday, Mr. Flint stuck by what he told The Associated Press. ''They told us to shoot,'' he said from his home in Clio, Mich. ''I told the other guys you can shoot all you want but I didn't believe in it.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Flint said he could not remember much of what happened after he was seriously wounded in the fighting. ''I don't hardly remember being sent to the hospital and I didn't remember anything for a long time after the war,'' he said. ''I do remember spending 18 months in the hospital at Valley Forge.''</p>
        <p>The Army refused to comment on the new evidence uncovered by the news organizations this week.</p>
        <p>''In order to maintain the integrity of the No Gun Ri review, we will not address the accuracy of any press reports,'' Charles L. Cragin, acting under secretary of defense for personnel, said in a statement. ''It is premature to discuss our findings until the review is complete.''</p>
        <p>The Army has concluded that as many as several hundred civilians were killed at No Gun Ri and is focusing on the orders given to the American soldiers at the bridge, according to a senior Army official.</p>
        <p>''It's not just the taking of innocent life,'' said the senior Army official, who noted that more than one million people died in that war. ''What was unique in this situation was this notion that it was intentional.''</p>
        <p>A senior Pentagon official said the Army had interviewed hundreds of witnesses, American and South Korean, and was examining thousands of pages of documents to discover whether G.I.'s killed civilians accidentally in the heat of battle, whether they were ordered to do so, or whether they thought they were under orders to do so, as some of the A.P. witnesses asserted.</p>
        <p>The doubts about some sources are coming out just over a month after the board of the Pulitzer Prizes at Columbia University awarded the Associated Press its prize for investigative reporting, ''for revealing, with extensive documentation, the decades-old secret of how America soldiers early in the Korean War killed hundreds of Korean civilians in a massacre at No Gun Ri Bridge.''</p>
        <p>In a statement this week and in later interviews, A.P. officials defended its work, saying that Mr. Daily's account was not central to the original dispatch nor to subsequent accounts. And they said they do not question the ambiguous and sometimes contradictory evidence of how the killings at No Gun Ri occurred -- indeed, they say, their reports reflected that ambiguity.</p>
        <p>Kelly Smith Tunney, the director of corporate communications for the news agency, said yesterday: ''The first question is what happened at the bridge. We have done extensive research and double and triple-checked facts. And we're not apologetic about what we've done. It was all dependent on distant records, and there were many ambiguities, all of which was in our original reporting.''</p>
        <p>The A.P. released an article early yesterday on the Army's continuing investigation into No Gun Ri. The article cited the documents uncovered by Stripes.com that contradicted the news agency's investigation, and noted that U.S. News was preparing a report on the matter.</p>
        <p>Former soldiers initially interviewed by The Associated Press gave accounts that contradict the new reports, and placed Mr. Daily at No Gun Ri, according to one of the reporters. One former soldier, an officer, described Mr. Daily's receipt of a battlefield commission.</p>
        <p>And another soldier present, Jim Kerns, drew reporters a diagram of his machine-gun emplacement and those on either side, according to Martha Mendoza, one of the three reporters who wrote the article. ''I was on the right-hand side, Daily was on the left, and Harold Blanc, he was in the middle,'' Mr. Kerns said.</p>
        <p>The incident at the railroad bridge near the village of No Gun Ri took place in the early days of the Korean War. Army commanders feared that North Korean infiltrators were among the refugees fleeing the fighting between the two Korean armies.</p>
        <p>The A.P. said its reporters had spoken to six veterans who said they fired at the refugees and six others who said they witnessed a mass killing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daily and Mr. Flint were two of the veterans who have said they were at the bridge and were ordered to fire on civilians. After the first A.P. report, they were interviewed by other newspapers, magazines and television networks, and expanded on their original charges.</p>
        <p>But the records unearthed by Stripes.com show that neither man was at No Gun Ri when the refugees came under fire. The evidence about Mr. Daily's presence at the scene is the most sharply disputed.</p>
        <p>According to the newly uncovered documents, Mr. Daily did not serve in the unit, and did not receive the battlefield commission he described to The Associated Press. The documents also dispute other examples that Mr. Daily has cited of his military record.</p>
        <p>In an autobiographical sketch for a history of his division's Korean War experiences, Mr. Daily claimed to have been awarded the Distinguished Service Cross, Silver Star, Bronze Star and three Purple Heart medals, none of which appear in his official record, according to the newly uncovered documents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daily could not be reached for comment at his home in Tennessee,  but Ms. Mendoza, in an interview yesterday, quoted from the text of videotape interviews with Robert Carroll, a first lieutenant at the time of the massacre.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mendoza quoted Mr. Carroll describing Mr. Daily's battlefield commission: ''Daily was commissioned as a 19-year-old kid,'' he said. ''That's how short we were.''</p>
        <p>Some of the other documentary evidence contradicts the memories of other principals, according to Associated Press journalists.</p>
        <p>Charles J. Hanley, another of the three A.P. reporters, said that Eugene Hesselman, in an early interview, contradicted the daily report for his unit.</p>
        <p>The unit's ''morning report'' indicates that he had been wounded and evacuated on the day the killing began. Mr. Hanley said that Mr. Hesselman had explained to a reporter months before the publication of the No Gun Ri report that he had received a shrapnel wound to the hand, but had remained at the site after being bandaged.</p>
        <p>According to an Army regimental document obtained by Stripes.com, one witness, Mr. Flint, had been evacuated for medical treatment on July 25, 1950, the day before the shooting of refugees began. But The Associated Press quotes a ''morning report'' that said he was wounded on July 26, 1950.</p>
        <p>''The fact that some guy isn't credible doesn't mean we don't have a problem,'' said a senior Pentagon official. ''But it is a warning that there is bad information floating around.''</p>
        <p>In those first months of the war, the Army was underequipped and poorly trained, according to Col. David R. Hughes, now retired, who as a lieutenant earned a Distinguished Service Cross and two Silver Stars in Korea.</p>
        <p>''There was a seven-mile retreat just before No Gun Ri and the first units got chewed up badly,'' said Colonel Hughes who arrived in Korea a few months after the incident.</p>
        <p>Last September, The Associated Press published its long account, which is still on its Web site  (www.ap.org), complete with videotapes containing sections of interviews with Mr. Daily and Mr. Hesselman.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
