<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Tiger Lady' Vows to Fight an Order to Close Compound</title>
    <meta content="13TIGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199069"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sanitation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jackson Township (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Maria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Byron-Marasek, Joan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tassini, John R (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE7DB123BF930A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Tiger Lady' Vows to Fight an Order to Close Compound</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIA NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Maria</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joan Byron-Marasek, who has 26 tigers housed at compound in Jackson Township, NJ, is in danger of losing her legal fight against closing preserve; her lawyer will file court document saying why she should be allowed to continue operating under her current license to keep and exhibit tigers as she has for more than two decades; Administrative Law Judge John R Tassini recommends compound be closed finding that it is unsanitary and rat-infested and that Ms. Byron-Marasek failed to keep adequate records or cooperate with state inspectors (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even as New Jersey officials work to find a new home for 26 tigers housed at a compound in Jackson Township, Joan Byron-Marasek, the ''Tiger Lady'' who has been raising the animals on her property for 24 years, is determined to continue her legal fight against a judge's order last month to shut down the preserve.</p>
        <p>Ms. Byron-Marasek's lawyer, Valter H. Must, said yesterday that he planned to file a court document on Tuesday saying why she should be allowed to continue operating her Tigers Only Preservation Society in Jackson Township. Last month, John R. Tassini, an administrative law judge, upheld a decision by the State Division of Fish, Game and Wildlife not to renew Ms. Byron-Marasek's license to keep and exhibit the tigers on her property. The judge recommended the compound be closed, finding that it was ''unsanitary and rat-infested'' and that Ms. Byron-Marasek failed to keep adequate records or cooperate with state inspectors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even as New Jersey officials work to find a new home for 26 tigers housed at a compound in Jackson Township, Joan Byron-Marasek, the ''Tiger Lady'' who has been raising the animals on her property for 24 years, is determined to continue her legal fight against a judge's order last month to shut down the preserve.</p>
        <p>Ms. Byron-Marasek's lawyer, Valter H. Must, said yesterday that he planned to file a court document on Tuesday saying why she should be allowed to continue operating her Tigers Only Preservation Society in Jackson Township. Last month, John R. Tassini, an administrative law judge, upheld a decision by the State Division of Fish, Game and Wildlife not to renew Ms. Byron-Marasek's license to keep and exhibit the tigers on her property. The judge recommended the compound be closed, finding that it was ''unsanitary and rat-infested'' and that Ms. Byron-Marasek failed to keep adequate records or cooperate with state inspectors.</p>
        <p>He gave Ms. Byron-Marasek ''a reasonable period of time'' to move the tigers to properly licensed compounds elsewhere, but instead, she and her lawyer say they intend to exhaust all legal remedies before giving up.</p>
        <p>Under state law, the commissioner of the State Department of Environmental Conservation, which oversees the fish and game division, has 45 days to accept, modify or reject the administrative law judge's decision. If he accepts it, Ms. Byron-Marasek could appeal the ruling to the Appellate Division of the state court system.</p>
        <p>''She's not going to give up her fight to stay open,'' Mr. Must said. ''The tigers are my client's life's meaning. Joan knows that if they close her down, the division would end up killing her tigers.''</p>
        <p>State officials say they have never said they would euthanize the tigers if they shut her  compound. Sharon Southard, a spokeswoman for the Department of Environmental Protection, said officials had worked with several private groups around the country that have  offered to take the tigers and care for them if Ms. Byron-Marasek's compound closes.</p>
        <p>''It is Joan's responsibility to remove the tigers, not the department's,'' Ms. Southard said. ''But we have been willing to help her.''</p>
        <p>One group that has been in touch with the state is the Wild Animal Orphanage in San Antonio, which is part of a larger organization, the American Sanctuary Association, that provides refuge for exotic animals.</p>
        <p>The association was founded two years ago by four people, including the actress Tippi Hedren, out of concern that more and more people are buying exotic pets and then abandoning them when they do not know how to care for them or the animals get too big for their surroundings.</p>
        <p>''There are a couple of thousand big cats purchased every year in Texas alone,'' said Carol Asvestas, the director of the Wild Animal Orphanage. ''These animals are literally thrown away.''</p>
        <p>In the case of Ms. Byron-Marasek, she did not recently buy her animals, and she is certainly not abandoning them. More than two decades ago, Ms. Byron-Marasek, an actress who worked as a teenager for an importer of wild animals, moved to New Jersey and with her husband bought five 8-week-old tigers after obtaining a permit from the state. The permit allows people to keep wild or exotic animals for theatrical or educational purposes, but the state says Ms. Byron-Marasek never used them for that reason, a charge she denies.</p>
        <p>In an interview last year, she said she accumulated tigers because she wanted to help preserve the species from extinction, and said they were her life's work.</p>
        <p>The compound came under scrutiny by the state in January 1999, when a 4-year-old 431-pound tiger wandering loose in the area had to be killed by police officers after they were unable to sedate it with tranquilizer darts.</p>
        <p>The tiger was found close to Ms. Byron-Marasek's compound and to Great Adventure, a theme park that also keeps tigers. A check of the park and its records found all of its tigers accounted for, but similar efforts to check Ms. Byron-Marasek's property and records were met with denials that the escaped tiger was hers.</p>
        <p>Ms. Asvestas of the Wild Animal Orphanage in Texas said Ms. Byron-Marasek's claims that she is raising the animals to save them from extinction were illogical because she was not providing any of the proper conditions to do so.</p>
        <p>She said Ms. Byron-Marasek was allowing the animals to inbreed, which will result in offspring with physical and emotional problems. ''These animals would never be able to live on their own in the wild,'' Ms. Asvestas said, ''and no zoo or conservation facility would ever take these animals.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
