<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="22FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216722"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3D7143AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1184" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Israeli Hopes Rise At Mideast Peace Talks  The Israeli peace delegation's mood shifted from dire to hopeful as officials outside Camp David said Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel believed the chances for the summit meeting's success had improved. President Clinton, who is attending an economic meeting of the leading industrial nations in Okinawa, also sounded upbeat.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Clinton Meets With Putin  President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia met with President Clinton to argue against American deployment of a national missile shield. They met during a break in the Group of 8 meeting in Okinawa.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Israeli Hopes Rise At Mideast Peace Talks  The Israeli peace delegation's mood shifted from dire to hopeful as officials outside Camp David said Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel believed the chances for the summit meeting's success had improved. President Clinton, who is attending an economic meeting of the leading industrial nations in Okinawa, also sounded upbeat.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Clinton Meets With Putin  President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia met with President Clinton to argue against American deployment of a national missile shield. They met during a break in the Group of 8 meeting in Okinawa.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Strengthening Ties With Cuba  Successive House and Senate votes to ease restrictions on American travel and certain sales to Cuba are the latest evidence of a gradual but seismic shift toward normalizing ties with the Marxist-run island, said lawmakers and Cuba experts.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Hurdle Sought in Ivory Coast  Ivoirians are to vote on a proposed constitutional change whose major parts were intended specifically to exclude Alassane Ouattara, a former prime minister, from running in the presidential election.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Battle Over International Court  Canada ratified the treaty creating the International Criminal Court and announced that it was the first nation to have brought its national laws in line with the new tribunal, while the United States fought to prevent Americans from falling under the court's jurisdiction.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Advance for Iranian Women  Young women in Iran make up nearly 60 percent of all university entrants although they are a minority of the population as a whole. They are also leaving home as single women in historically high numbers, leading a quiet revolution with wide-ranging implications for political and social relations.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Oil Taints Beaches in France  Crude oil continues to wash up on the Brittany coast, prompting one town to man its beaches with teams to reassure tourists.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A8-12, 16</p>
        <p>Special Counsel Finds U.S. Faultless in Waco Actions  John C. Danforth, the special counsel investigating the 1993 tear-gas assault by federal agents on the Branch Davidian compound, issued a sweeping report that cleared Attorney General Janet Reno and the government of any wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Asbestos Inquiry at E.P.A.  The Environmental Protection Agency is investigating why its officials ignored evidence for 18 years that W. R. Grace was using ore laden with asbestos in an array of building products. An agency study in 1982 found alarming levels of asbestos in ore that Grace had said included harmless amounts of the material.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Cheney as Bush Favorite  Richard B. Cheney, the former defense secretary who is heading Gov. George W. Bush's search for a vice presidential nominee, has emerged as a leading contender for the job, changing his voter registration to make his selection possible.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore asserted that Governor Bush's handling of the Texas budget proved he would be an incompetent steward of the national economy, inclined to squandering the surplus on tax cuts for the rich.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Opponents of Patrick J. Buchanan's efforts to win the Reform Party's presidential nomination say they have evidence of irregularities by his campaign in the primary that could disqualify him.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Pentagon Plans Gay Initiative  The Pentagon announced an ''anti-harassment action plan'' that would require military commanders to discipline service members who engaged in, condoned or ignored antigay behavior.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Arrests Linked to Hezbollah  Federal officials arrested 18 people in raids throughout the Charlotte, N.C., area, in what they called a broad conspiracy to aid the Islamic organization Hezbollah, listed by the government as a terrorist group.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Fined for Caviar Smuggling  A Maryland company, two of its officials and a third person pleaded guilty to federal fraud, smuggling and wildlife endangerment charges, capping a case that exposed a large-scale caviar smuggling ring.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Prosecutors Widen Inquiry Into Torricelli's '96 Race  Federal prosecutors are intensifying an investigation into the role that Senator Robert G. Torricelli's office may have played in illegal contributions to his 1996 Senate campaign, lawyers and others familiar with the case say. Mr. Torricelli is preparing to seek the Democratic nomination for governor of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Giuliani Faults Stance on Virus  Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani sharply criticized state and federal environmental officials for blocking the city from spraying pesticides in wetlands and other marsh areas in its battle against the West Nile virus, arguing that humans are more important than a few fish.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Interviews conducted in the city and suburbs indicated that many people feel ill-informed about both the dangers and specifics of West Nile, and the risks posed by pesticides, and that how people react depends largely on a complex array of factors, many of them subjective.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Opera Patron Charged in Theft  Manhattan prosecutors announced a 16-count indictment against Robert Whitehead, a financier who is a bountiful contributor to the Metropolitan Opera, on charges of grand larceny and securities fraud.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Religion Journal</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B7-16</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Woods Leads British Open  Tiger Woods shot a six-under-par 66 for a three-stroke lead heading into the third round. At 24, he can become the youngest player to complete the career Grand Slam.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Armstrong Wins Tour Stage  Lance Armstrong won a long individual time trial in the Tour de France and solidified his overall lead.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Charles C. I. Merritt  A Canadian Army officer who was taken captive in the Dieppe raid of World War II but emerged as a heroic figure on a disastrous day for his countrymen, he was 91.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>ABC Backs Off Marketing Plan  ABC backed away from a controversial plan to use sitcom stars to promote its fall lineup by leaving taped messages on the home answering machines of viewers.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Toysmart Settles With F.T.C.  The Federal Trade Commission said it had reached a settlement to permit Toysmart.com, a defunct online toy seller, to sell its customer database as part of its bankruptcy plan, over the continued objections of privacy advocates and attorneys general of 39 states.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Ericsson Shares Fall Sharply  Investors punished shares in the Swedish company Ericsson despite a healthy increase in second-quarter earnings as concern grew that Ericsson might be losing ground in the battle for control of the thriving market for wireless phones.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Amgen Advances Its Case  Amgen won another round in its patent infringement lawsuit against Transkaryotic Therapies when the judge overseeing the case eliminated some of the arguments Transkaryotic was trying to use.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A14-15</p>
        <p>Editorials: The Senate's diminishing appeal; Republican tax cuts; demolishing democracy in Fiji; cooler subways.</p>
        <p>Columns: Anthony Lewis.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B15  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B16  Crossword</p>
        <p>B14  Weather</p>
        <p>D8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
