<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ivory Coast's Junta Tries To Block Comeback Bid</title>
    <meta content="Y22IVOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Constitutional Amendments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ivory Coast</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guei, Robert (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ouattara, Alassane D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Onishi, Norimitsu</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ivory Coast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Ivory Coast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutional Amendments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E1DB143AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1361" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ivory Coast's Junta Tries To Block Comeback Bid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORIMITSU ONISHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Onishi, Norimitsu</byline>
      <dateline>ABIDJAN, Ivory Coast, July 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alassane Ouattara, mild-mannered international banker, vows to win presidential election in Ivory Coast even though constitutional amendment before voters on July 23 is intended to disqualify him; accuses country's military rulers, led by Gen Robert Guei, of trying to hold on to power; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This onetime redoubt of political stability and steady growth in West Africa has been through a lot in the last year: the fall of an unpopular president, the first coup in its history and military misrule that twice in the last month raised the possibility of another army uprising.</p>
        <p>During all this tumult the spotlight has stayed on one man, a former prime minister and mild-mannered international banker, Alassane Ouattara.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This onetime redoubt of political stability and steady growth in West Africa has been through a lot in the last year: the fall of an unpopular president, the first coup in its history and military misrule that twice in the last month raised the possibility of another army uprising.</p>
        <p>During all this tumult the spotlight has stayed on one man, a former prime minister and mild-mannered international banker, Alassane Ouattara.</p>
        <p>Since Mr. Ouattara returned here a year ago from Washington, where he served as the International Monetary Fund's deputy managing director, his political fortunes have been on a roller coaster. He is down again -- and, along with him, maybe the chances of Ivory Coast's smooth transition back to civilian rule.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, Ivoirians are to vote on a proposed constitutional change whose key parts were intended specifically to exclude Mr. Ouattara from running in the presidential election scheduled for September.</p>
        <p>Speaking with a bitterness and a weariness that people say are new to him, Mr. Ouattara, 58, vowed in an interview last week to win in September.</p>
        <p>''It's this group of mediocre people,'' Mr. Ouattara said of his main political opponents and the military government. ''They know that they could not stand competition. They have their toys they want to keep to themselves. They know that if we open up, they are so mediocre they would lose everything.''</p>
        <p>Today the country's military ruler, Gen. Robert Guei, declared a four-day state of emergency, which members of his junta said was intended to ensure that the referendum take place smoothly.</p>
        <p>For years President Henri Konan Bedie, who was ousted in a coup last Dec. 24, tried to eliminate Mr. Ouattara as a rival by arguing that he was less of an Ivoirian than others because his father was from neighboring Burkina Faso.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bedie's strategy was part of an overall concept of ''Ivoirite,'' which he argued was a set of values shared by pure Ivoirians, but which was essentially tribalism that sought to draw a line between Christian southerners and Muslim northerners like Mr. Ouattara.</p>
        <p>The cleavage was strange in a country that was long known for its ethnic tolerance. But even though Mr. Ouattara always maintained that both of his parents were Ivoirian and that he himself was as Ivoirian as anyone else, ethnic divisions have widened in the last year.</p>
        <p>For a few months after the fall of Mr. Bedie, General Guei preached ethnic reconciliation, and the general appeared to be on friendly terms with Mr. Ouattara.</p>
        <p>But as General Guei's intention to hold on to power has become clearer, the two men have stopped cooperating. The general, a member of a minority ethnic group from the southwest, has adopted the same ethnic strategy against Mr. Ouattara. A commission set up to prepare the constitutional referendum recommended that a presidential candidate must be Ivoirian-born of a father or mother born in Ivory Coast.</p>
        <p>On Monday evening, just six days before the referendum, General Guei decreed that only children of two Ivoirian-born parents could run for president. In a news conference, the general asserted that 15 of the country's 18 administrative regions had pressed him to tighten the requirement.</p>
        <p>''The people have expressed their wish,'' said the general, who came to power after young soldiers mutinied throughout Ivory Coast in late December. ''We are here to respond to their wishes.''</p>
        <p>But the change was widely interpreted as another effort to dislodge Mr. Ouattara. Another clause -- that a candidate should never have availed himself of another nationality -- also seemed aimed at Mr. Ouattara, who represented Burkina Faso for a West African financial institution earlier in his career, a relatively common practice at the time.</p>
        <p>Immediately after the coup, Mr. Ouattara described it as a ''popular revolution.'' He said he hoped that the new military ruler would not try to cling to power, the way others have typically done in Africa.</p>
        <p>''The general was in retirement,'' Mr. Ouattara said. ''So we thought he was really coming to help the process of restoring democracy as he said he would. But obviously once in power he wanted to confiscate and grab power. And this is quite a disappointment for all of us who consider ourselves democrats.''</p>
        <p>Arguing that none of the clauses affect his eligibility, Mr. Ouattara has told his followers to endorse the proposal, as have the two major political parties besides his. So while the outcome may not be in doubt, it will yield hints as to how the election in September might unfold.</p>
        <p>A constitutional court that will rule on the eligibility of presidential candidates recently got a new head: one of General Guei's legal advisers. If Mr. Ouattara is legally prevented from running, it is likely that the battle will spill into the streets.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure I'll get popular support,'' Mr. Ouattara said. ''But I hope it will not get to that point. I hope that the international community, the regional partners and domestic pressure will put sense into the head of the general.''</p>
        <p>A couple of weeks ago, in a news conference a day after meeting General Guei, the United States ambassador, George Mu, said Washington was worried about Ivory Coast's stability. The ambassador restated the State Department's position that General Guei, having seized power by force, should not be a presidential candidate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mu's comments came after two days of rioting by soldiers in Abidjan, the country's largest city. Displeased that they had not received money they said had been promised them, the soldiers shut down businesses and the airport.</p>
        <p>General Guei took refuge in the police headquarters and was able to defuse the situation only after agreeing to give soldiers about $1,500 each.</p>
        <p>The general accused Mr. Ouattara's party of fomenting the riots, a charge Mr. Ouattara denied. The American ambassador said the violence appeared to have been strictly over money.</p>
        <p>''The mutiny reduced the popularity of the general, who now looks weakened,'' said a Western diplomat here.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it was a reminder that since the coup, even the general has not had full control over the country's 14,000-member military. A military emboldened even further, and the resulting instability, would make it harder to reverse the country's slide and would turn it into a problem for the region, say many Ivoirians and foreigners here.</p>
        <p>After Nigeria, Ivory Coast is the economic leader in West Africa. It is the world's largest cacao producer and stands at the top of French-speaking Africa.</p>
        <p>But Abidjan, an African bright spot famous for its smooth roads and solid public works, is beginning to show the signs of being led by a government that has little money left. Gaping potholes and collapsed entry ramps have been left unrepaired for months.</p>
        <p>Saying he will run and win in September, Mr. Ouattara promised an International Monetary Fund-style cleanup of Ivory Coast's economy that would include a sweeping anti-corruption campaign and an overhaul of an inefficient bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>Having left the monetary fund only a year ago, Mr. Ouattara said he was pessimistic about Africa. He has seen too many African countries ground down by men whose only concern was to capture or keep power.</p>
        <p>''Clearly, if you have a system where the people can vote you out, the situation will be different,'' he said. ''But many people that get in are rigging elections or doing it by coup d'etat, because they are mediocre. They know they cannot stand competition. They confiscate power and continue to rule the country.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
