<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore, With Gusto, Attacks Bush on Budget</title>
    <meta content="Y22GORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E2DB143AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore, With Gusto, Attacks Bush on Budget</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore asserts that Gov George W Bush's handling of Texas budget proves he would be an incompetent steward of national economy, inclined to squander the surplus on tax cuts for the rich; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cramming several weeks of attacks on Gov. George W. Bush of Texas into one speech, Vice President Al Gore asserted today that the governor's handling of the state's budget proved he would be an incompetent steward of the national economy, inclined to squandering the surplus on tax cuts for the rich.</p>
        <p>Brimming with confidence in a speech before the leaders of 30 transportation unions, almost all of which have endorsed him, Mr. Gore wove together themes he had spun out separately in recent weeks, creating a tapestry of harsh questions about his Republican rival's fitness to be president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cramming several weeks of attacks on Gov. George W. Bush of Texas into one speech, Vice President Al Gore asserted today that the governor's handling of the state's budget proved he would be an incompetent steward of the national economy, inclined to squandering the surplus on tax cuts for the rich.</p>
        <p>Brimming with confidence in a speech before the leaders of 30 transportation unions, almost all of which have endorsed him, Mr. Gore wove together themes he had spun out separately in recent weeks, creating a tapestry of harsh questions about his Republican rival's fitness to be president.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, the vice president said, had frittered away a $6.4 billion surplus in Texas on tax cuts favoring the wealthy, leaving the state with a $610 million budget shortfall because of cost overruns in some programs. The governor, Mr. Gore said, could be expected to do the same in Washington, leaving no money for government programs that are particularly important to working people, like Social Security and Medicare.</p>
        <p>''One year ago, Texas had the biggest budget surplus in that state's history,'' Mr. Gore said. ''Governor Bush's top priority was a big tax break for the powerful interests. And now, in the midst of the strongest national economy ever in history, Texas has virtually eliminated that surplus and has a budget shortfall.</p>
        <p>''Now, Governor Bush wants to bring those same budget-busting tax policies to the nation as a whole,'' Mr. Gore continued. ''Which do you think is more important, his rhetoric or his record?''</p>
        <p>The vice president sarcastically accused Mr. Bush of having misplaced his priorities by using the surplus for tax cuts instead of improving services.</p>
        <p>''If you were governor of a state that had the worst record of any state in giving health care to the families of your state, and then all of a sudden you found yourself with the biggest budget surplus in the history of your state, don't you think you would consider using some of that surplus to maybe move your state from No. 50 to, say, 45 or maybe even higher?'' Mr. Gore said, eliciting titters from his audience. ''I would, of course, and shoot higher than that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides said the Texas budget was firmly balanced and would actually finish the coming fiscal year with a $1.4 billion surplus. The $610 million shortfall, caused by unexpectedly high expenditures on Medicaid and prison programs, will be quickly resolved with supplemental appropriations, they said. And the aides said much of Mr. Bush's tax cut was devoted to reducing sales and property taxes for middle-income Texans, not just the rich.</p>
        <p>''If this election comes down to Governor Bush's fiscal leadership versus Al Gore's credibility, we're going to win in a landslide,'' said Dan Bartlett, a spokesman for the Bush campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, wearing a conventional red tie with white shirt and black suit instead of his trademark khakis and polo shirt, seemed especially relaxed and confident today as he addressed his enthusiastic audience, which repeatedly interrupted him with standing ovations.</p>
        <p>Echoing the view of his aides that he has had a good few days on the stump, after many bad ones, the vice president said, ''I think that this week will be looked back upon as a turning point.''</p>
        <p>Working to pump the labor leaders, whose help will be vital in getting out the Democratic vote this November, Mr. Gore ticked off a series of pro-union pledges:  raising the minimum wage, enacting legislation to remove obstacles to organizing unions, making health insurance more accessible, ensuring that women receive equal pay for equal work.</p>
        <p>And in a subtle response to the criticisms of Ralph Nader, the Green Party candidate for president who contends that Mr. Gore is virtually a carbon copy of Mr. Bush, the vice president urged the crowd to ''fight off any cynics who say that they're all the same and it doesn't make any difference.''</p>
        <p>''It does make a difference,'' Mr. Gore continued. ''It makes a difference whether or not we're going to fight to keep Social Security or not. It makes a difference whether or not working families are going to get health care and their kids are going to get good public schools.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
