<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Finesse Is So Deep, It's Practically Subterranean</title>
    <meta content="22CARD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E2D6173AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="489" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Finesse Is So Deep, It's Practically Subterranean</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott Bridge column discusses play at European Junior team Championships; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If it were possible to stage the bridge equivalent of a Ryder Cup, North America against Europe, there would be no clear favorite. But if the contest were at junior level, the Europeans could be expected to win because they have vastly more international experience.</p>
        <p>Norway has produced several world-class junior players in recent years, and more seem to be on the way. Their representatives won the European Junior Team Championship in Antalya, Turkey, last week in a field of 18 countries. Netherlands and Israel took the silver and bronze medals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If it were possible to stage the bridge equivalent of a Ryder Cup, North America against Europe, there would be no clear favorite. But if the contest were at junior level, the Europeans could be expected to win because they have vastly more international experience.</p>
        <p>Norway has produced several world-class junior players in recent years, and more seem to be on the way. Their representatives won the European Junior Team Championship in Antalya, Turkey, last week in a field of 18 countries. Netherlands and Israel took the silver and bronze medals.</p>
        <p>There were few female players, but one attracted attention with brilliant play on the diagramed deal, reported by Martin Schaltz of Denmark. Marina Kelina of Russia, as South, arrived in three no-trump as  shown after her right-hand opponent, an Italian, chose to open one club.</p>
        <p>This was carrying the concept of opening light in third position beyond reason, and he eventually regretted his action.</p>
        <p>The opening lead of the heart queen was normal, but allowed South a vital trick. After winning with ace, she finesssed the heart ten to enter dummy.</p>
        <p>Then, with the opening bid to guide her, she led the club jack. When East covered with the queen and the king won, South noted the appearance of the eight on her left. She crossed to the heart king and led the club four. When East played the three, Kelina produced the two and made her game.</p>
        <p>In theory, it would have been a fraction better to lead the seven from dummy, protecting against the slight chance that West had falsecarded with a doubleton 8-6. But as it was, South could claim to have taken the deepest finesse of the year, or perhaps of any year.</p>
        <p>In the replay, the Italian declarer, Furio di Bello, also received the lead of the heart queen and won with the ace. But he had no clue to the club position from the bidding. In that suit he had the chance of a safety play to make exactly three tricks: cashing the ace and leading low to the jack.</p>
        <p>But three club tricks would not be enough unless there was a ninth trick to be found in another suit. He therefore made a good play by leading a low spade at the second trick. If West had held the king, the queen would have scored, permitting the safety play in clubs.</p>
        <p>As it was, however, East produced the spade king, and di Bello needed four club tricks. Later he cashed the ace and king hoping that the queen would appear, but had no luck at all. He had only seven tricks, for down two and a gain of 11 imps to Russia.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
