<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Lyrical Approach to Balanchine</title>
    <meta content="22BOLS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216648"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BALLET REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bolshoi Ballet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E1D6173AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="338" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Lyrical Approach to Balanchine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff reviews performance of Bolshoi Ballet at New York State Theater (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sprinkled with debuts, the Bolshoi Ballet's mixed bill settled down more happily on Thursday night than it had the night before.</p>
        <p>The young Svetlana Lunkina recovered from an injury to make her first appearance at the New York State Theater in George Balanchine's ''Symphony in C.'' Like Anastasia Goriacheva, the equally young corps member who was thrown into her role at short notice on Wednesday, Ms. Lunkina takes a more lyrical approach to the first movement of the Balanchine-Bizet ballet than her American counterparts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sprinkled with debuts, the Bolshoi Ballet's mixed bill settled down more happily on Thursday night than it had the night before.</p>
        <p>The young Svetlana Lunkina recovered from an injury to make her first appearance at the New York State Theater in George Balanchine's ''Symphony in C.'' Like Anastasia Goriacheva, the equally young corps member who was thrown into her role at short notice on Wednesday, Ms. Lunkina takes a more lyrical approach to the first movement of the Balanchine-Bizet ballet than her American counterparts.</p>
        <p>The music, conducted by Alexander Sotnikov to accommodate this focus on legato phrasing but graduating into the right brisk tempo, enhanced Ms. Lunkina's elegant image and clean Neo-Classical style.</p>
        <p>John Taras, who says he staged the ballet in Moscow with Tatiana Terekhova, has produced a version that differs somewhat from the current New York City Ballet's. But Sergei Filin's omission of the male solo in the first movement on Wednesday was not one of this production's idiosyncrasies. On Thursday, he opted to give this solo the benefit of his resilient jumps and the punch of his forceful pirouettes.</p>
        <p>Nina Ananiashvili also did better, replacing the exclamation points of her dancing with newfound regal serenity in the second movement. The corps, while still tending to push down when its energy should be up, had more of the requisite oomph. The thing to remember is that Balanchine was paying tribute here to the brio of French-Italian classicism, not to the grand style of the Russian Imperial Ballet.</p>
        <p>In the ''Don Quixote'' Grand Pas, Ms. Ananiashvili danced with the fan she previously did without in her rather free-form solo, and Mr. Filin was new as her relatively subdued partner. By contrast, Andrei Uvarov's debut as Solor to Galina Stepanenko's ever-impressive Nikiya in the Kingdom of the Shades scene from ''La Bayadere'' had an explosive power that his cautious preparations for steps did not promise. There is nobility to his lanky vertical silhouette. The corps was stunning in Petipa's crystalline patterns.</p>
        <p>BALLET REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
